<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eng000261" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Caesar</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>William</forename>
            <surname>Alexander</surname>
          </persName>
          <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q4019920</idno>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A16527_04.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
        </bibl>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The monarchicke tragedies Crœsus, Darius, The Alexandræan, Iulius Cæsar. Newly enlarged by William Alexander, Gentleman of the Princes priuie chamber.</title>
            <author>Stirling, William Alexander, Earl of, 1567 or 8-1640.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>199 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2012 November (TCP phase 2)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99835942</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 344.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg III:1009, I:260,261.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">177</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16527</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2240897091</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The monarchicke tragedies Crœsus, Darius, The Alexandræan, Iulius Cæsar. Newly enlarged by William Alexander, Gentleman of the Princes priuie chamber.</title>
            <title type="alt">Monarchick tragedies</title>
            <title type="alt">Tragedie of Croesus.</title>
            <title type="alt">Alexandraean tragedie.</title>
            <title type="alt">Tragedie of Iulius Caesar.</title>
            <title type="alt">Tragedie of Julius Caesar.</title>
            <author>Stirling, William Alexander, Earl of, 1567 or 8-1640.</author>
            <author>Stirling, William Alexander, 1567 or 8-1640.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[410] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by Valentine Simmes for Ed: Blount,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date type="publication_date">1607.</date>
            <date type="creation_date">1604</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>In verse.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: [pi]1 a2 B-M4 N2; A-K4 L2; A-Dd4 Ee2 (||-A2).</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Leaves K4 (second series) and A1 and E2 (third series) are blank.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>A reissue of the edition of 1604 with cancel general title page; "The tragedie of Darius" retains its original 1604 title page. A separately signed section has been added containing "The Alexandræan tragedie" and "The tragedie of Iulius Cæsar", each with separate dated title page.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The title page to "The Alexandræan tragedie" is a cancel with a mask ornament. The cancellandum has a lace ornament.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <person xml:id="eng000261-marcus-brutus" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Marcus Brutus</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000261-decius-brutus" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Decius Brutus</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000261-juno" sex="FEMALE">
            <persName>Juno</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000261-antonius" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Antonius</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000261-caesar" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Caesar</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000261-cicero" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Cicero</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000261-cassius" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Cassius</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000261-portia" sex="FEMALE">
            <persName>Portia</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000261-calphurnia" sex="FEMALE">
            <persName>Calphurnia</persName>
          </person>
          <personGrp xml:id="eng000261-chorus" sex="MALE">
            <name>Chorus</name>
          </personGrp>
          <person xml:id="eng000261-nuntius" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Nuntius</persName>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
      <textClass>
        <classCode scheme="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q80930</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1604">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="eng000261-e100030">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="eng000261-145-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="eng000261-145-b"/>
        <p>THE TRAGEDIE OF IVLIVS CAESAR. </p>
        <p>By William Alexander, Gentleman of the Princes priuie Chamber. </p>
        <quote>Carmine dij superi placantur, carmine manes. </quote>
        <p>LONDON Printed by VALENTINE SIMMES for ED: BLOVNT. 1607. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="preface" xml:id="eng000261-e100080">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="eng000261-146-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="eng000261-146-b"/>
        <head>The Argument. </head>
        <p>AT that time when the Romans trauelled with an vnsatiable ambition to subdue all Nations, by whose ouerthrow they could conceaue any exspectation, either of glory, or profit: Caius Iulius Caesar, a man of a loftie minde, and giuen to attempt great things, ascending by seuerall degrees to the Consullship, procured a power to warre against the Gaules: amongst whom, after a number of admirable battels and victories (by the approbation of all the world; hauing purchased a singular reputation, both for his courage and skill in Armes) he being long accustomed to command, was so drunken with a delight of soueraigntie, that disdaining the simplicitie of a priuate life, he was so farre from denuding himselfe of the authoritie that he had, that altogether transported with a desire of more; hee sent to the Senate, to haue his gouernment of the Gaules, prorogated for fiue years which sute being repugnant to the Lawes, (as directly tending to tyrranie) was by the people publikely repelled. By which occasion, and some others, rising from an aemulation betweene him and Pompey the great, pretending a high indignation, hee incontinent crossed the Alpes, with such forces (though few) as he had in readinesse, and with a great celeritie came to Rome, which hee found abandoned by Pompey, in whom the Senate had reposed their trust, whom shortly after, by a memorable battell in the fields of Pharsalia he discomfited: and hauing by the ouerthrow of Scipio, death of Cato, and flight of Pompeys sonnes, <pb xml:id="eng000261-147-a"/>as it were, rooted out all the contrary faction, hee returned to Rome, and indirectly by the meanes of Antonius, laboured to be proclaimed king: which hauing rendred him altogether odious; Caius Cassius, Marcus Brutus, Decius Brutus, Publius Casca, and diuers others (Noble men) conspired his death, and appointed a day for the same: at which time, notwithstanding that Caesar was disswaded from going foorth, by many monstrous apparitions, and ominous presages; yet being perswaded by Decius Brutus Albinus, hee went towards the fatall place, where the Senate was assembled. </p>
        <p>The Conspirators in like maner, had many terrors amongst others, Portia the wife of Marcus, Brutus, although she had insinuated her selfe in her husbands secret, by a notable proofe of extraordinary magnanimitie, yet on the day dedicated for the execution of their designe, through the apprehension of his danger she fainted diuers times, whereof Brutus was aduertised, yet shrinked not, but went forward with his confederats to the appointed place, where they accomplished their purpose, euery one of them giuing Caesar a wound, and me a ground wherevpon to build this present Tragedie. </p>
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="eng000261-147-b"/>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="eng000261-e100110">
        <pb xml:id="eng000261-148-a"/>
        <head>The Actors Names. </head>
        <list>
          <item>IVNO. </item>
          <item>CAESAR. </item>
          <item>ANTONIVS. </item>
          <item>CICERO. </item>
          <item>DECIVS BRVTVS. </item>
          <item>CAIVS CASSIVS. </item>
          <item>MARCVS BRVTVS. </item>
          <item>PORTIA. </item>
          <item>CALPHVRNIA. </item>
          <item>NVNTIVS. </item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="tragedy" xml:id="eng000261-e100240">
        <pb xml:id="eng000261-148-b"/>
        <head>THE Tragedie of Caesar. </head>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="eng000261-e100250">
          <head>ACT. I. </head>
          <sp who="#eng000261-juno" xml:id="eng000261-e100260">
            <speaker>Iuno. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>THough I a goddesse glance through th'azure round, </l>
              <l>Whilst the eie-feather'd birds my coach do moue: </l>
              <l>And am with radiant starres heauens Empresse crown'd, </l>
              <l>The sister, and the wife of thundring Ioue. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And though I banquet in th'Aetheriall bowres, </l>
              <l>Where Ambrosie and Nectar serues for meate: </l>
              <l>And at the meeting of th'immortall powres, </l>
              <l>Am still aduanc'd vnto the highest seate: </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Yet by those glorious shewes of boundlesse blisse, </l>
              <l>My martred minde can no way be relieu'd, </l>
              <l>Since immortalitie affords but this, </l>
              <l>That I may euer liue being euer grieu'd. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>In vaine, vaine mortals seeke for helpe at me, </l>
              <l>With Sacred odours on my Altars throwne: </l>
              <l>What expectation can they haue to see, </l>
              <l>One venge their wrongs, that cannot venge her owne? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Might Pallas once drowne thousands in the seas. </l>
              <l>And metamorphose Diomedes mates? </l>
              <l>And must mine enemies alwayes liue in ease, </l>
              <l>As me to spight, appointed by the fates? </l>
            </lg>
            <pb xml:id="eng000261-149-a"/>
            <lg>
              <l>Of all the dying race that liues below, </l>
              <l>With such indignities none could comport, </l>
              <l>As wound my breast, whom gods and men do know </l>
              <l>To be abusde by Ioue in many a sort. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Though knowne to me, from others if concealde, </l>
              <l>His faults might breed me griefe, but yet not shame: </l>
              <l>Where lo, now both through heauen &amp; earth reuealde, </l>
              <l>Each slanderous Theater doth his scorne proclame. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>If heauenly soules diuinely liu'd aloft, </l>
              <l>Th'inferior world would imitate them then: </l>
              <l>But humaniz'd by hanting mortals oft, </l>
              <l>Where men should grow like gods, gods grow like men. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>My painted Iris in her beauties pride, </l>
              <l>Smiles not on Phoebus with so many hues: </l>
              <l>As Ioue in diuers shapes himselfe can hide, </l>
              <l>When he poore maides by Cupid spurr'd pursues. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>He Danae in a golden showre deceiude, </l>
              <l>And did a Swanne in Ledaes bosome light, </l>
              <l>Then being a Bull Agenors daughter reau'd, </l>
              <l>And Iö made a Cow to mocke my sight. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>But would to god that with such wanton dames, </l>
              <l>He still to sport would as with me remaine, </l>
              <l>Not able then t'imbrace celestiall flames, </l>
              <l>All like the drunkards mother might be slaine. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Then such a troupe as Rheas bosome stores, </l>
              <l>Would not hold him and me at endlesse iarres: </l>
              <l>The heauens are pestred with my husbands whores, </l>
              <l>Whose lights impure, do taint the purest starres. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>All iniuries are heauie to digest, </l>
              <l>Yet th'actors greatnesse doth some griefe remoue: </l>
              <l>Of whom to suffer wrong it shames one least; </l>
              <l>If I were wrongde, I would be wrongde by Ioue. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>But (ah) this long hath tirraniz'd my breast, </l>
              <l>A man, a boy, a shepheard, yea and worse, </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-149-b"/>
              <l>The Phrygian fire-brand, the adultrous guest, </l>
              <l>That first wrought wrong by fraud and then by force. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>He, he, was he whose verdict mou'd me most, </l>
              <l>Whilst it on Ida wrong'd my beauties right; </l>
              <l>No wonder too though one all iudgement lost, </l>
              <l>That had three naked goddesses in sight. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And yet I know were not his wandring eyes, </l>
              <l>The Ciprian bribde by some lasciuious smiles, </l>
              <l>My pompous birds in triumph through the skies, </l>
              <l>Had borne the golde that oft her nimphes beguiles. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Am not I she whose greatnesse is admirde, </l>
              <l>Whom Ioue for wife, whom thousands court for loue? </l>
              <l>Whom haughtie Ixion once t'imbrace desirde, </l>
              <l>Yet with a clowde deluded did remooue. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>What needed me a matter to submit, </l>
              <l>Where my authoritie might haue auailde? </l>
              <l>Whilst though I promisde wealth, and Pallas wit, </l>
              <l>Yet with a yong man Venus gift preuaild. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>But how durst he t'ones pleasure thus giue place, </l>
              <l>Where two contemnd their honour would repaire? </l>
              <l>Is not our Sexe impatient of disgrace? </l>
              <l>Of which there's none, but loues to be thought faire. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>T'auenge my selfe no kinde of paine I sparde, </l>
              <l>And made his greatest gaine his greatest losse: </l>
              <l>As Venus gaue him Helen for reward, </l>
              <l>I gaue him Helen for his greatest crosse. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Nor did he long her loue with ioy enioy, </l>
              <l>Whose faithlesse flames his countrey did confound: </l>
              <l>Whilst armies arm'd, for her did Troy destroy, </l>
              <l>And leuel'd Neptunes labours with the ground. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Whilst Simois seem'de to be a buriall field, </l>
              <l>Whose streames as streetes were with dead bodies pau'd </l>
              <l>All Xanthus plaine as turnde t'a sea did yeeld </l>
              <l>A flood of blood, from Heroes wounds receiu'd </l>
            </lg>
            <pb xml:id="eng000261-150-a"/>
            <lg>
              <l>By brauing thousands once though much esteem'd, </l>
              <l>By dust and blood deform'd, of Hector slaine </l>
              <l>(Nor like Patrocius by the sword redeem'd) </l>
              <l>The bodie basely was bought backe againe. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Then by the same mans sonne that kild his sonne, </l>
              <l>Th' old Priamus surprizde sigh'd forth his breath: </l>
              <l>And being most harm'd where he for helpe had runne, </l>
              <l>Whilst taking th'Altar, taken was by death; </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Though wrestling long t'auoide the heauens decree, </l>
              <l>By th'enemies sword being parted from the light, </l>
              <l>He that lou'de Helen, and was loath de by me, </l>
              <l>Di'd as a sacrifice t'appease my spight. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Last hauing liu'd (if miserie be a life) </l>
              <l>T'entombe all hers, that high mishaps had tride </l>
              <l>Though once being both, nor mother then, nor wife, </l>
              <l>The fertile Hecub', as being barren dide. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Thus by those meanes it would haue seem'd to some, </l>
              <l>That my scornde beautie had bin highly vengde: </l>
              <l>But whilst they were ore-com'd they did ore-come, </l>
              <l>Since they for better states their states haue changde. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>I in one part, that people did confound, </l>
              <l>But did enlarge their power in euery place: </l>
              <l>Al warlike nations through the world renowned, </l>
              <l>Now from the Phrygian ruines raise their race. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And yet two traitors that betraide the rest, </l>
              <l>(O heauens, that treason thus should prosper whiles) </l>
              <l>Of the Dardanian race did chance the best, </l>
              <l>More happie then at home in their exiles. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Did not Antenor stealing through his foes, </l>
              <l>Neere to the Euganian mountaines build a towne, </l>
              <l>Of which some nurslings once shall seeke repose </l>
              <l>Amidst the waues, and in the depths sit downe? </l>
              <l>Their citie spousing Neptune, shall arise </l>
              <l>The rarest common-wealth that euer was. </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-150-b"/>
              <l>Whose people, if as stowt, as rich and wise, </l>
              <l>Might boast to bring miraculous things to passe. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Then false Aeneas (though but borne t'obey) </l>
              <l>Did of a fugitiue become a King: </l>
              <l>And some of his neere Tibers streames that stay, </l>
              <l>Would all the world to their obedience bring. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Their rauenous Eagles soaring ouer all lands, </l>
              <l>By violence th'imperiall prey haue wonne: </l>
              <l>That bastard broode of Mars with martiall bands, </l>
              <l>Haue conquerd both the mansions of the Sunne. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Their course by mountaines could not be controlde, </l>
              <l>No, Neptune could not keepe his bosome free. </l>
              <l>Th'antartike heate, nor yet the artike colde, </l>
              <l>No limites to their legions could decree. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>O of that cittie there could come no good, </l>
              <l>Whose rising walles with more than barbarous rage, </l>
              <l>The builder first bath'd with his brothers blood, </l>
              <l>Which their prodigious conquests did presage. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>That towne hath oft my soule with anguish filld, </l>
              <l>Whose new-borne state oft triumpht ouer my wrath: </l>
              <l>Like my olde foe that in his cradle killd, </l>
              <l>The serpents that I sent to giue him death. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>By Sabins, Albans, Tuscans oft assailde, </l>
              <l>Euen in her infancie I tossde Romes state: </l>
              <l>Yet stil Laomedons false race preuailde, </l>
              <l>And angry Iuno could doe nought but hate. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Then when the gallant Gaules had vanquisht Rome, </l>
              <l>That basely bought her libertie with golde: </l>
              <l>A banisht man Camillus chauncde to come, </l>
              <l>And her imballanc'd state redeemde of olde. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Great Hanniball our common cause pursude, </l>
              <l>And made his bands within their bounds remaine, </l>
              <l>With Consuls and with Praetors bloods imbrude, </l>
              <l>At Thrasimene and at Cannes slaine. </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-151-a"/>
              <l>In Romans mindes strange thoughts did feare infuse </l>
              <l>That did attend the taking of their towne: </l>
              <l>But he that vanquish could, not victory vse, </l>
              <l>Was by their brasen destinie throwne downe. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>O what a torrent of Barbarians once, </l>
              <l>Inunding ouer the Alpes their walles did bost, </l>
              <l>Whilst Teutons and the Cimbers bigge of bones, </l>
              <l>Like giants marcht a more than monstrous hoste. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>But though from vnknowne partes to ruine Rome, </l>
              <l>I led those troopes that all the world admirde, </l>
              <l>Yet did the tyrant Marius them orecome, </l>
              <l>And I in vaine to venge olde wrongs aspirde. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>By baser meanes I likewise sought her harmes, </l>
              <l>Whilst Ianus church imported neuer peace, </l>
              <l>I raisde vp abiect Spartacus in armes, </l>
              <l>That neere eclipsde Romes glorie with disgrace. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Though I that all the world for help haue sought, </l>
              <l>From Europe, Affrike, and from Asia thus: </l>
              <l>Gaules, Carthaginians, and Cimbers brought, </l>
              <l>Yet did the domage still redound to vs. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Of heauen and earth I all the powres haue prou'd, </l>
              <l>And for their wracke haue each aduantage watcht: </l>
              <l>But they by forraine force could not be mou'd, </l>
              <l>By Romans, Romans onely may be matcht. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And I at last haue kindled ciuill warre, </l>
              <l>That from their thoughts which now no reason bounds, </l>
              <l>Not only lawes, but Natures lawes doth barre, </l>
              <l>The sonne the sire, the brother brother wounds. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Whilst th'Eagles are opposde to th'Eagles so, </l>
              <l>O what contentment doth my mind containe: </l>
              <l>No wound is wrong bestow'd, each killes a foe, </l>
              <l>What euer side doth lose I alwayes gaine. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>But this my soule exceedingly annoyes, </l>
              <l>All are not subiect to the like mis-hap: </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-151-b"/>
              <l>The warre helps some as others it destroyes, </l>
              <l>And those that hate me most, haue still best hap. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Whilst with their blood their glory thousands spend, </l>
              <l>Ah, ones aduauncement aggrauates my woe: </l>
              <l>That vaunts himselfe from Venus to descend, </l>
              <l>As if he claimd by kinde to be my foe. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>I meane the man whose thoughts nought can appease </l>
              <l>Whilst them too high a blinde ambition bends, </l>
              <l>Whom as her minion Fortune bent to please, </l>
              <l>Her rarest treasures prodigally spends. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Not onely hath he daunted by the sword, </l>
              <l>The Gaules, the Germans, and th'Aegyptians now, </l>
              <l>But of all lordes pretends to be made lord, </l>
              <l>That who commaund the world to him may bow. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Thus dispossessing princes of their thrones, </l>
              <l>Whilst his ambition nothing can asswage: </l>
              <l>That the subiected world in bondage grones, </l>
              <l>The prey of pride, the sacrifice of rage. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Men raile on Ioue, and sigh for Saturnes time, </l>
              <l>And to the present still th'Age past preferre: </l>
              <l>Then burden would the gods with euery crime, </l>
              <l>And damne the heauens where only th'earth doth erre. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Though Ioue as stupid still with Cupid sportes, </l>
              <l>And not the humor of prowd Caesar spies: </l>
              <l>That may (if forcing thus the worlds chiefe forts) </l>
              <l>More powrefull than the Titans scale the skies. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Yet lest hee thrall him too that none free leaues, </l>
              <l>We from the bounds aboue must him repell: </l>
              <l>To brawle with Pluto in th'vmbragious caues, </l>
              <l>There since he will be first made first in hell. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>What? with that tyrant I will strait be euen, </l>
              <l>And send his soule to the Tartarian groue: </l>
              <l>For though Ione be not iealous of his heauen, </l>
              <l>Yet Iuno must be iealous of her Ioue; </l>
            </lg>
            <pb xml:id="eng000261-152-a"/>
            <lg>
              <l>And though none in the heaven would do him ill, </l>
              <l>He raise vp some in th'earth to haste his death; </l>
              <l>Yea though both heauen and earth neglect my will, </l>
              <l>Hell can afford me ministers of wrath. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Ile crosse Cocytus and the smoaking lakes, </l>
              <l>To borrow all my brothers damned bandes: </l>
              <l>The Furies arm'd with firebrands and with snakes, </l>
              <l>Shall plant their hell where Rome so stately stands. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Whilst by my furie Furies furious made, </l>
              <l>Do spare the dead to haue the lilting pin'd: </l>
              <l>O with what ioy will I that armie leade? </l>
              <l>Nought than reuenge more sweet t'a wronged minde. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Ile once make this a memorable age, </l>
              <l>By this high vengeance that I haue conceiu'd: </l>
              <l>But what though thousands die t'appease my rage? </l>
              <l>So Caesar perish, let no soule be sau'd. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000261-e103250">Exit. </stage>
          <div type="chorus" xml:id="eng000261-e103260">
            <head>Chorus. </head>
            <lg>
              <l>WE should be grieu'd t'offend the gods, </l>
              <l>That holde vs in a ballance still; </l>
              <l>And as they will, </l>
              <l>May weigh vs vp or downe, </l>
              <l>Those that by follie ingender pride, </l>
              <l>And doe deride </l>
              <l>The terrour of th'eternalls roddes, </l>
              <l>In seas of sinne their soules doe drowne. </l>
              <l>And others but abhorre them as vniust, </l>
              <l>Those that religion want deserue no trust. </l>
              <l>How dare fraile flesh presume to rise? </l>
              <l>Whilst it deserues heauens wrath to proue, </l>
              <l>On th'earth to moue, </l>
              <l>Lest that it op'ning straight, </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-152-b"/>
              <l>Giue death and buriall both at once: </l>
              <l>How dare such ones </l>
              <l>Looke vp vnto the skies, </l>
              <l>For feare to feele the thunders weight? </l>
              <l>All th'elements th'immortalls will attend, </l>
              <l>And are as prompt to plague as men t' offend. </l>
              <l>None scapes some plague that gods displease: </l>
              <l>Then whilst he Bacchus rites did scorne, </l>
              <l>Was Pentheus torne: </l>
              <l>The Delians high disdaine </l>
              <l>Made Niobe though turnd t'a stone, </l>
              <l>With teares still mone, </l>
              <l>And Pallas spite t'appease, </l>
              <l>Arrachne weaues loathd webbes in vaine. </l>
              <l>Heauen hath preparde or euer they beginne, </l>
              <l>A fall for pride, a punishment for sinne. </l>
              <l>Loe Iuno yet doth still retaine, </l>
              <l>That indignation once conceiu'd, </l>
              <l>For wrong receiu'd, </l>
              <l>From Paris as we finde, </l>
              <l>And for his cause, bent to disgrace </l>
              <l>The Troyan race, </l>
              <l>Doth hold a high disdaine, </l>
              <l>Long laide vp in a loftie minde, </l>
              <l>We should abstaine from irritating those, </l>
              <l>Whose thoughts (if wrongd) not till reuengde repose: </l>
              <l>Thus those for Paris fond desire, </l>
              <l>That of his pleasures had no part, </l>
              <l>For them must smart, </l>
              <l>Such be the fruites of lust. </l>
              <l>Can heauenly breasts so long time lodge, </l>
              <l>A secret grudge, </l>
              <l>Like mortalls thrall to ire, </l>
              <l>Till Iustice whiles doth seeme vniust? </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-153-a"/>
              <l>Of all the furies that afflict the soule, </l>
              <l>Lust and reuenge are har hardest to controule: </l>
              <l>The gods giue them but rarely rest, </l>
              <l>That do against their will contend, </l>
              <l>And plagues doe spend </l>
              <l>That fortunate in nought </l>
              <l>Their sprites being parted from repose, </l>
              <l>May still expose </l>
              <l>Th'vpbraiding troubled breast, </l>
              <l>A prey to each tyrannicke thought: </l>
              <l>All selfe-accusing soules no rest can finde, </l>
              <l>What greater torment than a, troubled minde: </l>
              <l>Let vs adore th'immortall powres, </l>
              <l>On whose decree, of euery thing </l>
              <l>The State doth hing, </l>
              <l>That farre from barbarous broiles, </l>
              <l>We of our life this little space </l>
              <l>May spend in peace, </l>
              <l>Free from afflictions showres, </l>
              <l>Or at the least from guiltie toiles, </l>
              <l>Let vs of rest the treasure striue t'attaine, </l>
              <l>Without the which nought can be had but paine. </l>
            </lg>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="eng000261-e103980">
          <head>ACT. II. </head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="eng000261-e103990">
            <head>SCENE I. </head>
            <stage xml:id="eng000261-e104000">Iulius Caesar, Marcus Antonius. </stage>
            <lg>
              <l>NOw haue my hopes attain'd th'exspected hauen, </l>
              <l>In spite of partiall enuies poisnous blasts: </l>
              <l>My fortune with my courage hath proou'd euen, </l>
              <l>No monument of miscontentment lasts. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Those that corriualld me, by me orethrowne, </l>
              <l>Did by their falles giue feathers to my flight: </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-153-b"/>
              <l>I rather in some corner liue vnknowne, </l>
              <l>Than shine in glorie, and not shine most bright, </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>What common is to two, rests no more, </l>
              <l>No Phaenix is in all the world saue one: </l>
              <l>Grieu'd of my deedes that any claimes a share, </l>
              <l>Would God that I had acted all alone. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And yet at last I neede to mourne no more, </l>
              <l>For enuie of the Macedonians praise; </l>
              <l>Since I haue equalld all that went before, </l>
              <l>My deedes in number doe exceede my dayes. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Some earst, (whose deedes rest registred by fame,) </l>
              <l>Did from their conquests glorious titles bring: </l>
              <l>But greatnes to be great must haue my name, </l>
              <l>It's more to be a Caesar than a King. </l>
            </lg>
            <sp who="#eng000261-antonius" xml:id="eng000261-e104260">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Those warlike nations that did nations spoile, </l>
              <l>Are by thy legions now, t'our laws made thrall; </l>
              <l>What can not vertue doe by time and toile, </l>
              <l>True magnanimitie triumphs ouer all. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e104310">
              <speaker>Caesar. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Th'outragious Gaules that in most monstrous swarmes, </l>
                <l>Went wasting Asia, thundring downe all things; </l>
                <l>And marching ouer the Macedonians armes, </l>
                <l>Did insolently make and vnmake kings. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Those Gaules that hauing the worlds conq'rors foild, </l>
                <l>As if the world might not haue matcht them then, </l>
                <l>Would sacrilegiously haue Delphos spoild: </l>
                <l>And warrd against the gods, contemning men, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yea those whose auncestors our cittie burn'd. </l>
                <l>The people that the Romans onely fear'd: </l>
                <l>By me Romes nursling matcht and orematcht murn'd, </l>
                <l>So what they first eclipsd againe they clear'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then as to subiects hauing giuen decrees, </l>
                <l>I left the Gaules their rash attempts to rue: </l>
                <l>And wounding Neptunes bosome with wing'd trees, </l>
                <l>The world diuided Britaines did subdue. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-154-a"/>
              <lg>
                <l>The Germans from their birth inurde to warre, </l>
                <l>Whose martiall minds still haughty thoughts haue bred, </l>
                <l>Whilst neither men nor walls my course could barre, </l>
                <l>Mask'd with my banners saw their Rhene runne red, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And th'orientall realmes amidst of late, </l>
                <l>My comming and orecomming was but one: </l>
                <l>With little paine so Pompey was calld great, </l>
                <l>That warrd with those whose glorious daies were gone: </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But what though thousands set ones praises forth, </l>
                <l>For fields which shadowes and not swords obtaind; </l>
                <l>Yet th'easie rate but vilifies the worth, </l>
                <l>No glorie without labour can be gain'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>From dangers past my comfort now proceedes, </l>
                <l>Since all difficulties I did ore come: </l>
                <l>And in few wordes to comprehend my deedes, </l>
                <l>Rome conquerd all the world, and Caesar Rome. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-antonius" xml:id="eng000261-e104720">
              <speaker>Anto. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Loe, those that striu'de your vertue to suppresse, </l>
                <l>And were opposde to all your actions still: </l>
                <l>Whilst labouring but too much to make you lesse, </l>
                <l>Haue made you to grow great against your will. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Great Pompeys pomp is past, his glorie gone, </l>
                <l>And austere Cato by himselfe lies killd: </l>
                <l>Than dastard Cicero more you honors none, </l>
                <l>Thus all your foes are with confusion filld. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The Senatours whose wrath could not b'affwag'd, </l>
                <l>Long to your preiudice their powre abusde, </l>
                <l>Till at their great ingratitude enrag'd, </l>
                <l>I saide our swordes would graunt what they refusde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>When hauing scap'd, endanger'd, and despisde, </l>
                <l>That Curio 'and I did to your campe resort, </l>
                <l>In olde bare gownes like some base slaues disguisde, </l>
                <l>All sigh'd to see vs wrongd in such a sort. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e104930">
              <speaker>Caesar </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Th'inhabitants of heauen that know all harts, </l>
                <l>They know my thoughts as pure as are their starres: </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-154-b"/>
                <l>And that constrainde I came from forraigne parts, </l>
                <l>To seeme vnciuill in the ciuill warres. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I mooude that warre which all the world bemones, </l>
                <l>Being vrgde by force to free my selfe from feares: </l>
                <l>Still when my hand gaue wounds, my heart gaue grones, </l>
                <l>No Romans blood was shed, but I shed teares. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But how could any cleuated spright, </l>
                <l>That had for honor hazarded his blood; </l>
                <l>Yet yeeld by froward foes outragious spight, </l>
                <l>To be defrauded of th'expected good. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>When as a multitude of battels wonne, </l>
                <l>Had made Romes Empire, and my glory great; </l>
                <l>And that the Gaules (oft vanquishde) had begunne </l>
                <l>T'embrace the yoke that they disdainde of late. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then pompous Pompey, my prowd sonne in law, </l>
                <l>And Cato, that still crossde what I designde, </l>
                <l>From fauouring me the people did withdraw, </l>
                <l>And vnto me a successour assignde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Not that he should succeed in dangerous broyles, </l>
                <l>But euen through enuie, as thay had ordain'd, </l>
                <l>That he might so triumph of all my toyles, </l>
                <l>And rob the glory that I dearely gain'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Could one with such indignities comport, </l>
                <l>That values honor deerer then the light? </l>
                <l>No, (whilst my soule rests soueraigne of this fort) </l>
                <l>None shall haue power to rob me of my right. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And yet by Ioue, that all the world commands, </l>
                <l>T'vse any violence I did mislike: </l>
                <l>And offred oft t'abandon all my bandes, </l>
                <l>If that my enemies would haue done the like. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But the tumultuous multitude that still </l>
                <l>As waues with windes are carried with conceits, </l>
                <l>With nought but my disgrace would bound their will, </l>
                <l>And I committed all vnto the fates. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-155-a"/>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet when at Rubicon I stood perplex'd, </l>
                <l>And weigh'd the horrour of my high attempt, </l>
                <l>My soule was with a thousand fancies vex'd, </l>
                <l>Which resolution buried in contempt. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-antonius" xml:id="eng000261-e105440">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Nought in a captaine more confounds his foes, </l>
                <l>Then sodaine resolutions swift effects; </l>
                <l>For so surpriz'd ere they their thoughts dispose, </l>
                <l>All good aduice prodigious care neglects. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Though when you march'd towards Rome, your power </l>
                <l>The sodaine newes so thundred in each eare: (was small, </l>
                <l>That (as if heauen had falne vpon them all,) </l>
                <l>They bred amazement, and th'amazement feare, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Some secret destinie as then appear'd, </l>
                <l>Doth guide mens actions and their iudgements bounds, </l>
                <l>Them whom huge armies could not once haue fearde: </l>
                <l>A shadow or a rumour whiles confounds. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Ist that th'encroaching danger dulles their sprits. </l>
                <l>And doth preuent their resolutions power, </l>
                <l>Or that some destinie distracts their wits, </l>
                <l>When heauens determin'd haue their fatall houre? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Pompey the great that was growne ag'd in armes, </l>
                <l>And had triumph'd ouer all the worlds three parts </l>
                <l>(Being quite discourag'd with imagin'd harmes) </l>
                <l>Fled Rome, though without reach of th'enemies darts. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then as t'a torrent all gaue place to you, </l>
                <l>Rome whom she cal'd a rebell made her Lord: </l>
                <l>Your successour Domitius forc'd to bow, </l>
                <l>Did trust your fauour more than feare your sword. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>When in th'Iberian bounds you did arriue, </l>
                <l>There th'aduersarie that did vainely vaunt, </l>
                <l>Had all th'aduantage that the ground could giue, </l>
                <l>And wealth of vittailes that with vs were scant. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet the celeritie that you had vsde </l>
                <l>Did so discourage their disordered band, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-155-b"/>
                <l>That (as Ioue in their breasts had feare infusde,) </l>
                <l>They had no strength against our strokes to stand. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And when Romes generall with braue Legions storde </l>
                <l>Seem'd to possesse all that his soule requirde, </l>
                <l>Whilst vs t'ouerthrow both famine and the sword, </l>
                <l>The sea, the land, and all in one conspirde; </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then for your offices they did contend, </l>
                <l>As those that of the victorie were sure: </l>
                <l>And where they might th'affaires of state attend </l>
                <l>In Rome, for lodgings fondly did procure. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet memorable now that day remaines, </l>
                <l>When all the world was in two armies rang'd: </l>
                <l>That Mars went raging through th'Aemathian plaines, </l>
                <l>And to dispaires high expectations chang'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>That famous field when the Pompeyans lost, </l>
                <l>(As Lyons doe their prey) you did pursue </l>
                <l>The scattred remnant of that ruin'd hoste, </l>
                <l>On which new heads still like to Hydra grew. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Though victorie in Affricke fatall seem'de </l>
                <l>To any armie that a Scipio led; </l>
                <l>Yet you shew'd there, for worth in warre esteem'd </l>
                <l>That Rome a better then a Scipio bred: </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And all our enemies were confounded thus, </l>
                <l>That vs in number euer did surmount; </l>
                <l>But Caesar and his fortune were with vs, </l>
                <l>Which we did more than many thousands count. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e106150">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>The sweetest comfort that my conquests gaue, </l>
                <l>It was the meane how to do many good; </l>
                <l>For euery day some Romans life I saue, </l>
                <l>That in the field to fight against me stood. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Thus may my minde be iudg'd by the euent, </l>
                <l>That (euen when by my greatest foes assailde) </l>
                <l>To win the battell neuer was more bent, </l>
                <l>Then prompt to pardon when I had preuailde. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-156-a"/>
              <lg>
                <l>Not couetous of blood of spoyles nor harmes, </l>
                <l>I (though being victor) did insult ouer none, </l>
                <l>But laid aside all hatred with my armes, </l>
                <l>A foe in fight, a friend when it was gone. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I like the praise of clemencie, more then </l>
                <l>Of force, that with affliction th'enemie lodes, </l>
                <l>For force prooues oft the worst thing that's in men, </l>
                <l>And clemencie the best thing in the gods. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Sterne Cato, but by Cato that would die, </l>
                <l>And either death or life, if giuen disdain'd; </l>
                <l>O, I enuie thy death that didst enuie, </l>
                <l>The glory that I sauing thee had gaind'. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet I to rents and dignities restore </l>
                <l>Euen those that my destruction had designde: </l>
                <l>And O, it doth delight my minde farre more </l>
                <l>By benefits then by constraint to binde. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-antonius" xml:id="eng000261-e106460">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <p>I would haue all my foes brought to their endes. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e106480">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <p>I rather haue my foes all made my friends. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-antonius" xml:id="eng000261-e106500">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <p>Their blood whom I suspect'd should quench all strife. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e106520">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <p>So might one doe that lik'd of nought but life. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-antonius" xml:id="eng000261-e106540">
              <speaker>An. </speaker>
              <p>Still life would be redeemde from dangers forth. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e106560">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <p>Not with a ransome then it selfe more worth. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-antonius" xml:id="eng000261-e106580">
              <speaker>An. </speaker>
              <p>Than life to man, what thing more deere succeeds? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e106600">
              <speaker>Caes </speaker>
              <p>The great contentment that true glory breeds. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-antonius" xml:id="eng000261-e106620">
              <speaker>An. </speaker>
              <p>Men by all meanes this blast of breath prolong. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e106640">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <l>Men should striue to liue well, not to liue long. </l>
              <l>And I would spend this momentarie breath, </l>
              <l>To liue by fame for euer after death: </l>
              <l>For I aspire in spight of fates to liue. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-antonius" xml:id="eng000261-e106690">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <p>I feare that some too soone your death contriue. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e106710">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <p>Who dare but lodge such thoughts within their mindes. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-antonius" xml:id="eng000261-e106730">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <p>Those that the shadow of your greatnes blindes. </p>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="eng000261-156-b"/>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e106750">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <p>The best are bound to me by gifts in store. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-antonius" xml:id="eng000261-e106770">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <p>But to their countrey they are bound far more. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e106790">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <p>Then loath they me as th'enemie of the state? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-antonius" xml:id="eng000261-e106810">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <p>You as th'vsurper of the same they hate. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e106830">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <p>I by huge battels haue enlarg'd their bounds. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-antonius" xml:id="eng000261-e106850">
              <speaker>An. </speaker>
              <p>By that they think your powre to much abounds. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e106870">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <p>Yet I from doing wrong refraine my will. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-antonius" xml:id="eng000261-e106890">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <p>They feare your powre, because it may do ill. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e106910">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>The present state still miscontentment brings </l>
                <l>To factious mindes affecting matters strange, </l>
                <l>That burdens to themselues irke of all things; </l>
                <l>And so they change, regard not what they change: </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>In populous townes where many make repaire, </l>
                <l>(Whose confluence by conference all things touch) </l>
                <l>They further than their bounds extend their care, </l>
                <l>The idle that doe nothing, must thinke much. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Lo, Rome (though wasted all with ciuill warres, </l>
                <l>Whilst priuate grudge pretended publike good; </l>
                <l>And that equalitie engendring iarres, </l>
                <l>Did proue too prodigall of Roman blood;) </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet hauing through huge toyles attain'd to rest, </l>
                <l>That it by yeelding t'one may banish teares: </l>
                <l>It if constrain'd disdaines t'imbrace the best, </l>
                <l>This word necessitie so woundes the eares. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And th'insolent with vile seditious words, </l>
                <l>That trembled whilst they heard the trumpets sound: </l>
                <l>Stirre now their tongues, as we did then our swords, </l>
                <l>And what Mars sparde, make Mercurie confound. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The people thus in time of peace agree, </l>
                <l>T'abase the greatest still, euen in that forme </l>
                <l>As in calme dayes they doe disbranch the tree, </l>
                <l>That shrowded them of late against a storme. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But now I look'd for libertie to bost, </l>
                <l>That once my deeds triumph'd had ouer enuie: </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-157-a"/>
                <l>As all darke shadowes doe evanish most, </l>
                <l>Then when the Sunne shines highest in the skie: </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And though their hatred deepely they disguise, </l>
                <l>Yet they conceale not so their soules desires: </l>
                <l>But that their spight rest sparkling through their eies, </l>
                <l>And bosts to burst out once in open fires. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-antonius" xml:id="eng000261-e107320">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Since first (great Caesar) I discernd thy worth, </l>
                <l>On all thy actions I did still attend: </l>
                <l>And therefore what some whisper, Ile speake foorth, </l>
                <l>T'admonish freely it becomes a friend. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Since first men did suspect that you aspire </l>
                <l>T'a Monarchie, the gouernement to change; </l>
                <l>They in their soules your ruine do conspire, </l>
                <l>And their affections farre from you estrange. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Since chaste Lucretia by prowd Tarquin stain'd, </l>
                <l>Wash'd with her blood the violated bed, </l>
                <l>Whilst by his power supreame Rome was constrain'd </l>
                <l>All things t'obey, that his curst braine had bred. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>This gouernment which some tyrranick call, </l>
                <l>It sounds so odious in the peoples eares, </l>
                <l>As Tyrants vild, that they detest them all </l>
                <l>Whose greatnesse giues them any cause of feares. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e107530">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I not affect the title of a king, </l>
                <l>For loue of glory, or desire of gaine, </l>
                <l>Nor for respect of any priuate thing, </l>
                <l>But that the state may by my trauels gaine. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>You know Sibillaes bookes that neuer faile, </l>
                <l>In many mindes haue an opinion bred: </l>
                <l>That ouer the Parthians Rome cannot preuaile, </l>
                <l>Till by a soueraigne prince her bands be led. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>For as confusion is the fruit we finde </l>
                <l>Of those affaires that diuers thoughts dispose; </l>
                <l>So soueraigntie match'd with a gallant mind, </l>
                <l>Breeds reuerence in ones owne, feare in his foes. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-157-b"/>
              <lg>
                <l>And, O it greeues me that these steps of ours, </l>
                <l>Haue trod so oft on many a millions neckes, </l>
                <l>Whilst yet the Parthian vilipends our powres, </l>
                <l>And all our victories vnuanquish'd checkes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Ah, should a Generall of the Romane race </l>
                <l>Be by Barbarians killd, and not reueng'd? </l>
                <l>And should his ensignes, signes of our disgrace, </l>
                <l>Rest in the ranke of conquer'd relikes rang'd? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>No, no, wretch'd Crassus, now thy selfe content, </l>
                <l>Ile pacifie thy ghost with Parthians spoiles: </l>
                <l>For still my boyling fancies haue bin bent </l>
                <l>T'ore-match th'vnmatch'd, and daunt th'vndaunted soiles </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-antonius" xml:id="eng000261-e107840">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>With victories being cloyd, will you not then </l>
              <l>Your saftie once, more then new warres respect? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e107870">
              <speaker>Caes </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>No, though I haue surmounted other men, </l>
                <l>My fancies yet do greater things affect: </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>In emulation of my selfe at last, </l>
                <l>Euen enuiouslie I looke on mine owne deedes; </l>
                <l>And bent to make the new surpasse things past, </l>
                <l>Now to my mind old praise no pleasure breeds. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-antonius" xml:id="eng000261-e107960">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>The world hath seene thee (great man) for Romes good, </l>
              <l>In danger oft of many a dangerous shelfe: </l>
              <l>Whilst for her glory thou engag'd thy blood, </l>
              <l>Of others carefull, carelesse of thy selfe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e108010">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Though whilst in th'April of my blooming age, </l>
                <l>I from the vulgar rate redeemd my name, </l>
                <l>Some with my deeds did burden youths hot rage, </l>
                <l>And an ambitious appetite of fame. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet since the coldnesse of declining yeares </l>
                <l>Bosts to congeale the blood that boild of late, </l>
                <l>Whilst else my life the sunne of glory cleares, </l>
                <l>That now of all the world remaine most great. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I cannot couet that thing which I haue, </l>
                <l>I haue all honour that can be requirde. </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-158-a"/>
                <l>And now (as th'only wanted thing) would craue, </l>
                <l>To taste the pleasures of a life retyrde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But onely now t'aduance the state I striue, </l>
                <l>For, O neglecting th'ecchoes of renowne </l>
                <l>I could content my selfe vnknowne to liue </l>
                <l>A priuate man, with a Plebeian gowne. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Since (Anthonie) thus for the state I care, </l>
                <l>And all delights that nature loues disdaine: </l>
                <l>Go, and in time the peoples mindes prepare, </l>
                <l>That as the rest, I may the title gaine. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet indirectly at the first, assay </l>
                <l>To what their doubtfull mindes do most incline: </l>
                <l>But as without my knowledge, that they may </l>
                <l>All marke your minde, and yet not thinke of mine. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="eng000261-e108320">Exeunt. </stage>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="eng000261-e108330">
            <head>ACT. II. SCENE. II. </head>
            <stage xml:id="eng000261-e108340">Cicero. Decius Brutus. </stage>
            <lg>
              <l>DId I suruiue th'impetuous Sillaes rage, </l>
              <l>And in a torrent of destruction stood: </l>
              <l>Whilst tyrants did make Rome a tragicke stage, </l>
              <l>Through a voluptuous appetite of blood? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Scap'd I confusion in a time so bad, </l>
              <l>Of libertie and honour once to taste, </l>
              <l>That bondage now might make my soule more sad, </l>
              <l>By the remembrance of my fortunes past? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>What though I once (when first by fame made known) </l>
              <l>From Catilines strange treason did preserue </l>
              <l>This town, that's still endangerd by her owne, </l>
              <l>Since first the world from equitie did swarue? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>A sparke of that conspiracie remaines, </l>
              <l>Not yet extinguish'd t' haue our state imbroyld; </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-158-b"/>
              <l>That now on Rome flames of confusion raines, </l>
              <l>Thus one was sparde that we might all be spoild. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>O worthy Cato, in whose wondrous minde, </l>
              <l>Three rarely matcht things Nature did reueale: </l>
              <l>Wit, honestie, and courage which designde </l>
              <l>A cittizen for Platoes common-weale. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Whilst curteous Pompey did things as a friend, </l>
              <l>Thou as a wiseman spake, and still foretold, </l>
              <l>To what all Caesars deedes would turne in th'end, </l>
              <l>If that his pride were not in time controlde. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And had we him as wisely thou aduisde, </l>
              <l>Giuen to the Germans whom he had iniur'd: </l>
              <l>We had not now bin thus like slaues despisde, </l>
              <l>To see Romes glorie, and our owne obscur'd. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>But yet I may disbending former cares, </l>
              <l>A space comport with that prowd tyrants powres; </l>
              <l>Age giues assurance by my witherd haires, </l>
              <l>That death will seale my suretie in few howres. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Yet ye whose youth and sprite might haue attaind </l>
              <l>Those dignities that Caesar hath vndone: </l>
              <l>O ye haue lost as much as he hath gaind, </l>
              <l>Whose rising hopes must be retrench'd so soone. </l>
            </lg>
            <sp who="#eng000261-decius-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e108800">
              <speaker>Dec. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Though innouations at the first seeme strange, </l>
                <l>Yet oft experience approbation brings: </l>
                <l>And if with vpright thoughts we weigh this change, </l>
                <l>On it the safetie of our cittie hings. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>As in the depths dasht with redoubling waues, </l>
                <l>A ship by different mindes rests more imbroilde, </l>
                <l>So was our cittie plag'd with diuerse lawes, </l>
                <l>By th'all-confounding multitude turmoilde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>As whilst t'one sickenesse diuerse drugges are vsde, </l>
                <l>Whose powres repugnant in digestion iarre: </l>
                <l>Th'impatient patients fancies rest confusde, </l>
                <l>So did we long distressd with ciuill warre. </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-159-a"/>
                <l>But now great Caesar from tempestuous windes, </l>
                <l>Romes scattred ruines recollects of late: </l>
                <l>A Pilote meete to calme tumultuous mindes, </l>
                <l>A doctor fit for a distemperd state. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-cicero" xml:id="eng000261-e109000">
              <speaker>Ci. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>The state from storms secure by drowning proues, </l>
                <l>Now whilst despaire doth doubtful feares appease: </l>
                <l>He with the life th'infirmitie remoues, </l>
                <l>Thus is the physicke worse than the disease. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>This commonweale (as whiles the world did spie) </l>
                <l>Though some prowd sprites in ciuill warres inuolu'd, </l>
                <l>Yet like blacke cloudes that would obscure the skie, </l>
                <l>Their tumid humours sodainely dissolu'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And no disgrace t'our gouernement redounds, </l>
                <l>But to th'ambitious that had it abusde: </l>
                <l>Who (had their powre like Caesars wanted bounds) </l>
                <l>Had whilst they rulde a greater rigor vsde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>There in all partes are people of all kindes, </l>
                <l>And as aduauncde some bad men did abide, </l>
                <l>Of powre their equalls, and of better mindes, </l>
                <l>Some alwayes vertuous were to curbe their pride. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But since that sacred libertie was lost, </l>
                <l>The publike powre t'a priuate vse one turnes: </l>
                <l>And as his lawlesse wayes did alwayes bost, </l>
                <l>The common weale by violence ore-turnes. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-decius-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e109260">
              <speaker>Dec. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Though what you burden Caesar with were true, </l>
                <l>Him of all crime Necessitie hath clear'd: </l>
                <l>That was foes force t'eschew, forcde to pursue, </l>
                <l>Whilst by contempt t'attempt gret things being cheerd: </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>To th'enemies enuie more oblig'd he rests, </l>
                <l>Then t'his owne wit that no such courses scand, </l>
                <l>Till by being barrd from vsing of requests, </l>
                <l>Not lookt for meanes were offred to command. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>All to mount high his haughtie thoughts did tempt, </l>
                <l>True worth disdaines to suffer open wrong: </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-159-b"/>
                <l>And a great courage kindled by contempt, </l>
                <l>Must by reuenge be quencht whilst rage makes strong. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-cicero" xml:id="eng000261-e109420">
              <speaker>Cic. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>O Decius, now a wrong accompt you cast, </l>
                <l>Th'intent; and not th'euent defines the minde: </l>
                <l>Treade backe the steppes of all his actions past, </l>
                <l>And at the marke he hit all aym'd we finde </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>As by some sprite inspirde prowd Scilla saide, </l>
                <l>That there in Caesar many Marians were: </l>
                <l>And Rome was warn'd in time to be afraide </l>
                <l>Of the euill-girded youth, with smoothe-comb'd haire. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then when (as still to quietnesse a foe,) </l>
                <l>The memorie of Marius he renewd: </l>
                <l>By re-erecting tyrants statues so, </l>
                <l>His thoughts all bent to tyranny were viewd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>That people-pleaser might haue bin perceiu'd, </l>
                <l>By curteous complements beneath his ranke; </l>
                <l>That lauishing forth gifts the world deceiu'd, </l>
                <l>And to gaine more than his, of his proou'd franke. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Though nought at all indulgent to his wife, </l>
                <l>By prostrated pudicitie disgracde: </l>
                <l>Yet did he saue th'adultrous Clodius life, </l>
                <l>To soothe the multitude whose steppes he tracde. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-decius-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e109680">
              <speaker>Dec. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>These be the means by which ambition mounts, </l>
                <l>Without most humble, when most high within: </l>
                <l>And as it fled from that thing which it hunts, </l>
                <l>Still wasting most, when most it mindes to winne. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-cicero" xml:id="eng000261-e109740">
              <speaker>Cic. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And he that still striu'd tyrannie t'embrace, </l>
                <l>Was thought conioynd with Catilin to bee; </l>
                <l>And had wise Catoes counsell taken place, </l>
                <l>Had with the rest receiu'd his death by me. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet hauing suncke himselfe in some mens soules, </l>
                <l>He with his partiall faction suting oft: </l>
                <l>Did get the consulship which nought controules, </l>
                <l>And matching pride with powre did looke aloft. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-160-a"/>
              <lg>
                <l>To flatter them that now must flatter him, </l>
                <l>His powre t'aduaunce vnlawfull lawes preuaild: </l>
                <l>And those to crosse that scornd he so should clime, </l>
                <l>He furnisht was with Force, where Reason faild. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But yet because he could not well b'assur'd, </l>
                <l>T'act all alone according to his will; </l>
                <l>To gouerne Fraunce he craftily procurde, </l>
                <l>So to be strengthned with an armie still; </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>As Rome first warr'd at home till being made strong, </l>
                <l>She thought her selfe of powre the world t'orecome: </l>
                <l>So Caesar warr'd against strange nations long, </l>
                <l>Till that he thought his might might conquer Rome. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then hauing all that force or fate assignes, </l>
                <l>He cause of discontentment did pretend; </l>
                <l>So to dissemble fore-conceiu'd designes, </l>
                <l>One soone may finde a fault that seekes t'offend. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But when he first in a prodigious dreame </l>
                <l>His mother seemde incestuously to vse: </l>
                <l>It might haue shewne to his eternall shame, </l>
                <l>How he the bounds that bare him went t'abuse. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-decius-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e110100">
              <speaker>Dec. </speaker>
              <l>And yet I thinke auoyding threatned harmes, </l>
              <l>He was constraind t'imbarke in ciuill broiles: </l>
              <l>Did he not couenant to quit his armes, </l>
              <l>As not desirous of his countries spoiles? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-cicero" xml:id="eng000261-e110150">
              <speaker>Cic. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Durst he with those that had his charge confind, </l>
                <l>Stand to prescribe conditions as their mate; </l>
                <l>Where t'haue attended and obeyd their minde, </l>
                <l>It was his duetie, and their due of late. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>What? what? durst he, whom borne t'obey the law, </l>
                <l>The people all did willingly promote; </l>
                <l>The sword which they bad giuen, against them draw, </l>
                <l>When it was sharpned first to cut their throat? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>That had not com'd which all our anguish breedes, </l>
                <l>If he vnforcde, when as his charge expirde, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-160-b"/>
                <l>Till that the Senate censurde had his deedes, </l>
                <l>Had from his prouince peaceably retirde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>No, he hath but betraid his natiue towne, </l>
                <l>Those bands by which she did him first preferre; </l>
                <l>T'extend her borders, and his owne renowne, </l>
                <l>Those hath he vsde to tyrannize ouer her. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>My passions (ah transported as you see, </l>
                <l>With an excessiue loue to my deere soile,) </l>
                <l>Haue made my tongue of my hearts-store too free, </l>
                <l>By flaming forth what in my breast doth boile. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-decius-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e110410">
              <speaker>Dec. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>That Ceasars part might iustly be excusde, </l>
                <l>Loe, with the cause alleadgd his course accords: </l>
                <l>Of which th'humanitie that he hath vsde, </l>
                <l>A testimonie to the world affords. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Though forcde to fight, he alwayes had great care, </l>
                <l>To saue our Cittizens as each man knowes; </l>
                <l>And bade his captaines still all Romans spare, </l>
                <l>But on Barbarians bodies spend their blowes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Of th'aduersaries after bloudie strife, </l>
                <l>When of the might haue made some captiues smart: </l>
                <l>Not onelie was he liberall of their life, </l>
                <l>But pardond them still to take Pompeys part. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Euen at th'infortunate Pharsalian field, </l>
                <l>When he securely might haue vsde the sword: </l>
                <l>He both did spare all th'enemies that would yeeld, </l>
                <l>And them to rents and dignities restord. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then when th'Aegyptians so t'obtaine reliefe, </l>
                <l>Brought to his sight pale Pompeys bloodlesse head; </l>
                <l>He testified with teares his inward griefe, </l>
                <l>And gracde his statues after he was dead. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Those his proceedings might appeare t'approue, </l>
                <l>That he against his will maintain'd this warre; </l>
                <l>And to his countrie beares a tender loue, </l>
                <l>That could comport to reine his rage so farre. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="eng000261-161-a"/>
            <sp who="#eng000261-cicero" xml:id="eng000261-e110720">
              <speaker>Cic. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Those counterfeited fauors which he shew, </l>
                <l>According to ones custome that aspires, </l>
                <l>Were spent on many as the world might view, </l>
                <l>T'insinuate himselfe in their desires. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But where he thus spar'd some, he spoild 'whole hosts </l>
                <l>And the Barbarians all to Rome not wrought </l>
                <l>Such harme as he that of his goodnes boasts, </l>
                <l>Yet her best men hath to confusion brought. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The great man that of no mishap could pause, </l>
                <l>But still preuaild, whilst warring without right, </l>
                <l>Armd for the common weale in a good cause, </l>
                <l>With Caesar did vnfortunately fight. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>From Lesbos fled with his afflicted wife, </l>
                <l>Three base-born grooms (can fortune change so soone) </l>
                <l>Stoode to consult vpon great Pompeys life, </l>
                <l>And did what thousands durst not once haue done. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then he whose knees had oft beene kissd by kings, </l>
                <l>(Most highly happy, had he dide in time) </l>
                <l>By one of his owne slaues with abiect things, </l>
                <l>Had his last funeralls framde (O monstrous crime) </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>T'entombe Romes greatest captaine all alone, </l>
                <l>The Roman that arriu'd with reason said, </l>
                <l>The fatall glory was too great for one, </l>
                <l>And to haue part of that last honour staid. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The teares bestowd by Caesar on his head, </l>
                <l>Forth from a guiltie minde remorce had throwne, </l>
                <l>Or else he wept to see his enemy dead, </l>
                <l>By any others hands than by his owne. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then constant Cato that euen death did scorne, </l>
                <l>The rare arch-tipe of an accomplisht man, </l>
                <l>That liu'd as not t'himselfe but t'all men borne, </l>
                <l>Moou'd by his tyranny to ruine ranne. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>He iustly whilst more iust, himselfe more strong </l>
                <l>Then Caesar thought, that for no Iustice carde, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-161-b"/>
                <l>And since discouering what he cloakd so long, </l>
                <l>Said right, that Caesar and not he was snarde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Thus Caesar conquerd all but Catoes minde, </l>
                <l>That would not by a tyrants tollerance breathe: </l>
                <l>But in such sort his famous course confinde, </l>
                <l>Than Caesars life more glorious was his death. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Those great men thus brought to disastrous ends, </l>
                <l>The authour of their death make me despise, </l>
                <l>That whilst t'vsurpe th'authoritie he tendes, </l>
                <l>By treading downe all good men striues to rise. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Now made most great by lessening all the great, </l>
                <l>He prowdly doth triumph in Rome, ouer Rome. </l>
                <l>And we must seeme t'applaud the present state, </l>
                <l>Whose doubtfull breath depends vpon his doome. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet had I not enlargde my griefes so long, </l>
                <l>To you whom Caesar doth pretend to loue; </l>
                <l>Wer't nor I know touch'd with the common wrong, </l>
                <l>A iust disdaine all generous mindes must moue. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-decius-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e111380">
              <speaker>Dec. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Had Caesar willingly resignd his armes, </l>
                <l>And rendred Rome her libertie at last, </l>
                <l>When as from foes he feard no further harmes, </l>
                <l>But had repaird his iust displeasures past. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>More then for all the loue that's shewd to me, </l>
                <l>He should haue had an Altar in my breast: </l>
                <l>As worthy for his vertuous deedes to be </l>
                <l>Feard by the bad, and honourd by the best. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But since though conq'ring all the world by might, </l>
                <l>He to himselfe a slaue would make Rome thrall; </l>
                <l>His benefits are loathsome in my sight, </l>
                <l>And I am grieu'd that he deserues to fall. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>My fancies moue not in so lowe a spheare, </l>
                <l>But I disdaine that one ouer Rome impires; </l>
                <l>Yet it is best, that with the time we beare, </l>
                <l>And with our powre proportion our desires. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-162-a"/>
              <lg>
                <l>Though I dissembled first your minde to trie, </l>
                <l>And tolde what Fame to Caesars praise relates; </l>
                <l>Yet was I pleasde that moe were grieu'd than I, </l>
                <l>All mis-contented men are glad of mates. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-cicero" xml:id="eng000261-e111640">
              <speaker>Cic. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Since tyrannie all libertie exiles, </l>
                <l>We must our selues no more our selues disguise; </l>
                <l>Then learne to maske a mourning minde with smiles, </l>
                <l>And seeme t'extoll that which we most despise. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet all our deedes not Caesars humor please, </l>
                <l>That (since mistrusted once) esteemes vs still </l>
                <l>When dumbe disdaineful, flatterers when we praise, </l>
                <l>If plaine, presumptuous, and in all things ill. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yea we, whose freedome Caesar now restraines, </l>
                <l>As his attenders all his steppes must trace; </l>
                <l>And know, yet not acknowledge his disdaines, </l>
                <l>But still pretend t'haue interest in his grace. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Though all my thoughts detest him as a foe, </l>
                <l>To honour him a thousand meanes I moue; </l>
                <l>Yet But to saue my selfe, and plague him so, </l>
                <l>No hate more harmes than it that lookes like loue. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>His pride that through prepostrous honour swels, </l>
                <l>Hath by the better sort, made him abhorrd; </l>
                <l>The gods are iealous, and men enuious els, </l>
                <l>To see a mortall man so much adord. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-decius-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e111900">
              <speaker>Dec. </speaker>
              <l>Well, Cicero let all meanes be entertaind, </l>
              <l>That may imbarke vs in his bosomes depths, </l>
              <l>Till either willingly or then constrain'd, </l>
              <l>He iustly quite what he vniustly keepes. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="eng000261-e111950">Exeunt. </stage>
            <div type="chorus" xml:id="eng000261-e111960">
              <head>Chorus. </head>
              <lg>
                <l>This life of ours is like a Rose, </l>
                <l>Which whilst it beauties rare array, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-162-b"/>
                <l>Doth then enioy the least repose </l>
                <l>When virgin-like it blush we see: </l>
                <l>Then is't euery hand the prey, </l>
                <l>And by each wind is blowne away: </l>
                <l>Yea though from violence scap'd free, </l>
                <l>(Whilst time triumphs, it leads all thralles) </l>
                <l>Yet doth it languish and decay. </l>
                <l>O Whilst the courage hottest boiles, </l>
                <l>And that our life seemes best to be, </l>
                <l>It is with dangers compast still, </l>
                <l>Whilst it each little change appalles, </l>
                <l>The body force without whiles foiles, </l>
                <l>It th'owne distemprature whiles spoiles: </l>
                <l>Of which, though none it chance to kill: </l>
                <l>As nature failes the bodie falles, </l>
                <l>Of which, saue death, nought bounds the toyles. </l>
                <l>What is this moouing tower in which we trust? </l>
                <l>A little winde closd in a cloud of dust. </l>
                <l>And yet some spirits though here being pent, </l>
                <l>In this fraile prisons narrow bounds, </l>
                <l>With what might suffice not content, </l>
                <l>Do alwayes bend their thoughts too hie, </l>
                <l>And aime at all the peopled grounds, </l>
                <l>Then whilst their breasts ambition wounds, </l>
                <l>Though feeding as bent straight to die. </l>
                <l>They build as they might alwayes liue, </l>
                <l>Being famishd for fames emptie sounds: </l>
                <l>Of such no end the trauels ends, </l>
                <l>But a beginning giues whereby </l>
                <l>They may b'imbroild worse then before, </l>
                <l>For whilst they still new hopes contriue, </l>
                <l>Th'exspected good more anguish sends </l>
                <l>Then the possessde contentment lends, </l>
                <l>Like beasts that taste not, but deuoure. </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-163-a"/>
                <l>They swallow much, and for more striue, </l>
                <l>Whilst still their hope new hap attends: </l>
                <l>And how can such but still themselues annoy, </l>
                <l>That know to conquere, but not how t'enioy? </l>
                <l>Since as a ship amidst the depthes, </l>
                <l>Or as an Eagle through the aire, </l>
                <l>Of which their way no impression keepes, </l>
                <l>Most swift when seeming least to moue: </l>
                <l>This breath of which we take such care, </l>
                <l>Doth tosse the bodie euery where, </l>
                <l>That it may hence with haste remoue: </l>
                <l>Life slippes and sleepes alwayes away, </l>
                <l>Then whence, and as it came goes bare, </l>
                <l>Whose steps behinde no trace doth leaue. </l>
                <l>Why should heauen-banish'd soules thus loue </l>
                <l>The cause, and bounds of their exile, </l>
                <l>Where they as restlesse strangers stray, </l>
                <l>And with such pain why should they reaue </l>
                <l>That which they haue no right to haue: </l>
                <l>Which with them selues within short while, </l>
                <l>As sommers beauties must decay, </l>
                <l>And can giue nought except the graue, </l>
                <l>Though all things doe to harme him what they can, </l>
                <l>No greater enemie then himselfe to man: </l>
                <l>Whilst oft enuiron'd with his foes </l>
                <l>That threatned death on euery side, </l>
                <l>Great Caesar parted from repose, </l>
                <l>As Atlas vnderneath the starres </l>
                <l>Did of a world the weight abide. </l>
                <l>But since a prey t'excessiue pride, </l>
                <l>More then by all the former warres, </l>
                <l>He now by it doth harmde remaine </l>
                <l>And of his fortune doth defide </l>
                <l>Made rich by many a Nations wrack, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-163-b"/>
                <l>He breaking through the liquid barres, </l>
                <l>In Neptunes armes his minion forc'd, </l>
                <l>Yet still pursude new hopes in vaine. </l>
                <l>Ah, would th'ambitious looking backe, </l>
                <l>Of their inferiours knowledge take, </l>
                <l>They from huge cares might be deuorc'd, </l>
                <l>Whilst veiwing few more wealth attaine, </l>
                <l>And many more than they to lacke. </l>
                <l>Lo, th'only plague from men that rest doth reaue, </l>
                <l>Is valuing what they want, not what they haue. </l>
                <l>Since thus the great themselues inuolue </l>
                <l>In such a laborinth of cares, </l>
                <l>Whence none to scape can well resolue, </l>
                <l>But by degrees is forward led </l>
                <l>Through waues of hopes, rockes of dispaires: </l>
                <l>Let vs anoyd ambitions snares, </l>
                <l>And farre from stormes by enuie bred, </l>
                <l>Still seeke securely a humble rest, </l>
                <l>With mindes where no prowd thought repaires, </l>
                <l>That in vaine shadowes doth delight: </l>
                <l>Thus may our fancies still be fed </l>
                <l>With that which Nature freely giues. </l>
                <l>Let vs iniquitie detest, </l>
                <l>And hold but what we owe of right, </l>
                <l>Th'eyes treasure is th'al-circling light: </l>
                <l>Not that vaine pompe for which th'earth striues, </l>
                <l>Whose glory but a poysnous pest, </l>
                <l>T'orethrow the soule delights the sight, </l>
                <l>Ease comes with ease where all by paine buy paine: </l>
                <l>Rest we in peace, by warre let others raigne. </l>
              </lg>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="eng000261-e112980">
          <pb xml:id="eng000261-164-a"/>
          <head>ACT. III. </head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="eng000261-e112990">
            <head>SCENE. I. </head>
            <stage xml:id="eng000261-e113000">Caius Cassius. Marcus Brutus. </stage>
            <lg>
              <l>NOw, Brutus now, we need no more to doubt, </l>
              <l>Nor with blind hopes our iudgement to suspend: </l>
              <l>Lo, all our exspectations are worne out, </l>
              <l>For now it's time t'attempt, and not t'attend. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Th'imperious people that did th'earth appall, </l>
              <l>Ah vanquishde by their victories at last, </l>
              <l>Are by their too much libertie made thrall, </l>
              <l>Since all their strength but serues themselues to cast. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And we that once seemd borne t'aime at great things, </l>
              <l>Of the worlds mistresse mightie minions once, </l>
              <l>That might haue labor'd to giue lawes to kings, </l>
              <l>Lawes from a king, must looke for now with grones. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>For such of Caesar is the monstrous pride, </l>
              <l>That though he domineers else at this houre, </l>
              <l>And to his clients kingdomes doth diuide, </l>
              <l>With an vnlimitd tyrranicke power. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Yet of Dictator he disdaines the name, </l>
              <l>And seekes a tyrants title with the place: </l>
              <l>Not for his honour, no, but for our shame, </l>
              <l>As onely bent to bragge of our disgrace. </l>
            </lg>
            <sp who="#eng000261-marcus-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e113260">
              <speaker>Marc. Brut. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I thought to see that man (as others are) </l>
                <l>Walke reapparrel'd with a priuate gowne, </l>
                <l>As one that had vnwillingly made warre </l>
                <l>T'hold vp himselfe, not to cast others downe. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>So Silla, though more inhumane then he, </l>
                <l>Whilst hauing all to what his heart aspirde, </l>
                <l>The soueraigntie resign'd, and set Rome free </l>
                <l>When all such exspectation was expirde. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-164-b"/>
              <lg>
                <l>By Caesars worth we must thinke that he too, </l>
                <l>Will libertie restore t'our troubled state: </l>
                <l>When first the world hath viewd what he might doe, </l>
                <l>His thoughts are generous as his minde is great. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And though some insolencies scape him whiles, </l>
                <l>His dying furie sparkles but a space: </l>
                <l>Nought th'inspirations quite of Mars exiles, </l>
                <l>Till one be vsde with th'innocencie of peace. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Those that by violence did t'all things tend, </l>
                <l>Scarse can themselues t'a quiet course conforme: </l>
                <l>Their stately cariage and franke words offend, </l>
                <l>Whilst peace cannot comport with warres rude forme. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I hope that Caesar setling ciuill broyles, </l>
                <l>When disaccustomde is intestin rage: </l>
                <l>Will striue to mitigate his countryes toyles, </l>
                <l>Bent all those flames that burn'd his brest t'asswage. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-cassius" xml:id="eng000261-e113570">
              <speaker>Ca Cass. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Thus of his course you by your own conceiu'd </l>
                <l>As if like thoughts of both did bound the will: </l>
                <l>Ah, honest mindes are with least paine deceiu'd: </l>
                <l>Those that themselues are good dreame not of ill. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But of bad mindes to sound th'vnsound deuice, </l>
                <l>Their inclination must your iudgement sway: </l>
                <l>The square of vertue cannot measure vice, </l>
                <l>Nor yet a line that's straight a crooked way. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>So Caesar may preuaile t'vsurpe the state, </l>
                <l>He cares not by what violence nor sleight: </l>
                <l>O, one may soone deceiue men and grow great, </l>
                <l>That leaues religion, honestie and right, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>When as the Senatours (no more their owne) </l>
                <l>Came to that Tyrant whom ambition blinds, </l>
                <l>And showde him by what honors they had showne, </l>
                <l>To gratifie his greatnesse gratefull mindes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>He in a chaire imperiously being plac'd, </l>
                <l>Not daign'd to rise nor bow in any sort: </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-165-a"/>
                <l>As both of them had but their due imbrac'd, </l>
                <l>When he a hautie, they an humble port. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But if he thus, ere we be throughly thrall'd </l>
                <l>Dare so disdainfully such great men vse: </l>
                <l>When in a regall throne by vs install'd </l>
                <l>Then will he breake that which he now doth bruse. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Was he not first that euer yet began, </l>
                <l>To violate the sacred Tribuns place; </l>
                <l>And punish'd them for punishing a man, </l>
                <l>That had transgressde the lawes in time of peace? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The lawes that doe of death all guiltie hold, </l>
                <l>Whose actions seeme to tirranie inclinde: </l>
                <l>So earnest were our ancestours of old, </l>
                <l>To quensh the light of tyrants ere it shinde: </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And shall our Nephews (heires of bondage) blame </l>
                <l>Vs dastard parents that their hopes deceiu'd, </l>
                <l>That saw, that suffred, that suruiu'd such shame, </l>
                <l>Not leauing dead, what we being borne receiu'd? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>By Caesars friendes to an assembly brought, </l>
                <l>The Senators intend to call him king. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-marcus-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e114060">
              <speaker>Brut. </speaker>
              <p>Ile not be there. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-cassius" xml:id="eng000261-e114080">
              <speaker>Cass. </speaker>
              <l>But what if we be sought </l>
              <l>T'assist as Praetors such a publike thing? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-marcus-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e114110">
              <speaker>Brut. </speaker>
              <l>Then Ile resist that violent decree; </l>
              <l>None of Romes crowne shall long securely bost, </l>
              <l>For ere that I liue thrall'd, Ile first die free: </l>
              <l>What can be kept when libertie is lost? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-cassius" xml:id="eng000261-e114160">
              <speaker>Cass. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>O with what ioy I swallow vp those wordes, </l>
                <l>Words worthy of thy worth, and of thy name: </l>
                <l>But Brutus be not fearde, this cause affords </l>
                <l>Thee many mates in danger, few in fame. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>When Anthonie prowde Caesars Image crown'd </l>
                <l>The people by a silent sorrow told, </l>
                <l>In what a depth of woes their thoughts were drown'd </l>
                <l>That Comet of confusion to behold. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-165-b"/>
              <lg>
                <l>What do those scroules throwne in thy chaire import, </l>
                <l>Which what thou art to thy remembrance brings? </l>
                <l>Be those the fancies of th'inferiour sort? </l>
                <l>No, none but noble mindes dreame of great things. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Of other Pretors people looke for showes, </l>
                <l>And distributions whose remembrance dyes: </l>
                <l>Whilst bloody fencers fall with mutuall blowes, </l>
                <l>And Affricks monsters made t'amaze their eyes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But from thy hands they libertie attend, </l>
                <l>A glory hereditarie to thy race, </l>
                <l>And following thee their blood will frankly spend, </l>
                <l>So thou succeed in thy great parents place; </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>That Romes redeemer once did Tarquin foile, </l>
                <l>Though from his birth obeyd, and without strife, </l>
                <l>Where thou shouldst but th'aspiring tirant spoile, </l>
                <l>That would t'extinguish'd tyrrany giue life. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-marcus-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e114470">
              <speaker>Brut. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I weigh thy words, with an afflicted heart, </l>
                <l>That for compassion of my countrey bleedes, </l>
                <l>And would to God that I might onely smart, </l>
                <l>So that all others scap'd th'euill that succeeds. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then neuer man himselfe from death did free </l>
                <l>With a more quiet and contented minde, </l>
                <l>Then I would perish, if I both could be </l>
                <l>To Caesar thankefull, and t'our countrey kinde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But though that great mans grace towards mee enlargde </l>
                <l>May challenge right in my affections store: </l>
                <l>Yet must the greatest debt be first dischargde, </l>
                <l>I ow him much, but to my countrey more. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>This in my breast hath great dissention bred; </l>
                <l>I Caesar loue, but yet Romes enemie hate: </l>
                <l>And as Ioue liues, I could be mou'd to shed </l>
                <l>My blood for Caesar, Caesars for the state. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I for my fathers death loathde Pompey long, </l>
                <l>Whilst iust disdaine did boyle within my breast, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-166-a"/>
                <l>Yet when he warr'd to venge the common wrong, </l>
                <l>I ioynde with him because his cause was best. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>A minde t'vsurpe if Caesar now reueale. </l>
                <l>I will in time precipitate his end </l>
                <l>Thus being still bent t'aduance the Common-weale, </l>
                <l>I help'd a foe, and now must hurt a friend. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-cassius" xml:id="eng000261-e114780">
              <speaker>Cass. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Least of his fauour thou the poyson proue, </l>
                <l>From swallowing of such baites (deere friend) beware: </l>
                <l>No tyrant (trust me) can intirely loue, </l>
                <l>Nor none that for himselfe doth only care. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>He by such curtesies doth but intend </l>
                <l>T'imbase thy vertues, vndermine thy minde, </l>
                <l>And thy suspected courage to disbend, </l>
                <l>Yea (though with silken bonds he would thee binde.) </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>This of all tyrants is the common tread, </l>
                <l>To wreake all those in whom most worth he findes: </l>
                <l>Or (whilst that terrors tosse his iealous head,) </l>
                <l>T'vse subtilties t'amuse the greatest mindes: </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>As when we for the Pretorship did striue, </l>
                <l>Then both were held in hope that so deceiu'd </l>
                <l>We others harmes might studie to contriue, </l>
                <l>Through emulation and disdaine conceiu'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Thus subtill Caesar by such sleights hath toyld </l>
                <l>To sow dissention, that we both may pause </l>
                <l>Of priuate wrongs; and by such means imbroil'd, </l>
                <l>Still courting him, neglect the common cause. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But nought from others must our thoughts estrange, </l>
                <l>That must in time the tyrants course restraine: </l>
                <l>Let other men lament, we must reuenge, </l>
                <l>I scorne to beare a sword and to complaine. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-marcus-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e115090">
              <speaker>Brut. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Though Caesar (now) I must conspire thy fall, </l>
                <l>My heart towards thee, yet neuer harbor'd hate: </l>
                <l>But (pardon me) who euer make it thrall, </l>
                <l>From bondage Brutus must redeeme the state, </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-166-b"/>
              <lg>
                <l>Of this my course what euer others iudge, </l>
                <l>Heere I protest it is for good design'd; </l>
                <l>My thoughts are guiltie of no priuate grudge, </l>
                <l>For reason, and not furie moues my minde. </l>
                <l>Nor is't ambition that inflames my breast, </l>
                <l>With a prodigious appetite to raigne, </l>
                <l>That when I haue made Caesar Plutoes guest, </l>
                <l>I in his rowme a monarch may remaine. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>No, if that glorie did my fancies charme, </l>
                <l>To which blind-folded tyrants doe aspire; </l>
                <l>I needed not to do, nor suffer harme, </l>
                <l>But with lesse paine might compasse my desire. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>For if I would but temporize a space, </l>
                <l>Till Time, or Death diminish Caesars might. </l>
                <l>He thinkes that I deserue t'enioy his place, </l>
                <l>And I could make my day succeede his night. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet doe I not endeere my selfe so much, </l>
                <l>That Ile seeke honor by my countries shame, </l>
                <l>But O, I would (my zeale to it is such) </l>
                <l>To saue it from reproch seeme worthy of blame. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yea so, that I may free with honourd wounds, </l>
                <l>My soile than is my soule more deere to me: </l>
                <l>I care not strait to be barr'd from the bounds, </l>
                <l>That at so deere a rate I would set free. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-cassius" xml:id="eng000261-e115440">
              <speaker>Cass. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What man doth breath of Mars his martiall race, </l>
                <l>But will with Brutus sacrifice his blood, </l>
                <l>And chargde with armes ere tyranie take place, </l>
                <l>Dare venture all things for his countries good? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Can any iudgement be deceiu'd so farre, </l>
                <l>But that it else most cleerely may beholde, </l>
                <l>How that this change Rome greatnes strait will marre, </l>
                <l>And raze the trophees that she rear'd of olde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Of olde in Rome all those that once had worne </l>
                <l>The peace-importing gowne, or warrelike shield, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-167-a"/>
                <l>Of dignities as capable being borne, </l>
                <l>Durst aime at all that libertie could yeeld. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Those in affaires to deale that would set forth, </l>
                <l>Were not discourag'd by their birth, though base, </l>
                <l>And pouertie could not holde backe true worth, </l>
                <l>From hauing honour both by warre and peace. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then emulation violently driu'd </l>
                <l>All gallant mindes t'attempt great actions still; </l>
                <l>That in the loue of venue riualls liu'd, </l>
                <l>Whilst Glorie in their bosomes balme did still. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Fabricius first was from the plow aduauncde, </l>
                <l>The rudder of the commonwealth to hold; </l>
                <l>Yet by no meanes his priuate wealth enhauncde, </l>
                <l>As rich in vertue still, as poore in golde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Rude Marius too, to match red Mars in fame </l>
                <l>Forth from the vulgar drosse his race remou'd, </l>
                <l>And loe, of Cicero the ridiculous name, </l>
                <l>As famous as the Fabians now hath prou'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Each abiect mind disdaind to be obscure, </l>
                <l>When still preferrement followd loftie cares, </l>
                <l>And that one might by dangers past procure, </l>
                <l>Fame to himselfe, and honour to his heires. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But since that state by Caesar is oreturn'd, </l>
                <l>Whilst all our liues depend vpon ones lips; </l>
                <l>Of breasts that once with loue of glorie burn'd, </l>
                <l>From soaring thoughts this course the feathers clips. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Aduauncement now attends not on desert, </l>
                <l>But on th'opinion of a flattred minde; </l>
                <l>That to th'applauding hireling doth impart, </l>
                <l>High honours that true worth can hardly finde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>To these all tyrants most addicted proue, </l>
                <l>Whom without reason they haue raisde too hie, </l>
                <l>As thinking those that stand but by their loue, </l>
                <l>To entertaine the same all meanes must trie. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-167-b"/>
              <lg>
                <l>Where they whose vertue reapes a due reward, </l>
                <l>Not building onely on th'aduauncers grace, </l>
                <l>Doe by deserts not gaine so great regarde, </l>
                <l>Whilst they maintaine, as they obtaine their place. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And if a worthie man to worke great things, </l>
                <l>Wing'd with th'vsurpers fauors raise his flight. </l>
                <l>The highest course to him most harme still brings, </l>
                <l>That till he fall, can not haue leaue to light. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Those that by force would haue th'affection mou'd, </l>
                <l>When willingly men hold such gallants deare. </l>
                <l>They rage that any should be freely lou'd, </l>
                <l>Whose vertue makes their vice more vile appeare. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The man that now to be preferrd aspires, </l>
                <l>Must with effronted flatteries seruile forme, </l>
                <l>Still soothing Caesar, seale all his desires, </l>
                <l>And in some shadow lurke t'auoyde a storme, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>A number else of that prowd rebells foes, </l>
                <l>Grieu'd to behold th'occasion of their griefe. </l>
                <l>Striue in obscuritie t'entombe their woes, </l>
                <l>So waiting, and not working for reliefe. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But we whose lofty mindes disdaine to lowre, </l>
                <l>As those that seeke but their owne safetie thus; </l>
                <l>When shall we spend an indignations powre, </l>
                <l>That's worthy of true Romans, and of vs; </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Since no indignitie resolu'd t'indure, </l>
                <l>I see our mindes doe simpathize in this, </l>
                <l>Should we by suffering seeke to liue secure, </l>
                <l>Whose action must amend what is amisse? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>No, no such abiect thought must staine our breast, </l>
                <l>To cure calamitie but by discourse, </l>
                <l>Whilst but like beasts, affecting foode and rest, </l>
                <l>Where men by reason should direct their course. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Like those of other parts secure from strife, </l>
                <l>If Caesar had bin borne, or chusde our Prince, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-168-a"/>
                <l>Then those that durst attempt to take his life, </l>
                <l>The world of treason iustly might conuince. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>For still the states that flourish for the time, </l>
                <l>By subiects should b' inuiolable thought; </l>
                <l>And those no doubt commit a monstrous crime, </l>
                <l>That lawfull soueraignty prophane in ought. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And we must thinke (though now being brought to bow, </l>
                <l>The Senate king, a subiect Caesar is, </l>
                <l>Th'authoritie that violating now, </l>
                <l>The world must damne as hauing done amisse. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>We will (deare Cassius) for our countries sake, </l>
                <l>Our selues expose to danger, or to death; </l>
                <l>And let vs now aduise what course to take, </l>
                <l>Whilst nought bur th'aire can beare away our breath. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-cassius" xml:id="eng000261-e116600">
              <speaker>Cass. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I thinke this matter needes not many wordes, </l>
                <l>Since but one deede can bound the common shame; </l>
                <l>In Caesars bodie we must sheathe our swordes, </l>
                <l>And by his death our libertie reclame. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But since his fortune did confound them all, </l>
                <l>That in the fields to match him did beginne; </l>
                <l>Whilst he by thousands made their bands to fall, </l>
                <l>With hoarie legions alwayes vsde to winne. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>As Pompeys, Scipioes, and Petreius ghosts, </l>
                <l>In lightlesse shades may by experience tell, </l>
                <l>That after th'ouerthrow of their numbrous hosts, </l>
                <l>All famous (though infortunately) fell, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And since prouided for the Parthian warre, </l>
                <l>His armie in armes attends on his decree, </l>
                <l>Where we sequestred from such forces farre, </l>
                <l>Would, if suspected, strait preuented be; </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>With some few friends, whom all things now t'assay, </l>
                <l>A loue to vs, or to their countrie bindes, </l>
                <l>We to his wracke must walke another way, </l>
                <l>Whilst ere our tongues, our handes doe tell our mindes. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-168-b"/>
              <lg>
                <l>Now when most high, and therefore hated most, </l>
                <l>Th'assembled Senate seekes to make him king; </l>
                <l>We must goe giue the blow before we boast, </l>
                <l>And him to death, Rome out of bondage bring. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-marcus-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e116910">
              <speaker>Brut. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>In all this course I onely one thing blame, </l>
                <l>That we should steale, what we may iustly take, </l>
                <l>By clothing honour with a cloake of shame, </l>
                <l>Which may our cause (thogh good) more odious make. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>O, I could wish, with honourable wounds </l>
                <l>T'affront Romes enemy in the battells dust; </l>
                <l>No sweeter musicke than the Trumpets sounds, </l>
                <l>When Right and Valour keepe a consort iust. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then free if quicke, else dead for nought being feard, </l>
                <l>I alwayes once contented might remaine; </l>
                <l>What tombe t'a man more glorious can be rear'd, </l>
                <l>Than mountaines made of them that he hath slaine? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But how are my transported thoughts growne such, </l>
                <l>That they disdaine a measure now t'admit? </l>
                <l>As bent not what to doe, but to do much, </l>
                <l>I on the throne of Glorie striu'd to sit. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>No, to the state me from my selfe I giue, </l>
                <l>Free from particular respects, t'expose </l>
                <l>My life and all for it, and whilst I liue, </l>
                <l>So that it gaine, I care not what I lose. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Ile neuer rest till he for euer rest, </l>
                <l>That giues my country such a cause of griefe; </l>
                <l>And that t'effect no forme I will detest, </l>
                <l>Nor for my fame endanger Romes reliefe. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But (worthy Cassius) ere we further doe, </l>
                <l>Let vs the mindes of our familiars feele, </l>
                <l>Of which I hope to haue assistance too, </l>
                <l>Who will not hazard for his countries weale. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-cassius" xml:id="eng000261-e117270">
              <speaker>Cass. </speaker>
              <l>Now whilst my soule rests rauisht in a traunce, </l>
              <l>I thinke I see great Rome her courage raise, </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-169-a"/>
              <l>Bent to beat th'aire with songs, th'earth with a daunce, </l>
              <l>And crowne thy vertues with deserued praise. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="eng000261-e117320">
            <head>ACT. III. SCENE II. </head>
            <stage xml:id="eng000261-e117330">Marcus Brutus, Portia. </stage>
            <lg>
              <l>MY dearest halfe, my comfort, my delight, </l>
              <l>That onely seru'st to sweeten all my sowres, </l>
              <l>Thou in my bosome vsde t'vncharge thy spright, </l>
              <l>And in my presence sparde afflictions powres. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Still when domestike broiles disturbde thy rest, </l>
              <l>Whilst by thy selfe thou labord for reliefe, </l>
              <l>Thou with calme wordes disguisde a stormie breast, </l>
              <l>Lest I had bin infected with thy griefe: </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>For such of me was thy respectiue care, </l>
              <l>No cause of miscontentment was made knowne, </l>
              <l>But with affections colors painted faire, </l>
              <l>All that might make me glad, was gladly showne. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>What makes thee then thy courage thus to lose, </l>
              <l>That thou can looke so sad, and in my sight? </l>
              <l>Lend me (deere loue) a portion of thy woes, </l>
              <l>A burden being diuided doth grow light. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>I see the Roses fading in thy face, </l>
              <l>The Lillies languish, Violets take their place. </l>
            </lg>
            <sp who="#eng000261-portia" xml:id="eng000261-e117570">
              <speaker>Port. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Thou hast (deere Lord) preuented my designe, </l>
                <l>Which was to aske of thee, what makes me pale; </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>It Phoebus had no light, could Phoebe shine? </l>
                <l>No, with the cause of force th'effect must faile. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The mirrour but giues backe as it receiues, </l>
                <l>A iust resemblance of th'obiected forme: </l>
                <l>And such impression as th'engrauer leaues, </l>
                <l>The wax retaines still to the stampe conforme. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-169-b"/>
              <lg>
                <l>O I'm the mirrour that reflects thy minde, </l>
                <l>According to the influence of thine eies, </l>
                <l>I take the state in which thy state I finde, </l>
                <l>Such is my colour as thy countnance dies. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then how can I reioyce whilst thou art sad, </l>
                <l>Whose breast of all thy crosses is the scroule? </l>
                <l>I am still as thou art, if grieu'd, or glad, </l>
                <l>Thy bodies shadow, th'essence of thy soule. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>On that great planet that diuides the yeares, </l>
                <l>As th'increase of th'inferiour fields depends; </l>
                <l>And as it doth euanish, or appeares, </l>
                <l>In th'earths cold bosome life beginnes, or ends: </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Sunne of my soule, so I subsist by thee, </l>
                <l>Whose course rests to thy secret motions thrall, </l>
                <l>For when thou art from cloudie fortunes free, </l>
                <l>I rise in ioyes, but if thou faint, I fall. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-marcus-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e117890">
              <speaker>Bru. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>This countnance with my custome but accords, </l>
                <l>That as you know yet neuer from my birth, </l>
                <l>Light gestures vsde ioynd with lasciuious words, </l>
                <l>Nor yet ridiculous fashions that mooue mirth. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>My melancholious nature feedes on cares, </l>
                <l>Whilst smotherd sorrow by a habite smokes, </l>
                <l>A thoughtfull breast that's burdend with affaires, </l>
                <l>Doth make a silent mouth, and speaking lookes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>As for my palenesse it imports but good, </l>
                <l>Th'abasing of the bodie mounts the mind: </l>
                <l>Where fatnesse com'd from food, but serues for food, </l>
                <l>In fattest bodies leanest sprites we finde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Ah, since I saw th'abhorr'd Thessalian bounds </l>
                <l>All drench'd with blood of Senators and kings: </l>
                <l>(As if my soule yet smarted in their wounds,) </l>
                <l>A secret sorrow oftentimes me stings. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But since thy famous father with strange blowes, </l>
                <l>In the most hideous form affronted death, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-170-a"/>
                <l>To him my minde a sad remembrance owes, </l>
                <l>Which sorrow shall exact still whilst I breath. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet am I grieu'd t'haue giuen thee cause of griefe, </l>
                <l>That thought some new mis-hap did me dismay; </l>
                <l>To such olde soares it's worst to giue reliefe, </l>
                <l>But time in end may weare my woes away. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-portia" xml:id="eng000261-e118200">
              <speaker>Por. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Why shouldst thou so from me thy thoghts conceale? </l>
                <l>From thine owne soule that in thy bosome sleepes, </l>
                <l>To whom, though shewne, thou dost them not reueale, </l>
                <l>But in thy selfe more inwardly them keepst? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And thou canst hardly hide thy selfe from me, </l>
                <l>That straight in thee each alteration spie, </l>
                <l>I can comment on all that comes from thee, </l>
                <l>True loue still lookes with a suspitious eye. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Rests not within our bosome euery thought, </l>
                <l>Tun'd by a simpathy of mutuall loue? </l>
                <l>Thou marrst the musicke if thou change in ought, </l>
                <l>Which straight by my distemperature I proue. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Soule of my soule, vnfold what is amisse, </l>
                <l>My minde some great disaster doth diuine, </l>
                <l>And euen excuse my couriousnesse in this, </l>
                <l>Since it concernes thy state, and therefore mine. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-marcus-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e118410">
              <speaker>Brut. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I wonder that thou dost thy frailtie shew, </l>
                <l>All women are by nature curious still; </l>
                <l>And yet till now thou neuer crau'd to know, </l>
                <l>More then I pleasde t'impart of my free will. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Nought saue the wife a man within the walles, </l>
                <l>Nor nought saue him without fits her t'embrace: </l>
                <l>And it's vnseemely though it sometime falles, </l>
                <l>When any sexe vsurpes anothers place. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Deere, their wounted course thy cares inure; </l>
                <l>I may haue matters that import the state, </l>
                <l>Whose opning vp might my disgrace procure, </l>
                <l>Whose weight would for thy weaknesse be too great. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="eng000261-170-b"/>
            <sp who="#eng000261-portia" xml:id="eng000261-e118570">
              <speaker>Port. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I was not (Brutus) match'd with thee, to bee </l>
                <l>A partner only of thy boorde and bed, </l>
                <l>Each seruile whore in those might equall me, </l>
                <l>That did her selfe to nought but pleasure wed; </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>No, Portia spousde thee with a minde t'abide </l>
                <l>Thy fellow in all fortunes, good, or ill. </l>
                <l>With chaines of mutuall loue together tyde, </l>
                <l>As those that haue two breasts, one heart, two soules, one will. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>With sacred bands whom holy Hymen bindes, </l>
                <l>They tweene them should communicate all things; </l>
                <l>Yea both the bodies labors, and the mindes, </l>
                <l>Whence either pleasure or displeasure springs. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>If thus thou seeke thy sorrowes to conceale </l>
                <l>Through a disdaine, or a mistrust of me; </l>
                <l>Then to the world what way can I reueale, </l>
                <l>How great a matter I would doe for thee. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And though our sexe too talkatiue be deem'd, </l>
                <l>As those whose tongues import our greatest powres, </l>
                <l>For secrets still bad treasurers esteem'd </l>
                <l>Of others greedy, prodigall of ours; </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Good education may reforme defects, </l>
                <l>And I this vantage haue t'a vertuous life, </l>
                <l>Which other mindes do want, and mine respects: </l>
                <l>I'm Catoes daughter, and I'm Brutus wife; </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet would I not repose my trust in ought, </l>
                <l>Still thinking that thy crosse was great to beare, </l>
                <l>Till that my courage was t'a triall brought, </l>
                <l>Which suffring for thy cause can nothing feare. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>For first t'experience how I could comport, </l>
                <l>With sterne afflictions spirit-enfeebling blowes, </l>
                <l>Ere I would seeke t'assault thee in this sort, </l>
                <l>To whom my soule a duteous reuerence owes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Loe, heere a wound, which makes me not to smart, </l>
                <l>Though by my selfe being made, to make me knowne, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-171-a"/>
                <l>Since thy distresse strikes deeper in my heart, </l>
                <l>Thy griefe (lifes ioy) makes me neglect mine owne. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-marcus-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e119030">
              <speaker>Brut. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Thou must (deare loue) that which thou sought receiue, </l>
                <l>Thy heart so high a saile t'a tempest beares, </l>
                <l>That thy great courage doth deserue to haue </l>
                <l>Our enterprise entrusted to thine eares. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Thy magnanimitie preuailes so farre, </l>
                <l>That it my resolution must controule: </l>
                <l>And of my bosome doth the depths vnbarre, </l>
                <l>To lodge thee in the centre of my soule. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Thou seest in what a state the state now stands, </l>
                <l>Of whose strong pillars Caesar spoil'd the best: </l>
                <l>Whilst by his owne preuenting others handes, </l>
                <l>Our famous father fell amongst the rest. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>That insolent vsurper doth presume </l>
                <l>To re-erect detested Tarquines throne, </l>
                <l>Thus the worlds mistresse all-commanding Rome, </l>
                <l>Must entertaine no minion now but one. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Th'old blood of Mars that marks to what he tends, </l>
                <l>Swells with disdaine, their countryes scorne to see, </l>
                <l>And I'm one of the number that intends </l>
                <l>By his death, or mine owne, to be made free. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-portia" xml:id="eng000261-e119290">
              <speaker>Port. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And without me can thou resolue so soone </l>
                <l>T'assay the dangers of a doubtfull strife? </l>
                <l>As if dispair'd and alwayes to b'vndone, </l>
                <l>Being tyr'd of me, yea tyr'd of thy life. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet since thou thus thy rash designe hath showne, </l>
                <l>Leaue Portias portion, venter not her part: </l>
                <l>Endanger nought but that which is thine owne, </l>
                <l>Go where thou lik'st, I will hold still thy heart. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But lest by holding of thy best part backe, </l>
                <l>That th'other perish t'aggrauate my grones, </l>
                <l>That would be so thought guiltie of thy wrack, </l>
                <l>Take all thy treasure to the Seaes at once. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-171-b"/>
              <lg>
                <l>Like th'Asian Monarks wife that with short haires, </l>
                <l>(Sad signes of bondage) past still where he past, </l>
                <l>To weare away, or beare away thy cares, </l>
                <l>Ile folow thee, and of thy fortune taste. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>These hands that were with my owne blood imbru'd, </l>
                <l>To strike another may more strength afford: </l>
                <l>At least when thou by th'enemie art pursu'de, </l>
                <l>Ile set my selfe betwixt thee and his sword. </l>
                <l>But if too great a priuiledge I claime, </l>
                <l>Whose actions all should be disposde by thee: </l>
                <l>Ah, pardon me (deare Brutus,) do but blame </l>
                <l>These my excessiue sorrowes, and not mee. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-marcus-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e119590">
              <speaker>Brut. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Thou ask'st what thou shouldst giue, forgiue deare mate, </l>
                <l>This ventrous course of mine, which must haue place, </l>
                <l>Though it make fortune tyrant of our state, </l>
                <l>Whose fickle foot-steps vertue grieues to trace. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And wonder not, though this towards thee I proue, </l>
                <l>Since priuate passions now all powre haue left; </l>
                <l>For I regard not glory, profit, loue, </l>
                <l>Nor no respect that doth import me most: </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>So to the land of which I hold my life, </l>
                <l>I may performe the worke that I intend, </l>
                <l>Let me be call'd vnkind vnto my wife: </l>
                <l>Yea worst of all, ingrate vnto my friend: </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But as th'instinct of nature makes vs know, </l>
                <l>There are degrees of dutie to be past: </l>
                <l>Of which the first we to th'immortalls owe, </l>
                <l>The next t'our Countrey, and t'our friends the last. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Prowd tyrants from his natiue bounds to driue, </l>
                <l>Did th'author of my race with ardent zeale, </l>
                <l>Make those to die whom he had made to liue, </l>
                <l>And spoild himselfe to aduance the commonweale? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>To raise the state which Caesar now ore-throwes, </l>
                <l>That bred so many braue men whilst it stood, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-172-a"/>
                <l>He with the Tyrant interchanging blowes, </l>
                <l>Most gloriously did offer vp his blood. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And did that man t'oppresse the common fo, </l>
                <l>Then damne his sonnes to death? and with drie eyes? </l>
                <l>And is his successor degenerd so, </l>
                <l>That he in abiect bondage basely lyes? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>No, his posteritie his name not staines, </l>
                <l>That t'imitate his steps doth yet draw neere; </l>
                <l>Yet of his spirit in vs some sparke remaines, </l>
                <l>That more then life our libertie hold deare. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-portia" xml:id="eng000261-e120000">
              <speaker>Port. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Then prosecute thy course, for I protest, </l>
                <l>Though with some griefe, my soule the same approues: </l>
                <l>This resolution doth become thy breast, </l>
                <l>Where in the spheare of honor vertue moues. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And doe this interprise no more deferre, </l>
                <l>What thee contents, to me contentment brings; </l>
                <l>I to my life thy saftie doe preferre, </l>
                <l>But hold thy honor deare aboue all things. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>It would but let the world my weaknesse see, </l>
                <l>If I sought my delights, not thy desires: </l>
                <l>Though it giue griefe, and threaten death to me, </l>
                <l>Goe follow forth that which thy fame requires. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Though nature, sexe, and education breed </l>
                <l>No power in me, that's with my purpose euen; </l>
                <l>He lend assistance to th'intended deed, </l>
                <l>If vowes and prayers may penetrate the heauen: </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But difficulties huge my fancie findes, </l>
                <l>Saue the successe nought can defray my feare: </l>
                <l>Ah, Fortune alwayes frownes on worthy mindes, </l>
                <l>As hating all that trust in ought saue her. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet I dispaire not but thou may preuaile, </l>
                <l>And by this course t'appease my present grones, </l>
                <l>I this aduantage haue which cannot faile, </l>
                <l>Ile be a freemans wife, or else be nones. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-172-b"/>
              <lg>
                <l>For if all prosper not as we pretend, </l>
                <l>And that the heauens Romes bondage do decree, </l>
                <l>Straight with thy libertie my life shall end, </l>
                <l>Who haue no comfort but what comes from thee. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>My father hath me taught what way to die, </l>
                <l>By which if I be barr'd t'encounter death, </l>
                <l>Another meanes (though farre more strange) Ile trie, </l>
                <l>For after Brutus none shall see me breathe. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-marcus-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e120410">
              <speaker>Brut. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Thou for my cause abandon'd others else, </l>
                <l>But now forsakst thy selfe t'adhere to me, </l>
                <l>That of thy passions thus the powre repells, </l>
                <l>And with thy minde discords with mine t'agree. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Ile since by thee approou'd securely goe, </l>
                <l>And vilipend the dangers of this life, </l>
                <l>Heauens make my enterprise to prosper so, </l>
                <l>That I prooue worthy of so worthy a wife. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But ah! of all thy words those grieue me most, </l>
                <l>That bost me with th'abridgement of thy dayes; </l>
                <l>What? though I in so good a cause were lost, </l>
                <l>None flies th'appointed fate that for him staies. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Do not defraud the world of thy rare worth, </l>
                <l>But of thy Brutus the remembrance loue, </l>
                <l>And from so faire a prison breake not forth, </l>
                <l>Till first the fates haue forcde thee to remoue. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-portia" xml:id="eng000261-e120620">
              <speaker>Port. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I feare the heauens haue our confusion sworne, </l>
                <l>Since this ill age can with no good accord; </l>
                <l>Thou and my father (ah) should haue bin borne, </l>
                <l>When Vertue was aduauncde, and Vice abhorrd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then ere the light of vertue was declinde, </l>
                <l>Your worth had reuerencde bin, not throwne away, </l>
                <l>Where now ye both haue but in darkenes shinde, </l>
                <l>As starres by night, that had bin sunnes by day. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-marcus-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e120730">
              <speaker>Brut. </speaker>
              <l>My treasure, striue to pacifie thy breast, </l>
              <l>Lest sorrowes but sinistrously presage, </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-173-a"/>
              <l>That which thou would not wish, and hope the best, </l>
              <l>Though vertue now must act on Fortunes stage. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="eng000261-e120780">Exeunt. </stage>
            <div type="chorus" xml:id="eng000261-e120790">
              <head>Chorus. </head>
              <lg>
                <l>THan libertie of earthly things </l>
                <l>What more delights a generous breast? </l>
                <l>That doth receiue, </l>
                <l>And can conceiue, </l>
                <l>The matchlesse treasure that it brings; </l>
                <l>It making men securely rest, </l>
                <l>As all perceiue, </l>
                <l>Doth none deceiue, </l>
                <l>Whilst weigh'd with doubts none ballanc'd hings, </l>
                <l>But feard for nought, doth what seemes best: </l>
                <l>Then men are men when they are all their owne, </l>
                <l>Not but by others badges when made knowne. </l>
                <l>Yet should we not mis-spending houres, </l>
                <l>A freedome seeke, as oft it falles, </l>
                <l>With an intent, </l>
                <l>But to content </l>
                <l>These vaine delights and appetites of ours, </l>
                <l>For then but being made greater thralles, </l>
                <l>We might repent, </l>
                <l>Our not being pent </l>
                <l>In stricter bounds by others powres, </l>
                <l>Whilst feare licentious thoughts appalles: </l>
                <l>Of all the tyrants that the world affords, </l>
                <l>Ones owne affections are the fiercest Lords. </l>
                <l>As Libertines those onely liue, </l>
                <l>That from the bands of vice set free, </l>
                <l>Vile thoughts cancell, </l>
                <l>And seeke t'excell </l>
                <l>In all that doth true glorie giue, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-173-b"/>
                <l>From which when as no tyrants be, </l>
                <l>Them to repell, </l>
                <l>And to compell </l>
                <l>They deedes against their thoughts to striue, </l>
                <l>They blestare in a high degree, </l>
                <l>For such of same the scroules can hardly fill, </l>
                <l>Whose wit is bounded by anothers will. </l>
                <l>That Rome from Tarquins yoke redeemde, </l>
                <l>Who first obtaind, </l>
                <l>And then maintaind </l>
                <l>Their libertie so deerely lou'd; </l>
                <l>They from all things that odious seemd, </l>
                <l>Though not constraind, </l>
                <l>Themselues restraind, </l>
                <l>And willingly all good approu'd, </l>
                <l>Bent to be much, yet wel esteemd; </l>
                <l>And how could such but aime at some great end, </l>
                <l>Whom libertie did leade, and glory attend? </l>
                <l>They leading valorous legions foorth, </l>
                <l>Though wanting kings, triumph'd ouer kings, </l>
                <l>And still aspird, </l>
                <l>By Mars inspir'd </l>
                <l>To conquer all from South to North; </l>
                <l>Then lending Fame their Eagles wings, </l>
                <l>They all acquir'd, </l>
                <l>That was requir'd, </l>
                <l>To make them rare for rarest things, </l>
                <l>The world being witnesse of their Worth: </l>
                <l>Thus those great minds that domineer'd ouer all. </l>
                <l>Did make themselues first free, then others thrall: </l>
                <l>But we that hold nought but their name, </l>
                <l>From that to which they in times gone, </l>
                <l>Did high ascend, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-174-a"/>
                <l>Must low discend, </l>
                <l>And bound their glory with our shame. </l>
                <l>Whilst on an abiect tyrants throne </l>
                <l>We basely attend, </l>
                <l>And doe intend, </l>
                <l>Vs for our fortune still to frame, </l>
                <l>Not it for vs, and all for one: </l>
                <l>As libertie a courage doth impart, </l>
                <l>So bondage doth disbend, els breake the heart. </l>
                <l>Yet O who knowes but Rome to grace, </l>
                <l>Another Brutus may arise, </l>
                <l>That may effect </l>
                <l>What we affect: </l>
                <l>And Tarquins steppes make Caesar trace, </l>
                <l>Though seeming dangers to dispise, </l>
                <l>He doth suspect, </l>
                <l>What we exspect, </l>
                <l>Which from his breast hath banish'd peace, </l>
                <l>Though fairely he his feares disguise: </l>
                <l>Of tyrants th'iniurie reuenge affords, </l>
                <l>All feare but theirs, and they feare all mens swords. </l>
              </lg>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="eng000261-e121640">
          <head>ACT. IIII. </head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="eng000261-e121650">
            <head>SCENE. I. </head>
            <stage xml:id="eng000261-e121660">Decius Brutus Albinus, Marcus Brutus. Caius Cassius. </stage>
            <lg>
              <l>DEare cosin, Cassius did acquaint mine eares, </l>
              <l>With a designe that toss'd my minde a space, </l>
              <l>For when strange newes a strangers breath first beares, </l>
              <l>Then should not trust t'each rash report giue place. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>I would not then discouer what I thought: </l>
              <l>Lest he t'entrap my tongue a snare had fram'd, </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-174-b"/>
              <l>Till I with thee t'a conference first was brought, </l>
              <l>Whom he for patron of his purpose namde. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>One should beware to whom his minde he leaues, </l>
              <l>In dangerous times when tales by walles are tolde, </l>
              <l>Men make themselues most miserably slaues, </l>
              <l>Of those to whom their secrets they vnfolde. </l>
            </lg>
            <sp who="#eng000261-marcus-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e121820">
              <speaker>M. Bru. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>As Cassius tolde thee pittying Romes distresse, </l>
                <l>That t'our disgrace in bondage doth remaine, </l>
                <l>We straight intend what euer we professe, </l>
                <l>With Caesars blood to wash away this staine. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Though for this end a few sufficient are, </l>
                <l>To whom their vertue courage doth impart, </l>
                <l>Yet were wee loath to wrong thy worth so farre, </l>
                <l>As of such glorie to giue thee no part. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Since both this cause, and that thy name thee binde, </l>
                <l>In this aduentrous band to be comprisde, </l>
                <l>There needes no rhetoricke to raise thy minde, </l>
                <l>That t'execute which thou should haue deuisde. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-decius-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e121980">
              <speaker>D. Bru. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I thoght no creature shuld my purpose know </l>
                <l>But he whose intrest promisde mutuall cares, </l>
                <l>Of those to whom one would his secrets show, </l>
                <l>No greater pledge of trust than to know theirs. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>As when two meet being mask'd (though whiles neare frends) </l>
                <l>With them as strangers no respect takes place, </l>
                <l>But when that friendship one of them pretends, </l>
                <l>Then th'other likewise doth vncloude his face: </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>So as thou first, Ile now at last be bold </l>
                <l>My breast with the same birth long great hath gone, </l>
                <l>Yet I t'another durst it not vnfolde, </l>
                <l>Nor yet attempt to compasse it alone. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But since this course, of which I long did pause, </l>
                <l>On such great pillars now so strongly stands, </l>
                <l>Whose countanaunce may giue credite t'any cause, </l>
                <l>It hath my heart, and it shall haue my hands. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="eng000261-175-a"/>
            <sp who="#eng000261-cassius" xml:id="eng000261-e122190">
              <speaker>C. Cass. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>T'our enterprise propitious signes are sent, </l>
                <l>So that the gods would giue vs courage thus, </l>
                <l>For all that euer heard of our intent, </l>
                <l>Would willingly engage themselues with vs, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Let other men discourse of vertuous rites, </l>
                <l>Ours but by th'action only should be showne, </l>
                <l>Bare speculation is but for such sprites, </l>
                <l>As want of powre or courage keepes vnknowne, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>In those that Vertue view when crown'd with deeds, </l>
                <l>Whose beauties through the glasse of glory shinde, </l>
                <l>Sh'a violent desire t'imbrace her breedes, </l>
                <l>As th'adamant to th'yrne being to the minde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>What though a number now in darkenesse lies, </l>
                <l>That are too weake for matters of such weight, </l>
                <l>We that are eminent in all mens eies, </l>
                <l>Let vs still hold the height of honour straight. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-marcus-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e122400">
              <speaker>M. Br. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Whilst that our faction might be strangthned thus </l>
                <l>I labord much to purchase all their powres, </l>
                <l>Whom hate towards Caesar, loue to Rome, or t'vs, </l>
                <l>Might moue t'imbarke in those great hopes of ours. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>By sickenesse being imprison'd in his bed, </l>
                <l>Whilst I Ligarius spide whom paines did pricke, </l>
                <l>When I had said with words that anguish bred, </l>
                <l>In what a time Ligarius art thou sicke. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>He answerd straight as I had phisicke brought, </l>
                <l>Or that he had imagin'd my designe, </l>
                <l>If worthy of thy selfe thou wouldst do ought, </l>
                <l>Then Brutus I am whole, and wholie thine. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Since Caesar causde him be accusde of late, </l>
                <l>For taking Pompeys part, yet at this houre, </l>
                <l>He (though absolu'd) doth still the tyrant hate, </l>
                <l>For being endangerd by his lawlesse powre. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Whilst it exasprates thus such great sprites spites, </l>
                <l>Heauen of our course the progresse doth direct, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-175-b"/>
                <l>One inspiration all our soules incites, </l>
                <l>That haue aduisdly sworne this fact t'effect. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-decius-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e122660">
              <speaker>D. Br. </speaker>
              <l>So I with Cicero did conferre at length, </l>
              <l>Who I perceiue the present state detests, </l>
              <l>And though that age deminisht haue his strength, </l>
              <l>In him a will t'auenge his country rests. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-marcus-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e122710">
              <speaker>M. Br. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>That man whose loue stil towards his country shind, </l>
                <l>Would willingly the commonwealth restore, </l>
                <l>Then he I know, though he conceales his minde, </l>
                <l>None Caesar more dislikes, nor likes vs more. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet to his custodie Ile not commit, </l>
                <l>The secrets of our enterprise so soone, </l>
                <l>Men may themselues be oftentimes not fit, </l>
                <l>To doe the things that they would wish were done, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>He still being timorous, and by age growne worse, </l>
                <l>Might chance to lay our honor in the dust, </l>
                <l>All cowards must inconstant be of force, </l>
                <l>With bold designes none fearefull breasts can trust. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then some of ours would holde their hands still pure, </l>
                <l>That ere they be suspected, for a space </l>
                <l>Amidst the tumult may remaine secure, </l>
                <l>And with the people mediate our peace. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But who than Tullius fitter for that turne, </l>
                <l>Whose eloquence is vsde t'enchant their eares? </l>
                <l>His banishment they in balcke gownes did mourne, </l>
                <l>Whose age and merites each one reurence beares. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-cassius" xml:id="eng000261-e122970">
              <speaker>C. Cass. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Those studious wits that haue through dangers gone, </l>
                <l>Would still be out, ere that they enter in; </l>
                <l>Who must of many things, resolue of none, </l>
                <l>And thinking of the end, cannot beginne. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The mind that lookes no further than the eie, </l>
                <l>And more to Nature trusts, than vnto Art, </l>
                <l>Such doubtfull fortunes fittest is to trie, </l>
                <l>A furious actor for a desprate parte. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-176-a"/>
              <lg>
                <l>We haue enow, and of the best degree, </l>
                <l>Whose hands are to their hearts, their hearts t'vs true, </l>
                <l>And if that we seeke moe, I feare we be </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>T' act close too many, if disclosde, too few. </l>
                <l>Let vs aduise with an industrious care, </l>
                <l>Now ere the tyrant intercept our mindes; </l>
                <l>The time, the place, the manner, when, and where, </l>
                <l>That we should trust our treasure to the windes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And since our fortunes in the ballance hing, </l>
                <l>Let euery point be circumspectly weight'd, </l>
                <l>A circumstance, or an indifferent thing, </l>
                <l>May whiles marre all for not being well conueigh'd. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-marcus-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e123230">
              <speaker>M. Br. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>As for the time, none could be wish'd more fit, </l>
                <l>Than this that's present to performe our vow, </l>
                <l>Since all the people must allow of it, </l>
                <l>Mou'd by a recent miscontentment now. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>When represented in his triumph past, </l>
                <l>Great Catoes mangled entrailes made them weepe, </l>
                <l>And desprate Scipio whilst he leap'd at last, </l>
                <l>To seeke a Sanctuarie amidst the depth. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then all those great men that in seuerall partes, </l>
                <l>Bent for Romes freedome Caesar did ouerthrow, </l>
                <l>Did by their pictures pierce the peoples harts, </l>
                <l>And made a pitteous (though a pompous) show. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>So that they did conceiue a iust disdaine, </l>
                <l>To be vpbraided in so strange a sort, </l>
                <l>Whilst he that onely by their losse did gaine </l>
                <l>Of their calamitie but made a sport. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But yet his purpose grieues them most of all, </l>
                <l>Since that he striues to be proclaimd a King, </l>
                <l>And not contents himselfe to make vs thrall, </l>
                <l>But to perpetuall bondage would vs bring. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Thus whilst the people are with him displeasde, </l>
                <l>We best may doe that which t'our part belongs; </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-176-b"/>
                <l>For after this they may be best appeas'd, </l>
                <l>If whilst their wrath doth last we venge their wrongs. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And since we nought intend but what is right, </l>
                <l>Whilst from our contrey we remooue disgrace: </l>
                <l>Let all be acted in the Senates sight, </l>
                <l>A common cause, and in a common place. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Let those whose guiltie thoughts doe damne their deeds </l>
                <l>In corners like Mineruaes birds abide: </l>
                <l>That which t'our countrey good, t'vs glory breeds, </l>
                <l>May by the lights of heauen and earth be tryde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The Senatours by our ensample mou'd, </l>
                <l>Pleasde with this action that imports them too, </l>
                <l>To haue the yoke of tyrranie remou'd, </l>
                <l>May at the least authorize what we doe. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>So all the Senatours were said of old, </l>
                <l>To haue king Romulus amongst them torne: </l>
                <l>That than to tyrranize was growne to bold, </l>
                <l>And from his first humanitie had worne. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-decius-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e123740">
              <speaker>D. Brut. </speaker>
              <l>Yea, what though Caesar were immortall made </l>
              <l>As Romulus, whose deitie him reuiues? </l>
              <l>It's easier as a God t'adore him dead, </l>
              <l>Then as a king t'obey him whilst he liues. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-cassius" xml:id="eng000261-e123790">
              <speaker>C. Cass. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>That place indeed, most for our glory makes, </l>
                <l>A Theater worthy of so great an act: </l>
                <l>Where in their sight from whom most power he takes, </l>
                <l>We of the tyrant vengeance may exact. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But I must recommend vnto your minde, </l>
                <l>A course (though strict) of which we must allowe, </l>
                <l>Least it ore-throw all that we haue design'd, </l>
                <l>Being past recouerie, if neglected now, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>There is Antonius Caesars greatest friend, </l>
                <l>A man whose nature tyrranie affects, </l>
                <l>Whom all the souldiors doe delight t'attend, </l>
                <l>As one that nought but to command respects. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-177-a"/>
              <lg>
                <l>I feare that he when we haue Caesar slaine, </l>
                <l>To th'other faction furnish still a head: </l>
                <l>So when we ende, we must beginne againe, </l>
                <l>Against one liuing worse then he that's dead. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And in my iudgement, I would thinke it best, </l>
                <l>When sacrifiz'd the prowd vsurper lyes, </l>
                <l>That that seditious enemie of rest, </l>
                <l>Should fall with him with whom he first did rise, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Thus of our libertie we now may lay, </l>
                <l>A solid ground that can be shak'd by none: </l>
                <l>Those of their purpose that a part delay </l>
                <l>Two labours haue, that might haue had but one. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-marcus-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e124100">
              <speaker>M. Brut. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I cannot Cassius condiscend to kill </l>
                <l>(Thus from the path of Iustice to decline) </l>
                <l>One faultlesse yet, lest after he prooue ill, </l>
                <l>So to preuent his guiltinesse by mine. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>No, no, that neither honest were, nor iust, </l>
                <l>Which rigorous forme would but the worlde affright: </l>
                <l>Men by this meane our meaning might mistrust, </l>
                <l>And for a little wrong damne all that's right; </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>If we but only kill the common foe, </l>
                <l>Our zeale t'our countrey must acquire due praise: </l>
                <l>But if like Tyrants tyrannizing so, </l>
                <l>We will be thought that which we raze to raise. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And where we but intend t'aduance the state, </l>
                <l>Though by endangering what we hold most deare; </l>
                <l>If slaying him as arm'd e by priuate hate, </l>
                <l>We to the world still partiall will appeare. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Ah, ah, we must but too much murder see, </l>
                <l>That without doing euill cannot do good: </l>
                <l>And would the gods that Rome could be made free, </l>
                <l>Without th'effusion of one drope of blood. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then their is hope that Anthonie in ende, </l>
                <l>When first our vertue doth direct the way: </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-177-b"/>
                <l>Will leagu'd with vs the libertie defend, </l>
                <l>And being brought backe will blush for going astray. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-cassius" xml:id="eng000261-e124410">
              <speaker>C. Cass. </speaker>
              <l>Well Brutus, I protest against my will, </l>
              <l>From this blacke clowd, what euer tempest fall, </l>
              <l>That mercie but most cruellie doth kill. </l>
              <l>Which thus saues one, that once may plague vs all. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-decius-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e124460">
              <speaker>D. Brut. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>When Caesar with the Senators sits downe, </l>
                <l>In this your iudgements generally accord; </l>
                <l>That for affecting wrongfully the crowne, </l>
                <l>He lawfully may perish by the sword. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>No greater harme t'our purpose can be brought, </l>
                <l>Then by protracting of th'appointed time, </l>
                <l>Least that which acted would b'a vertue thought, </l>
                <l>Be (if preuented) consterd as a crime. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Can one thing long in many mindes be pent? </l>
                <l>No, purposes would neuer be delaid </l>
                <l>That are interpreted but by th'euent, </l>
                <l>If prospering reason, treason if betraid. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>There may amongst our selues some man remaine, </l>
                <l>Whom if afraid, his pardon to procure, </l>
                <l>Or if being greedie for the hope of gaine, </l>
                <l>Time to disclose his consorts may allure. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then ruine for our recompence we reape, </l>
                <l>If ought our course by being abortiue marre, </l>
                <l>For if discouer'd once, we cannot scape, </l>
                <l>As Tyrants eares heare much, their hands reach farre. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-cassius" xml:id="eng000261-e124720">
              <speaker>C. Cass. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>The breast in which so deepe a secret dwelles, </l>
                <l>Would not be long chargde with so weightie cares, </l>
                <l>For I coniecture by appearance else, </l>
                <l>Mo priuie are t'our minds then we to theirs: </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Euen but of late one Casca came to see, </l>
                <l>That curious was to haue our purpose knowne, </l>
                <l>And said to him that which thou bidst from me, </l>
                <l>To me by Brutus hath at length bin showen. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-178-a"/>
              <lg>
                <l>Then by some things that he had learn'd before, </l>
                <l>He of our course deepe in discourse did fall, </l>
                <l>Till Casca thinking that he had knowne more, </l>
                <l>Scarse kept his tongue from staggering out with all. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then Laena to vs once came in like sort, </l>
                <l>And wish'd that our designe might prosper well; </l>
                <l>Yet vs to haste did earnestly exhort, </l>
                <l>Since others told what we refusde to tell: </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Whilst strangers rest familiar with our minde, </l>
                <l>And ere t'our knowledge thus t'our counsell rise, </l>
                <l>Make forward fast, or we will come behind. </l>
                <l>Fame wing'd with breath most violently flies. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-marcus-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e124980">
              <speaker>M. Brut. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Their words but from vncertainties burst forth, </l>
                <l>For whilst considering of their bondage thus: </l>
                <l>Of Caesars tyrranie, and of our worth, </l>
                <l>They thinke this should be done, and done by vs: </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Such coniurations to confirme of olde, </l>
                <l>Some drinking others bloods; swore on their swords, </l>
                <l>And cursing those that did their course vnfold, </l>
                <l>Vsde imprecations, execrable words. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And yet then this though voluntarily vow'd, </l>
                <l>Free from all bonds, saue that which vertue bindes, </l>
                <l>More constantly no course was still allow'd. </l>
                <l>Till now that th'end must manifest our minds. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And since so many frankly keepe their faith, </l>
                <l>Still what they first design'd t'accomplish bent: </l>
                <l>No doubt in spight of fickle fortunes wrath, </l>
                <l>But the successe shall yeeld our soules content. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Might some few Thebans from the Spartans pride, </l>
                <l>By diuers tyrants deaths redeeme their towne? </l>
                <l>And one Athenian that his vertue tryde, </l>
                <l>By thirtie Tyrants ruins win renowne? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And to the Greekes are we inferiour growne, </l>
                <l>That where they haue so many tyrants spoild, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-178-b"/>
                <l>There cannot one be by vs all orethrowne, </l>
                <l>Whose state yet brangling may be soone imbroyld? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>O I'm resolu'd, and with my thoughts decree, </l>
                <l>What euer fortune either sweet or sowre, </l>
                <l>I shall my soyle from tyrannie set free, </l>
                <l>Or then my selfe free from the tyrants powre. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-decius-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e125340">
              <speaker>D. Br. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>By Lepidus inuited this last night, </l>
                <l>Whilst Caesar went to suppe, and I with him, </l>
                <l>Of all deaths shapes to talke we tooke delight, </l>
                <l>So at the table to beguile the time. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And whilst our iudgements all about were tride, </l>
                <l>Straight Caesar (as transported) to the rest </l>
                <l>With a most sodaine exclamation cride, </l>
                <l>O, of all deaths vnlookt for death is best. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>For from our selues it steales our selues so fast, </l>
                <l>That euen the mind no fearefull forme can see, </l>
                <l>Then is the paine ere apprehended past, </l>
                <l>All sowres ere tasted would disgested be. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The threatned destinie thus he diuinde, </l>
                <l>It would appeare diuinely being inspirde, </l>
                <l>For now I hope that he shall shortly finde, </l>
                <l>That forme of death which he himselfe desirde. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-cassius" xml:id="eng000261-e125550">
              <speaker>C. Cass. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Whilst of our band the fury flames most hot, </l>
                <l>And that their will t'atchiue this worke is such, </l>
                <l>Lest Caesars absence disappoint the plot, </l>
                <l>Which would of some abate the courage much, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>It (Decius) were exceedingly well done, </l>
                <l>That to his lodging you addressd your way, </l>
                <l>Him by some meanes to further forward soone, </l>
                <l>Lest by some sodaine chaunce allur'd to stay. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-decius-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e125660">
              <speaker>D. Br. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>There where the Senate minds this day to sit, </l>
                <l>Stand all prepar'd t'approach where danger dwells, </l>
                <l>And for the sacrifice when all is fit, </l>
                <l>Ile bring an offring consecrated else. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="eng000261-e125720">Exeunt </stage>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="eng000261-e125730">
            <pb xml:id="eng000261-179-a"/>
            <head>ACT. IIII. SCENE II. </head>
            <stage xml:id="eng000261-e125740">Caesar, Calphurnia, Decius Brutus. </stage>
            <lg>
              <l>LOng-lookt for time that should the glory yeeld, </l>
              <l>Which I through Neptunes trustlesse raigne haue sought, </l>
              <l>And through the dust of many a bloodie field, </l>
              <l>As by all dangers worthy to be bought. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Thy comming now those lowring shadowes cleares, </l>
              <l>That did th'horizon of my hopes ore-cast, </l>
              <l>This day defrayes the toyles of many yeares, </l>
              <l>And brings the haru'st of all my labors past. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>The Senators a messenger haue sent, </l>
              <l>Most earnestly entreating me to come, </l>
              <l>And heare my selfe discernd by their consent, </l>
              <l>To weare a crowne ouer all excepting Rome. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Thus they deuise conditions at this houre, </l>
              <l>For him, of whom Mars hath made them the prey; </l>
              <l>As subiects limite could their soueraignes powre, </l>
              <l>That must haue minde of nought but to obey. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>But hauing pacifide those present things, </l>
              <l>I minde to leade my valorous legions forth, </l>
              <l>To th'orientall realmes, adoring kings </l>
              <l>That can exhibite honors due to worth. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Than swimme my thoughts in th'Ocean of delight, </l>
              <l>Whilst on the pillow of soft praise reposde, </l>
              <l>Those eies to gaze vpon my glories light, </l>
              <l>That enuy op'ned, admiration closde. </l>
            </lg>
            <sp who="#eng000261-calphurnia" xml:id="eng000261-e126050">
              <speaker>Cal. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ah, though your fancies great contentment find, </l>
                <l>Whilst thus the world your vertue doth aduance, </l>
                <l>Yet a prepostrous terrour stings my minde, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-179-b"/>
                <l>And boasts me with I know not what mischance, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>My wauering hopes oreballanc'd are with feares, </l>
                <l>That to my soule sinistrous signes impart, </l>
                <l>And ominous rumours so assault mine eares, </l>
                <l>That they almost make breaches in my heart. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e126160">
              <speaker>Caesar. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What, doe debattelld Pompeys followers striue </l>
                <l>To recollect their ruines from the dust? </l>
                <l>Dare they that only by my tollerance liue, </l>
                <l>More to their strength than to my fauour trust? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Or dost thou feare his sonnes deiected state, </l>
                <l>That steales infamous flying through those floods, </l>
                <l>Which his great father, Admiral of late, </l>
                <l>Did plant with ships til all their waues seemd woods? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then makes his brothers death his courage more, </l>
                <l>Since by them straited in a bloodie strife, </l>
                <l>I, that in all the battels giuen before, </l>
                <l>Did fight for victorie, then fought for life. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Or whilst to march toward Parthia I prepare, </l>
                <l>Doth a suspition thus afflict thy sprite, </l>
                <l>For Crassus fortune feard that perisht there, </l>
                <l>Th'opprobrious prey of the Barbarians spight? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>To those same bands that Cassius thence brought back, </l>
                <l>A place amongst my legions Ile allow, </l>
                <l>Whose foes shall find whilst they auenge th'olde wracke </l>
                <l>Though the same sheep, another shepheard now. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Do not imagine matters to bemone, </l>
                <l>For whilst there stands a world, can Caesar fall? </l>
                <l>Though thousand thousands were coniurd in one, </l>
                <l>I, and my fortune might confound them all. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-calphurnia" xml:id="eng000261-e126470">
              <speaker>Cal. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>No, none of those my minde doth miscontent, </l>
                <l>That vndisguisde still like themselues remaine, </l>
                <l>Vnlookt for harmes are hardest to preuent, </l>
                <l>There is no guard against concealde disdaine, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But in whom further can your trust repose, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-180-a"/>
                <l>Whom danger now ouer all, by all attends, </l>
                <l>Where priuate men but onely feare their foes, </l>
                <l>Oft kings haue greatest cause to feare their frends, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>For since being trusted fittest to betray, </l>
                <l>Those vnto whom ones fauour force affords, </l>
                <l>May for his life the worst ambushments lay, </l>
                <l>Whilst falsest hearts are hid with fairest words. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And some report (though priuately) yet plaine, </l>
                <l>That Dolabella and Antonius now, </l>
                <l>By your destruction do pretend t'obtaine, </l>
                <l>That which you keepe by making all men bow. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e126680">
              <speaker>Caesar. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>No corpulent sanguinians make me feare, </l>
                <l>That with more paine their beards than th'enimies strike </l>
                <l>And doe themselues like th'epicurians beare, </l>
                <l>To Bacchus, Mars, and Venus borne alike. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Their hearts do alwayes in their mouthes remaine, </l>
                <l>As streams, whose murmuring shews the course not deep </l>
                <l>Then still they loue to sport, though grosse and plaine, </l>
                <l>And neuer dreame of ought but when they sleep. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But those high sprites that hold their bodies downe, </l>
                <l>Whose visage leane their restlesse thoughts records, </l>
                <l>Whilst they their cares depth in their bosoms drowne, </l>
                <l>Their silence feares me more than th'others words. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Thus Cassius now and Brutus seeme to hold </l>
                <l>Some great thing in their mind, whose fire whiles smoks </l>
                <l>What Brutus would, he vehemently would, </l>
                <l>Thinke what they like, I like not their pale lookes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet with their worth this cannot well agree, </l>
                <l>In whom of vertue th'image seeme to shine, </l>
                <l>Can those that haue receiu'd their liues from me, </l>
                <l>Prooue so ingrate againe as to take mine? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Dare Cassius me pursue new hopes to haue, </l>
                <l>At th' Helespont that fortune feard to trie, </l>
                <l>And like a dastard did his Gallies leaue, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-180-b"/>
                <l>In all (saue corage) though more strong than I? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Shall I suspect that Brutus seekes my blood, </l>
                <l>Whose safetie still I tendred with such care, </l>
                <l>Who when the heauens from mortalls me seclude, </l>
                <l>Is only worthy to be Caesars heire? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-calphurnia" xml:id="eng000261-e127040">
              <speaker>Cal. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>The corners of the heart are hard to know, </l>
                <l>Though of those two the world the best doth deeme, </l>
                <l>Yet do not trust too much th'externall show, </l>
                <l>For men may differ much from what they seeme. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>None oft more fierce than those that look most mild, </l>
                <l>Impietie sometime appeares deuout, </l>
                <l>And that the world the more may be beguilde, </l>
                <l>Whiles Vice can clothe it selfe with Vertues cote. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Though that they haue long since laid hatred downe, </l>
                <l>By benefits bestow'd, you might attend, </l>
                <l>There's no respect can counterpoise a crowne, </l>
                <l>Ambition hath no bounds, nor greed no end. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Through vindicatiue hate, and emulous pride, </l>
                <l>Since some your person, some your place pursue, </l>
                <l>All threatned dangers to preuent prouide, </l>
                <l>Being wise in time, lest out of time you rue. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e127250">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <p>No armor is that can hold treason out. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-calphurnia" xml:id="eng000261-e127270">
              <speaker>Cal. </speaker>
              <p>T'affright your foes with bands be backt about. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e127290">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <p>So dastard tyrants striue themselues to beare. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-calphurnia" xml:id="eng000261-e127310">
              <speaker>Cal. </speaker>
              <p>It better is to giue, than to take feare. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e127330">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <p>No stronger guard than is the peoples loue. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-calphurnia" xml:id="eng000261-e127350">
              <speaker>Calp. </speaker>
              <p>But nought in th'earth dooth more inconstant proue. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e127370">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <p>Guardes shewing feare t'inuade me men might tempt. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-calphurnia" xml:id="eng000261-e127390">
              <speaker>Cal. </speaker>
              <p>Guardes would put them from hope, you from contempt. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e127410">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <p>My breast from terror hath bin alwayes cleare. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-calphurnia" xml:id="eng000261-e127430">
              <speaker>Cal. </speaker>
              <p>When one feares least, oft daunger lurkes most neare. </p>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="eng000261-181-a"/>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e127450">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <p>It's better once to die, than still feare death. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-calphurnia" xml:id="eng000261-e127470">
              <speaker>Cal. </speaker>
              <p>But worst of all to fall by th'enemies wrath. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e127490">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ile not dis-taste my present pleasures so, </l>
                <l>By apprehending what may chaunce to come, </l>
                <l>This world affords but too much time for woe, </l>
                <l>Whilst crosses come contentment to orecome. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>By ioyes in time we must imbrace reliefe, </l>
                <l>That when they end, we in some measure may, </l>
                <l>By their remembrance mitigate the griefe, </l>
                <l>Which still attends all those on th'earth that stay. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I thinke the Senate is assembled now, </l>
                <l>And for my comming doth beginne to gaze, </l>
                <l>Ile goe condignely once t'adorne my brow, </l>
                <l>And feast mine eares by drinking in due praise. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-calphurnia" xml:id="eng000261-e127650">
              <speaker>Cal. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Stay, stay (deere Lord) retire thy steps againe, </l>
                <l>And spare one day to prorogate whole yeares, </l>
                <l>Let not this ominous day beginne thy raigne, </l>
                <l>That fatall and vnfortunate appeares. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>An Astrologian through the world renownde, </l>
                <l>Thy horoscopes iust calculation layes, </l>
                <l>And doth affirme as he by signes hath found, </l>
                <l>That th'Ides of March doe boast to bound thy dayes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Walke not this days where harmes may be receiu'd, </l>
                <l>Since by no great necessity being forcde, </l>
                <l>For though his iudgement may be farre deceiu'd, </l>
                <l>In things that touch thy life, suspect the worst. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e127810">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Whilst I reform'd the Calender by fits, </l>
                <l>That long disordred th'order of the yeare; </l>
                <l>I waded through the depths of all their wits, </l>
                <l>That of the starres the mysteries make cleare. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Those pregnant sprites that walke betwixt the poles, </l>
                <l>And lodge at all the zodiackes seuerall signes, </l>
                <l>Do reade strange wonders wrapt in th'azure scroules, </l>
                <l>Of which our deedes are wordes, our liues are lines. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-181-b"/>
              <lg>
                <l>By speculation of superior powres, </l>
                <l>Some Natures secrets curious are to know, </l>
                <l>As how celestiall bodies rule ouer ours, </l>
                <l>And what their influence effects below. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yea they sometime may strange coniectures make, </l>
                <l>Of those whose parts they by their birth doe proue, </l>
                <l>Since naturally all inclination take, </l>
                <l>From Planets then predominant aboue. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And yet no certaintie can so be had, </l>
                <l>Some vertuously against their starres haue striu'd, </l>
                <l>As Socrates that grew, (though borne but bad,) </l>
                <l>The most accomplisht man that euer liu'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But of the houre ordain'd to close our lights, </l>
                <l>No earth-clogd soule can to the knowledge come; </l>
                <l>For O the destinies farre from our sights, </l>
                <l>In clowds of darknes haue inuolu'd our doome. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And some but onely guesse at great mens falles, </l>
                <l>By bearded comets, and prodigious starres, </l>
                <l>Whose sight-distracting shapes the world appalles, </l>
                <l>As still denouncing terrour, death, or warres. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The time vncertaine is of certaine death, </l>
                <l>And that fantastike man farre past his bounds, </l>
                <l>He is too bold that with ambiguous breath, </l>
                <l>Not speaks of things to come, whose deeps none sounds </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-calphurnia" xml:id="eng000261-e128220">
              <speaker>Cal. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>But this all day did my repose extort, </l>
                <l>And from my breast of cares a tribute clam'd, </l>
                <l>Now vilipend not that which Ile report, </l>
                <l>Though but a dreame, and by a woman dreamd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I thought (alas) the thought yet wounds my breast, </l>
                <l>Then whilst we both as those whom Morpheus weds, </l>
                <l>Lay softly buried with a pleasant rest, </l>
                <l>I in thy bosome, thou within the beds. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then from my soule strange terrours did withdrawe </l>
                <l>Th'exspected peace by apprehended harmes; </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-182-a"/>
                <l>For I imagin'd, no, no doubt I saw, </l>
                <l>And did imbrace thee bloodie in mine armes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Thus whilst my soule by sorrowes was surchargde, </l>
                <l>Of which huge weight it yet some burden beares; </l>
                <l>I big with griefe two elements enlargde, </l>
                <l>Th'aire with my sighes, the water with my teares. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e128430">
              <speaker>Caesar. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>That which I heard, with thy report accords, </l>
                <l>Whilst thou all seemd dissolu'd in griefe at once, </l>
                <l>A heauy murmuring made with mangled words, </l>
                <l>Was interrupted oft by tragicke grones. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The memory, but not the iudgement makes </l>
                <l>Th'impression thus of passions in the braine, </l>
                <l>For what the soule most suffers when it wakes, </l>
                <l>With it asleepe it doth turmoyld remaine. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>From superstitious feares this care proceedes, </l>
                <l>Which stil would watch o're that which thou dost loue, </l>
                <l>And in thy minde melancholy thus breedes, </l>
                <l>Which doth those strange imaginations moue. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-calphurnia" xml:id="eng000261-e128590">
              <speaker>Cal. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ah, in so light account leaue off to hold </l>
                <l>Those fatall warnings that the heauens haue made, </l>
                <l>Which by all meanes most manifest vnfold, </l>
                <l>What dangers huge do hing aboue thy head. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>He with the sacred garlands that diuines, </l>
                <l>By th'entrailes of the consecrated beast, </l>
                <l>Sees in the sacrifice sinistrous signes, </l>
                <l>And I intreate thee do not hence make haste. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e128700">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <l>When I in Spaine against yong Pompey went, </l>
              <l>Thus the diuiner threatned me before, </l>
              <l>Yet did I prosecute my first intent, </l>
              <l>Which with new laurells did my browes decore. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-calphurnia" xml:id="eng000261-e128750">
              <speaker>Cal. </speaker>
              <l>And yet you hardly there as whiles I heare, </l>
              <l>From dangers (farre engagde) redeemd your life, </l>
              <l>But now more monstrous tokens do appeare, </l>
              <l>And I suspect farre worse than open strife. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="eng000261-182-b"/>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e128800">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Lest I too much seeme wedded to my will, </l>
                <l>As one that others counsels scornes t'alow, </l>
                <l>With iealous eyes Ile search about me still, </l>
                <l>And euen mistrust my selfe to trust thee now. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet if I stay the Senators deceiu'd, </l>
                <l>May my beginning straight begin to hate, </l>
                <l>So might I perish seeking to be sau'd, </l>
                <l>By flying, many fall vpon their fate. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But heere one comes that can resolue me much, </l>
                <l>With whom I vse t'aduise affaires of weight: </l>
                <l>Whence comst thou Decius, that thy haste is such? </l>
                <l>Is ought occurr'd that craues our knowledge straight? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-decius-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e128960">
              <speaker>Decius. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I come to tell you how the Senate staies, </l>
                <l>Till your exspected presence blesse their sight, </l>
                <l>And the conclusion yet of all delayes, </l>
                <l>Till that your approbation make it right. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>T'accomplish your contentment they intend, </l>
                <l>And all their thoughts seeme at one obiect bent, </l>
                <l>Saue that they doe amongst themselues contend, </l>
                <l>Who you to please shall strangest wayes inuent. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e129070">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Than that no treasure to my soule more deere, </l>
                <l>Which straight t'enioy from hence I long to part, </l>
                <l>But yet I know not what arrests me heere, </l>
                <l>And makes my feet rebellious to my heart. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>From thee (deare friend) I neuer do conceale </l>
                <l>The waightiest secrets that concerne me most: </l>
                <l>And at this time I likewise will reueale, </l>
                <l>How heauens by signes me with destruction bost: </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>To superstition though not being inclinde, </l>
                <l>My wife by dreames doth now presage my fall: </l>
                <l>It a Sooth-sayer likewise hath diuin'd, </l>
                <l>The sacrifice prodigious seemes t'vs all; </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>So that till this disastrous day be gone, </l>
                <l>All companie I purpose to disuse. </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-183-a"/>
                <l>And to the Senators Ile send some one </l>
                <l>To paint my absence with a faire excuse. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-decius-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e129280">
              <speaker>D. Brut. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Do not repose on superstitious signes, </l>
                <l>You to suspect the people thus to bring, </l>
                <l>Whilst soueraigne-like you limit their designes, </l>
                <l>Seeme not a tyrant seeking to be king. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>How can we satisfie the worlds conceit, </l>
                <l>Whose tongues still in all eares your praise proclames? </l>
                <l>O! shal we bid them leaue to deale in state, </l>
                <l>Till that Calphurnia first haue better dreames? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>If that this day you priuate would remayne, </l>
                <l>The Senate to dissolue your selfe must goe, </l>
                <l>And then incontinent come backe againe, </l>
                <l>When you haue showne towards it some reuerence so. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-caesar" xml:id="eng000261-e129440">
              <speaker>Caes. </speaker>
              <l>With thy aduise (as powrefull) I agree, </l>
              <l>The Senators shall haue no cause to grudge: </l>
              <l>A little space, all part apart from mee, </l>
              <l>And Ile be shortly ready to dislodge. </l>
              <stage xml:id="eng000261-e129490">Caesar alone. </stage>
              <lg>
                <l>WHence come this huge and admirable change, </l>
                <l>That in my brest hath vncouth thoghts infus'd? </l>
                <l>Doth th'earth then erst yield terrors now more strange, </l>
                <l>Or but my minde lesse courage then it vsde? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>What spitefull fate against my state contends, </l>
                <l>That I must now t'vnlook'd for plagues giue place, </l>
                <l>By foes not mou'd, yet fear'd amongst my friends, </l>
                <l>By warre secure, endanger'd but by peace? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>T'encounter me when strongest troups did come, </l>
                <l>Then did my heart the highest hopes conceiue: </l>
                <l>I warr'd with many, many to ouercome, </l>
                <l>The greatest battels, greatest glory gaue. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>As th'enemies number still my courage grew, </l>
                <l>Oft haue I through the depths of dangers past, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-183-b"/>
                <l>Yet neuer did those boundlesse labors rue, </l>
                <l>To haue none greater first, none equall last. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>When as the Gaules fear'd by their neighbours falles, </l>
                <l>Had from the fields, no, from my furie fled, </l>
                <l>And hid themselues with armes, their armes with walles, </l>
                <l>Whilst I my troupes t'inclose Alexia led: </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then though there swarm'd foorth from the bounds about, </l>
                <l>Huge hostes to compasse me, enflam'd with wrath, </l>
                <l>That the besieger being besieg'd about </l>
                <l>Seem'd drawne with danger in the nets of death. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet I that could not with the pride comport, </l>
                <l>That those Barbarians by vaine bosts bewrayd, </l>
                <l>Did reassault th'assaulters in such sort, </l>
                <l>That words by wounds, wounds were by death repayd, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Of those within the towne t'asswage their toyles, </l>
                <l>Till being ore-com'd their comming was not knowne: </l>
                <l>Who straight vpbrayded by the barbarous spoiles, </l>
                <l>Did yeeld themselues with th'others as ore-throwne, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then whilst with liquid legions tumid bosts, </l>
                <l>The trident-bearer striu'd my spoyles to beare: </l>
                <l>Though threatned thrise amidst his humid hosts, </l>
                <l>I alwayes scorn'd t'acquaint my selfe with feare. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I vsde those Pirats that had me surpriz'd, </l>
                <l>Still as my seruants thundring threatnings forth, </l>
                <l>And gaue them money more than they deuisde, </l>
                <l>Greeu'd to be rated at too little worth. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet gathering ships, I sign'd not long the shore, </l>
                <l>But trac'd their printles steps through th'vnpau'd way: </l>
                <l>And taking them, as I had vow'd before, </l>
                <l>By nought but death their ransome would defray. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then when without th'aduise of others minds, </l>
                <l>Iventred through the hoarie waues by night, </l>
                <l>Whilst in a little barke against great winds, </l>
                <l>That euen the Pilote look'd not for the light </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-184-a"/>
              <lg>
                <l>The roaring waues themselues seem'd to diuide, </l>
                <l>That in their grauell I might chuse a graue. </l>
                <l>And in a christall arch aboue me bide, </l>
                <l>That I of me a tombe might worthy haue. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Whilst dangers seem'd to merite Caesars death, </l>
                <l>As Neptune raisde his head, raisde my heart; </l>
                <l>And shewing what I was with constant breath, </l>
                <l>t'amazde Amiclas courage did impart, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Was I not once amidst large Nilus flot, </l>
                <l>Whilst me to wound a wood of darts did flie, </l>
                <l>Yet swim'd so carelesse of my enemies shot, </l>
                <l>That in my hand I held some papers drie? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>With open dangers thus in euery place, </l>
                <l>I whilst being compass'd both by sea and land, </l>
                <l>Did vndismaid looke horror in the face, </l>
                <l>As borne for nought but onely to commaund. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But since a world of victories haue fill'd, </l>
                <l>With Trophees Temples, Theaters with my praise, </l>
                <l>That bath'd with balme from th'oyle of glory still'd, </l>
                <l>With friends in peace I look'd to spend my daies. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The chambers musicke now affrights me more, </l>
                <l>Then once the trumpets sound amids the field, </l>
                <l>And gownes (though signes of peace) worse, then before </l>
                <l>The pompous splendour of a flaming shield. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Those thoughts of late that had disdain'd to doubt, </l>
                <l>Though I alone had march'd amongst my foes, </l>
                <l>Lo, whilst amongst my friends I'm back'd about, </l>
                <l>Doe greater dangers now then th'eies disclose. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>If ought t'assemble any number brings, </l>
                <l>I insurrections feare from common wrath; </l>
                <l>Yea, if two talke apart of priuate things, </l>
                <l>Straight I suspect that they conspire my death. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>When suddaine rumors rise from vulgar smoake, </l>
                <l>Whilst th'inward motions roule my restlesse eies; </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-184-b"/>
                <l>I at each corner for ambushments looke, </l>
                <l>And start astonish'd least some tumult rise. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>When rising Titans beames renew th'earths toiles, </l>
                <l>I still dispaire to re-enioy the night, </l>
                <l>And when mine eyes th'all-couering darknesse spoiles, </l>
                <l>I neuer looke t'enrich them with the light. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>For when that light with darknesse makes a change, </l>
                <l>To flatter mortals with a dreame of rest, </l>
                <l>What ougly Gorgons, what Chimeraes strange, </l>
                <l>Do bost the little world within my breast? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Th'appointed time t'appease impetuous cares </l>
                <l>Doth double mine, that view most when being blind: </l>
                <l>I apprehen'd huge horrors and dispaires, </l>
                <l>Whilst th'outward obiect not distract my minde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>What comfort of my conquests now remaines? </l>
                <l>Where is the peace pursude by many a strife? </l>
                <l>Haue I but taken paine t'abound in paines, </l>
                <l>And sought by dangers for a dangerous life? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Is this the period of aspiring powers, </l>
                <l>In promisde calmes to be most plagu'd by stormes? </l>
                <l>Lurke poisnous serpents vnder fairest flowers. </l>
                <l>And hellish furies vnder heauenly formes? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>It will not greeue my gost below to goe, </l>
                <l>If circumuented in the warres I end, </l>
                <l>As bold Marcellus by Romes greatest foe, </l>
                <l>That gaue his ashes honor as a friend. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Or like Epaminondas prosprous death, </l>
                <l>O would to God I had amidst th'alarmes </l>
                <l>Being chargde with recent spoyles, bin spoil'd of breath, </l>
                <l>Whilst I toward Pluto might haue march'd in armes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet t'end this life that nought but toyles affords, </l>
                <l>Ile pay to death the tribute that he owes, </l>
                <l>Straight with my blood set some come die their swords, </l>
                <l>My body shall be bar'd t'embrace their blowes. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-185-a"/>
              <lg>
                <l>But ah, how haue the furies seaz'd my breast, </l>
                <l>And poison'd thus my sprit with desp'rate rage: </l>
                <l>That with their horrid serpents barr'd from rest, </l>
                <l>Nought can imagin'd be my toiles t'asswage. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>No, Atropos, yet spare my threed a space, </l>
                <l>That ere I to the Stigian streames go downe, </l>
                <l>I may of honor haue the highest place, </l>
                <l>And if I fall, yet fall beneath a crowne. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Whilst I would bend my eares t'applauding shoutes, </l>
                <l>My thoughts diuided are within my breast, </l>
                <l>And my tossde soule doth flote between two doubts, </l>
                <l>Yet knowes not on what ground to build her rest. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The Senators they haue this day designde, </l>
                <l>To shew the world how they esteeme my worth; </l>
                <l>Yet do portentuous signes perturb my minde, </l>
                <l>By which the heauens would point my danger forth; </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The gods from me with indignation gone, </l>
                <l>Haue charactred in euery thing my death, </l>
                <l>And must both heauen and earth conspire in one, </l>
                <l>To quench a little sparke of still-tossde breath? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>My saftie would that I should stay within, </l>
                <l>Till this disastrous day giue darknesse place: </l>
                <l>But honor hunts me forward to begin, </l>
                <l>To reape the glory of my painfull race: </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And Ile aduance in spight of threatned broyles, </l>
                <l>For though the fates effect that which we dreame, </l>
                <l>When death retires from forcing those fraile spoyles, </l>
                <l>Though breathlesse, Ile be breath'd ouer all by fame. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="eng000261-e131300">Exit. </stage>
            <div type="chorus" xml:id="eng000261-e131310">
              <head>Chorus. </head>
              <lg>
                <l>WHat furie 'is this that filles the breast, </l>
                <l>With a prodigious rash desire, </l>
                <l>Which banishing their soules from rest </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-185-b"/>
                <l>Doth make those liue that high aspire, </l>
                <l>Whilst it within their bosome boyles </l>
                <l>As Salamanders in the fire, </l>
                <l>Or like to serpents changing spoiles </l>
                <l>Their witherd beauties to renew: </l>
                <l>Like Vipers with vnnaturall toiles, </l>
                <l>Of such the thoughts themselues pursue, </l>
                <l>That for all lynes themselues do square, </l>
                <l>Whilst like Camelions changing hue, </l>
                <l>They only feed but on the aire. </l>
                <l>To passe ambition monstrous matters brings. </l>
                <l>And (saue contentment) can attaine all things. </l>
                <l>This actiue passion doth disdaine </l>
                <l>To match with any vulgar minde, </l>
                <l>As in base breasts where terrors raigne, </l>
                <l>To great a guest to be confinde; </l>
                <l>It doth but loftie thoughts frequent, </l>
                <l>Where it a spatious field may finde, </l>
                <l>It selfe with honor to content, </l>
                <l>Where reuerenc'd fame doth lowdest sound: </l>
                <l>Those at great things that t'aime are bent, </l>
                <l>(Farre lifted from this lumpish round) </l>
                <l>Would in the spheare of glory moue, </l>
                <l>Whilst loftie thoughts which nought can bind, </l>
                <l>All riualls liue in vertues loue: </l>
                <l>On abiect preyes as th'Eagle neuer lights, </l>
                <l>Ambition poisons but the greatest sprights. </l>
                <l>And of this restles vultures brood, </l>
                <l>If't grow not to too great a flame, </l>
                <l>A little sparke may whyles do good, </l>
                <l>Which makes great minds affecting fame, </l>
                <l>To suffer still all kinde of paine: </l>
                <l>There fortune at the bloody game, </l>
                <l>Who hazard would for hope of gaine. </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-186-a"/>
                <l>Were not burn'd by a thrist of praise: </l>
                <l>The learned loe, t'a higher straine, </l>
                <l>Their wits by emulation raise, </l>
                <l>As those that hold applauses deare: </l>
                <l>And what great mind at which men gaze, </l>
                <l>It selfe can of ambition cleare, </l>
                <l>Which is being rated at the highest price, </l>
                <l>A generous error, a heroicke vice. </l>
                <l>But when this frensie flaming bright </l>
                <l>Doth so the soules of some surprise, </l>
                <l>That they can taste of no delight </l>
                <l>But what from soueraigntie doth rise; </l>
                <l>Then huge affliction it affords, </l>
                <l>Such must themselues so to disguise, </l>
                <l>Prooue prodigall of courteous words, </l>
                <l>Giue much to some, and promise all, </l>
                <l>Then seruile seeme, to be made Lords, </l>
                <l>Yea first being made to many thrall, </l>
                <l>Must pittie impart if not support, </l>
                <l>T'all those that crush'd by fortune fall, </l>
                <l>And grieue themselues to please each sort: </l>
                <l>Are not those wretch'd that ouer a dangerous snare </l>
                <l>Hing but by hopes, being ballanc'd in the aier? </l>
                <l>Then when they haue the port attainde, </l>
                <l>That was through Seas of dangers sought, </l>
                <l>They (lo) at last but losse haue gainde, </l>
                <l>And by great trouble, trouble bought. </l>
                <l>There minds are married still with feares, </l>
                <l>T'engender many a iealous thought, </l>
                <l>With searching eyes and watching eares, </l>
                <l>To learne that which they grieue to know. </l>
                <l>The breast that such a burden beares, </l>
                <l>What huge afflictions toyle t'orethrow: </l>
                <l>Thus princes are as all perceiue, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-186-b"/>
                <l>No more exalted than brought low, </l>
                <l>Of many a Lord, to many a slaue. </l>
                <l>That idoll greatnesse which th'earth doth adore, </l>
                <l>Is conquerd with great paine, and kept with more </l>
                <l>He that to this imagin'd good, </l>
                <l>Did through his countries entrailes tend, </l>
                <l>Neglecting friendship, duety, blood, </l>
                <l>And all on which trust can depend, </l>
                <l>Or by which loue could be conceiu'd, </l>
                <l>Doth finde of what he did attend, </l>
                <l>His exspectations farre deceiu'd; </l>
                <l>For since suspecting secret snares, </l>
                <l>His soule hath still of rest bin reau'd. </l>
                <l>Whilst squadrons of tumultuous cares, </l>
                <l>Forth from his breast extort depth grones: </l>
                <l>Thus Caesar now of life despaires, </l>
                <l>Whose hap his hope exceeded once, </l>
                <l>And who can long well keepe an euill wonne state? </l>
                <l>Those perish must by some whome all men hate. </l>
              </lg>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="eng000261-e132230">
          <head>ACT. V. </head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="eng000261-e132240">
            <head>SCENE. I. </head>
            <stage xml:id="eng000261-e132250">Marcus Brutus, Chorus, Antonius, Caius Cassius, Marcus Tullius Cicero. </stage>
            <lg>
              <l>A Regenerous Romans so degenerd now, </l>
              <l>That they from honor haue estrangde their hands? </l>
              <l>And vsde with burdens do not blush to bow, </l>
              <l>Yea (though being broken) shake not off their bands. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>This glorious worke was worthy of your paine, </l>
              <l>Whose best ye may by others dangers haue, </l>
              <l>But what enchaunts you thus that ye abstaine, </l>
              <l>That (which ye should haue taken) to receiue? </l>
            </lg>
            <pb xml:id="eng000261-187-a"/>
            <lg>
              <l>Where be those inundations of delight, </l>
              <l>That should burst out through thoughts ore-flow'd with ioy, </l>
              <l>Whilst emulous vertue may your mindes incite, </l>
              <l>That which we conquerd haue, at least t'enioy? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Or quite conformd vnto your former state, </l>
              <l>Do still your mindes of seruitude allow, </l>
              <l>As broken by aduersitie of late, </l>
              <l>Not capable of better fortune now? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Loe, we that by the tyrants fauour stoode, </l>
              <l>And grieu'd but at the yoke that you outrag'd, </l>
              <l>Haue our aduauncement, riches, rest, and blood, </l>
              <l>All liberally for libertie engag'd. </l>
            </lg>
            <sp who="#eng000261-chorus" xml:id="eng000261-e132510">
              <speaker>Chor. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Thou like thy great progenitour in this, </l>
                <l>Hast glorie to thy selfe, t'vs freedome brought, </l>
                <l>Than libertie what greater treasure is? </l>
                <l>Small with it much, without it much seemes nought. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But pardon vs (heroicke man) though we </l>
                <l>T'a high perfection hardly can aspire, </l>
                <l>Though euery man cannot a Brutus be, </l>
                <l>That which we cannot imitate, w'admire. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>At this strange course with too much light made blind </l>
                <l>We our opinions must suspend a space, </l>
                <l>When any sodaine chance dismayes the minde, </l>
                <l>The iudgement to the passion first giues place, </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-antonius" xml:id="eng000261-e132670">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What wonder now though this most barbarous deed, </l>
                <l>Haue with amazement closde your iudgement in, </l>
                <l>Which O I feare shall great confusion breed, </l>
                <l>When Caesars toiles did end, Romes did begin. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The most suspitious mindes had not beleeu'd, </l>
                <l>That Romans reuerenc'd for their worth by vs, </l>
                <l>Would haue presumde to kill, yea, or t'haue greeu'd, </l>
                <l>A inuiolable hallowd bodie thus. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Who would but once haue dreamd of such despight? </l>
                <l>What strange hostilitie in time of peace, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-187-b"/>
                <l>To slay, though not accusde, against all right, </l>
                <l>A sacred man, and in a sacred placed </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-cassius" xml:id="eng000261-e132830">
              <speaker>C Cass. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>If Caesar as a Cittizen had liu'de, </l>
                <l>And had by lawe decided euery strife, </l>
                <l>Then I would grant those treason had contriu'd, </l>
                <l>That went without a lawe to take his life. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But to peruert the lawes, subuert the state, </l>
                <l>If all his trauells did directly tend, </l>
                <l>Then I must say, we did no wrong of late, </l>
                <l>Why should not tyrants make a tragicke end? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-chorus" xml:id="eng000261-e132940">
              <speaker>Chor. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Since destinies did Caesars soule enlarge, </l>
                <l>What course can we for his recouerie take? </l>
                <l>Ah, th'vnrelenting Charons restlesse barge </l>
                <l>Stands to transport all ouer, but brings none backe. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Of lifes fraile glasse when broken, with vaine grones </l>
                <l>What earthly powre the ruines can repaire? </l>
                <l>Or who can gather vp when scatterd once, </l>
                <l>Ones blood from th'earth, or yet his breath from th'aire? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Let vs of those that passe Obliuions flood, </l>
                <l>B'obliuious still since hope of help is gone, </l>
                <l>And spend our cares where cares may doe most good, </l>
                <l>Lest Rome waile many, where she wailes but one. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-antonius" xml:id="eng000261-e133100">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Still concord for the common-weale were best, </l>
                <l>To reconcile diuided thoughts againe, </l>
                <l>Then discord to great townes no greater pest, </l>
                <l>Whose violence no reuerence can restraine. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet oftentimes those warie wits haue err'd, </l>
                <l>That would buy wealth and ease at any cost, </l>
                <l>Let honesty to profit be preferr'd, </l>
                <l>And t'a vile peace, warre when it wounds vs most. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But seeking peace what suretie can we finde? </l>
                <l>Can faithlesse men giue faith iust feares to stay? </l>
                <l>No sacred band impietie can binde, </l>
                <l>That sweares for trust, seekes trust but to betray. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-188-a"/>
              <lg>
                <l>What help'd it Caesar that we all had sworne, </l>
                <l>His body still from dangers to redeeme, </l>
                <l>Those that are once periur'd hold othes in scorne, </l>
                <l>All are most franke of what they least esteeme. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-marcus-brutus" xml:id="eng000261-e133310">
              <speaker>M. Br. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>None needs in states that are from tirants free, </l>
                <l>Loathde execrations to confirme his will, </l>
                <l>Where willingly men would with good agree, </l>
                <l>And without danger might despise all ill. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>All odious othes by those are onely crau'd, </l>
                <l>Whose sute from reason doth a warrant want, </l>
                <l>Whilst all deceiuers feard to be deceau'd, </l>
                <l>Seek of men thralld what none being free would grant </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>When Caesar had preuailde in Libia and Spaine, </l>
                <l>His fortune building on his countries wracke, </l>
                <l>Of libertie a shadow to retaine, </l>
                <l>We gaue him all that he was bent to take. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The Senate had reseru'd nought but a show, </l>
                <l>Whose course to it by Caesar was imposde, </l>
                <l>That lifted vp by bringing others lowe, </l>
                <l>Of offices and prouinces disposde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then that our witherd hopes might neuer spring, </l>
                <l>When bent t'abide the Parthians woodden showre, </l>
                <l>He for fiue yeares disposde of euery thing, </l>
                <l>Euen in his absence leauing vs no powre. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>O how some aggrauate our deede with hate, </l>
                <l>That durst by violence his body straine, </l>
                <l>Though consecrated by constraint of late, </l>
                <l>Yea but reputed holie, yet prophane, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And doe forget how he (a wondrous case) </l>
                <l>Did violate the tribune ship t'our scorne, </l>
                <l>Which our forefathers (free) in time of peace, </l>
                <l>Aduisdly had inuiolable sworne. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Did he not once appropriate (swolne with wrath) </l>
                <l>The publike treasure to his priuate vse, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-188-b"/>
                <l>And to the sacred Tribune threatned death, </l>
                <l>That did resist, grieu'd at so great a'abuse? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Tweene Romans and a tyrant what auailes </l>
                <l>A couenant whilst right rests troad on thus? </l>
                <l>Who can build further when the ground first failes? </l>
                <l>Could we saue him that sought to ruine vs? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-cicero" xml:id="eng000261-e133770">
              <speaker>Cic. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>So absolutely good no man remaines, </l>
                <l>Whose naturall weakenesse neuer him beguiles, </l>
                <l>Euen vertues die from vice may take some staines, </l>
                <l>And worthy mindes foule imperfections whiles. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>As in fine fruits or weeds fat earth abounds, </l>
                <l>Euen as the laborers spend or spare their paine, </l>
                <l>The greatest sprites disdaining vulgar bounds, </l>
                <l>Of what they seeke the highest height must gaine. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>They, that the crowne of glory may b'enioyd, </l>
                <l>As onely borne to be in action still, </l>
                <l>Had rather be (than idle) euill employd, </l>
                <l>Great sprites must doe great good, or then great ill. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The glorious Sunne that golden raies doe arme, </l>
                <l>The treasure of the world that doth most good, </l>
                <l>Whilst on a time misgouernd did much harme, </l>
                <l>Till th'ouerbold Coach-man fell amidst a flood. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then whilst he by the rules of reason liu'd, </l>
                <l>When lawfully elected by the State, </l>
                <l>What glorious deedes by Caesar were atchiu'd, </l>
                <l>Which all the world as wonders must relate. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But when of right he buried all respects, </l>
                <l>As blind ambition had bewitcht his minde, </l>
                <l>What harme ensude by pittifull effects. </l>
                <l>We at the first, he at the last did finde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Whilst like Narcissus with himselfe in loue, </l>
                <l>He with our bondage banqueted his sight, </l>
                <l>And for a while vncertaine ioyes to proue, </l>
                <l>Would sawce with all our sorrowes his delight, </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-189-a"/>
              <lg>
                <l>How could such gallant vertuous men as those, </l>
                <l>That of their countries weale are iealous still, </l>
                <l>But stowtly to all stormes their states expose, </l>
                <l>So th'authour of their infamy to kill? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But since our freedome flowes from Caesars blood, </l>
                <l>Let vs imbrace that which too long we lacke, </l>
                <l>Peace giues to Iustice powre, and it t'all good, </l>
                <l>Where war breeds wrong, and wrong al kind of wracke. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>This cittie hath experienc'd with great paine, </l>
                <l>Th'all-burdning troubles of intestine strife, </l>
                <l>Which by her ruines registred remaine, </l>
                <l>Since first the Gracchi gaue contention life. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>When Silla once and Marius (mad through pride) </l>
                <l>Seemd but to striue who most tyrannicke prou'd, </l>
                <l>What memorable miseries were tride </l>
                <l>From Romans mindes can neuer be remou'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then last by Caesar and his sonne in lawe, </l>
                <l>What thousands ghosts to Pluto were dispatchd? </l>
                <l>Ah that the world those hosts diuided sawe, </l>
                <l>Which ioynd in one no world of worlds had matchd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet with this wit that we haue dearely bought, </l>
                <l>Let vs abhorre th'apparance of such broiles, </l>
                <l>Lest when we haue our selues to ruine brought, </l>
                <l>In end Barbarians beare away our spoyles. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-chorus" xml:id="eng000261-e134430">
              <speaker>Chor. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Rome to those great men hardly can afford, </l>
                <l>A recompence according to their worth, </l>
                <l>That by a tyrants ore-throw haue restord, </l>
                <l>The light of libertie that was put forth. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet by due praises with their merites euen, </l>
                <l>Let vs illustrate their illustrous mindes, </l>
                <l>And to their charge let prouinces be giuen; </l>
                <l>Still vertue growes when it preferrement findes. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-antonius" xml:id="eng000261-e134540">
              <speaker>Anton. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Those barbarous realmes by whose respectiue wil, </l>
                <l>Of Caesars conquests monuments are showne, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-189-b"/>
                <l>As if they held them highly honord still, </l>
                <l>That warrd with Caesar though they were orethrowne. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Can this disgrace by their prowde minds be borne, </l>
                <l>Whilst we dishonor whom they honor thus, </l>
                <l>And shall we not (whilst as a tyrant torne,) </l>
                <l>Giue him a tombe that gaue the world to vs? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Must his decrees be all reducde againe, </l>
                <l>And those degraded whom he gracde of late, </l>
                <l>As worthy men vnworthily did gaine </l>
                <l>Their roomes of reputation in the state? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>If as a tyrant we him damne so soone, </l>
                <l>And for his murd'rers do rewards deuise, </l>
                <l>Then what he did, must likewise be vndone, </l>
                <l>For which I feare a fowle confusion rise. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-chorus" xml:id="eng000261-e134750">
              <speaker>Chor. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ah (great Antonius) sow not seeds of warre, </l>
                <l>And if thou alwayes dost delight in armes, </l>
                <l>The haughty Parthians yet vndaunted are, </l>
                <l>Which may giue thee great praise, and vs no harmes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Detest in time th'abhominable broiles, </l>
                <l>For which no conquerour to triumph hath com'd, </l>
                <l>Whilst this wretch'd towne (which stil som party spoils) </l>
                <l>Must loathe the victor, and lament th'orecomd, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And shall we still contend against all good, </l>
                <l>To make the yoke where we should bound abide? </l>
                <l>Must still the commons sacrifize their blood, </l>
                <l>As onely borne to serue the great mens pride. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-antonius" xml:id="eng000261-e134910">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Whilst I the depths of my affection found, </l>
                <l>And reade but th'obligations which I owe, </l>
                <l>I finde my selfe by othes, and duetie bound, </l>
                <l>All Caesars foes, or then my selfe t'orethrow. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But when I weigh what to the state belongs, </l>
                <l>The which to plague no passion shall get place, </l>
                <l>Then I with griefe digesting priuate wrongs, </l>
                <l>Warre with my selfe to giue my country peace. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-190-a"/>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet whilst my thoughts of this last purpose muse, </l>
                <l>I altogether dis-assent from this, </l>
                <l>That we should Caesars fame, or bodie abuse, </l>
                <l>By torturing tyrants as the custome is. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Lest guiltie of ingratitude we seeme, </l>
                <l>(If guerdoning our benefactors thus) </l>
                <l>Great Caesars body from disgrace redeeme, </l>
                <l>And let his acts be ratified by vs. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then for the publicke weale of which we pause, </l>
                <l>Towards those that haue him killd t'extend regard, </l>
                <l>Let them be pardond for their kinsmens cause, </l>
                <l>Remission giuen for euill is a reward. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-cassius" xml:id="eng000261-e135170">
              <speaker>C. Cass. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We stand not dasht like malefactors heere, </l>
                <l>With a deiected and remorcefull minde, </l>
                <l>So in your presence supplicants t'appeare, </l>
                <l>As who themselues of death doe guiltie finde; </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But looking boldely with a loftie brow, </l>
                <l>Through a delight of our designe conceiu'd, </l>
                <l>We come to challenge gratefulnesse of you, </l>
                <l>That haue of vs so great a good receiu'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But if ye will suspend your thoughts a space, </l>
                <l>Though not the giuers, entertaine the gift, </l>
                <l>Do vs reiect, yet libertie imbrace, </l>
                <l>To haue you free, loe, that was all our drift. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>So Rome her antient liberties enioy, </l>
                <l>Let Brutus, and let Cassius banisht liue, </l>
                <l>Thus banishment would breede vs greater ioy, </l>
                <l>Than what at home a tyrants wealth could giue. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Though some misconster may this course of ours, </l>
                <l>By ignorance or then by hate deceiu'd, </l>
                <l>Yet truth depends not on opinions powres, </l>
                <l>But is it selfe how euer misconceiu'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Though none themselues t'acknowledge vs woulde daigne, </l>
                <l>Our merite of it selfe is a rewarde, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-190-b"/>
                <l>Of doing good none should repent their paine, </l>
                <l>Though neither getting guerdon nor regard. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Ile venture yet my fortune in the fielde, </l>
                <l>With euery one that Rome to bondage drawes: </l>
                <l>And as for me, how euer others yield, </l>
                <l>Ile nought obey but reason and the Lawes. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-cicero" xml:id="eng000261-e135530">
              <speaker>Cicer. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What fooles are those that further trauell take, </l>
                <l>For that which else they past recouery know? </l>
                <l>Who can reuiue the dead, or bring time backe? </l>
                <l>At least no mortall that remaines below. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Great Pompey (now) for whom the world still weepes, </l>
                <l>Lies low, neglected on a barbarous shore; </l>
                <l>Selfe-slaughtred Scipio flotes amidst the depthes, </l>
                <l>Whom it may be sea-monsters do deuoure. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Of Libian wolues wise Cato feasts the wombes, </l>
                <l>Whose death of worth the world defrauded leaues: </l>
                <l>Thus some that merited Mausolean tombes, </l>
                <l>Not haue a title grau'd vpon their graues. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And yet may Caesar that procur'd their death, </l>
                <l>By braue men slaine be buried with his race: </l>
                <l>All ciuill warre being banish'd with his breath, </l>
                <l>Let him now dead, and vs aliue haue peace. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>We should desist our thoughts on things to set, </l>
                <l>That may harme some, and can giue help to none, </l>
                <l>Learne to forget that which we can not get, </l>
                <l>And let our cares be gone, of all that's gone. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Those that would striue all crosses to ore-come, </l>
                <l>Must to the present time conforme their course: </l>
                <l>And doing the best for that which is to come, </l>
                <l>Not medle with things past but by discourse. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Seeke not the thing which doth not good being found, </l>
                <l>Since Caesar now is dead, how euer dead; </l>
                <l>Let all our griefe goe with him to the ground, </l>
                <l>For sorrow best becomes a lightlesse shade. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-191-a"/>
              <lg>
                <l>It's best that reconioynde with mutuall loue, </l>
                <l>We phisicke for this wounded state prepare: </l>
                <l>Neglecting those that from the world remoue, </l>
                <l>All men on earth for earthly things must care. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-chorus" xml:id="eng000261-e135940">
              <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>O how those great men friendship can pretend, </l>
                <l>By soothing others thus with painted windes, </l>
                <l>And seeme to trust, where treason they attend, </l>
                <l>Whilst loue their mouth, and malice filles their mindes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Those but to them poore simple soules appeare, </l>
                <l>Whose countnance doth discouer what they thinke, </l>
                <l>That make their words as is their meaning cleare, </l>
                <l>And from themselues can neuer seeme to shrinke. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Lo how Anthonius faines to quench all iarres, </l>
                <l>And kindly the conspirators t'imbrace, </l>
                <l>Yet as he further'd first the former warres, </l>
                <l>It's fear'd he now be enemie to peace. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Now where Calphurnia stayes our steps adresse, </l>
                <l>By this last sodaine chance her losse was chiefe: </l>
                <l>All visite should their neighbours in distresse, </l>
                <l>To giue some comfort, or to get some griefe. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="eng000261-e136150">Exeunt. </stage>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="eng000261-e136160">
            <head>Act. V. Scene II. </head>
            <stage xml:id="eng000261-e136170">Calphurnia, Nuntius, Chorus. </stage>
            <lg>
              <l>WHen darknesse last imprisond had mine eies, </l>
              <l>Such monstrous visions did my soule affright, </l>
              <l>That my deiected sprite still stupid dyes, </l>
              <l>Through terrors then contracted in the night. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>A melancholious cloud so dimmes my breast, </l>
              <l>That it my mind fit for misfortune makes, </l>
              <l>A lodging well disposde for such a guest, </l>
              <l>Where nought of sorrow but th'impression lackes. </l>
            </lg>
            <pb xml:id="eng000261-191-b"/>
            <lg>
              <l>And I imagine euery man I see </l>
              <l>(My senses so corrupted are by feares) </l>
              <l>A Herauld to denounce mishaps to me, </l>
              <l>That should infuse confusion in mine cares. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>O there he comes to violate my peace, </l>
              <l>In whom the obiect of my thoughts I see: </l>
              <l>Thy message is charecter'd in thy face, </l>
              <l>Which by thy lookes directed is to me: </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Thy troubled eyes rest rouling for releife, </l>
              <l>As lately frighted by some ougly sight, </l>
              <l>Thy breath doth pant as if being big with griefe, </l>
              <l>And fear'd to bring some monstrous birth to light. </l>
            </lg>
            <sp who="#eng000261-nuntius" xml:id="eng000261-e136430">
              <speaker>Nun. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>The man of whom the world in doubt remain'd, </l>
                <l>If that his minde, or fortune was more great, </l>
                <l>Whose valour conquer'd, clemencie retain'd </l>
                <l>All nations subiect to the Romane state; </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Him fraude harm'd more then force, friends more then, foes </l>
                <l>Ah, must this sad discourse by mee be made? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-calphurnia" xml:id="eng000261-e136520">
              <speaker>Calph. </speaker>
              <l>Stay; ere thou further goe defray my woes, </l>
              <l>How doth my loue? wher is my life? Num. Dead. Cal. dead. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-chorus" xml:id="eng000261-e136550">
              <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Though apprehending horrors in her minde, </l>
                <l>Now since she hath a certaintie receiu'd, </l>
                <l>She by experience greater griefe doth finde, </l>
                <l>Till borne, the passions cannot be conceiu'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>When as a high disaster force affords, </l>
                <l>O how that tyrant whom affliction beares, </l>
                <l>Barres theares from comfort, &amp; the mouth from words. </l>
                <l>And being obdur'd cannot dissolue in teares. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-calphurnia" xml:id="eng000261-e136660">
              <speaker>Calph. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ah, since the lights of that great light are set, </l>
                <l>Why doth not darknesse spread it selfe ouer all? </l>
                <l>At least what further comfort can I get </l>
                <l>Whose pleasures had no period but his fall. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>O would the gods I alwayes might confine </l>
                <l>Aetna 'in my breast, and th'Ocean in mine eyes, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-192-a"/>
                <l>That t'entertaine so great a griefe as mine, </l>
                <l>Thence might sufficient furniture arise. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet I disdaine though by distresse ore-throwne, </l>
                <l>By such externall meanes to seeke reliefe: </l>
                <l>The greatest sorrowes are by silence showne, </l>
                <l>Whilst all the sences are shut vp with griefe: </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But miserie doth so tyrannicke grow, </l>
                <l>That it of sighes and teares a tribute claimes: </l>
                <l>Ah, when the cup is full it must ore-flow, </l>
                <l>And fires that burne must offer vp some flames. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet though that thy last words my last might be, </l>
                <l>Which are deepe sunke within a melted heart, </l>
                <l>Of my liues death report each point to me, </l>
                <l>That I for euery circumstance may smart. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-nuntius" xml:id="eng000261-e136920">
              <speaker>Nun. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What fatall warnings did fore-go his end, </l>
                <l>Which by his stay to frustrate some did try? </l>
                <l>But he that scorn'd excuses to pretend, </l>
                <l>Was by the Destinies drawne forth to die. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Whilst by the way he chanc'd t'encounter one </l>
                <l>That had his deaths-day nam'd, he to him said; </l>
                <l>Now th'Ides of March be com'd, but yet not gone, </l>
                <l>Straight th'other answerd, and still constant staide. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Another brought a letter with great speed, </l>
                <l>Which the conspiracie at length did touch, </l>
                <l>And gaue it Caesar in his hand to reade, </l>
                <l>Protesting that it did import him much. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet did he lay it vp where still it rests, </l>
                <l>As do the great whom happy th'earth reputes, </l>
                <l>That grieu'd to be importun'd by requests, </l>
                <l>Of simple supplicants neglect the sutes: </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Or he of it the reading did deferre, </l>
                <l>Still troubled by attendanrs at the gate, </l>
                <l>Whilst some to shew their credite did conferre </l>
                <l>To flatter some, for something some t'entreat. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-192-b"/>
              <lg>
                <l>Not only did the gods by diuers signes </l>
                <l>Giue Caesar warning of his threatned harmes, </l>
                <l>But did disturbe all th'aduersaries designes, </l>
                <l>And to their troubled thoughts gaue strange alarmes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>A Senator that by some words we finde, </l>
                <l>To the conspiratours (though none of theirs) </l>
                <l>Had showne himselfe familiar with their minde, </l>
                <l>Then chanc'd to deale with Caesar in affaires. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>That sight their soules did with confusion fill, </l>
                <l>For thinking that he told their purposde deeds; </l>
                <l>They straight themselues, or Caesar thought to kill </l>
                <l>A guiltie conscience no accuser needes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But marking that he vsde (when taking leaue) </l>
                <l>The gesture of a suter that gaue thankes, </l>
                <l>They of their course did greater hopes conceiue, </l>
                <l>And rang'd themselues according to their rankes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then Caesar march'd forth to the fatall place, </l>
                <l>Neere Pompyes theater where the Senate was, </l>
                <l>Where when he had remain'd a little space, </l>
                <l>All the confederates flock'd about. Calph. Alas. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-nuntius" xml:id="eng000261-e137430">
              <speaker>Nun. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>First for the forme Metellus Cimber crau'd, </l>
                <l>To haue his brother from exile restor'd; </l>
                <l>Yet with the rest a rude repulse receiu'd, </l>
                <l>Whilst it they all too ernestly implor'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then Cimber that in strife with him did stand, </l>
                <l>Did draw the gowne ouer Caesars sacred head: </l>
                <l>But the first blow was giuen by Cascaes hand, </l>
                <l>Which on his necke a little wound but made. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then Caesar starting whilst the stroke he spi'd, </l>
                <l>By strength from further striking Casca stayde: </l>
                <l>Whilst both the two burst out at once and cry'd, </l>
                <l>Th'one traitor Casca, th'other brother ayde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then all the rest against him did arise </l>
                <l>Like desperate men, whose furie force affords, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-193-a"/>
                <l>That Caesar on no side could set his eyes, </l>
                <l>But euery looke r'encountred with some swordes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet as a Lyon when by nets surprisde, </l>
                <l>Stands strugling still so long as he hath strength; </l>
                <l>So Caesar, as he had their powre dispisde, </l>
                <l>Did with great rage resist; till at the length </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>He thus cry'd out (when spying Brutus come) </l>
                <l>And thou my sonne? then griefe did backe rebound, </l>
                <l>Nought but vnkindnesse Caesar could ore-come, </l>
                <l>That of all things doth giue the deepest wound. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-chorus" xml:id="eng000261-e137740">
              <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
              <l>Ah, when vnkindnes is where loue was thought, </l>
              <l>A tender passion breakes the strongest heart, </l>
              <l>For of all those that giue offence in ought, </l>
              <l>Men others hate, but for th'vnkinde they smart. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-nuntius" xml:id="eng000261-e137790">
              <speaker>Nun. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ah, taking then no more delight in light, </l>
                <l>As which would then his life haue bitter fram'd: </l>
                <l>Or then from Brutus blow t'absent his sight, </l>
                <l>As of so great ingratitude asham'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>He with his gowne being couer'd first ouer all, </l>
                <l>As one that neither sought, nor wisht reliefe; </l>
                <l>Not wronging maiestie in state did fall, </l>
                <l>No sigh consenting to betray his griefe. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet (if by chaunce or force I cannot tell,) </l>
                <l>Euen at the place whereas his statue stood, </l>
                <l>As crauing Pompey pardon Caesar fell, </l>
                <l>That in reuenge it might exhaust his blood. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But when his corps abandond quite by breath </l>
                <l>Did Fortunes frailties monument remaine, </l>
                <l>That all might haue like interest in his death; </l>
                <l>And guilty alike, looke for like praise or paine. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then Cassius, Brutus, and the rest began </l>
                <l>With that great Emperours blood t'imbrue their hands: </l>
                <l>What beast in th'earth more cruell is than man, </l>
                <l>When ouer his reason passion once commands? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="eng000261-193-b"/>
            <sp who="#eng000261-calphurnia" xml:id="eng000261-e138050">
              <speaker>Calph. </speaker>
              <l>Whilst brutish Brutus, and prowde Cassius thus </l>
              <l>Romes greatest Captaine vnder trust deceiu'd, </l>
              <l>Where was Anthonius (since a friend to vs,) </l>
              <l>That he not lost himselfe, or Caesar sau'd? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-nuntius" xml:id="eng000261-e138100">
              <speaker>Nun. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>The whole conspirators remainde in doubt, </l>
                <l>Had he and Caesar ioyn'd, to be vndone; </l>
                <l>And so causde one him t'entertaine without, </l>
                <l>Who fain'd a conference till the fact was done. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then knowing well in such tumultuous broyles, </l>
                <l>That the first danger alwayes is the worst, </l>
                <l>He fled in haste, disguisde with vnknowne spoiles, </l>
                <l>For rage and for disdaine being like to burst. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-calphurnia" xml:id="eng000261-e138210">
              <speaker>Calph. </speaker>
              <l>The Senators that were assembled there, </l>
              <l>When they beheld that great man brought t'an end, </l>
              <l>What was their part? to what inclin'd their care? </l>
              <l>I feare affliction could not find a friend. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-nuntius" xml:id="eng000261-e138260">
              <speaker>Nun. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Of those that in the Senate-house did sit, </l>
                <l>As greeu'd so sad an obiect to behold: </l>
                <l>Or feard what further murdrers might commit, </l>
                <l>Each towards his house a seuerall way did hold. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>This act with horror did confound their sight, </l>
                <l>And vnawares their iudgement did surprise, </l>
                <l>When any hastie harmes vnlook'd for light, </l>
                <l>The resolution hath not time to rise. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>That man on whome the world did once rely, </l>
                <l>By all being reuerenc'd, and ador'd by some, </l>
                <l>Had none t'attend him left, but two and I. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-chorus" xml:id="eng000261-e138410">
              <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>To what an ebbe may fortunes full whiles come: </l>
                <l>Why should men following on the smoake of pride, </l>
                <l>Leaue certaine ease to seeke a dream'd delight, </l>
                <l>Which when they haue by many dangers tride, </l>
                <l>They neither can with safetie keepe, nor quite? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The people that by force subdude remaine, </l>
                <l>May pittie those by whome oppressd they rest. </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-194-a"/>
                <l>They but one tyrant haue, where as there raigne, </l>
                <l>A thousand Tyrants in one tyrants breast. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>What though that Caesar once commanded kings, </l>
                <l>Whose only name whole nations did appall? </l>
                <l>Yet now (let no man trust in worldly things) </l>
                <l>A little earth holdes him that held it all. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-calphurnia" xml:id="eng000261-e138580">
              <speaker>Calph. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ah, had he but beleeu'd my faithfull cares, </l>
                <l>That t'haue his state establish'd alwayes striu'd: </l>
                <l>Then scaping this conspiracie of theirs, </l>
                <l>He honorde still, and I had happie liu'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Did I not spend of supplications store, </l>
                <l>That he within his house this day would waste, </l>
                <l>As I by dreames aduertis'd was before, </l>
                <l>Which shew'd that was to come, which now is past: </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Whilst the sooth-sayers sacrifiz'd did finde, </l>
                <l>A beast without a heart their altars staine: </l>
                <l>By that presage my soule might haue diuin'd </l>
                <l>That I without my heart would soone remaine. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But all those terrors could not terrors giue, </l>
                <l>To that great mind whose thoghts could not be tam'd; </l>
                <l>But by his fortune confident did liue, </l>
                <l>As him t'obey the heauens had all things fram'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet though he ended haue his fatall race, </l>
                <l>T'insult for this let not his murdrers striue, </l>
                <l>For, O I hope to see within short space, </l>
                <l>Him dead ador'd, and them abhor'd aliue. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Though now his name the multitude respects, </l>
                <l>Since murdering one that had held him so deare, </l>
                <l>Whilst th'inward thoughts ech outward thing reflects, </l>
                <l>Some monstrous shape to Brutus must appeare. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Iust Nemesis must plague prowde Cassius soone, </l>
                <l>And make him kill himselfe from hopes estrang'd; </l>
                <l>Once all the wrongs by foes to Caesar done, </l>
                <l>May by themselues be on themselues reueng'd. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="eng000261-194-b"/>
            <sp who="#eng000261-chorus" xml:id="eng000261-e138940">
              <speaker>Chor. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Some for th'earths soueraigne Fortune striue to proue </l>
                <l>As heauens their course confusdly did aduance, </l>
                <l>Nought comes to men below, but from aboue, </l>
                <l>By prouidence, not by a staggering chance. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Though to the cause that last foregoes the end, </l>
                <l>Some attribute th'euent of euery thing, </l>
                <l>That cause on other causes doth depend, </l>
                <l>From heauen to earth that chaind together hing. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Of those decrees that heauens for vs appoint, </l>
                <l>Who-euer them approues, or yet disprooues, </l>
                <l>No mortall man can dissappoint a point, </l>
                <l>But as they please heere mooues, or hence remooues. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>We when once com'd the worlds vaine pomp to trie, </l>
                <l>Led by the fates, t'our iournies end must haste, </l>
                <l>For when first borne, we striaght begin to die, </l>
                <l>Lifes first day is a steppe vnto the last. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And is there ought more swift than daies and yeares, </l>
                <l>Which weare away this breath of ours so soone? </l>
                <l>Whilst Lachesis to no request giues eares, </l>
                <l>But spinnes the threedes of life till they be done. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet foolish worldelings following that which flies, </l>
                <l>As if they had assurance still to breathe, </l>
                <l>To fraile preferrement fondly striue to rise, </l>
                <l>Which but a burden weighes them downe to death. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-nuntius" xml:id="eng000261-e139250">
              <speaker>Nun. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ther's none of vs but must remember still, </l>
                <l>How that the gods by many a wondrous signe, </l>
                <l>Did shew as 'twere how that against their will, </l>
                <l>The destinies would Caesars dayes confine. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>A monstrous starre amidst the heauen hath beene, </l>
                <l>Stil since they first against him did conspire, </l>
                <l>The solitary birds at noone were seene, </l>
                <l>And men to walke enuirond all with fire. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>What woonder though the heauens at such a time, </l>
                <l>Vpbraide the earth with apparitions strange, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-195-a"/>
                <l>Then whilst intending such a monstrous crime, </l>
                <l>Vnnaturall men make natures course to change. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-chorus" xml:id="eng000261-e139410">
              <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Thogh all such things seem wonderful to some, </l>
                <l>They may by reason comprehended be, </l>
                <l>Yet if ought more than common custome come, </l>
                <l>It th'ignorant with wondring eies must see. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Those bastard starres not heritours of th'aire, </l>
                <l>Are first conceiu'd below, then borne aboue, </l>
                <l>And when fore-knowing things sprites take most care, </l>
                <l>And by illusions superstition moue. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet this no doubt a great regard should breed, </l>
                <l>When Nature hath brought forth a monstrous birth, </l>
                <l>Where men in secret characters may reade, </l>
                <l>The wrath of heauen, and wickednesse of earth. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The Naturalists, and th'Astrologians skill, </l>
                <l>May whiles r'encountring manifest like care, </l>
                <l>Since th'one lookes backe, and th'other forward still, </l>
                <l>Th'one may tell what, and th'other why things are. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-nuntius" xml:id="eng000261-e139620">
              <speaker>Nu. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Shall sorrow through the waues of woes to saile </l>
                <l>Haue still your teares for seas, your sighs for windes, </l>
                <l>t'affliction what do base complaints auaile? </l>
                <l>A higher course becomes heroicke mindes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>None are orecom'd saue onely those that yeelde, </l>
                <l>Though they from froward fortune blowes haue borne. </l>
                <l>Let Vertue be t'aduersitie a shield, </l>
                <l>No greater griefe to griefe than th'enemies scorne. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>This makes your foes but laugh to see you weepe; </l>
                <l>At least these teares but for your selfe bestow, </l>
                <l>And not for that great sprite, whose spoils heauens keep, </l>
                <l>For he no doubt rests deified ere now. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000261-calphurnia" xml:id="eng000261-e139780">
              <speaker>Calp. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I onely waile my life, and not his death, </l>
                <l>That now amongst th'immortalls doth repose, </l>
                <l>And shall so long as I haue blood or breath, </l>
                <l>To furnish forth those elements of woes. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-195-b"/>
              <lg>
                <l>I care not who reioyce, so I lament, </l>
                <l>That do to darkenes dedicate my daies, </l>
                <l>And since the light of my delight is spent, </l>
                <l>Shall haue in horror all Apolloes raies. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I will retire my selfe to waile alone, </l>
                <l>As do the trustie Turtles for their mates, </l>
                <l>And my misfortune alwayes bent to mone, </l>
                <l>Will spurne at pleasures, as empoisond baites. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>No second guest shall presse great Caesars bed, </l>
                <l>Warmd by the flames to which he first gaue life, </l>
                <l>I thinke there may be greater honour had, </l>
                <l>Being Caesars widow, than anothers wife. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>This had afforded comfort for my harmes, </l>
                <l>If I (ere chancde abandond thus to be,) </l>
                <l>Had had a little Caesar in mine armes, </l>
                <l>That represented had his sire to me. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet doth that idoll which my thoughts adore, </l>
                <l>With me of late most strictly match remaine, </l>
                <l>For where my armes but held him whiles before, </l>
                <l>Now in my heart I shall him still retaine. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>That (though I haue no pretious things t'impart) </l>
                <l>Thy deity may by me b'acknowledgde oft, </l>
                <l>Still offring vp my thoughts vpon my hart, </l>
                <l>My sacred flame shall alwayes mount aloft. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="eng000261-e140140">Exeunt </stage>
            <div type="chorus" xml:id="eng000261-e140150">
              <head>Chorus. </head>
              <lg>
                <l>WHat fooles are those that do repose their trust, </l>
                <l>On what this masse of miserie affords? </l>
                <l>And bragging but of th'excrements of dust, </l>
                <l>Of lifelesse treasures labour to be lords: </l>
                <l>Which like the Syrens songs, or Circes charmes, </l>
                <l>With shadows of delight hide certaine harmes. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000261-196-a"/>
              <lg>
                <l>Ah whilst they sport on pleasures icie ground, </l>
                <l>Oft poisond by prosperitie with pride, </l>
                <l>A sodaine fall doth floating ioyes confound, </l>
                <l>Of those that stumble after th'eielesse guide, </l>
                <l>That so inconstantly her selfe doth beare, </l>
                <l>To hope th'vnhappy, happy haue cause to feare. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The fortunate that bathe in flouds of ioyes, </l>
                <l>To perish whiles amidst their pleasures chaunce, </l>
                <l>And mirthlesse wretches wallowing in annoyes, </l>
                <l>Oft by aduersitie themselues aduance: </l>
                <l>Whilst fortune bent to mocke vain worldlings eares </l>
                <l>Doth change dispaires in hopes, hopes in dispaires. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>That gallant Graecian, whose great wit so soone </l>
                <l>Th'innumerable army did orecome, </l>
                <l>Were not he was vndone, had bin vndone, </l>
                <l>And if not banisht had not had a home: </l>
                <l>To him feare corage gaue (what wondrous change,) </l>
                <l>And many doubts a resolution strange. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>He that tolde one that then was fortunes childe, </l>
                <l>As if with horror to congeale his blood, </l>
                <l>That Caius Marius being from Rome exilde: </l>
                <l>Wretch'd on the ruines of great Carthage stood: </l>
                <l>Thogh both being plag'd by griefe, and by disgrace </l>
                <l>The consulship regain'd, and di'd in peace. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And that great Pompey (all the worlds delight,) </l>
                <l>Whom of his theater then th'applauses pleasd, </l>
                <l>Whilst praise-transported eies endeerd his sight, </l>
                <l>That by youths toiles should haue his age then easde: </l>
                <l>He by one blow of fortune lost farre more, </l>
                <l>Then many a battell conquerd had before. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Such sodaine changes so disturbe the soule, </l>
                <l>That still the iudgement ballancde is by doubt, </l>
                <l>But on around, what wonder though things roule, </l>
                <l>And since within a circle turne about? </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-196-b"/>
                <l>Whilst heauen on earth strange alterations brings, </l>
                <l>To scorne our confidence in worldly things. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And chancde there euer accidents more strange, </l>
                <l>Than in this stormie bounds where we remaine? </l>
                <l>A shepheardes Staffe did here t'a Scepter change, </l>
                <l>The nurceling of a woolfe ouer men to raigne: </l>
                <l>A little village grew a mightie towne, </l>
                <l>Which whilst it had no king, held many a crowne. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then by how many sundry sortes of men, </l>
                <l>Hath this great state bin rulde? though now by none, </l>
                <l>Which first obeyd but one, then two, then ten, </l>
                <l>Then by degrees returnd to two, and t'one, </l>
                <l>Of which three states their ruine did abide, </l>
                <l>Two by twoes lusts, and one by two mens pride. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>What reuolutions huge haue hapned thus, </l>
                <l>All by a secret violence being led, </l>
                <l>Though seeming but by accident to vs, </l>
                <l>Yet in the depths of heauenly breasts first bred; </l>
                <l>As arguments demonstratiue to proue, </l>
                <l>That weaknesse dwells below, and powre aboue. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Lo Caesar, though being burdend in short space, </l>
                <l>Both with strange nations, and his countries spoiles, </l>
                <l>Euen when he seemd by warre t'haue purchasde peace, </l>
                <l>And roses of sweete rest from thornes of toiles: </l>
                <l>Then whilst his minde and fortune raise most hie, </l>
                <l>Hath bin constraind the last distresse to trie. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>What warnings large were in a time so short, </l>
                <l>Of that darke course which by his death now shines? </l>
                <l>It speechlesse wonders plainely did report, </l>
                <l>It men reueald by words, and gods by signes: </l>
                <l>Yet by the chaines of destinies being bound, </l>
                <l>He saw the sword, but could not scape the wound. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>O what a curtine ouer our knowledge hings! </l>
                <l>Whiles closde, whiles op'ned by th'aetheriall hoste, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000261-197-a"/>
                <l>Which makes vs sometime sharpe to see small things, </l>
                <l>And yet quite blinde when as we should see most: </l>
                <l>That curious braines may rest amazde at it, </l>
                <l>Whose ignorance makes them presume of it. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then let vs liue, since all things change below, </l>
                <l>When raisde most high as those that once may fall, </l>
                <l>And hold when by disasters brought more lowe, </l>
                <l>The minde still free what euer else be thrall: </l>
                <l>Those Lordes of Fortune sweeten euery state, </l>
                <l>That can command themselues, thogh not their fate. </l>
              </lg>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="eng000261-e141160">
        <pb xml:id="eng000261-197-b"/>
        <head>Some verses written to his Maiestie by the Authour at the time of his Maiesties first entrie into England. </head>
        <lg>
          <l>Stay tragick muse with those vntimely verses, </l>
          <l>With raging accents and with dreadfull sounds, </l>
          <l>To draw dead Monarkes out of ruin'd herses, </l>
          <l>T'affright th'applauding world with bloudie wounds: </l>
          <l>Raze all the monuments of horrours past, </l>
          <l>T'aduance the publike mirth our treasures wast. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>And pardon (olde Heroes) for O I finde, </l>
          <l>I had no reason to admire your fates: </l>
          <l>And with rare guiftes of body and of minde, </l>
          <l>Th'vnbounded greatnesse of euill-conquerd states. </l>
          <l>More glorious actes then were atchieu'd by you, </l>
          <l>Do make your wonders thought no wonders now. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>For yee the Potentates of former times, </l>
          <l>Making your will a right, your force a law: </l>
          <l>Staining your conquest with a thousand crimes, </l>
          <l>Still raign'd like tyrants but obey'd for awe: </l>
          <l>And whilst your yoake none willingly would beare, </l>
          <l>Dyed oft the sacrifice of wrath and feare. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>But this age great with glorie hath brought forth </l>
          <l>A matchlesse Monarke whom peace highlie raises, </l>
          <l>Who as th'vn'tainted Ocean of all worth </l>
          <l>As due to him hath swallow'd all your praises. </l>
          <l>Whose cleere excellencies long knowne for such, </l>
          <l>All men must praise, and none can praise too much. </l>
          <pb xml:id="eng000261-198-a"/>
          <l>For that which others hardly could acquire, </l>
          <l>With losse of thousands liues and endlesse paine, </l>
          <l>Is heapt on him euen by their owne desire, </l>
          <l>That thrist t'enioy the fruites of his blest raigne: </l>
          <l>And neuer conquerour gain'd so great a thing, </l>
          <l>As those wise subiects gaining such a King. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>But what a mightie state is this I see? </l>
          <l>A little world that all true worth inherites, </l>
          <l>Strong without art, entrench'd within the sea, </l>
          <l>Abounding in braue men full of great spirits: </l>
          <l>It seemes this Ile would boast, and so she may, </l>
          <l>To be the soueraigne of the world some day. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>O generous IAMES the glorie of thir parts, </l>
          <l>In large dominions equall with the best: </l>
          <l>But the most mightie Monarke of mens harts, </l>
          <l>That euer yet a Diadem possest: </l>
          <l>Long maist thou liue, well lou'd &amp; free from dangers, </l>
          <l>The comfort of thine owne, the terrour of strangers. </l>
        </lg>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="eng000261-e141650">
        <pb xml:id="eng000261-198-b"/>
        <head>Some verses written shortly thereafter by reason of an Inundation of Douen, a water neere vnto the Authors house, wherevpon his Maiestie was sometimes wont to Hawke. </head>
        <lg>
          <l>WHat wonder though my melancholious muse, </l>
          <l>Whose generous course some lucklesse starre controules: </l>
          <l>Her bold attempts to prosecute refuse, </l>
          <l>And would faine burie my abortiue scroules. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>To what perfection can my lines be raisd, </l>
          <l>Whilst many a crosse would quench my kindling fires: </l>
          <l>Lo for Parnassus by the Poets prais'd, </l>
          <l>Some sauage mountaines shadow my retires. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>No Helicon her treasure here vnlockes, </l>
          <l>Of all the sacred band the chiefe refuge: </l>
          <l>But dangerous Douen rumbling through the rockes, </l>
          <l>Would scorne the raine-bowe with a new deluge. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>As Tiber mindefull of his olde renowne, </l>
          <l>Augments his floodes to waile the faire chang'd place: </l>
          <l>And greeu'd to glide through that degener'd towne, </l>
          <l>Toyles with his depthes to couer their disgrace. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>So doth my Douen rage greeu'd in like sort, </l>
          <l>While as his wonted honour comes to minde: </l>
          <l>To that great Prince whilst he afforded sport, </l>
          <l>To whom his Trident Neptune hath resign'd. </l>
        </lg>
        <pb xml:id="eng000261-199-a"/>
        <lg>
          <l>And as the want of waters and of swaines, </l>
          <l>Had but begotten to his bankes neglect: </l>
          <l>He striues t'encroch vpon the bordering plaines, </l>
          <l>Againe by greatnesse to procure respect. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Thus all the creatures of this orphand boundes, </l>
          <l>In their own kindes moou'd with the common crosse: </l>
          <l>With many a monstrous forme all forme confoundes, </l>
          <l>To make vs mourne more feelingly our losse. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>We must our breastes to baser thoughts inure, </l>
          <l>Since we want all that did aduance our name: </l>
          <l>For in a corner of the world obscure, </l>
          <l>We rest vngrac'd without the boundes of fame. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>And since our Sunne shines in another part, </l>
          <l>Liue like th'Antipodes depriu'd of light: </l>
          <l>Whilst those to whom his beames he doth impart, </l>
          <l>Begin their day whilst we begin our night. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>This hath discourag'd my high-bended minde, </l>
          <l>And still in doale my drouping Muse arrayes: </l>
          <l>Which if my Phoebus once vpon me shin'd, </l>
          <l>Might raise her flight to build amidst his rayes. </l>
        </lg>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
        <pb xml:id="eng000261-199-b"/>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
