<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eng000259" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Darius</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>William</forename>
            <surname>Alexander</surname>
          </persName>
          <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q4019920</idno>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A16527_02.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
        </bibl>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The monarchicke tragedies Crœsus, Darius, The Alexandræan, Iulius Cæsar. Newly enlarged by William Alexander, Gentleman of the Princes priuie chamber.</title>
            <author>Stirling, William Alexander, Earl of, 1567 or 8-1640.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>199 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2012 November (TCP phase 2)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99835942</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 344.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg III:1009, I:260,261.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">177</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16527</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2240897091</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The monarchicke tragedies Crœsus, Darius, The Alexandræan, Iulius Cæsar. Newly enlarged by William Alexander, Gentleman of the Princes priuie chamber.</title>
            <title type="alt">Monarchick tragedies</title>
            <title type="alt">Tragedie of Croesus.</title>
            <title type="alt">Alexandraean tragedie.</title>
            <title type="alt">Tragedie of Iulius Caesar.</title>
            <title type="alt">Tragedie of Julius Caesar.</title>
            <author>Stirling, William Alexander, Earl of, 1567 or 8-1640.</author>
            <author>Stirling, William Alexander, 1567 or 8-1640.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[410] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by Valentine Simmes for Ed: Blount,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date type="publication_date">1607.</date>
            <date type="creation_date">1604</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>In verse.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: [pi]1 a2 B-M4 N2; A-K4 L2; A-Dd4 Ee2 (||-A2).</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Leaves K4 (second series) and A1 and E2 (third series) are blank.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>A reissue of the edition of 1604 with cancel general title page; "The tragedie of Darius" retains its original 1604 title page. A separately signed section has been added containing "The Alexandræan tragedie" and "The tragedie of Iulius Cæsar", each with separate dated title page.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The title page to "The Alexandræan tragedie" is a cancel with a mask ornament. The cancellandum has a lace ornament.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <person xml:id="eng000259-darius">
            <persName>Darius</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000259-parmenio">
            <persName>Parmenio</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000259-alexander">
            <persName>Alexander</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000259-statira">
            <persName>Statira</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000259-sisigambis">
            <persName>Sisigambis</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000259-statira_daughter">
            <persName>Statira Daughter</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000259-hephaestion">
            <persName>Hephaestion</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000259-bessus">
            <persName>Bessus</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000259-nabarzanes">
            <persName>Nabarzanes</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000259-tiriotes">
            <persName>Tiriotes</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000259-artabazus">
            <persName>Artabazus</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000259-polystratus">
            <persName>Polystratus</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000259-nuntius">
            <persName>Nuntius</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000259-chorus">
            <persName>Chorus</persName>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
      <textClass>
        <classCode scheme="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q80930</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1603">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="eng000259-e100030">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="eng000259-050-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="eng000259-050-b"/>
        <p>THE TRAGEDIE OF DARIVS. </p>
        <p>By William Alexander of Menstrie. </p>
        <quote>Omne tulit punctum qui miscuit vtile dulci. </quote>
        <p>LONDON Printed by G. Elde for Edward Blount. 1604. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="eng000259-e100080">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="eng000259-051-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="eng000259-051-b"/>
        <head>In praise of the Author, and his Poeme. </head>
        <lg>
          <head>A SONNET. </head>
          <l>GIue place all yee to dying Darius wounds </l>
          <l>(While this great Greeke him in his throne enstalles) </l>
          <l>That fell before seauen ported Thebes walles, </l>
          <l>Or vnder Ilions olde sky-threatning rounds. </l>
          <l>Your sowre-sweete sighes not halfe so sadlie sounds, </l>
          <l>Though, I confesse, most famous be your falles, </l>
          <l>Slaine, sacrifizd, transported, and made thralles; </l>
          <l>pracipate, burnt, bannish'd from your bounds: </l>
          <l>Whome Sophocles, Euripides haue song, </l>
          <l>Aeschylus end in stately Tragick tune: </l>
          <l>Yet none of all hath so diuinely done, </l>
          <l>As matchlesse Menstrie in his natiue toung. </l>
          <l>So Darius ghost seemes glad for to be so </l>
          <l>Triumpht on twise by Alexanders two. </l>
        </lg>
        <signed>Io. MVRRAY. </signed>
      </div>
      <div type="sonnet" xml:id="eng000259-e100250">
        <pb xml:id="eng000259-052-a"/>
        <head>A Sonnet </head>
        <l>WHen as the Macedonian conquerour came </l>
        <l>To great Achilles Tomb, he sigh'd, and said; </l>
        <l>Well may thy ghost, braue champion, be appay'd, </l>
        <l>That Homers Muse was trumpet of thy fame. </l>
        <l>But if that Monarch great in deedes and name, </l>
        <l>Now once againe with mortall vaile array'd, </l>
        <l>Came to the Tomb where Darius hath beene lay'd, </l>
        <l>This speech more iustly sighing might he frame: </l>
        <l>My famous foe, whom I lesse hate, then pitty, </l>
        <l>Euen I, who vanquish'd thee, enuie thy glory, </l>
        <l>In that such one doth sing thy ruines story, </l>
        <l>As matcheth Homer in his sweetest ditty; </l>
        <l>Yet ioy I that he Alexander hight, </l>
        <l>And sounds in thy ore-throw my matchles might. </l>
        <signed>W. Quin. </signed>
      </div>
      <div cert="high"
              type="encomium"
              xml:id="eng000259-e100410"
              xml:lang="lat">
        <head>Eiusdem in nomen Authoris GVLIELMVS ALEXANDER, Anagramma. I, LARGVS MELLE EXVNDA. Tetrasticon. </head>
        <l>CVm tibi det Genius, Musa, ingeniumque, Poēsis </l>
        <l>Floribus é varijs Attica mella lega; </l>
        <l>I, largus melle exunda, mellitáque funde </l>
        <l>Carmina: sic facias nomine fata iubent. </l>
      </div>
      <div type="preface" xml:id="eng000259-e100460">
        <pb xml:id="eng000259-052-b"/>
        <head>THE ARGVMENT. </head>
        <p>DARIVS, the fourteenth from Cyrus King of Persia, being after the death of Occhus for his singular valour from the gouernment of Armenia advanced to the Persian empyre, became so arrogant (Fortune, as it were, setting him forward to confusion) as he sent to demand tribute of Phillip, then King of Macedonia: who being of a hautie nature, and inferiour to none of that age in courage, or militarie discipline, requited this contumelius message with as disdainfull an answere; threatning that he would come and deliuer it in Persepolis. But being preuented by death he left the execution of his designe to his sonne Alexander, who for the great victories which thereafter he obtained was surnamed the great. He inheriting the hatred of his Father towards Darius, and far surmounting him in ambition, past in person to Asia with an armie of thirtie thousand only. </p>
        <p>After his arriuall, Darius wrote to him in a proud and contemptible manner, ascribing to himselfe the title of the King of Kings, and kinsman of the Gods, and naming Alexander his seruant. Hee also in vaunting manner boasted that he would haue that mad boy, the sonne Philip (for so in derision he tearmed him) bound, and beaten with rods, and after brought to his presence apparrelled like a Prince. For performance whereof he directed one of his Minions with fourtie thousand, to make impediment to his passage at the riuer of Granick; where by the wonderfull valour of Alexander <pb xml:id="eng000259-053-a"/>they were ouer-throwne. Darius being aduertised of this, came himselfe in proper person, accompanied with infinite, (but euill ordered) nombers; and encountred Alexander beside Isso, in the straites of Cilicia: where hauing fought a doubtfull and bloody battell, in ende by the invincible valour, and neuer-fayling Fortune of Alexander his armie was defeated, himselfe put to flight, and his mother, wife, and children made captiues. They were most courteouslie entertained by Alexander: who notwithstanding their exceeding great beautie yet would not abuse them, or suffer them to be abused by others: nor visited he them more oft then once (and that to comfort them) all the time of their imprisonment. </p>
        <p>Darius, notwithstanding of all his losses (his courage being in the full, whilst his Fortune was in the waine) wrote very proudly to Alexander, taking still the title of a King to himselfe, but not giuing it him, offering him as much gold, as Macedon could containe, for ransome of the Captiues. Which being very disdainfully refused by Alexander, he hauing re-enforced his troupes, &amp; comming forwarder to fight with greater force then before, was enformed how his wife had died in prison, whose death he bewaild with exceeding great sorrowe. And vnderstanding what courtesie Alexander had vsed towards her, he sent to sue for peace, not for any feare of his force, but allured (as he alledged) by his courtesie. This sute being likewise reiected, he fought beside Arbella with no better Fortune then before. Yet for all these misfortunes being of an inuincible courage, and dispayring of peace, he re-assembled all his forces, which were augmented by the comming of the Bactrians, &amp; was comming forward with intention at last either to die, or preuaile. But <pb xml:id="eng000259-053-b"/>in the meane time two traiterous subiects of his owne, to wit, Bessus whom he had promoted to be gouernour of Bactria, &amp; Nabarzanes one in speciall credite with him, conspired his death. Which danger, though it was reuealed to him by Patron, Captaine of the Greekes, yet he could not, or rather would not eschue. At length, those two traitours tooke and bound him with golden chaines, and cast him in an olde Chariot, with purpose to present him to Alexander. But they hearing how he would not accept their present, and how he was comming to inuade them, threw their darts at Darius, and left him for dead. In this estate he was found by Polistratus, and after the deliuery of some fewe words dyed. Alexander hauing exceedinglie lamented his miserable and vndeserued end, directed his bodie to his mother Sisigambis to be honourably buried. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="eng000259-e100500">
        <pb xml:id="eng000259-054-a"/>
        <head>The persons names that speakes. </head>
        <list>
          <item>Darius. </item>
          <item>Sisigambis, his mother. </item>
          <item>Statira Re. his wife. </item>
          <item>Statira Virg his daughter. </item>
          <item>Tiriotes, their Eunuch. </item>
          <item>Nabarzanes two traitours. </item>
          <item>Bessus. two traitours. </item>
          <item>Patron, Captaine of the mercenary Greekes. </item>
          <item>Nuntius. </item>
          <item>Alexander. </item>
          <item>Parmenio, his Lieutenant. </item>
          <item>Hephestion, his Minion. </item>
          <item>Polistratus, a souldier. </item>
          <item>Artabazus, a noble man of Persia. </item>
          <item>Chorus, all Persians. </item>
        </list>
        <p>The Scene supposed in Babilon. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="tragedy" xml:id="eng000259-e100690">
        <pb xml:id="eng000259-054-b"/>
        <head>THE TRAGEDY OF DARJƲS. </head>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="eng000259-e100700">
          <head>Actus Primus. </head>
          <sp who="#eng000259-darius" xml:id="eng000259-e100710">
            <speaker>DARIVS. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>WHat thundering power grow'n jealous of my state </l>
              <l>With such hostilitie my troupes o're-throwes, </l>
              <l>And arm'd with lightning, breathing flames of hate, </l>
              <l>Big with disdaine, high indignation showes </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Whil'st sooth'd with selfe conceits asham'd to doubt, </l>
              <l>In greatnesse shadowe I securelie slept, </l>
              <l>Lo change-affecting Fortune wheeles about, </l>
              <l>And ruines all that me from ruine kept. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Thus I, whose onlie name amaz'd my foes, </l>
              <l>Whom th'earth ador'd, as Monarche, once ouer all, </l>
              <l>Am so degraded now, and sunke in woes, </l>
              <l>That who admir'd my might, admire my fall. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Ah then indeed I fell, when gallants stood, </l>
              <l>And Phoenix-like renew'd their life by death, </l>
              <l>Who hauing seald their force and faith with blood, </l>
              <l>Would rather die, then draw a borrowed breath. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Yet I, but then not I, view'd not aveng'd, </l>
              <l>Those monstrous mountaines of my subjects slaine, </l>
              <l>Although my conscience hath my courage cleng'd, </l>
              <l>And knowes what valour was employ'd in vaine. </l>
            </lg>
            <pb xml:id="eng000259-055-a"/>
            <lg>
              <l>Through greatest dangers death I did pursue, </l>
              <l>Till heapes of slaughtred bodies bar'd my way, </l>
              <l>And chang'd my Chariot to a scarlet hue, </l>
              <l>Ere wounded honour could be drawne away. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>O how I enuy yet their happie Ghostes, </l>
              <l>Who died whil'st hope of victorie remain'd, </l>
              <l>And in the presence of two famous hostes </l>
              <l>Left bloodie recordes that they died vnstain'd? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Shall I suruiue that soule-ouerwhelming shame, </l>
              <l>To be th'eternall staine of Persians praise? </l>
              <l>No rather let me die, and let my name, </l>
              <l>Be quite exstinguish'd with my hatefull dayes. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Starre-bosting Babilon blush to behold </l>
              <l>One cald thy King surmounted and abated: </l>
              <l>How may thy Towrs but tremble, when it's told, </l>
              <l>Thy Prince entreats, whome Princes earst entreated? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Not vassal-like; I will not yeeld to this: </l>
              <l>Were all my Empire to a period come, </l>
              <l>Yet none shall vaunt that euer I was his: </l>
              <l>Hartes holding courage are not all o're-come. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>This tongue inur'd still to command doth scorne </l>
              <l>To breath base words, to scape a minutes paines. </l>
              <l>Let them obey, who to obey were borne: </l>
              <l>For Darius this indignitie disdaines. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Since I was once iudg'd worthie to command, </l>
              <l>Shall I returne to be a base entreater? </l>
              <l>No, whil'st a sword yeelds homage to this hand, </l>
              <l>Ile not acknowledge in the world a greater. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Braue spirites, who now possesse the pleasant bowers, </l>
              <l>And glorious gardens of th'Elisian plaine, </l>
              <l>(For if deserts may moue th'infernall powers, </l>
              <l>That happie shade your shadowes must containe) </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Those fields where-as your praises are set forth </l>
              <l>Do burie but your bodies, not your fame: </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-055-b"/>
              <l>Men shall adore the relickes of your worth, </l>
              <l>And reare immortall Trophees to your name. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Ile sacrifize as incense to your soules, </l>
              <l>His dying sighes, and sorrowing parents teares, </l>
              <l>Who now, while none his insolence controules, </l>
              <l>Our conquer'd ensignes in his triumphe beares. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>For it may ease your Ghostes to heare his grones, </l>
              <l>Whil'st th'earth ouer-burdend sends rebounding back </l>
              <l>A plaintife Echo from the woods and stones, </l>
              <l>To sound through all the aire his armies wrack. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Why spend I speaches to disturbe your rest? </l>
              <l>What idle disputations do I hold? </l>
              <l>A mightie furour hath enflam'd my brest, </l>
              <l>And burnes me, till I be aueng'd seuen-fold. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Did I that strong Cadusian first affront, </l>
              <l>Who durst aduance himselfe to braue our bandes, </l>
              <l>Then turn'd applauded, and in high account, </l>
              <l>Charg'd with his spoiles the honour of my hands? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And could I then all kinde of doubt remoouing, </l>
              <l>Aduenter only to an Armies shame? </l>
              <l>And should I now that auncient praise disprouing, </l>
              <l>With squadrons compast loose that glorious name? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Blinde fortune, O, thy stratagems are strange: </l>
              <l>Thou wrak'st my greatnes, wound'st mine honour to, </l>
              <l>And hauing made my state the stage of change, </l>
              <l>Hast acted all inconstancie could do. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Lo I, who late of swarming troupes did bost, </l>
              <l>Am spoil'd of all in whome I then repos'd, </l>
              <l>And those imprison'd, whome I fancie most, </l>
              <l>Are to th'insulting victours pride expos'd. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>O torment but to thinke, death to beleeue, </l>
              <l>That any may command my deerest part, </l>
              <l>And wretched I notable to releeue </l>
              <l>The Iewell of mine eye, ioy of my hart. </l>
            </lg>
            <pb xml:id="eng000259-056-a"/>
            <lg>
              <l>Deere obiect of my thoughtes, my life, my loue, </l>
              <l>Sweete source of my delights, my one, my all, </l>
              <l>Bright Image of excellencies aboue, </l>
              <l>What? do'st thou breath, and com'st not when I call? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And can I be, and not be where thou art? </l>
              <l>Hath heauen the force me from thy face to barre? </l>
              <l>Or are my hands growne traitors to my hart, </l>
              <l>That they should shrinke from doing what it dare? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>O could my minde but distribute a space </l>
              <l>These emulating thoughts that tosse my brest, </l>
              <l>Among those pointles Cyphers that spend place: </l>
              <l>Then I alone might animate the rest. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Since in this great disgrace I chanc'd to fall, </l>
              <l>Now nothing rests to rase my fame forlorne, </l>
              <l>But to doe desperatly, and hazard all. </l>
              <l>Ile liue with praise, or by my death flie scorne. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Some prosperous issue afterward may purge </l>
              <l>This crime, with which th'euent would burthen me, </l>
              <l>This crime, that carries with it selfe a scourge: </l>
              <l>No greater torment than the want of thee. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>But what hope rests to re-obtaine that treasure, </l>
              <l>Which auaritious tyrants once possesse? </l>
              <l>Another now disposes at his pleasure </l>
              <l>Of all my wealth: how can I looke for lesse? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Now, not till now, I deeme my state in danger, </l>
              <l>When I imagine how my best belou'd </l>
              <l>Must entertaine my enemy a stranger, </l>
              <l>I being far from offering aide remou'd. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>A host of furies in my brest I finde, </l>
              <l>Which do my soule with dreadfull horrours fill, </l>
              <l>And foster in my melancholious minde </l>
              <l>Strange apprehensions that affright me still. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And this surmiz'd disgrace, grown throughly strong, </l>
              <l>Reades hourely in my eares a hatefull scroule </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-056-b"/>
              <l>Of an imagin'd, yet recureles wrong, </l>
              <l>Such poison'd thoughtes like serpents sting my soule. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Blind loue beguiles me not, sharpe-sighted feares </l>
              <l>Finde great apparances for to suspect thee: </l>
              <l>Would God I had no hart, nor eyes, nor eares, </l>
              <l>To thinke, to see, or heare thou shouldst neglect me. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>This aggrauates the wight of my dispaire, </l>
              <l>When doubt obiects, t'annull loues fast defence, </l>
              <l>How he is young and feirce, she young, and faire, </l>
              <l>He bent t'offend, and she exposd t'offence, </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>From which I feare both cannot long abstaine: </l>
              <l>Her beauty is sufficient to allure: </l>
              <l>His brauery is sufficient to obtaine. </l>
              <l>Captaines will force, and captiues must endure, </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>O Alexander, tender my renowne, </l>
              <l>Although thou trauell to vsurpe my throne. </l>
              <l>I rage to haue ariuall in my Crowne: </l>
              <l>But in my loue I can comport with none. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Lode her not with disgrace, and me with griefe, </l>
              <l>Least so thou rob her honour, and my life: </l>
              <l>Spare in this point t'ouercharge me with mischiefe: </l>
              <l>In all things els let armes decide our strife. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>But where doth fury thus transport my spirits, </l>
              <l>With light beleefe my best halfe to mistrust? </l>
              <l>Deere, pardon, I trespasse to wrong thy merits, </l>
              <l>Whom I haue still found faithfull louing iust. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Pure chaistitie doth then most firmelie stand, </l>
              <l>When fortified it is with wedlockes band. </l>
              <l>Yet let me doubt, or let me leaue to loue: </l>
              <l>To feare the worst it is affections part. </l>
              <l>I'l not mistrust thy truth? yet it may proue, </l>
              <l>Thy face betray thy faith, thy hap thy hart. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>But on thy loue approou'd my hope relyes, </l>
              <l>This doth dissolue suspitions power to nought. </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-057-a"/>
              <l>I will repell reports, as slanderous lyes, </l>
              <l>Which second not thy vertue, and my thought. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Though vertues foe, and worth-envying fortune, </l>
              <l>Hath wrong'd my valour with an euill successe; </l>
              <l>Life of my life, yet must I thee importune, </l>
              <l>Ioyne not with her to double my distresse. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000259-e102740">Exit. </stage>
          <div type="chorus" xml:id="eng000259-e102750">
            <head>CHORVS. </head>
            <lg>
              <l>O More then miserable minde, </l>
              <l>That of all things it selfe worst knowes, </l>
              <l>And being through presumption blinde </l>
              <l>Is puffed vp with euery winde, </l>
              <l>Which fortune in derision blowes. </l>
              <l>Such one no stable blisse can finde, </l>
              <l>Whose hart is guided by his eye, </l>
              <l>And trustes vnto betraying showes, </l>
              <l>Which seeme not as they be. </l>
              <l>Oft short prosperity, </l>
              <l>Breedes long aduersity: </l>
              <l>For who abuse the first, the last o're-throwes. </l>
              <l>A dead security all care exiles: </l>
              <l>Tis no small danger to be happie whiles. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Who on himselfe too much depends, </l>
              <l>A makes an Idole of his witt, </l>
              <l>For euery favour fortune sends, </l>
              <l>Self-flatterer himselfe commends, </l>
              <l>And will no sound aduise admit, </l>
              <l>But at himselfe beginnes, and ends, </l>
              <l>And neuer takes a moments leasure, </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-057-b"/>
              <l>To try what fault he may commit, </l>
              <l>But drunke with frothes of pleasure, </l>
              <l>Thirstes for praise aboue measure, </l>
              <l>Imaginary treasure, </l>
              <l>Which slowly commes, and soone away doth flit: </l>
              <l>And what is most affected at this time, </l>
              <l>Succeeding ages may account a crime. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>A Potentate that is respected, </l>
              <l>And by his subiects thought a God, </l>
              <l>Thinkes, as his name on high erected </l>
              <l>Hath what he list at home effected, </l>
              <l>It may like wonders worke abrod. </l>
              <l>O how his folly is detected! </l>
              <l>For though he sit in Royall seate, </l>
              <l>And as he list his vassalls lod; </l>
              <l>Yet others that are great. </l>
              <l>Liue not by his conceate, </l>
              <l>Nor ponder what he threat, </l>
              <l>But plague his pride oft ere he feare the rod. </l>
              <l>There are rare qualities required in Kings: </l>
              <l>A naked name can never worke great things. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>They who themselues too much esteeme, </l>
              <l>And vainly vilipend their foe, </l>
              <l>Oft finde not fortune, as they deeme, </l>
              <l>And with their treasure would redeeme </l>
              <l>Their errour past: Behold euen so </l>
              <l>From blame who can our King exeeme, </l>
              <l>Who his aduersary to scorne, </l>
              <l>Thought he who in his name did goe </l>
              <l>The laurell should haue worne, </l>
              <l>His triumphe to adorne? </l>
              <l>But he with shame hath shorne </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-058-a"/>
              <l>The fruites of follie euer ripe with woe. </l>
              <l>An enemie (if it be well aduis'd) </l>
              <l>Though he seeme weake, should neuer be despis'd. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>But what? the Minions of our Kings, </l>
              <l>Who speake at large, and are beleeued, </l>
              <l>Dare boast of many mightie things, </l>
              <l>As they could flie, though wanting wings, </l>
              <l>And deeds by wordes might be atchëeued, </l>
              <l>But time at length their lies to light, </l>
              <l>Their soueraigne to confusion brings. </l>
              <l>Yet so they gaine, they are not greeue'd, </l>
              <l>But charme their Princes sight, </l>
              <l>And make what's wrong seeme right. </l>
              <l>Thus ruine they his might, </l>
              <l>That when he would, he cannot be releeued. </l>
              <l>Moe kings in chambers fall by flatterers charmes, </l>
              <l>Then in the field by th'aduersaries armes. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>All that the successe hath approoued </l>
              <l>By Charidemus was foreshowne: </l>
              <l>Yet with his wordes no man was mooued: </l>
              <l>For good men first must be remooued, </l>
              <l>Before their worth can well be knowne. </l>
              <l>The King would heare but what he looued, </l>
              <l>And what him pleasd not did dispise. </l>
              <l>So were the beeter sort o'er-throwne, </l>
              <l>And Sycophants vnwise, </l>
              <l>Who could the trueth disguise, </l>
              <l>Were suffered for to rise, </l>
              <l>That him, who rais'd them vp, they might cast downe. </l>
              <l>Thus Princes will not heare, though such deceaue them, </l>
              <l>Things as they are, but as themselues conceaue them. </l>
            </lg>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="eng000259-e103660">
          <pb xml:id="eng000259-058-b"/>
          <head>ACTVS SECVNDVS. </head>
          <stage xml:id="eng000259-e103670">ALEXANDER. PARMENTO. </stage>
          <lg>
            <l>BEholde, the heauens with a benigne aspect, </l>
            <l>To prosper this braue enterprise intend, </l>
            <l>And with propitious starres seeme to direct </l>
            <l>This great beginning to a glorious end. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Who would be famous must of force aspite: </l>
            <l>All those astonish'd, who my troupes do view, </l>
            <l>Doubt of those two which most they should admire; </l>
            <l>My comming, or my conquering with so few. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>So mightie mindes t'atchieue great actions bent </l>
            <l>Force Fortune oft to fauour them in all: </l>
            <l>Where baser breasts deuining euill euent, </l>
            <l>Through superstitious feares procure their fall. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>O howe I wonder, when I call to minde </l>
            <l>That monstrous camp, which not so much as doubted! </l>
            <l>Dimme seem'd the Sunne, while-as their armour shind </l>
            <l>Men had not heard the thunder, whil'st they shouted. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Th'auant-courours, that came for to examine, </l>
            <l>When they so meane my nombers had perceau'd, </l>
            <l>Did thinke them small to satisfie the famine, </l>
            <l>That their huge hoste of daughter had conceau'd. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>And yet in end this prou'd a poyson'd foode, </l>
            <l>Which of their owne to their confusion yeeldes </l>
            <l>Mountaines of murthered corps, and seas of blood: </l>
            <l>Vnburied bodies buried all the fieldes. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>So now that fewe, whome they contemn'd so farre, </l>
            <l>(See how mortalitie it selfe deceaues) </l>
            <l>Haue farre ouer-match'd their multitudes in warre, </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000259-059-a"/>
            <l>And made the world waste to people the graues. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Then, deere Parmenio, since the fates afforde </l>
            <l>So faire an entrie to our first designes, </l>
            <l>Let vs goe prosecute with dint of sworde </l>
            <l>That fortune, which the heauens our hopes assignes. </l>
          </lg>
          <sp who="#eng000259-parmenio" xml:id="eng000259-e104080">
            <speaker>Parm. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>This high attempt, as we would wish succeeds. </l>
              <l>What hostes haue we ouerthrow'n? what citties raz'd? </l>
              <l>Loe, populous Asia trembles at our deedes, </l>
              <l>And martiall Europe doth remaine amaz'd. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Proud Greece, whose spirits oft preast to skorne the skyes, </l>
              <l>A prostrate supplicant before thee falles: </l>
              <l>Rebellious Thebes, that durst thy power dispyse, </l>
              <l>Lyes now entomb'd within her broken walles. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>That sea-impyring Tyre, reposing much </l>
              <l>In liquide Castels, and a wauing maine, </l>
              <l>Hath ratified thy forces to be such, </l>
              <l>That nothing can resist thy iust disdaine. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>No doubt the auncient Graecians ghosts are glad </l>
              <l>To see the fierce Barbarians brought so lowe; </l>
              <l>Yet are for enuy of thy fortune sad, </l>
              <l>And though vnbo-died blush at this ouerthrowe. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Miltiades by all men was admir'd, </l>
              <l>Who once in Greece their flying troupes pursued: </l>
              <l>And he that with a stratageme retir'd, </l>
              <l>And Salaminaes straites with blood imbrued. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>But yet for all the Captaines of that age </l>
              <l>The Easterne Monarckes empire was enlarg'd, </l>
              <l>Who comming to their countrie, warres to wage, </l>
              <l>The sea with shippes, the land with armies charg'd. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>He with moe swarmes of men, then th'Autumns clusters, </l>
              <l>Dry'd riuers vp, &amp; march'd on Neptunes backe; </l>
              <l>By measure, not by nomber made his musters, </l>
              <l>And did attempt the mountaines plaine to make. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Then Europe fear'd for to be forc'd to bowe, </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-059-b"/>
              <l>Wil'st th'earth did groane to beare so great an host? </l>
              <l>But thou hast come, seene, and ouercom'd them nowe </l>
              <l>Euen in the boundes wherein their might was most. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>That hautie foe, who vilipended oft </l>
              <l>Our predecessours armies, and our owne, </l>
              <l>Now laide as lowe, as he was once aloft, </l>
              <l>With his disgrace must make thy valour knowne. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>He cannot but acknowledge his distresse </l>
              <l>In labouring first to haue his friends restor'd: </l>
              <l>This message (potent Prince) imports no lesse: </l>
              <l>By his request thy conquest is decor'd. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>For the recouerie of his captiu'd Queene </l>
              <l>He offred hath innumerable golde; </l>
              <l>And would present a treasure to be seene </l>
              <l>More, as they say, then Macedon may holde. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>My counsell is that you accept those offers, </l>
              <l>And render her, as th'auncient custome bindes; </l>
              <l>Who would make warre must not haue empty coffers: </l>
              <l>For hope of gaine moues mercenarie mindes. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And further, if those Princesses doe tarrie, </l>
              <l>It sumptuous is to entertaine their state. </l>
              <l>Wemen, and babes are cumbersome to carrie; </l>
              <l>Th'one young in yeares, and th'other in conceat. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e104740">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>If I were come to traffick in this land, </l>
              <l>And like a greedie merchant to embrace </l>
              <l>Before all hope of glorie gaine in hand, </l>
              <l>This your inuild opinion might haue place. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>But soone I surfet of such melting things, </l>
              <l>And famish but for fame, and crownes of Kings. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000259-parmenio" xml:id="eng000259-e104830">
            <speaker>Parm </speaker>
            <p>So, were I Alexander, would I do. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e104850">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <p>If I Parmenio were, so would I to. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000259-parmenio" xml:id="eng000259-e104870">
            <speaker>Par. </speaker>
            <p>Their ransome would defray your souldiers fee. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e104890">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <p>I'le rather without ransome set them free. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000259-parmenio" xml:id="eng000259-e104910">
            <speaker>Parm. </speaker>
            <p>The good is loste that's done vnto a fo. </p>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="eng000259-060-a"/>
          <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e104930">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <p>The greater glorie to o'recomme him so. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000259-parmenio" xml:id="eng000259-e104950">
            <speaker>Parm. </speaker>
            <p>Golde is the God that conquers in all parts. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e104970">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <p>True magnanimitie doth rauish harts. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000259-parmenio" xml:id="eng000259-e104990">
            <speaker>Parm. </speaker>
            <p>Riche treasures serue for th'arters of the war. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e105010">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <p>No, but couragious harts that all things darre. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000259-parmenio" xml:id="eng000259-e105030">
            <speaker>Parm. </speaker>
            <p>The want of wages makes a mutinous band. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e105050">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <p>But who dare disobey, when I command? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000259-parmenio" xml:id="eng000259-e105070">
            <speaker>Par. </speaker>
            <p>Why should you, Sir, contemne so rich a treasure? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e105090">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <p>A noble spirit with praise no gain doth measure. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000259-parmenio" xml:id="eng000259-e105110">
            <speaker>Parm. </speaker>
            <p>But who delites in such an airie store? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e105130">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <p>If I be singular, I aske no more. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000259-parmenio" xml:id="eng000259-e105150">
            <speaker>Parm. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Although that you conceaue no such suspition, </l>
              <l>Yet I heare how your souldiers oft exclame, </l>
              <l>They sacrifize their bloods for your ambition, </l>
              <l>And perish to perpetuate your name. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And yet, without regarde what they indure, </l>
              <l>You compasse all the empire of the East, </l>
              <l>And more within your minde: this may procure </l>
              <l>Some suddaine tumult, when you feare it least. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Retire in time, while as the heauens are cleare: </l>
              <l>You haue perform'd, perform'd, and that right sone, </l>
              <l>More than your own could hope, your foes could feare, </l>
              <l>Or then the world can credite, when 'tis done. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Your worth in warre is wonderfullie showne, </l>
              <l>And to the terrour of all Asia tryde: </l>
              <l>Now let your skill in peace be likewise knowne, </l>
              <l>And for the maint'nance of your state prouide. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Good gouernment the same of Kings doth raise </l>
              <l>No lesse then conquest made of Realmes and townes: </l>
              <l>'Tis harder farre, and doth deserue more praise </l>
              <l>To guide, then get: to keepe, then conquere crownes. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Your glorie in her hiest spheare is plac'd, </l>
              <l>And may not moue except it be more lowe: </l>
              <l>And if it once discend to be disgrac'd, </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-060-b"/>
              <l>Each artizan your statues will o're-throwe, </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>For in the warre, as you may well perceiue, </l>
              <l>No little part dependeth vpon fame: </l>
              <l>If we but once the least affront receiue, </l>
              <l>The world will gather to exstripe our name. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Then tempt not Fortune further then you neede, </l>
              <l>Let reason bridle this aspyring thought: </l>
              <l>Least, whil'st your hopes with trophees faind you feed, </l>
              <l>A moment turne your trauels all to nought. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Let Darius be a liuelie patrone now </l>
              <l>Of th'euer-changing course of states and crownes: </l>
              <l>That Prince to whom the Orient once did bow, </l>
              <l>His desolation onely now renounes. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>He scarselie loat length become content </l>
              <l>To call you King, though twise put in dis-order: </l>
              <l>In dowrie with his daughter doth present </l>
              <l>The famous Euphrates, to be your border. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Or otherwise he condiscends to giue </l>
              <l>Great store of Gold, or what your selfe desires, </l>
              <l>If that his mother, wife, and children liue, </l>
              <l>To haue them rend'red, as he oft requires. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And let not vaine ambition blind your eies: </l>
              <l>Remember what strange nations will imbrace him, </l>
              <l>Whom scarce he knowes by name, or neuer sees, </l>
              <l>Where if he fled, your troups would tire to chace him. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e105760">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Peace, peace Parmenio, now thou makest me rage, </l>
              <l>With these words vn-worthy of our eares: </l>
              <l>It seemes the coldenesse of decaying age, </l>
              <l>Hath kil'd thy courage with a frost of feares. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Did I abandone thee my natiue soile, </l>
              <l>And shaddow'd with my Ensignes vnknow'n coastes; </l>
              <l>That after infinite distresse and toile, </l>
              <l>Whil'st in contempt of vs our foe yet boastes, </l>
              <l>I should retire, effecting nought at last, </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-061-a"/>
              <l>But sharpned a desire, t'augment my merites, </l>
              <l>Then die in discontentment, when 'tis past </l>
              <l>The time, that should haue pacified my spirites? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>No, I will raigne, and I will raigne alone: </l>
              <l>From this desseigne my fancie neuer wanders, </l>
              <l>For as the heau'ns can hold no Sunne but one: </l>
              <l>The earth cannot containe two Alexanders. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>The ample circuite of this spacious round </l>
              <l>Seemes insufficient to confine my thought: </l>
              <l>And ô would God there could moe worlds be found, </l>
              <l>That many might t'adorne our deedes be brought. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>O, I could wish that th'Ocean were firme land, </l>
              <l>Where none but hideous Giants had retreat, </l>
              <l>Such as at Phlegra fielde in striefe did stand </l>
              <l>Against the Gods for the Etheriall seate. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>These could encourage martiall mindes to strike, </l>
              <l>Who being wonne would yeeld eternall praise: </l>
              <l>I conquere men; but many did the like: </l>
              <l>And after-ages may my equall raise. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>But since none such my triumphes are to grace, </l>
              <l>Such as there are I'le to subiection bring: </l>
              <l>And heere I sweare no kinde of ease t'embrace, </l>
              <l>Till all the world adore me for their King. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>If you or any else that liue in dreede </l>
              <l>With-drawe your selues, your Princes part despysing; </l>
              <l>Remember alwaies in his greatest neede </l>
              <l>Ye flie to stop his honour in the rysing. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Passe home, and liue like men in prison pent: </l>
              <l>I measure not my courage by my numbers. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000259-parmenio" xml:id="eng000259-e106240">
            <speaker>Parm. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Your Maiestie misconsters my intent: </l>
              <l>You know what I haue thold, what cares, what cumbers, </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And all for you: I to your eies appeale, </l>
              <l>Which well can witnes what my hands haue wrought. </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-061-b"/>
              <l>All that I spake, proceeded of a zeale </l>
              <l>And not of cowardice, or feare of ought. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Nor matche I vile repose with honest paines: </l>
              <l>My courage is nor yet become so colde: </l>
              <l>That wounted vigour hath not left my vaines, </l>
              <l>Which spurd my spirit in youth, though I be olde. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e106380">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>'Tis not ynough that you your selfe be so: </l>
              <l>To be the same you should the rest exhort. </l>
              <l>Is he return'd, who was ordain'd to go </l>
              <l>And viewe the Captiues, what doth he report? </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000259-parmenio" xml:id="eng000259-e106440">
            <speaker>Parm. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>As we were since by some of them instructed, </l>
              <l>While they as yet not of support dispair'd, </l>
              <l>And to a tent were courteously conducted, </l>
              <l>Which we of purpose caus'd to be prepar'd; </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Euen in the way one fortun'd to espy </l>
              <l>The Diademe that Darius earst had borne, </l>
              <l>Which on the earth so abiectly did lie, </l>
              <l>As each thing his calamine would scorne. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Then they imagin'd, from his royall head, </l>
              <l>Whose dignity it some-time did decore, </l>
              <l>None could it cast, except himselfe were dead: </l>
              <l>And if so were, they long'd to liue no more. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>When they had entred in the tent to weepe, </l>
              <l>Leonatus came and at the entrie knocked: </l>
              <l>They stood so still, he thought an yornie sleepe </l>
              <l>Had lock'd their eies, or else that he was mocked. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>At length by force he made a patent way, </l>
              <l>And was aduanc'd them louingly to greet; </l>
              <l>When loe, these dolorous Ladies prostrate lay, </l>
              <l>And with a flood of teares bedew'd his feete. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Then sobbing saide, we not refuse to die: </l>
              <l>Let vs entombe first Darius like a King: </l>
              <l>Then when that we his latter honour see, </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-062-a"/>
              <l>Death cannot but a great contentment bring. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>This so they vrg'd, as he could scarce perswade </l>
              <l>That Darius was not dead as they suppos'd, </l>
              <l>But liu'd, in hope through dangers Seas to wade </l>
              <l>And in the pow'r of other Realmes repos'd. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And further he protested on your part, </l>
              <l>That they might looke for clemencie and grace. </l>
              <l>Thus after that I had asswag'd their smart, </l>
              <l>It seem'd they longd to see my Soueraignes face. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e106850">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Of my good-will they may themselues assure: </l>
              <l>I neuer war'd with such as were subiected: </l>
              <l>And if my presence may their ease procure, </l>
              <l>Straight to their tent my steppes shall be directed. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000259-e106910">Exeunt. </stage>
          <div type="chorus" xml:id="eng000259-e106920">
            <head>CHORVS. </head>
            <lg>
              <l>OF all the passions that possesse the soule, </l>
              <l>None so disturbes vaine mortals mindes </l>
              <l>As this Ambition, that so blindes </l>
              <l>The sense of man, that nothing can controule </l>
              <l>Nor curb their thoughts who will aspyre. </l>
              <l>This raging vehement desire </l>
              <l>Of soueraignty no satisfaction findes, </l>
              <l>But in the breastes of men doth euer roule </l>
              <l>The restlesse stone of Sisiph to torment them. </l>
              <l>And as his hart, who steal'd the hev'nly fire, </l>
              <l>The vulture gnawes, so doth Ambition rent them: </l>
              <l>Had they the world, the world would not content them. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>This race of Ixion to embrace the cloudes, </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-062-b"/>
              <l>Contemne the state wherein they stand, </l>
              <l>And would all but themselues command, </l>
              <l>As one desire is quench'd another buds: </l>
              <l>When they haue trauel'd all their time, </l>
              <l>Heaps blood on blood, and crime on crime, </l>
              <l>There is a hier power that guides their hand. </l>
              <l>More happie he whome a poore cottage shroudes </l>
              <l>Against the tempest of the threatning heauen, </l>
              <l>He stands in feare of none, none enuy him: </l>
              <l>His hart is vpright, and his wayes are eauen, </l>
              <l>Where others states are still twixt sixe and seauen. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>That damned wretch vp with Ambition blow'n, </l>
              <l>While-as he turnes the wheele about, </l>
              <l>Whiles cast within, whiles cast without, </l>
              <l>In striuing for the top is still throwne downe. </l>
              <l>Those that delight in climbing hie </l>
              <l>Oft with a precepice doe die: </l>
              <l>So doe the starres sky-climbling worldlings flout. </l>
              <l>But this disease is fatall to a croune; </l>
              <l>Kings, who haue most striue most t'augment their bounds; </l>
              <l>And if they be not all, they can not be: </l>
              <l>Which to their domage commonly redounds. </l>
              <l>Too great a state her proper waight confounds. </l>
              <l>Th'ambitious toyling to enlarge their state </l>
              <l>Themselues exceedingly deceaue, </l>
              <l>In hazarding the hap they haue </l>
              <l>For a felicitie that they conceate. </l>
              <l>Though their dominions they incres, </l>
              <l>Yet their desires growe neuer les: </l>
              <l>For though they conquer Climats, more they craue. </l>
              <l>This is the miserie of being great. </l>
              <l>Such eye-beguyling pompe is all but fume; </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-063-a"/>
              <l>Such glorious showes disguise the minds distres; </l>
              <l>And who to conquere all the earth presume, </l>
              <l>A little earth shall them at last consume. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And if it fortune that they die in peace </l>
              <l>(A wonder wondrous rarelie seene) </l>
              <l>Who conquere first; their empire cleene </l>
              <l>Is ruin'd by some persons of their race: </l>
              <l>Who comming to the crowne with rest, </l>
              <l>And hauing all in peace possest, </l>
              <l>Do straight forget what bloody broils haue bene </l>
              <l>Before their Fathers could attaine that place. </l>
              <l>As th'Ocean flowes, and ebbes states rise and fall: </l>
              <l>And Princes, when their actions prosper best, </l>
              <l>For feare their greatnes should oppresse the smal, </l>
              <l>Are of some hated, and envy'd of all. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>We knowe what end the mightie Cyrus made, </l>
              <l>Whome, while he striu'd to conquere still, </l>
              <l>A woman did most vildlie kill, </l>
              <l>And in a bloodie vessell rold his head; </l>
              <l>Then said, Content thy selfe with blood: </l>
              <l>Thou still didst famish for such food: </l>
              <l>Now quench thy thirst of blood with blood at will. </l>
              <l>Some of his successors, since he was dead </l>
              <l>Haue raign'd a space with pompe, and yet with paine. </l>
              <l>Now all their glorie cannot doe vs good. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>What they so long haue laboured to obtaine, </l>
              <l>All in an instant must be lost againe. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Loe, Darius once so magnified by fame, </l>
              <l>By one whome he contemn'd o'recome, </l>
              <l>For all his brauerie now made dombe, </l>
              <l>With downe-cast eyes must signifie his shame. </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-063-b"/>
              <l>Who puft up with pernitious pride </l>
              <l>Thinke still t'haue fortune on their side, </l>
              <l>They cannot scape to be a pray to some. </l>
              <l>They spend their prosperous days as in a dreame, </l>
              <l>And as it were in fortunes bosome sleeping, </l>
              <l>They in this dull securitie abide, </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And of their doubtfull state neglect the keeping, </l>
              <l>Whilst gaistlie ruine comes vpon them creeping. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Thus the vicissitude of worldly things </l>
              <l>Doth to our eyes it selfe detect, </l>
              <l>When heauenly powers exalt, deiect, </l>
              <l>Confirme, confound, erect and ruine Kings. </l>
              <l>So Alexander mightie now, </l>
              <l>To whome the vanquish'd world doth bow. </l>
              <l>With all submission, homage, and respect </l>
              <l>Doth flie a borrow'd flight with Fortunes wings: </l>
              <l>Nor enters he his dangerous course to ponder, </l>
              <l>Yet, if that Fortune bend her cloudie browe: </l>
              <l>All those, who at his suddaine successe wonder, </l>
              <l>May gaze as much to see himselfe brought vnder. </l>
            </lg>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="eng000259-e107980">
          <head>ACTVS TERTIVS. </head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="eng000259-e107990">
            <head>Scen. I. </head>
            <stage xml:id="eng000259-e108000">SISIGAMBIS Regina, STATIRA Virgo. </stage>
            <lg>
              <l>O Dismall day detested by the light, </l>
              <l>And would to God (but God neglects our cace) </l>
              <l>The world were wrapt in a Cymerian night, </l>
              <l>That no proud eye might gaze on our disgrace. </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-064-a"/>
              <l>Why did the heauens reserue my feeble age, </l>
              <l>To goe to graue with infamie and grief? </l>
              <l>Could nothing but my shame their wrath asswage </l>
              <l>Thus offred vpon th'altar of mischief? </l>
              <l>Ah, haue I spent my youth in pompe and pleasure, </l>
              <l>And had my spring-time grac'd with pleasant flowres, </l>
              <l>That Autumne, which should reape the Sommers treasure, </l>
              <l>Might be disastred with such stormy showres? </l>
              <l>And did smooth calmes, and sun-shines of delight </l>
              <l>Make all my voyage through the world a sport; </l>
              <l>That tossed with a tempest of despight </l>
              <l>I now might perish entring at my port? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Yet for all this, were I expos'd alone </l>
              <l>Th'accursed obiect of heauens plaguing-armes, </l>
              <l>I should not thinke I had iust cause to mone, </l>
              <l>When I but waild mine owne, not others harmes. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Ay me, on those, whom more then life I loue </l>
              <l>The state-disturbing blastes of Fortune fall: </l>
              <l>Yet each of them some seuerall sorrowes moue, </l>
              <l>But wretch I suffer ship-wracke in them all. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>I suffered, when I sawe Oxatres slaine, </l>
              <l>My louing sonne, and most entirelie lou'd: </l>
              <l>dy'd in Darius, when he try'd in vaine, </l>
              <l>What fates would doe, yet still their hatred prou'd. </l>
              <l>Ah, doe the destinies extend my breath </l>
              <l>For further euill? O extreame crueltie, </l>
              <l>To vse so many instruments of death, </l>
              <l>Against one burthend with calamitie. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Yet Ioue, if this may dis-en-flame thine ire, </l>
              <l>Let all thy lightning light vpon mine head: </l>
              <l>To be consum'd with a celestiall fire </l>
              <l>Some comfort were, since that I must be dead. </l>
            </lg>
            <sp who="#eng000259-statira" xml:id="eng000259-e108420">
              <speaker>Stat. Reg. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Leaue mother these immoderate laments </l>
                <l>To me the very source, and seate of sorrowe, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-064-b"/>
                <l>Whose dayes are burthen'd with so sad euents, </l>
                <l>That hell it selfe may of my torments borrow. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Loe, the deere Lord and treasure of my thought, </l>
                <l>Whose presence I my Paradice esteem'd, </l>
                <l>To such a headlong praecipice is brought, </l>
                <l>That with the world his glorie dead is deem'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Ah, on what prop can I repose my trust, </l>
                <l>When first the greatnesse of his state I ponder; </l>
                <l>Next how his Diademe drencht in the dust </l>
                <l>Was Fortunes Trophee, and all Asias wonder? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>He whose imperious speach the world respected, </l>
                <l>And as an oracle had in regarde, </l>
                <l>Now vanquish't and contemptiblie neglected </l>
                <l>Can scarcely as a supplicant be heard. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And yet I know this more his minde afflicts, </l>
                <l>Then doth the ruine of his rigall state, </l>
                <l>That him my sight another interdicts, </l>
                <l>Who am the soueraigne of his soules conceat. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Shall he, pure quintessence of my best part, </l>
                <l>Then onely testifie the loue he beares? </l>
                <l>No, by mine eyes I will distill my hart, </l>
                <l>And for his sake dissolue my selfe in teares. </l>
                <l>Would God my breast like Cristall were transparent, </l>
                <l>That all the world might see my sinceare minde, </l>
                <l>And that my loyall thoughts were all apparent, </l>
                <l>Whose great affection cannot be confinde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>They haue imprison'd onely my poore eies, </l>
                <l>And banish'd them from th'obiect of their ioy: </l>
                <l>My firie hart with winged fancies flies </l>
                <l>And where thou goest doth still my steps conuoy. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Thy Queene is such, as whilst thou draw'st this aire, </l>
                <l>In counting captives men may still accept her: </l>
                <l>For whilst thou liust, how can thy spouse dispaire, </l>
                <l>Whom thou prefer'st euen to thy soule and scepter? </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-065-a"/>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet flatter I my selfe that am accurst: </l>
                <l>The apprehension, which with griefe I cherish, </l>
                <l>Of thy mishap may serue to make me burst. </l>
                <l>Ah, ah I faint, I feele my spirits perish. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e108920">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <p>Help, help allace, allace, the Empresse falles. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-statira_daughter" xml:id="eng000259-e108940">
              <speaker>Sta. Virg. </speaker>
              <p>O dolefull day of darknes; world of woes. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e108960">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>This greeuous spectacle my spirite appalles: </l>
                <l>Heauen, earth, and all are now become our foes. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-statira_daughter" xml:id="eng000259-e109000">
              <speaker>Sta. Virg. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I may more iustly mone then any other, </l>
                <l>Whose eares haue heard the hard hap of my father; </l>
                <l>Whose eies behold the anguish of my mother, </l>
                <l>Whom both do loade with all the woes of either. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-statira" xml:id="eng000259-e109060">
              <speaker>Stat. Reg. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What inhumaine humanity is this, </l>
                <l>With such a cruell pittie to oppresse; </l>
                <l>To bring pale ghostes backe from the fields of blis, </l>
                <l>Yet to be plung'd in th'Ocean of distresse? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>O vnkinde kindenesse that by sauing slayes, </l>
                <l>And would with louelesse loue my loue controule. </l>
                <l>Ah, of this odious Sunne th'unhappie rayes </l>
                <l>Doe cleere mine eyes but to confound my soule. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e109170">
              <speaker>Sisi. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Deare daughter, striue your passions to restraine, </l>
                <l>Least that the torrent of your greefe grow such, </l>
                <l>That it both carie you to' groundlesse a maine, </l>
                <l>And him o'rewhelme for whom, ye mourne so much. </l>
                <l>No doubt but he, if we rest captiues thus, </l>
                <l>Disdaining these indignities of ours, </l>
                <l>T'auenge himselfe in re-obtaining vs </l>
                <l>Will hazard all his Orientall pow'rs. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But ah, what comfort can a wretch afforde, </l>
                <l>Whose care-worne bread the word of wo containes? </l>
                <l>Yet though my hart would faine impugne my worde, </l>
                <l>I hope-lesse speake of hope, t'appease her paines. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-statira" xml:id="eng000259-e109320">
              <speaker>Stat. Reg. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Such consolations now came not in season, </l>
                <l>Since we must hold our greefe the greatest good: </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-065-b"/>
                <l>Dissemble not your sorrow, we haue reason </l>
                <l>Yea to sigh out our sprites and weepe our blood. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e109380">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <p>I waile my sonne. Stat. Reg. And I my husbandes fall. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-statira_daughter" xml:id="eng000259-e109400">
              <speaker>Sta. Virg. </speaker>
              <p>I waile my father, and in him vs all. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e109420">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>No woe like mine, mine cannot be releeu'd. </l>
                <l>I waile his woe, who should my woe asswage, </l>
                <l>Who liues by me, by whom I should haue liu'd, </l>
                <l>Sport of my youth, and piller of mine age. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-statira" xml:id="eng000259-e109480">
              <speaker>Stat. Reg. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>No wo like mine, who faithful to my pheere </l>
                <l>For loue of him all others had forsaken. </l>
                <l>But what a pheere? my selfe, or one more deere: </l>
                <l>Yet from my selfe my selfe by force am taken. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-statira_daughter" xml:id="eng000259-e109540">
              <speaker>Stat. Virg. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>No wo like mine, who borne a Monarkes childe </l>
                <l>Thought that my birth good hap should heape vpon me: </l>
                <l>Yet all my expectations are beguil'd, </l>
                <l>And what I hop'd in most hath most vndone me. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e109600">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <p>I mourne for him who in my womb was form'd. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-statira" xml:id="eng000259-e109620">
              <speaker>St. Reg. </speaker>
              <p>I mourne for him in whom loue me transform'd. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-statira_daughter" xml:id="eng000259-e109640">
              <speaker>Stat. Virg. </speaker>
              <p>I mourne for him by whom I formed was. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e109660">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <p>Shall I not see my selfe in that cleere glasse? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-statira" xml:id="eng000259-e109680">
              <speaker>St. Reg. </speaker>
              <p>Ah! shall I neuer in his ioy reioyce? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-statira_daughter" xml:id="eng000259-e109700">
              <speaker>St. Virg. </speaker>
              <p>Ah! shall I neuer here his cheerefull voice? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e109720">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <p>Would God from death my death might him exeeme. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-statira" xml:id="eng000259-e109740">
              <speaker>St. Reg. </speaker>
              <p>would God my life my liues life might redeeme. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-statira_daughter" xml:id="eng000259-e109760">
              <speaker>St. Vir. </speaker>
              <p>Would God the life he gaue him life might giue. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e109780">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <p>Must these gray haires my sons green youth suruiue? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-statira" xml:id="eng000259-e109800">
              <speaker>Sta. Reg. </speaker>
              <p>I will preuent him and not liue to languishe. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-statira_daughter" xml:id="eng000259-e109820">
              <speaker>Sta. Virg. </speaker>
              <p>Can I remaine behinde to liue in anguishe? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e109840">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>But whiles our wretched state we iustly mone, </l>
                <l>We may lament this infant too a space, </l>
                <l>Who in mishap inferiour were to none, </l>
                <l>If he could apprehend his tragic cace. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-statira" xml:id="eng000259-e109900">
              <speaker>Sta. Reg. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>O then how can my hart but burst a-sunder, </l>
                <l>Whom nature moues most to bemone his harmes? </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-066-a"/>
                <l>I thinke I see the hostes of heau'n all thunder </l>
                <l>On me, my spouse, and this babe in my armes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Deere image of my selfe, in whom I liue, </l>
                <l>Thy shape shames not the greatnesse of thy Syre, </l>
                <l>But of thy birth cleere euidence doth giue: </l>
                <l>Thy soure-sweete sight addes coales to my desire. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Thou that shouldst comfort most, torment'st thou me? </l>
                <l>Huge hostes of passions now my soule assembles. </l>
                <l>O how I grieue! and yet am glad to see </l>
                <l>Thee, though not him, whom thy sweet face resembles, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Goe, beare this babe from hence: a wound too deep </l>
                <l>Makes in my breast compassion of his part: </l>
                <l>Yet let him stay; I ioy to heare him weepe: </l>
                <l>This motherly affection melts my hart. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Of many woes this last is not the least, </l>
                <l>That vn-begun thy glorie must be ended; </l>
                <l>Thy fortunes Sunne, my Sonne, set in the East, </l>
                <l>While thy faire-rysing all the world attended. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Ah! must this innocent taste of mishap, </l>
                <l>Whose tender age cannot discerne his state, </l>
                <l>And be thus plagu'd, yea in his nurses lap </l>
                <l>Inherite woe by birth? Ah cruell fate. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>If thou could'st hope, what great hopes hast thou lost </l>
                <l>That art defrauded of so faire a throne? </l>
                <l>Ah in thy cradle must I see thee crost, </l>
                <l>Whom I design'd so great when we were gone? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet happy haplesse childe, thou canst not know </l>
                <l>From whence the fountaine of our sorrow flowes, </l>
                <l>Nor what it is for to be hie, or low, </l>
                <l>Nor on what thorne the rose of honour growes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet hast thou felt the pricke before the smell. </l>
                <l>Is this the benefit thy birth-right brings </l>
                <l>Heere in constrain'd captiuitie to dwell? </l>
                <l>Then better not be borne, then come of Kings. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-066-b"/>
              <lg>
                <l>O what a noise is that that doth affright me? </l>
                <l>I trow to interrupt these teares of mine, </l>
                <l>Least that such sad lamentings should delight me, </l>
                <l>They will not let me plaine, yet make me pine. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Or is it some that doth condole our cace, </l>
                <l>And commes with pittie moou'd to see vs pyn'd, </l>
                <l>And to beholde how we can death imbrace, </l>
                <l>Death soueraigne salue of a diseased minde? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e110460">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>By many signes we may our selues assure, </l>
                <l>'Tis Alexander, whom we long'd not for. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-statira" xml:id="eng000259-e110500">
              <speaker>Stat. Reg. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What? ah I die! and must my eye indure </l>
                <l>Th'vpbraiding obiect which I most abhorre? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e110540">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Suppresse such speaches now, least all go wrong. </l>
                <l>We are enuiron'd with outrageous hostes: </l>
                <l>And weaknesse must giue place vnto the strong: </l>
                <l>For Victours rage, when as the vanquish'd hostes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I will entreat him to, not for my selfe </l>
                <l>(Mine olde-age is become to death a debter) </l>
                <l>But that you may eschew this wrackfull shelfe, </l>
                <l>Whose flowre pot faded yet deserueth better. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-statira" xml:id="eng000259-e110650">
              <speaker>Stat. Reg. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>No, if you needs will sue, sue for my graue: </l>
                <l>I will not be indebted to him liuing: </l>
                <l>I rather death should once the maistrie haue, </l>
                <l>Then I should die so oft with death still striuing. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="eng000259-e110710">
            <head>ACTVS TERTIVS. Scen. II. </head>
            <stage xml:id="eng000259-e110720">ALEXANDER, SISIGAMBIS, STATIRA Regina, HEPHESTION. </stage>
            <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e110730">
              <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>RIse mother, rise, remoue those causles feares: </l>
                <l>I come t'appease nort to procure your woe: </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-067-a"/>
                <l>The honour which I owe those aged heares </l>
                <l>Permits me not to see you prostrate so. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e110790">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Most gracious Prince, forgiue me if I er'd, </l>
                <l>In taking him for you, that standeth by. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e110830">
              <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I finde no fault to see my friend prefer'd </l>
                <l>Euen to my selfe: this is another I. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e110870">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>My sorrowes so confounded haue my minde, </l>
                <l>That scarce I know my selfe, much lesse another: </l>
                <l>My soule in such an agonie I finde, </l>
                <l>As if some mightie mountaine did me smoother. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e110930">
              <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I pray you, mother, set those plaints apart: </l>
                <l>They vexe me more then sterne Bellonaes broiles. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e110970">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>This tender name of mother wounds my hart, </l>
                <l>Pronounc'd by him who of that name me spoiles. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I was (woe that I was) a mother late </l>
                <l>Of two faire sonnes, faire sonnes lights of my life: </l>
                <l>Now th'one is dead, and in a worse estate, </l>
                <l>Doth th'other liue involu'd in woe and strife, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Like th'auncient trunke of some dis-branched tree, </l>
                <l>Which Eols rage hath to confusion brought, </l>
                <l>Dis-arm'd of all those impes that sprung from me, </l>
                <l>Vn-profitable stock I serue for nought. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-statira" xml:id="eng000259-e111110">
              <speaker>Stat. Reg. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I serue for nought, since him I cannot serue, </l>
                <l>Whose sight may onlie my dead ioyes reuiue. </l>
                <l>I with the famine of all comfort sterue, </l>
                <l>Since I want him for whom I wish'd to liue. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I liue without my halfe, without my whole, </l>
                <l>Prodigious monster, whome the world admires: </l>
                <l>I want the point, the Pilote, and the Pole, </l>
                <l>That drew, addrest, and gouern'd my desires, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Now toss'd with stormes in th'Ocean of dispaire </l>
                <l>By ruine onely I attend releefe, </l>
                <l>Threatned aboue with pitchie cloudes of care, </l>
                <l>Threatned belowe with swelling gulfes of greefe. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-067-b"/>
              <lg>
                <l>My soule seemes to presage disastrous chances, </l>
                <l>And varying with her selfe hath neuer peace: </l>
                <l>My hare opprest falles into deadly trances: </l>
                <l>My eyes must grace the ground of my disgrace. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Hell hath assembled all her horrours heere: </l>
                <l>Ah, in the concaue of this cursed breast, </l>
                <l>As in the darke Tartarian groues, appeere </l>
                <l>A thousand shaddowes to bereaue my rest. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e111370">
              <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Faire Princesse, spare those passionate complaints </l>
                <l>Which may augment, but not amend your harmes: </l>
                <l>This voice, which with your woe the world acquaints, </l>
                <l>Doth moue me more, then all the Persians armes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Madame, take courage, be affraide of none: </l>
                <l>You may expect what helpe I can afforde: </l>
                <l>I sweare by Ioues inviolable throne, </l>
                <l>And doe protest by my imperiall worde, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>That neither I, nor any wight shall wrong you. </l>
                <l>Yea more then this, I lay my faith in paund, </l>
                <l>You shall be honoured heere as doth belong you: </l>
                <l>And, as it were, in your owne Court command. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-statira" xml:id="eng000259-e111530">
              <speaker>Sta. Reg. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ah how can I command, whilst I am thrall? </l>
                <l>What can I haue who wanting one want all? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e111570">
              <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Though it seeme glorious in some victors sight </l>
                <l>T'abuse their captiues, and triumph in ill: </l>
                <l>The larger growe the limites of my might, </l>
                <l>The more I striue for to restraine my will, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The saue garde of my fauour shall extend </l>
                <l>Not only t'wards you, but t'wards all your traine. </l>
                <l>I shall haue care that who on me attend </l>
                <l>From offering wrong you, or yours refraine. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>If any prease t'impugne what I appoint, </l>
                <l>Or would in ambush for your honour lie, </l>
                <l>Or discontent you but in any point, </l>
                <l>As Alexander liues, that wretch shall die. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="eng000259-068-a"/>
            <sp who="#eng000259-statira" xml:id="eng000259-e111730">
              <speaker>Sta. Reg. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>O what a hoste of euils, where ere I goe, </l>
                <l>Are still encroaching on my down-cast state? </l>
                <l>And must I be beholden to my foe, </l>
                <l>Who doth deuide me from my royall mate? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Should he helpe me who would extermine him? </l>
                <l>Curst be my hart, if it betray him thus. </l>
                <l>Eternall shaddowes mot these eies first dim, </l>
                <l>Ere such a light be gratefull vnto vs. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I holde not of my selfe; Lord, I am thine: </l>
                <l>Thy loue was sow'ne not in a barren field, </l>
                <l>But in a fertile ground: this hart of mine </l>
                <l>To thee, my deere, no small increase doth yeeld. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet this good fortune doth mis-fortune bring; </l>
                <l>My constancie shall now be clearlie knowne: </l>
                <l>Another might haue lou'd a happie King: </l>
                <l>But I will loue thee though thou be ore-throwne. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e111940">
              <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Faine would I striue to confort in some measure </l>
                <l>This mourning Queene, and mitigate her paine; </l>
                <l>Whose woe doth make my victorie no pleasure, </l>
                <l>But hath ensowr'd the sweetnesse of my gaine. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e112000">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Most mightie King, thou do'st deserue indeed </l>
                <l>That, as for Darius, we should pray for thee, </l>
                <l>Who doest so farre in clemencie exceed, </l>
                <l>That thou bewailst our losse no lesse then he. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Thou hast not onely by thy worth surmounted </l>
                <l>All other Kings in dignitie alone, </l>
                <l>And benefits of Fortune most accounted, </l>
                <l>But in all vertues worthie of a throne. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Thou do'st vouchsafe on me (more then I craue) </l>
                <l>The title of a Queene, and mother still: </l>
                <l>But I confesse my selfe thy humble slaue, </l>
                <l>Whose life hath now no limits but thy will. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I haue all that imagin'd good forgote, </l>
                <l>Which greatnesse gaue: I'le looke no more so sadlie: </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-068-b"/>
                <l>But will alow of this my present lot, </l>
                <l>And beare the burthen of my bondage gladly. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>If that this wretched woman heere were free, </l>
                <l>Who hath no heauen except her husbands face, </l>
                <l>I could content my selfe (great Prince) to be </l>
                <l>The meanest hand-maide that attends your grace. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e112260">
              <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You may command me, as I were your Sonne, </l>
                <l>Whose duteous loue shall prooue no lesse intire. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e112300">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Heauens recompence the court'sy thou hast done </l>
                <l>Which all succeeding ages shall admire. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e112340">
              <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Those captiu'd Princesses haue pierc'd my soule, </l>
                <l>Who eu'n amid'st our heauen haue found a hell. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-hephaestion" xml:id="eng000259-e112380">
              <speaker>Hep. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What stoick brow his passions could controule, </l>
                <l>As not to weepe, if he re-marked well </l>
                <l>The teares of these faire Ladies causing wonder, </l>
                <l>Who neede not challenge nature of her duty; </l>
                <l>But borne to bring, although they be brought vnder, </l>
                <l>Giue greefe a grace for to apparrell beauty, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Sir, such a victorie hath not beene seene </l>
                <l>As you haue gain'd, whose greatnesse well appeares; </l>
                <l>The largest kingdome, and the fairest Queene, </l>
                <l>That Asia vaunted of these many yeares. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Durst Ledaes or Agenors brood compare </l>
                <l>With that sweete Queene, the honour of her kinde? </l>
                <l>But as she is aboue all other faire, </l>
                <l>As farre her daughters make her go behinde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>It seem'd at first that sorrow had beene sleeping </l>
                <l>While as these Virgines in their Grand-dames bosome </l>
                <l>With weeping beautie, and with beauties weeping </l>
                <l>Did with a haile of pearle blast beauties blossome. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>So large a pow'r is to no Prince allotted, </l>
                <l>As to loues Empire in their face confynd. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e112640">
              <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>O how is my Hephestion thus assotted? </l>
                <l>Dare follie seeke t'assault so braue a minde? </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-069-a"/>
              <lg>
                <l>Dare Cupid enter in an armed campe, </l>
                <l>And Mars owne minions thus presume to danton? </l>
                <l>Must his soft seale steele-wearing stomacks stampe, </l>
                <l>And make them tributaries to that wanton? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-hephaestion" xml:id="eng000259-e112730">
              <speaker>Hep. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We dare resist (whil'st many a thousand dies) </l>
                <l>Against th'inuasion of a world of men: </l>
                <l>Yet if in yuorie orbes two Sunnie eies </l>
                <l>Assault the soule at vnawares, O then </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Some secret sympathie, some vn-knowne motion </l>
                <l>So charmes the minde, that vaine are all defenses. </l>
                <l>The hart drunke with the eies contagious potion </l>
                <l>Corrupts the spirits and poysons all the senses. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e112840">
              <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>But I in my conceat doe skorne all such: </l>
                <l>No, I resolue to be a thrall to none: </l>
                <l>Yea, ere I but abase my selfe so much, </l>
                <l>I'le rather die ten thousand deathes in one. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Should I be bound with vile affections chaines, </l>
                <l>As one obliuious of my former fame? </l>
                <l>This resolution still my soule retaines, </l>
                <l>To ballance nothing with a noble name. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>O what a great indignity is this </l>
                <l>To see a Conquerour to his lust a slaue? </l>
                <l>Who would the title of true worth were his </l>
                <l>A minde surmounting euery vice must haue. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The brauest trophee euer man obtain'd </l>
                <l>Is that, which ou'r himselfe himselfe hath gain'd. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-hephaestion" xml:id="eng000259-e113030">
              <speaker>Hep. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I ioy, my soueraigne, that as you excell </l>
                <l>Not onely men, but Mars himselfe in armes: </l>
                <l>So you by vertues might the power repell </l>
                <l>Of beautie, loue, and Cithereas charmes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Your vertue bright, whose rayes shine in your words </l>
                <l>And thence to harts center are reflected; </l>
                <l>Now ouer my selfe such pow'r to me affords, </l>
                <l>That with fond loue I loth to he infected. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="eng000259-e113140">
            <pb xml:id="eng000259-069-b"/>
            <head>ACTVS TERTIVS. Scen. III. </head>
            <stage xml:id="eng000259-e113150">BESSVS, NARBAZANES. </stage>
            <sp who="#eng000259-bessus" xml:id="eng000259-e113160">
              <speaker>Bes. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>NOw since, Narbazanes, we are come hither, </l>
                <l>Let vs accomplish what we haue intended: </l>
                <l>And ioyne our wit, our force, and all together, </l>
                <l>That it may be no sooner knowne then ended. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>You see occasion call vs, whil'st we sleepe, </l>
                <l>And point vs out the way to be aduanc'd; </l>
                <l>Yea blames our sluggishnesse that cannot keepe </l>
                <l>The course of things which for our weale haue chanc'd </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The heauens abhorre our King, &amp; striue t'vndo him: </l>
                <l>Nothing doth prosper that he enterprises: </l>
                <l>Some new disaster daylie falles vnto him: </l>
                <l>Some crosse o'er-thwarts all things that he deuises. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>In no strict limites should our thoughts be bounded </l>
                <l>Whom so great happines seemes to importune: </l>
                <l>For since our King is like to be confounded, </l>
                <l>Vpon his fall we both may builde our fortune. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-nabarzanes" xml:id="eng000259-e113370">
              <speaker>Na. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I shall not faile for to performe my part: </l>
                <l>I of your words exceedingly allow: </l>
                <l>Honour, and wealth are the idols of my hart, </l>
                <l>Which if I may obtaine, I care hot how. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And yet I would we had some faire pretence. </l>
                <l>Our countries care must seeme our soules to comber: </l>
                <l>This seeming zeale must shaddow our offence: </l>
                <l>For such a show will satisfie a number. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Let vs be well aduis'd, ere we resolue: </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-070-a"/>
                <l>And then endeuour t'execute it soone. </l>
                <l>If we our selues once in this worke involue, </l>
                <l>And then not finishe it, we are vndone. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-bessus" xml:id="eng000259-e113530">
              <speaker>Bes. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>He hath sent one to Alexander late </l>
                <l>To speake of peace, but did the same in vaine: </l>
                <l>And now involu'd in a despair'd estate, </l>
                <l>Bar'd from accorde, he cannot warie sustaine. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>His purpose is his Captaines to convene, </l>
                <l>To aske of them some counsell for his saftie: </l>
                <l>A time more fit for vs could not haue beene. </l>
                <l>Who minde to compasse Kings must: needs be crafty. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>For to atchieue that which we thinke to doe, </l>
                <l>A course more fit we by no meanes could finde, </l>
                <l>Then crooked seeming-vpright counsell to </l>
                <l>Disguise our practises, and maske our minde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>We will aduise him to renounce a space </l>
                <l>His state to some one, whom he may desire </l>
                <l>But for the fashion to accept his place, </l>
                <l>And as himselfe a certaine time impyre. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Whose better fortune may perchance bring back </l>
                <l>That which his euer ebbing beares away: </l>
                <l>Then he againe his Diademe shall take, </l>
                <l>And as before the regall scepter sway. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-nabarzanes" xml:id="eng000259-e113790">
              <speaker>Na. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Well then amongst our selues, t'auoid, debate </l>
                <l>Which vndermines so many a mighty action. </l>
                <l>I will preferre you to the imperiall seate. </l>
                <l>And to approoue the same will frame my faction. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-bessus" xml:id="eng000259-e113850">
              <speaker>Bes. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>All that is one, which of vs two receiue it, </l>
                <l>Since euery thing doth equallie belong vs: </l>
                <l>I'le take it for the forme, not that I craue it, </l>
                <l>For we will part his Empire all among vs. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But if he condiscend to this we craue, </l>
                <l>Which at the first vnfolding would seeme good: </l>
                <l>Let him not thinke vs two such fooles to leaue </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-070-b"/>
                <l>That which so many Monarkes buy with blood. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Who once aduanc'd would willingly goe downe, </l>
                <l>And not loue in authoritie to stand? </l>
                <l>'Tis not the custome so to quite a Crowne, </l>
                <l>When one hath know'n how sweet it's to command. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>This name of faith but to get credite fain'd, </l>
                <l>If it were ballanc'd with a kingdome, straight </l>
                <l>In them whose consciences are most restrain'd </l>
                <l>T'would soone succumbe, a scepter hath such waight. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-nabarzanes" xml:id="eng000259-e114060">
              <speaker>Na. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet to betray our King we haue no reason: </l>
                <l>When I muse on th'attempt it makes me sorrie: </l>
                <l>Our name stain'd with this odious stile of treason </l>
                <l>Shall leaue our successours more shame, then glorie. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>We first must end all our designes with paine, </l>
                <l>Then raigne with feare, and liue securelie neuer; </l>
                <l>As in a dreame a space with pompe remaine, </l>
                <l>Then die disgrac'd, infamie for euer. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The sacred title of a Soueraigne King </l>
                <l>Doth strike a terrour in my troubled thought, </l>
                <l>And maiestie, t'amaze my minde, doth bring, </l>
                <l>Whose aspect only hath great wonders wrought. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-bessus" xml:id="eng000259-e114220">
              <speaker>Bes. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>To idle sounds, and frivolous reports </l>
                <l>Giue thou a pasporte, for they last not long: </l>
                <l>And all that thou alledgest nought imports. </l>
                <l>A Crowne may couer any kinde of wrong. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>What hainous thing so odious is by nature, </l>
                <l>That for a Kingdome hath not beene committed: </l>
                <l>To be a King let me be cal'd a traitour; </l>
                <l>Faith, if for ought, for this may be omitted. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Those are but feeble braines, which fancies lode </l>
                <l>With timorous dreames, that bare surmising brings. </l>
                <l>Who feare vaine shaddowes must not come abrode. </l>
                <l>Too warie-wits dare neuer worke great things. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>If our braue proiect happilie succeede, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-071-a"/>
                <l>(As now I doubt not but it shall do soone) </l>
                <l>We straight will finde enough t'applaud our deede, </l>
                <l>And sooth vs vp in all that we haue done. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-nabarzanes" xml:id="eng000259-e114430">
              <speaker>Na. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>To haue the time and manner then praefixt, </l>
                <l>Command the Bactrians all themselues to arme, </l>
                <l>And to attend till we aduertise next, </l>
                <l>Prompt for all perils at the first alarme. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then through the Campe a rumour we will spread, </l>
                <l>That hopelesse Darius hath dispairdlie gone </l>
                <l>With violence to dwell amongst the dead, </l>
                <l>And seeme therefore excessiuelie to mone. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The Persians we with promises must feede, </l>
                <l>So to disarme him of his natiue pow'rs: </l>
                <l>Then we will apprehend himselfe with speede: </l>
                <l>For while that he is free nothing is ours. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>That we may seeme to vse him with respect, </l>
                <l>(As to the state of such a Prince pertaines:) </l>
                <l>We will not this last ornament neglect; </l>
                <l>He shall be bound, but bound with golden chaines. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>To Alexander after we will send, </l>
                <l>And offer Darius in his hands t'appease him; </l>
                <l>Then craue his fauour, that he will defend </l>
                <l>Vs as his friends, who haue done all to please him; </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>If his good-will we cannot thus procure, </l>
                <l>And he vs with extremitie pursue; </l>
                <l>With Darius death we will our states assure, </l>
                <l>Then raise fresh forces, and the warres renue. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-bessus" xml:id="eng000259-e114740">
              <speaker>Bos. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Let vs henceforth for nothing be dismaide, </l>
                <l>But striue our selues courageouslie to beare: </l>
                <l>This dangerous action would not be delai'd, </l>
                <l>Least time worke his assurance, and our feare. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="eng000259-e114800">Exeunt. </stage>
            <div type="chorus" xml:id="eng000259-e114810">
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-071-b"/>
              <head>CHORVS. </head>
              <lg>
                <l>TYme, through Ioues iudgement iust, </l>
                <l>Huge alterations brings: </l>
                <l>Those are but fooles that trust </l>
                <l>In transitory things, </l>
                <l>Whose tailes beare mortall stings, </l>
                <l>Which in the end will wound. </l>
                <l>And let none thinke it strange, </l>
                <l>Though all things earthly change </l>
                <l>In this inferiour rounde. </l>
                <l>What is from ruine free? </l>
                <l>The elements which be </l>
                <l>At variance (as we see) </l>
                <l>Eache other doe confound: </l>
                <l>The earth and aire make warre: </l>
                <l>The fire and water are </l>
                <l>Still wrestling at debate: </l>
                <l>All those through colde and heate, </l>
                <l>Through drouth, and moisture iar: </l>
                <l>No wonder though men change and fade, </l>
                <l>Who of those changing elements are made. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>How dare vaine worldlings vaunt </l>
                <l>Of fortunes goods not lasting, </l>
                <l>Euils that our wittes enchaunt, </l>
                <l>Expos'd to losse and wasting. </l>
                <l>Loe we to death are hasting, </l>
                <l>Whilst we these things discusse. </l>
                <l>All things from their beginning, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-072-a"/>
                <l>Vnto an end are running: </l>
                <l>Heauen hath ordain'd it thus. </l>
                <l>We heare how heauen doth thunder; </l>
                <l>We see th'earth burst asunder; </l>
                <l>And yet we neuer ponder, </l>
                <l>What this imports to vs. </l>
                <l>Those fearfull signes doe proue, </l>
                <l>That th'angrie pow'rs aboue </l>
                <l>Are mou'd to indignation </l>
                <l>Against this wretched nation, </l>
                <l>Which they no longer loue: </l>
                <l>What are we but a puffe of breath, </l>
                <l>Who liue assur'd of nothing but of death? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Who was so happie yet, </l>
                <l>As neuer had some crosse: </l>
                <l>Though on a Throne he sit, </l>
                <l>And is not vs'd with losse, </l>
                <l>Yet fortune once will tosse </l>
                <l>Him, when that least he would. </l>
                <l>If one had all at ones </l>
                <l>Hydaspes pretious stones, </l>
                <l>And yellow Tagus golde, </l>
                <l>All th'Orient all treasure, </l>
                <l>And euery earthly pleasure, </l>
                <l>Euen in the greatest measure, </l>
                <l>It should not make him bold. </l>
                <l>For while he liues secure, </l>
                <l>His state is most vnsure. </l>
                <l>When it doth least appeere, </l>
                <l>Some heauie plague drawes neere, </l>
                <l>Destruction to procure. </l>
                <l>We may compare th'earths glory to a flowre, </l>
                <l>That flourisheth and fadeth in an houre. </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-072-b"/>
                <l>In what we most repose </l>
                <l>We finde our comfort light: </l>
                <l>The thing we soonest lose </l>
                <l>That's precious in our sight. </l>
                <l>For honour, riches, might </l>
                <l>Our liues impaund we lay: </l>
                <l>Yet all like flying shadowes, </l>
                <l>Or flowers enambling medowes, </l>
                <l>Evanish and decay. </l>
                <l>Long time we toile to finde </l>
                <l>Those idols of the minde, </l>
                <l>Which got we cannot binde </l>
                <l>T'abide with vs one day. </l>
                <l>Then why should we presume </l>
                <l>On treasures that consume, </l>
                <l>Difficile to obtaine, </l>
                <l>Difficile to retaine, </l>
                <l>A dreame, a breath, a fume; </l>
                <l>Which vexe them most who them possesse, </l>
                <l>Who starue with store, and famish with excesse. </l>
              </lg>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="eng000259-e115650">
          <head>ACTVS QVARTVS. </head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="eng000259-e115660">
            <head>Scen. I. </head>
            <stage xml:id="eng000259-e115670">DARIVS, TIRIOTES. </stage>
            <sp who="#eng000259-tiriotes" xml:id="eng000259-e115680">
              <speaker>Tir. </speaker>
              <l>AH, must I poyson now my Princes eares </l>
              <l>with the worst newes that euer burthē'd fame? </l>
              <l>Had I as many tongues, as I haue teares, </l>
              <l>All would not serue my sorrowes to proclame. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-darius" xml:id="eng000259-e115730">
              <speaker>Dar. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Great signes of greefe I in thy face discerne: </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-073-a"/>
                <l>Spare not for to report this heauie crosse </l>
                <l>To one, I feare, whome it doth most concerne. </l>
                <l>Ist death, disgrace, distruction, treason, losse? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Tell on the summe of honour at the first: </l>
                <l>With no ambiguous words my paine prolong: </l>
                <l>'Tis comfort to a wretch to know the worst: </l>
                <l>And I haue learn'd to be vnhappy long. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>What least I speake, and yet suspect too much, </l>
                <l>Ist some ludibrious message of my skorne, </l>
                <l>Which must wound me? but ah no torment such, </l>
                <l>As this to them who that disgrace haue borne. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-tiriotes" xml:id="eng000259-e115890">
              <speaker>Tir. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>She was not wrong'd, as you haue misconceiu'd. </l>
                <l>The Gods haue had a care for to preserue her: </l>
                <l>Such fauour of the victour she receiu'd, </l>
                <l>As of her subiects that were bound to serue her. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But what a vollie doth my voice prepare </l>
                <l>Of woes to charge your eares, woes full of dread? </l>
                <l>Would God ere I the somme thereof declare, </l>
                <l>That I might die in saying she is dead. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Curst caitiue, was it not enough, allas, </l>
                <l>That I beheld her die, and would haue died, </l>
                <l>But that I must arm'd with sad tydings pas </l>
                <l>To wound all them that heare what I haue spied? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>See how he fares shot with these words of mine, </l>
                <l>As one become the pray of greefe, and death. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-darius" xml:id="eng000259-e116080">
              <speaker>Dar. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet doth the Sunne on my affliction shine, </l>
                <l>And sees the aire infected with my breath. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And can I liue, and looke them in the face, </l>
                <l>That haue my ignominious o're-throw seene? </l>
                <l>And how I vanquish'd, vanquish'd with disgrace </l>
                <l>Engag'd at once my kingdome, and my Queene? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Heauen bruse me all to powder with thy thunder, </l>
                <l>That I no more may in the world remaine </l>
                <l>The obiect of thy wrath, and Fortunes wonder; </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-073-b"/>
                <l>Spoil'd of all hope; yet kept for greater paine. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Ah! art thou dead, and doe I lieu behinde thee? </l>
                <l>Thy faultie husband thinkst thou so to flie? </l>
                <l>If it be thus, then I know where to finde thee. </l>
                <l>This onely greeues me that too late I die. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>O Alexander, what such hainous ill </l>
                <l>Haue I done thee, that thou requit'st me thus? </l>
                <l>Whom of thy friendes, or kindred did I kill? </l>
                <l>This crueltie comes vndeseru'd of vs. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Think that thou hadst iust causes to make warre: </l>
                <l>Yet vpon women should thy wrath be wroken? </l>
                <l>This Tirrannie shall all thy Triumphe marre, </l>
                <l>And euer shall to thy reproach be spoken. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-tiriotes" xml:id="eng000259-e116370">
              <speaker>Tir. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Sir, without cause you guiltie him esteeme. </l>
                <l>I know her death did grieuouslie displease him: </l>
                <l>A wondrous thing (which few, or none would deeme) </l>
                <l>He tooke it so, that nothing could appease him. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Euen as my Soueraigne now, so then he smarted; </l>
                <l>And when he came to ease your mothers griefe, </l>
                <l>As if that his owne mother had departed; </l>
                <l>He seem'd to need, not for to giue reliefe. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-darius" xml:id="eng000259-e116480">
              <speaker>Dar. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>If any sparkes of that respect remaine, </l>
                <l>Which should with reason mooue thy minde to ruth, </l>
                <l>I pray the Tiriotes now be plaine, </l>
                <l>Or els strange torments shall exact the truth: </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I loth to let this question scape my mouth, </l>
                <l>Which both I blush to craue, and long to know, </l>
                <l>Ist possible so insolent a youth </l>
                <l>Did neuer tempt the treasure which I owe? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Could this imperious Prince in flowre of age </l>
                <l>Haue such a peerelesse beautie in his power, </l>
                <l>And yet not seeke to quench his ardent rage </l>
                <l>With the destruction of her honours flowre? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Spare not to tell vpon what deadly shelfe </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-074-a"/>
                <l>My ioy is perish'd quite, and I defac'd. </l>
                <l>The feare of euill is worse then th'euill it selfe: </l>
                <l>i'ts to die twise, to die, and die disgrac'd. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-tiriotes" xml:id="eng000259-e116690">
              <speaker>Ti. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Let not those loue-bred feares abuse your thought: </l>
                <l>By all the world no fable I contriue. </l>
                <l>If I speake partiallie, or lie in ought, </l>
                <l>Earth open vp, and swallow me aliue. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>He whom your Grace so wrongfully suspects, </l>
                <l>No, not in thought, hath once your Queene abus'd, </l>
                <l>But as his sister still in all respects, </l>
                <l>As chastlie, and as honourablie vs'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>When fortune first our warlike troupes had scattered, </l>
                <l>And with great slaughter put them all to flight; </l>
                <l>We, whom she late so louingly had flattered, </l>
                <l>Were made the patternes of that changlings might. </l>
                <l>For hauing found a Crowne troad on the ground. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-darius" xml:id="eng000259-e116860">
              <speaker>Dar. </speaker>
              <p>O lasting shame that cannot be recur'd. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-tiriotes" xml:id="eng000259-e116880">
              <speaker>Tir. </speaker>
              <l>We straight imagin'd that some cruell wound </l>
              <l>Had kild my Lord, and wail'd it as assur'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-darius" xml:id="eng000259-e116910">
              <speaker>Dar. </speaker>
              <l>Would God I then had died, as I desir'd, </l>
              <l>So t'haue preuented those ensuing harmes; </l>
              <l>Before my honour and my hap expir'd, </l>
              <l>With Crowne on head, &amp; with my Queene in armes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-tiriotes" xml:id="eng000259-e116960">
              <speaker>Tir. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>But Alexander hauing heard our cries </l>
                <l>Sent one t'enquire th'occasion of our woe; </l>
                <l>Who finding whence our errour did arise, </l>
                <l>Gaue full assurance that it was not so. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then he himselfe vnto our tent resorted, </l>
                <l>And with most courteous speaches full of loue </l>
                <l>Your mother, wife, and children oft exhorted </l>
                <l>Such vaine surmized terrours to remoue. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>With protestation that they should expect </l>
                <l>No harme of him their courage to appale: </l>
                <l>Each thing he did accordinglie direct, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-074-b"/>
                <l>That no man might endomage them at all. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Thus hauing them against all dangers arm'd </l>
                <l>(I thinke for feare, for who would not haue fear'd </l>
                <l>Least such an Angels graces had him charm'd) </l>
                <l>He neuer more before her face appear'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Or was it vertue that would flie the sting </l>
                <l>Of trustlesse pleasures that abuse the sense? </l>
                <l>So continent a victour, and a king </l>
                <l>Was neuer seene. He fled what caus'd offence. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>He doth his fame aboue all things prefer, </l>
                <l>And will not be where it may blemish finde, </l>
                <l>Nor giue his eyes commoditie to erre, </l>
                <l>Nor suffer impure thoughts to staine his minde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>He stai'd till that faire face had lost all vigour, </l>
                <l>And with the coulours of pale death was painted. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-darius" xml:id="eng000259-e117300">
              <speaker>Dar. </speaker>
              <l>Iniurious heauen that with such hellish rigour </l>
              <l>The purest worke that nature made hath tainted. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-tiriotes" xml:id="eng000259-e117330">
              <speaker>Tir. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>When he beheld death triumph in that face, </l>
                <l>Which late had triumph'd ou'r a Monarcks hart, </l>
                <l>He mon'd no lesse her miserable cace, </l>
                <l>Then you that loste in her your better part. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And when some dayes his dolour had ou'r-come, </l>
                <l>Her funerals solemnelie to decore </l>
                <l>He vs'd such honour, as might well become </l>
                <l>The Persian pompe in prosperous times before. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-darius" xml:id="eng000259-e117440">
              <speaker>Dar. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>O supreame pow'r that of Empires disposest, </l>
                <l>And ratifiest thy will with fearfull thunder, </l>
                <l>Who, as thou pleasest, placest, and de-posest </l>
                <l>Vncertaine worldlings whiles aboue, whiles vnder, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I pray thy Deitie in my soules distresse, </l>
                <l>If that th'inhabitants of heauen can heare </l>
                <l>The plaints of those who this lowe point possesse, </l>
                <l>Or that th'immortall can giue mortals eare, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Vouchsafe this my last sute for to fulfill: </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-075-a"/>
                <l>Establish first this scepter in my hand: </l>
                <l>But if through my deserving, or thy will </l>
                <l>The race of Cyrus must no more command; </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And if thy heauenly breast such hate contracts, </l>
                <l>That I must needs my Diadem forgoe: </l>
                <l>Let him succeed who prooues in all his acts </l>
                <l>So iust a Victour, and so milde a foe. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="eng000259-e117650">
            <head>ACTVS QVARTVS. Scen. II. </head>
            <stage xml:id="eng000259-e117660">DARIVS, ART ABAZVS, NARBAZENES PATRON, BESSVS. </stage>
            <sp who="#eng000259-darius" xml:id="eng000259-e117670">
              <speaker>Dar. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>IF Fortune had ioynd me with dastard mindes, </l>
                <l>Who to a noble death base life prefer'd, </l>
                <l>I should not harrengue heere vnto the windes, </l>
                <l>But be content to haue my fate defer'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>O, I repent I proou'd your worth too much, </l>
                <l>Who still haue follow'd me in all estates. </l>
                <l>I rather should, then doubt that you are such, </l>
                <l>Prease to proue worthy of so worthie mates. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yee onlie rest of all that I conducted, </l>
                <l>Of whose great force and faith, which many sing, </l>
                <l>I by two fights, and flights haue beene instructed: </l>
                <l>Yet hauing you I thinke my selfe a King. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>He hath plac'd traitours in my townes most ample, </l>
                <l>Not that he honours them (he hates their humour) </l>
                <l>But to seduce you to by their example, </l>
                <l>Then bannish all for euery little rumour. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yee haue not to my Fortune had regarde, </l>
                <l>But freelie-follow'd my euill fortun'd warres: </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-075-b"/>
                <l>Which, though that I might not, Ioue would rewarde, </l>
                <l>And all the world extoll you to the starres. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>How long shall I a vagabond remaine, </l>
                <l>And flie a stranger who my right would reaue? </l>
                <l>Since by one battell we may re-obtaine </l>
                <l>All that we lost, or loose all that we haue. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Like those vile traitours, whom I will arraigne </l>
                <l>To holde me vp, shall I goe cast me downe? </l>
                <l>Must Darius onlie by entreatie raigne? </l>
                <l>No, none hath pow'r to take, or giue my Crowne. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I shall not my authoritie sur-viue, </l>
                <l>Nor will I proffer a submissiue breath: </l>
                <l>My hand shall holde a scepter while I liue: </l>
                <l>My head shall beare a Diadem till death. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>If those franke thoughts that doe possesse my soule, </l>
                <l>Such flames of vertue kindled haue in you; </l>
                <l>A Macedonian neuer shall controule </l>
                <l>Our noble actes, nor laugh to see vs bow. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>My state may testifie fraile Fortunes change: </l>
                <l>May she not him o're-whelme, as well as me? </l>
                <l>At least our hands beare death, if not revenge: </l>
                <l>For who can stop a stout hart for to die? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Thinke of your auncestors, I you exhort, </l>
                <l>Who made the Grecians tributaries euer; </l>
                <l>And of whose wondrous actes men do report </l>
                <l>Great things, the fame whereof shall perish neuer. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Shall future ages in your praise be dombe, </l>
                <l>Whil'st they your Fathers memorie adore? </l>
                <l>I am resolu'd, my Triumphe, or my Tombe </l>
                <l>A Laurell, or a Cipresse shall decore. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-artabazus" xml:id="eng000259-e118280">
              <speaker>Art. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What vaine amazement doth disturbe our spirits? </l>
                <l>Let vs consult no further but goe to. </l>
                <l>He, who the Persians wonted worth inherites, </l>
                <l>Will not rest long aduising what to doe? </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-076-a"/>
              <lg>
                <l>Come let vs with our best attire and armes </l>
                <l>Accompanie our King to this last strife: </l>
                <l>Through bloody squadrons, and through hote alarmes </l>
                <l>By slaughter onlie we must looke for life. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And when our host, as I hope shall preuaile, </l>
                <l>Our countrie shall haue peace, we praise of right: </l>
                <l>And if our Fortune, not our courage, faile, </l>
                <l>We die with honour in our Soueraignes sight. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Let vs, if vanquish'd, be asham'd to be. </l>
                <l>A glorious death may greater honour giue. </l>
                <l>Doe to o're-come, and yet not feare to die. </l>
                <l>It's needfull that we fight, not that we liue, </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-nabarzanes" xml:id="eng000259-e118490">
              <speaker>Na. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>My words will first your Maiestie displease: </l>
                <l>Yet dutie makes me speake where silence spilles: </l>
                <l>The fine Phisician cures a sharpe disease </l>
                <l>With some sowre potion that corruption killes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The skilfull Pilote when he feares a storme, </l>
                <l>To saue the ship will cast out precious things: </l>
                <l>Yet I perswade you not in any forme </l>
                <l>To further, but to stay what ruine brings. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>We warre against the Gods, we cannot speede: </l>
                <l>To all our actions Fortune is oppos'd. </l>
                <l>We must of force some other way proceede: </l>
                <l>So haue the heau'ns of our affaires dispos'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Deare Sir, giue ou'r the gouernment and stile </l>
                <l>To some more happie man, not in effect? </l>
                <l>But cloth him with your shaddow for a while, </l>
                <l>Till he your Realmes halfe ruin'd re-erect. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>When he hath clam'd this tempest now so hote, </l>
                <l>And setled Asia with a good successe? </l>
                <l>He will your kingdomes lost with what he gote </l>
                <l>Restore: appearance promises no lesse. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>All Bactria yet abides at your command: </l>
                <l>The Indians, loe, would die to doe you good: </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-076-b"/>
                <l>Yea many thousand thousands armed stand, </l>
                <l>Bent for your pleasure to bestow their blood. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>What? should we rush like beastes to needlesse strife? </l>
                <l>Be well prepar'd, and then pursue that stranger: </l>
                <l>Braue mindes should death despise not lothing life. </l>
                <l>Base cowards craue to die for feare of danger. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But vertue, to haue no support ou'r past, </l>
                <l>Will first on all meanes possible be thinking: </l>
                <l>And when that all is proou'd, death is the last, </l>
                <l>To which it is ynough to goe not shrinking. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Now for the time let Bactria be our seat, </l>
                <l>To Bessus for the forme your Crowne resigne: </l>
                <l>Who, when he once hath re-aduanc'd you state, </l>
                <l>Shall quite all soueraigntie at the first signe. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-darius" xml:id="eng000259-e118950">
              <speaker>Dar. </speaker>
              <l>Wretch, trauellest thou thy soueraigne to betray? </l>
              <l>Such treason darest thou to our eares impart? </l>
              <l>Such treason vnder trust? Stay traitour, stay: </l>
              <l>Ile sheath my sworde euen in thy traiterous hart. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-artabazus" xml:id="eng000259-e119000">
              <speaker>Art. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Sir, you must striue to haue this passion broken. </l>
                <l>Consider what they are, what is the time: </l>
                <l>It may be they through ignorance haue spoken: </l>
                <l>In thought, and not in word, consists a crime. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Since to affront your enimie you goe, </l>
                <l>You must not stirre for euery little obiect: </l>
                <l>But tollerate your owne, t'offend your foe. </l>
                <l>For now i'ts time time to loue not lose a subiect. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I shall get triall vpon what pretence </l>
                <l>This ou'r-sight in aduise hath beene committed. </l>
                <l>If through simplicitie, not for offence, </l>
                <l>He must be pardon'd and his speech remitted. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-darius" xml:id="eng000259-e119160">
              <speaker>Dar. </speaker>
              <l>I wish that it were so. I take no pleasure </l>
              <l>To ruine them that would my fortune cherish. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-nabarzanes" xml:id="eng000259-e119190">
              <speaker>Na. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Your grace wil grant me mercie in some measure. </l>
                <l>First heare, and if I faile then let me perish. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-077-a"/>
              <lg>
                <l>I call the Gods to witnesse of my cace, </l>
                <l>Who can decipher euery secret thought: </l>
                <l>If I intended treason toward your Grace, </l>
                <l>Straight where I stand let me be turn'd to nought. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I counsel'd but according to my skill: </l>
                <l>It was my vpright minde that made me bolde. </l>
                <l>I rue my wit not answer'd to my will: </l>
                <l>Yet zeale what it conceiues must needes vnfolde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>We should beware to speake in great affaires, </l>
                <l>Where words are damn'd, or ballanc'd by th'euent. </l>
                <l>For if things faile, the fault is still thought theirs </l>
                <l>Who gaue th'aduise, though of a good intent. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I fall before your feete heere for refuge: </l>
                <l>Then let me not be without cause reiected: </l>
                <l>At least, examine first before you iudge: </l>
                <l>Ile rather die absolu'd, then liue suspected. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-darius" xml:id="eng000259-e119430">
              <speaker>Dar. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Your fond opinion first was to be feared, </l>
                <l>Which seem'd indeede sinistriouslie inclind: </l>
                <l>For at the first your speech to me appear'd </l>
                <l>Th'envenom'd birth of some malitious minde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But since you purge you so, Ile not arraign you, </l>
                <l>Not further call your loyalty in doubt: </l>
                <l>But in the same degree of grace retaine you, </l>
                <l>That you were in before these wordes brake out. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I thinke that Patron lookes with speaking eies, </l>
                <l>As if his minde were mightily perplexed: </l>
                <l>Come, Patron, tell what in thy bosome lies, </l>
                <l>Wherewith thou seemest so wonderfullie vexed. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-parmenio" xml:id="eng000259-e119590">
              <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Sir, I would speake in priuie, If I could, </l>
                <l>That which th'affection of my soule affordes: </l>
                <l>It must be seal'd with silence, and I would </l>
                <l>That none were present to report my words. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Of fifty thousand Greekes foure only rest, </l>
                <l>Companions in all perils with your host: </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-077-b"/>
                <l>Alike with you delighted and distrest: </l>
                <l>As faithfull now as when you florish'd most. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Where you remaine we must remaine with you: </l>
                <l>All kinde of fortunes haue vs ioyn'd together. </l>
                <l>Appoint our tents for your Pauilion now; </l>
                <l>And we will guard you, if that you come thither. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>We haue abandon'd Greece, our natiue soile: </l>
                <l>We haue no Bactria to be our retreat: </l>
                <l>Our hope is all in you: those that would spoile </l>
                <l>Vs of your person ruine all our state. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Would God that all your armie did their due: </l>
                <l>To vse moe words th'occasion is not fit. </l>
                <l>I should not vrge you, if your owne were true, </l>
                <l>Your custodie to strangers to commit. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-darius" xml:id="eng000259-e119850">
              <speaker>Dar. </speaker>
              <l>What suddaine accident doth this dismay you </l>
              <l>That you such inconveniences forecast? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-parmenio" xml:id="eng000259-e119880">
              <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Sir, Bessus and Narbazanes betray you! </l>
                <l>This day to you, or them will be the last. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>They faine repentance onlie to dissemble, </l>
                <l>Till euery thing be for the fact prepar'd. </l>
                <l>Their friends in hast doe all their force assemble, </l>
                <l>And once ere night minde to inuade your guarde. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-darius" xml:id="eng000259-e119970">
              <speaker>Dar. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I credite you: but yet I cannot wrong </l>
                <l>My subiects so, to thinke of them the worst: </l>
                <l>Shall I leaue them who follow'd me so long? </l>
                <l>By doing so to make my selfe accurst. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I will awaite on what the heau'ns will offer, </l>
                <l>For who can stand when fates his fall conspire? </l>
                <l>Among mine owne I willingly will suffer. </l>
                <l>I liue too long if they my death desire. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-bessus" xml:id="eng000259-e120080">
              <speaker>Bes. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Take heede, Sir, to this subtile-witted Greeke: </l>
                <l>The Graecian faith to all the world is knowne. </l>
                <l>I am enform'd he by all meanes doth seeke </l>
                <l>To win his grace who hath your state o're-throwne. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-078-a"/>
              <lg>
                <l>And maruell not though mercenarie men, </l>
                <l>Who sell themselues, sell all: beleeue them neuer. </l>
                <l>They haue no God but gold, nor house: how then </l>
                <l>Can they be constant that are changing euer? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Although that he pre-occupie you thus, </l>
                <l>And others who themselues abuse your Grace: </l>
                <l>Faith shall be found inuiolate in vs, </l>
                <l>When our accuser dare not show his face. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-darius" xml:id="eng000259-e120240">
              <speaker>Dar. </speaker>
              <l>Who hope to haue of Alexander gaine, </l>
              <l>Or honour to be false, they haue no reason: </l>
              <l>No man on earth doth traitours more disdaine, </l>
              <l>Nor more seuearly will b'aueng'd on treason. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-bessus" xml:id="eng000259-e120290">
              <speaker>Bes. </speaker>
              <l>Well, Sir, you shall see shortlie what we are: </l>
              <l>I will goe see your Ensignes all displaied. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-darius" xml:id="eng000259-e120320">
              <speaker>Dar. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>It's better now since things are gone so farre, </l>
                <l>Then seeme for to mistrust, to be betraide. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Loe Artabazus, I haue acted heere </l>
                <l>My part of greatnesse, and my glasse is run. </l>
                <l>Now Patrons speech doth euident appeare. </l>
                <l>I see my end, yet can it no way shun. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-artabazus" xml:id="eng000259-e120410">
              <speaker>Art. </speaker>
              <l>The Bactrians only medled haue with this. </l>
              <l>Go to the Graecians campe, when that is done. </l>
              <l>And when your danger once divulged is, </l>
              <l>The Persians all will follow after soone. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-darius" xml:id="eng000259-e120460">
              <speaker>Dar. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And what if I were gone to patrons Tent, </l>
                <l>And guarded with the Greekes as you desire: </l>
                <l>He hath but thousands foure that are well bent; </l>
                <l>They thirty thousand that my fall conspire. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And doing this I should their deede excuse, </l>
                <l>In giuing them a motion who haue might. </l>
                <l>They may indeede my lenitie abuse: </l>
                <l>But by my deede they shall pretend no right. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-artabazus" xml:id="eng000259-e120570">
              <speaker>Art. </speaker>
              <l>O deplorable Prince, who can but weepe </l>
              <l>To see thee now reduc'd to this estate? </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="eng000259-078-b"/>
            <sp who="#eng000259-darius" xml:id="eng000259-e120600">
              <speaker>Dar. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Retire you all, and seeke your selues to keepe: </l>
                <l>I heere attend the issue of my fate. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I knowe yee wonder all how I can stand, </l>
                <l>Downe from the top of all contentment throwne, </l>
                <l>And not die desperately by mine owne hand. </l>
                <l>Ile die through others guilt, not through mine owne. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>None of you all haue falsified your troath, </l>
                <l>But with me loyall still to th'end yee abide. </l>
                <l>Now I you all disburthen of your oath: </l>
                <l>Leaue me alone, and for your selues prouide. <stage xml:id="eng000259-e120740">Exeunt. </stage>
                </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-darius" xml:id="eng000259-e120750">
              <speaker>DARIVS. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>O Wretched Monarchie, vaine mortals choice, </l>
                <l>The glorious step to a disgrace-full fall: </l>
                <l>Our pow'r depends vpon the peoples voice, </l>
                <l>And to seeme soueraigne needs we must serue all. </l>
                <l>Yet blowne, like blathers, with ambitions winde, </l>
                <l>On enuied scepters weaklie we relie: </l>
                <l>And calling not our fraile estate to minde, </l>
                <l>Not onlie earth, but heauens themselues defie. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>This hellish hag our restlesse minde doth tosse, </l>
                <l>While carried with a popular applause, </l>
                <l>T'enlarge our limites with our neighbours losse, </l>
                <l>We of our owne confusions are the cause. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And when th'ecclipse comes of our glories light, </l>
                <l>Then what auailes th'adoring of our name: </l>
                <l>A meere illusion made to mock the sight, </l>
                <l>Whose best was but the shaddow of a dreame? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Let greatnesse of her glascie scepters vaunt; </l>
                <l>Not sceptours, no, but reeds, soone brus'd soone broken: </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-079-a"/>
                <l>And let this worldlie pompe our wits inchant. </l>
                <l>All fades, and scarcelie leaues behinde a token. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Those golden Pallaces, those gorgeous halles, </l>
                <l>With fourniture superfluouslie faire: </l>
                <l>Those statelie Courts, those sky-encountring walles </l>
                <l>Evanish all like vapours in the aire. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>O what affliction iealous greatnesse beares, </l>
                <l>That still must trauell to hold others downe; </l>
                <l>Whil'st all our guardes not guard vs from our feares? </l>
                <l>So greevous is the burthen of a Crowne. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Where are they all who at my feete did bowe, </l>
                <l>While I was made the idole of so many? </l>
                <l>What ioy had I not then? what haue I nowe? </l>
                <l>Then honoured of all, now scarce of any. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Our painted pleasures but apparrell paine: </l>
                <l>We spend our dayes in dread, our liues in dangers, </l>
                <l>Balles to the starres, and thralles to Fortunes raigne, </l>
                <l>Knowne vnto all, yet to our selues but strangers. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>A golden Crowne doth couer leaden cares: </l>
                <l>The Scepter cannot lulle their thoughts a-sleepe, </l>
                <l>Whose breasts are fraught with infinite dispaires, </l>
                <l>Of which the vulgar wits sounds not the deepe. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The Bramble growes, although it be obscure; </l>
                <l>While mightie Cedars feele the blustering windes: </l>
                <l>And milde Plebeian spirits may lieu secure, </l>
                <l>While mightie tempests tosse imperiall mindes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>What are our daies, but dreames, our raignes but trances, </l>
                <l>Whil'st brain-sick reaving with our Fortunes feuer. </l>
                <l>We still are vext with changes and mischances, </l>
                <l>Till death vs both from life and scepter seuer? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The vanitie of greatnesse I haue proou'd, </l>
                <l>And beene the wonder of each gazing eye: </l>
                <l>Now that deceauing shaddow is remoou'd; </l>
                <l>And I my wretched state too late espie. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-079-b"/>
              <lg>
                <l>Now bound with chaines, (which though they be of gold, </l>
                <l>Diminish not my thraldome ought the more) </l>
                <l>When this preposterous honour I beholde, </l>
                <l>It but vpbraides me what I was before. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And what was I before (though to each eye </l>
                <l>The forme of my affliction was not knowne) </l>
                <l>But fettred in effect, while I seem'd free, </l>
                <l>And in a labyrinth of labours throwne? </l>
                <l>Was I not bound to serue then all mens humour, </l>
                <l>Or to be censur'd with some Critick storie; </l>
                <l>Still clog'd with cares, as slought for euery rumour. </l>
                <l>O glorious bondage, burthen-able glorie. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>That dignitie which deified me late, </l>
                <l>And made the world doe homage to my name, </l>
                <l>Now cannot succour my accursed state, </l>
                <l>But hath with my mis-fortune fethered same. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>My best was but a momentarie blis, </l>
                <l>Which leaues behinde this euerlasting sting, </l>
                <l>That of all woe no woe is like to this, </l>
                <l>To thinke I was, and am not now a King. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>No man with me in all accomplish'd ioyes, </l>
                <l>That satisfie the soule, could once compare: </l>
                <l>No man may matche me now in sad annoyes, </l>
                <l>And all the miseries that breede dispaire. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Thrise Fortune did my gallant troupes entrap, </l>
                <l>And I to fall did desperately stand; </l>
                <l>Yet could not be so happie in mishap, </l>
                <l>As for t'haue died by some renowmed hand. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But for my greater griefe, disgrace, and scorne, </l>
                <l>(The mindes of men so apt are to deceaue) </l>
                <l>They whome aloft my favours wings haue borne, </l>
                <l>Ev'n they made me their maister thus a slaue. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Ah, did not death in prison from me reaue </l>
                <l>The sacred soueraigne of my soules desires, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-080-a"/>
                <l>I wretch not being present to receaue </l>
                <l>The last cold kisse that might asswage my fires? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet ô thrise happie thou, that hast not liu'd </l>
                <l>To beare a burthen of this great disgrace. </l>
                <l>More then a thousand deaths this had thee grieu'd, </l>
                <l>To know I died, and died in such a cace. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Ah, doe the pledges of our mutuall loue </l>
                <l>(The onlie comfort that the fates haue left me) </l>
                <l>Rest prison'd yet? And may I not remooue </l>
                <l>My mother thence? then is all blisse bereft me. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>My paines are more then with my pleasures ev'n, </l>
                <l>Since first I in authoritie did enter. </l>
                <l>Was I exalted once vp to the heau'n, </l>
                <l>To be cast head-long downe to mischiefes center? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>My ample Empire, and my Princelie birth, </l>
                <l>My great magnificence, and vaine excesse, </l>
                <l>All cannot yeelde my minde one minutes mirth, </l>
                <l>To ease me now in this extreame distresse. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Loe heere, reduc'd vnto the worst of illes, </l>
                <l>Past helpe, past hope, and only great in griefe, </l>
                <l>I wait vpon two abiect vassals willes, </l>
                <l>And dare not, no, not thinke vpon reliefe. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Death would I scorne (my course must once haue run) </l>
                <l>If I had first repair'd mine honours breach, </l>
                <l>Whose wounds so thrill my soule, as vnbegun </l>
                <l>The life I wish that does my fame impeach. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>This mortall vaile I willinglie resigne, </l>
                <l>Since to an ende my dayes the destinies bring: </l>
                <l>Nor will I so from Maiestie decline, </l>
                <l>As to doe ought vn-worthie of a King. <stage xml:id="eng000259-e122190">Exit. </stage>
                </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <div type="chorus" xml:id="eng000259-e122200">
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-080-b"/>
              <head>CHORVS. </head>
              <lg>
                <l>SOme new disaster day lie doth for showe </l>
                <l>Our comming ruine: We haue seene our best. </l>
                <l>Now fortune bent vs vtterly t'ore-throw, </l>
                <l>Throwes down our King from her wheels top so low, </l>
                <l>As by no meanes his state can be redrest. </l>
                <l>And since his foes by armes haue him opprest, </l>
                <l>His friendes, and seruants leaue him all alone. </l>
                <l>Few haue compassion of his state distrest: </l>
                <l>Yea, false to him them selues doe many show. </l>
                <l>So foes and feigned friendes conspire in one; </l>
                <l>Fraile Fortune, and the fates with them agree. </l>
                <l>With axes all runne on this falling tree. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>This Prince in prosperous state hath florish'd long, </l>
                <l>And neuer dream'd of any euill successe, </l>
                <l>But was well follow'd while his state was strong: </l>
                <l>Him flattering Syrens with a charming song </l>
                <l>Striu'd to exalt: while-as he did possesse </l>
                <l>This earthly drosse, that with a vaine excesse </l>
                <l>He might reward their mercenary loue. </l>
                <l>But now when fortune driues him to distresse, </l>
                <l>His fauorites whom he remain'd among, </l>
                <l>With foes and fortune straight their faith remoue. </l>
                <l>And who for gaine to follow him were wont, </l>
                <l>They after gaine by his destruction hunt. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>O more then happie ten times were that King, </l>
                <l>Who were vnhappie but a little space, </l>
                <l>So that it did no vtter ruine bring, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-081-a"/>
                <l>But made him proue (a profitable thing) </l>
                <l>Who of his traine, did best deserue his grace; </l>
                <l>Then could, and would of those the best imbrace, </l>
                <l>And flie such vultures as deuour him liuing; </l>
                <l>That these whom he found faithful might have place. </l>
                <l>O how this doth a generous stomacke sting, </l>
                <l>To see some grac'd for craft and lies contryuing? </l>
                <l>This is the griefe that bursts an honest hart; </l>
                <l>Lords fauour commes by chance, not by desart. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Those Minions to whom Princes do extend, </l>
                <l>Aboue their worth, immoderate good-will, </l>
                <l>To the disgrace of good men, shew in end </l>
                <l>They onely in prosperity depend </l>
                <l>Not vpon them, but on their Fortune still. </l>
                <l>Which if it change, they change. then though they fil, </l>
                <l>Their hopes with honour, and their chests with coine </l>
                <l>Yet if they fall, or their affaires goe ill, </l>
                <l>Those whom they rais'd, will not with them descend, </l>
                <l>But with th'ascending Sunne wil straight way ioyne. </l>
                <l>And doe forget all that they gaue before, </l>
                <l>For that of them they can expect no more. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The truth hereof in end now hath th'euent </l>
                <l>In Bessus, and Narbazanes approoued: </l>
                <l>On whom their Prince so prodigallie spent </l>
                <l>Affection, honour, titles, treasure, rent, </l>
                <l>And all that might each honest mind haue mooued </l>
                <l>So bountifull a Prince for to haue loued, </l>
                <l>Who so benignly tendred their estate. </l>
                <l>Yet they to him vyle traitours now haue proued: </l>
                <l>By them he is in-chain'd, disgrac'd and shent; </l>
                <l>So as he well may rue, although too late, </l>
                <l>That he such slie Camelions changing hew </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-081-b"/>
                <l>Prefer'd to seruants dutifull and trew. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But though a while those traitours speede, </l>
                <l>No doubt the heau'ns once vengeance will exact: </l>
                <l>The very horrour of this haynous deede </l>
                <l>Doth make the harts of honest men to bleede: </l>
                <l>Yea, euen the wicked hate this barbarous act: </l>
                <l>The heauens no hier choller can contract, </l>
                <l>Then for th'invasion of a sacred King: </l>
                <l>Who, as it were, out of the starres extract, </l>
                <l>Should feare and reuerence inferiours breede, </l>
                <l>To whom from him both health and wealth doth spring. </l>
                <l>But though on earth men should neglect this wrong, </l>
                <l>Heauens will those traitors plague ere it be long. </l>
              </lg>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="eng000259-e122990">
          <head>ACTVS QVINTVS. </head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="eng000259-e123000">
            <head>Scen. I. </head>
            <stage xml:id="eng000259-e123010">HEPHESTION, ALEXANDER, POLISTRATVS. </stage>
            <sp who="#eng000259-hephaestion" xml:id="eng000259-e123020">
              <speaker>He. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>WHat story or what fable can recorde </l>
                <l>Of such a nombrous troupe so strangely lost? </l>
                <l>I know they quak'd to know it was my Lord, </l>
                <l>Whose name alone is worth anothers host. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>It scarce seemes credible in many partes: </l>
                <l>But traitors feare though al the world would backe them. </l>
                <l>They were but bodies destitute of harts: </l>
                <l>Moe prisoners they were then men to take them. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Who would beleeue so few durst striue to finde </l>
                <l>So great an armie, and the armie shrinkes </l>
                <l>What is impossible to a braue minde? </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-082-a"/>
                <l>True valour dare attempt all that it thinkes </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e123180">
              <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>In this encounter for t'haue had the best </l>
                <l>It would content more then a common thought: </l>
                <l>But since we want the chiefe, what of the rest? </l>
                <l>I would be satisfied in all, or nought. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Those traitours thought t'haue finish'd all the warre </l>
                <l>With giuing me their Lord, whom they had bound: </l>
                <l>But I distrust not mine owne force so farre, </l>
                <l>As for to builde vpon so base a ground. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Although indeede that Darius did me wrong, </l>
                <l>I will not suffer others to oppresse him. </l>
                <l>I keepe him for my selfe: he doth belong </l>
                <l>To me alone: none other should distresse him. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Whilst he did onely in himselfe confide, </l>
                <l>I labour'd by all meanes to make him bow: </l>
                <l>But since his hard estate abates that pride, </l>
                <l>Turn'd is my fury to compassion now. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Although he oft contemn'd me by his letter, </l>
                <l>Yet I am greeu'd to see him so deceiu'd. </l>
                <l>If he had but acknowledg'd me his better, </l>
                <l>'Twas not his blood, nor kingdome that I crau'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And if those traitours haue not kild him straight, </l>
                <l>Yet his deliuerie shall my name renoune: </l>
                <l>I would not loose a subiect of such waight, </l>
                <l>By which my clemencie might be made knowne: </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-polystratus" xml:id="eng000259-e123490">
              <speaker>Po. </speaker>
              <p>Sir, now your comming cannot doe him good. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e123510">
              <speaker>Al. </speaker>
              <p>What al are fled? none haue my force withstood? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-polystratus" xml:id="eng000259-e123530">
              <speaker>Po. </speaker>
              <p>Yet Darius cannot be redeem'd againe. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e123550">
              <speaker>Al. </speaker>
              <p>Why, haue they set him free? or is he slaine? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-polystratus" xml:id="eng000259-e123570">
              <speaker>Po. </speaker>
              <l>Now hath he got a liberty at last </l>
              <l>With no lesse ransome then his dearest breath. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e123600">
              <speaker>Al. </speaker>
              <l>Then is all Asias expectation past. </l>
              <l>Tell on at length the maner of his death. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-polystratus" xml:id="eng000259-e123630">
              <speaker>Po. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>The boyling ardour of th'ascending Sunne </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-082-b"/>
                <l>Had caus'd in me a moysture parching drouth, </l>
                <l>Which made me from the way a little runne, </l>
                <l>To finde some fountaine to refresh my mouth, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Their where a source her liquors softly scatters, </l>
                <l>Which shaddow'd was from Titans parching beames, </l>
                <l>I coold my thirst with the colde christall waters. </l>
                <l>Which seem'd to murmur that I forc'd their streames. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>When loe I sawe (a lamentable sight) </l>
                <l>Two wounded horses drawe a bloody coache, </l>
                <l>All clad with skinnes in most vncomely plight, </l>
                <l>Which narrowlie t'espy I did approach. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>One was within, who could not long escape </l>
                <l>The doubtfull passage of th'infernall gates: </l>
                <l>Yet maiestie triumphing ou'r mishap, </l>
                <l>He seem'd to threaten fortune; and the Fates, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And as not to so basse a fortune borne, </l>
                <l>While all his blood aboundantly deval'd, </l>
                <l>Burst forth into these words in Fortunes scorne, </l>
                <l>As one whose courage could not be appal'd, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>You gaze to see, and haue good cause wherefore, </l>
                <l>A man, no man; a King, no King; what monster? </l>
                <l>Now lesse then nought, who once was both, &amp; more: </l>
                <l>Which few now by my present state would conster. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And yet amidst my euils I must reioyce, </l>
                <l>That this last comfort doth fore-goe my end: </l>
                <l>I speake to one that vnderstands my voice, </l>
                <l>And not in vaine my dying-speeches spend. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I am, but how? in name, but not in pow'r, </l>
                <l>That wretched Darius (which I should suppresse) </l>
                <l>Once happy, as you heard, but at this houre </l>
                <l>The very patterne of extreame distresse; </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then a while pawsing after thus proceeded: </l>
                <l>Tell Alexander these last wordes from me: </l>
                <l>Although my hatred still t'wards him exceeded, </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-083-a"/>
                <l>Yet I am forc'd far in his debt to die. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I thanke him highlie for his great good-will, </l>
                <l>My mother, wife, and children so preseruing. </l>
                <l>Pray him t'vse them that rest as gently still </l>
                <l>For his owne goodnesse sake, not my deseruing. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>They to his foe pertaine, and yet he striues </l>
                <l>To haue them honour'd now, as in times past: </l>
                <l>But those who held of me both lands and liues, </l>
                <l>Of land and life haue me depriu'd at last. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I pray you on my part entreat him thus </l>
                <l>Not to permit that vnreueng'd belowe </l>
                <l>My ghost do wander. By his care of vs </l>
                <l>That men his Iustice, and their fault may knowe. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Beside the honour, which he shall acquire </l>
                <l>In plaguing them that haue betraide my trust; </l>
                <l>Men shall his magnanimitie admire, </l>
                <l>And feare t'offend him whome they finde so iust. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Loe, all my pompe is past, my time expir'd: </l>
                <l>My wealth evanished like watrie bubbles. </l>
                <l>Ou'r many a mightie people I impyr'd: </l>
                <l>Yet hath my life beene but a stage of troubles. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And since my glasse is runne, my glory gone, </l>
                <l>And I dead to the world, the world to me; </l>
                <l>I wish that all parts of th'earths globe in one </l>
                <l>May condescend his subiects for to be. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then drouping downe, faint, bloodles, and halfe dead, </l>
                <l>He prai'd to giue him water that stood by. </l>
                <l>(A small request by such a Monarcke made) </l>
                <l>Which when that he had gote: yet, ere I die, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>This crosse must come (said he) t'vndoe me quite: </l>
                <l>Though most parts of the world once homage ought me; </l>
                <l>I haue not now the power for to requite </l>
                <l>This little benefit that thou hast brought me. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But Alexander shall rewarde thee well; </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-083-b"/>
                <l>And him the heauens, who hath not done amisse, </l>
                <l>To those that haue beene mine: his foe must tell </l>
                <l>That vndeserued courtesie of his. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Though none haue pow'r his pleasure to controule; </l>
                <l>If he entreate them well whom he retaines; </l>
                <l>It will procure no small rest to my soule, </l>
                <l>And make him famous, while the world remaines. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>When my sprit parts out of this tent of clay, </l>
                <l>Entreat some with my buriall to take order; </l>
                <l>Least churlish Charon force me for to stray </l>
                <l>An vn-respected ghost on Stygian border. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Let first my corps be carried to my mother, </l>
                <l>Who may it with my auncestors entombe: </l>
                <l>And, as she hath more cause then any other, </l>
                <l>May waile this wofull burthen of her wombe. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>In pledge of that affection, which I beare </l>
                <l>Thy Soueraignes worth, whom now I must see neuer, </l>
                <l>Haue heere a Princes hand, I hold him deare, </l>
                <l>And recommend me to his grace for euer. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I scarce had got his hand, or toucht his vesture, </l>
                <l>When like a torch whose waxe and weeke is spent, </l>
                <l>Somewhat perplext, yet with a princely gesture, </l>
                <l>He died in peace: his sprit appear'd content. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e124790">
              <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Who could refraine from teares to heare declar'd </l>
                <l>The desolation of this wretched wight: </l>
                <l>Haue subiects slaine their prince whom strangers spar'd? </l>
                <l>Vs hath he fled, that perish thus he might? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I for his fall am wonderfully sorie, </l>
                <l>Who Nestors age was worthie t'haue attain'd: </l>
                <l>I envie death, because it rob'd the glorie, </l>
                <l>Which I in giuing him his life had gain'd. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-hephaestion" xml:id="eng000259-e124900">
              <speaker>Hep. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Since death hath put a periode to his woes, </l>
                <l>The fauour that t'wards him you thought t'extend, </l>
                <l>Conuert to furour now against his foes. </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-084-a"/>
                <l>For your designes can haue no fairer end. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>So shall you both attaine perpetuall praise, </l>
                <l>And winne their harts who see their Lord reveng'd, </l>
                <l>Then reape no little profite in your dayes, </l>
                <l>To haue the countrie of such vipers cleng'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>If but one vertue should adorne a King, </l>
                <l>It should be Iustice: many great defects </l>
                <l>Are vaild thereby; whereas each vertuous thing </l>
                <l>In one that is vniust, the world suspects. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e125060">
              <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Although your counsell, or yet his request </l>
                <l>Had not the pow'r to penetrate my eares: </l>
                <l>A generous stomack could not well disgest </l>
                <l>So great a wrong: my minde it hardly beares. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>My spirit impatient of repose disdaines </l>
                <l>That they so long this infamie surviue. </l>
                <l>But I will punish with most greevous paines </l>
                <l>The horrid treason that they did contriue. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>What? do they thinke, deceau'd with some illusion. </l>
                <l>That Bactria is a bulwarke for my ire? </l>
                <l>Flie where they list, they cannot scape confusion: </l>
                <l>My wrath shall follow like consuming fire. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Heauen cannot be a sanctuarie for them: </l>
                <l>I dare to force th'infernall caves adventer: </l>
                <l>Th'earth cannot keepe them safe, if I abhorre them: </l>
                <l>Ile search them out though they were in the center. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And hauing gotten once those malefactors, </l>
                <l>Betwixt the bending boughes of two strong trees, </l>
                <l>Vnto th'eternall terrour of all traitours, </l>
                <l>They shall dismembred be before my eyes. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-polystratus" xml:id="eng000259-e125320">
              <speaker>Pol. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, may it please your Grace to take some care, </l>
              <l>That some his funerall offices performe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-alexander" xml:id="eng000259-e125350">
              <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
              <l>Goe presentlie and euery thing prepare </l>
              <l>According to the militarie forme. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="eng000259-e125380">
            <pb xml:id="eng000259-084-b"/>
            <head>ACTVS QVINTVS. Scen. 2. </head>
            <stage xml:id="eng000259-e125390">SISIGAMBIS, NVNTIVS, CHORVS. </stage>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e125400">
              <speaker>Sisi. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>THis looke, alas, hath fraught my soule with feares, </l>
                <l>Speake, for my life doth on thy lips depend: </l>
                <l>Thy count'nance (ah) a dolefull coppie beares </l>
                <l>Of some sad summons to denounce my end. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Starue not my eares with famish for thy words: </l>
                <l>That swallow'd yet may make my hart to burst. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-nuntius" xml:id="eng000259-e125490">
              <speaker>Nun. </speaker>
              <l>Madame the message that my soule affordes </l>
              <l>Must once be known, and once knowne still accurst, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e125520">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <p>Be not a niggard of euil newes. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-nuntius" xml:id="eng000259-e125540">
              <speaker>Nun. </speaker>
              <p>And why? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e125560">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <p>Fame will tell the world. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-nuntius" xml:id="eng000259-e125580">
              <speaker>Nun. </speaker>
              <p>But first to you. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e125600">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <p>Tel sone. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-nuntius" xml:id="eng000259-e125620">
              <speaker>Nun. </speaker>
              <p>Your son is dead. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e125640">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <p>Then let me die. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-chorus" xml:id="eng000259-e125660">
              <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
              <p>Her ioyes and pleasures are all perish'd now. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e125680">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Why opens not the earth for to deuoure </l>
                <l>A cursed caitiue, that all ioy hath loste? </l>
                <l>The longer that I liue, my griefe growes more: </l>
                <l>Borne I am to mischiefe, kept to be crost. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Would God this body in mishappes abounding </l>
                <l>Were couered with some mountaine of huge waight; </l>
                <l>Or else that th'Ocean ou'r these fieldes inunding </l>
                <l>Might make my buriall in her bosome straight. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>O Alexander, hast thou robd his life, </l>
                <l>Yet entertain'd me still in hope to finde him? </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-085-a"/>
                <l>Why didst thou not first kill this poore old wim </l>
                <l>Who was not worthie to haue liu'd behind hi? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Ah, tended all thy courtesie to this, </l>
                <l>That I should liue till thou hast slaine my sonne? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-nuntius" xml:id="eng000259-e125870">
              <speaker>Nun. </speaker>
              <l>You wrong that worthie Prince: for he and his </l>
              <l>Came him to helpe, who was ere then vndone. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e125900">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <l>What impious hands durst one that wore a crown, </l>
              <l>And was thereof most worthie, murther so? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-nuntius" xml:id="eng000259-e125930">
              <speaker>Nun. </speaker>
              <l>Two whom himself rais'd vp haue cast him down: </l>
              <l>More faithfull then his owne he found his foe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e125960">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Tell on thy message, message of my death, </l>
                <l>And load my minde with all mischiefe and horrour: </l>
                <l>That in sad sighes I may dissolue my breath, </l>
                <l>Whilst thou relat'st these tydings full of terrour. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-nuntius" xml:id="eng000259-e126020">
              <speaker>Nun. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>When Alexander eftsoones back had sent </l>
                <l>Th'Ambassadours that peace had sought in vaine, </l>
                <l>A generall muster, then to try th'euent </l>
                <l>Of doubtfull Mars, King Darius did ordaine, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And in one battell to aduenture all </l>
                <l>Intending, caus'd his will to be proclaim'd, </l>
                <l>While two vile traitours did conspire his fall, </l>
                <l>Who Bessus, and Narbazanes were nam'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>These two in counsell did discouer first </l>
                <l>Some portion of the poison of their hart: </l>
                <l>Which caus'd the King suspect, but not the worst. </l>
                <l>Yet with a sword he sought to make them smart. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But hauing scap'd the first brunt of his rage, </l>
                <l>With teares of Crocodiles they so lamented, </l>
                <l>As they his indignation did asswage, </l>
                <l>Whil'st in appearance onlie they repented. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>They came to Artabazus, honest man, </l>
                <l>Who iudg'd of others by his vpright minde, </l>
                <l>And could not, or through bountie would not scan </l>
                <l>What they with craft and malice had desing'd. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="eng000259-085-b"/>
            <sp who="#eng000259-chorus" xml:id="eng000259-e126280">
              <speaker>Chor. </speaker>
              <l>A sinceare minde is euer least suspitious: </l>
              <l>They think all faulty who themselues are vitious. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-nuntius" xml:id="eng000259-e126310">
              <speaker>Nun. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>They vrg'd him with the King to interceede. </l>
                <l>That in his fauour he would giue them place; </l>
                <l>With promise that by some notorious deede </l>
                <l>Of armes they would seeke to deserue his grace. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>He in their fauour first enform'd the King, </l>
                <l>The battell would beare witnesse of their truth; </l>
                <l>Then both before his maiesty did bring, </l>
                <l>Who was by their submission moou'd to ruth. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Their hands streatchd vp to heau'n, &amp; humbled knees, </l>
                <l>Their teares like those the Crocodiles doe shed, </l>
                <l>Woe in their face, and pitty in their eyes </l>
                <l>Did for compassion and for mercie plead. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The king of nature milde, prompt to receiue them, </l>
                <l>While they dissembledly were thus complaning, </l>
                <l>Not onelie of his lenitie forgaue them, </l>
                <l>But wept in earnest too while they were faining. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then as he vs'd, his danger now not feeling, </l>
                <l>He mounted to his Coach: they came behinde </l>
                <l>With a submissiue voyce most humbly kneeling </l>
                <l>To him, whom shortly they were bent to binde. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The Graecian Captaine follow'd them with speede, </l>
                <l>Who being cal'd, and ask'd what he desir'd, </l>
                <l>Sollicited the King to take good heede </l>
                <l>Of those that had against his life conspir'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>He tolde him how he had their treason tri'de, </l>
                <l>And seene the Bactrians to a tumult bent; </l>
                <l>Then prai'd him for his safety to prouide, </l>
                <l>In going with him to his trusty tent. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The King grow'n carelesse, and his safety shunning </l>
                <l>Refus'd this offer on affection grounded. </l>
                <l>Or with some pow'rfull fate his fall fore-running, </l>
                <l>Was carried headlong thus to be confounded. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-086-a"/>
              <lg>
                <l>The Greeke past thence dispairing of his safety, </l>
                <l>Who thus recurelesse helpe and health refus'd. </l>
                <l>Then Bessus did begin with speeches craftie </l>
                <l>To purge himselfe, and errours past excus'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The King then Artabazus did command </l>
                <l>T'approch, and Patrons speech at length reported: </l>
                <l>He then did doubt what danger was at hand, </l>
                <l>And to go with the Greeke his Grace exhorted. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But when he found this resolution plac'd, </l>
                <l>Within his brest, no peril for to flie: </l>
                <l>With mutuall teares each other they embrac'd, </l>
                <l>Parting like two, that liuing went to die, </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Now silent night in pitchie vapours cled </l>
                <l>Had mustred mists, and march'd vnto the West, </l>
                <l>A shadowie horrour ou'r the earth was spread, </l>
                <l>The Santinelles were set, and all at rest. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>When a strange terrour troubled all the hoste: </l>
                <l>The multitudes did murmure in all parts: </l>
                <l>They did resemble ships in stormes neere lost, </l>
                <l>Whilst each to th'other cause of feares imparts. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Those who their King appointed were to guarde </l>
                <l>All shrunke away to corners none staid there: </l>
                <l>And hauing to his danger no regarde </l>
                <l>His better-fortunes Minions fled else where. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The desolation then was wonderous great: </l>
                <l>With a few Eunuches Darius left alone </l>
                <l>Did enter deepely to reuolue his state, </l>
                <l>And thus be-spake them; who did for him mone. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Depart in peace and for your selues prouide, </l>
                <l>Least yee be likewise with my ruine caught: </l>
                <l>I will the issue of my fate abide: </l>
                <l>They hearing this, as of their wits distraught </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Went howling through the host with dolorous cries: </l>
                <l>This made the King as dead to be bewaild. </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-086-b"/>
                <l>And in the armie did a rumour rise, </l>
                <l>That he had kild himselfe, when all hope fail'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The Persians greeu'd, while these things did occurre, </l>
                <l>Did first encourage all their countrie bands </l>
                <l>To helpe their Prince: but yet they durst not sturre </l>
                <l>For feare of falling in the Bactrians hands. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Ev'n in the time when this confusion was </l>
                <l>The traitours, to deferre the fact no more, </l>
                <l>Did to their soueraignes owne Pavilion passe, </l>
                <l>And rooke, and bound him, whome they seru'd before. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>He, who in golden coach superbelie rode, </l>
                <l>Was cast in one for bassest carriage vs'd: </l>
                <l>And who of late was honoured like a God, </l>
                <l>By seruants as a bond slaue was abus'd. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Those royall hands to beare a scepter borne </l>
                <l>Were bound with chains: this also much did grieue him </l>
                <l>That fortune his aduersitie would scorne </l>
                <l>With golden bands, that seru'd not to releeue him. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then Alexander, hauing heard in end </l>
                <l>That Darius came not forward to affront him, </l>
                <l>To finde him out did all his forces bend, </l>
                <l>Not doubting but he eftsoones would surmount him. </l>
                <l>But being at the last at length inform'd </l>
                <l>How he was made a Captiue to his owne, </l>
                <l>At this indignitie he highlie storm'd, </l>
                <l>And swore he would avenge it by his crowne. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Out of his hoste he did select a fewe, </l>
                <l>Who were best hors'd, whose equipage was light: </l>
                <l>With whom his foes he did so fast pursue, </l>
                <l>That, ere they could suspect, he came in sight. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The traitours troubled with this he had done </l>
                <l>Came to the Cart wherein the King was carried, </l>
                <l>And bad him mount on horse back, and flee soone, </l>
                <l>Least that his foe should take him if he tarried. </l>
              </lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-087-a"/>
              <lg>
                <l>He look'd aloft, and cry'd aloud: this day </l>
                <l>Th'eternall Iusticer sees through the starres: </l>
                <l>I will not with such periur'd rebelles stay, </l>
                <l>And flie from him, who moou's but honest warres. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then those in whom impietie aboundes, </l>
                <l>Throw'd darts at him whom they should haue defended </l>
                <l>And hurte the horses with an hundreth woundes. </l>
                <l>While they perform'd the Parricide intended. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Their hands were feeble, as their harts vntrue: </l>
                <l>For when their foes began them once to comber, </l>
                <l>The traitours first, then all the traiterous crue </l>
                <l>Fled them, who were inferiour farre in number. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>But to the confines of deathes kingdome brought </l>
                <l>The King retir'd out from the way aside, </l>
                <l>More wounded with ingratitude then ought, </l>
                <l>Did flie the world whose follies he had tri'de. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Scarce was the lasting last diuorcement made </l>
                <l>Twixt soule and body whilst that th'eyes grew dim </l>
                <l>When Alexander came, and found him dead, </l>
                <l>Who long had labour'd for t'haue ruin'd him. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet with the vesture which himselfe then wore </l>
                <l>He couered the dead corps, and not eschew'd it; </l>
                <l>But eu'n with teares his coffin did decore, </l>
                <l>To the great wonder of all them that view'd it. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And hauing waild his death aboue all measure, </l>
                <l>For t'haue his funerals made in Princely wise </l>
                <l>He bids you spare no coste, but vse his treasure, </l>
                <l>And them, as best becommes, to solemnise. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>He hath his body hither sent by me, </l>
                <l>That the last honours you to him may do: </l>
                <l>He thinkes they so shall best accomplish'd be, </l>
                <l>And who him bare shall see him buried to. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-chorus" xml:id="eng000259-e127960">
              <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
              <l>Behold how griefe hath her of sense bereft, </l>
              <l>And choak'd her breath with super-abounding grones, </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000259-087-b"/>
              <l>No will or power to liue is to her left, </l>
              <l>Since all her weale evanish'd is at ones. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#eng000259-sisigambis" xml:id="eng000259-e128010">
              <speaker>Sis. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ah shall I see (no let me first be blinde) </l>
                <l>That body breath-lesse, which I brought to light? </l>
                <l>Where would my soule a force sufficient finde </l>
                <l>T'endure the dolour of that deadly sight. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>O flintie hardned hart, that wilt not breake </l>
                <l>With the remembrance of so many woes, </l>
                <l>Why part'st thou not, faint sprit, that whil'st I speake, </l>
                <l>In opening of my lips mine eyes might close? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>This heritage of death, this withered stock </l>
                <l>Is but a receptacle of dispaires: </l>
                <l>A torture to it selfe, a stumbling block, </l>
                <l>Whose aged furrowes fertile are in cares. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>What helpes it now to haue bene made the mother </l>
                <l>Of one who to such dignitie did clim? </l>
                <l>More miserable now then any other, </l>
                <l>I liue to waile my death, who di'd in him. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Aye me, malitious Fates haue done me wrong: </l>
                <l>Who came first to the world should first depart. </l>
                <l>It not becommes the olde t'ou'r-liue the yong: </l>
                <l>This dealing is praeposterous and ou'r-thwart. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Ah, why should death so indiscreet be found </l>
                <l>To saue a caitiue, and confound a Prince: </l>
                <l>My halfe-dead body, weigh'd downe to the ground, </l>
                <l>Through griefe is grow'n ripe for the graue long since. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <div type="chorus" xml:id="eng000259-e128320">
              <head>CHORVS. </head>
              <lg>
                <l>WHat makes vaine worldlings so to swell with pride, </l>
                <l>Who came of earth, and to the earth returne? </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-088-a"/>
                <l>So hellish furies with their fire brands burne </l>
                <l>Proude and ambitious men, as they deuise </l>
                <l>Them from themselues, and so turmoile their mindes, </l>
                <l>That all their time they studie still </l>
                <l>How to content a bound-lesse will, </l>
                <l>Which neuer yet a full contentment findes. </l>
                <l>Who so this flame within his bosome smothers </l>
                <l>Doth many fantasies contriue, </l>
                <l>And euen forgets himselfe a-liue, </l>
                <l>To be remembred after death by others. </l>
                <l>Thus while he is his paines are neuer ended; </l>
                <l>That while he is not, he may be commended. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>What can this helpe the happinesse of Kings, </l>
                <l>So to subdue their neighbours, as they doe, </l>
                <l>And make strange nations tributaries to? </l>
                <l>The greater state the greater trouble brings. </l>
                <l>Their pompes and triumphes, stands them in no stead: </l>
                <l>Their Arches, Tombes, Piramides hie, </l>
                <l>And Statues are but vanitie: </l>
                <l>They die, and yet would liue in what is dead: </l>
                <l>And while they liue, we see their glorious actions </l>
                <l>Oft wrested to the worst: and all their life </l>
                <l>Is but a stage of endlesse toile and strife, </l>
                <l>Of tumults, vprores, mutinies, and factions. </l>
                <l>They rise with feare, and lie with danger downe: </l>
                <l>There is no burthen weightier then a Crowne. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And as Ambition Princes vndermines; </l>
                <l>So doth it those that vnder them rule all. </l>
                <l>We see in how short time they rise, and fall; </l>
                <l>How oft their light eclips'd but dimlie shines. </l>
                <l>They studie by all shifts and slights to moue </l>
                <l>Their Prince of their deserts t'account: </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-088-b"/>
                <l>And when they by his fauour mount, </l>
                <l>O what a danger is't to be aboue? </l>
                <l>For straight expos'd to hatred, and despight, </l>
                <l>With all their skill they cannot march so euen, </l>
                <l>But some opprobrious scandall will be giuen: </l>
                <l>For all men enuy those that haue most might. </l>
                <l>And if the King dislike them once, then straight </l>
                <l>The wretched Courtiers fal with their own waight. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Some of a poorer Spirite, who would be prais'd, </l>
                <l>And yet haue not wherefore to be esteem'd, </l>
                <l>What they are not indeede would faine be deemd, </l>
                <l>And indirectly labour to be rais'd. </l>
                <l>This crue each publike place of honour haunts, </l>
                <l>And changing garments euery day </l>
                <l>While they woulde hyde, doe but bewray </l>
                <l>With outward ornaments their inward wants. </l>
                <l>And men of better iudgement iustly loth </l>
                <l>Those, who in outwarde showes place all their care, </l>
                <l>And deck their bodies, while their mindes are bare, </l>
                <l>Like to a shaddow, or a painted cloth. </l>
                <l>The multitude, who but th'apparrell notes, </l>
                <l>Doth homage not to them, but to their cotes. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet Princes must be seru'd, and with all sorts, </l>
                <l>Some both to doe, and counsell what is best: </l>
                <l>Some serue for Ciphers to set out the rest, </l>
                <l>Like liue lesse pictures, that adorne the ports. </l>
                <l>Faire pallaces replenish'd are with feares: </l>
                <l>Those seeming pleasures are but snares: </l>
                <l>The Royall Robe doth couer cares, </l>
                <l>Th' Assyrian dye deere buyth he, that it beares. </l>
                <l>Those dainty delicates, and far fetch'd foode </l>
                <l>Oft through suspition sauour out of season: </l>
                <pb xml:id="eng000259-089-a"/>
                <l>Embrodered beds and tapesteries hatche treason: </l>
                <l>The golden goblets mingled are with blood. </l>
                <l>Such glorious gorgeous showes do serue for nought: </l>
                <l>All cannot calme the tempest of the thought. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>O happy he, who far from fame at home </l>
                <l>Doth sit securely by a quiet fire, </l>
                <l>Who hath not much, and doth not much desire, </l>
                <l>Nor curious is to learne who goe, or come, </l>
                <l>For satisfied with what his father left </l>
                <l>His minde he measures by his store, </l>
                <l>And is not pyn'd to gape for more; </l>
                <l>Nor eates ought that iniquity hath reft: </l>
                <l>He hath his little cleanly, and in peace, </l>
                <l>And lookes not with suspitious eye. </l>
                <l>No poyson comes in Cups of tree: </l>
                <l>No treason harbours in so poore a place. </l>
                <l>No troublous dreame doth interrupt his sleepe: </l>
                <l>A quiet conscience doth his cottage keepe. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>He doth not study oft what stormes may blow: </l>
                <l>His pouerty cannot be much impair'd: </l>
                <l>He feares no forraine force, and craues no guarde: </l>
                <l>None coueteth his spoile, none lookes so low: </l>
                <l>Where as the great are commonly once crost, </l>
                <l>As Darius hath beene in his flowre, </l>
                <l>Or Sisigambis at this houre, </l>
                <l>Who hath scap'd long, and now at length is lost. </l>
                <l>But how commes this that Potentates oft fall, </l>
                <l>Forc'd to confesse th' afflictions of their soule? </l>
                <l>There is some hier pow'r that can controule </l>
                <l>The Monarches of the earth, and censure all, </l>
                <l>Who once will call their doings to accompt, </l>
                <l>Their pride repressing, who t'oppresse were prompt. </l>
              </lg>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
        <closer>
          <signed>W. A. </signed>
        </closer>
        <trailer>Finis. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back></back>
  </text>
</TEI>
