<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Enkyklochoreia, or, Vniversal motion being part of that magnificent entertainment by the noble prince, De la Grange, Lord Lieutenant of Lincolns Inn, presented to the High and Mighty Charles II, Monarck of Great Brittain, France and Ireland, on Friday 3 of January 1662.</title>
        <author>
          <persName>Anon.</persName>
          <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q4233718</idno>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <idno type="dracor" xml:base="https://dracor.org/id/">ep000560</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A38208.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <p>
            This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is available for reuse, according to the terms of
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>
            . The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
          </p>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull>
              <titleStmt>
                <title>Enkyklochoreia, or, Vniversal motion being part of that magnificent entertainment by the noble prince, De la Grange, Lord Lieutenant of Lincolns Inn, presented to the High and Mighty Charles II, Monarck of Great Brittain, France and Ireland, on Friday 3 of January 1662.</title>
                <author>De la Grange.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>7 p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                <date>1662.</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>Title transliterated from Greek.</note>
                <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000560-e10">
        <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000560-001-a"/>
        <p>Εγκυκλοχορεία OR Vniversal Motion, Being part of that Magnificent Entertainment by the Noble Prince, De la GRANGE, LORD LIEVTENANT of <hi>LINCOLNS INN</hi>, </p>
        <p>Presented to the High and Mighty CHARLES II. </p>
        <p>Monarck of Great <hi>Brittain, France </hi>and Ireland. </p>
        <p>On Friday 3 of January 1662. </p>
        <p>LONDON Printed 1662. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="treatise_on_dance" xml:id="ep000560-e140">
        <pb xml:id="ep000560-002-a"/>
        <pb n="3" xml:id="ep000560-002-b"/>
        <head>Εγκυκλοχορεία OR Vniversal Motion, The several Modes of Dancing, according to the Primitive Invention of different Nations, performed in 12 Entries, In the habit of each Countrey, </head>
        <byline>By English men. </byline>
        <div n="1" type="part" xml:id="ep000560-e180">
          <head>I. </head>
          <p>A <hi>Clownish Carrier </hi>with a Packet of Books to be distributed by the Master of the Ceremonies, wherein is described the whole designe: who daunceth a Darbishire Round. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="part" xml:id="ep000560-e220">
          <head>II. </head>
          <p>Gives you a Bouree, in the habit of a Thrasonical Gasconian; To let you know, all Frenchmen are not Butterflies. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="part" xml:id="ep000560-e260">
          <head>III. </head>
          <p>Presents the variety of Expressions, made by Motions and Actions of the Body only; For which we are indebted to the Quaker, the last Inventor of Ecclesiastical postures, who turnd Informer, is like to be troublesome to our Assembly. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="part" xml:id="ep000560-e310">
          <pb n="4" xml:id="ep000560-003-a"/>
          <head>IV. </head>
          <p>Shews the truest and most genuine steps of Ballet. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="part" xml:id="ep000560-e350">
          <head>V. </head>
          <p>Two other Clownes with their Lasses, (a double pair of Northern Tikes) who dance a Iigge, the first-born of a Scottish Bagpipe. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="6" type="part" xml:id="ep000560-e380">
          <head>VI. </head>
          <p>Presents you with a <hi>Phantastick Saraband</hi>, manag'd by a Spaniard, To shew a Phantastick Don can be as ridiculous as the most Antick Mounsieur. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="7" type="part" xml:id="ep000560-e420">
          <head>VII. </head>
          <p>Throws you in a Drunkard, with steps proper only to that humor: suitable to the Windmil of his Pericranium, which motions we owe to the lightness of a Dutchmans Breeches. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="8" type="part" xml:id="ep000560-e470">
          <head>VIII. </head>
          <p>Gives you a Country Dance, perform'd by Sheapheards and Sheapherdesses, in the habits of Arcadian Pastorals; who set forth the Innocency of their minds, by the simplicity of their manners. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="9" type="part" xml:id="ep000560-e530">
          <head>IX. </head>
          <p>Presents a Corant single and figured, and a <hi>Saraband serious</hi>, both ascrib'd to the Ingenuity, and <hi>Bon mene </hi>of a well temperd Frenchman. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="10" type="part" xml:id="ep000560-e590">
          <head>X. </head>
          <p>An entry of <hi>Italian Pantaloons</hi>; to shew there <pb n="5" xml:id="ep000560-003-b"/>are Madmen and Fools in every Countrey, even at <hi>Rome, Paris</hi>, and particularly in London. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="11" type="part" xml:id="ep000560-e650">
          <head>XI. </head>
          <p>Presents you (the delight of its age) the Canaryes, first invented by the lofty Italian, who generally has more wit than honesty. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="12" type="part" xml:id="ep000560-e700">
          <head>XII. </head>
          <p>An entry of Swisses, who had rather fight than dance, but loves the Argent better then both. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="descant" xml:id="ep000560-e750">
        <head>A Descant upon the several Movements. </head>
        <lg>
          <l>GReat Sir, y'ave seen Vs, like the active Sun </l>
          <l>To please the World, through the whole Zodiack run; </l>
          <l>Y'have seen the Noble Spaniard Countermand </l>
          <l>All France, ith Marches of a Saraband: </l>
          <l>And yet with such <hi>wise care </hi>his Limbs dispose </l>
          <l>As if h'ad got the Frenchman in his Hose. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Y'ave seen the Mounsieur move, his Arm, Foot, Knee, </l>
          <l>And shrugge, as if no Nation danct but he: </l>
          <l>His Alamod Corant, his Saraband Pace, </l>
          <l>His Bourees; all performd, with the Bon-Grace. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Y'ave seen th' Italian dance the Pantaloon? </l>
          <l>No Region wants a Madman or Buffoon! </l>
          <l>Th' Arcadian Sheapheards in soft measures move. </l>
          <l>As if their dancing was their <hi>School of Love.</hi>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <pb n="6" xml:id="ep000560-004-a"/>
          <l>The Bonny Scotchman and his merry Lasses, </l>
          <l>At Jigge and Bagpipe all the rest surpasses; </l>
          <l>What mischief did (that Scotch-witch) Covenant do, </l>
          <l>Who charmd the Organs and the Bagpipes too? </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Most Excellent! active Nations! all put down </l>
          <l>The Brittish <hi>Bard, sufferd </hi>to Act the Clown. </l>
          <l>To move the Carriers pace: or Coupee over </l>
          <l>With Packets from proud Calais to poor Dover. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>And yet nor Seigniour, nor the stately Don </l>
          <l>Are much above the middle Region: </l>
          <l>Tis well in Rome or Spain, if you can see </l>
          <l>A handsome Ball once in a <hi>Iubilee.</hi>! </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>O but the Mounsieur, <hi>Englands Dancing Master </hi>
          </l>
          <l>He walks on Parian Marble, Paris-Plaister! </l>
          <l>Like th' Element of fire, his spirit soon </l>
          <l>Lifts him up, to the Concave of the Moon. </l>
          <l>Dances as soft and nimble as the Aire; </l>
          <l>Who vies with him practises to despair! </l>
          <l>Dull Englishman is forct to go to France </l>
          <l>To change his Gold wear clothes, and learn to dance. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Since t'must be so, weel strike sail and submit, </l>
          <l>Wishing the French more Pride, our selves more Wit. </l>
          <l>Grant their Minerva, curious, neat, exact, </l>
          <l>What ere they can Imagine we dare Act. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <pb n="7" xml:id="ep000560-004-b"/>
          <l>Inspir'd with Plumbroth we dance every man, </l>
          <l>Save (vho eats none) our Presbyterian; </l>
          <l>Hee's pardon'd if he move no more, but will </l>
          <l>Quietly, with his good <hi>Good Old Cause</hi>, sit still, </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Thanks to the Quaker our Last-mover, he </l>
          <l>Listed himself into our Company, </l>
          <l>Who went <hi>good man</hi>! to teach the Pope at Rome, </l>
          <l>A Babylon-slip; the Time yet was not come! </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>But turn'd our Pursevant, a Lurch, a Pryer; </l>
          <l>We wisht the Iesuited knave a Cloyster'd Fryer </l>
          <l>Good Saint to shew what weight his Talents beare </l>
          <l>Begot a Negro, no Christian you may sweare! </l>
          <l>How ere his various postures heplt to prove, </l>
          <l>The Brittish Orbe, like other Spheares can move. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>England I am sure in former times could dance, </l>
          <l>Wittness her many Capers into France. </l>
        </lg>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
