<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eng000372" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Alphonsus, Emperor of Germany</title>
        <author>
          <persName>Anon.</persName>
          <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q4233718</idno>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A31675.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
        </bibl>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The tragedy of Alphonsus, Emperour of Germany as it hath been [v]ery often a[cte]d (with great appl[ause]) at the privat house in Black-Friers by His Maiesties servants / by George Chapman, Gent.</title>
            <author>Chapman, George, 1559?-1634.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>39 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2004 March (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">12043046</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Wing C1952.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">53017</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31675</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2248529234</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The tragedy of Alphonsus, Emperour of Germany as it hath been [v]ery often a[cte]d (with great appl[ause]) at the privat house in Black-Friers by His Maiesties servants / by George Chapman, Gent.</title>
            <author>Chapman, George, 1559?-1634.</author>
            <author>Peele, George, 1556-1596.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[4], 17 [i.e. 71] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed for Humphrey Moseley ...,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date type="publication_date">1654.</date>
            <date type="creation_date">1594</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Caption and running title: Alphonsus, Emperour of Germany.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Ascribed variously to George Chapman and George Peele. Cf. Camb. hist., v. 6, p. 40; DNB., etc.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of original in British Library.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Imperfect: t.p. badly mutilated, some letters missing.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <personGrp xml:id="eng000372-soldiers" sex="MALE">
            <name>Soldiers</name>
          </personGrp>
          <person xml:id="eng000372-lorenzo" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Lorenzo</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000372-alphonsus" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Alphonsus</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000372-bohemia" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Bohemia</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000372-mentz" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Mentz</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000372-palsgrave" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Palsgrave</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000372-collen" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Collen</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000372-saxony" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Saxony</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000372-trier" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Trier</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000372-brandenburgh" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Brandenburgh</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000372-empress" sex="FEMALE">
            <persName>Empress</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000372-alexander" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Alexander</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000372-richard" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Richard</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000372-edward" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Edward</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000372-hedewick" sex="FEMALE">
            <persName>Hedewick</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000372-jerick" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Jerick</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000372-hans" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Hans</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000372-captain" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Captain</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000372-messenger" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Messenger</persName>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
      <textClass>
        <classCode scheme="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q80930</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1594">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="eng000372-e100030">
        <pb xml:id="eng000372-001-a"/>
        <p>THE TRAGEDY OF ALPHONSUS EMPEROUR OF GERMANY As it hath been very often acted (with great applause) at the Private house in BLACK-FRIERS by his MAIESTIES Servants. </p>
        <p>By George Chapman Gent. </p>
        <p>LONDON, Printed for HUMPHREY MOSELEY, and are to be sold at his Shopp at the Princes Arms in St. Pauls Church-yard 1614. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="eng000372-e100070">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="eng000372-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="eng000372-002-b"/>
        <head>To the Reader </head>
        <p>I Shall not need to bespeak thee Courteous, if thou hast seen this Piece presented with all the Elegance of Life and Action on the Black-Friers Stage; But if it be a Stranger to thee, give me leave to prepare thy acceptation, by telling thee, it was receiv'd with general applause, and thy judgement (I doubt not) will be satisfied in the reading. </p>
        <p>I will not raise thy Expectation further, nor delay thy Entertainment by a tedious Preface. The Design is high, the Contrivement subtle, and will deserve thy grave Attention in the perusall. </p>
        <closer>Farewell. </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="eng000372-e100110">
        <pb xml:id="eng000372-003-a"/>
        <list>
          <head>Dramatis Personae. </head>
          <item>ALphonsus Emperour of Germany <list>
              <head>The seven Electors of the German Empire. </head>
              <item>King of Bohemia. </item>
              <item>Bishop of Mentz. </item>
              <item>Bishop of Collen. </item>
              <item>Bishop of Tryer. </item>
              <item>Pallatine of the Rhein. </item>
              <item>Duke of Saxon. </item>
              <item>Marquess of Brandenburgh. </item>
            </list>
          </item>
          <item>Prince Edward of England. </item>
          <item>Richard Duke of Cornwall: </item>
          <item>Lorenzo de Cipres, Secretary to the Emperour. </item>
          <item>Alexander his Son, the Emperours Page. </item>
          <item>Isabella the Empress. </item>
          <item>Hedewick Daughter to the Duke of Saxon. </item>
          <item>Captain of the Guard. </item>
          <item>Souldiers. </item>
          <item>Jaylor. </item>
          <item>Two Boores. </item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="play" xml:id="eng000372-e100330">
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="eng000372-e100340">
          <pb n="1" xml:id="eng000372-003-b"/>
          <head>ALPHONSUS Emperour of Germany. </head>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e100350">Enter Alphonsus the Emperour in his night-gown, and his shirt, and a torch in his hand, Alexander de Tripes his Page following him. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e100360">
            <speaker>Al. </speaker>
            <l>BOy, give me the Master Key of all the doors. </l>
            <l>To Bed again, and leave me to my self. </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e100390">[Exit Alexder. </stage>
            <l>Is Richard come? have four Electors sworn </l>
            <l>To make him Keisar in despite of me? </l>
            <l>Why then Alphonsus it is time to wake. </l>
            <l>No Englishman, thou art too hot at hand, </l>
            <l>Too shallow braind to undermine my throne; </l>
            <l>The Spanish Sun hath purifi'd my wit, </l>
            <l>And dry'd up all gross humours in my head, </l>
            <l>That I am sighted as the King of Birds, </l>
            <l>And can discern thy deepest Stratagems. </l>
            <l>I am the lawful German Emperour, </l>
            <l>Chosen, enstall'd, by general consent; </l>
            <l>And they may tearm me Tyrant as they please, </l>
            <l>I will be King, and Tyrant if I please; </l>
            <l>For what is Empire but a Tyrannie? </l>
            <l>And none but children use it otherwise. </l>
            <l>Of seven Electors, four are falln away, </l>
            <l>The other three I dare not greatly trust; </l>
            <l>My Wife is Sister to mine enemy, </l>
            <l>And therefore wisely to be dealt withall; </l>
            <l>But why do I except in special, </l>
            <l>When this position must be general, </l>
            <pb n="2" xml:id="eng000372-004-a"/>
            <l>That no man living must be credited, </l>
            <l>Further than tends unto thy proper good. </l>
            <l>But to the purpose of my silent walk; </l>
            <l>Within this Chamber lyes my Secretary, </l>
            <l>Lorenzo de Cipres, in whose learned brain </l>
            <l>Is all the compass of the world containd; </l>
            <l>And as the ignorant and simple age </l>
            <l>Of our forefathers, blinded in their zeal, </l>
            <l>Receiv'd dark answers from Appollo's shrine, </l>
            <l>And honour'd him as Patron of their bliss; </l>
            <l>So I, not muffled in simplicitie, </l>
            <l>Zealous indeed of nothing but my good, </l>
            <l>Hast to the Augur of my happiness, </l>
            <l>To lay the ground of my ensuing Wars. </l>
            <l>He learns his wisdom, not by flight of Birds, </l>
            <l>By prying into sacrificed beasts, </l>
            <l>By Hares that cross the way, by howling Wolves, </l>
            <l>By gazing on the Starry Element, </l>
            <l>Or vain imaginary calculations; </l>
            <l>But from a setled wisdom in it self </l>
            <l>Which teacheth to be void of passion. </l>
            <l>To be Religious as the ravenous Wolf, </l>
            <l>Who loves the Lamb for hunger, and for prey; </l>
            <l>To threaten our inferiors with our looks; </l>
            <l>To flatter our Superiors at our need; </l>
            <l>To be an outward Saint, an inward Devill; </l>
            <l>These are the lectures that my Master reads. </l>
            <l>This Key commands all Chambers in the Court; </l>
            <l>Now on a sudain will I try his wit, </l>
            <l>I know my comming is unlook'd for. </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e100910">He opens the door and finds Lorenzo sleep a loft. </stage>
            <l>Nay sleep, Lorenzo, I will walk a while. </l>
            <l>As nature in the framing of the world, </l>
            <l>Ordain'd there should be nihil vacuum; </l>
            <l>Even so me thinks his wisdom should contrive, </l>
            <l>That all his Study should be full of wit, </l>
            <l>And every corner stuft with sentences? </l>
            <l>What's this? Plato? Aristotle? tush these are ordinary, </l>
            <l>It seems this is a note but newly written. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e101000">[He reads a note which he finds among his Books. </stage>
          <pb n="3" xml:id="eng000372-004-b"/>
          <p>Una arbusta non alit duos Erithicos; which being granted, the Roman Empire will not suffice Alphonsus King of Castile, and Richard Earl of Cornwall his competitor; thy wisdom teacheth thee to cleave to the strongest; Alphonsus is in possession, and therefore the strongest, but he is in hatred with the Electors, and men rather honour the Sunrising than the Sun going down. I marry this is argued like himself, and now me thinks he wakes. </p>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e101020">Lorenzo Riseth, and snatches at his sword which hung by his Bed side.] </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-lorenzo" xml:id="eng000372-e101030">
            <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
            <l>What are there thieves within the Emperour's Court? </l>
            <l>Villain thou dy'st; what mak'st thou in my Chamber? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e101060">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>How now Lorenzo, wilt thou slay thy Lord? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-lorenzo" xml:id="eng000372-e101080">
            <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
            <l>I do beseech your sacred Majesty to pardon me, </l>
            <l>I did not know your grace. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e101110">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Ly down Lorenzo, I will sit by thee, </l>
            <l>The ayr is sharp and piercing; tremble not, </l>
            <l>Had it been any other but our self, </l>
            <l>He must have been a villain and a thief. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-lorenzo" xml:id="eng000372-e101160">
            <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
            <l>Alas my Lord! what means your excellence, </l>
            <l>To walk by night in these so dangerous times? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e101190">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Have I not reason now to walk and watch, </l>
            <l>When I am compast with so many foes? </l>
            <l>They ward, they watch, they cast, and they conspire, </l>
            <l>To win confederate Princes to their aid, </l>
            <l>And batter down the Eagle from my creast. </l>
            <l>O, my Lorenzo, if thou help me not, </l>
            <l>Th' Imperial Crown is shaken from my head, </l>
            <l>And giv'n from me unto an English Earl. </l>
            <l>Thou knowest how all things stand as well as we, </l>
            <l>Who are our enemies, and who our friends, </l>
            <l>Who must be threatned, and who dallyed with, </l>
            <l>Who won by words, and who by force of arms; </l>
            <l>For all the honour I have done to thee. </l>
            <l>Now speak, and speak to purpose in the cause; </l>
            <l>Nay rest thy body, labour with thy brain, </l>
            <l>And of thy words my self will be the scribe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-lorenzo" xml:id="eng000372-e101360">
            <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
            <l>Why then my Lord, take Paper, Pen and Ink, </l>
            <l>Write first this maxim, it shall do you good. </l>
          </sp>
          <p>1. A Prince must be of the nature of the Lion and the Fox; but not the one without the other. </p>
          <pb n="4" xml:id="eng000372-005-a"/>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e101400">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>The Fox is subtil, but he wanteth force; </l>
            <l>The Lion strong, but scorneth policie; </l>
            <l>I'l imitate Lysander in this point, </l>
            <l>And where the Lion's hide is thin and scant, </l>
            <l>I'l firmly patch it with the Foxes fell. </l>
            <l>Let it suffice I can be both in one. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-lorenzo" xml:id="eng000372-e101470">
            <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
            <p>2. A Prince above all things must seem devout; but there is nothing so dangerous to his state, as to regard his promise or his oath. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e101490">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Tush, fear not me, my promise; are sound, </l>
            <l>But he that trusts them shall be sure to fail. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-lorenzo" xml:id="eng000372-e101520">
            <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
            <l>Nay my good Lord, but that I know your Majesty, </l>
            <l>To be a ready quickwitted Scholar, </l>
            <l>I would bestow a comment on the text. </l>
            <p>3. Trust not a reconciled friend; for good turns cannot blot out old grudges. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e101570">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Then must I watch the Palatine of the Rhein, </l>
            <l>I caus'd his Father to be put to death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-lorenzo" xml:id="eng000372-e101600">
            <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
            <l>Your Highness hath as little cause to trust </l>
            <l>The dangerous mighty Duke of Saxony; </l>
            <l>You know, you sought to banish him the Land; </l>
            <l>And as for Cullen, was not he the first </l>
            <l>That sent for Richard into Germany? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e101660">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>What's thy opinion of the other four? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e101680">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>That Bohemie neither cares for one nor other, </l>
            <l>But hopes this deadly strife between you twain, </l>
            <l>Will cast th' Imperial Crown upon his head. </l>
            <l>For Trier and Brandenberg, I think of them </l>
            <l>As simple men that wish the common good; </l>
            <l>And as for Mentz I need not censure him, </l>
            <l>Richard hath chain'd him in a golden bond, </l>
            <l>And sav'd his life from ignominious death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e101770">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Let it suffice, Lorenzo, that I know, </l>
            <l>When Churfurst Mentz was taken Prisoner, </l>
            <l>By young victorious Otho Duke of Brunschweige </l>
            <l>That Richard Earl of Cornwall did disburse </l>
            <l>The ransome of a King, a million, </l>
            <l>To save his life, and rid him out of bands, </l>
            <l>That sum of gold did fill the Brunschweige bags; </l>
            <l>But since my self have rain'd a golden shower. </l>
            <pb n="5" xml:id="eng000372-005-b"/>
            <l>Of bright Hungarian Ducates and Crusadoes, </l>
            <l>Into the private Coffers of the Bishop, </l>
            <l>The English Angels took their wings and fled; </l>
            <l>My crosses bless his Coffers, and plead for me, </l>
            <l>His Voice is mine, bought with ten tun of Gold, </l>
            <l>And at the meeting of the seven Electors, </l>
            <l>His Princely double-dealing holiness </l>
            <l>Will spoyl the English Emperour of hope. </l>
            <l>But I refer these matter to the sequel. </l>
            <l>Proceed Lorenzo forward to the next. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-lorenzo" xml:id="eng000372-e101960">
            <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
            <l>I'm glad your grace hath dealt so cunningly, </l>
            <p>With that victorious fickle minded Prelate; for in election his voice is first but to the next. </p>
            <l>4. 'Tis more safety for a Prince to be feared than loved. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e102000">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Love is an humour pleaseth him that loves; </l>
            <l>Let me be hated, so I please my self. </l>
            <l>Love is an humour mild and changeable; </l>
            <l>But fear er graves a reverence in the heart. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-lorenzo" xml:id="eng000372-e102050">
            <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
            <p>5. To keep an usurped Crown, a Prince must swear, forswear, poyson, murder, and commit all kind of villanies, provided it be cunningly kept from the eye of the world. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e102070">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>But my Lorenzo that's the hardest point, </l>
            <l>It is not for a Prince to execute, </l>
            <l>Physicians and Apothecaries must know, </l>
            <l>And service fear or Counsel-breaking bribes, </l>
            <l>Will from a Peasant in an hour extort </l>
            <l>Enough to overthrow a Monarchy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-lorenzo" xml:id="eng000372-e102140">
            <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
            <l>Therefore my Lord set down this sixt and last Article. </l>
            <l>6. Be alwaies jealous of him that knows your secrets, </l>
            <l>And therefore it behooves you credit few; </l>
            <l>And when you grow into the least suspect. </l>
            <l>With silent cunning must you cut them off. </l>
            <l>As for example, Iulio Lentulus, </l>
            <l>A most renowned Neapolitan, </l>
            <l>Gave me this Box of poyson, t'was not long </l>
            <l>But therewithall I sent him to his grave. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e102240">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>And what's the special vertue of the same? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-lorenzo" xml:id="eng000372-e102260">
            <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
            <l>That it is twenty days before it works. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e102280">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>But what is this? </l>
          </sp>
          <pb n="6" xml:id="eng000372-006-a"/>
          <sp who="#eng000372-lorenzo" xml:id="eng000372-e102300">
            <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
            <l>This an infection that kils suddainly; </l>
            <l>This but a toy to cast a man asleep. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e102330">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>How? bing drunk? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-lorenzo" xml:id="eng000372-e102350">
            <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
            <l>No, being smelt unto. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e102370">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Then smell Lorenzo, I did break thy sleep; </l>
            <l>And, for this time, this lecture shall suffice. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-lorenzo" xml:id="eng000372-e102400">
            <speaker>Loraen. </speaker>
            <l>What have you done my Lord? y'ave made me safe, </l>
            <l>For stirring hence these four and twenty hours. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e102430">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>I see this charms his senses sudainly. </l>
            <l>How now Lorenzo, half asleep already? </l>
            <l>Aeneas Pilot by the God of dreams, </l>
            <l>Was never lull'd into a sounder trance; </l>
            <l>And now Alphonsus over-read thy notes. </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e102490">[He reads. </stage>
            <l>These are already at my fingers ends, </l>
            <l>And lest the world should find this little Schedule, </l>
            <l>Thus will I rend the text, and after this, </l>
            <l>On my behaviour set so fair a gloss, </l>
            <l>That men shall take me for a Convertite; </l>
            <l>But some may think, I should forget my part, </l>
            <l>And have been over rash in renting it, </l>
            <l>To put them out of doubt I study sure, </l>
            <l>I'le make a backward repetition, </l>
            <l>In being jealous of my Counsel keepers, </l>
            <l>This is the poyson that kils sudainly, </l>
            <l>So didst thou unto Iulius Lentulus, </l>
            <l>And blood with blood must be requited thus. </l>
            <l>Now am I safe, and no man knows my Counsels, </l>
            <l>Churfurst of Mentz, if now thou play thy part, </l>
            <l>Erning thy gold with cunning workmanship, </l>
            <l>Upon the Bemish Kings ambition, </l>
            <l>Richard shall shamefully fail of his hope, </l>
            <l>And I with triumph keep my Emperie. </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e102690">Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e102700">Enter the King of Bohemia, the Bishops of Mentz, Collen, Trier, the Pallatine of the Rhein, The Duke of Saxon, The Marquess of Brandenburg. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e102710">
            <speaker>Bohe. </speaker>
            <l>Churfursts and Princes of the Election, </l>
            <l>Since by the adverse fortune of our age, </l>
            <l>The sacred and Imperial Majesty </l>
            <pb n="7" xml:id="eng000372-006-b"/>
            <l>Hath been usurp'd by open Tyranny, </l>
            <l>We the seven Pillars of the German Empire, </l>
            <l>To whom successively it doth belong </l>
            <l>To make election of our Emperours, </l>
            <l>Are here assembled to unite a new </l>
            <l>Unto her former strength and glorious type, </l>
            <l>Our half declining Roman Monarchy, </l>
            <l>And in that hope, I Henry King of Bohem, </l>
            <l>Churfurst and Sewer to the Emperour, </l>
            <l>Do take my seat next to the sacred throne. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e102850">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>Next seat belongs to Iulius Florius </l>
            <l>Archbishop of Mentz, Chancelor of Germany, </l>
            <l>By birth the Duke of fruitful Pomerland. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-palsgrave" xml:id="eng000372-e102890">
            <speaker>Pal. </speaker>
            <l>The next place in election longs to me, </l>
            <l>George Cassimirus Palsgrave of the Rhein, </l>
            <l>His Highness Taster, and upon my knee </l>
            <l>I vow a pure sincere innated zeal </l>
            <l>Unto my Country, and no wrested hate, </l>
            <l>Or private love shall blind mine intellect. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e102960">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>Brave Duke of Saxon, Dutchlands greatest hope, </l>
            <l>Stir now or never, let the Spanish tyrant, </l>
            <l>That hath dishonoured us, murder'd our Friends, </l>
            <l>And stain'd this seat with blood of innocents, </l>
            <l>At last be chastis'd with the Saxon sword, </l>
            <l>And may Albertus Archbishop of Collen, </l>
            <l>Chancelor of Gallia and the fourth Elector; </l>
            <l>Be thought unworthy of his place and birth, </l>
            <l>But he assist thee to his utmost power. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e103060">
            <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
            <l>Wisdom, not words, must be the soveraign salve, </l>
            <l>To search and heal these grievous festred wounds, </l>
            <l>And in that hope Augustus Duke of Saxon, </l>
            <l>Arch-Marshall to the Emperour take my place. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-trier" xml:id="eng000372-e103110">
            <speaker>Trier. </speaker>
            <l>The like doth Frederick Arch-Bishop of Trier, </l>
            <l>Duke of Lorrain, Chancelour of Italie. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e103140">
            <speaker>Bran. </speaker>
            <l>The seventh and last is Ioachim Carolus, </l>
            <l>Marquess of Brandenburg, overworn with age, </l>
            <l>Whose Office is to be the Treasurer; </l>
            <l>But Wars have made the Coffers like the Chair. </l>
            <l>Peace bringeth plenty, Wars bring poverty; </l>
            <l>Grant Heauens, this meeting may be to effect, </l>
            <l>Establish Peace, and cut off Tyrannie. </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e103220">
              <pb n="8" xml:id="eng000372-007-a"/>Enter the Empress Isabella King John's Daughter, </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e103230">
            <speaker>Empress. </speaker>
            <l>Pardon my bold intrusion mighty Churfursts, </l>
            <l>And let my words pierce deeply in your hearts. </l>
            <l>O! I beseech you on my bended Knees, </l>
            <l>I the poor miserable Empress, </l>
            <l>A stranger in this Land, unus'd to broyls, </l>
            <l>Wife to the one, and Sister to the other </l>
            <l>That are Competitors for Soveraignty; </l>
            <l>All that I pray, is, make a quiet end; </l>
            <l>Make Peace between my Husband and my Brother. </l>
            <l>O think how grief doth stand on either side, </l>
            <l>If either party chance to be miss; </l>
            <l>My Husband is my Husband; but my Brother, </l>
            <l>My heart doth melt to think he should miscarry. </l>
            <l>My Brother is my Brother; but my Husband, </l>
            <l>O how my joynts do shake fearing his wrong! </l>
            <l>If both should dye in these uncertain broyls. </l>
            <l>O me, why do I live to think upon't! </l>
            <l>Bear with my interrupted speeches Lords, </l>
            <l>Tears stop my voice, your wisdoms know my meaning. </l>
            <l>Alas I know my Brother Richard's heart </l>
            <l>Affects not Empire, he would rather choose </l>
            <l>To make return again to Palestine, </l>
            <l>And be a scourge unto the Infidels; </l>
            <l>As for my Lord, he is impatient, </l>
            <l>The more my grief, the lesser is my hope, </l>
            <l>Yet Princes thus he sends you word by me, </l>
            <l>He will submit himself to your award, </l>
            <l>And labour to amend what is amiss. </l>
            <l>All I have said, or can device to say, </l>
            <l>Is few words of great worth, Make unity, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e103540">
            <speaker>Bohe. </speaker>
            <l>Madam, that we have suffer'd you to kneel so long, </l>
            <l>Agrees not with your dignity nor ours; </l>
            <l>Thus we excuse it, when we once are set, </l>
            <l>In solemn Councel of Election, </l>
            <l>We may not rise till somewhat be concluded. </l>
            <l>So much for that; touching your earnest sure, </l>
            <l>Your Majestie doth know how it concerns us, </l>
            <l>Comfort your self, as we do hope the best; </l>
            <pb n="9" xml:id="eng000372-007-b"/>
            <l>But tell us, Madam, wher's your Husband now? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e103640">
            <speaker>Empress. </speaker>
            <l>I left him at his prayers, good my Lord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e103660">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>At prayers? Madam, that's a miracle. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-palsgrave" xml:id="eng000372-e103680">
            <speaker>Pall. </speaker>
            <l>Vndoubtedly your Highness did mistake; </l>
            <l>'Twas sure some Book of Conjuration; </l>
            <l>I think he never said pray'r in his life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e103720">
            <speaker>Empress. </speaker>
            <l>Ah me, my fear, I fear, will take effect; </l>
            <l>Your hate to him, and love unto my Brother, </l>
            <l>Will break my heart, and spoil th' Imperial peace. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e103760">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord of Saxon, and Prince Pallatine, </l>
            <l>This hard opinion yet is more than needs; </l>
            <l>But, gracious Madam, leave us to our selves. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e103800">
            <speaker>Empress. </speaker>
            <l>I go, and Heav'n that holds the Hearts of Kings, </l>
            <l>Direct your Counsels unto unity. </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e103830">Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e103840">
            <speaker>Bohe. </speaker>
            <l>Now to the depth of that we have in hand; </l>
            <l>This is the question, whether the King of Spain </l>
            <l>Shall still continue in the Royal throne, </l>
            <l>Or yield it up unto Plantagenet, </l>
            <l>Or we proceed unto a third Eelection. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e103900">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>E're such a viperous blood-thirsty Spaniard </l>
            <l>Shall suck the hearts of our Nobility, </l>
            <l>Th' Imperial Sword which Saxony doth bear, </l>
            <l>Shall be unsheath'd to War against the world. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-palsgrave" xml:id="eng000372-e103950">
            <speaker>Pall. </speaker>
            <l>My hate is more than words can testifie, </l>
            <l>Slave as he is he murdered my Father. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e103980">
            <speaker>Coll. </speaker>
            <l>Prince Richard is the Champion of the world, </l>
            <l>Learned, and mild, fit for the Government. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e104010">
            <speaker>Bohe. </speaker>
            <l>And what have we to do with Englishmen? </l>
            <l>They are divided from our Continent. </l>
            <l>But now that we may orderly proceed </l>
            <l>To our high Office of Election, </l>
            <l>To you my Lord of Mentz it doth belong, </l>
            <l>Having first voice in this Imperial Synod, </l>
            <l>To name a worthy man for Emperour. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e104090">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>It may be thought, most grave and reverend Princes, </l>
            <l>That in respect of divers sums of gold, </l>
            <l>Which Richard of meer charitable love, </l>
            <l>Not as a bribe, but as a deed of Alms, </l>
            <l>Disburs'd for me unto the Duke of Brunschweige, </l>
            <l>That I dare name no other man but he, </l>
            <pb n="10" xml:id="eng000372-008-a"/>
            <l>Or should I nominate an other Prince, </l>
            <l>Upon the contrary I may be thought </l>
            <l>A most ingrateful wretch unto my Friend; </l>
            <l>But private cause must yield to publick good; </l>
            <l>Therefore me thinks it were the fittest course, </l>
            <l>To choose the worthiest upon this Bench. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e104220">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>We are all Germans, why should we be yoak'd </l>
            <l>Either by Englishmen or Spaniards? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e104250">
            <speaker>Saxo. </speaker>
            <l>The Earl of Cornwall by a full consent </l>
            <l>Was sent for out of England. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e104280">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>Though he were, </l>
            <l>Our later thoughts are purer than our first, </l>
            <l>And to conclude, I think this end were best, </l>
            <l>Since we have once chosen him Emperour, </l>
            <l>That some great Prince of wisdom and of power, </l>
            <l>Whose countenance may overbear his pride, </l>
            <l>Be joynd in equal Government with Alphonsus. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e104360">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>Your Holiness hath soundly in few words </l>
            <l>Set down a mean to quiet all these broyls. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-trier" xml:id="eng000372-e104390">
            <speaker>Trier. </speaker>
            <l>So may we hope for peace if he amend; </l>
            <l>But shall Prince Richard then be joynd with him? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-palsgrave" xml:id="eng000372-e104420">
            <speaker>Pal. </speaker>
            <l>Why should your Highness ask that question? </l>
            <l>As if a Prince of so high Kingly Birth, </l>
            <l>Would live in couples with so base a Cur? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e104460">
            <speaker>Bohe. </speaker>
            <l>Prince Pallatine, such words do ill become thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e104480">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>He said but right, and call'd Dog a Dog. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e104500">
            <speaker>Bohe. </speaker>
            <l>His Birth is Princely. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e104520">
            <speaker>Saxo. </speaker>
            <l>His manners villanous, </l>
            <l>And vertuous Richard scorns so base a yoak. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e104550">
            <speaker>Bohe. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord of Saxon, give me leave to tell you, </l>
            <l>Ambition blinds your judgement in this case; </l>
            <l>You hope, if by your means Richard be Emperour, </l>
            <l>He, in requital of so great advancement, </l>
            <l>Will make the long-desired Marriage up </l>
            <l>Between the Prince of England and your Sister, </l>
            <l>And to that end Edward the Prince of Wales, </l>
            <l>Hath born his Uncle Company to Germany. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e104640">
            <speaker>Saxo. </speaker>
            <l>Why King of Bohem i'st unknown to thee, </l>
            <l>How oft the Saxons Sons have marryed Queens, </l>
            <l>And Daughters Kings, yea mightiest Emperours? </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000372-008-b"/>
            <l>If Edward like her beauty and behaviour, </l>
            <l>He'l make no question of her Princely Birth; </l>
            <l>But let that pass, I say, as erst I said, </l>
            <l>That vertuous Richard scorns so base a yoak. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e104720">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>If Richard scorn, some one upon this Bench, </l>
            <l>Whose power may overbear Alphonsus pride, </l>
            <l>Is to be named. What think you my Lords? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e104760">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>I think it was a mighty mass of Gold, </l>
            <l>That made your grace of this opinion. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e104790">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord of Saxony, you wrong me much, </l>
            <l>And know I highly scorn to take a bribe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-palsgrave" xml:id="eng000372-e104820">
            <speaker>Pal. </speaker>
            <l>I think you scorn indeed to have it known: </l>
            <l>But to the purpose, if it must be so, </l>
            <l>Who is the fittest man to joyn with him? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e104860">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>First with an Oxe to plough will I be yok'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e104880">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>The fittest is your grace in mine opinion. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e104900">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>I am content, to stay these mutinies, </l>
            <l>To take upon me what you do impose. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e104930">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>Why here's a tempest quickly overblown. </l>
            <l>God give you joy my Lord of half the Empire; </l>
            <l>For me I will not meddle in the matter, </l>
            <l>But warn your Majestie to have a care, </l>
            <l>And vigilant respect unto your person, </l>
            <l>I'l hie me home to fortifie my Towns, </l>
            <l>Not to offend, but to defend my self. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-palsgrave" xml:id="eng000372-e105010">
            <speaker>Pals. </speaker>
            <l>Ha' with you Cosin, and adieu my Lords, </l>
            <l>I am afraid this suddain knitted Peace, </l>
            <l>Will turn unto a tedious lasting War; </l>
            <l>Only thus much we do request you all, </l>
            <l>Deal honourably with the Earl of Cornwall, </l>
            <l>And so adieu. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e105080">Exeunt. Saxon. and Pals. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e105090">
            <speaker>Brand. </speaker>
            <l>I like not this strange Farewel of the Dukes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e105110">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>In all elections some are malcontent. </l>
            <l>It doth concern us now with speed to know, </l>
            <l>How the Competitors will like of this, </l>
            <l>And therefore you my Lord Archbishop of Trier, </l>
            <l>Impart this order of arbitrament </l>
            <l>Unto the Emperour, bid him be content, </l>
            <l>To stand content with half, or lose the whole. </l>
            <l>My Lord of Mentz go you unto Prince Richard, </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000372-009-a"/>
            <l>And tell him flatly here's no Crown, nor Empire </l>
            <l>For English Islanders; tell him, 'twere his best, </l>
            <l>To hie him home to help the King his Brother, </l>
            <l>Against the Earl of Leicester and the Barons. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e105240">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord of Mentz, sweet words will qualifie, </l>
            <l>When bitter tearms will adde unto his rage. </l>
            <l>'Tis no small hope that hath deceiv'd the Duke; </l>
            <l>Therefore be mild; I know an Englishman, </l>
            <l>Being flattered, is a Lamb, threatned, a Lion; </l>
            <l>Tell him his charges what so e're they are </l>
            <l>Shalbe repaid with treble vantages; </l>
            <l>Do this; we will expect their resolutions. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e105330">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>Brother of Collen, I entreat your grace </l>
            <l>To take this charge upon you in my stead; </l>
            <l>For why I shame to look him in the face. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e105370">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>Your Holiness shall pardon me in this, </l>
            <l>Had I the profit I would take the pains; </l>
            <l>With shame enough your Grace may bring the message. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e105410">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>Thus am I wrong'd, God knows, unguiltily. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e105430">
            <speaker>Brand. </speaker>
            <l>Then arm your countenance with innocency, </l>
            <l>And boldly do the message to the Prince; </l>
            <l>For no man else will be the messenger. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e105470">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>Why then I must, since ther's no remedy. </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e105490">[Exit. Mentz </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e105500">
            <speaker>Brand. </speaker>
            <l>If Heav'n that guides the hearts of mighty men, </l>
            <l>Do calm the Winds of these great Potentates, </l>
            <l>And make them like of this Arbitrament, </l>
            <l>Sweet Peace will tryumph thorough Christendom, </l>
            <l>And Germany shall bless this happy day. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e105560">Enter Alexander de Toledo the Page. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e105570">
            <speaker>Alexand. </speaker>
            <l>O me most miserable O my dear Father! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e105590">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>What means this passionate accent? what art thou </l>
            <l>That sounds these acclamations in our ears? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e105620">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Pardon me Princes, I have lost a Father, </l>
            <l>O me, the name of Father kils my heart. </l>
            <l>O! I shall never see my Father more, </l>
            <l>H'as tane his leave of me for age and age. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e105670">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>What was thy Father? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e105690">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Ah me I what was a not? </l>
            <pb n="13" xml:id="eng000372-009-b"/>
            <l>Noble, Rich, valiant, well-belov'd of all, </l>
            <l>The glory and the wisdom of his age, </l>
            <l>Chief Secretary to the Emperour. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e105740">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>Lorenzo de Toledo, is he dead? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e105760">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Dead, ay me dead, ay me my life is dead, </l>
            <l>Strangely this night bereft of breath and sense, </l>
            <l>And I, poor I, am comforted in nothing, </l>
            <l>But that the Emperour laments with me, </l>
            <l>As I exclame, so he, he rings his hands, </l>
            <l>And makes me mad to see his Majesty </l>
            <l>Excruciate himself with endless sorrow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e105840">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>The happiest news that ever I did hear; </l>
            <l>Thy Father was a villain murderer, </l>
            <l>Witty, not wise, lov'd like a Scorpion, </l>
            <l>Grown rich by the impoverishing of others, </l>
            <l>The chiefest cause of all these mutinies, </l>
            <l>And Caesar's tutor to all villanie. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e105910">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>None but an open lyar terms him so. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e105930">
            <speaker>Col. </speaker>
            <l>What Boy, so malepert? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e105950">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>Good Collen bear with him, it was his Father, </l>
            <l>Dutch-land is blessed in Lorenzo's Death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e105980">
            <speaker>Brand. </speaker>
            <l>Did never live a viler minded man. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e106000">Exeunt. Manet Alex. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e106010">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Nor King, nor Churfurst should be privileg'd </l>
            <l>To call me Boy, and rayl upon my Father, </l>
            <l>Were I wehrsafflig; but in Germany, </l>
            <l>A man must be a Boy at 40. years, </l>
            <l>And dares not draw his weapon at a Dog, </l>
            <l>Till being soundly box'd about the ears, </l>
            <l>His Lord and Master gird him with a sword; </l>
            <l>The time will come I shall be made a man, </l>
            <l>Till then I'l pine with thought of dire revenge, </l>
            <l>And live in Hell untill I take revenge. </l>
            <pb type="blank" xml:id="eng000372-010-a"/>
            <pb n="13" type="blank" xml:id="eng000372-010-b"/>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="eng000372-e106120">
          <pb n="14" xml:id="eng000372-011-a"/>
          <head>ACT. II. </head>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e106130">Enter Alphonsus, Richard Earl of Cornwall, Mentz, Trier, Prince Edward, Bohemia, Collen, Brandenburge, Attendants, and Pages with a sword. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e106140">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>Behold here come the Princes hand in hand, </l>
            <l>Pleas'd highly with the sentence as it seems. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e106170">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Princes and Pillars of the Monarchy, </l>
            <l>We do admire your wisdoms in this cause, </l>
            <l>And do accept the King of Bohemia, </l>
            <l>As worthy partner in the Government. </l>
            <l>Alas my Lords, I flatly now confess, </l>
            <l>I was alone too weak to underprop </l>
            <l>So great a burden as the Roman Empire, </l>
            <l>And hope to make you all admire the course </l>
            <l>That we intend in this conjunction. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e106270">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>That I was call'd from England with consent </l>
            <l>Of all the seven Electors to this place, </l>
            <l>Your selves best know, who wrote for me to come. </l>
            <l>'Twas no ambition mov'd me to the journey, </l>
            <l>But pitty of your half declining State; </l>
            <l>Which being likely now to be repayr'd, </l>
            <l>By the united force of these two Kings, </l>
            <l>I rest content to see you satisfied. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e106360">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>Brave Earl, wonder of Princely patience, </l>
            <l>I hope your grace will not mis-think of me, </l>
            <l>Who for your good, and for the Empires best, </l>
            <l>Bethought this means to set the world at Peace. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e106410">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>No doubt this means might have been thought upon, </l>
            <l>Although your Holiness had dy'd in Prison. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e106440">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>Peace, peace young Prince, you want experience; </l>
            <l>Your Unckle knows what cares accompany, </l>
            <l>And wait upon the Crowns of mightiest Kings, </l>
            <l>And glad he is that he hath shak'd it off. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e106490">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Heark in your ear my Lord, hear me one word, </l>
            <l>Although it were more than a million, </l>
            <l>Which these two Kings bestow'd upon your grace, </l>
            <l>Mine Unckle Richards million sav'd your life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e106540">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>Your were best to say, your Vnckle brib'd me then. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb n="15" xml:id="eng000372-011-b"/>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e106560">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>I do but say mine Vnckle sav'd your life, </l>
            <l>You know Count Mansfield your fellow Prisoner, </l>
            <l>Was by the Duke of Brunschwig put to death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e106600">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>You are a Child my Lord, your words are wind. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e106620">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>You are a Fox my Lord, and past a Child. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e106640">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord of Cornwall, your great forwardness, </l>
            <l>Crossing the Seas with aid of Englishmen, </l>
            <l>Is more than we can any way requite; </l>
            <l>But this your admirable patience, </l>
            <l>In being pleas'd with our election, </l>
            <l>Deserves far more than thanks can satisfie, </l>
            <l>In any thing command the Emperours, </l>
            <l>Who live to honour Richard Earl of Cornwall. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e106730">
            <speaker>Alpho. </speaker>
            <l>Our deeds shall make our Protestations good, </l>
            <l>Mean while, brave Princes, let us leave this place, </l>
            <l>And solace us with joy of this accord. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e106770">Enter Isabella the Empress, Hedewick the Duke of Saxon's Daughter, apparelled like Fortune, drawn on a Globe, with a Cup in her hand, wherein are Bay leaves, whereupon are written the lots. A train of Ladies following with Musick. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e106780">
            <speaker>Empress. </speaker>
            <l>To gratulate this unexpected Peace, </l>
            <l>This glorious league confirm'd against all hope, </l>
            <l>Joyful Isabella doth present this shew, </l>
            <l>Of Fortunes triumph, as the custom is </l>
            <l>At Coronation of our Emperours; </l>
            <l>If therefore every party be well pleas'd, </l>
            <l>And stand content with this arbitriment, </l>
            <l>Then daign to do as your Progenitors, </l>
            <l>And draw in sequence Lots for Offices. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e106880">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>This is an order here in Germany, </l>
            <l>For Princes to disport themselves with all, </l>
            <l>In sign their hearts so firmly are conjoyn'd, </l>
            <l>That they will bear all fortunes equally, </l>
            <l>And that the world may know I scorn no state, </l>
            <l>Or course of life to do the Empire good, </l>
            <l>I take my chance: My Fortune is to be the Forrester, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e106960">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>If we want Venson either red or fallow, </l>
            <pb n="16" xml:id="eng000372-012-a"/>
            <l>Wild bore or bear, you must be fin'd my Lord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e106990">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>The Emperour's Taster I. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e107010">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>Your Majesty hath been tasted to so oft, </l>
            <l>That you have need of small instructions. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e107040">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>I am the bowr, Sister what is my charge? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e107060">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>Tyr'd like a Carter, and a Clownish Bowr, </l>
            <l>To bring a load of Wood into the Kitchin. </l>
            <l>Now for my self, Faith I am Chamber Maid, </l>
            <l>I know my charge; proceed unto the next. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e107110">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Prince Edward standeth melancholy still, </l>
            <l>Please it your Grace, my Lord, to draw your lot. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e107140">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>Nephew you must be solemn with the sad, </l>
            <l>And given to myrth in sportful Company, </l>
            <l>The German Princes when they will be lusty, </l>
            <l>Shake of all cares, and Clowns and they are Fellows. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e107190">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Sweet Aunt, I do not know the Country guise, </l>
            <l>Yet would be glad to learn all fashions. </l>
            <l>Since I am next, good Fortune be my guide. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e107230">
            <speaker>Brand. </speaker>
            <l>A most ingenuous countenance hath this Prince, </l>
            <l>Worthy to be the King of England's Heir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e107260">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Be it no disparagement to you my Lords, </l>
            <l>I am your Emperour. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e107290">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Sound trumpets, God save the Emperour. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e107310">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>The world could never worse have fitted me, </l>
            <l>I am not old enough to be the Cook. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e107340">
            <speaker>Empress. </speaker>
            <l>If you be Cook, there is no remedy </l>
            <l>But you must dress one Mess of meat you self. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e107370">
            <speaker>Branden. </speaker>
            <l>I am Physician. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-trier" xml:id="eng000372-e107390">
            <speaker>Trier. </speaker>
            <l>I am Secretary. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e107410">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>I am the Jester. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e107430">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>O excellent! is your Holiness the Vice? </l>
            <l>Fortune hath fitted you y'faith my Lord, </l>
            <l>You'l play the Ambodexter cunningly. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e107470">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>Your Highness is to bitter in your Jests. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e107490">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Come hither Alexander, to comfort thee, </l>
            <l>After the death of thy beloved Father, </l>
            <l>Whose life was deer unto his Emperour, </l>
            <l>Thou shalt make one in this solemnity, </l>
            <l>Yet e're thou draw, my self will honour thee, </l>
            <l>And as the custom is make thee a man. </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000372-012-b"/>
            <l>Stand stiff Sir Boy, now com'st thou to thy tryal; </l>
            <l>Take this, and that, and therewithall this Sword; </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e107580">[He gives Alexander a Box on the ear or two. </stage>
            <l>If while thou live, thou ever take the like, </l>
            <l>Of me, or any man, I here pronounce </l>
            <l>Thou art a schelm, otherwise a man. </l>
            <l>Now draw thy lot, and Fortune be thy speed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e107630">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Vnckle I pray why did be box the fellow? </l>
            <l>Foul lubber as he is, to take such blows. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e107660">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>Thus do the Princes make their Pages men. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e107680">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>But that is strange to make a man with blows. </l>
            <l>We say in England that he is a man, </l>
            <l>That like a man dare meet his enemy, </l>
            <l>And in my judgement 'tis the sounder tryal. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e107730">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Fortune hath made me Marshall of the tryumphs. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e107750">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Now what remains? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e107770">
            <speaker>Emperess. </speaker>
            <l>That Fortune draw her lot. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e107790">She opens it, and gives it to the Emperess to read. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e107800">
            <speaker>Empress. </speaker>
            <l>Sound trumpets, Fortune is your Emperess. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e107820">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>This happens right: for Fortune will be Queen. </l>
            <l>Now Emperour you must unmask her face, </l>
            <l>And tell us how you like your Emperess, </l>
            <l>In my opinion England breeds no fairer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e107870">
            <speaker>Bohe. </speaker>
            <l>Fair Hedewick the Duke of Saxons daughter, </l>
            <l>Young Prince of England, you are bravely match'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e107900">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Tell me sweet Aunt, is that this Saxon Princess, </l>
            <l>Whose beauties fame made Edward cross the Seas? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e107930">
            <speaker>Emperess. </speaker>
            <l>Nephew, it is; hath fame been prodigal, </l>
            <l>Or over sparing in the Princess praise? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e107960">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Fame I accuse thee, thou did'st niggardize, </l>
            <l>And faintly sound my loves perfections. </l>
            <l>Great Lady Fortune, and fair Emperess, </l>
            <l>Whom chance this day hath thrown into my arms, </l>
            <l>More welcome than the Roman Emperess. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e108020">[Edward kisses her. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hedewick" xml:id="eng000372-e108030">
            <speaker>Hede. </speaker>
            <l>See doch, dass ist hier kein gebrauch, </l>
            <l>Mein Got ist dass dir Englisch manier, dass dich. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e108060">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>What meaneth this? why chafes my Emperess? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e108080">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Now by my troth, I did expect this jest, </l>
            <l>Prince Edward us'd his Country fashion. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e108110">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>I am an Englishman, why should I not? </l>
          </sp>
          <pb n="18" xml:id="eng000372-013-a"/>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e108130">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>Fy Nephew Edward, here in Germany </l>
            <l>To kiss a Maid, a fault intollerable. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e108160">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <p>Why should not German Maids be kist aswell as others? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e108180">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>Nephew, because you did not know the fashion, </l>
            <l>And want the language to excuse your self, </l>
            <l>I'l be your spokes-man to your Emperess. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e108220">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Excuse it thus: I like the first so well, </l>
            <l>That tell her, she shall chide me twice as much </l>
            <l>For such an other; nay tell her more than so, </l>
            <l>I'l double kiss on kiss, and give her leave </l>
            <l>To chide and braul, and cry ten thousand dass dich, </l>
            <l>And make her weary of her fretting humour, </l>
            <l>E're I be weary of my kissing vein, </l>
            <l>Dass dich a Iungfraw angry for a kiss. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e108310">
            <speaker>Empress. </speaker>
            <l>Nephew, she thinks you mock her in her mirth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e108330">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>I think the Princes make a scorn of me. </l>
            <l>If any do, I'l prove it with my Sword, </l>
            <l>That English Courtship leaves it from the world. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e108370">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>The pleasant'st accident that I have seen. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e108390">
            <speaker>Bran. </speaker>
            <l>Me thinks the Prince is chaf'd as well as she. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e108410">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l xml:lang="ger">Gnediges frawlin. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hedewick" xml:id="eng000372-e108430">
            <speaker>Hede. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Dass dich, mast ich arme kindt zu schanden gemacht werden. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e108450">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l xml:lang="ger">Dass dich I have kist as good as you, </l>
            <l>Pray Unckle tell her; if she mislike the kiss, </l>
            <l>I'l take it off agen with such an other. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e108490">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l xml:lang="ger">Ey Lirbes frawlin nim es all fur gutti </l>
            <l xml:lang="ger">Es ist die Englisch manier Und gebrauche. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hedewick" xml:id="eng000372-e108520">
            <speaker>Hede. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Ewer gnaden weissts woll es ist mir ein grosse schande. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e108540">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Good Aunt teach me so much Dutch to ask her pardon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e108560">
            <speaker>Empress. </speaker>
            <l xml:lang="ger">Say so: Gnediges frawlin vergebet mirs, ich wills nimmermehr thuen, </l>
            <l>Then kiss your hand three times upsy Dutch. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e108590">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Ich wills nimmermehr thuen, if I understand it, right, </l>
            <l>That's as much to say, as I'l do so no more. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e108620">
            <speaker>Empr. </speaker>
            <l>True Nephew. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e108640">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <p>Nay Aunt pardon me I pray, I hope to kiss her many thousand times, </p>
            <pb n="19" xml:id="eng000372-013-b"/>
            <p>And shall I go to her like a great Boy, and say I'l do so no more. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e108670">
            <speaker>Empress. </speaker>
            <l>I pray Cosin say as I tell you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e108690">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Gnediges frawlin vergebet mirss ich wills nimmermehr thuen. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e108710">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l xml:lang="ger">For wahr kein schandt. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hedewick" xml:id="eng000372-e108730">
            <speaker>Hedew. </speaker>
            <l xml:lang="ger">Gnediger hochgeborner Furst vndt herr </l>
            <l xml:lang="ger">Wan ich konte so vil englisch sprechen ich wolt ewer Gnaden. </l>
            <l xml:lang="ger">Fur wahr ein filtz geben, ich hoffe aber ich soll etnmahl </l>
            <l xml:lang="ger">So viel lernen dass Die mich verstrhen soll. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e108780">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>What says she? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e108800">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>O excellent young Prince look to your self, </l>
            <l>She swears she'l learn some English for your sake, </l>
            <l>To make you understand her when she chides. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e108840">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>I'l teach her English, she shall teach me Dutch, <foreign xml:lang="ger">Gnediges frawlin, &amp;c.</foreign>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e108860">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>It is great pitty that the Duke of Saxon, </l>
            <l>Is absent at this joyful accident, </l>
            <l>I see no reason if his Grace were here, </l>
            <l>But that the Marriage might be solemniz'd, </l>
            <l>I think the Prince of Wales were well content. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e108920">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>I left sweet England to none other end; </l>
            <l>And though the Prince her Father be not here, </l>
            <l>This Royal presence knows his mind in this. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e108960">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>Since you do come so roundly to the purpose, </l>
            <l>'Tis time for me to speak, the Maid is mine, </l>
            <l>Giv'n freely by her Father unto me, </l>
            <l>And to the end these broyls may have an end, </l>
            <l>I give the Father's interest and mine own, </l>
            <l>Unto my Nephew Edward Prince of Wales. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e109030">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>A Jewel of incomparable price, </l>
            <l>Your Majesty hath here bestowed on me, </l>
            <l>How shall I ask her if she be content? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e109070">
            <speaker>Empr. </speaker>
            <l>Say thus, <foreign xml:lang="ger">ist ewer gnaden woll hiemit zufrieden</foreign>. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e109090">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l xml:lang="ger">Ist ewer Gnaden woll hiemit zufrieden. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hedewick" xml:id="eng000372-e109110">
            <speaker>Hede. </speaker>
            <l xml:lang="ger">Wass ihr durleichtigkeit dass will dass will mein vattter vndt </l>
            <l xml:lang="ger">Wass mein vatter will darmit muss ich zufrieden sein. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e109140">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>It is enough, she doth confirm the match; </l>
            <pb n="20" xml:id="eng000372-014-a"/>
            <l>We will dispatch a Post unto her Father, </l>
            <l>On Sunday shall the Revels and the Wedding, </l>
            <l>Be both solemnized with mutual joy. </l>
            <l>Sound trumpets, each one look unto his charge, </l>
            <l>For preparation of the Festivals. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e109210">Exeunt. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e109220">Manent Alphonsus and Alexander. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e109230">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Come hither Alexander, thy Fathers joy. </l>
            <l>If tears and sighs, and deep-fetcht deadly groans, </l>
            <l>Could serve t' evert inexorable fate, </l>
            <l>Divine Lorenzo, whom in life my heart, </l>
            <l>In death my soul and better part adores, </l>
            <l>Had to thy comfort and his Prince's honour, </l>
            <l>Surviv'd, and drawn this day this breath of life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e109310">
            <speaker>Alexan. </speaker>
            <l>Dread Caesar, prostrate on my bended Knee, </l>
            <l>I thank your Majesty for all favours shewn </l>
            <l>To my deceased Father and my self. </l>
            <l>I must confess, I spend but bootless tears, </l>
            <l>Yet cannot bridle nature, I must weep, </l>
            <l>Or heart will break with burden of my thoughts, </l>
            <l>Nor am I yet so young or fond withall, </l>
            <l>Causless to spend my gall, and fret my heart, </l>
            <l>'Tis not that he is dead, for all must dye; </l>
            <l>But that I live to hear his lives reproach. </l>
            <l>O sacred Emperour, these ears have heard, </l>
            <l>What no Sons ears can unrevenged hear, </l>
            <l>The Princes all of them, but specially, </l>
            <l>The Prince Elector Archbishop of Collen, </l>
            <l>Revil'd him by the names of murderer, </l>
            <l>Arch villain, robber of the Empires fame, </l>
            <l>And Caesars tutor in all wickedness, </l>
            <l>And with a general voice applaus'd his death, </l>
            <l>As for a special good to Christendome. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e109510">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Have they not reason to applaud the deed </l>
            <l>Which they themselves have plotted? ah my Boy, </l>
            <l>Thou art too young to dive into their drifts. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e109550">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Yet old enough I hope to be reveng'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e109570">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>What wilt thou do, or whither wilt thou run? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e109590">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Headlong to bring them death, then dye my self. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e109610">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>First hear the reason why I do mistrust them. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb n="21" xml:id="eng000372-014-b"/>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e109630">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>They had no reason for my Father's death, </l>
            <l>And I scorn reason till they all be dead. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e109660">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Thou wilt not scorn my Counsel in revenge? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e109680">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>My rage admits no Counsel but revenge. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e109700">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>First let me tell thee whom I do mistrust. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e109720">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Your Highness said you did mistrust them all. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e109740">
            <speaker>Alpho. </speaker>
            <l>Yea Alexander, all of them, and more than all, </l>
            <l>My most especiall neerest dearest friends. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e109770">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>All 's one to me, for know thou Emperour, </l>
            <l>Were it thy Father, Brother, or thine Empress, </l>
            <l>Yea were 't thy self, that did'st conspire his death, </l>
            <l>This fatal hand should take away thy life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e109820">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Spoke like a Son, worthy so dear a Father. </l>
            <l>Be still and hearken, I will tell thee all, </l>
            <l>The Duke of Saxon </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e109860">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>O, I thought no less. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e109880">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Suppress thy choler, hearken to the rest. </l>
            <l>Saxon I say so wrought with flattering Mentz, </l>
            <l>Mentz with Bohemia, Trier, and Brandenburg, </l>
            <l>For Collen and the Palsgrave of the Rhein </l>
            <l>Were principals with Saxon in the Plot, </l>
            <l>That in a general meeting to that purpose, </l>
            <l>The seven selected Emperours electors, </l>
            <l>Most hainously concluded of the murder; </l>
            <l>The reason why they doom'd him unto death, </l>
            <l>Was his deep wisdom and sound policy; </l>
            <l>Knowing while he did live my state was firm, </l>
            <l>He being dead my hope must dye with him. </l>
            <l>Now Alexander will we be reveng'd </l>
            <l>Upon this wicked whore of Babylon, </l>
            <l>This hideous monster with the seven-fold head: </l>
            <l>We must with cunning level at the heart, </l>
            <l>With pierc'd and perisht all the body dyes: </l>
            <l>Or strike we off her heads by one and one, </l>
            <l>Behooveth us to use dexterity, </l>
            <l>Lest she do trample us under her feet, </l>
            <l>And tryumph in our honours overthrow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e110100">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Mad and amazd to hear this tragicke doom, </l>
            <l>I do subscribe unto your sound advice. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e110130">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Then hear the rest; these seven gave but she sentence, </l>
            <pb n="22" xml:id="eng000372-015-a"/>
            <l>A neerer hand put it in execution, </l>
            <l>And but I lov'd Lorenzo as my life, </l>
            <l>I never would betray my dearest Wife. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e110180">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>What? what the Empress accessary to? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e110200">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>What cannot kindred do? her Brother Richard, </l>
            <l>Hoping thereby to be an Emperour, </l>
            <l>Gave her a dram that sent him to his grave. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e110240">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>O my poor Father, wert thou such an eye-sore, </l>
            <l>That 9. the greatest Princes of the earth </l>
            <l>Must be confederate in thy tragedy? </l>
            <l>But why do I respect their mightiness, </l>
            <l>Who did not once respect my Fathers life? </l>
            <l>Your Majesty may take it as you please, </l>
            <l>I'l be reveng'd upon your Emperess, </l>
            <l>On English Richard, Saxon, and the Palsgrave, </l>
            <l>On Bohem, Collen, Mentz, Trier, and Brandenburg, </l>
            <l>If that the Pope of Rome himself were one </l>
            <l>In this confederacy, undaunted I. </l>
            <l>Amidst the College of his Cardinals, </l>
            <l>Would press, and stab him in St. Peters chair, </l>
            <l>Though clad in all his Pontificalibus. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e110390">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Why Alexander? do'st thou speak to me </l>
            <l>As if thou didst mistrust my forwardness? </l>
            <l>No, thou shalt know my love to him was such, </l>
            <l>And in my heart I have proscrib'd them all, </l>
            <l>That had to do in this conspiracy. </l>
            <l>The bands of Wedlock shall not serve her turn, </l>
            <l>Her fatal lot is cast among the rest, </l>
            <l>And to conclude, my soul doth live in Hell </l>
            <l>Till I have set my foot upon their necks, </l>
            <l>That gave this spur of sorrow to my heart; </l>
            <l>But with advice it must be managed, </l>
            <l>Not with a head-long rage as thou intend'st, </l>
            <l>Nor in a moment can it be perform'd, </l>
            <l>This work requires long time, dissembling looks, </l>
            <l>Commixt with undermining actions, </l>
            <l>Watching advantages to execute. </l>
            <l>Our foes are mighty, and their number great, </l>
            <l>It therefore follows that our Strangems </l>
            <l>Must branch forth into manifold deceits, </l>
            <pb n="23" xml:id="eng000372-015-b"/>
            <l>Endless devices, bottomless conclusions. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e110600">
            <speaker>Alexan. </speaker>
            <l>What by your Majesty is prescrib'd to me, </l>
            <l>That will I execute or dye the death. </l>
            <l>I am content to suck my sorrows up, </l>
            <l>And with dull patience will attend the time, </l>
            <l>Gaping for every opportunity </l>
            <l>That may present the least occasion; </l>
            <l>Although each minute multiply mine anguish, </l>
            <l>And to my view present a thousand forms </l>
            <l>Of senseless bodies in my Fathers shape, </l>
            <l>Yelling with open throat for just revenge. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e110710">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Content thy self, he shall not cry in vain, </l>
            <l>I have already plotted Richards death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e110740">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>That hath my Fathers sacred Ghost inspir'd, </l>
            <l>O tell me, shall I stab him suddainly? </l>
            <l>The time seems long, till I be set a work. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e110780">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Thou knowest in griping at our lots to day, </l>
            <l>It was Prince Richard's hap to be the bowr; </l>
            <l>So that his Office is to drive the Cart, </l>
            <l>And bring a load of Wood into the Kitchin. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e110830">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>O excellent, your Grace being Forester, </l>
            <l>As in the thicket he doth load the Cart, </l>
            <l>May shoot him dead, as if he were a Deer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e110870">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>No Alexander, that device were shallow, </l>
            <l>Thus it must be, there are two very howrs </l>
            <l>Appointed for to help him in the Wood, </l>
            <l>These must be brib'd or cunningly seduc'd, </l>
            <l>Instead of helping him to murder him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e110930">
            <speaker>Ale. </speaker>
            <l>Verbum satis sapienti, it is enough, </l>
            <l>Fortune hath made me Marshal of the sports </l>
            <l>I hope to Marshal them to th' Devils Feast. </l>
            <l>Plot you the rest, this will I execute, </l>
            <l>Dutch bowrs as towsandt schelms and gold to tempt them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e110990">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>'Tis right, about it then, but cunningly. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e111010">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Else let me lose that good opinion </l>
            <l>Which by your Highness I desire to hold, </l>
            <l>By Letters which I'l strew within the Wood, </l>
            <l>I'l undermine the bowrs to murder him, </l>
            <l>Nor shall they know who set them so a work, </l>
            <l>Like a familiar will I fly about, </l>
            <pb n="24" xml:id="eng000372-016-a"/>
            <l>And nimbly haunt their Ghosts in every nook. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e111090">Exit. Manet Alphonsus. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e111100">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>This one nayl helps to drive the other out, </l>
            <l>I slew the Father, and bewitch the Son, </l>
            <l>With power of words to be the instrument </l>
            <l>To rid my foes with danger of his life. </l>
            <l>How easily can subtil age intice, </l>
            <l>Such credulous young novices to their death? </l>
            <l>Huge wonders will Alphonsus bring to pass, </l>
            <l>By the mad mind of this enraged Boy; </l>
            <l>Even they which think themselves my greatest friends, </l>
            <l>Shall fall by this deceit, yea my Arch-enemies </l>
            <l>Shall turn to be my chief confederates. </l>
            <l>My sollitary walks may breed suspect, </l>
            <l>I'le therefore give my self to Companie, </l>
            <l>As I intended nothing out these sports, </l>
            <l>Yet hope to send most actors in this Pageant, </l>
            <l>To Revel it with Rhadamant in Hell. </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e111270">Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e111280">Enter Richard Earl of Cornwall like a Clown. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e111290">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>How far is Richard now unlike the man </l>
            <l>The crost the Seas to win an Emperie? </l>
            <l>But as I plod it like a plumper Bowr, </l>
            <l>To fetch in Fewel for the Kitchin fire, </l>
            <l>So every one in his vocation, </l>
            <l>Labours to make the pastimes plausible; </l>
            <l>My Nephew Edward jets it through the Court, </l>
            <l>With Princess Hedewick Empress of his Fortune, </l>
            <l>The demy Caesar in his hunters suit, </l>
            <l>Makes all the Court to Ring with Horns and Hounds, </l>
            <l>Collen the Cook bestirs him in the Kitchin; </l>
            <l>But that which joyes me most in all these sports, </l>
            <l>Is Mentz, to see how he is made an Ass? </l>
            <l>The common scorn and by-word of the Court; </l>
            <l>And every one to be the same he seems, </l>
            <l>Seems to forget to be the same he is. </l>
            <l>Yet to my roabs I cannot suit my mind, </l>
            <l>Nor with my habit shake dishonour off, </l>
            <l>The seven Electors promis'd me the Empire, </l>
            <l>The perjur'd Bishop Mentz did swear no less, </l>
            <pb n="25" xml:id="eng000372-016-b"/>
            <l>Yet I have seen it shar'd before my face, </l>
            <l>While my best friends do hide their heads for shame; </l>
            <l>I bear a shew of outward full content, </l>
            <l>But grief thereof hath almost kill'd my heart. </l>
            <l>Here rest thee Richard, think upon a mean, </l>
            <l>To end thy life, or to repair thine honour, </l>
            <l>And vow never to see fair Englands bounds, </l>
            <l>Till thou in Aix be Crowned Emperour. </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e111580">Enter two Bowrs. </stage>
            <l>Holla, me thinks there cometh Company, </l>
            <l>The Bowrs I troe that come to hew the Wood, </l>
            <l>Which I must carry to the Kitchen Fire, </l>
            <l>I'le lye a while and listen to their talk. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e111630">Enter Hans and Jerick two Dutch Bowrs. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-jerick" xml:id="eng000372-e111640">
            <speaker>Je. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Kom hier hans wore bist dow, warumb bist dow so trawrick? biss frolick kan wel gelt verdienen, wir will ihn bey potts tawsandt todt schlagen. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hans" xml:id="eng000372-e111660">
            <speaker>Hans. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Lat mich die brieffe sehen. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e111680">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <p>Me thinks they talk of murdering some body, I'l listen more. </p>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e111700">Reads the Letter. </stage>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Hans vnd Ierick, mein liebe freinde, ich bitte lasset es bey euch bleiben in geheim, vnd schlaget den Engellander zu todt. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e111720">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <p>What's that? Hans vnd Ierick my good friend, I pray be secret and murder the Englishman. </p>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e111740">Jerick reads. </stage>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Hear weiter, den er ist kein bowre nicht, er ist ein Iuncker, vnd hatt viel gelt vnd kleinothen bey sich. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e111760">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <p>For he is no Bowre but a Gentleman, and hath store of Gold and Jewels by him. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-jerick" xml:id="eng000372-e111780">
            <speaker>Jeric.. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Noch weiter: ihr solt solche gelegenheit nicht versahmen, vnd wan ihr gethan habet, ich will euch sagen, was ich fur ein guter Rarl bin der euch raht gegeben habe. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e111800">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <p>Skip not this opportunity, and when you have done, I will discover who gave you the Counsel. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-jerick" xml:id="eng000372-e111820">
            <speaker>Jerick. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Wat sagst dow wilt dow es thun? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hans" xml:id="eng000372-e111840">
            <speaker>Hans. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Wat will ich nich fur gelt thun? see potts tausendt, dar ist er. </p>
          </sp>
          <pb n="26" xml:id="eng000372-017-a"/>
          <sp who="#eng000372-jerick" xml:id="eng000372-e111860">
            <speaker>Jerick. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Ia, bey potts tausends slapperment, er ists, holla guter morgen, gluck zu Iuncker. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hans" xml:id="eng000372-e111880">
            <speaker>Hans. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Iuncker, der divell he is ein bowre! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e111900">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Dow bist ein schelm, weich von mir. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-jerick" xml:id="eng000372-e111920">
            <speaker>Jerick. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Holla, holla, bist dow so hoffertick? Iuncker bowre, kompt hier, oder dieser vnd jenner selleuch holen. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e111940">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Ich bien ein Furst, bried mich nicht ihr schelms, ihr verrahters. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-jerick #eng000372-hans" xml:id="eng000372-e111960">
            <speaker>Bath. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Sla to, fla to, wir will yow furstlick tractieren. </p>
            <p>Richard having nothing in his hand but his whip, defends himself a while, and then fall's down, as if he were dead: </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e111990">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">O Got, nimb meine seele in deine hande. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-jerick" xml:id="eng000372-e112010">
            <speaker>Jerick. </speaker>
            <p>O excellent, hurtick he is todt, he is todt. </p>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Lat vns see wat he hat for gelt bey sich, holla hier is all enough all satt, dor is for dich, and dor is for mich, vnd ditt will ich darto haben: </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e112040">Ierick puts the chain about his neck. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hans" xml:id="eng000372-e112050">
            <speaker>Hans. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">How so Hans Narhals, geue mir die kette hier. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-jerick" xml:id="eng000372-e112070">
            <speaker>Jerick. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Ia ein dreck, dit kett stehet hupsch vmb mein hals, ditt will ich tragen. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hans" xml:id="eng000372-e112090">
            <speaker>Hans. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Dat dich potts velten leiden, dat soltu nimmermehr thun dow schelm. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-jerick" xml:id="eng000372-e112110">
            <speaker>Jerick. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Wat solt dow mich schelm heiten nimb dat. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hans" xml:id="eng000372-e112130">
            <speaker>Hans. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Dat dich hundert tonnen divells, harr ich will dich lernen. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-jerick" xml:id="eng000372-e112150">
            <speaker>Jerick. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Wiltud hawen oder stechen? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hans" xml:id="eng000372-e112170">
            <speaker>Hans. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Ich will redlich hawen; </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-jerick" xml:id="eng000372-e112190">
            <speaker>Jerick. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Nun wollan, dor ist mein ruck, sla to. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e112210">They must have axes made for the nonst to fight withall, and while one strikes, the other holds his back without defence. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hans" xml:id="eng000372-e112220">
            <speaker>Hans. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Nimb dow das, vnd dar hast mein ruck. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-jerick" xml:id="eng000372-e112240">
            <speaker>Jerick.. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Nach amahl: O excellent, ligst dow dar, nun will ich alles haben, gelt vnd kett, vnd alle mit einander, O hurtig, frisch-vp lustig, nun bin ich ein hurtig Iuncker. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e112260">Richard rises up again and snatcheth up the fellows hatchet that was slain. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e112270">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <p>N Hercules contra duos, yet pollicy hath gone beyond them both. </p>
            <pb n="27" xml:id="eng000372-017-b"/>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Du hudler schelm, morder, kehre dich, feestu mich? gebe mir die kett vnd gelt wieder; </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-jerick" xml:id="eng000372-e112300">
            <speaker>Jerick. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Wat bistu wieder labendig worden, so mus ich meren, wat wiltu stechen oder hawen? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e112320">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">So will ich machen du schelm. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-jerick" xml:id="eng000372-e112340">
            <speaker>Jerick. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Harr, harr, bistu ein redlich karle, so fight redlich, O ich sterb, ich sterb, lat mich leben! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e112360">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Sagt mir dan wer hatt die brieffe geschrieben? </p>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Lie nicht sondern sagt die warheit: </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-jerick" xml:id="eng000372-e112390">
            <speaker>Jerick. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">O mein fromer, guter, edler, gestrenger Iuncker, dar ist dat gelt vnd kett wieder, yow soll alles haben, aber wer hatt die brieffe geschrieben, dat wet ich bey meiner seele nicht. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e112410">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l xml:lang="ger">Lig dor still, still ich sag. </l>
            <l>The villain swears, and deeply doth protest </l>
            <l>He knows not who incited them to this, </l>
            <l>And as it seems the scrowl imports no less. </l>
            <l xml:lang="ger">So sterb du mir schelm. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-jerick" xml:id="eng000372-e112470">
            <speaker>Jerick. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">O ich sterb, awe, awe, awe dat dich der divell hole! </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e112490">As Richard kils the Bowr. Enter Saxon and the Palsgrave. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e112500">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Fy dich an loser schelm, hastu dein gesellen todt geschlagen? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-palsgrave" xml:id="eng000372-e112520">
            <speaker>Palsgr. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Last vs den schelmen angreiffen. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e112540">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>Call you me shelme how dare you then </l>
            <l>Being Princes offer to lay hands on me? </l>
            <l>That is the Hangmans Office here in Dutch-land. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e112580">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>But this is strange, our Bours can speak no English, </l>
            <l>What bistum more than a damn'd murderer? </l>
            <l>That thou art so much we are witnesses. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e112620">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>Can then this habit alter me so much, </l>
            <l>That I am call'd a villain by my friends? </l>
            <l>Or shall I dare once to suspect your graces, </l>
            <l>That for you could not make me Emperour, </l>
            <l>Pittying my sorrow through mine honour lost, </l>
            <l>You set these slaves to rid me of my life, </l>
            <l>Yet far be such a thought from Richard's heart. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb n="28" xml:id="eng000372-018-a"/>
          <sp who="#eng000372-palsgrave" xml:id="eng000372-e112700">
            <speaker>Pals. </speaker>
            <l>How now? what do I hear Prince Richard speak? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e112720">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>The same: but wonder that he lives to speak. </l>
            <l>And had not policy helpt above strength, </l>
            <l>These sturdy swains had rid me of my life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e112760">
            <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
            <l>Far be it from your Grace for to suspect vs. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e112780">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>Alas, I know not whom I should suspect; </l>
            <l>But yet my heart cannot misdoubt your Graces? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e112810">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>How came your Highness into this apparrel? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e112830">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>We as the manner is drew lots for Offices, </l>
            <l>My hap was hardest to be made a Carter, </l>
            <l>And by this letter which some villain wrote, </l>
            <l>I was betray'd, here to be murdered; </l>
            <l>But Heav'n which doth defend the Innocent, </l>
            <l>Arm'd me with strength and policy together, </l>
            <l>That I escap'd out of their treacherous snare. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-palsgrave" xml:id="eng000372-e112910">
            <speaker>Pals. </speaker>
            <l>Were it well sounded, I dare lay my life, </l>
            <l>The Spanish tyrant knew of this conspiracie; </l>
            <l>Therefore the better to dive into the depth </l>
            <l>Of this most devillish murderous complot, </l>
            <l>As also secretly to be beholders, </l>
            <l>Of the long-wisht for wedding of your daughter, </l>
            <l>We will disrobe these bowrs of their apparrel, </l>
            <l>Clapping their rustick cases on our backs, </l>
            <l>And help your Highness for to drive the Cart. </l>
            <l>T' may be the traytor that did write these lines, </l>
            <l>Mistaking us for them will shew himself. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e113030">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>Prince Palatine this plot doth please me well, </l>
            <l>I make no doubt if we deal cunningly, </l>
            <l>But we shall find the writer of this seroul. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e113070">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>And in that hope I will disrobe this slave. </l>
            <l>Come Princes in the neighbouring thicket here, </l>
            <l>We may disguise our selves, and talk at pleasure; </l>
            <l>Fye on him heavy lubber how he weighs. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e113120">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>The sin of murder hangs upon his soul, </l>
            <l>It is no mervail then if he be heavy. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e113150">Exeunt. </stage>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="eng000372-e113160">
          <pb n="29" xml:id="eng000372-018-b"/>
          <head>ACT. III. </head>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e113170">Enter to the Revels. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e113180">Edward with an Imperial Crown. Hedewig the Empress. Bohemia the Taster. Alphonsus the Forrester. Mentz the Gester. Empress the Chambermaid. Brandenburg Physician. Tryer Secretarie. Alexander the Marshal, with his Marshals staff, and all the rest in their proper apparrel, and Attendants and Pages. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e113190">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <p>Princes and Princes Superiors, Lords and Lords fellows, Gentlemen and Gentlemens Masters, and all the rest of the States here assembled, as well Masculine as Feminine, be it known unto you by these presence, that I Alexander de Toledo, Fortunes chief Marshal, do will and command you, by the authority of my said Office, to take your places in manner and form following, First the Emperour and the Empress, then the Taster, the Secretary, the Forrester, the Physician, as for the Chambermaid and my self, we will take our places at the neither end, the Jester is to wait up, and live by the crums that fall from the Emperours trencher, But now I have Marshal'd you to the table, what remains? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e113210">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <p>Every fool can tell that, when men are set to dinner they commonly expect meat. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e113230">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <p>That's the best Jest the fool made since he came into his Office. Marshal walk into the Kitchin, and see how the Churfurst of Collen bestirs himself. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e113250">Exit. Alex. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e113260">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <p>Shall I go with him too? I love to be imploy'd in the Kitchin. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e113280">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <p>I prethee go, that we may be rid of thy wicked Jests. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e113300">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <p>Have with thee Marshal, the fool rides thee? </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e113320">Exit. on Alex. back. </stage>
          <pb n="30" xml:id="eng000372-019-a"/>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e113330">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <p>Now by mine honour, my Lord of Mentz plays the fool the worst that ever I saw. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e113350">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <p>He do's all by contraries; for I am sure he playd the wiseman like a fool, and now he plays the fool wisely. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e113370">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Princes and Churfursts let us frolick now, </l>
            <l>This is a joyful day to Christendome, </l>
            <l>When Christian Princes joyn in amity, </l>
            <l>Schinck bowls of Reinfal and the purest Wine, </l>
            <l>We'l spend this evening lustie upsie Dutch, </l>
            <l>In honour of this unexpected league. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e113440">
            <speaker>Empres. </speaker>
            <l>Nay gentle Forrester, there you range amiss, </l>
            <l>His looks are fitly suited to his thoughts. </l>
            <l>His glorious Empress makes his heart tryumph, </l>
            <l>And hearts tryumphing makes his countenance stai'd, </l>
            <l>In contemplation of his lives delight. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e113500">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Good Aunt let me excuse my self in this, </l>
            <l>I and an Emperour but for a day, </l>
            <l>She Empress of my heart while life doth last; </l>
            <l>Then give me leave to use Imperial looks. </l>
            <l>Nay if I be an Emperour I'l take leave, </l>
            <l>And here I do pronounce it openly, </l>
            <l>What I have lately whisper'd in her ears, </l>
            <l>I love mine Empress more than Empery, </l>
            <l>I love her looks above my fortunes hope. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e113600">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Saving your looks dread Emperour es gelt a bowl, </l>
            <l>Unto the health of your fair Bride and Empress. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e113630">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <p>
              <foreign xml:lang="ger">Sain Got es soll mir en liebe drunk sein</foreign>, so much Dutch have I learnt since I came into Germany. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e113650">
            <speaker>Bran. </speaker>
            <l>When you have drunk a dozen of these bowls, </l>
            <l>So can your Majesty with a full mouth, </l>
            <l>Trowl out high Dutch, till then it sounds not right, </l>
            <l>Darauff es gelt noch eins thr Maiestat. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e113700">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l xml:lang="ger">Sain Got lass lauffen. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e113720">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord of Brandenburg spoken like a good Dutch Brother; </l>
            <l>But most unlike a good Physician, </l>
            <l>You should consider what he has to do, </l>
            <l>His Bride will give you little thanks to night. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e113770">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Ha, ha my Lord, now give me leave to laugh, </l>
            <l>He need not therefore shun one Beaker full. </l>
            <pb n="31" xml:id="eng000372-019-b"/>
            <l>In Saxon Land you know it is the use, </l>
            <l>That the first night the Bridegroom spares the Bride. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e113820">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>'Tis true indeed, that had I quite forgotten. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e113840">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>How understand I that? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e113860">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>That the first night, </l>
            <l>The Bride and Bridegroom never sleep together. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e113890">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>That may well be, perchance they wake together. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e113910">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>Nay without fallace they have several Beds. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e113930">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>I in one Chamber, that is most Princely. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e113950">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Not onely several Beds, but several Chambers, </l>
            <l>Lockt soundly too, with Iron Bolts and Bars. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e113980">
            <speaker>Empr. </speaker>
            <l>Beleeve me Nephew, that's the custom here. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e114000">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>O my good Aunt, the world is now grown new, </l>
            <l>Old customs are but superstitions. </l>
            <l>I 'm sure this day, this presence all can witness, </l>
            <l>The high and mighty Prince th' Archbishop of Collen, </l>
            <l>Who now is busie in the skullery, </l>
            <l>Joyn'd us together in St. Peters Church, </l>
            <l>And he that would disjoyn us two to night, </l>
            <l>'Twixt jest and earnest be it proudly spoken, </l>
            <l>Shall eat a piece of ill-digesting Iron. </l>
            <l>Bride wilt dow dis nicht ben mee schlapen. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hedewick" xml:id="eng000372-e114110">
            <speaker>Hede. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Da behute mich Gott fur, Ich hoffe Eure maiestat wills von mir mitt, begeran. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e114130">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>What says <foreign xml:lang="ger">she behuie mich Got fur</foreign>? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e114150">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>She says God bless her from such a deed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e114170">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Tush Empress, clap thy hands upon thy head, </l>
            <l>And God will bless thee, I have a Iacobs staff, </l>
            <l>Shall take the Elevation of the Pole; </l>
            <l>For I have heard it sayd, the Dutch North star, </l>
            <l>Is a degree or two higher than ours. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e114230">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>Nay though we talk lets drink, and Emperour, </l>
            <l>I'l tell you plainly what you must trust unto, </l>
            <l>Can they deceive you of your Bride to night, </l>
            <l>They'll surely do't, therefore look to your self. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e114280">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>If she deceive me not, let all do their worst. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e114300">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Assure you Emperour she'l do her best. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e114320">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>I think the Maids in Germany are mad, </l>
            <l>E're they be marryed they will not kiss, </l>
            <l>And being marryed will not go to Bed. </l>
            <pb n="32" xml:id="eng000372-020-a"/>
            <l>We drink about, let's talk no more of this, </l>
            <l>Well warn'd half arm'd our English proverb say </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e114380">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Holla Marshal, what says the Cook? </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e114400">Enter Alexander. </stage>
            <l>Belike he thinks we have fed so well already, </l>
            <l>That we disdain his simple Cookery. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e114430">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <p>Faith the Gook says so, that his Office was to dress a mess of meat with that Wood which the English Prince should bring in, but he hath neither seen Dutch Wood nor English prince, therefore he desires you hold him excus'd. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e114450">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>I wonder where Prince Richard stays so long. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e114470">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>An't, please your Majesty, he's come at length, </l>
            <l>And with him has he brought a crew of Bowrs, </l>
            <l>A hipse bowr maikins fresh as Flow'rs in May, </l>
            <l>With whom they mean to dance a Saxon round, </l>
            <l>In honour of the Bridegroom and his Bride. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e114530">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>So has he made amends for his long tarrying. </l>
            <l>I prethee Marshall them into the presence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e114560">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <p>Lives Richard then? I had thought th' hadst made him sure. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e114580">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>O, I could tear my flesh to think upon 't, </l>
            <l>He lives and secretly hath brought with him, </l>
            <l>The Palsgrave and the Duke of Saxonie, </l>
            <l>Clad like two Bowrs, even in the same apparrel </l>
            <l>That Hans and Ierick wore when they went out to murder him, </l>
            <l>It now behooves us to be circumspect. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e114650">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>It likes me not; Away Marshal bring them. </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e114670">Exit. Alexander. </stage>
            <l>I long to see this sports conclusion. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e114690">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>I'st not a lovely sight to see this couple </l>
            <l>Sit sweetly billing like two Turtle Doves. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e114720">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>I promise you it sets my Teeth an Edge, </l>
            <l>That I must take mine Empress in mine arms. </l>
            <l>Come hither Isabel, though thy roabs be homely, </l>
            <l>Thy face and countenance holds colour still. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e114770">
            <pb n="33" xml:id="eng000372-020-b"/>Enter Alexander, Collen, Mentz, Richard, Saxony, Palsgrave, Collen Cook, with a gamon of raw bacon, and links or puddings in a platter, Richard, Palsgrave, Saxon, Mentz, like Clowns with each of them a Miter with Corances on their heads. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e114780">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>Dread Emperour and Emperess for to day, </l>
            <l>I Your appointed Cook untill to morrow, </l>
            <l>Have by the Marshal sent my just excuse, </l>
            <l>And hope your Highness is therewith content, </l>
            <l>Our Carter here for whom I now do speak, </l>
            <l>Says that his Axletree broke by the way, </l>
            <l>That is his answer, and for you shall not famish, </l>
            <l>He and his fellow bowrs of the next dorp, </l>
            <l>Have brought a schinkel of good raw Bacon, </l>
            <l>And that's a common meat with us, unsod, </l>
            <l>Desiring you, you would not scorn the fare, </l>
            <l>'Twil make a cup of Wine taste nippitate. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e114910">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <p>Welcome good fellows, we thank you for your present. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e114930">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>So spell fresh up and let us rommer daunsen. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e114950">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Please it your Highness to dance with your Bride? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e114970">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Alas I cannot dance your German dances. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e114990">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>I do beseech your Highness mock us not, </l>
            <l>We Germans have no changes in our dances, </l>
            <l>An Almain and an upspring that is all, </l>
            <l>So dance the Princes, Burgers, and the Bowrs. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e115040">
            <speaker>Brand. </speaker>
            <l>So daunc'd our Auncestors for thousand years. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e115060">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>It is a sign the Dutch are not new fangled. </l>
            <l>I'le follow in the measure; Marshal lead. </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e115090">Alexander and Mentz have the fore dance with each of them a glass of Wine in their hands, then Edward and Hedewick, Palsgrave and Empress, and two other couple, after Drum and Trumpet. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e115100">The Palsgrave whispers with the Empress. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e115110">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>I think the Bowr is amorous of my Empress. </l>
            <l>Fort bowr and leffel morgen, when thou com'st to house. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e115140">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>Now is your Graces time to steal away, </l>
            <pb n="34" xml:id="eng000372-021-a"/>
            <l>Look to't or else you'l lie alone to night. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e115170">Edward steals away the Bride. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e115180">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>(Drinketh to the Palsgrave.) Skelt bowre. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-palsgrave" xml:id="eng000372-e115200">
            <speaker>Palsgrave. </speaker>
            <l>Sain Gott. </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e115220">The Palsgrave requests the Empress. </stage>
            <l>Ey Iungfraw helpe mich doch ein Iungfraw drunck </l>
            <l>Es gelt guter fcenudt ein frolecken drink. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e115250">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l xml:lang="ger">Sam Gott mein frundt ich will gern bescheidt thun </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e115270">(Alphonsus takes the Cup of the Palsgrave, and drinks to the King of Bohemia, and after he hath drunk puts poyson into the Beaker.) </stage>
            <l>Half this I drink unto your Highness health, </l>
            <l>It is the first since we were joynd in Office. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e115300">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>I thank your Majesty, I'le pledge you half. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e115320">(As Bohem is a drinking, e're he hath drunk it all out, Alphonsus pulls the Beaker from his mouth.) </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e115330">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Hold, hold, your Majesty, drink not too much. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e115350">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>What means your Highness. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e115370">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Methinks that something grates between my teeth, </l>
            <l>Pray God there be not poyson in the bowl. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e115400">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>Marry God forbid. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e115420">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>So were I pepper'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e115440">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>I highly do mistrust this schelmish bowr, </l>
            <l>Lay hands on him I le make him drink the rest. </l>
            <l xml:lang="ger">Whas ist whas ist wat will you nut mee machen </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e115480">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Drink out, drink out <foreign xml:lang="ger">oder der divell soll dich holen</foreign>. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-palsgrave" xml:id="eng000372-e115500">
            <speaker>Pals. </speaker>
            <l xml:lang="ger">Ey geb you to frieden ich will gein drink. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e115520">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>Drink not Prince Pallatine, throw it on the ground, </l>
            <l>It is not good to trust his Spanish flies. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e115550">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>Saxon and Palsgrave, this cannot be good. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e115570">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>'Twas not for nought my mind misgave me so; </l>
            <l>This hath Prince Richard done t'entrap our lives. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e115600">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>No Alphonsus, I disdain to be a traytor. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e115620">
            <speaker>Empress. </speaker>
            <p>O sheath your swords, forbear these needless broyls. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e115640">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Away, I do mistrust thee as the rest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e115660">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>Lord's hear me speak, to pacify these broyls; </l>
            <l>For my part I feel no distemperature, </l>
            <l>How do you feel your self? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e115700">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <p>I cannot tell, not ill, and yet methinks I am not well. </p>
          </sp>
          <pb n="35" xml:id="eng000372-021-b"/>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e115720">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>Were it a poyson 'twould begin to work. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e115740">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Not so, all poysons do not work alike. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-palsgrave" xml:id="eng000372-e115760">
            <speaker>Pals. </speaker>
            <l>If there were poyson in, which God forbid, </l>
            <l>The Empress and my self and Alexander, </l>
            <l>Have cause to fear as well as any other. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e115800">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Why didst thou throw the Wine upon the earth? </l>
            <l>Hadst thou but drunk, thou hadst satisfied our minds. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-palsgrave" xml:id="eng000372-e115830">
            <speaker>Pals. </speaker>
            <l>I will not be enforc't by Spanish hands. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e115850">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>If all be well with us that schuce shall serve, </l>
            <l>If not, the Spaniards blood will be reveng'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e115880">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>Your Majesty is more afraid than hurt. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e115900">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>For me I do not fear my self a whit, </l>
            <l>Let all be friends, and forward with our mirth. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e115930">Enter Edward in his night-gown and his shirt. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e115940">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>Nephew, how now? is all well with you? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e115960">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>I lay my life the Prince has lost his bride. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e115980">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>I hope not so, she is but stray'd a little. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e116000">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Your Grace must not be angry though we laugh. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e116020">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>If it had hapned by default of mine, </l>
            <l>You might have worthily laught me to scorn; </l>
            <l>But to be so deceiv'd, so over reach'd, </l>
            <l>Even as I meant to clasp her in mine arms, </l>
            <l>The grief is intollerable, not to be guest, </l>
            <l>Or comprehended by the thought of any, </l>
            <l>But by a man that hath been so deceiv'd, </l>
            <l>And that's by no man living but my self. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e116110">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>My Princely Son-in-Law God give you joy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e116130">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Of what my Princely Father? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e116150">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>O' my Daughter. </l>
            <l>Your new betroathed Wife and Bed-fellow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e116180">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>I thank you Father, indeed I must confess </l>
            <l>She is my Wife, but not my Bed-fellow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e116210">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>How so young Prince? I saw you steal her hence, </l>
            <l>And as me thought she went full willingly. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e116240">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>'Tis true, I stole her finely from amongst you, </l>
            <l>And by the Arch-Bishop of Collens help, </l>
            <l>Got her alone into the Bride-Chamber, </l>
            <l>Where having lockt the Door, thought all was well. </l>
            <l>I could not speak but pointed to the Bed, </l>
            <pb n="36" xml:id="eng000372-022-a"/>
            <l>She answered Ia and gan for to unlace her; </l>
            <l>I seeing that suspected no deceit, </l>
            <l>But straight untrust my points, uncas'd my self, </l>
            <l>And in a moment slipt between the Sheets; </l>
            <l>There lying in deep contemplation, </l>
            <l>The Princess of her self drew neer to me, </l>
            <l>Gave me her hand, spake prettily in Dutch </l>
            <l>I know not what, and kist me lovingly, </l>
            <l>And as I shrank out of my luke warm place </l>
            <l>To make her room, she clapt thrice with her feet, </l>
            <l>And through a trap-door sunck out of my sight; </l>
            <l>Knew I but her Confederates in the deed </l>
            <l>I say no more. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e116430">
            <speaker>Empress. </speaker>
            <l>Tush Cosin, be content; </l>
            <l>So many Lands, so many fashions, </l>
            <l>It is the German use, be not impatient, </l>
            <l>She will be so much welcomer to morrow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e116480">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>Come Nephew, we'l be Bed-fellows to night. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e116500">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Nay if I find her not, I'le lye alone, </l>
            <l>I have good hope to ferret out her Bed, </l>
            <l>And so good night sweet Princess all at once. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e116540">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Godnight to all; Marshal discharge the train. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e116560">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>To Bed, to Bed the Marshal crys 'tis time. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e116580">Exeunt. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e116590">Flourish Cornets, Manent Saxon, Richard, Palsgrave, Collen, Empress. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e116600">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>Now Princes it is time that we advise, </l>
            <l>Now we are all fast in the Fowlers gin, </l>
            <l>Not to escape his subtle snares alive, </l>
            <l>Unless by force we break the Nets asunder. </l>
            <l>When he begins to cavil and pick quarrels, </l>
            <l>I will not trust him in the least degree. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e116670">
            <speaker>Empress. </speaker>
            <l>It may beseem me evill to mistrust </l>
            <l>My Lord and Emperour of so foul a fact; </l>
            <l>But love unto his honour and your lives, </l>
            <l>Makes me with tears intreat your Excellencies </l>
            <l>To fly with speed out of his dangerous reach, </l>
            <l>His cloudy brow foretells a suddain storm </l>
            <l>Of blood not natural but prodigious. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e116750">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>The Castle gates are shut, how should we fly; </l>
            <pb n="37" xml:id="eng000372-022-b"/>
            <l>But were they open, I would lose my life, </l>
            <l>E're I would leave my Nephew to the slaughter; </l>
            <l>He and his Bride were sure to bear the brunt. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e116800">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>Could I get out of doors, I'ld venture that, </l>
            <l>And yet I hold their persons dear enough, </l>
            <l>I would not doubt, but e're the morning Sun </l>
            <l>Should half way run his course into the South, </l>
            <l>To compass and begirt him in his Fort, </l>
            <l>With Saxon lansknights and brunt-bearing Switzers, </l>
            <l>Who lye in Ambuscado not far hence, </l>
            <l>That he should come to Composition, </l>
            <l>And with safe conduct bring into our tents, </l>
            <l>Both Bride and Bridegroom, and all other friends. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e116910">
            <speaker>Empress. </speaker>
            <l>My Chamber Window stands upon the Wall, </l>
            <l>And thence with ease you may escape away. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e116940">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>Prince Richard, you will bear me Company? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e116960">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>I will my Lord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e116980">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>And you Prince Pallatine? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-palsgrave" xml:id="eng000372-e117000">
            <speaker>Pals. </speaker>
            <l>The Spanish Tyrant hath me in suspect </l>
            <l>Of poysoning him, I'l therefore stay it out, </l>
            <l>To fly upon't were to accuse my self. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e117040">
            <speaker>Empress. </speaker>
            <l>If need require, I'le hide the Pallatine, </l>
            <l>Untill to morrow, if you stay no longer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e117070">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>If God be with us, e're to morrow noon, </l>
            <l>We'll be with Ensigns spread before the Walls, </l>
            <l>We leave dear pledges of our quick return. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e117110">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>May the Heavens prosper your just intents. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e117130">Exeunt. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e117140">Enter Alphonsus. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e117150">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>This dangerous plot was happily overheard, </l>
            <l>Here didst thou listen in a blessed howr. </l>
            <l>Alexander, where do'st thou hide thy self? </l>
            <l>I've sought thee in each Corner of the Court, </l>
            <l>And now or never must thou play the man. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e117210">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>And now or never must your Highness stir, </l>
            <l>Treason hath round encompassed your life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e117240">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>I have no leasure now to hear thy talk. </l>
            <l>Seest thou this Key? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e117270">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <p>Intends your Majesty that I should steal into the Princes Chambers, </p>
            <pb n="38" xml:id="eng000372-023-a"/>
            <l>And sleeping stab them in their Beds to night? </l>
            <l>That cannot be. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e117310">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Wilt thou not hear me speak? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e117330">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>The Prince of England, Saxon, and of Collen, </l>
            <l>Are in the Empress Chamber privily. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e117360">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>All this is nothing, they would murder me, </l>
            <l>I come not there to night; seest thou this Key? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e117390">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>They mean to fly out at the Chamber Window, </l>
            <l>And raise an Army to beseege your Grace, </l>
            <l>Now may your Highness take them with the deed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e117430">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>The Prince of Wales I hope is none of them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e117450">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Him and his Bride by force they will recover. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e117470">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>What makes the cursed Palsgrave of the Rhein? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e117490">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Him hath the Empress taken to her charge, </l>
            <l>And in her Closet means to hide him safe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e117520">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>To hide him in her Closet? of bold deeds, </l>
            <l>The dearest charge that e're she undertook, </l>
            <l>Well let them bring their Complots to an end, </l>
            <l>I'le undermine to meet them in their works, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e117570">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Will not your Grace surprize them e're they fly? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e117590">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>No, let them bring their purpose to effect, </l>
            <l>I'le fall upon them at my best advantage, </l>
            <l>Seest thou this Key? there take it Alexander; </l>
            <l>Yet take it not unless thou be resolv'd; </l>
            <l>Tush I am fond to make a doubt of thee; </l>
            <l>Take it I say, it doth command all Doors, </l>
            <l>And will make open way to dire revenge. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e117670">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>I know not what your Majesty doth mean. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e117690">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Hie thee with speed into the inner Chamber, </l>
            <l>Next to the Chappe, and there shalt thou find </l>
            <l>The danty trembling Bride coutcht in her Bed, </l>
            <l>Having beguil'd her Bridegroom of his hopes, </l>
            <l>Taking her farewel of Virginity, </l>
            <l>Which she to morrow night expects to lose, </l>
            <l>By night all Cats are gray, and in the dark, </l>
            <l>She will imbrace thee for the Prince of Wales, </l>
            <l>Thinking that he hath found her Chamber out, </l>
            <l>Fall to thy business and make few words, </l>
            <l>And having pleas'd thy senses with delight, </l>
            <pb n="39" xml:id="eng000372-023-b"/>
            <l>And fild thy beating vains with stealing joy, </l>
            <l>Make thence agen before the break of day, </l>
            <l>What strange events will follow this device, </l>
            <l>We need not study on, our foes shall find. </l>
            <l>How now? how standst thou? hast thou not the heart? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e117860">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Should I not have the heart to do this deed, </l>
            <l>I were a Bastard villain and no man; </l>
            <l>Her sweetness, and the sweetness of revenge, </l>
            <l>Tickles my senses in a double sense, </l>
            <l>And so I wish your Majesty good night. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e117920">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>God night, sweet Venus prosper thy attempt. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e117940">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Sweet Venus and grim Ate I implore, </l>
            <l>Stand both of you to me auspicious. </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e117970">Exit. Alexander. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e117980">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>It had been pitty of his Fathers life, </l>
            <l>Whose death hath made him such a perfect villain. </l>
            <l>What murder, wrack, and causeless enmity, </l>
            <l>'Twixt dearest friends that are my strongest foes, </l>
            <l>Will follow suddainly upon this rape, </l>
            <l>I hope to live to see, and laugh thereat, </l>
            <l>And yet this peece of practice is not all. </l>
            <l>The King of Bohem though he little feel it, </l>
            <l>Because in twenty hours it will not work, </l>
            <l>Hath from my Knives point suck'd his deadly bane, </l>
            <l>Whereof I will be least of all suspected; </l>
            <l>For I will feign my self as sick as he, </l>
            <l>And blind mine enemies eyes with deadly groans; </l>
            <l>Upon the Palsgrave and mine Emperess, </l>
            <l>Heavy suspect shall light to bruze their bones; </l>
            <l>Though Saxon would not suffer him to taste, </l>
            <l>The deadly potion provided for him, </l>
            <l>He cannot save him from the Sword of Iustice, </l>
            <l>When all the world shall think that like a villain, </l>
            <l>He hath poyson'd two great Emperours with one draught; </l>
            <l>That deed is done, and by this time I hope, </l>
            <l>The other is a doing, Alexander </l>
            <l>I doubt it not will do it thorowly. </l>
            <l>While these things are a brewing I'l not sleep, </l>
            <l>But sudainly break ope the Chamber doors, </l>
            <l>And rush upon my Empress and the Palsgrave, </l>
            <pb n="40" xml:id="eng000372-024-a"/>
            <l>Holla wher's the Captain of the Guard? </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e118260">Enter Captain, and Souldiers. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-captain" xml:id="eng000372-e118270">
            <speaker>Cap. </speaker>
            <l>What would your Majesty? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e118290">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Take six travants well arm'd and followe, </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e118310">They break with violence into the Chamber, and Alphonsu trayls the Empress by the hair. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e118320">Enter Alphonsus, Empress, Souldiers, &amp;c. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e118330">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Come forth thou damned Witch, adulteror Whore, </l>
            <l>Foul scandal to thy name, thy sex, thy blood. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e118360">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>O Emperour, gentle Husband, pitty me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e118380">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Canst thou deny thou wert confederate, </l>
            <l>With my arch enemies that sought my blood? </l>
            <l>And like a Strumpet through thy Chamber Window, </l>
            <l>Hast with thine own hands helpt to let them down, </l>
            <l>With an intent that they should gather arms, </l>
            <l>Besiege my Court, and take away my life? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e118450">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>Ah my Alphonsus. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e118470">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Thy Alphonsus Whore? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e118490">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>O pierce my heart, trail me not by my hair; </l>
            <l>What I have done, I did it for the best. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e118520">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>So for the best advantage of thy lust, </l>
            <l>Hast thou in secret Clytemnestra like, </l>
            <l>Hid thy Aegestus thy adulterous love. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e118560">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>Heav'n be the record 'twixt my Lord and me, </l>
            <l>How pure and sacred I do hold thy Bed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e118590">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Art thou so impudent to bely the deed, </l>
            <l>Is not the Palsgrave hidden in thy Chamber? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e118620">
            <speaker>Empe. </speaker>
            <l>That I have hid the Palsgrave I confess; </l>
            <l>But to no ill intent your conscience knows. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e118650">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Thy treasons, murders, incests, sorceries, </l>
            <l>Are all committed to a good intent; </l>
            <l>Thou know'st he was my deadly enemy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e118690">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>By this device I hop'd to make your friends. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e118710">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Then bring him forth, we'l reconcile our selves. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e118730">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>Should I betray so great a Prince's life? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e118750">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Thou holdst his life far dearer than thy Lords, </l>
            <l>This very night hast thou betrayd my blood, </l>
            <pb n="41" xml:id="eng000372-024-b"/>
            <l>But thus, and thus, will I revenge my self, </l>
            <l>And but thou speedily deliver him, </l>
            <l>I'le trail thee through the Kennels of the Street, </l>
            <l>And cut the Nose from thy bewitching face, </l>
            <l>And into England send thee like a Strumpet. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e118830">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>Pull every hair from off my head, </l>
            <l>Drag me at Horses tayls, cut off my nose </l>
            <l>My Princely tongue shall not betray a Prince. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e118870">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>That will I try. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e118890">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>O Heav'n revenge my shame. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e118910">Enter Palsgrave. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-palsgrave" xml:id="eng000372-e118920">
            <speaker>Pal. </speaker>
            <l>Is Caesar now become a torturer, </l>
            <l>A Hangman of his Wife, turn'd murderer? </l>
            <l>Here is the Pallatine, what wouldst thou more? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e118960">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Upon him Souldiers, strike him to the ground. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e118980">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>Ah Souldiers, spare the Princely Pallatine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e119000">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Down with the damn'd adulterous murderer, </l>
            <l>Kill him I say, his blood be on my head. </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e119030">They kill the Pallatine. </stage>
            <l>Run to the Tow'r, and Ring the Larum Bell, </l>
            <l>That fore the world I may excuse my self, </l>
            <l>And tell the reason of this bloody deed. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e119070">Enter Edward in his night gown and shirt. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e119080">
            <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
            <l>How now? what means this sudain strange Allarm? </l>
            <l>What wretched dame is this with blubbered cheeks, </l>
            <l>And rent dishevel'd hair? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e119120">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>O my dear Nephew, </l>
            <l>Fly, fly the Shambles, for thy turn is next. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e119150">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>What, my Imperial Aunt? then break my heart. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e119170">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Brave Prince be still; as I am nobly born, </l>
            <l>There is no ill intended to thy person. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e119200">Enter Mentz, Tryer, Branden. Bohem. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e119210">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>Where is my Page? bring me my two hand Sword. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-trier" xml:id="eng000372-e119230">
            <speaker>Tryer. </speaker>
            <l>What is the matter? is the Court a fire </l>
          </sp>
          <pb n="42" xml:id="eng000372-025-a"/>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e119250">
            <speaker>Bran. </speaker>
            <l>Whos's that? the Emperour with his weapon drawn? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e119270">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>Though deadly sick yet am I forc'd to rise, </l>
            <l>To know the reason of this hurley burley. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e119300">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Princes be silent, I will tell the cause, </l>
            <l>Though sudainly a grining at my heart </l>
            <l>Forbids my tongue his wanted course of speech. </l>
            <l>See you this Harlot, traytress to my life, </l>
            <l>See you this murderer, stain to mine honour, </l>
            <l>These twain I found together in my Bed, </l>
            <l>Shamefully committing lewd Adultery, </l>
            <l>And hainously conspiring all your deaths, </l>
            <l>I mean your deaths, that are not dead already; </l>
            <l>As for the King of Boheme and my self, </l>
            <l>We are not of this world, we have our transports </l>
            <l>Giv'n in the bowl by this adulterous Prince, </l>
            <l>And least the poyson work too strong with me, </l>
            <l>Before that I have warnd you of your harms, </l>
            <l>I will be brief in the relation. </l>
            <l>That he hath staind my Bed, these eyes have seen, </l>
            <l>That he hath murder'd two Imperial Kings, </l>
            <l>Our speedy deaths will be too sudain proof; </l>
            <l>That he and she have bought and sold your lives, </l>
            <l>To Saxon, Collen, and the English Prince, </l>
            <l>Their Ensigns spread before the Walls to morrow </l>
            <l>Will all too sudainly bid you defiance. </l>
            <l>Now tell me Princes have I not just cause, </l>
            <l>To slay the murderer of so many souls? </l>
            <l>And have not all cause to applaud the deed? </l>
            <l>More would I utter, but the poysons force </l>
            <l>Forbids my speech, you can conceive the rest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-bohemia" xml:id="eng000372-e119580">
            <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
            <l>Your Majesty reach me your dying hand, </l>
            <l>With thousand thanks for this so just revenge. </l>
            <l>O, how the poysons force begins to work! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e119620">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>The world may pitty and applaud the deed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e119640">
            <speaker>Brand. </speaker>
            <l>Did never age bring forth such hainous acts. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e119660">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>My senses are confounded and amaz'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e119680">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>The God of Heav'n knows my unguiltiness. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e119700">Enter Messenger. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-messenger" xml:id="eng000372-e119710">
            <speaker>Mes. </speaker>
            <l>Arm, arm my Lords, we have descry'd a far, </l>
            <pb n="43" xml:id="eng000372-025-b"/>
            <l>An Army of ten thousand men at arms. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e119740">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Some run unto the Walls, some draw up the Sluce, </l>
            <l>Some speedily let the Purculless down. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e119770">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>Now may we see the Emperours words are true. </l>
            <l>To prison with the wicked murderous Whore. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e119800">Exeunt. </stage>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="eng000372-e119810">
          <head>ACT. IV. </head>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e119820">Enter Saxon and Richard with Souldiers. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e119830">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord of Cornwall, let us march before, </l>
            <l>To speedy rescue of our dearest friends, </l>
            <l>The rereward with the armed Legions, </l>
            <l>Committed to the Prince of Collen's charge, </l>
            <l>Cannot so lightly pass the mountain tops. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e119890">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>Let's summon sudainly unto a Parly, </l>
            <l>I do not doubt but e're we need their helps, </l>
            <l>Collen with all his forces will be here. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e119930">Enter Collen with Drums and an Army. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e119940">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>Your Holiness hath made good hast to day, </l>
            <l>And like a beaten Souldier lead your troops. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e119970">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>In time of peace I am an Arch-Bishop, </l>
            <l>And like a Church-man can both sing and say; </l>
            <l>But when the innocent do suffer wrong, </l>
            <l>I cast my rocket off upon the Altar, </l>
            <l>And like a Prince betake my self to arms. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e120030">Enter above Mentz, Tryer, and Brandeburg. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e120040">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>Great Prince of Saxonie, what mean these arms? </l>
            <l>Richard of Cornwall, what may this intend? </l>
            <l>Brother of Collen no more Churchman now, </l>
            <l>Instead of Miter, and a Crossier Staff, </l>
            <l>Have you betane you to your Helm and Targe? </l>
            <l>Were you so merry yesterday as friends, </l>
            <l>Cloaking your treason in your Clowns attire? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e120120">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>Mentz, we return the traytor in thy face. </l>
            <l>To save our lives, and to release our friends, </l>
            <pb n="44" xml:id="eng000372-026-a"/>
            <l>Out of the Spaniards deadly trapping Snares, </l>
            <l>Without intent of ill, this power is rais'd; </l>
            <l>Therefore grave Prince Marquess of Brandenburg, </l>
            <l>My loving Cosin, as indifferent Judge, </l>
            <l>To you an aged Peace-maker we speak, </l>
            <l>Deliver with safe conduct in our tents, </l>
            <l>Prince Edward and his Bride, the Pallatine, </l>
            <l>With every one of high or low degree, </l>
            <l>That are suspicious of the King of Spain, </l>
            <l>So shall you see that in the self same howr </l>
            <l>We marched to the Walls with colours spread, </l>
            <l>We will cashier our troups, and part good friends. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e120270">
            <speaker>Brand. </speaker>
            <l>Alas my Lord, crave you the Pallatine? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e120290">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>If craving will not serve, we will command. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e120310">
            <speaker>Brand. </speaker>
            <l>Ah me, since your departure, good my Lords, </l>
            <l>Strange accidents of bloud and death are hapned. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e120340">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>My mind misgave a massacre this night. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e120360">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>How do's Prince Edward then? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e120380">
            <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
            <l>How do's my Daughter? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e120400">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>How goes it with the Palsgrave of the Rhein? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e120420">
            <speaker>Brand. </speaker>
            <l>Prince Edward and his Bridle do live in health, </l>
            <l>And shall be brought unto you when you please. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e120450">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>Let them be presently deliver'd? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e120470">
            <speaker>Coll. </speaker>
            <l>Lives not the Palsgrave too? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e120490">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <p>In Heaven or Hell he lives, and reaps the merrit of his deeds. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e120510">
            <speaker>Coll. </speaker>
            <l>What damned hand hath butchered the Prince? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e120530">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>O that demand is needless, who but he, </l>
            <l>That seeks to be the Butcher of us all; </l>
            <l>But vengeance and revenge shall light on him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e120570">
            <speaker>Bran. </speaker>
            <l>Be patient noble Princes, hear the rest. </l>
            <l>The two great Kings of Bohem and Castile, </l>
            <l>God comfort them, lie now at point of death, </l>
            <l>Both poyson'd by the Palsgrave yesterday. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e120620">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>How is that possible? so must my Sister, </l>
            <l>The Pallatine himself, and Alexander, </l>
            <l>Who drunk out of the bowl, be poysoned too. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e120660">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>Nor is that hainous deed alone the cause, </l>
            <l>Though cause enough to ruin Monarchies; </l>
            <l>He hath defil'd with lust th' Imperial Bed, </l>
            <pb n="45" xml:id="eng000372-026-b"/>
            <l>And by the Emperour in the fact was slain. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e120710">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>O worthy guiltless Prince, O had he fled. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e120730">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>But say where is the Empress, where's my Sister. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e120750">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>Not burnt to ashes yet, but shall be shortly. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e120770">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>I hope her Majesty will live to see </l>
            <l>A hundred thousand flattering turncoat slaves, </l>
            <l>Such as your Holiness, dye a shameful death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e120810">
            <speaker>Brand. </speaker>
            <l>She is in prison, and attends her tryal. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e120830">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>O strange heart-breaking mischievous intents, </l>
            <l>Give me my children if you love your lives, </l>
            <l>No safety is in this enchanted Fort. </l>
            <l>O see in happy hour there comes my Daughter, </l>
            <l>And loving son, scapt from the Massacre. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e120890">Enter Edward and Hedewick. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e120900">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>My body lives, although my heart be slain, </l>
            <l>O Princes this hath been the dismall'st night, </l>
            <l>That ever eye of sorrow did behold, </l>
            <l>Here lay the Palsgrave weltring in his bloud, </l>
            <l>Dying Alphonsus standing over him, </l>
            <l>Upon the other hand the King of Bohem, </l>
            <l>Still looking when his poyson'd bulk would break; </l>
            <l>But that which pierc'd my soul with natures touch </l>
            <l>Was my tormented Aunt with blubberd cheeks, </l>
            <l>Torn bloody Garments, and disheveld 'hair, </l>
            <l>Waiting for death; deservedly or no, </l>
            <l>That knows the searcher of all humane thoughts; </l>
            <l>For these devices are beyond my reach. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e121040">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l xml:lang="ger">Sast dorh liches doister, who wart dow dicselbirmafl. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hedewick" xml:id="eng000372-e121060">
            <speaker>Hede. </speaker>
            <l xml:lang="ger">Ais who who solt ich sem ich war in bette. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e121080">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l xml:lang="ger">Wert dow allrin so wart dow gar vorschrocken. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hedewick" xml:id="eng000372-e121100">
            <speaker>Hede. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Ich ha mist audes gememt dam das ich wolt allrin geschlaffne haben, abur vmb mitternaist kam meiner bridegroom, bundt si flaffet bey mir, bis wir mit dem getunnuel erwacht waren. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e121120">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>What says she? came her Bridegroom to her at midnight? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e121140">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>Nephew, I see you were not over-reach'd; </l>
            <l>Although she slipt out of your arms at first, </l>
            <l>You ceiz'd her surely, e're you left the chace. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e121180">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>But left your Grace, your Bride alone in Bed? </l>
            <pb n="46" xml:id="eng000372-027-a"/>
            <l>Or did she run together in the Larum? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e121210">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Alas my Lords, this is no time to jest; </l>
            <l>I lay full sadly in my Bed alone, </l>
            <l>Not able for my life to sleep a wink, </l>
            <l>Till that the Larum Bell began to Ring, </l>
            <l>And then I starred from my weary couch. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e121270">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>How now? this rimes not with my daughters speech, </l>
            <l>She says you found her Bed, and lay with her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e121300">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Not I, your Highness did mistake her words. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e121320">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>Deny it not Prince Edward, 'tis an honour. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e121340">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>My Lords I know no reason to deny it; </l>
            <l>T' have found her Bed, I would have given a million. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e121370">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l xml:lang="ger">Hedswick der Furst sagt er satt mist be dir schlafin. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hedewick" xml:id="eng000372-e121390">
            <speaker>Hede. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Es gefelt ihm also zum sagun aber ich habes woll gerfralet. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e121410">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>She say's you are dispos'd to jest with her; </l>
            <l>But yesternight she felt it in good earnest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e121440">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Unckle these jests are too unsavorie, </l>
            <l>Ill suited to these times, and please me not, </l>
            <l>Lab ich bin you geshlapen yesternight. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hedewick" xml:id="eng000372-e121480">
            <speaker>Hede. </speaker>
            <l xml:lang="ger">I leff, warum snlt ihrs fragen. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e121500">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>Edward, I tell thee 'tis no jesting matter, </l>
            <l>Say plainly, wa'st thou by her I or no? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e121530">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>As I am Prince, true heir to Englands Crown, </l>
            <l>I never toucht her body in a Bed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hedewick" xml:id="eng000372-e121560">
            <speaker>Hede. </speaker>
            <l xml:lang="ger">Das haste gethan order holle mich der divell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e121580">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>Nephew, take heed, you hear the Princess words. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e121600">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>It is not she, nor you, nor all the world, </l>
            <l>Shall make me say I did anothers deed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e121630">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>Anothers deed? what think'st thou her a whore? </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e121650">Saxon strikes Edward. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e121660">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>She may be Whore, and thou a villain too. </l>
            <l>Strook me the Emperour I will strike again. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e121690">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>Content you Princes, buffet not like boys. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e121710">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>Hold you the one, and I will hold the other. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hedewick" xml:id="eng000372-e121730">
            <speaker>Hede. </speaker>
            <l>O her got, help, help, oich arms kindt. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e121750">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>Souldiers lay hands upon the Prince of Wales, </l>
            <l>Convey him speedily unto a prison, </l>
            <l>And load his Legs with grievous bolts of Iron; </l>
            <l>Some bring the Whore my Daughter from my fight; </l>
            <l>And thou smooth Englishman to thee I speak, </l>
            <pb n="47" xml:id="eng000372-027-b"/>
            <l>My hate extends to all thy Nation, </l>
            <l>Pack thee out of my sight, and that with speed </l>
            <l>Your English practises have all to long, </l>
            <l>Muffled our German eyes, pack, pack I say. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e121850">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>Although your Grace have reason for your rage, </l>
            <l>Yet be not like a madman to your friends. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e121880">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>My friends? I scorn the friendship of such mates, </l>
            <l>That seek my Daughters spoil, and my dishonour; </l>
            <l>But I will teach the Boy another lesson, </l>
            <l>His head shall pay the ransom of his fault. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e121930">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>His head? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e121950">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>And thy head too, O how my heart doth swell! </l>
            <l>Was there no other Prince to mock but me? </l>
            <l>First woo, then marry her, then lye with her, </l>
            <l>And having had the pleasure of her Bed, </l>
            <l>Call her a Whore in open audience, </l>
            <l>None but a villain and a slave would do it, </l>
            <l>My Lords of Mentz, of Tryer, and Brandenburg, </l>
            <l>Make ope the Gates, receive me as a friend, </l>
            <l>I'le be a scourge unto the English Nation. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e122050">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>Your Grace shall be the welcom'st guest alive, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e122070">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>None but a madman would do such a deed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e122090">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>Then Collen count me mad, for I will do it. </l>
            <l>I'le set my life and Land upon the hazard, </l>
            <l>But I will thoroughly found this deceit. </l>
            <l>What will your Grace leave me or follow me? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e122140">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>No Saxon know I will not follow thee, </l>
            <l>And leave Prince Richard in so great extreams. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e122170">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>Then I defy you both, and so farwell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e122190">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>Yet Saxon hear me speak before thou go, </l>
            <l>Look to the Princes life as to thine own, </l>
            <l>Each perisht hair that falleth from his head </l>
            <l>By thy default, shall cost a Saxon City, </l>
            <l>Henry of England will not lose his heir, </l>
            <l>And so farwel and think upon my words. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e122260">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>Away, I do disdain to answer thee. </l>
            <l>Pack thee with shame again into thy Countrie, </l>
            <l>I'le have a Cock-boat at my proper charge, </l>
            <l>And send th' Imperial Crown which thou hast won, </l>
            <l>To England by Prince Edward after thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e122320">Exeunt. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e122330">Man. Rich. and Coll. </stage>
          <pb n="48" xml:id="eng000372-028-a"/>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e122340">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>Answer him not Prince Richard, he is mad, </l>
            <l>Choler and grief have rob'd him of his senses. </l>
            <l>Like accident to this was never heard. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e122380">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>Break heart and dye, flie hence my troubled spirit, </l>
            <l>I am not able for to underbear </l>
            <l>The weight of sorrow which doth bruze my soul, </l>
            <l>O Edward, O sweet Edward, O my life. </l>
            <l>O noble Collen last of all my hopes, </l>
            <l>The only friend in my extremities, </l>
            <l>If thou doest love me, as I know thou doest, </l>
            <l>Unsheath thy sword, and rid me of this sorrow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e122470">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>Away with abject thoughts, fie Princely Richard, </l>
            <l>Rowze up thy self, and call thy senses home, </l>
            <l>Shake of this base pusillanimitie, </l>
            <l>And cast about to remedie these wrongs. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e122520">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>Alas I see no means of remedie. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e122540">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>The hearken to my Counsel and advice, </l>
            <l>We will Intrench our selves not far from hence, </l>
            <l>With those small pow'rs we have, and send for more, </l>
            <l>If they do make assault, we will defend; </l>
            <l>If violence be offer'd to the Prince, </l>
            <l>We'l rescue him with venture of our lives; </l>
            <l>Let us with patience attend advantage, </l>
            <l>Time may reveal the author of these treasons, </l>
            <l>For why undoubtedly the sweet young Princess, </l>
            <l>Fowly beguild by night with cunning shew, </l>
            <l>Hath to some villain lost her Maiden-head. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e122660">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>O that I knew the foul incestuous wretch, </l>
            <l>Thus would I tear him with my teeth and nails. </l>
            <l>Had Saxon sense he would conceave so much, </l>
            <l>And not revenge on guiltless Edwards life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e122710">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>Perswade your self he will be twice advis'd. </l>
            <l>Before he offer wrong unto the Prince. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e122740">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>In that good hope I will have patience. </l>
            <l>Come gentle Prince whose pitty to a stranger </l>
            <l>Is rare and admirable, not to be spoken. </l>
            <l>England cannot requite this gentleness. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e122790">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>Tush talk not of requital, let us go, </l>
            <l>To fortifie our selves within our trench. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e122820">Exeunt. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e122830">
            <pb n="49" xml:id="eng000372-028-b"/>Enter Alphonso (carried in the Couch) Saxony, Mentz, Tryer, Brandenburg, Alexander. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e122840">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>O most excessive pain, O raging Fire! </l>
            <l>Is burning Cancer or the Scorpion, </l>
            <l>Descended from the Heavenly Zodiack, </l>
            <l>To parch mine Entrals with a quenchless flame? </l>
            <l>Drink, drink I say, give drink or I shall dye. </l>
            <l>Fill a thousand bowls of Wine, Water I say </l>
            <l>Water from forth the cold Tartarian hils. </l>
            <l>I feel th' ascending flame lick up my blood, </l>
            <l>Mine Entrals shrink together like a scrowl </l>
            <l>Of burning parchment, and my Marrow fries, </l>
            <l>Bring hugie Cakes of Ice, and Flakes of Snow, </l>
            <l>That I may drink of them being dissolved. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e122970">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>We do beseech your Majestie have patience, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e122990">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Had I but drunk an ordinary poyson, </l>
            <l>The sight of thee great Duke of Saxony, </l>
            <l>My friend in death, in life my greatest foe, </l>
            <l>Might both allay the venom and the torment; </l>
            <l>But that adulterous Palsgrave and my Wife, </l>
            <l>Upon whose life and soul I vengeance cry, </l>
            <l>Gave me a mineral not to be digested, </l>
            <l>Which burning eats, and eating burns my heart. </l>
            <l>My Lord of Tryer, run to the King of Bohem, </l>
            <l>Commend me to him, ask him how he fares, </l>
            <l>None but my self can rightly pitty him; </l>
            <l>For none but we have sympathie of pains. </l>
            <l>Tell him when he is dead, my time's not long, </l>
            <l>And when I dye bid him prepare to follow. </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e123140">Exit. Tryer. </stage>
            <l>Now, now it works a fresh; are you my friends? </l>
            <l>Then throw me on the cold swift running Rhyn, </l>
            <l>And let me bath there for an hour or two, </l>
            <l>I cannot bear this pain. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e123190">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>O would th' unpartial fates afflict on me, </l>
            <l>These deadly pains, and ease my Emperour, </l>
            <l>How willing would I bear them for his sake. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e123230">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>O Mentz, I would not wish unto a Dog, </l>
            <l>The least of thousand torments that afflict me, </l>
            <l>Much less unto your Princely holiness. </l>
            <pb n="50" xml:id="eng000372-029-a"/>
            <l>See, see my Lord of Mentz, he points at you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e123280">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>It is your fantasie and nothing else; </l>
            <l>But were death here, I would dispute with him, </l>
            <l>And tell him to his teeth he doth unjustice, </l>
            <l>To take your Majesty in the prime of youth; </l>
            <l>Such wither'd rotten branches as my self, </l>
            <l>Should first be lopt, had he not partial hands; </l>
            <l>And here I do protest upon my Knee, </l>
            <l>I would as willingly now leave my life, </l>
            <l>To save my King and Emperour alive, </l>
            <l>As erst my Mother brought me to the world. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e123390">
            <speaker>Brand. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord of Mentz, this flattery is too gross, </l>
            <l>A Prince of your experience and calling, </l>
            <l>Should not so fondly call the Heavens to witness. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e123430">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>Think you my Lord, I would not hold my word? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e123450">
            <speaker>Brand. </speaker>
            <l>You know my Lord, death is a bitter guest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e123470">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>To ease his pain and save my Emperour, </l>
            <l>I sweetly would embrace that bitterness. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e123500">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>If I were death, I knew what I would do. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e123520">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>But see, his Majesty is faln a sleep, </l>
            <l>Ah me, I fear it is a dying slumber. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e123550">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord of Saxonie do you hear this jest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e123570">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>What should I hear my Lord? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e123590">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Do you not hear </l>
            <l>How loudly death proclames it in mine ears, </l>
            <l>Swearing by trophies, Tombs and deadmens Graves, </l>
            <l>If I have any friend so dear to me, </l>
            <l>That to excuse my life will lose his own, </l>
            <l>I shall be presently restor'd to health. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e123660">Enter Tryer. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e123670">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>I would he durst make good his promises. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e123690">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord of Tryer, how fares my fellow Emperour? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-trier" xml:id="eng000372-e123710">
            <speaker>Tryer. </speaker>
            <l>His Majesty is eas'd of all his pains. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e123730">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>O happy news, now have I hope of health. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e123750">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>My joyful heart doth spring within my bodie, </l>
            <l>To hear those words, </l>
            <l>Comfort your Majestie I will excuse you, </l>
            <l>Or at the least will bear you Company. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb n="51" xml:id="eng000372-029-b"/>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e123800">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>My hope is vain, now, now my heart will break, </l>
            <l>My Lord of Tryer you did but flatter me, </l>
            <l>Tell me the truth, how fares his Majestie. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-trier" xml:id="eng000372-e123840">
            <speaker>Tryer. </speaker>
            <l>I told your Highness, eas'd of all his pain. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e123860">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>I understand thee now, he's eas'd by death, </l>
            <l>And now I feel an alteration; </l>
            <l>Farewel sweet Lords, farewel my Lord of Mentz, </l>
            <l>The truest friend that ever earth did bear, </l>
            <l>Live long in happiness to revenge my death, </l>
            <l>Upon my Wife and all the English brood. </l>
            <l>My Lord of Saxonie your Grace hath cause. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e123940">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>I dare thee death to take away my life. </l>
            <l>Some charitable hand that loves his Prince, </l>
            <l>And hath the heart, draw forth his Sword and rid me of my life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e123980">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>I love my Prince, and have the heart to do it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-mentz" xml:id="eng000372-e124000">
            <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
            <l>O stay a while. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e124020">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Nay now it is to late. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e124040">
            <speaker>Bran. </speaker>
            <l>Villain what hast thou done? th' ast slain a Prince. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e124060">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>I did no more than he intreated me, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e124080">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>How now, what make I in my Couch so late? </l>
            <l>Princes why stand you so gazing about me? </l>
            <l>Or who is that lies slain before my face? </l>
            <l>O I have wrong, my soul was half in Heaven, </l>
            <l>His holiness did know the joys above, </l>
            <l>And therefore is ascended in my stead. </l>
            <l>Come Princes let us bear the body hence; </l>
            <l>I'le spend a Million to embalm the same. </l>
            <l>Let all the Bels within the Empire Ring, </l>
            <l>Let Mass be said in every Church and Chappel, </l>
            <l>And that I may perform my latest vow, </l>
            <l>I will procure so much by Gold or friends, </l>
            <l>That my sweet Mentz shall be Canonized, </l>
            <l>And numbred in the Bed-role of the Saints, </l>
            <l>I hope the Pope will not deny it me, </l>
            <l>I'le build a Church in honour of thy name, </l>
            <l>Within the antient famous Citie Mentz, </l>
            <l>Fairer than any one in Germany, </l>
            <l>There shalt thou be interrd with Kingly Pomp, </l>
            <l>Over thy Tomb shall hang a sacred Lamp, </l>
            <pb n="52" xml:id="eng000372-030-a"/>
            <l>Which till the day of doom shall ever burn, </l>
            <l>Yea after ages shall speak of thy renown, </l>
            <l>And go a Pilgrimage to thy sacred Tomb. </l>
            <l>Grief stops my voice, who loves his Emperour, </l>
            <l>Lay to his helping hand and bear him hence, </l>
            <l>Sweet Father and redeemer of my life. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e124350">Exeunt. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e124360">Manet Alexander. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e124370">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Now is my Lord sole Emperour of Rome, </l>
            <l>And three Conspirators of my Fathers death, </l>
            <l>Are cunningly sent unto Heaven or Hell; </l>
            <l>Like subtilty to this was never seen. </l>
            <l>Alas poor Mentz! I pittying thy prayers, </l>
            <l>Could do no less than lend a helping hand, </l>
            <l>Thou wert a famous flatterer in thy life, </l>
            <l>And now hast reapt the fruits thereof in death; </l>
            <l>But thou shalt be rewarded like a Saint, </l>
            <l>With Masses, Bels, dirges and burning Lamps; </l>
            <l>'Tis good, I envie not thy happiness: </l>
            <l>But ah the sweet remembrance of that night, </l>
            <l>That night I mean of sweetness and of stealth, </l>
            <l>When for a Prince, a Princess did imbrace me, </l>
            <l>Paying the first fruits of her Marriage Bed, </l>
            <l>Makes me forget all other accidents. </l>
            <l>O Saxon I would willingly forgive, </l>
            <l>The deadly trespass of my Fathers death, </l>
            <l>So I might have thy Daughter to my Wife, </l>
            <l>And to be plain, I have best right unto her, </l>
            <l>And love her best, and have deserv'd her best; </l>
            <l>But thou art fond to think on such a match; </l>
            <l>Thou must imagin nothing but revenge, </l>
            <l>And if my computation fail me not, </l>
            <l>Ere long I shall be thorowly reveng'd. </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e124630">Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e124640">Enter the Duke of Saxon, and Hedewick with the Child. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e124650">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>Come forth thou perfect map of miserie, </l>
            <l>Desolate Daughter and distressed Mother, </l>
            <l>In whom the Father and the Son are curst; </l>
            <l>Thus once again we will assay the Prince. </l>
            <l>'T may be the sight of his own flesh and blood </l>
            <pb n="53" xml:id="eng000372-030-b"/>
            <l>Will now at last pierce his obdurate heart. </l>
            <l>Jailor how fares it with thy prisoner? </l>
            <l>Let him appear upon the battlements. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hedewick" xml:id="eng000372-e124740">
            <speaker>Hede. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">O mein deere vatter, ich habe in dis lang lang 30. weeken, welche mich duncket sein 40. iahr gewesen, ein litte Englisch gelernet, vnd ich hope, he will me verstohn, vnd shew me a little pittie. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e124760">Enter Edward on the Walls and Iailor. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e124770">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>Good morrow to your grace Edward of Wales, </l>
            <l>Son and immediate Heir to Henry the third, </l>
            <l>King of England and Lord of Ireland, </l>
            <l>Thy Fathers comfort, and the peoples hope; </l>
            <l>'Tis not in mockage nor at unawares, </l>
            <l>That I am ceremonious to repeat </l>
            <l>Thy high descent ioynd with thy Kingly might; </l>
            <l>But therewithall to intimate unto thee </l>
            <l>What God expecteth from the higher powers, </l>
            <l>Justice, and mercie, truth, sobrietie, </l>
            <l>Relenting hearts, hands innocent of blood. </l>
            <l>Princes are Gods chief substitutes on earth, </l>
            <l>And should be Lamps unto the common sort. </l>
            <l>But you will say I am become a Preacher, </l>
            <l>No, Prince, I am an humble suppliant, </l>
            <l>And to prepare thine ears make this exordium, </l>
            <l>To pierce thine eyes and heart, behold this spectacle, </l>
            <l>Three Generations of the Saxon blood, </l>
            <l>Descended lineallie from forth my Loyns, </l>
            <l>Kneeling and crying to thy mightiness; </l>
            <l>First look on me, and think what I have been, </l>
            <l>For now I think my self of no account, </l>
            <l>Next Caesar, greatest man in Germanie, </l>
            <l>Neerly a lyed, and ever friend to England; </l>
            <l>But Womens sighs move more in manly hearts, </l>
            <l>O see the hands she elevates to Heaven; </l>
            <l>Behold those eyes that whilome were thy joyes, </l>
            <l>Uttering domb eloquence in Christal tears; </l>
            <l>If these exclames and sights be ordinarie, </l>
            <l>Then look with pittie on thy other self, </l>
            <l>This is thy flesh, and blood, bone of thy bone, </l>
            <pb n="54" xml:id="eng000372-031-a"/>
            <l>A goodly Boy the Image of his sire. </l>
            <l>Turn'st thou away? O were thy Father here, </l>
            <l>He would, as I do, take him in his arms, </l>
            <l>And sweetly kiss his Grand-child in the face. </l>
            <l>O Edward too young in experience, </l>
            <l>That canst not look into the grievous wrack, </l>
            <l>Ensuing this thy obstinate deniall; </l>
            <l>O Edward too young in experience, </l>
            <l>That canst not see into the future good, </l>
            <l>Ensuing thy most just acknowledgement; </l>
            <l>Hear me thy truest friend, I will repeat them; </l>
            <l>For good thou hast an Heir indubitate, </l>
            <l>Whose eyes already sparckle Majesty, </l>
            <l>Born in true Wedlock of a Princely Mother, </l>
            <l>And all the German Princes to thy friends; </l>
            <l>Where on the contrary thine eyes shall see, </l>
            <l>The speedy Tragedie of thee and thine; </l>
            <l>Like Athamas first will I ceize upon </l>
            <l>Thy young unchristened and despised Son, </l>
            <l>And with his guiltless brains bepaint the Stones; </l>
            <l>Then like Virginius will I kill my Child, </l>
            <l>Unto thine eyes a pleasing spectacle; </l>
            <l>Yet shall it be a momentarie pleasure, </l>
            <l>Henry of England shall mourn with me; </l>
            <l>For thou thy self Edward shall make the third, </l>
            <l>And be an actor in this bloody Scean. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hedewick" xml:id="eng000372-e125350">
            <speaker>Hede. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Ah myne seete Edouart, mein herzkin, myne scherzkin, mein herziges, einiges herz, mein allerleivest husband, I preedee mein leefe see me friendlich one, good feete harte tell de trut: and at lest to me, and dyne allerleefest schild shew pitty! dan ich bin dyne, vnd dow bist myne, dow hast me geven ein kindelein; O Edouart, feete, Edouart erbarmet sein! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e125370">
            <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
            <l>O Hedewick peace, thy speeches pierce my soul. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hedewick" xml:id="eng000372-e125390">
            <speaker>Hede. </speaker>
            <p>Hedewick doe yow excellencie hight me Hedewick seete Edouart yow weete ich bin yowr allerlieueste wife. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e125410">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>The Priest I must confess made thee my Wife, </l>
            <l>Curst be the damned villanous adulterer, </l>
            <l>That with so fowl a blot divorc'd our love. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hedewick" xml:id="eng000372-e125450">
            <speaker>Hede. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">O mein allerleevester, hieborne Furst vnd Herr, <pb n="55" xml:id="eng000372-031-b"/>dinck dat unser Herr Gott sitts in himmells trone, and sees dat hart vnd will my cause woll recken: </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e125470">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>Edward hold me not up with long delays; </l>
            <l>But quickly say, wilt thou confess the truth? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e125500">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>As true as I am born of Kingly Linage, </l>
            <l>And am the best Plantagenet next my Father, </l>
            <l>I never carnallie did touch her body. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e125540">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>Edward this answer had we long ago, </l>
            <l>Seest thou this brat? speak quickly or he dyes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e125570">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>His death will be more piercing to thine eyes, </l>
            <l>Than unto mine, he is not of my kin. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hedewick" xml:id="eng000372-e125600">
            <speaker>Hede. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">O Father, O myne Uatter spare myne kindt O Edouart O Prince Edouart spreak now oder nimmermehr die kindt ist mein, it soll nicht sterben: </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e125620">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>Have I dishonoured my self so much, </l>
            <l>To bow my Knee to thee, which never bow'd </l>
            <l>But to my God, and am I thus rewarded? </l>
            <l>Is he not thine? speak murderous-minded Prince. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e125670">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>O Saxon, Saxon mitigate thy rage. </l>
            <l>First thy exceeding great humilitie, </l>
            <l>When to thy captive prisoner thou didst kneel, </l>
            <l>Had almost made my lying tongue confess, </l>
            <l>The deed which I protest I never did; </l>
            <l>But thy not causeless furious madding humour, </l>
            <l>Together with thy Daughters pitious cryes, </l>
            <l>Whom as my life and soul I dearly love, </l>
            <l>Had thorowly almost perswaded me, </l>
            <l>To save her honour and belie my self, </l>
            <l>And were I not a Prince of so high blood, </l>
            <l>And Bastards have no scepter-bearing hands, </l>
            <l>I would in silence smother up this blot, </l>
            <l>And in compassion of thy Daughters wrong, </l>
            <l>Be counted Father to an others Child; </l>
            <l>For why my soul knows her unguiltiness. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e125840">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>Smooth words in bitter sense; is thine answer? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hedewick" xml:id="eng000372-e125860">
            <speaker>Hede. </speaker>
            <l xml:lang="ger">Ey vatter geue mir mein kindt, die kind ist mein. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e125880">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Das weis ich woll, er sagt esist nicht sein; therefore it dyes. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e125900">He dashes out the Childs brains. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hedewick" xml:id="eng000372-e125910">
            <speaker>Hede. </speaker>
            <l xml:lang="ger">O Got in seinem trone, O mein kindt mein kindt. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e125930">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>There murderer take his head, and breathless lymbs, </l>
            <pb n="56" xml:id="eng000372-032-a"/>
            <l>Ther's flesh enough, bury it in thy bowels, </l>
            <l>Eat that, or dye for hunger, I protest, </l>
            <l>Thou getst no other food till that be spent. </l>
            <l>And now to thee lewd Whore, dishonour'd strumpet, </l>
            <l>Thy turn is next, therefore prepare to dye. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e126000">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>O mighty Duke of Saxon, spare thy Child. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e126020">
            <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
            <l>She is thy Wife Edward, and thou shouldst spare her. </l>
            <l>One Gracious word of thine will save her life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e126050">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>I do confess Saxon she is mine own, </l>
            <l>As I have marryed her, I will live with her, </l>
            <l>Comfort thy self sweet Hedewick and sweet Wife. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hedewick" xml:id="eng000372-e126090">
            <speaker>Hede. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">Ach, ach vnd wehe, warumb sagt your Excellence nicht so before, now ist to late, vnser arme kindt ist kilt. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e126110">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Though thou be mine, and I do pittie thee, </l>
            <l>I would not Nurse a Bastard for a Son. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hedewick" xml:id="eng000372-e126140">
            <speaker>Hede. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">O Edouard now ich mark your mening ich sholdt be your whore, mein Uatter ich begehr upon meine knee, last mich lieber sterben, ade falce Edouart, falce Prince, ich begehrs nicht. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e126160">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>Unprincely thoughts do hammer in thy head, </l>
            <l>I'st not enough that thou hast sham'd her once, </l>
            <l>And seen the Bastard torn before thy face; </l>
            <l>But thou wouldst get more brats for Butcherie? </l>
            <l>No Hedewick thou shalt not live the day. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hedewick" xml:id="eng000372-e126220">
            <speaker>Hede. </speaker>
            <l xml:lang="ger">O Herr Gott, nimb meine feele in deiner henden. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e126240">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>It is thy hand that gives this deadly stroak. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-hedewick" xml:id="eng000372-e126260">
            <speaker>Hede. </speaker>
            <p xml:lang="ger">O Herr Sabote, das mein vnschuldt an tag kommen mocht. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e126280">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Her blood be on that wretched villains head, </l>
            <l>That is the cause of all this misery. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e126310">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>Now murderous-minded Prince, hast thou beheld </l>
            <l>Vpon my Child, and Childs Child, thy desire, </l>
            <l>Swear to thy self, that here I firmly swear, </l>
            <l>That thou shall surely follow her to morrow. </l>
            <l>In Company of thy adulterous Aunt, </l>
            <l>Jaylor convey him to his Dungeon, </l>
            <l>If he be hungrie, I have thrown him meat, </l>
            <l>If thirstie let him suck the newly born lymbs. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb n="57" xml:id="eng000372-032-b"/>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e126400">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>O Heavens and Heavenly powers, if you be just, </l>
            <l>Reward the author of this wickedness. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e126430">Exit. Edw. &amp; Iaoler. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e126440">Enter Alexander. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e126450">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>To arms great Duke of Saxonie, to arms, </l>
            <l>My Lord of Collen, and the Earl of Cornwall, </l>
            <l>In rescue of Prince Edward and the Empress, </l>
            <l>Have levy'd fresh supplies, and presently </l>
            <l>Will bid you battail in the open Field. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e126510">
            <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
            <l>They never could have come in fitter time; </l>
            <l>Thirst they for blood? and they shall quench their thirst. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e126540">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>O piteous spectacle! poor Princess Hedewick. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e126560">
            <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
            <l>Stand not to pittie, lend a helping hand. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e126580">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>What slave hath murdered this guiltless Child? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e126600">
            <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
            <l>What? dar'st thou call me slave unto my face? </l>
            <l>I tell thee villain, I have done this deed, </l>
            <l>And seeing the Father and the Grand-sires heart, </l>
            <l>Can give consent and execute their own, </l>
            <l>Wherefore should such a rascal as thy self </l>
            <l>Presume to pittie them, whom we have slain? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e126670">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Pardon me, if it be presumption </l>
            <l>To pittie them, I will presume no more. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e126700">
            <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
            <l>Then help, I long to be amidst my foes. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e126720">Exeunt. </stage>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="eng000372-e126730">
          <head>ACT. V. </head>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e126740">Alarum and Retreat. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e126750">Enter Richard and Collen with Drums and Souldiers. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e126760">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>What means your Excellence to sound retreat? </l>
            <l>This is the day of doom unto our Friends; </l>
            <l>Before Sun set, my Sister, and my Nephew, </l>
            <l>Vnless we rescue them, must lose their lives; </l>
            <l>The cause admits no dalliance nor delay. </l>
            <l>He that so tyrant-like hath slain his own, </l>
            <l>Will take no pittie on a strangers blood. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e126840">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>At my entreaty e're we strike the battail, </l>
            <l>Let's summon out our enemies to a parle. </l>
            <l>Words spoken in time, have vertue, power, and price, </l>
            <pb n="58" xml:id="eng000372-033-a"/>
            <l>And mildness may prevail and take effect, </l>
            <l>When dynt of Sword perhaps will aggravate. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e126900">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>Then sound a Parly to fulfill your mind, </l>
            <l>Although I know no good can follow it. </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e126930">A Parley. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e126940">Enter Alphonso, Empress, Saxon, Edward prisoner, Tryer, Brandenburg, Alexander and Souldiers. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e126950">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Why how now Emperour that should have been, </l>
            <l>Are these the English Generals bravado's? </l>
            <l>Make you assault so hotly at the first, </l>
            <l>And in the self same moment sound retreat? </l>
            <l>To let you know, that neither War nor words, </l>
            <l>Have power for to divert their fatall doom, </l>
            <l>Thus are we both resolv'd; if we tryumph, </l>
            <l>And by the right and justice of our cause </l>
            <l>Obtain the victorie, as I doubt it not, </l>
            <l>Then both of you shall bear them Company, </l>
            <l>And e're Sun set we will perform our oaths, </l>
            <l>With just effusion of their guilty bloods; </l>
            <l>If you be Conquerours, and we overcome, </l>
            <l>Carry not that conceit to rescue them, </l>
            <l>My self will be the Executioner, </l>
            <l>And with these Ponyards frustrate all your hopes, </l>
            <l>Making you tryumph in a bloodie Field. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e127130">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>To put you out of doubt that we intend it, </l>
            <l>Please it your Majesty to take your Seate, </l>
            <l>And make a demonstration of your meaning. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e127170">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>First on my right hand bind the English Whore, </l>
            <l>That venemous Serpent nurst within my breast </l>
            <l>To suck the vitall bloud out of my veins, </l>
            <l>My Empress must have some preheminence, </l>
            <l>Especially at such a bloodie Banquet, </l>
            <l>Her State, and love to me deserves no less. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e127240">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>That to Prince Edward I may shew my love, </l>
            <l>And do the latest honour to his State, </l>
            <l>These hands of mine that never chained any, </l>
            <l>Shall fasten him in fetters to the Chair. </l>
            <l>Now Princes are you ready for the battail? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e127300">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>Now art thou right the picture of thy self, </l>
            <l>Seated in height of all thy Tyrannie; </l>
            <pb n="59" xml:id="eng000372-033-b"/>
            <l>But tell us what intends this spectacle. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e127340">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>To make the certaintie of their deaths more plain, </l>
            <l>And Cancel all your hopes to save their lives, </l>
            <l>While Saxon leads the troups into the Field, </l>
            <l>Thus will I vex their souls, with sight of death, </l>
            <l>Loudly exclaming in their half dead ears; </l>
            <l>That if we win they shall have companie, </l>
            <l>Viz. The English Emperour, </l>
            <l>And you my Lord Archbishop of Collen, </l>
            <l>If we be vanquisht, then they must expect </l>
            <l>Speedy dispatch from these two Daggers points. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e127450">
            <speaker>Collen. </speaker>
            <l>What canst thou tyrant then expect but death? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e127470">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Tush hear me out, that hand which shed their blood, </l>
            <l>Can do the like to rid me out of bonds. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e127500">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>But that's a damned resolution. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e127520">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>So must this desperate disease be cur'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e127540">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>O Saxon I'le yield my self and all my power, </l>
            <l>To save my Nephew, though my Sister dye. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e127570">
            <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
            <l>Thy Brothers Kingdom shall not save his life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e127590">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Uncle, you see these savage minded men </l>
            <l>Will have no other ransom but my blood, </l>
            <l>England hath Heirs, though I be never King, </l>
            <l>And hearts and hands to scourge this tyrannie, </l>
            <l>And so farewel. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e127650">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>A thousand times farewel, </l>
            <l>Sweet Brother Richard and brave Prince of Collen. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e127680">
            <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
            <l>What Richard, hath this object pierc'd thy heart? </l>
            <l>By this imagine how it went with me, </l>
            <l>When yesterday I slew my Children. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e127720">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>O Saxon I entreat thee on my Knees. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e127740">
            <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
            <l>Thou shalt obtain like mercy with thy kneeling, </l>
            <l>As lately I obtaind at Edward's hands. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e127770">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>Pitty the tears I powr before thy feet. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e127790">
            <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
            <l>Pitty those tears? why I shed bloudie tears. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e127810">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>I'le do the like to save Prince Edwards life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e127830">
            <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
            <l>Then like a Warrior spill it in the Field, </l>
            <l>My griefull anger cannot be appeaz'd, </l>
            <l>By sacrifice of any but himself, </l>
            <l>Thou hast dishonour'd me, and thou shalt dye; </l>
            <pb n="60" xml:id="eng000372-034-a"/>
            <l>Therefore alarum, alarum to the fight, </l>
            <l>That thousands more may bear thee company. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e127900">
            <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
            <l>Nephew and Sister now farewell for ever. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e127920">
            <speaker>Ed. </speaker>
            <l>Heaven and the Right prevail, and let me die; </l>
            <l>Uncle farewell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e127950">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>Brother farewell untill wee meet in Heaven. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e127970">Exeunt. Manent Alphon. Edw. Emp. Alex. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e127980">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Here's farewell Brother, Nephew, Vncle, Aunt, </l>
            <l>As if in thousand years you should not meet; </l>
            <l>Good Nephew, and good Aunt content your selves, </l>
            <l>The Sword of Saxon and these Daggers-points, </l>
            <l>Before the Evening-Star doth shew it self, </l>
            <l>Will take sufficient order for your meeting. </l>
            <l>But Alexander, my trustie Alexander, </l>
            <l>Run to the Watch-Tow'r as I pointed thee, </l>
            <l>And by thy life I charge thee look unto it </l>
            <l>Thou be the first to bring me certain word </l>
            <l>I we be Conquerors, or Conquered. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e128100">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>With carefull speed I will perform this charge. </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e128120">Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e128130">
            <speaker>Alphon </speaker>
            <l>Now have I leasure yet to talk with you. </l>
            <l>Fair Isabell, the Palsgrave's Paramour, </l>
            <l>Wherein was he a better man than I? </l>
            <l>Or wherfore should thy love to him, effect </l>
            <l>Such deadly hate unto thy Emperour? </l>
            <l>Yet welfare wenches that can love Good fellows, </l>
            <l>And not mix Murder with Adulterie. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e128210">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>Great Emperor, I dare not call you Husband, </l>
            <l>Your Conscience knows my hearts unguiltiness. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e128240">
            <speaker>Alpho. </speaker>
            <l>Didst thou not poison, or consent to poison us? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e128260">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>Should any but your Highness tell me so, </l>
            <l>I should forget my patience at my death, </l>
            <l>And call him Villain, Liar, Murderer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e128300">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>She that doth so miscall me at her end, </l>
            <l>Edward I prethee speak thy Conscience, </l>
            <l>Thinkst thou not that in her prosperitie </l>
            <l>Sh'hath vext my Soul with bitter Words and Deeds? </l>
            <l>O Prince of England I do count thee wise </l>
            <l>That thou wilt not be cumber'd with a wife, </l>
            <l>When thou hadst stoln her daintie rose Corance, </l>
            <l>And pluck'd the flow'r of her virginitie. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb n="61" xml:id="eng000372-034-b"/>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e128390">
            <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
            <l>Tyrant of Spain thou liest in thy threat. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e128410">
            <speaker>Alpho. </speaker>
            <l>Good words, thou seest thy life is in our hands. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e128430">
            <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
            <l>I see thou art become a common Hangman, </l>
            <l>An Office farre more fitting to thy mind </l>
            <l>Than princelie to the Imperiall dignitie. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e128470">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>I do not exercise on common persons, </l>
            <l>Your Highness is a Prince, and she an Empress, </l>
            <l>I therefore count not of a dignitie. </l>
            <l>Hark Edward how they labour all in vain, </l>
            <l>With loss of many a valiant Soldiers life, </l>
            <l>To rescue them whom Heaven and we have doom'd; </l>
            <l>Dost thou not tremble when thou think'st upon't? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e128550">
            <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
            <l>Let guiltie minds tremble at sight of Death, </l>
            <l>My heart is of the nature of the Palm, </l>
            <l>Not to be broken, till the highest Bud </l>
            <l>Be bent and ti'd unto the lowest Root; </l>
            <l>I rather wonder that thy Tyrants heart </l>
            <l>Can give consent that those thy Butcherous hands </l>
            <l>Should offer violence to thy Flesh and Blood. </l>
            <l>See how her guiltless innocence doth plead </l>
            <l>In silent Oratorie of her chastest tears. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e128650">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Those tears proceed from Fury and curst heart. </l>
            <l>I know the stomach of your English Dames. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e128680">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>No Emperour, these tears proceed from grief. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e128700">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Grief that thou canst not be reveng'd of Vs. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e128720">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>Grief that your Highness is so ill advis'd, </l>
            <l>To offer violence to my Nephew Edward; </l>
            <l>Since then there must be sacrifice of Blood, </l>
            <l>Let my heart-blood save both your bloods unspilt, </l>
            <l>For of his death, thy Heart must pay the guilt. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e128780">
            <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
            <l>No Auut, I will not buy my life so dear: </l>
            <l>Therefore Alphonso if thou beest a man </l>
            <l>Shed manly blood. and let me end this strife. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e128820">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Here's straining curtesie at a bitter Feast. </l>
            <l>Content thee Empress for thou art my Wife, </l>
            <l>Thou shalt obtain thy Boon and die the death, </l>
            <l>And for it were unprinceby to deny </l>
            <l>So slight request unto so great a Lord, </l>
            <l>Edward shall bear thee company in Death. </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e128890">A Retreat. </stage>
            <l>But hark the heat of battail hath an end; </l>
            <pb n="62" xml:id="eng000372-035-a"/>
            <l>One side or other hath the victory, </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e128920">Enter Alexander. </stage>
            <l>And see where Alexander sweating comes; </l>
            <l>Speak man, what newes, speak, shall I die or live? </l>
            <l>Shall I stab sure, or els prolong their lives </l>
            <l>To grievous Torments? speak, am I Conquerour? </l>
            <l>What, hath thy hast bereft thee of thy speech? </l>
            <l>Hast thou not breath to speak one siliable? </l>
            <l>O speak, thy dalliance kills me, wonn or lost? </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e129000">Amaz'd lets fall the Daggers. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e129010">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Lost. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e129030">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Ah me my Senses fail! my sight is gon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e129050">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Will not your Grace dispatch the Strumpet Queen? </l>
            <l>Shall she then live, and we be doom'd to death? </l>
            <l>Is your Heart faint, or is your Hand too weak? </l>
            <l>Shall servill fear break your so sacred Oaths? </l>
            <l>Me thinks an Emperour should hold his word; </l>
            <l>Give me the Weapons, I will soon dispatch them, </l>
            <l>My Fathers yelling Ghost cries for revenge, </l>
            <l>His Blood within my Veins boyls for revenge; </l>
            <l>O give me leave Cesar to take revenge. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e129150">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Vpon condition that thou wilt protest </l>
            <l>To take revenge upon the Murtherers, </l>
            <l>Without respect of dignity, or State, </l>
            <l>Afflicted, speedy, pittiless Revenge, </l>
            <l>I will commit this Dagger to thy trust, </l>
            <l>And give thee leave to execute thy Will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e129220">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>What need I here reiterate the Deeds </l>
            <l>Which deadly sorrow made me perpetrate? </l>
            <l>How neer did I entrap Prince Richard's life? </l>
            <l>How sure set I the Knife to Mentz his heart? </l>
            <l>How cunninglie was Palsgrave doom'd to death? </l>
            <l>How subtilly was Bohem poisoned? </l>
            <l>How slily did I satisfie my lust </l>
            <l>Commixing dulcet Love with deadly Hate, </l>
            <l>When Princesse Hedwick lost her Maidenhead, </l>
            <l>Sweetly embracing me for Englands Heir? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e129330">
            <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
            <l>O execrable deeds! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e129350">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>O salvage mind! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e129370">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Edward, I give thee leave to hear of this, </l>
            <l>But will forbid the blabbing of your tongue. </l>
            <l>Now gratious Lord and sacred Emperour, </l>
            <pb n="63" xml:id="eng000372-035-b"/>
            <l>Your highness knowing these and many more, </l>
            <l>Which fearles pregnancie hath wrought in me, </l>
            <l>You do me wrong to doubt that I will dive </l>
            <l>Into their hearts that have not spar'd their betters, </l>
            <l>Be therefore suddain lest we die our selves. </l>
            <l>I know the Conquerour hasts to rescue them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e129470">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Thy Reasons are effectuall, take this Dagger; </l>
            <l>Yet pawse a while. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e129500">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>Sweet Nephew now farewell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e129520">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>They are most dear to me whom thou must kill. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e129540">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Hark Aunt he now begins to pittie you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e129560">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>But they consented to my Fathers death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e129580">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>More then consented, they did execute. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e129600">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>I will not make his Majestie a Lyar, </l>
            <l>I kill'd thy Father, therefore let me die, </l>
            <l>But save the life of this unguilty Prince. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e129640">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>I kill'd thy Father, therefore let me die, </l>
            <l>But save the life of this unguiltie Empress. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e129670">
            <speaker>Alphon </speaker>
            <l>Hark thou to me, and think their words as wind. </l>
            <l>I kill'd thy Father, therfore let me die, </l>
            <l>And save the lives of these two guiltless Princes. </l>
            <l>Art thou amaz'd to hear what I have said? </l>
            <l>There, take the weapon, now revenge at full </l>
            <l>Thy Fathers death, and those my dire deceits </l>
            <l>That made thee murtherer of so many Souls. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e129750">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>O Emperour, how cunningly wouldst thou entrap </l>
            <l>My simple youth to credit Fictions? </l>
            <l>Thou kill my Father, no, no Emperour, </l>
            <l>Caesar did love Lorentzo all to dearly: </l>
            <l>Seeing thy Forces now are vanquished, </l>
            <l>Frustrate thy hopes, thy Highness like to fall </l>
            <l>Into the cruel and revengefull hands </l>
            <l>Of merciless incensed Enemies, </l>
            <l>Like Caius Cassius wearie of thy life, </l>
            <l>Now wouldst thou make thy Page an instrument </l>
            <l>By suddain stroak to rid thee of thy bonds. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e129870">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Hast thou forgotten how that very night </l>
            <l>Thy Father dy'd, I took the Master-Key, </l>
            <l>And with a lighted Torch walk'd through the Court. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e129910">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>I must remember that, for to my death. </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000372-036-a"/>
            <l>I never shall forget the slightest deed, </l>
            <l>Which on that dismall Night or Day I did. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e129950">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Thou wast no sooner in thy restfull Bed, </l>
            <l>But I disturb'd thy Father of his rest, </l>
            <l>And to be short, not that I hated him, </l>
            <l>But for he knew my deepest Secrets, </l>
            <l>With cunning Poison I did end his life: </l>
            <l>Art thou his Son? express it with a Stabb, </l>
            <l>And make account if I had prospered, </l>
            <l>Thy date was out, thou wast already doom'd, </l>
            <l>Thou knewst too much of me to live with me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e130050">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>What wonders do I hear great Emperour? </l>
            <l>Not that I do stedfastlie believe </l>
            <l>That thou didst murder my beloved Father; </l>
            <l>But in meer pittie of thy vanquish'd state </l>
            <l>I undertake this execution: </l>
            <l>Yet, for I fear the sparkling Majestie. </l>
            <l>Which issues from thy most Imperial, eyes </l>
            <l>May strike relenting Passion to my heart, </l>
            <l>And after wound receiv'd from fainting hand, </l>
            <l>Thou fall halfe dead among thine Enemies, </l>
            <l>I crave thy Highness leave to bind thee first. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e130170">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Then bind me quickly, use me as thou please </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e130190">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>O Villain, wilt thou kill thy Sovereign? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e130210">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Your Highness sees that I am forc'd unto it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e130230">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Fair Empress. I shame to ask thee pardon, </l>
            <l>Whom I have wrong'd so many thousand waies. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e130260">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>Dread Lord and Husband, leave these desperat thoughts, </l>
            <l>Doubt not the Princes may be reconcil'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e130290">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>'T may be the Princes will be reconciled, </l>
            <l>But what is that to me? all Potentates on Earth </l>
            <l>Can never reconcile my grieved Soul. </l>
            <l>Thou slew'st my Father, thou didst make this hand </l>
            <l>Mad with Revenge to murther Innocents, </l>
            <l>Now hear, how in the height of all thy pride </l>
            <l>The rightfull Gods hove powr'd their justfull wrath </l>
            <l>Upon thy Tyrants head, Devill as thou art. </l>
            <l>And sav'd by miracle these Princes lives; </l>
            <l>For know, thy side hath got the Victory; </l>
            <l>Saxon triumphs over his dearest friends; </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000372-036-b"/>
            <l>Richard and Collen, both are Prisoners, </l>
            <l>And every thing hath sorted to thy wish; </l>
            <l>Only hath Heaven put it in my mind </l>
            <l>(for he alone directed then my thoughts </l>
            <l>Although my meaning was most mischievous) </l>
            <l>To tell thee thou hadst lost, in certain hope </l>
            <l>That suddainly thou wouldst have stain them both, </l>
            <l>For if the Princes came to talk about it, </l>
            <l>I greatly feard their lives might be prolong'd. </l>
            <l>Art thou not mad to think on this deceit? </l>
            <l>Ile make thee madder, with tormenting thee. </l>
            <l>I tell thee Arch-Thief, Villain, Murtherer, </l>
            <l>Thy Forces have obtaind the Victory, </l>
            <l>Victory leads thy Foes in captive bands; </l>
            <l>This Victory hath crown'd thee Emperour, </l>
            <l>Only my self have vanquisht Victory, </l>
            <l>And triumph in the Victors overthrow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e130580">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>O Alexander spare thy Princes life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e130600">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Even now thou didst entreat the contrary. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e130620">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Think what I am that begg my life of thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e130640">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Think what he was whom thou hast doom'd to death. </l>
            <l>But least the Princes do surprize us here </l>
            <l>Before I have perform'd my strange revenge, </l>
            <l>I will be suddain in the execution. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e130690">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>I will accept any condition. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e130710">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Then in the presence of the Emperess, </l>
            <l>The captive Prince of England, and my self, </l>
            <l>Forswear the joyes of Heaven, the sight of God, </l>
            <l>Thy Souls salvation, and thy Saviour Christ, </l>
            <l>Damning thy Soul to endless pains of Hell. </l>
            <l>Do this or die upon my Rapiers point. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e130780">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>Sweet Lord and Husband, spit in's face. </l>
            <l>Die like a man, and live not like a Devill. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e130810">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>What? wilt thou save thy life, and damn thy Soul? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e130830">
            <speaker>Alph. </speaker>
            <l>O hold thy hand, Alphonsus doth renounce. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e130850">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Aunt stop your years, hear not this Blasphemy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e130870">
            <speaker>Empr. </speaker>
            <l>Sweet Husband think that Christ did dy for thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alphonsus" xml:id="eng000372-e130890">
            <speaker>Alphon. </speaker>
            <l>Alphonsus doth renounce the joyes of Heaven, </l>
            <l>The sight of Angells and his Saviours blood, </l>
            <l>And gives his Soul unto the Devills power. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e130930">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Thus will I make delivery of the Deed, </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000372-037-a"/>
            <l>Die and be damn'd, now am I satisfied. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e130960">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>O damned Miscreant, what hast thou done? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e130980">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>When I have leasure I will answer thee: </l>
            <l>Mean while I'le take my heels and save my self. </l>
            <l>If I be ever call'd in question, </l>
            <l>I hope your Majesties will save my life, </l>
            <l>You have so happily preserved yours; </l>
            <l>Did I not think it, both of you should die. </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e131050">Exit Alex. </stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e131060">Enter Saxon, Branden. Tryer, (Richard and Collen as prisoners) and Soldiers. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e131070">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>Bring forth these daring Champions to the Block, </l>
            <l>Comfort your selves you shall have company. </l>
            <l>Great Emperor where is his Majestie? </l>
            <l>What bloody spectacle do I behold? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e131120">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>Revenge, revenge, O Saxon, Brandenburg, </l>
            <l>My Lord is slain, Caesar is doom'd to death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e131150">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Princes make haste, follow the murtherer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e131170">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>Is Caesar slain? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e131190">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Follow the Murtherer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-empress" xml:id="eng000372-e131210">
            <speaker>Emp. </speaker>
            <l>Why stand you gasing on an other thus? </l>
            <l>Follow the Murtherer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e131240">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>What Murtherer? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e131260">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>The villain Alexander hath slain his Lord, </l>
            <l>Make after him with speed, so shall you hear </l>
            <l>Such villanie as you have never heard. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e131300">
            <speaker>Brand. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord of Tryer, we both with our light Horse </l>
            <l>Will scoure the Coasts and quickly bring him in. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e131330">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>That can your Excellence alone perform, </l>
            <l>Stay you my Lord, and guard the Prisoners, </l>
            <l>While I, alas, unhappiest Prince alive, </l>
            <l>Over his Trunk consume my self in Tears. </l>
            <l>Hath Alexander done this damned deed? </l>
            <l>That cannot be why should he slay his Lord? </l>
            <l>O cruel Fate, O miserable me! </l>
            <l>Me thinks I now present Mark Antony, </l>
            <l>Folding dead Iulius Caesar in mine arms. </l>
            <l>No, no, I rather will present Achilles, </l>
            <l>And on Patroclus Tomb do sacrifise. </l>
            <pb n="67" xml:id="eng000372-037-b"/>
            <l>Let me be spurn'd and hated as a Dogg, </l>
            <l>But I perform more direfull bloody Rites </l>
            <l>Than Thetis Son for Menctiades. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e131480">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Leave mourning for thy Foes, pitty thy Friends. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e131500">
            <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
            <l>Friends have I none, and that which grieves my Soul, </l>
            <l>Is want of Foes to work my wreak upon; </l>
            <l>But were you Traitors 4, four hundred thousand, </l>
            <l>Then might I satisfie my self with Blood. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000372-e131550">Enter Brandenb. Alexand. and Soldiers. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e131560">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>See Alexander where Caesar lieth slain, </l>
            <l>The guilt whereof the Traitors cast on thee; </l>
            <l>Speak, canst thou tell who slew thy Soveraign? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e131600">
            <speaker>Alexan. </speaker>
            <l>Why who but I? how should I curse my self </l>
            <l>If any but my self had done this deed? </l>
            <l>This happy hand, blest be my hand therefore, </l>
            <l>Reveng'd my Fathers death upon his Soul: </l>
            <l>And Saxon thou hast cause to curse and bann </l>
            <l>That he is dead, before thou didst inflict </l>
            <l>Torments on him that so hath torn thy heart. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e131680">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>What Mysteries are these? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e131700">
            <speaker>Bran. </speaker>
            <l>Princes, can you inform us of the Truth? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e131720">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>The Deed's so heinous that my faltering tongue </l>
            <l>Abhorres the utterance. Yet I must tell it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e131750">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Your Highness shall not need to take the pains, </l>
            <l>What you abhorr to tell, I joy to tell, </l>
            <l>Therefore be silent and give audience. </l>
            <l>You mighty men, and Rulers of the Earth, </l>
            <l>Prepare your Ears, to hear of Stratagems </l>
            <l>Whose dire effects have gaul'd your princely hearts, </l>
            <l>Confounded your conceits, muffled your eyes: </l>
            <l>First to begin this villanous Fiend of Hell </l>
            <l>Murther'd my Father, sleeping in his Chair, </l>
            <l>The reason why, because he only knew </l>
            <l>All Plotts, and complots of his villanie; </l>
            <l>His death was made the Basis and the Ground </l>
            <l>Of every mischief that hath troubled you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e131890">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>If thou, thy Father and thy Progenie </l>
            <l>Were hang'd and burnt, and broken on the Wheel, </l>
            <pb n="68" xml:id="eng000372-038-a"/>
            <l>How could their deaths heap mischief on our heads? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e131930">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>And if you will not hear the Reason chuse. </l>
            <l>I tell thee I have slain an Emperour, </l>
            <l>And thereby think my self as good a man </l>
            <l>As thou, or any man in Christendom, </l>
            <l>Thou shalt entreat me ere I tell thee more. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e131990">
            <speaker>Brand. </speaker>
            <l>Proceed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e132010">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Not I. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e132030">
            <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
            <l>I prethe now proceed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e132050">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Since you intreat me then, I will proceed. </l>
            <l>This murtherous Devill having slain my Father, </l>
            <l>Buz'd cunningly into my credulous ears, </l>
            <l>That by a General Councell of the States, </l>
            <l>And as it were by Act of Parlement, </l>
            <l>The seven Electors had set down his death, </l>
            <l>And made the Empress Executioner, </l>
            <l>Transferring all the guilt from him to you. </l>
            <l>This I believ'd, and first did set upon </l>
            <l>The life of Princely Richard, by the Boors, </l>
            <l>But how my purpose faild in that, his Grace best knows; </l>
            <l>Next, by a double intricate deceit, </l>
            <l>Midst all his Mirth was Bohem poysoned, </l>
            <l>And good old Mentz to save Alphonso's life, </l>
            <l>(Who at that instant was in perfect health) </l>
            <l>Twixt jest and earnest was made a Sacrifice; </l>
            <l>As for the Palatine, your Graces knew </l>
            <l>His Highness and the Queens unguiltines; </l>
            <l>But now my Lord of Saxon hark to me, </l>
            <l>Father of Saxon should I rather call you, </l>
            <l>Twas I that made your Grace a Grandfather: </l>
            <l>Prince Edward plow'd the ground, I sow'd the Seed, </l>
            <l>Poor Hedewick bore the most unhappy fruit, </l>
            <l>Created in a most unluckie hour, </l>
            <l>To a most violent and untimely death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e132310">
            <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
            <l>O loathsome Villain, O detested deeds, </l>
            <l>O guiltless Prince, O me most miserable. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-brandenburgh" xml:id="eng000372-e132340">
            <speaker>Brand. </speaker>
            <l>But tell us who reveal'd to thee at last </l>
            <l>This shamefull guilt, and our unguiltiness? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e132370">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Why that's the wonder Lords, and thus it was </l>
            <l>When like a tyrant he had tane his seat, </l>
            <pb n="69" xml:id="eng000372-038-b"/>
            <l>And that the furie of the Fight began, </l>
            <l>Upon the highest Watch-Tow'r of the Fort, </l>
            <l>It was my office to behold alofft </l>
            <l>The Warres event, and having seen the end, </l>
            <l>I saw how Victory with equal wings </l>
            <l>Hang hovering 'twixt the Battails here and there, </l>
            <l>Till at the last, the English Lyons fled, </l>
            <l>And Saxon's side obtain'd the Victory; </l>
            <l>Which seen, I posted from the turrets top, </l>
            <l>More furiously than ere Laocoon ran, </l>
            <l>When Trojan hands drew in Troy's overthrow, </l>
            <l>But yet as fatally as he or any. </l>
            <l>The tyrant seeing me, star'd in my face, </l>
            <l>And suddainly demanded whats the newes, </l>
            <l>I, as the Fates would have it, hoping that he </l>
            <l>Even in a twinkling would have slain 'em both, </l>
            <l>For so he swore before the Fight began, </l>
            <l>Cri'd bitterly that he had lost the day, </l>
            <l>The sound whereof did kill his dastard heart, </l>
            <l>And made the Villain desperatly confess </l>
            <l>The murther of my Father, praying me, </l>
            <l>With dire revenge, to ridd him of his life; </l>
            <l>Short tale to make, I bound him cunningly, </l>
            <l>Told him of the deceit, triumphing over him, </l>
            <l>And lastly with my Rapier slew him dead. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e132650">
            <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
            <l>O Heavens! justly have you tane revenge. </l>
            <l>But thou, thou murtherous adulterous slave, </l>
            <l>What Bull of Phalaris, what strange device, </l>
            <l>Shall we invent to take away thy life? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e132700">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>If Edward and the Empress, whom I sav'd, </l>
            <l>Will not requite it now, and save my life, </l>
            <l>Then let me die, contentedly I die, </l>
            <l>Having at last reveng'd my Fathers death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e132750">
            <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
            <l>Villain, not all the world shall save thy life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e132770">
            <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
            <l>Hadst thou not been Author of my Hedewicks death, </l>
            <l>I would have certainly sav'd thee from death; </l>
            <l>But if my Sentence now may take effect, </l>
            <l>I would adjudge the Villain to be hang'd </l>
            <l>As here the Jewes are hang'd in Germany. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e132830">
            <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
            <l>Young Prince it shall be so; go dragg the Slave </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000372-039-a"/>
            <l>Unto the place of execution: </l>
            <l>There let the Iudas, on a Jewish Gallowes, </l>
            <l>Hang by the heels between two English Mastives, </l>
            <l>There feed on Doggs, let Doggs there feed on thee, </l>
            <l>And by all means prolong his miserie. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-alexander" xml:id="eng000372-e132900">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>O might thy self and all these English Currs, </l>
            <l>Instead of Mastive-Doggs hang by my side, </l>
            <l>How sweetly would I tugg upon your Flesh. </l>
            <stage xml:id="eng000372-e132940">Exit Alex. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-saxony" xml:id="eng000372-e132950">
            <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
            <l>Away with him, suffer him not to speak. </l>
            <l>And now my lords, Collen, Tryer, and Barndenburg, </l>
            <l>Whose Hearts are bruz'd to think upon these woes, </l>
            <l>Though no man hast such reason as my self, </l>
            <l>We of the seven Electors that remain, </l>
            <l>After so many bloody Massacres, </l>
            <l>Kneeling upon our Knees, humbly intreat </l>
            <l>Your Excellence to be our Emperour. </l>
            <l>The Royalties of the Coronation </l>
            <l>Shall be, at Aix, shortly solemnized. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e133060">
            <speaker>Cullen. </speaker>
            <l>Brave Princely Richard now refuse it not, </l>
            <l>Though the Election be made in Tears, </l>
            <l>Joy shall attend thy Coronation. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e133100">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>It stands not with mine Honour to deny it, </l>
            <l>Yet by mine Honour, fain I would refuse it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e133130">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Uncle, the weight of all these Miseries </l>
            <l>Maketh my heart as heavy as your own, </l>
            <l>But an Imperial Crown would lighten it, </l>
            <l>Let this one reason make you take the Crown. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e133180">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>What's that sweet nephew? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-edward" xml:id="eng000372-e133200">
            <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
            <l>Sweet Uncle, this it is, </l>
            <l>Was never Englishman yet Emperour, </l>
            <l>Therefore to honour England and your self, </l>
            <l>Let private sorrow yield to publike Fame, </l>
            <l>That once an Englishman bare Caesar's name. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e133260">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>Nephew, thou hast prevail'd; Princes stand up, </l>
            <l>We humbly do accept your sacred offer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e133290">
            <speaker>Cullen. </speaker>
            <l>Then sound the Trumpets, and cry Vivat Caesar. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard #eng000372-edward #eng000372-saxony #eng000372-brandenburgh #eng000372-soldiers"
                   xml:id="eng000372-e133310">
            <speaker>All. </speaker>
            <l>Vivat Caesar. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000372-collen" xml:id="eng000372-e133330">
            <speaker>Cullen. </speaker>
            <p>Richardus Dei gratia Romanorum Imperator, semper Augustus, Comes Cornubiae. </p>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="eng000372-039-b"/>
          <sp who="#eng000372-richard" xml:id="eng000372-e133350">
            <speaker>Richard. </speaker>
            <l>Sweet Sister now let Caesar comfort you, </l>
            <l>And all the rest that yet are comfortless; </l>
            <l>Let them expect from English Caesar's hands </l>
            <l>Peace, and abundance of all earthly Joy. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
      </div>
      <trailer>FINIS </trailer>
    </body>
    <back></back>
  </text>
</TEI>
