<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000124" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Masque of the Inner Temple and Gray's Inn</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Francis</forename>
            <surname>Beaumont</surname>
          </persName>
          <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q313932</idno>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A06150.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="A06150-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull n="TCP source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">The masque of the Inner Temple and Grayes Inne Grayes Inne and the Inner Temple, presented before his Maiestie, the Queenes Maiestie, the Prince, Count Palatine and the Lady Elizabeth their Highnesses, in the Banquetting house at White-hall on Saturday the twentieth day of Februarie, 1612.</title>
                <author>Beaumont, Francis, 1584-1616.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>15 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
                <date>2001</date>
                <idno type="marc">99850786</idno>
                <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 1664.</idno>
                <idno type="vid">16013</idno>
                <idno type="DLPS">A06150</idno>
                <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2240872627</idno>
                <availability>
                  <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
                </availability>
              </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
            <biblFull n="printed source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">The masque of the Inner Temple and Grayes Inne Grayes Inne and the Inner Temple, presented before his Maiestie, the Queenes Maiestie, the Prince, Count Palatine and the Lady Elizabeth their Highnesses, in the Banquetting house at White-hall on Saturday the twentieth day of Februarie, 1612.</title>
                <author>Beaumont, Francis, 1584-1616.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[32] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Imprinted by F[elix] K[ingston] for George Norton, and are to be sold at his shoppe neere Temple-bar,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication_date">[1613]</date>
                <date type="creation_date">1613</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>
                  <p>Anonymous. By Francis Beaumont.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Printer's name and publication date from STC.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>The first leaf is blank.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Another edition, with cancel title page omitting Beaumont's name, of the edition published earlier the same year.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Signatures: A-D4.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University. Library.</p>
                </note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <person xml:id="ep000124-mercury">
            <persName>Mercury</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000124-iris">
            <persName>Iris</persName>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1613">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
    <listRelation>
      <relation name="wikidata"
                   active="https://dracor.org/entity/ep000124"
                   passive="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q7750543"/>
    </listRelation>
  </standOff>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000124-e100030">
        <pb xml:id="ep000124-001-a"/>
        <p>THE MASQVE OF THE INNER TEMPLE AND GRAYES INNE: GRAYES INNE AND THE INNER TEMPLE, PRESENTED BEFORE his Maiestie, the Queenes Maiestie, the Prince, Count Palatine and the Lady Elizabeth their Highnesses, in the Banquetting house at White-hall on Saturday the twentieth day of Februarie, 1612. </p>
        <p>By FRANCIS BEAMONT, Gent. </p>
        <p>AT LONDON, Imprinted by F. K. for George Norton, and are to be sold at his shoppe neere Temple-bar. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="title" xml:id="ep000124-e100070">
        <pb xml:id="ep000124-001-b"/>
        <p>THE MASQVE OF THE INNER TEMPLE AND GRAYES INNE: GRAYES INNE AND THE INNER TEMPLE, PRESENTED BEFORE his Maiestie, the Queenes Maiestie, the Prince, Count Palatine and the Lady Elizabeth their Highnesses, in the Banquetting house at White-hall on Saturday the twentieth day of Februarie, 1612. </p>
        <p>AT LONDON, Imprinted by F. K. for George Norton, and are to be sold at his shoppe neere Temple-bar. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="introduction" xml:id="ep000124-e100100">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000124-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000124-002-b"/>
        <head>THE MASKE OF THE INNER TEMPLE AND GRAYES INNE, GRAYES INNE and the Inner Temple, presented before his Maiestie, the Queenes, &amp;c. </head>
        <p>THis Maske was appointed to haue beene presented the Shroue-tuesday before, at which time the Maskers with their attendants and diuers others gallant young Gentlemen of both houses, as their conuoy, set forth from Winchester house which was the Rendezvous towards the Court, about seuen of the clocke at night. </p>
        <p>This voyage by water was performed in great Triumph. The gentlemen Maskers being placed by themselues in the Kings royall barge with the rich furniture of state, and adorned with a great number of lights placed <pb xml:id="ep000124-003-a"/>in such order as might make best shew. </p>
        <p>They were attended with a multitude of barges and gallies, with all variety of lowde Musicke, and seuerall peales, of Ordnance. And led by two Admiralls. </p>
        <p>Of this shew his Maiesty was gratiously pleased to take view, with the Prince, the Count Palatine, and the Lady Elizabeth: their highnesses at the windowes of his priuy gallerie vpon the water, till their landing, which was at the priuy staires; where they were most honorablie receiued by the Lord Chamberlaine, and so conducted to the Vestry. </p>
        <p>The Hall was by that time filled with company of very good fashion, but yet so as a very great number of principall Ladies, and other noble persons were not yet come in, wherby it was foreseen that the roome would be so scanted as might haue been inconuenient. And there vpon his Maiesty was most gratiously pleased with the consent of the gentlemen Maskers, to put off the night vntil Saturday following with this special fauour and priuiledge, that there should bee no let, <pb xml:id="ep000124-003-b"/>as to the outward ceremony of magnificence vntill that time. </p>
        <p>At the day that it was presented, there was a choice roome reserued for the gentlemen, of both their houses, who comming in troope about seuen of the clocke, receiued that speciall honor and noble fauour, as to be brought to their places, by the Right Honourable the Earle of Northampton, Lord Priuie Seale. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000124-e100170">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000124-004-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000124-004-b"/>
        <head>TO THE WORTHIE SIR FRANCIS BACON, HIS MAIESTIES SOLLICITOR GENErall, and the graue and learned Bench of the anciently allied houses of Grayes Inne, and the Inner Temple, the Inner Temple, and Grayes Inne. </head>
        <p>YEe that spared no time nor trauell, in the setting forth, ordering, &amp; furnishing of this Masque, being the first fruits of honor in this kinde, which these two societies haue offered to his Maiestie: Will not thinke much now to looke backe vpon the effects of your owne care and worke: for that whereof the successe was then doubtfull, is now happily performed and gratiously accepted. And that which you were then to thinke of in straites of time, you may now peruse at leysure: And you Sir Francis Bacon especially, as you did then by your countenance, and louing affection aduance it, so let your good word grace it, and defend it, which is able to adde value to the greatest, and least matters. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="text" xml:id="ep000124-e100200">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000124-005-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000124-005-b"/>
        <head>THE DEVISE OR ARGVMENT OF THE MASQVE. </head>
        <p>Iupiter and Iuno willing to doe honour to the Mariage of the two famous Riuers Thamesis and Rhone, imploy their Messengers seuerally, Mercurie and Iris for that purpose. They meete and contend: then Mercurie for his part brings forth an Anti-masque all of Spirits or diuine Natures; but yet not of one kinde or liuerie (because that had been so much in vse heretofore) but as it were in consort like to broken Musicke: And preseruing the proprietie of the deuise; for that Riuers in nature are maintained either by Springs from beneath, or Shewers from aboue: He raiseth foure of the Naiades out of the Fountaines, and bringeth <pb xml:id="ep000124-006-a"/>downe fiue of the Hyades out of the Cloudes to daunce hereupon Iris scoffes at Mercurie for that hee had deuised a daunce but of one Sexe, which could haue no life: but Mercurie who was prouided for that exception, and in token that the Match should be blessed both with Loue and Riches calleth forth out of the Groues foure Cupids, and brings downe from Iupiters Altar foure Statuaes of gold and siluer to daunce with the Nymphes and Starres: in which daunce the Cupids being blinde, and the Statuaes hauing but halfe life put into them, and retaining still somewhat of their old nature, giueth fit occasion to new and strange varieties both in the Musick and paces. This was the first Anti-masque. </p>
        <p>Then Iris for her part in scorne of this high-flying deuise, and in token that the Match shall likewise be blessed with the loue of the Common People, calles to Flora her confederate (for that the Moneths of flowers are likewise the Moneths of sweete shewers, and Raine bowes) to bring in a May daunce or Rurall daunce, consisting likewise not of <pb xml:id="ep000124-006-b"/>any suted persons, but of a confusion or commixture of all such persons as are naturall and proper for Countrey sports. This is the second Anti-masque. </p>
        <p>Then Mercurie and Iris after this vying one vpon the other, seeme to leaue their contention; and Mercurie by the consent of Iris brings downe the Olympian Knights, intimating that Iupiter hauing after a long discontinuance reuiued the Olympian games, and summoned thereunto from all parts the liueliest &amp; actiuest persons that were had enioyned them before they fell to their games to doe honour to these Nuptials. The Olympian games portend to the Match, Celebritie, Victorie, and Felicitie. This was the maine Masque. </p>
        <p>The Fabricke was a Mountaine with two descents, and seuered with two Trauesses. </p>
        <div type="part" xml:id="ep000124-e100250">
          <head>At the entrance of the King. </head>
          <p>THe first Trauers was drawne, and the lower descent of the Mountaine discouered, which was the Pendant of a hill to <pb xml:id="ep000124-007-a"/>life, with diuers boscages and Grouets vpon the steepe or hanging grounds thereof; and at the foote of the Hill, foure delicate Fountaines running with water and bordered with sedges and water flowers. </p>
          <p>Iris first appeared; and presently after Mercurie striuing to ouertake her. </p>
          <p>Iris apparelled in a robe of discoulored Taffita figured in variable colours, like the Raine-bowe, a cloudie wreath on her head, and Tresses. </p>
          <p>Mercurie in doublet and hose of white Taffita, a white hat, wings on his shoulders and feet, his Caduceus in his hand, speaking to Iris as followeth: </p>
          <sp who="#ep000124-mercury" xml:id="ep000124-e100300">
            <speaker>MERCVRIE. </speaker>
            <l>STay, Stay. </l>
            <l>Stay light foot Iris, for thou striuest in vaine, </l>
            <l>My wings are nimbler then thy feete. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000124-iris" xml:id="ep000124-e100340">
            <speaker>IRIS. </speaker>
            <l>Away, </l>
            <l>Dissembling Mercury; my messages </l>
            <l>Aske honest haste, not like those wanton ones </l>
            <l>Your thundring father sends. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000124-007-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000124-mercury" xml:id="ep000124-e100390">
            <speaker>MERCVRIE. </speaker>
            <l>Stay foolish Maid, </l>
            <l>Or I will take my rise vpon a hill, </l>
            <l>When I perceiue thee seated in a cloud, </l>
            <l>In all the painted glorie that thou hast, </l>
            <l>And neuer cease to clap my willing wings, </l>
            <l>Till I catch hold of thy discolour'd Bow, </l>
            <l>And shiuer it beyond the angry power </l>
            <l>Of your curst Mistresse, to make vp againe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000124-iris" xml:id="ep000124-e100480">
            <speaker>IRIS. </speaker>
            <l>Hermes forbeare, Iuno will chide and strike; </l>
            <l>Is great Ioue iealous that I am imploy'd </l>
            <l>On her loue errands? she did neuer yet </l>
            <l>Claspe weake mortalitie in her white armes, </l>
            <l>As he hath often done: I onely come </l>
            <l>To celebrate the long wisht Nuptials, </l>
            <l>Heere in Olympia, which are now perform'd </l>
            <l>Betwixt two goodly Riuers, which haue mixt </l>
            <l>Their gentle rising waues, and are to grow </l>
            <l>Into a thousand streames, great as themselues; </l>
            <l>I need not name them, for the sound is lowde </l>
            <l>In heauen and earth, and I am sent from her </l>
            <l>The Queene of Mariage, that was present heere, </l>
            <l>And smil'd to see them ioyne, and hath not chid </l>
            <l>Since it was done: good Hermes let me go. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000124-008-a"/>
          <sp who="#ep000124-mercury" xml:id="ep000124-e100640">
            <speaker>MERCVRIE. </speaker>
            <l>Nay you must stay, Ioues message is the same, </l>
            <l>Whose eies are lightning, and whose voice is thunder, </l>
            <l>Whose breath is any winde, he will, who knowes </l>
            <l>How to be first on earth as well as heauen. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000124-iris" xml:id="ep000124-e100690">
            <speaker>IRIS. </speaker>
            <l>But what hath he to doe with Nuptiall rights? </l>
            <l>Let him keepe state vpon his starry throne, </l>
            <l>And fright poore mortals with his thunderbolts, </l>
            <l>Leauing to vs the mutuall darts of eyes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000124-mercury" xml:id="ep000124-e100740">
            <speaker>MERCVRIE. </speaker>
            <l>Alas, when euer offer'd he t'abridge </l>
            <l>Your Ladies power, but onely now in these, </l>
            <l>Whose match concernes his generall gouernment? </l>
            <l>Hath not each god a part in these high ioyes? </l>
            <l>And shall not he the King of gods presume </l>
            <l>Without proud Iunoes licence? let her know </l>
            <l>That when enamor'd Ioue first gaue her power </l>
            <l>To linke soft hearts in Vndissolued bonds, </l>
            <l>He then foresaw, and to himselfe reseru'd </l>
            <l>The honor of this Mariage: thou shalt stand </l>
            <l>Still as a Rocke, while I to blesse this feast </l>
            <l>Will summon vp with my all charming rod, </l>
            <l>The Nymphes of fountains, from whose watry locks </l>
            <l>Hung with the dew of blessing and encrease, </l>
            <l>The greedie Riuers take their nourishment. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000124-008-b"/>
            <l>You Nymphes, who bathing in your loued springs, </l>
            <l>Beheld these Riuers in their infancie, </l>
            <l>And ioy'd to see them, when their circled heads </l>
            <l>Refresht' the aire, and spread the ground with flowers: </l>
            <l>Rise from your Wells, and with your nimble feete </l>
            <l>Performe that office to this happie paire; </l>
            <l>Which in these plaines, you to Alpheus did; </l>
            <l>When passing hence through many seas vnmixt, </l>
            <l>He gain'd the fauour of his Arethuse. </l>
          </sp>
          <p>Immediatlie vpon which speech, foure Naiades arise gentlie out of their seuerall Fountaines, and present themselues vpon the Stage, attired in long habits of sea-greene Taffita, with bubbles of Christall intermixt with powdering of siluer resembling drops of water blewish Tresses on their heads, garlands of Water-Lillies. They fall into a Measure, daunce a little, then make a stand. </p>
          <sp who="#ep000124-iris" xml:id="ep000124-e101000">
            <speaker>IRIS. </speaker>
            <l>IS Hermes growne a louer, by what power </l>
            <l>Vnknowne to vs, calls he the Naiades? </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000124-009-a"/>
          <sp who="#ep000124-mercury" xml:id="ep000124-e101030">
            <speaker>MERCVRIE. </speaker>
            <l>Presumptuous Iris, I could make thee daunce </l>
            <l>Till thou forgott'st thy Ladies messages, </l>
            <l>And rann'st backe crying to her, thou shalt know </l>
            <l>My power is more, onely my breath, and this </l>
            <l>Shall moue fix'd starres, and force the firmament </l>
            <l>To yeeld the Hyades, who gouerne showers, </l>
            <l>And dewie clouds, in whose dispersed drops </l>
            <l>Thou form'st the shape of thy deceitfull Bow. </l>
            <l>You maids, who yearely at appointed times, </l>
            <l>Aduance with kindly teares, the gentle flouds, </l>
            <l>Descend, and powre your blessing on these streames, </l>
            <l>Which rolling downe from heauen aspiring hils, </l>
            <l>And now vnited in the fruitfull vales; </l>
            <l>Beare all before them rauisht with their ioy, </l>
            <l>And swell in glorie till they know no bounds. </l>
          </sp>
          <p>Fiue Hyades descend softly in a cloud from the firmament, to the middle part of the hill, apparelled in skie-coloured Taffita robes, spangled like the Heauens, golden Tresses, and each a faire Starre on their head; from thence descend to the Stage, at whose sight the Naiades seeming to reioyce, meete and ioyne in a dance. </p>
          <pb xml:id="ep000124-009-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000124-iris" xml:id="ep000124-e101200">
            <speaker>IRIS. </speaker>
            <l>GReat witte and power hath Hermes to contriue </l>
            <l>A liuelesse dance, which of one sexe consists. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000124-mercury" xml:id="ep000124-e101230">
            <speaker>MERCVRIE. </speaker>
            <l>Alas poore Iris, Venus hath in store </l>
            <l>A secret Ambush of her winged boyes, </l>
            <l>Who lurking long within these pleasant groues; </l>
            <l>First strucke these Louers with their equall darts, </l>
            <l>Those Cupids shall come forth, and ioyne with these, </l>
            <l>To honor that which they themselues begun. </l>
          </sp>
          <p>Enter foure Cupids from each side of the Boscage, attired in flame coloured Taffita close to their bodie, like naked Boyes, with Bowes, Arrowes, and wings of gold; Chaplets of flowers on their heads, hoodwinckt with Tiffiny scarfs, who ioyne with the Nymphes and the Hyades in another daunce. That ended, Iris speakes. </p>
          <sp who="#ep000124-iris" xml:id="ep000124-e101310">
            <speaker>IRIS. </speaker>
            <l>BEhold the Statuaes which wise Vulcan plac'd </l>
            <l>Vnder the Altar of Olympian Ioue, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000124-010-a"/>
            <l>Shall daunce for ioy of these great Nuptialls: </l>
            <l>And gaue to them an Artificiall life, </l>
            <l>See how they moue, drawne by this heauenly ioy, </l>
            <l>Like the wilde trees, which follow'd Orpheus Harpe. </l>
          </sp>
          <p>The Statuaes enter, supposed to be before descended from Ioues Altar, and to haue been prepared in the couert with the Cupids, attending their call. </p>
          <p>These Statuaes were attired in cases of gold and siluer close to their bodie, faces, hands and feete, nothing seene but gold and siluer, as if they had been solid Images of mettall, Tresses of haire as they had been of mettall imbossed, girdles and small aprons of oaken leaues, as if they likewise had been carued or molded out of the mettall: at their comming, the Musicke changed from Violins to Hoboyes, Cornets, &amp;c. And the ayre of the Musicke was vtterly turned into a soft time, with drawing notes, excellently expressing their natures, and the Measure likewise was fitted vnto the same, and the Statuaes placed in such seuerall postures, sometimes all together in the Center of the daunce, and <pb xml:id="ep000124-010-b"/>sometimes in the foure vtmost Angles, as was very gracefull, besides the noueltie and so concluded the first Anti-masque. </p>
          <sp who="#ep000124-mercury" xml:id="ep000124-e101400">
            <speaker>MERCVRIE. </speaker>
            <l>ANd what will Iunoes Iris do for her? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000124-iris" xml:id="ep000124-e101420">
            <speaker>IRIS. </speaker>
            <l>Iust match this shew; or my Inuention failes, </l>
            <l>Had it beene worthier, I would haue inuok'd </l>
            <l>The blazing Comets, Clouds and falling Starres, </l>
            <l>And all my kindred Meteors of the Ayre </l>
            <l>To haue excell'd it, but I now must striue </l>
            <l>To imitate Confusion, therefore thou </l>
            <l>Delightfull Flora, if thou euer felt'st </l>
            <l>Encrease of sweetnesse in those blooming plants, </l>
            <l>On which the hornes of my faire bow decline; </l>
            <l>Send hither all the Rurall company, </l>
            <l>Which decke the May-games with their Countrey sports; </l>
            <l>Iuno will haue it so. </l>
          </sp>
          <p>The second Anti-masque rush in, daunce their Measure, and as rudely depart; consisting of a Pedant May Lord, May Lady, Seruingman, Chambermaide, <pb xml:id="ep000124-011-a"/>A Countrey Clowne, or Shepheard, Countrey Wench, An Host, Hostesse, A Hee Baboone, Shee Baboone, A Hee Foole, Shee Foole vshering them in. </p>
          <p>All these persons apparelled to the life, the Men issuing out of one side of the Boscage, and the Woemen from the other: the Musicke was extremely well fitted, hauing such a spirit of Countrey iolitie as can hardly be imagined; but the perpetuall laughter and applause was aboue the Musicke. </p>
          <p>The dance likewise was of the same strain; and the Dancers, or rather Actors expressed euery one their part so naturally and aptly, as when a Mans eye was caught with the one, and then past on to the other, hee could not satisfie himselfe which did best. It pleased his Maiestie to call for it againe at the end, as he did likewise for the first Anti-masque; but one of the Statuaes by that time was vndressed. </p>
          <pb xml:id="ep000124-011-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000124-mercury" xml:id="ep000124-e101580">
            <speaker>MERCVRIE. </speaker>
            <l>IRis we striue, </l>
            <l>Like windes at libertie, who should do worst </l>
            <l>Ere we returne. If Iuno be the Queene </l>
            <l>Of Mariage, let her giue happie way </l>
            <l>To what is done, in honor of the State </l>
            <l>She gouernes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000124-iris" xml:id="ep000124-e101650">
            <speaker>IRIS. </speaker>
            <l>Hermes, so it may be done </l>
            <l>Meerely in honor of the State, and these </l>
            <l>That now haue prou'd it, not to satisfie </l>
            <l>The lust of Iupiter, in hauing thankes </l>
            <l>More then his Iuno, if thy snakie rod </l>
            <l>Haue power to search the heauens, or found the sea, </l>
            <l>Or call together all the ends of earth, </l>
            <l>To bring in any thing that may do grace </l>
            <l>To vs, and these; do it, we shall be pleas'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000124-mercury" xml:id="ep000124-e101750">
            <speaker>MERCVRY. </speaker>
            <l>Then know that from the mouth of Ioue himselfe, </l>
            <l>Whose words haue wings, and need not to be borne; </l>
            <l>I tooke a message, and I bare it through </l>
            <l>A thousand yeelding clouds, and neuer stai'd </l>
            <l>Till his high will was done: the Olympian games </l>
            <l>Which long haue slept, at these wish'd Nuptials, </l>
            <l>He pleas'd to haue renew'd and all his Knights </l>
            <l>Are gathered hither, who within their tents </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000124-012-a"/>
            <l>Rest on this hill, vpon whose rising head. </l>
            <l>Behold Ioues Altar, and his blessed Priests </l>
            <l>Mouing about it: come you holy men, </l>
            <l>And with your voices draw these youthes along, </l>
            <l>That till Ioues musicke call them to their games, </l>
            <l>Their actiue sports may giue a blest content </l>
            <l>To those, for whom they are againe begun. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="ep000124-e101910">
          <head>The Maine Masque. </head>
          <p>THe second Trauers is drawne, and the higher ascent of the Mountaine is discouered; wherein vpon a leuell after a great rise of the Hill, were placed two Pauilions: open in the front of them, the Pauilions were to sight as of cloth of gold, and they were trimmed on the inside with rich Armour and Militarie furniture hanged vp as vpon the walles; and behind the Tents there were represented in prospectiue, the tops of diuers other Tents, as if it had been a Campe. In these Pauilions were placed fifteene Olympian Knights, vpon seates a little imbowed neere the forme of a Croisant, and the Knights appeared first, as consecrated persons all in vailes, like to Coapes, of siluer Tiffinie, gathered, <pb xml:id="ep000124-012-b"/>and falling a large compasse about them, and ouer their heads high Miters with long pendants behind falling from them; the Miters were so high, that they receiued their hats and feathers, that nothing was seene but vaile: in the midst betweene both the Tents vpon the very top of the hill, being a higher leuell then that of the Tents, was placed Iupiters Altar gilt, with three great Tapers vpon golden Candlesticks burning vpon it: and the foure Statuaes, two of gold, and two of siluer, as supporters, and Iupiters Priests in white robes about it. </p>
          <p>Vpon the sight of the King, the vailes of the Knights did fall easilie from them, and they appeared in their owne habit. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="ep000124-e101940">
          <head>The Knight's attire. </head>
          <p>ARming doublets of Carnation satten embrodered with Blazing Starres of siluer plate, with powderings of smaller Starres betwixt; gorgets of siluer maile; long hose of the same, with the doublets laide with siluer <pb xml:id="ep000124-013-a"/>lace spangled, and enricht with embroderie betweene the lace; Carnation like stockins imbrodered all ouer; garters and roses sutable; Pumpes of Carnation satten imbrodered as the doublets; hats of the same stuffe and embroderie cut like a helmet before, the hinder part cut into Scallops, answering the skirts of their doublets; the bands of the hats were wreathes of siluer in forme of garlands of wilde Oliues, white feathers with one fall of Carnation; Belts of the same stuffe and embrodered with the doublet; Siluer swords; little Italian bands and cuffes embrodered with siluer faire long Tresses of haire. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="ep000124-e101960">
          <head>The Priests habits. </head>
          <p>LOng roabes of white Taffita; long white heads of haire: The high-Priest a cap of white silke shagge close to his head, with two labels at the eares, the midst rising in forme of a Pyramis, in the top thereof a branch of siluer, euery Priest playing vpon a Lute: twelue in number. </p>
          <pb xml:id="ep000124-013-b"/>
          <p>The Priests descend and sing this song following; after whom the Knights likewise descends first laying aside their vailes belts, and swords. </p>
          <lg>
            <head>The first Song. </head>
            <l>SHake off your heauy traunce, </l>
            <l>And leape into a daunce, </l>
            <l>Such as no mortals vse to treade, </l>
            <l>Fit only for Apollo </l>
            <l>To play to, for the Moone to lead, </l>
            <l>And all the Starres to follow. </l>
          </lg>
          <p>The Knights by this time are all descended and fallen into their place, and then daunce their first Measure. </p>
          <lg>
            <head>The second Song. </head>
            <l>ON blessed youthes, for loue doth pause </l>
            <l>Laying aside his grauer lawes </l>
            <l>For this deuice, </l>
            <l>And at the wedding such a paire, </l>
            <l>Each daunce is taken for a praier, </l>
            <l>Each song a sacrifice. </l>
          </lg>
          <pb xml:id="ep000124-014-a"/>
          <p>The Knights daunce their second Measure. </p>
          <lg>
            <head>The third Song. </head>
            <head>Single. </head>
            <l>MOre pleasing were these sweet delights, </l>
            <l>If Ladies mou'd as well as Knights; </l>
            <l>Runne eu'ry one of you and catch </l>
            <l>A Nymph in honor of this match; </l>
            <l>And whisper boldly in her eare, </l>
            <l>Ioue will but laugh, if you forsweare. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <head>All. </head>
            <l>And this daye's sinnes he doth resolue </l>
            <l>That we his Priests should all absolue. </l>
          </lg>
          <p>The Knights take their Ladies to daunce with them Galliards, Durets, Corantoes, &amp;c. and leade them to their places. Then loude Musicke sound's, supposed to call them to their Olympian games. </p>
          <lg>
            <head>The fourth Song. </head>
            <l>YE should stay longer if we durst, </l>
            <l>Away, alas that he that first </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000124-014-b"/>
            <l>Gaue Time wilde wings to fly away, </l>
            <l>Hath now no power to make him stay. </l>
            <l>But though these games must needs be plaid, </l>
            <l>I would this Paire, when they are laid, </l>
            <l>And not a creature nie them, </l>
            <l>Could catch his scythe, as he doth passe, </l>
            <l>And cut his wings, and breake his glasse, </l>
            <l>And keepe him euer by them. </l>
          </lg>
          <p>The Knights daunce their parting Measure and ascend, put on their Swords and Belts; during which time, the Priests sing the fifth and last Song. </p>
          <lg>
            <l>PEace and silence be the guide </l>
            <l>To the Man, and to the Bride, </l>
            <l>If there be a ioy yet new </l>
            <l>In mariage, let it fall on you, </l>
            <l>That all the world may wonder. </l>
            <l>If we should stay, we should doe worse, </l>
            <l>And turne our blessing to a curse, </l>
            <l>By keeping you asunder. </l>
          </lg>
        </div>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated">
        <head>Machine-generated castlist</head>
        <list n="161-c1axw">
          <item n="9">
            <seg type="character_name">c1axw-mercury</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="8">
            <seg type="character_name">c1axw-iris</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
          </item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
