<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000458" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The rape, or, The innocent impostors a tragedy acted at the Theatre-Royal by Their Majesties servants.</title>
        <author>
<!--Brady, Nicholas-->
          <persName>
            <forename>Nicholas</forename>
            <surname>Brady</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A29152.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <p>
            This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is available for reuse, according to the terms of
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>
            . The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
          </p>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull>
              <titleStmt>
                <title>The rape, or, The innocent impostors a tragedy acted at the Theatre-Royal by Their Majesties servants.</title>
                <author>Brady, Nicholas, 1659-1726.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[8], 56 p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Printed for F. Saunders ...,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                <date>1692.</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>Attributed to Nicholas Brady. Cf. Nicoll, A. Hist. of Engl. drama, 1660-1900, 1961, v. 1, p. 394.</note>
                <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc/>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000458-e10">
        <pb xml:id="ep000458-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000458-001-b"/>
        <p>THE RAPE: OR, THE <hi>Innocent Impostors</hi>, A TRAGEDY. Acted at the Theatre-Royal By Their MAJESTIES SERVANTS. </p>
        <q>
          <seg xml:lang="unk">〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>. </q>
        <bibl>Hom. </bibl>
        <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>F. Saunders</hi>, at the Blue-Anchor in the Lower Walk of the New-Exchange, 1692. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000458-e120">
        <pb xml:id="ep000458-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000458-002-b"/>
        <head>To the Right Honourable CHARLES EARL OF DORSET and MIDDLESEX, &amp;c. </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My Lord, </salute>
        </opener>
        <p>WEre I not sufficiently assured, that your Candour is as great as your Judgment, I should not have expos'd the following Trifle to your Lordship's Censure; whose discerning Eyes would not fail to discover the smallest fault, did not your Goodness draw a veil over them: It is to that I humbly offer up this youthful Essay, which aims no higher than to obtain your Pardon, since it cannot pretend to your Approbation, having nothing to recommend it, but the Zeal of the Presenter: And this, my Lord, has been growing up with me from my earliest Years; that extraordinary Genius, and those admirable Qualifications, which distinguish your Lordship <pb xml:id="ep000458-003-a"/>from the rest of Mankind, having created in me a proportionable respect and Reverence for their Owner, as soon as I was capable to taste true Sense, or to relish the excellency of those Writings with which your Lordship has sometimes been pleased to oblige the World. But as these Considerations gave me a very great Esteem and Veneration for your Lordship; so that which raised them to the highest degree imaginable, is that hearty Zeal, and unaffected Sincerity, with which you daily labour to support the Interest of that Government, for which I have been no inconsiderable Sufferer: And as this engages me in your Lordship's Service with all possible Devotion, so give me leave to hope that it entitles me in some measure to your Lordship's Protection; since the very same Principle causes us mean ones to suffer for it, which engages those of your exalted Quality to strengthen and uphold it; namely, a true Affection to the <hi>Protestant Religion</hi>, and the <hi>English Liberties</hi>; Both which were visibly struck at, and had infallibly been overturned, had not Providence made use of their present Majesties to rescue and relieve them. But I forget that I am robbing the Publick, while I detain you from your more serious Employments; I shall only beg <pb xml:id="ep000458-003-b"/>your Lordship not to judge of the respect I bear you by the meanness of this Present; but to believe, that I shall always look upon the Honour of your Lordship's Patronage, as too great a Recompence for all my former Sufferings; and that no Title can be more considerable to me, than that of, </p>
        <closer>
          <salute>MY LORD, </salute>
          <signed>Your Lordship's Most Obedient, Most Obliged, and Most Humble Servant, &amp;c. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="prologue" xml:id="ep000458-e240">
        <pb xml:id="ep000458-004-a"/>
        <head>PROLOGUE, <hi rend="stage">Spoke by Mr. BETTERTON</hi>. </head>
        <l>'TIS not long since when the well judging Age, </l>
        <l>View'd nicely all the Labours of the Stage? </l>
        <l>Then ablest Writers hardly purchas'd Praise; </l>
        <l>Which now each puny Scribler gets with ease. </l>
        <l>True Nature then and solid Sence took place, </l>
        <l>Now ackward Farce prevails; with dull Grimace. </l>
        <l>Thus little Poets cheaply get a Name, </l>
        <l>Whilst Nokes, and Leigh insure the Author's fame. </l>
        <l>It were less strange if such lewd Toys as these </l>
        <l>Did the loose Race of Cap'ring Monsieurs please: </l>
        <l>Who still their Judgements like their Stomachs treat, </l>
        <l>Loath hearty Dishes of substantial Meat, </l>
        <l>And Write and Judge as slightly as they eat. </l>
        <l>But why should English, who in both excel, </l>
        <l>And always us'd to feed, and judge so well, </l>
        <l>Be now content on Snails or Herbs to dine; </l>
        <l>And for light Kick-Shaws quit the lusty Chine? </l>
        <l>Were our great Ben alive, how would he rage! </l>
        <l>How would he scourge the folly of this Age, </l>
        <l>And lash the Vermine who infect the Stage! </l>
        <l>Who with so little Nature, and less Art, </l>
        <l>A Theater would to a Booth convert: </l>
        <l>For shame redeem your Credit, and forbear </l>
        <l>To favour Drolls, such Piteous Smithfield Ware: </l>
        <l>Try if to Night you can digest a Play </l>
        <l>Cook'd in the plain, but wholesom English way. </l>
        <l>'Tis no new fashion'd Mess, nor savour'd strong </l>
        <l>With Poignant Sauce, of Dance, Machine, and Song. </l>
        <l>It boasts no gaudy Scenes to Court the view, </l>
        <l>And to save Wit, but little Musick too. </l>
        <l>Nay, what is worse, prepare for Mortial noise, </l>
        <l>Trumpet, and Drum, instead of Flute and Voice. </l>
        <l>Yet let no Beau, who hears the frightful sounds, </l>
        <l>Start, or look pale at thought of Blood, and Wounds. </l>
        <l>But Cock, talk big, and hide his growing fears: </l>
        <l>A Play-House Drum ne're beats for Volunteers. </l>
      </div>
      <div type="epilogue" xml:id="ep000458-e730">
        <pb xml:id="ep000458-004-b"/>
        <head>EPILOGUE </head>
        <byline>By Mr. SHADWELL. </byline>
        <stage xml:id="ep000458-e770">Spoken by Mrs. Bracegirdle. </stage>
        <l>HOw full of Beaus this Circle does appear </l>
        <l>Who hate all Camps, and will not leave us here, </l>
        <l>For all the Fame of <hi>Talbot, Sydney, Vere</hi>. </l>
        <l>'Las a Beau's tender, subject to catch cold, </l>
        <l>And a rough Camp will make one look so old; </l>
        <l>The cold so pinch, the heat so tan his Face, </l>
        <l>He ne'er can ogle more with any Grace: </l>
        <l>Poor miserable Beau is quite undone, </l>
        <l>The lustre of his dear Complexion gone; </l>
        <l>Besides Wounds in the Face, alack! and Woe! </l>
        <l>Some cruel Bullet may cut off a Beau: </l>
        <l>Out on't, who but a Sot wou'd not prefer </l>
        <l>Pulvillio to Match and Gunpowder? </l>
        <l>Or who would leave, so careless of dear Gut, </l>
        <l>Locket's or Long's, for a vile Sutler's Hut? </l>
        <l>Or would lie cold in Tents, or hard in Trenches, </l>
        <l>Rather than in warm Beds with pretty Wenches? </l>
        <l>Sweet Sparks do you continue in good mind, </l>
        <l>Let others follow Drums, stay you behind. </l>
        <l>You profitable Bees yield Wax and Honey, </l>
        <l>To Poets Matter, and to Players Money. </l>
        <l>If you, dear Beaus, should have so little Wit, </l>
        <l>For grinning Honour your Delights to quit, </l>
        <l>How should we want you inside Box and Pit. </l>
        <l>Spite of old English Magnanimity, </l>
        <l>Be you from Foreign fighting ever free, </l>
        <l>And let us have your sweet Society. </l>
        <l>Discourse at home of Van and Flank and Reer, </l>
        <l>And rout French Monsieurs o'er a Bottle here, </l>
        <l>But to the filthy Camp pray come not near. </l>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="ep000458-e1140">
        <pb xml:id="ep000458-005-a"/>
        <head>Dramatis Personae. </head>
        <list>
          <label>Gunderic, </label>
          <item>Mr. Betterton. </item>
          <label>Genselaric, </label>
          <item>Mr. Williams. </item>
          <label>Briomer, </label>
          <item>Mr. Hodgson. </item>
          <label>Albimer, </label>
          <item>Mr. Zibber. </item>
          <label>Rodoric, </label>
          <item>Mr. Freeman. </item>
          <label>Almeric, </label>
          <item>Mr. Harris. </item>
          <label>Agilmond, </label>
          <item>Mrs. Butler. </item>
          <label>Valdaura, </label>
          <item>Mr. <hi>Mic. Lee.</hi>
          </item>
          <label>Amalazontha, </label>
          <item>Mrs. Betterton. </item>
          <label>Rhadegonda, </label>
          <item>Mrs. Lee. </item>
          <label>Eurione, </label>
          <item>Mrs. Bracegirdle. </item>
          <label>Merinda. </label>
          <item>Mrs. Richardson. </item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <head>
        <pb n="1" xml:id="ep000458-005-b"/>THE RAPE: OR, THE <hi>Innocent Impostors</hi>, </head>
      <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="ep000458-e1560">
        <head>ACT I. </head>
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000458-e1580">
          <head>
            <hi>SCENE I. </hi>The Palace Garden. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e1610">Enter Briomer and Albimer. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e1640">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>HAS the King din'd?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e1670">
            <speaker>Albi. </speaker>
            <l>— He has; and the rich Fumes </l>
            <l>Of Corsick Wines, which he too freely swallow'd, </l>
            <l>Have made him vain; now he fights o're his Battels </l>
            <l>Of 20 Years, and numbers all his Conquests; </l>
            <l>Whilst the base Herd of Fawning Courtiers screw </l>
            <l>Their servile Looks to seeming Admiration, </l>
            <l>And cry him up a second Alexander. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e1780">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>Could you endure the fulsom Pageantry; </l>
            <l>Or be the Eccho to their loose Applause? </l>
            <l>You could not sure; a generous Disdain </l>
            <l>Shoots from your Eyes, and tells me, every Boast </l>
            <l>Of this Vain-glorious King brands us for Slaves: </l>
            <l>For sure the Haughty Vandal could not miss, </l>
            <l>In all his Catalogue of former Triumphs, </l>
            <l>That which made us his Vassals.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e1890">
            <speaker>Albi. </speaker>
            <l>— No, he did not: </l>
            <l>That was his labour'd Theme, his darling Topick, </l>
            <l>The Gothish Conquest! that he justly stil'd </l>
            <l>His Valour's Master-piece; began the Story </l>
            <pb n="2" xml:id="ep000458-006-a"/>
            <l>From the first Breach; not sixteen tedious years </l>
            <l>Had worn away the slightest Circumstance: </l>
            <l>And while he spoke, the Honourable Wounds, </l>
            <l>Which for my slaughter'd Master I took nobly, </l>
            <l>Seem'd to bleed freshly at it, like a Corpse </l>
            <l>In presence of its Murtherer— There I left him, </l>
            <l>And, in the midst of all his vain Harangue, </l>
            <l>Stole from the Presence. But no more: the King </l>
            <l>Is come to walk; let us observe at distance. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e2050">Enter <hi>Gunderic, Genselaric, Ferrismond</hi>, Guards and Attendants. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e2070">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>Was it not brave? Speak thou, Genselaric, </l>
            <l>For thou wert near me still, and thy keen Sword </l>
            <l>Well copy'd out the Deaths which mine had drawn, </l>
            <l>As if thou lik'dst the Great Original; </l>
            <l>Was't not a glorious day?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e2150">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— Yes, Royal Sir, </l>
            <l>A day which should in Vandal Annals stand, </l>
            <l>Redeem'd from time, in Golden Characters, </l>
            <l>When dreadful Rhadagaise, the Valiant Goth— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e2240">
            <speaker>Albi. </speaker>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e2260">aside </stage>
            <l>'Tis the same hateful subject; let's retire. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e2280">Ex. Bri. and Alb. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e2310">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>Thou speak'st him right; well he deserv'd that Title, </l>
            <l>Whom haughty Rome with twenty thousand Talents </l>
            <l>Brib'd high to quit her wasted Provinces, </l>
            <l>And thought it easie purchase. Him return'd, </l>
            <l>With all his Fame about him, I attempted; </l>
            <l>Him in the head of all his Troops encounter'd, </l>
            <l>Nor shun'd he my Assault. Like two large Comets </l>
            <l>That blaze in opposition we appear'd; </l>
            <l>Our waiting Armies watch'd the dreadful shock, </l>
            <l>And in our lifted arms was wrap'd the fate </l>
            <l>Of thousand Vulgar Souls. </l>
            <l>Then, my Genselaric, then Ferrismond, </l>
            <l>For you were present too, how did we tug </l>
            <l>For Empire and for life! 'till cover'd o're </l>
            <l>With well-plac'd Wounds, the Gothish Monarch sunk, </l>
            <l>And my superiour Fortune triumph'd o're him. </l>
            <l>By Heav'ns! I cou'd have hug'd my dying Foe, </l>
            <l>Almost have envy'd him, he fell so nobly! </l>
            <l>And made me sweat so hard for glorious Conquest! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e2560">
            <speaker>Fer. </speaker>
            <l>If such his Fame, (and he deserv'd no less,) </l>
            <l>What then is yours, who bravely ovecrame him? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e2600">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>Right, Ferrismond, and 'tis for that I prize </l>
            <l>This Conquest more than all my other Trophies: </l>
            <l>In all my chase of Fame, I never met </l>
            <l>A braver Foe; for this his Captive Queen </l>
            <pb n="3" xml:id="ep000458-006-b"/>
            <l>And all his Female Issue I preserv'd; </l>
            <l>The Males, to make my Conquest more secure, </l>
            <l>Embrac'd their Father's Fate.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e2700">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— 'Twas fitting Policy. </l>
            <l>But, sacred Sir, your Pardon, if I dare </l>
            <l>To sound the Secrets of your Royal Bosom, </l>
            <l>And humbly beg to learn why you design </l>
            <l>To wed the eldest of those Princely Orphans </l>
            <l>To Agilmond, our lovely Prince, and graft </l>
            <l>A Captive Cien on your Royal Stock? </l>
            <l>Now must I beg to know, what known will blast me. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e2810">Aside. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e2820">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>I'le tell thee, Nephew, </l>
            <l>For thou art brave, and therefore 'tis I love thee. </l>
            <l>Ten years I reap'd the precious sweets of Love </l>
            <l>Without success; for tho' my fruitful Queen </l>
            <l>Was blest with numerous Births, yet all were Female </l>
            <l>A Sex unfit for Sway; and my large Conquests </l>
            <l>Must have been parcell'd out to Neighbour Princes, </l>
            <l>As they grew ripe for Wedlock: Thus I murmur'd, </l>
            <l>Till angry Fate snatch'd all my blooming Offspring, </l>
            <l>And crush'd them in the Blossom— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e2940">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— I remember, </l>
            <l>'Twas just before the Gothish Expedition: </l>
            <l>And soon the heat of War dry'd up your Tears. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e3000">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>It did— </l>
            <l>But when I parted from my Queen, I left her </l>
            <l>Just ready to lay down another Burthen; </l>
            <l>Then grief and rage forc'd out this Solemn Vow: </l>
            <l>If still you blast my Hopes, and your full Womb </l>
            <l>Again disclose another Female Birth, </l>
            <l>By my just rage it dies.— This said, we parted. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e3090">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>Something like this was buzz'd about the Court, </l>
            <l>Scatter'd in Whispers by the attending Ladies; </l>
            <l>But soon it dy'd; and I had almost lost </l>
            <l>The loose remembrance, 'till your words reviv'd it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e3150">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>Th' Event of things soon bury'd it: For Fate </l>
            <l>Shook at my dire Resolve, and as o're-aw'd, </l>
            <l>Cast in a Nobler Mold her pliant Issue, </l>
            <l>And Stamp'd it with the Image of a Man. </l>
            <l>The welcome News, by winged Couriers born, </l>
            <l>Found me returning from my Gothish Conquest, </l>
            <l>And cover'd o're with Lawrels.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e3250">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— What could Fate </l>
            <l>Do more, than make you great at once and happy? </l>
            <l>Than give at once two such important Blessings, </l>
            <l>A Kingdom and an Heir? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e3310">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>'Twas much indeed: And I with fitting joy </l>
            <pb n="4" xml:id="ep000458-007-a"/>
            <l>Receiv'd the mighty Presents— </l>
            <l>But oh! Genselaric, </l>
            <l>How little do my present Comforts answer </l>
            <l>The large Idea which my thoughts then form'd! </l>
            <l>The Prince, my Valiant Nephew— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e3400">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— Sacred Sir, </l>
            <l>Give your thoughts vent; and oh! forbid it, Heav'n, </l>
            <l>That Sigh shou'd be occasion'd by the Prince, </l>
            <l>The lovely Prince. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e3460">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— The lovely Prince indeed, </l>
            <l>And there thou summ'st his Praise: I wish thou could'st, </l>
            <l>Instead of that faint Epithet, have put </l>
            <l>The Manly or the Valiant: but alas! </l>
            <l>His outward Composition shews him Woman </l>
            <l>In all things but the Sex; and much I fear </l>
            <l>His very Soul's a Woman. Balls and Dances, </l>
            <l>The Conversation of conceited Ladies </l>
            <l>And fluttering Courtiers, are his chief delight: </l>
            <l>He loves not Arms, to break the Warlike Steed, </l>
            <l>Or dart the well-aim'd Javelin. Is he fit </l>
            <l>To hold the Reins of stubborn Conquer'd Nations, </l>
            <l>To keep my Fame up, and convey my Glory </l>
            <l>To Ages yet to come?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e3620">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— His tender years </l>
            <l>Are yet unripe for Action; time may change </l>
            <l>And form his thoughts to a more Manly temper. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e3670">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>'Tis true indeed, it may; but that forc'd Smile </l>
            <l>In which you dress your Face, seems to inform me, </l>
            <l>That you my Armies headed at his Years, </l>
            <l>And brought home Victory. Here lies my Grief, </l>
            <l>The Remedy's behind. The conquer'd Goths, </l>
            <l>Who brook my Sway uneasily, though rank'd </l>
            <l>With my own Vandals both in Trust and Favour, </l>
            <l>Yet wish a Prince whom they may call their own. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e3790">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>I have of late observ'd a sullen haughtiness </l>
            <l>In most of them; the sign of forc'd Respect, </l>
            <l>And ebbing Duty.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e3840">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— If to me they pay </l>
            <l>But an unwilling Service, what must Agilmond, </l>
            <l>Weak Agilmond expect, unless secur'd </l>
            <l>By politick desences? Therefore 'tis </l>
            <l>That I design to wed him to Eurione, </l>
            <l>The eldest of the Captive Princesses; </l>
            <l>That so her Title may secure his Interest, </l>
            <l>And the respect they pay her Father's Blood </l>
            <l>Blot out the Hatred which they owe to mine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e3980">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>But, Royal Sir, forgive me, if I tell you </l>
            <pb n="5" xml:id="ep000458-007-b"/>
            <l>The Prince is much averse to this design, </l>
            <l>And all the Tribute of his Heart and Eyes </l>
            <l>Are to the younger paid, the proud Valdaura. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e4050">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>Too well I know it, but I know as well </l>
            <l>To make my self obey'd: Valdaura! no, </l>
            <l>Her Temper's too imperious; in her Face </l>
            <l>I see the fierceness of her Father's looks; </l>
            <l>It is not safe to plant too near my Throne </l>
            <l>One of her haughty nature. But I trifle; </l>
            <l>My Resolution's fix'd unalterably, </l>
            <l>Nor dares he thwart my Will,— </l>
            <l>Who have a double Title to his Duty, </l>
            <l>As Father, and as King. Go you, Genselaric, </l>
            <l>Attend the Prince, and bid him wait my Pleasure </l>
            <l>Upon the Terrace Walk.— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e4210">Exeunt <hi>Gunderick, Ferrismond</hi>, Guards and Attendants, </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e4230">
            <speaker>Gen. solus. </speaker>
            <l>Death to my hopes! he's fix'd unmoveably, </l>
            <l>And all my Wishes blasted: But shall I, </l>
            <l>Who nobly past through twenty rough Campaigns, </l>
            <l>Tamely look on, and see a puling Boy, </l>
            <l>A young effeminate Stripling, ravish from me </l>
            <l>A Mistress and a Crown! It must not be: </l>
            <l>Let Patient Slavish Fools drudge on, and bear </l>
            <l>Th' uneasie Yoak of forc'd Obedience; </l>
            <l>Such tame results as those never attend </l>
            <l>The Lover and the Brave— Ambition single </l>
            <l>Shou'd be too strong a Match for feeble Virtue; </l>
            <l>But when </l>
            <l>Almighty Love does with Ambition close, </l>
            <l>What Force can their united Pow'r oppose? </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e4390">Exit. </stage>
        </div>
        <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000458-e4400">
          <head>SCENE a Chamber-Royal. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e4430">Enter <hi>Rhadegonda, Eurione</hi>, and Valdaura. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e4460">
            <speaker>Rhad. </speaker>
            <l>Altho' the Honour Gunderick designs </l>
            <l>Our ruin'd Family by this Alliance, </l>
            <l>Be greater than our humble hopes cou'd aim at: </l>
            <l>Yet still methinks a melancholly Cloud </l>
            <l>Hangs on Eurione, and seems to tell me, </l>
            <l>The Prince's coldness damps her comforts more. </l>
            <l>Than all his Father's kindness can assure them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e4570">
            <speaker>Eur. </speaker>
            <l>Madam, I must confess the Prince's coldness </l>
            <l>Disturbs my troubled Breast; but 'tis because </l>
            <l>I blush to think that one who shares your Blood </l>
            <l>Should live to bear a slight.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e4630">
            <speaker>Val. </speaker>
            <l>— Oh! my lov'd Sister, </l>
            <pb n="6" xml:id="ep000458-008-a"/>
            <l>How well that thought becomes your Royal Birth! </l>
            <l>For the Prince, </l>
            <l>Think not, Eurione, charming as he is, </l>
            <l>That I will e'er receive his loath'd Addresses, </l>
            <l>Though lately paid with undissembled fervour: </l>
            <l>His slight of you provokes my hatred more </l>
            <l>Than all his Court to me can raise my love. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e4740">
            <speaker>Rhad. </speaker>
            <l>Be careful though, my Daughter, how you treat </l>
            <l>The youthful Prince; and since you must deny him, </l>
            <l>Mix no disdain to make refusal harsher: </l>
            <l>Humility and Meekness best become </l>
            <l>The Conquer'd and the Captive.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e4810">
            <speaker>Val. </speaker>
            <l>— True, we are so, </l>
            <l>I mean our Bodies, but our Souls are free,— </l>
            <l>Those he cou'd neither Captivate nor Conquer: </l>
            <l>The Vandal Triumph is too great already; </l>
            <l>Let's not encrease it, Madam, nor allow </l>
            <l>That it can reach our minds— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e4900">
            <speaker>Rhad. </speaker>
            <l>— No, my Valdaura; </l>
            <l>Just Heav'n forbid that Rhadagaise's Widow </l>
            <l>Shou'd own a thought so mean! but sit it is </l>
            <l>We shou'd dissemble; since a short Complaisance </l>
            <l>To all the Actions of our future life, </l>
            <l>May give unbounded Freedom.— You, Valdaura, </l>
            <l>Retire a while; and when my faithful Briomer </l>
            <l>And Albimer arrive, conduct 'em hither. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e5050">Exit Valdaura. </stage>
            <l>Now, my Eurione, disburthen now </l>
            <l>Your swelling Breast of its uneasie load, </l>
            <l>And breathe your Griefs into a Mother's Ear: </l>
            <l>Love is no Crime, and sure the Prince has Charms </l>
            <l>Sufficient to excuse a Female fondness; </l>
            <l>Nor did you love unsought; and if your Passion </l>
            <l>Continues still to Flame when his grows cold, </l>
            <l>Unhappy it may make you, but not faulty. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e5160">
            <speaker>Eur. </speaker>
            <l>Blest be those Friendly and Relenting Pow'rs </l>
            <l>That have inspir'd your Breast with such indulgence! </l>
            <l>'Tis true, I love, still love th' ingrateful Prince; </l>
            <l>False as he is, he's the same Charmer still, </l>
            <l>Lord of my tender'st and most dear Affections: </l>
            <l>And though I dare not to my Rival Sister, </l>
            <l>Whose Spirit awes me, own my lasting Passion, </l>
            <l>It burns as bright as ever.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e5260">
            <speaker>Rhad. </speaker>
            <l>—— Cherish it: </l>
            <l>Valdaura's scorn will quickly send him back </l>
            <l>To find a gentler Treatment in your Love: </l>
            <l>Besides, the King commands him, and his Will, </l>
            <l>Though ne'er so rash, when he is once resolv'd, </l>
            <pb n="7" xml:id="ep000458-008-b"/>
            <l>Cannot be safely thwarted.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e5350">
            <speaker>Eur. </speaker>
            <l>— Still I fear; </l>
            <l>For sure my haughty Sister cannot long </l>
            <l>Resist the lovely Prince.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e5400">
            <speaker>Rhad. </speaker>
            <l>— Fear not, Eurione, </l>
            <l>Take it upon a Queen, and Mother's word, </l>
            <l>Valdaura cannot wrong you. But no more, </l>
            <l>She comes, and with her Briomer and Albimer: </l>
            <l>Withdraw a while, and try to ease your Griefs </l>
            <l>With pleasing hopes of his returning Passion. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e5520">Exit Eurione. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e5540">Enter <hi>Valdaura, Briomer</hi>, and Albimer. </stage>
            <l>Welcome, my Noble Friends; you that continue </l>
            <l>Faithful and just to ruin'd Majesty, </l>
            <l>I waited for your coming. </l>
            <l>Valdaura, sooth </l>
            <l>Your Sister in her Errour; 'tis not safe </l>
            <l>To trust her with the mighty secret yet. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e5640">Exit Valdaura. </stage>
            <l>Have you, my Lords, dispers'd the weighty News </l>
            <l>Amongst my Faithful Goths, that yet a Prince </l>
            <l>Of Rhadagaise's Royal Blood is living, </l>
            <l>And if they dare but struggle for their Freedom, </l>
            <l>Will soon appear to head them?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e5730">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>— Madam, we have, </l>
            <l>And they with undissembled joy receiv'd it, </l>
            <l>But mix'd with some Distrust; they seem to doubt </l>
            <l>The mighty Blessing; but assur'd of that, </l>
            <l>They vow to Sacrifice to his just Interest </l>
            <l>What e'er they hold most dear.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e5810">
            <speaker>Albi. </speaker>
            <l>— Nor are they weak </l>
            <l>In number, or in quality; the King, </l>
            <l>To banish all resentment from their minds, </l>
            <l>And make them fond of Slavery, admits them </l>
            <l>To Offices of Profit, and of Trust; </l>
            <l>The very Troops that Guard him are not free </l>
            <l>From Gothish mixture.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e5910">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>— These are all our own, </l>
            <l>And once confirm'd that they have yet a Prince </l>
            <l>Of your Illustrious Line, will soon shake off </l>
            <l>The Vandal Yoak, which now unwillingly </l>
            <l>They bear, and seat him in his Father's Throne. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e5990">
            <speaker>Rhad. </speaker>
            <l>They know me, and my Royal word's to them </l>
            <l>Sufficient Confirmation; but to you </l>
            <l>I will unlock the Secret, how I sav'd </l>
            <l>And kept conceal'd a Treasure of such value. </l>
            <l>But here we are too open; let's retire </l>
            <pb n="8" xml:id="ep000458-009-a"/>
            <l>Into my private Closet; there we'll share </l>
            <l>A joy too great for me alone to bear. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e6080">Exeunt. Briomer drops a Paper. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e6100">Enter Genselarick and a Lady. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e6120">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>The Princess indispos'd! and will admit </l>
            <l>No Visitants?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e6160">
            <speaker>Lady. </speaker>
            <l>— My Lord, she's just laid down </l>
            <l>To take some rest, to which of late she's grown </l>
            <l>A Stranger.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e6210">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— May her sleep be soft and quiet </l>
            <l>As that of Infants— Whilst my waking thoughts, </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e6250">Exit Lady. </stage>
            <l>Are as disturb'd as Dreams of guilty Men. </l>
            <l>Ha! what is this;— </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e6280">Takes up a Paper folded. </stage>
            <l>— Though 'tis not generous </l>
            <l>To pry into the Secrets of another; </l>
            <l>A Lover, near the Chamber of his Mistress </l>
            <l>May plead a just excuse for being curious. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e6330">Opens it, and Reads. </stage>
            <floatingText type="letter">
              <body>
                <opener>
                  <salute>My Lord, </salute>
                </opener>
                <p>YOV may safely depend upon my Intelligence; I have it from no worse a hand than our Royal Mistress's; therefore be assured that when your Party is fully formed, a Prince of her own Blood shall appear to head it. Meet me without fail at the appointed place and time, where I will inform you farther. </p>
              </body>
            </floatingText>
            <l>How's this? a Faction forming? and a Prince </l>
            <l>Of Gothish Blood to head it? this confirm'd </l>
            <l>By her who best should know, the Captive Queen? </l>
            <l>Is then the cruel Policy of Gunderic </l>
            <l>Deceiv'd, and a surviving Male yet left </l>
            <l>To take sharp Vengeance for his slaughter'd Kinsmen? </l>
            <l>Kind Fate that brought this Secret to my hands, </l>
            <l>Meant not it shou'd be useless: this well manag'd </l>
            <l>May either serve my Interest, or my Love, </l>
            <l>Perhaps may forward both: let me consider— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e6510">Enter Rodorick and Almerick. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e6540">
            <speaker>Rod. </speaker>
            <l>This way the General went— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e6570">
            <speaker>Alm. </speaker>
            <l>— See there he stands; </l>
            <l>And by the fix'd composure of his look, </l>
            <l>Something uncommon fills his working thoughts: </l>
            <l>Let's wait a while.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e6630">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— The destinies of Men </l>
            <l>Are not more surely Charactred </l>
            <pb n="9" xml:id="ep000458-009-b"/>
            <l>In Fate's eternal Volume, than mine here. </l>
            <l>Suppose I tell the King, </l>
            <l>One of these two fatal Evils must attend it: </l>
            <l>Either his Rage flames high, not to be quench'd, </l>
            <l>But by the Blood o● 〈◊〉 that Royal Race, </l>
            <l>And so I give my 〈◊〉 up to Slaughter: </l>
            <l>(Horrour and 〈…〉 Shocks my Soul to think it.) </l>
            <l>Or if his Policy 〈…〉 his Anger, </l>
            <l>The Fatal 〈…〉 the Prince and her, </l>
            <l>To settle 〈…〉 and I throw </l>
            <l>The only 〈…〉 I love </l>
            <l>Into my 〈…〉— </l>
            <l>〈…〉 must not, cannot, shall not be. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e6800">
            <speaker>Rod. </speaker>
            <l>〈◊〉 seems disturb'd, as if his thoughtful Soul </l>
            <l>Were 〈…〉 betwixt two deep Designs, </l>
            <l>And doubtful which to fix on— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e6850">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>Suppose I carry it to the Captive Queen; </l>
            <l>And since the Lives of her and all her Nation </l>
            <l>Are in my Hands, say I disclose my Passion </l>
            <l>For ●●ght Eurione, and make her the Price </l>
            <l>Of my Important Silence; if that fails, </l>
            <l>Add my Assistance too, to join in it; </l>
            <l>By Heav'n it wears a forward face of hope, </l>
            <l>Nor can it fail to take— it shall be so. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e6960">
            <speaker>Alm. </speaker>
            <l>His looks clear up; the Resolution's taken, </l>
            <l>Be't what it will.— My Lord, we wait your leisure. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e7000">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>O! my best Friends, you come most opportunely: </l>
            <l>I want your kind Assistance in some matters </l>
            <l>Of mighty Moment; and so much I trust </l>
            <l>Your well experienc'd Faith, I will not doubt </l>
            <l>But you dare follow wheresoe'er I lead, </l>
            <l>Although the Path I tread be full of danger. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e7080">
            <speaker>Rod. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord, you judge us right; all our Employments </l>
            <l>Are but your Gift, when the Ungrateful Court </l>
            <l>Repuls'd and cast us off, you took us in, </l>
            <l>Stemm'd the rough Torrent, drest us in fresh Honours, </l>
            <l>And fix'd us near your self: </l>
            <l>And if for you we forfeit all, </l>
            <l>We pay but back your own. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e7170">
            <speaker>Alm. </speaker>
            <l>— Our Lives are Trifles, </l>
            <l>Which for a Drunken Friend we oft expose; </l>
            <l>How shou'd we then refuse to lay them down </l>
            <l>For you our Friend and Patron?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e7230">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— Read this Paper; </l>
            <l>The hand I guess; but to inform me farther, </l>
            <l>Are you acquainted with it? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e7280">
            <speaker>Rod. </speaker>
            <l>— Let me see, </l>
            <pb n="10" xml:id="ep000458-010-a"/>
            <l>This Writing is familiar to my eyes; </l>
            <l>And now the weighty matter it contains </l>
            <l>Instructs my Memory: 'Tis Briomer's. </l>
            <l>I oft have seen't when jointly we commanded </l>
            <l>The Vandal and the Gothish Cavalry; </l>
            <l>Most certain 'tis his own.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e7400">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— It is not doubted. </l>
            <l>Now take the Darling Secret of my Soul; </l>
            <l>I'll turn my Heart quite outwards to your view, </l>
            <l>Nor shall one thought escape you. O, my Friends, </l>
            <l>I love Eurione; love her beyond Victory </l>
            <l>Ravish'd from valiant Foes, that made Success </l>
            <l>Hang doubtful long.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e7500">
            <speaker>Rod. </speaker>
            <l>— She's destin'd for the Prince; </l>
            <l>And if I err not much, her Inclinations </l>
            <l>Bend that way too.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e7550">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— They're biass'd by her Interest; </l>
            <l>He's Heir to mighty Kingdoms, she a Captive. </l>
            <l>But wave we that? You see the dreadful Secret </l>
            <l>Contain'd within that Scrowl; dare you join it? </l>
            <l>I'm sure you dare; dare any thing, but basely </l>
            <l>Desert a Friend that trusts you with his life, </l>
            <l>Nay more, his Love— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e7640">
            <speaker>Alm. </speaker>
            <l>— We are your Creatures, Sir, </l>
            <l>And are resolv'd to move as you direct us. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e7680">
            <speaker>Rod. </speaker>
            <l>Besides, this blest occasion wakes the memory </l>
            <l>Of former wrongs, which call aloud for Vengeance. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e7720">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>Let me infold you thus; in this Embrace </l>
            <l>I tie my Fortunes to you: in our walk </l>
            <l>We'll settle matters further.— </l>
            <l>As some rich Merchant, when the Billows roar, </l>
            <l>Holds fast one Casket full of precious Store, </l>
            <l>Whilst all his meaner Treasure's tumbled o'er: </l>
            <l>So while Love's safe, securely I survey </l>
            <l>Fame, Profit, Honour, Virtue, cast away. </l>
            <l>Rather than see my Darling Love distrest; </l>
            <l>Let wide Destruction swallow all the rest. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e7840">Exeunt. </stage>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="ep000458-e7850">
        <pb n="11" xml:id="ep000458-010-b"/>
        <head>ACT II. </head>
        <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000458-e7870">
          <head>SCENE, a Terrace-Walk. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e7900">Enter Gunderick. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e7920">
            <l>THe Prince's ill-plac'd love to proud Valdaura, </l>
            <l>With the loud Murmurs of my Gothish Subjects, </l>
            <l>Distract my careful thoughts by Day, and haunt </l>
            <l>My restless Dreams by night. Hard Fate of Kings! </l>
            <l>Whose outward Grandure only serves to guild </l>
            <l>The Slavery they undergo within! </l>
            <l>And yet these Ills admit one common Cure, </l>
            <l>His Marriage with Eurione, a Remedy </l>
            <l>Which must not be delay'd; their Discontents, </l>
            <l>And his loose Passion, if we give them time, </l>
            <l>Will daily grow more strong; it is resolv'd, </l>
            <l>And Fate, if it had otherwise decreed, </l>
            <l>Shou'd sooner change than I.— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e8090">Enter Agilmond. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e8110">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— I was inform'd </l>
            <l>Your Majesty commanded my Attendance, </l>
            <l>I had not else presum'd to interrupt </l>
            <l>Your private thoughts— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e8170">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— Come nearer, Agilmond, </l>
            <l>Nor think your Presence interrupts my thoughts, </l>
            <l>For they were full of you.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e8230">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— I could not wish </l>
            <l>To fill a Nobler Scene; yet humbly hope </l>
            <l>That melancholly Cloud which shades your Brow </l>
            <l>Was not occasion'd by the thoughts of me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e8290">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>And yet it was: For you, my Agilmond, </l>
            <l>My careful Brain toils daily, and my Sleeps </l>
            <l>Are nightly broken; all to make you great, </l>
            <l>And to that Greatness happy— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e8360">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— Royal Sir, </l>
            <l>If still I hold your Favour, I am both; </l>
            <l>In that my Greatness lies, in that my Happiness. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e8410">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>Priz'd you my favour at so high a rate, </l>
            <l>You wou'd not dare to contradict my Will; </l>
            <l>A Will whose chief and only aim it is </l>
            <l>To make your Fortunes certain: Put not on </l>
            <l>A Face of seeming Ignorance, my meaning </l>
            <l>Is soon unriddled; why are your Addresses </l>
            <l>So coldly paid to fair Eurione, </l>
            <l>Your destin'd Bride? My Will has made her such; </l>
            <pb n="12" xml:id="ep000458-011-a"/>
            <l>And yours, if mine you valu'd as you ought, </l>
            <l>Shou'd hand in hand go with it.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e8540">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>Your Pardon, Sir, </l>
            <l>'Tis worse than Death to me to disobey you; </l>
            <l>And yet 'tis worse than that to marry one </l>
            <l>I cannot love.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e8600">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— How! cannot love? take heed, </l>
            <l>It is not safe to dally with my Anger: </l>
            <l>Is she not Chast and Fair? Of Royal Birth </l>
            <l>And Princely Education? flows there not </l>
            <l>A winning Sweetness from her? Is there ought </l>
            <l>That's hard in this Injunction?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e8680">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— Only this, </l>
            <l>'Tis hard to force Affection: fair Eurione </l>
            <l>Has Charms to Conquer any Heart, but mine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e8740">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>'Tis then because that Heart of yours is steel'd </l>
            <l>With Disobedience: but no more— Valdaura, </l>
            <l>The proud Valdaura, whom you know I hate, </l>
            <l>She is the Darling Object of your Love: </l>
            <l>And doubly disobedient as you are, </l>
            <l>You shun what I desire, and fondly seek </l>
            <l>What most I loath.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e8850">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— 'Tis my Unhappiness, </l>
            <l>To have my Actions undergo so harsh </l>
            <l>A Misconstruction: but to prove my Innocence, </l>
            <l>And that I am not what your Anger stiles me, </l>
            <l>Stubborn and Disobedient; be you pleas'd </l>
            <l>To cancel the Commands you laid on me </l>
            <l>To wed Eurione whom I cannot love, </l>
            <l>And I will quit all claim to fair Valdaura, </l>
            <l>Nor see, nor speak to her.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e8980">
            <speaker>Gun. </speaker>
            <l>— By Heav'n, the Boy </l>
            <l>Begins to Article, and I must treat </l>
            <l>On equal terms, and meet him half the way; </l>
            <l>Whilst his Compliance but keeps pace with mine, </l>
            <l>Moves just as far, no farther. Hear me, you </l>
            <l>That dare thus trifle with your King and Father, </l>
            <l>Hear this my fix'd Resolve: </l>
            <l>By all my Glory, by my thirst of Fame, </l>
            <l>And my great Name in War, to Morrow's Sun </l>
            <l>Shall see you Wedded to the fair Eurione, </l>
            <l>Or never more acknowledg'd as my Son. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e9120">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>O Sacred Sir! call back that dismal Vow; </l>
            <l>Kill me, and I will kiss the hand that does it; </l>
            <l>But oh! condemn me not to loath'd Embraces; </l>
            <l>See, on my Knees I beg it.— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e9180">Kneeling and Embracing his Knees. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e9190">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— Loose your hold, </l>
            <pb n="13" xml:id="ep000458-011-b"/>
            <l>Or I will force my way; thou! that art Manly </l>
            <l>In nothing but in Disobedience; </l>
            <l>That too is Womanish, 'tis Wilfulness </l>
            <l>A Female Vice; no more, you know my Will, </l>
            <l>Prepare to meet it— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e9270">Breaks from him and Exit. Agilmond lies down. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e9290">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— Rather to meet my Death, </l>
            <l>For that must be the fatal Consequence. </l>
            <l>Thus my sad Sentence runs, [<hi>To Morrow's Sun </hi>
            </l>
            <l>Shall see you Wedded to the Fair Eurione:] </l>
            <l>To Morrow's Sun will then disclose a Secret </l>
            <l>Which Sixteen Years have faithfully conceal'd: </l>
            <l>Unhappy Agilmond! thy latest Glass </l>
            <l>Of Life is running now, and the last Sand </l>
            <l>Will steal away to Morrow.— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e9430">Enter Amalazontha. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e9450">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>— I met the King </l>
            <l>With Fury in his Looks, regardlesly </l>
            <l>He past along, and in a surly tone </l>
            <l>Bad me, go teach my Son Obedience. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e9510">Sees the Prince. </stage>
            <l>See, there he lies! alas! is that a Couch </l>
            <l>Fit for the Heir of Mighty Gunderic? </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e9550">Goes to him. </stage>
            <l>What means my Agilmond? what sawcy Grief </l>
            <l>Usurps a Breast so dear to me as thine? </l>
            <l>And yet I fear to ask, for sure it is </l>
            <l>Of Mighty Weight, that bows you to the Earth </l>
            <l>As you were rooted there.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e9620">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— Forgive me, Madam, </l>
            <l>That must alarm your Ears with sounds more dismal </l>
            <l>Than Groans of Mandrakes, or the Scritch-Owl's Note; </l>
            <l>The Croaks of Ravens at a Sickman's Window </l>
            <l>Would be but Musick to the News I bear. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e9690">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>Alas! what means this dreadful Preparation? </l>
            <l>Is the great Secret of your Sex disclos'd? </l>
            <l>Has Gunderick discover'd what you are? </l>
            <l>He has not sure; for as I enter'd here </l>
            <l>He spoke to me of you, and call'd you Son. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e9770">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>'Tis true, he has not yet; but oh! to Morrow. </l>
            <l>To Morrow he has vow'd that I shall wed </l>
            <l>Eurione, and then the fatal Secret </l>
            <l>Must needs be known; and well you know his Vows, </l>
            <l>However rash, are obstinately kept. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e9850">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>— Too well I know it; </l>
            <l>Nor is this Vow the first. O! cruel Gunderick! </l>
            <l>Was't not enough, rash and inhuman Prince! </l>
            <l>That when this precious Burthen fill'd my Womb, </l>
            <l>You doom'd it then to Death? but must I now, </l>
            <l>When Sixteen Years have made it dearer to me, </l>
            <l>And ty'd it to my Heartstrings, see it Butcher'd </l>
            <pb n="14" xml:id="ep000458-012-a"/>
            <l>By thy unnatural and savage rage? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e9960">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>Be witness, Heav'n, how little that afflicts me! </l>
            <l>Your Danger sinks me, under that I bend, </l>
            <l>Unable to sustain it. Permit me, Madam, </l>
            <l>To dye for both; to Morrow dooms me; </l>
            <l>Let me but dye now; </l>
            <l>And the important Secret dies with me, </l>
            <l>And gives new life to you.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e10050">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>— No, Agilmond, </l>
            <l>Our Case is dangerous, but not desperate: </l>
            <l>Through all these Clouds I spye one Ray of Hope </l>
            <l>Break brightly forth, and gild the horrid Scene: </l>
            <l>Eurione is Virtuous and Discreet; </l>
            <l>We'll trust th'important Secret to her knowledge; </l>
            <l>And sure she will not scruple to assist </l>
            <l>Two Royal Suppliants. Come, my Agilmond, </l>
            <l>Wait on the King, and seemingly comply, </l>
            <l>Leave the Event of things to me and Heav'n; </l>
            <l>The Gods that watch'd to guard your Infant state, </l>
            <l>Will save you still, and their own Work compleat. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e10220">Exeunt. </stage>
        </div>
        <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000458-e10230">
          <head>SCENE A lonely Walk within prospect of the Palace. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e10260">Enter Briomer. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e10280">
            <l>Curse on my Negligence! to lose a Paper </l>
            <l>Of such a vast Concern! my life's wrap'd in it; </l>
            <l>My life's a trifle; but the lives of all </l>
            <l>My Countrymen, nay ev'n the Queen's and Prince's </l>
            <l>Are by my fatal carelessness expos'd. </l>
            <l>The best that I can hope, is that the Queen </l>
            <l>Her self has found it; yet suppose ev'n that, </l>
            <l>How wretched must I be! How should I look </l>
            <l>On one so much endanger'd by my Folly! </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e10380">Enter <hi>Gen. Rod. </hi>&amp; Alm. </stage>
            <l>O that I had it! tho' for every Letter </l>
            <l>I paid a ruddy drop of that rich Blood </l>
            <l>Which warms my Heart, I should not think it dear. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e10440">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>He's here! and by that gloomy look confirms me </l>
            <l>The Writing was his own, and that already </l>
            <l>He has mist the Letter; wait a while without </l>
            <l>And be not seen, I'll sound him at a distance. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e10500">Ex. Rod. &amp; Alm. </stage>
            <l>My Lord, I have observ'd, for Friendship's Eye </l>
            <l>Is quick and piercing, in your Face of late </l>
            <l>Unusual Mixtures, seriousness and joy; </l>
            <l>As if your busie Soul were burthen'd with </l>
            <l>Some weighty matter, happy at once and dangerous. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e10580">
            <pb n="15" xml:id="ep000458-012-b"/>
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>Your Eyes, my Lord, are ill Intelligencers, </l>
            <l>To represent as things of Weight and Moment, </l>
            <l>The sudden Starts of an uneven temper. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e10630">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>And yet I fear your Tongue has scarcely given </l>
            <l>So just an Information as my Eyes. </l>
            <l>But wave we this discourse: hear you no News? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e10680">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>Not I, my Lord; 'twas always my Opinion, </l>
            <l>That Curious and Inquisitive were names </l>
            <l>Fit for the softer Sex.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e10730">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— I'll tell you then. </l>
            <l>'Tis whisper'd to the King that still a Prince </l>
            <l>Of Gothish Blood is living.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e10790">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>— Ha! what says he? </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e10820">Aside. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e10830">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>Now you, my Lord, if such a one there be, </l>
            <l>Can sure inform me of't.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e10870">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>— Dreams, idle Dreams: </l>
            <l>For were there such, I could not but have known it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e10910">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>Why so 'tis whisper'd too; and that your self </l>
            <l>Now form a Faction to assist his Cause </l>
            <l>Amongst the discontented Goths.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e10970">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>— My Lord, </l>
            <l>I know my Duty to my General: </l>
            <l>Had any other dar'd to speak these words, </l>
            <l>My Sword e're now had been unsheath'd, to right </l>
            <l>My injur'd Honour. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e11040">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>This Paper would have forc'd it back again, </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e11070">Shews the Letter. </stage>
            <l>And nail'd it to the Scabbard. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e11090">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>— 'Tis the same, </l>
            <l>And he's alone; blest opportunity! </l>
            <l>My Lord, you have my Secret; but you must </l>
            <l>Restore me that, or with it take my life. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e11150">Draws. Genselaric whistles, </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e11170">Enter Rodoric and Almeric, they rush on him and disarm him. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e11200">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>I will be forc'd to neither— Disarm him. So; </l>
            <l>Give me his Sword: now leave us to our selves, </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e11240">Ex. Rod. and Alm. </stage>
            <l>And on your lives no word of what has happen'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e11280">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>What shall I judge </l>
            <l>Of these Proceedings? Base at once and Generous? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e11320">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>You seem to be surpriz'd, and your amazement </l>
            <l>Is too well grounded to create my Wonder: </l>
            <l>Yet think not that I summon'd these to help me </l>
            <l>Because I fear'd your Sword; you know I fear not; </l>
            <l>But could not wound the Breast of one I honour, </l>
            <l>Nor suffer you to kill the Friend that loves you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e11400">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord, I understand you not, your words </l>
            <l>Are full of Mystery: </l>
            <l>But could you be a Friend to so much Misery, </l>
            <l>'Twere noble to excess.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e11460">
            <pb n="16" xml:id="ep000458-013-a"/>
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— I can, and will be. </l>
            <l>Believe me, Briomer, 'tis a Solemn Truth, </l>
            <l>I hate this Gunderick, this Tyrant, more </l>
            <l>Than happy Men the thoughts of Death with Torture; </l>
            <l>And if there be a Hatred beyond that, </l>
            <l>I hate the Prince yet more.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e11560">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>— 'Tis wondrous strange! </l>
            <l>So favour'd, so belov'd!— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e11600">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— Grant all this true, </l>
            <l>That I am great in Favour, and in Trust; </l>
            <l>If they at the same time tear from my Heart </l>
            <l>The only Person that my Soul is fond of, </l>
            <l>And give her to th' Embraces of another; </l>
            <l>Does not this cancel all?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e11680">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>— 'Tis true indeed, </l>
            <l>That injur'd Love admits no Compensation. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e11720">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>This is my case: now tell me, Briomer, </l>
            <l>What may that Man deserve, that being Master </l>
            <l>Of this important Secret, which commands </l>
            <l>The Lives and Fortunes of a mighty Nation, </l>
            <l>Not only locks it safe within his Breast, </l>
            <l>And buries it in silence, but breaks through </l>
            <l>The Solemn Ties of Duty, and of Blood, </l>
            <l>To tempt an equal hazard, nay, to make </l>
            <l>By his assistance the Attempt secure, </l>
            <l>And past the fear of failing.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e11850">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>— He deserves </l>
            <l>What e'er his forward Wishes can aspire to, </l>
            <l>What e'er a rescu'd Nation can bestow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e11900">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>Cou'd this, or more, deserve the fair Eurione, </l>
            <l>I durst perform it for her: now you have </l>
            <l>The mighty Secret: tell me, my Lord, </l>
            <l>May I have leave to hope?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e11970">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>— Not only hope, </l>
            <l>But Certainty attends you. I dare pawn </l>
            <l>My yet untainted Honour, that the Queen </l>
            <l>Will give a glad consent: your Birth is Princely, </l>
            <l>Your Fame is great, and what you now design </l>
            <l>Is more than Kingly.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e12050">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— Take your Sword, My Lord; </l>
            <l>And that I may not leave a doubt upon you, </l>
            <l>Thus I disperse your fears.— Now take me to you, </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e12100">Tears the Letter. </stage>
            <l>And mould me as you please.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e12120">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>—— Welcome, brave Sir, </l>
            <l>Be this Embrace the Seal of lasting Friendship </l>
            <l>Between us two; I'll lead you to the Queen, </l>
            <l>Who shall confirm all that your hopes can aim at. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e12180">
            <pb n="17" xml:id="ep000458-013-b"/>
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>O my best Friend, make good this mighty Promise, </l>
            <l>And Heav'n it self has nothing more to give me. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e12220">Exeunt. </stage>
        </div>
        <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000458-e12230">
          <head>SCENE a Chamber-Royal. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e12260">Enter Eurione, and Merinda. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e12290">
            <speaker>Eur. </speaker>
            <l>The sence of former Happiness encreases </l>
            <l>Our present Misery; and the fresh remembrance </l>
            <l>Of those dear Vows which Agilmond once paid, </l>
            <l>Does but imbitter more his late neglect. </l>
            <l>Merinda, sing the Song I so well lov'd, </l>
            <l>Since Agilmond grew false.— </l>
          </sp>
          <lg type="song">
            <head>SONG. </head>
            <lg>
              <l>HOw long must Women wish in vain </l>
              <l>A constant Love to find? </l>
              <l>No Art can fickle Man retain, </l>
              <l>Or fix a roving Mind. </l>
              <l>Yet fondly we our selves deceive, </l>
              <l>And empty Hopes pursue; </l>
              <l>Though false to others, we believe </l>
              <l>They will to us prove true. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>But oh! the Torment! to discern </l>
              <l>A Perjur'd Lover gone; </l>
              <l>And yet by sad experience learn </l>
              <l>That we must still love on! </l>
              <l>How strangely are we fool'd by Fate, </l>
              <l>Who tread the Maze of Love! </l>
              <l>When most desirous to retreat, </l>
              <l>We know not how to move. </l>
            </lg>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e12600">Enter Amalazontha. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e12620">
            <speaker>Mer. </speaker>
            <l>Madam, the Queen.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e12650">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>What, fair Eurione, </l>
            <l>Indulging still those melancholly thoughts </l>
            <l>Which prey upon your inward Peace, and cloud </l>
            <l>The lustre of your Eyes? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e12720">
            <speaker>Eur. </speaker>
            <l>My thoughts and looks </l>
            <l>Are such as well become the humble Fortune </l>
            <l>Of our unhappy House. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e12770">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>Fortune's unjust </l>
            <l>To wound such Innocence (yet I must join </l>
            <pb n="18" xml:id="ep000458-014-a"/>
            <l>In her Unjustice too) I come, Eurione, </l>
            <l>To put your Virtue to a mighty Tryal; </l>
            <l>To trust you with a Secret of such weight </l>
            <l>As must admit no other Ear but yours. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e12860">
            <speaker>Eur. </speaker>
            <l>Merinda, wait without— Madam, you honour me, </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e12900">Ex. Mer. </stage>
            <l>To think me worthy of so great a Trust; </l>
            <l>Nor can I e'er be guilty of such baseness, </l>
            <l>As to abuse so generous a Confidence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e12950">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>'Tis that belief makes me unlock my Heart, </l>
            <l>And give its darling Secret to you; know then, </l>
            <l>To Morrow Gunderick designs to wed you </l>
            <l>To Agilmond; blush not, Eurione, </l>
            <l>The Chast and Virtuous Love you bear the Prince </l>
            <l>Carries no Guilt along with it; and sure </l>
            <l>The Gods themselves inspir'd you with that Love, </l>
            <l>To save his life and mine— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e13080">
            <speaker>Eur. </speaker>
            <l>— Can any danger </l>
            <l>Threaten such precious lives? O! bless me, Madam, </l>
            <l>By making me the happy Instrument </l>
            <l>Of saving them, though at th' expence of mine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e13140">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>We would not purchase ours at such a rate: </l>
            <l>But, generous Eurione, prepare </l>
            <l>To hear surprizing News; summon your Virtue, </l>
            <l>For you will need it all: Suppose I come, </l>
            <l>Like early Frosts, to nip your blooming hopes, </l>
            <l>And blast the Fruit for ever.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e13230">
            <speaker>Eur. </speaker>
            <l>— Hope of late </l>
            <l>Has been a Stranger here. I well perceive </l>
            <l>Your Majesty approves not of that Honour </l>
            <l>The King designs me; and I cannot murmur, </l>
            <l>But mourn my want of Merit.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e13300">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>— Fair Eurione, </l>
            <l>Mistake me not, I grant you merit all things; </l>
            <l>And were he capable to meet your love, </l>
            <l>How gladly would I forward it!— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e13370">
            <speaker>Eur. </speaker>
            <l>Not capable? </l>
            <l>Alas! the killing word! My Rival Sister </l>
            <l>Has Charms, I find, too strong for me to strive with. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e13420">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>Still you mistake me; take it in a word, </l>
            <l>My Agilmond— But see we are prevented. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e13470">Enter <hi>Gunderic, Rhadegonda, Agilmond, Valdaura, Genselarick, Ferrismond, Rodorick, Almerick, Briomer, Albimer, </hi>Guards and Attendants. </stage>
            <l>Embrace the offer which the King will make, </l>
            <l>Till I inform you farther.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e13510">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>Though Right of Conquest, and the chance of War </l>
            <pb n="19" xml:id="ep000458-014-b"/>
            <l>Have firmly join'd the Gothish Crown to mine; </l>
            <l>Yet still methinks Possession seems uneasie, </l>
            <l>Since you, my Royal Sister, are a Mourner: </l>
            <l>And whilst your Tears attend my yearly Triumphs, </l>
            <l>That Scene of Sorrow dashes all my Joys, </l>
            <l>And palls the Tast of Pleasure.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e13610">
            <speaker>Rhad. </speaker>
            <l>— Tears, my Lord, </l>
            <l>Are a just Tribute I must hourly pay </l>
            <l>For Rhadagaise's loss.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e13670">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— Forget it, Madam, </l>
            <l>And suffer yours, like other Griefs, to find </l>
            <l>A cure from time.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e13720">
            <speaker>Rhad. </speaker>
            <l>(— They will, I hope, and soon.) </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e13750">Aside. </stage>
            <l>No time, my Lord, can ever end my Griefs, </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e13770">To him. </stage>
            <l>But that which ends me too— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e13790">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— Hope better, Madam; </l>
            <l>Or if time fails, let me your kinder Comforter </l>
            <l>Prescribe a cure; a cure which shall at once </l>
            <l>Heal all your Griefs, and dry up all your Tears, </l>
            <l>Or change the sad and melancholly Current </l>
            <l>To chearful Streams of Joy. Draw near, my Agilmond, </l>
            <l>And trust a Father's care to make your life, </l>
            <l>And all the remainder of your time to come, </l>
            <l>Happy at once, and Great.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e13910">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— I stand prepar'd </l>
            <l>To meet your Royal Will with full Obedience. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e13950">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>Come to my Arms, thou Comfort of my Age. </l>
            <l>Dare you to my Disposal, Madam, trust </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e13990">To Rhad. </stage>
            <l>This Beauteous Princess?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e14020">
            <speaker>Rhad. </speaker>
            <l>— She is yours, my Lord, </l>
            <l>So are we all, your Captives, and your Slaves; </l>
            <l>How should we then deny to be dispos'd </l>
            <l>By you, our Master, and our Conquerour? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e14080">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>The Names of Captive, and of Conquerour </l>
            <l>This hour shall cancel, and blot out for ever; </l>
            <l>But for the mighty Trust you now repose, </l>
            <l>Thus low I bow to thank you. Noble Nephew; </l>
            <l>And you, my Lords, attend to what I say. </l>
            <l>Though the rough hand of War first ty'd the Knot </l>
            <l>Which binds together both my Diadems, </l>
            <l>Yet the soft bands of Love shall fasten it. </l>
            <l>Approach, fair Virgin, and receive from me, </l>
            <l>The greatest Present Gunderick can make, </l>
            <l>My Agilmond, and with him both my Kingdoms; </l>
            <l>And if my flattering hopes deceive me not, </l>
            <l>In giving him, I give the greater Gift. </l>
            <l>Why are you silent, lovely Innocence? </l>
            <pb n="20" xml:id="ep000458-015-a"/>
            <l>Methinks the vastness of a Gift like this </l>
            <l>Should justly challenge Thanks.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e14280">
            <speaker>Rhad. </speaker>
            <l>— Impute her Silence </l>
            <l>To Maiden Modesty, and her just surprise; </l>
            <l>A Virgins Tongue moves only in her looks, </l>
            <l>And she in Blushes speaks her glad consent. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e14340">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>My Wishes are compleat; nor shall our joys </l>
            <l>Be cramp'd by dull delay. To Morrow's Sun </l>
            <l>That yearly Celebrates my Gothish Triumph, </l>
            <l>Shall shine with double Light, whilst to his Splendor, </l>
            <l>Their Marriage-Torch shall add a brighter lustre. </l>
            <l>My Lords, prepare to grace the wish'd Solemnity </l>
            <l>With all becoming Honours. You, Genselaric, </l>
            <l>Draw forth my Troops, and see the Pomp set off </l>
            <l>With all the glorious Pageantry of War. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e14470">Exeunt omnes, praeter <hi>Genselaric, Rodoric</hi>, and <hi>Almeric. Agil</hi>. drops a Dagger as he goes out, Rod. takes it up. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e14510">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>Confusion on them all! How could I stand </l>
            <l>Thus tamely by, and see my panting Heart </l>
            <l>Pluck'd from my trembling Bosom fresh and bleeding </l>
            <l>By this inhumane King? Am I a Coward? </l>
            <l>Answer me, Friends, am I that wretched thing? </l>
            <l>I must be sure; I could not else look on, </l>
            <l>And see the Tyrant ravish from my Soul </l>
            <l>All it holds dear and precious.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e14610">
            <speaker>Rod. </speaker>
            <l>— 'Tis a patience </l>
            <l>Extreamly hard to practice; nor could you </l>
            <l>So well disguise your thoughts, but that I fear'd, </l>
            <l>The King, when he addrest himself to you, </l>
            <l>Wou'd have discover'd something.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e14680">
            <speaker>Alm. </speaker>
            <l>— 'Twas most lucky </l>
            <l>That he retir'd so soon; for I perceiv'd </l>
            <l>Your Forehead glow, your eager Pulse beat fast, </l>
            <l>And your full Breast swell at the harsh injunction. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e14740">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>By Heav'ns he mock'd me—" You, Genselaric, </l>
            <l>" Draw forth my Troops, and see the Pomp set off. </l>
            <l>Yes, I will set it off; but in a manner </l>
            <l>They little think of; now, by all my wrongs </l>
            <l>It is a Noble thought: draw near, my Friends, </l>
            <l>And swear on this good Sword to undertake </l>
            <l>Whatever I desire; nor shall the danger </l>
            <l>Be yours alone, I'll share in all the hazard, </l>
            <l>And shoot the Gulf as well as you— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e14860">
            <speaker>Rod. </speaker>
            <l>I swear </l>
            <l>To execute whatever you command; </l>
            <l>Nor Racks, nor Tortures shall deter me from it, </l>
            <l>Or force the weighty Secret from my Bosom. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e14920">
            <speaker>Alm. </speaker>
            <l>I swear the same.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e14950">
            <pb n="21" xml:id="ep000458-015-b"/>
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— O! let me rivet you </l>
            <l>For ever to my Breast, the truest Friends </l>
            <l>That ever Man was blest with. Listen both, </l>
            <l>And to your Bosoms I'll impart a business </l>
            <l>Would startle any Courage less than yours. </l>
            <l>I must enjoy Eurione, or die; </l>
            <l>This Night, the Eve of all my destin'd Sorrows, </l>
            <l>Shall make me blest, and revel in full Joys. </l>
            <l>The Princess every Night, as I'm inform'd, </l>
            <l>Walks singly forth, and in a lonely Arbour </l>
            <l>Enjoys her private thoughts; the place I know; </l>
            <l>Thither we'll haste, and, shrouded from all eyes, </l>
            <l>Expect her coming, seize the trembling Prey, </l>
            <l>And rifle all the Treasures of her Beauty: </l>
            <l>Then if the Prince feasts on her Sweets to Morrow, </l>
            <l>He shall have but the leavings of my Riot. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e15140">
            <speaker>Rod. </speaker>
            <l>Th' attempt is full of hazard; but to make </l>
            <l>Our after-game more safe, take my Advice, </l>
            <l>As a sure means to free us from discovery. </l>
            <l>Know you this Dagger?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e15200">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— Yes, 'tis Agilmond's, </l>
            <l>Remarkable and known to all the Court. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e15250">
            <speaker>Rod. </speaker>
            <l>As he went out he dropt it; in the Crowd </l>
            <l>I stoop'd and took it up, but had no time </l>
            <l>To give it him. Take it, and when your Sences </l>
            <l>Are surfeited with Pleasure, drop this Weapon </l>
            <l>Near to the Ravish'd Princess: this will be </l>
            <l>Ten thousand Witnesses against the Prince, </l>
            <l>To fix Suspicion of the Deed on him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e15340">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>'Tis well contriv'd, nor can it fail to hit: </l>
            <l>His long profess'd Aversion to this Marriage, </l>
            <l>Though late he faintly gave a forc'd Assent, </l>
            <l>Will make it pass unquestion'd; and the Walks </l>
            <l>That lead unto this Scene of killing Joy, </l>
            <l>At such late hours are barr'd from all our Sex, </l>
            <l>Except the King and Prince. 'Tis fit we hasten, </l>
            <l>That while the Pass is open we may enter, </l>
            <l>And lie conceal'd. Methinks I see already </l>
            <l>Her dying Looks, her seeming faint Resistance, </l>
            <l>And feel the mighty Transports of hot Love! </l>
            <l>Let but Success on this blest Moment wait, </l>
            <l>The rest of Life I freely leave to Fate. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e15490">Exeunt. </stage>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="ep000458-e15500">
        <pb n="22" xml:id="ep000458-016-a"/>
        <head>ACT III. </head>
        <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000458-e15520">
          <head>SCENE a Chamber-Royal. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e15550">Enter Agilmond and Amalazontha. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e15580">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>THe King is gone to Bed, the busie Courtiers </l>
            <l>All scatter'd and dispers'd; but I in vain </l>
            <l>Shou'd seek for rest, till first I know what past </l>
            <l>In your late Conference with Eurione. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e15650">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>I found her, Agilmond, (for I must yet </l>
            <l>Give you that name) compos'd throughout of Sweetness; </l>
            <l>And I ne'er wish'd more earnestly you were </l>
            <l>What you pretend to be, than for her sake, </l>
            <l>Who pants for you with all the modest warmth </l>
            <l>Of Innocence and Love.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e15740">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— Alas! I pity her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e15770">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>When first I told her I must blast her hopes, </l>
            <l>Something that look'd like Anger seem'd to rise; </l>
            <l>But as a Stranger, soon was banish'd thence, </l>
            <l>And sunk to humble Sorrow.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e15830">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— 'Twas a sight </l>
            <l>Wou'd have affected the most Savage heart, </l>
            <l>To see such mourning Virtue.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e15880">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>— First, she thought, </l>
            <l>Or seem'd to think, that her small Stock of Merit </l>
            <l>Bred my dislike of the intended Marriage; </l>
            <l>But undeceiv'd in that, her jealous thoughts </l>
            <l>Suggested to her straight, that all your love </l>
            <l>Was on Valdaura fix'd, her haughty Sister. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e15970">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>And did not that opinion shock her temper? </l>
            <l>For sure she has a Soul above her Sex, </l>
            <l>If yet unmov'd by such Assaults as these. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e16020">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>Still the same meekness, still the same composure. </l>
            <l>I told her then that she was yet mistaken; </l>
            <l>And just as I was going to impart </l>
            <l>The mighty Secret of your Sex, the King </l>
            <l>Attended by your self and all the Court, </l>
            <l>Enter'd the Room, and hinder'd the Discovery. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e16100">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>'Twas most unlucky. When I parted from you, </l>
            <l>As you advis'd me, I found out the King, </l>
            <l>Humbly implor'd his Pardon, and assur'd him </l>
            <l>I was in all things ready to obey him: </l>
            <l>He press'd me close, commanded all to follow, </l>
            <l>And led us streight to you, and to Eurione. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e16190">
            <pb n="23" xml:id="ep000458-016-b"/>
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>Late as it is, 'tis fit you see Eurione; </l>
            <l>Disclose your Secret to her, and instead </l>
            <l>Of those returns of Passion which she looks for, </l>
            <l>And which you cannot pay, offer such Love </l>
            <l>As tender Sisters to each other bear: </l>
            <l>Tell her, the glorious Title of a Queen, </l>
            <l>And all the dazling Pomp of Royalty </l>
            <l>Are hers, if she complies.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e16300">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— Madam, I go. </l>
            <l>This clear calm Night will tempt the Princess forth </l>
            <l>To her lov'd Solitude; there I'll surprise her, </l>
            <l>And to her private ear disclose my Secret, </l>
            <l>Soft Rest attend your Majesty. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e16370">Leads her to the Door, and Exeunt severally. </stage>
        </div>
        <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000458-e16380">
          <head>SCENE a Night-Piece of a Garden. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e16410">Enter Genselaric disguis'd, coming as out of an Arbour, and peeping about. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e16430">
            <l>I wonder that the Princess comes not yet; </l>
            <l>'Tis past her usual hour; and shou'd she fail, </l>
            <l>How miserably wretched should I be! </l>
            <l>Fool that I was! like an unthrifty Gamester, </l>
            <l>To venture all my stock of Happiness </l>
            <l>On one uncertain chance! Hist, Rodoric, <stage xml:id="ep000458-e16510">Enter Rodoric and Almeric disguised. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>And Almeric! discern you nothing yet? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e16560">
            <speaker>Rod. </speaker>
            <l>Nothing. You need not whisper so; there's not </l>
            <l>A living Creature within hearing of you </l>
            <l>Besides our selves.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e16610">
            <speaker>Alm. </speaker>
            <l>— The Court is gone to rest. </l>
            <l>The Windows all are darken'd, except one </l>
            <l>That's in the Lodgings of the Gothish Queen; </l>
            <l>And see, a light darts through the Gallery, </l>
            <l>And seems to move this way.—— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e16690">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— It is the Princess; </l>
            <l>She's now undress'd, and comes to take her walk. </l>
            <l>By Heav'ns, I see her yonder; quick, retire, </l>
            <l>And when she comes seize the attending Maid, </l>
            <l>And stop her clamorous Throat; leave me alone </l>
            <l>To grapple with the Princess. Oh! ye Gods! </l>
            <l>How my full Veins swell, and my boiling Blood </l>
            <l>Bubbles and foams, as it would break its Channels! </l>
            <l>Sure my hot Flames will thaw her Ice, and melt </l>
            <l>Her frozen Heart; whilst rowling in her Snow, </l>
            <l>I cool the raging burnings of my Feaver. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e16820">Exeunt as into the Arbour. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e16830">
            <pb n="24" xml:id="ep000458-017-a"/>Enter Eurione and Merinda. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e16860">
            <speaker>Eur. </speaker>
            <l>Methinks I have no mind to walk to night, </l>
            <l>And yet an unseen Pow'r conducts me on: </l>
            <l>I stumbl'd at my entrance, and upon </l>
            <l>My heavy Heart hangs a dead Weight of Sorrow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e16920">
            <speaker>Mer. </speaker>
            <l>Pardon me, Madam, if I blame this Sadness, </l>
            <l>When Fortune seems to court you with fresh Honours, </l>
            <l>And all your eager hopes are almost Crown'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e16970">
            <speaker>Eur. </speaker>
            <l>Alas! my dear Merinda, Fortune's smiles </l>
            <l>Are falser than the Tears of wicked Women: </l>
            <l>And though she seems to promise fairly to me, </l>
            <l>Yet my too truly boding Heart assures me </l>
            <l>That I shall ne'er be happy. Fetch my Lute </l>
            <l>To yonder Arbour, there I'll sit a while, </l>
            <l>And try if Musick can compose my mind, </l>
            <l>In which I nothing now but Discords find. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e17080">Exit Merinda. </stage>
            <l>Not all the Royal Favours of the King, </l>
            <l>Nor Agilmond's compliance with his Will, </l>
            <l>Can bring me Comfort equal to those Fears </l>
            <l>Which the Queen's doubtful words inspire me with. </l>
            <l>Yet why should I despair? perhaps the Queen </l>
            <l>But dally'd with me; and that Scene of Sorrow </l>
            <l>Was drawn, to make my coming Joys look greater. </l>
            <l>I'll trust my Fate: the Gods can never prove </l>
            <l>Averse to Chast Desires, and Virtuous Love. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e17200">Exit as into the Arbour. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e17210">Enter Agilmond. </stage>
            <l>The solitude and silence of this Place, </l>
            <l>Join'd with the native Horror of the Night, </l>
            <l>Have fill'd my trembling Heart with doubts and terrours. </l>
            <l>Alas! how ill such Fears become this habit! </l>
            <l>Ha! </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e17280">Shrieks within. </stage>
            <l>What dismal shriek was that? or was't my Fancy? </l>
            <l>'Tis there again! I dare not venture farther: </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e17310">Shrieks again. </stage>
            <l>Yet more! defend me, Gods! and guard me forth </l>
            <l>From this most dismal place in Peace and Safety. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e17340">Exit Agilmond. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e17360">Enter Merinda with a Lute. </stage>
            <l>'Twas sure the Prince I met, he seem'd in haste </l>
            <l>And discompos'd; this was the cause I find </l>
            <l>Of sending me to fetch her Instrument, </l>
            <l>That she might meet the Prince with greater liberty. </l>
            <pb n="25" xml:id="ep000458-017-b"/>
            <l>'Twas well I came no sooner; now he's gone, </l>
            <l>I'll see if yet her mind be out of Tune. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e17440">Exit as into the Arbour. </stage>
        </div>
        <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000458-e17450">
          <head>The Scene draws, and discovers Eurione in an Arbour, gagg'd and bound to a Tree, her hair dishevel'd as newly Ravish'd, a Dagger lying by her. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e17480">Enter Merinda with a Lute </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e17500">
            <speaker>Mer. </speaker>
            <l>Madam, I've brought the Lute— Defend me, Heav'n! </l>
            <l>What means this dismal Vision! O, my Princess! </l>
            <l>What barb'rous Villain, black as Hell could make him! </l>
            <l>Durst bind those lovely Arms? </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e17560">Vnbinding her. </stage>
            <l>O tell me, Madam, </l>
            <l>What worse than Devil durst attempt yet farther, </l>
            <l>For so the dismal Scene too well informs me? </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e17600">Eurione falls down, Merinda a chafing her. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e17630">Enter Valdaura in a Night-Gown. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e17650">
            <speaker>Val. </speaker>
            <l>It could not be a Dream; the mournful Accents </l>
            <l>Of some distressed Creature pierc'd my Ears, </l>
            <l>Like shrieks of Ravish'd Virgins: and just now </l>
            <l>Entring, I heard a Female Voice lamenting: </l>
            <l>Who's that? Merinda weeping? Where's my Sister? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e17730">
            <speaker>Eur. </speaker>
            <l>Alas! here's she that was Eurione; </l>
            <l>Now she is nothing but a loathsome Leprosie, </l>
            <l>Which spread all o'er the Gothish Royal Blood, </l>
            <l>Infects the Noble Race.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e17810">
            <speaker>Val. </speaker>
            <l>— Alas, my Sister, </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e17840">Kneeling by her. </stage>
            <l>What killing words are these?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e17860">
            <speaker>Eur. </speaker>
            <l>— Stand off, Valdaura, </l>
            <l>And come not near me; I am contagious sure, </l>
            <l>And all chaste hands will blister that but touch me, </l>
            <l>Were all the Gods that succour Innocence, </l>
            <l>Deaf to my Cries, and blind to all my Wrongs? </l>
            <l>That no relenting Power would send one Bolt </l>
            <l>To strike me dead, and save my Ravish'd Honour? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e17960">
            <speaker>Val. </speaker>
            <l>Ha! Ravish'd said you? Ravish'd! name the Villain; </l>
            <l>That my fierce Wrath, like an impetuous Torrent, </l>
            <l>May overtake and hurry him to ruine, </l>
            <l>Preventing the slow Vengeance of the Gods, </l>
            <l>Tell me: but know you speak not to Valdaura, </l>
            <l>But to the Prince Ambiomer, your Brother, </l>
            <l>For such I am; and I will write my self </l>
            <l>Such in my fell Revenge. Now, name the Villain; </l>
            <l>He lives too long already, by this Minute </l>
            <pb n="26" xml:id="ep000458-018-a"/>
            <l>That he is yet unknown.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e18100">
            <speaker>Eur. </speaker>
            <l>— Alas! I know him not. </l>
            <l>Disguis'd he came, as if he hid his Face </l>
            <l>From Night it self; seiz'd like a Bird of Prey </l>
            <l>His trembling Quarry; gagg'd and bound me fast, </l>
            <l>And then— Oh! let me die, and stifle so </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e18170">Sees the Dagger. </stage>
            <l>The harsh remembrance!— Ha! what's this? a Dagger? </l>
            <l>Blest be the Friendly Pow'rs that sent me this </l>
            <l>To heal my Griefs for ever. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e18210">Going to stab her self. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e18220">
            <speaker>Val. </speaker>
            <l>— Hold, Eurione; </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e18260">Wresting it from her. </stage>
            <l>The Gods design'd not this for your Destruction, </l>
            <l>But to discover who the Villain is, </l>
            <l>And mark him for my Vengeance.— Is it possible? </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e18300">Looking on it. </stage>
            <l>By all our Wrongs, it is the Prince's Dagger. </l>
            <l>Is he the Ravisher? Can so much Villany </l>
            <l>Lurk under such a chast and modest semblance? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e18340">
            <speaker>Mer. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord, I met the Prince; he seem'd disorder'd, </l>
            <l>And haste and fear were in his Gate and Eyes: </l>
            <l>But though I found the Princess newly Ravish'd, </l>
            <l>I could not think him guilty of the Fact, </l>
            <l>Till this plain Evidence convinc'd me of it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e18410">
            <speaker>Eur. </speaker>
            <l>Was this a sit return for chast desires, </l>
            <l>And virtuous Love like mine?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e18450">
            <speaker>Val. </speaker>
            <l>— Oh! the young Ravisher! </l>
            <l>Here on my Knees I swear, upon this Dagger </l>
            <l>(Which though a Villains, yet shall bind my Oath </l>
            <l>As firmly as if Fate it self had Seal'd it) </l>
            <l>My thoughts shall never know a Moment's peace, </l>
            <l>Till I have drench'd this Weapon in the Blood </l>
            <l>That warms his lustful Heart. Merinda, help, </l>
            <l>Convey my Sister in; and at her Chamber </l>
            <l>We'll lay the Method of our just Revenge. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e18570">Exeunt. </stage>
        </div>
        <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000458-e18580">
          <head>SCENE a Night-Piece of a Wood. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e18610">Enter Genselaric and Almeric. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e18640">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>Still I'm in pain for Rodoric, and dread </l>
            <l>The fatal Consequences of his stay. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e18690">
            <speaker>Alm. </speaker>
            <l>The Ladder's breaking, caus'd by too much haste, </l>
            <l>Was (I confess) unlucky; but suppose </l>
            <l>The worst, that he is taken; all the Tortures </l>
            <l>Invented by ingenious Cruelty, </l>
            <l>Will never from his stedfast Faith extort </l>
            <l>The smallest word to prejudice his Friend. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e18770">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>I neither doubt his Friendship, nor his Courage, </l>
            <l>But oh! my Almeric, what mighty Transports </l>
            <l>Am I indebted for to him and you! </l>
            <pb n="27" xml:id="ep000458-018-b"/>
            <l>Methought, in one short moment I possess'd </l>
            <l>The crowded joys of a long life's delight; </l>
            <l>As if some friendly Power by Chimic Art, </l>
            <l>Had drawn the Spirit of an Age's pleasure, </l>
            <l>Contracting all into that happy Minute </l>
            <l>To make the Cordial rich.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e18890">
            <speaker>Alm. </speaker>
            <l>— My Lord, your joys </l>
            <l>Have made you wanton, but methinks 'tis strange </l>
            <l>That Pleasure forc'd shou'd give such vast delight. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e18940">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>I hate a tedious Siege, but love to Storm; </l>
            <l>'Tis Soldier-like: </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e18980">Whistling within. </stage>
            <l>But hark! I hear one whistle, answer him; </l>
            <l>It must be Rodoric— And see he's here. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e19020">Enter Rodoric. </stage>
            <l>Welcome, my Friend, your fortunate escape </l>
            <l>Quiets my mind, and makes my Joys sit easie. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e19060">
            <speaker>Rod. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord, your better Genius, I believe, </l>
            <l>Contriv'd my stay; for by it I have made </l>
            <l>Discov'ries of great weight.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e19110">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— You are your self </l>
            <l>My better Genius, and direct my Fortunes </l>
            <l>With as successful care, and with a Pow'r </l>
            <l>As absolute as his. But say, my Rodoric, </l>
            <l>What's the important Novelty?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e19190">
            <speaker>Rod. </speaker>
            <l>— My Lord, </l>
            <l>When disappointed by the Ladder's breaking </l>
            <l>Of coming off, I silently return'd </l>
            <l>To my old private Covert, near the Scene </l>
            <l>Of your late Joys, resolving there to wait, </l>
            <l>Till Fortune should present me with a way </l>
            <l>To leave it unobserv'd: Scarce was I settled, </l>
            <l>When first I found Merinda was return'd, </l>
            <l>And mourning o'er her Mistress: then, Valdaura </l>
            <l>Alarmed by her Sister's shrieks, arriv'd </l>
            <l>With hasty steps— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e19340">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— 'Tis true, she strugled so, </l>
            <l>I could not get the Gag into her Mouth </l>
            <l>So soon as I design'd it.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e19390">
            <speaker>Rod. </speaker>
            <l>— But, my Lord, </l>
            <l>That which surpriz'd me most, as 'twill do you, </l>
            <l>Was, that the haughty Princess in her Transport </l>
            <l>Of furious Rage to find her Sister Ravish'd, </l>
            <l>Own'd that she was the Prince Ambiomer, </l>
            <l>And Son, not Daughter, to the Gothish Queen; </l>
            <l>Her Sex (no doubt, for politick designs) </l>
            <l>Thus long conceal'd.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e19510">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— 'Tis most amazing News: </l>
            <l>And yet ('tis true) I often have observ'd, </l>
            <pb n="28" xml:id="ep000458-019-a"/>
            <l>And wonder'd at the Manly Air and Mein, </l>
            <l>The haughty Carriage and resolv'd Assurance, </l>
            <l>Of the suppos'd Valdaura. This is he </l>
            <l>Whom Briomer and all the Gothish Faction </l>
            <l>Design'd their head: This Secret must be manag'd </l>
            <l>With caution and discretion. But say, Rodoric, </l>
            <l>What of the Prince's Dagger? was that found, </l>
            <l>Or lay it there neglected?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e19670">
            <speaker>Rod. </speaker>
            <l>— All your Stars </l>
            <l>Have been at work for you to Night. The Princess </l>
            <l>Found it by chance, and with a sudden fury </l>
            <l>Had plung'd it in her Breast, but that her Brother </l>
            <l>Seiz'd and prevented her. Soon as he view'd it, </l>
            <l>He knew its owner; and whilst that was breeding </l>
            <l>Suspition of his Guilt; Merinda told them, </l>
            <l>She met the Prince but just before, returning </l>
            <l>With fear and great disorder from the Garden. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e19790">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>'Twas wondrous lucky. But what brought him thither </l>
            <l>At that late hour?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e19830">
            <speaker>Rod. </speaker>
            <l>— His ill, and your good Fate. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e19860">
            <speaker>Alm. </speaker>
            <l>This sure with t'other Circumstance confirm'd them </l>
            <l>He did the Fact.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e19900">
            <speaker>Rod. </speaker>
            <l>— It put it past all doubt. </l>
            <l>The Prince rav'd high, and made them all retire </l>
            <l>With dreadful Imprecations of Revenge </l>
            <l>Upon the lustful Agilmond, for such </l>
            <l>His Errour stil'd him: Soon as they were gone, </l>
            <l>Finding all still and hush'd, I ventur'd forth, </l>
            <l>Mended my broken Ladder, and escap'd </l>
            <l>Unseen by any.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e20010">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— Asl this Night's Adventure </l>
            <l>Has met with such Success, that it could scarce </l>
            <l>Have happen'd better, had the Prince contriv'd </l>
            <l>To be his own Betrayer. But the day </l>
            <l>Begins to break; 'tis fit we all disperse, </l>
            <l>And gain our several Lodgings. Worthy Friends, </l>
            <l>Command whate'er is mine; 'tis all too little </l>
            <l>For the vast Service of this happy Night. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e20110">Exeunt severally. </stage>
        </div>
        <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000458-e20120">
          <pb n="29" xml:id="ep000458-019-b"/>
          <head>SCENE a Chamber-Royal. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e20150">Eurione is discover'd lying on a Couch, her hair dishevel'd (as before) Merinda weeping by her. </stage>
          <lg type="song">
            <head>SONG to a Lute and Flu●t. </head>
            <lg n="1">
              <head>I. </head>
              <l>BEneath a gloomy Cypress Grove, </l>
              <l>Within a dismal unfrequented Cave, </l>
              <l>Sad, as the Mansions of despairing Love, </l>
              <l>And dark and silent as the Grave, </l>
              <l>The Ravish'd Philomela weeping lies, </l>
              <l>Chief Mourner at her Honours Obsequies. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
              <head>II. </head>
              <l>A living Herse she's stretch'd along, </l>
              <l>Grief does her active Faculties benumb; </l>
              <l>Had not the Lustful Slave torn out her Tongue, </l>
              <l>Her mighty Wrongs had struck her dumb: </l>
              <l>Yet thus her silent Wishes mount the Skie, </l>
              <l>" Give me Revenge, ye Powers, or let me die. </l>
            </lg>
          </lg>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e20370">
            <l>Musick to me! alas! 'tis lost upon me </l>
            <l>As soon it might divert a dying Wretch </l>
            <l>That's stretch'd upon the Engine of his Torture. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e20410">Enter to her <hi>Rhadegonda, Valdaura, Briomer, Albimer, </hi>and other Goths. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e20440">
            <speaker>Rhad. </speaker>
            <l>Behold, my Lords, the Ruines of your Princess! </l>
            <l>See there the destin'd Bride of Agilmond, </l>
            <l>Rifl'd of all her Sweets by his hot Lust </l>
            <l>That should this day have wedded her. The stain, </l>
            <l>Though chiefly ours, will yet reflect on you, </l>
            <l>And brand the Gothish Nation with disgrace, </l>
            <l>Unless you vindicate her suffering Honour, </l>
            <l>By taking sharp Revenge. If ye are Slaves, </l>
            <l>And would be so, bow down your servile Necks, </l>
            <l>To cruel Gunderic and his lustful Son, </l>
            <l>And bring your Virgin Daughters to be Ravish'd </l>
            <l>By his voluptuous Race, as mine has been. </l>
            <l>But if you bravely wish, as sure you do, </l>
            <l>To break your Chains, and right your injur'd Queen, </l>
            <pb n="30" xml:id="ep000458-020-a"/>
            <l>Behold this Prince, his slaughter'd Father's Image, </l>
            <l>No longer now Valdaura, but Ambiomer, </l>
            <l>Constrain'd these Sixteen Years to shroud his Sex, </l>
            <l>And in a Female habit shun the Rage </l>
            <l>Of cruel Gunderic that doom'd to Death </l>
            <l>The Royal Gothish Males. He stands prepar'd </l>
            <l>To lead you on to Honour and Renown, </l>
            <l>To Liberty, and what's yet more, Revenge. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e20750">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>Curs'd be that Coward, that denies to follow </l>
            <l>Where such a Prince does lead: and doubly curs'd </l>
            <l>Be he that shall refuse to take Revenge </l>
            <l>For so much injur'd Virtue! Royal Master, </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e20810">Kneeling. </stage>
            <l>Permit your faithful Subject thus to tender </l>
            <l>His vow'd Allegiance; and may young Ambiomer </l>
            <l>In all resemble his renowned Father, </l>
            <l>But his untimely Fate.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e20870">
            <speaker>Alb. &amp; Goths. </speaker>
            <l>— We jointly wish, </l>
            <l>And vow the same.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e20910">
            <speaker>Val. </speaker>
            <l>— My Lords, I thank you all; </l>
            <l>And shall endeavour by my future Actions </l>
            <l>To fix your Love and Service, but must blush </l>
            <l>To see the tenders of your Duty paid </l>
            <l>To this effeminate outside. Now 'tis fit </l>
            <l>We should consult about the means and method </l>
            <l>Of a secure Revenge. That Agilmond </l>
            <l>Committed this foul Fact, the Prooss are pregnant; </l>
            <l>His Dagger dropp'd, Merinda meeting him </l>
            <l>In haste and discomposure.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e21050">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>— 'Tis most strange, </l>
            <l>That he who was design'd this day to wed her, </l>
            <l>Should be the guilty Ravisher.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e21100">
            <speaker>Val. </speaker>
            <l>— Perhaps </l>
            <l>He look'd upon her as his Father's Slave, </l>
            <l>And scorn'd to wed so low; but he might safer </l>
            <l>Have hugg'd a pois'nous Serpent in his Bosom, </l>
            <l>Than such a thought as that. Perhaps he meant </l>
            <l>By this last desp'rate Remedy to avoid </l>
            <l>A Match he always shunn'd. 'Tis out of question </l>
            <l>He did the Fact; and our short time calls on us, </l>
            <l>Not to dispute, but act: first let us seize him, </l>
            <l>And when that's done, if he has ought to urge, </l>
            <l>He shall have quiet hearing.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e21230">
            <speaker>Rhad. </speaker>
            <l>— Sure his Guilt </l>
            <l>Will keep him on his Cuard, and make his Seizure </l>
            <l>Almost impossible.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e21280">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>— Leave that to me: </l>
            <l>The General, his Cousin's firmly ours; </l>
            <pb n="31" xml:id="ep000458-020-b"/>
            <l>And he by some Device shall train him out. </l>
            <l>Besides to cloak his Guilt, he will not fail </l>
            <l>To make his Visits early. This strong Cittadel, </l>
            <l>Where, Madam, you have kept your Royal Court, </l>
            <l>Is under my Command, and firmly Guarded </l>
            <l>By chosen faithful Goths. Here Albimer </l>
            <l>Shall, whilst you shift your Habit, and appear </l>
            <l>Like what the Gods design'd you, guard your Majesty. </l>
            <l>Let me find out Genselaric: I'll pawn </l>
            <l>My Life, nay more, my Honour, that I'll bring </l>
            <l>The Prince within two hours to your disposal. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e21460">
            <speaker>Val. </speaker>
            <l>We'll trust your management, but be sure you fail not; </l>
            <l>For if you do, though next my Royal Mother </l>
            <l>I hold you dear, by Heav'ns I'll take the Forfeiture. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e21510">Exeunt one way, Briomer the other way. </stage>
        </div>
        <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000458-e21530">
          <head>SCENE The Palace-Garden. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e21560">Enter Agilmond. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e21580">
            <l>My last Night's Fears unhappily prevented </l>
            <l>My meeting with Eurione; </l>
            <l>'Tis fit she know the mighty Secret soon; </l>
            <l>For since the great Affair with which I labour, </l>
            <l>Has in suspence hung doubtful, Sleep has been </l>
            <l>A Stranger to my Eyes, and from my Breast </l>
            <l>All quiet has been banish'd.— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e21670">Enter Briomer. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e21690">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>— Sure the General </l>
            <l>Has some important business, that detains him </l>
            <l>Abroad so long! he has all night been absent, </l>
            <l>Nor know I where to seek him.— Ha! the Prince! </l>
            <l>Can so much Villany be shrouded under </l>
            <l>So sweet an outside? sure it cannot be; </l>
            <l>He is abus'd; but that he may be clear'd, </l>
            <l>He must endure a Tryal first.— My Lord, </l>
            <l>I come, led by my Duty and Respect, </l>
            <l>To wait your Highness to the Queen and Princess. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e21810">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>I was just going to the Cittadel, </l>
            <l>Designing to surprize them. Lead me to them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e21850">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>By all my Honours, he is innocent: </l>
            <l>He could not else with such an even Brow </l>
            <l>Treat of a Subject, which, had he been guilty, </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e21900">Aside. </stage>
            <l>Had stung his Conscious Heart.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e21920">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— Conduct me, Briomer; </l>
            <l>I long to see the Princess. Grant, good Heaven, </l>
            <l>That fair Eurione with pitying ears </l>
            <l>May hear my fatal Story; and may all </l>
            <pb n="32" xml:id="ep000458-021-a"/>
            <l>Those Pow'rs that of the Innocent take care, </l>
            <l>Dispose her to be good, as she is fair. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e22020">Exeunt. </stage>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="ep000458-e22030">
        <head>ACT IV. </head>
        <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000458-e22050">
          <head>SCENE, the Cittadel. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e22080">Enter Ambiomer in his own Habit, <hi>Albimer, Gothish </hi>Lords, &amp;c. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e22110">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>COuld my sad Soul be sensible of Comfort </l>
            <l>Whilst wrong'd Eurione is unreveng'd; </l>
            <l>This day, the whitest day of all my life, </l>
            <l>Had brought me wondrous joy; in which I first </l>
            <l>Appear to be what Nature made me, Man, </l>
            <l>And what my Birth design'd me for, your King. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e22200">
            <speaker>Albi. </speaker>
            <l>To make that joy sincere and undisturb'd </l>
            <l>(In which, as in your Griefs, permit your Subjects </l>
            <l>To bear a share) let generous anger chase </l>
            <l>All melancholly thoughts, and fix your eyes </l>
            <l>On the near prospect of a brave Revenge. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e22270">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord, you counsel well; let Women grieve, </l>
            <l>Unable to take Vengeance; but for us, </l>
            <l>We'll make us Cordials of our great Revenge, </l>
            <l>To chear our sinking Spirits. Briomer </l>
            <l>Is wondrous slow; the time is almost laps'd, </l>
            <l>And he not yet return'd.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e22360">
            <speaker>Albi. </speaker>
            <l>— My Royal Lord, </l>
            <l>Doubt not his Zeal; the great design he manages </l>
            <l>Will, if th' attempt succeed, make large amends </l>
            <l>For such a small delay.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e22420">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— I am to blame </l>
            <l>To censure him of slowness: 'tis not that, </l>
            <l>'Tis the fierce motion of my eager wishes, </l>
            <l>That leaves the swiftest diligence behind, </l>
            <l>Unable to keep pace.— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e22490">Enter a Goth. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e22510">
            <speaker>Goth. </speaker>
            <l>— My Lord, the Prince </l>
            <l>And Briomer are enter'd.—— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e22560">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— For thy News </l>
            <l>Take this: Draw up the Bridge, and on your lives </l>
            <l>Let no Man have admittance. O, ye Gods, </l>
            <l>I see that ye are just; and I your Substitute, </l>
            <l>Will execute your Justice to the full </l>
            <l>On this young Ravisher.— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e22640">He sits, the rest stand bare about him. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e22650">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— Whither, my Lord, </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e22680">Enter Agil. and Brio. </stage>
            <pb n="33" xml:id="ep000458-021-b"/>
            <l>Have you conducted me? I came to seek </l>
            <l>The Queen and Princess, and you have led me </l>
            <l>To faces that I know not.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e22740">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— Seize the Villain, </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e22770">They seize and disarm him. </stage>
            <l>The lustful Ravisher.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e22790">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— Ha! what means this language? </l>
            <l>And what this usage? Lustful Ravisher! </l>
            <l>And Villain! do these execrable Names </l>
            <l>Belong to me? How am I chang'd o'th' sudden, </l>
            <l>And grown a Monster?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e22860">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— Yes, a fouler Monster </l>
            <l>Than ever Africk bred.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e22910">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— And what are you, </l>
            <l>That dare so near my Royal Father's Palace </l>
            <l>Thus use the Heir of mighty Gunderic?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e22970">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— I am </l>
            <l>The Vandal Scourge, reserv'd by Fate punish </l>
            <l>Your bloody Father, and his lustful Issue: </l>
            <l>You knew Valdaura once, now know Ambiomer, </l>
            <l>For both are one; the sole surviving Son </l>
            <l>Of Rhadagaise King of the Goths, and Brother </l>
            <l>To wrong'd Eurione, or what's my Noblest Title, </l>
            <l>Avenger of her Wrongs.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e23130">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— This strange discovery </l>
            <l>May well create my wonder, not my fear: </l>
            <l>I cannot think, you will be so unjust, </l>
            <l>To execute Revenge for Wrongs receiv'd </l>
            <l>Upon my Innocence.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e23200">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— A Ravisher! </l>
            <l>And yet plead Innocence!— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e23240">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— Again that Name? </l>
            <l>Instruct me by what dire mistake you brand me </l>
            <l>With such a hated Title.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e23290">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— See the Hypocrite: </l>
            <l>With what a seeming Ignorance he sounds </l>
            <l>My knowledge of his Guilt! Away with him, </l>
            <l>I cannot bear his Presence. Albimer, </l>
            <l>Be sure you guard him well: convey him straight </l>
            <l>To the sad Queen, and to the Ravish'd Princess; </l>
            <l>Perhaps the sight of such a dreadful Ruin </l>
            <l>As his hot Lust has made, may wake his Conscience, </l>
            <l>And draw a free Confession.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e23410">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— Ha! what said he? </l>
            <l>The Princess Ravish'd! Could the Gods look on, </l>
            <l>And unconcern'd see so much Goodness suffer? </l>
            <l>Nay, then I wonder not that they can see </l>
            <l>My feebler Virtue wrong'd.— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e23480">He is led off by Albimer guarded. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e23500">
            <pb n="34" xml:id="ep000458-022-a"/>
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— But that the Proofs </l>
            <l>Which make his Guilt apparent, are too strong </l>
            <l>To leave a place for doubt, I should my self </l>
            <l>Be shock'd to see his carriage: But he knows </l>
            <l>His life's at stake, and therefore 'tis not strange </l>
            <l>He acts his part so well.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e23580">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>— My Royal Master, </l>
            <l>Thus low I beg you would compose your thoughts, </l>
            <l>And hear your Servant speak.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e23630">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— Speak on, my Lord, </l>
            <l>My mind is calm, and I prepar'd to hear you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e23670">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>Let me not meet your Anger, when I tell you, </l>
            <l>I judge the Prince is innocent: Restrain </l>
            <l>Your Passion, Royal Sir, and hear my Reasons. </l>
            <l>The course of all his former life, renown'd </l>
            <l>For Modesty and Virtue; his late coming </l>
            <l>Unforc'd, unsent for; his surprise and wonder </l>
            <l>To hear that she was Ravish'd; all these join'd, </l>
            <l>Perswade me to conclude that he's not guilty </l>
            <l>Of this most horrid Fact.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e23780">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— I must confess </l>
            <l>They carry wondrous weight: but sure those Proofs </l>
            <l>Which fix the Guilt upon him, have no less. </l>
            <l>But yet, my Lord, such is my Zeal for Justice, </l>
            <l>I'll weigh things nicely, e'er I pass a Sentence </l>
            <l>That cannot be recall'd; for as I wish </l>
            <l>To take just Vengeance for my Sister's Wrongs; </l>
            <l>So Heav'n forbid that Innocence should suffer </l>
            <l>By my mistaken Rage.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e23890">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>— Now Blessings on you, </l>
            <l>Such was your Father's temper. Give me leave </l>
            <l>Humbly to offer something of Advice, </l>
            <l>To try the Prince's Guilt; propose to him </l>
            <l>This fatal choice, to marry her or die: </l>
            <l>If he be guilty, since he knows his life </l>
            <l>Is in your free disposal, he will yield </l>
            <l>To ransom that by wedding her; if not, </l>
            <l>His Royal Blood will prompt him to endure </l>
            <l>Ten thousand Deaths, rather than marry one </l>
            <l>That's Ravish'd by another: make this Tryal, </l>
            <l>And as you find him Innocent or Guilty, </l>
            <l>Absolve, or else Condemn him: for my self, </l>
            <l>My jealous doubts bend all another way, </l>
            <l>But they are yet too young; when they grow riper, </l>
            <l>I beg that to your Royal Ear I may </l>
            <l>Impart my knowledge of them.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e24080">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— With full freedom. </l>
            <pb n="35" xml:id="ep000458-022-b"/>
            <l>'Tis fit, in the mean time, we all prepare </l>
            <l>To meet the rage of cruel Gunderic. </l>
            <l>My Lord, how is this Cittadel provided. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e24150">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>So well, that it will mock the vain attempts </l>
            <l>Of all the Tyrant's Forces, till our Levies </l>
            <l>Are gather'd to an head, and strong enough </l>
            <l>For us to take the Field. For underhand </l>
            <l>We have been working long, and Warlike Vinderic </l>
            <l>Will not be slow to join us. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e24240">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— I dare rely </l>
            <l>On your known Faith, and long Experience. </l>
            <l>Now, Gunderic, sit fast, or I will join </l>
            <l>Thy Crown to that which thou Usurp'st of mine. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e24310">Exeunt. </stage>
        </div>
        <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000458-e24320">
          <head>SCENE the Anti-Chamber. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e24350">A Consort of Martial Musick is heard for some time. Then Enter <hi>Gunderic, Amalazontha, Genselaric, Ferrismond, Rodoric, Almeric, </hi>Guards and Attendants. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e24370">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>This day the Goths to my Victorious Sword </l>
            <l>Gave up their long kept Freedom; and this day </l>
            <l>Shall give them back the Liberty they lost; </l>
            <l>Whilst all distinctions shall be blotted out </l>
            <l>Of Victor and of Vanquish'd; Agilmond </l>
            <l>Our pledge of Love, and theirs, Eurione, </l>
            <l>Shall bind the Faith of Nations, and unite </l>
            <l>Millions of Souls in Bonds of Love and Friendship. </l>
            <l>Methinks I see their Valiant Offspring Reign </l>
            <l>O'er half the Conquer'd Universe! whilst from </l>
            <l>Their Mother's Line they Courage draw, from his </l>
            <l>Both Courage and Success.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e24540">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— He little thinks </l>
            <l>How vain and barren all these hopes must prove. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e24580">Aside. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e24590">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>Where is the Prince, the Gothish Queen and Princesses? </l>
            <l>Methinks e'er now their Presence should have grac'd </l>
            <l>The destin'd Triumph of this happy Day. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e24650">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>The Prince long since, as eager Bridegrooms use, </l>
            <l>Went with Lord Briomer to the Cittadel, </l>
            <l>To attend his lovely Bride. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e24710">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>'Tis well: whilst we expect them, let us try </l>
            <l>To make the lazie Minutes pass more pleasantly </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e24750">A Dance to Hoboys, Kittle-Drums, and Trumpets. After the Entertainment, enter a Vandal. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e24770">
            <speaker>Vand. </speaker>
            <l>Forgive me, Royal Sir, if I declare </l>
            <l>Such News as will astonish and enrage you </l>
            <l>Beyond what you have ever heard.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e24820">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— What means </l>
            <pb n="36" xml:id="ep000458-023-a"/>
            <l>This most amazing Preface to your Story? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e24860">
            <speaker>Vand. </speaker>
            <l>Dread Sir, I should not dare to utter it, </l>
            <l>But that it can no longer be conceal'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e24900">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>Think'st thou my Virtue is so much declin'd, </l>
            <l>I cannot stand the Shock of any Tidings </l>
            <l>Which thou hast heart to bear?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e24950">
            <speaker>Vand. </speaker>
            <l>— My Royal Master, </l>
            <l>Prince Agilmond— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e25000">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— What is he dead?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e25030">
            <speaker>Vand. </speaker>
            <l>— Not so, </l>
            <l>But you will be as much surpriz'd with wonder, </l>
            <l>To hear that he is Seiz'd, Confin'd, and Guarded </l>
            <l>Within the Cittadel.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e25090">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— The Prince Confin'd, </l>
            <l>And Seiz'd! Remove the Madman from me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e25130">
            <speaker>Vand. </speaker>
            <l>Would I were mad, or any thing, or nothing, </l>
            <l>So this were not a truth.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e25170">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— One wish thou hast, </l>
            <l>For mad thou art— A Guard upon the Prince! </l>
            <l>Within the Cittadel! I'th' heart of all my Strength! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e25220">
            <speaker>Vand. </speaker>
            <l>When you shall know by whom he is imprison'd— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e25250">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>Imprison'd! in the middle of my Guards! </l>
            <l>By whom? There is no Mortal dares attempt </l>
            <l>What thou relat'st. But speak what thou art full of; </l>
            <l>I am content a while to hear thee rave. </l>
            <l>By whom?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e25320">
            <speaker>Vand. </speaker>
            <l>— By young Ambiomer.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e25360">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— Madder still! </l>
            <l>What Phantome is this young Ambiomer! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e25410">
            <speaker>Vand. </speaker>
            <l>He is the Gothish Prince.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e25450">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— Furies and Hell! </l>
            <l>How dar'st thou trifle thus with me?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e25490">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>— What Prince? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e25520">
            <speaker>Vand. </speaker>
            <l>Th' Heir Male to the late Gothish King.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e25560">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— Traitor, </l>
            <l>I'll nail thee to the Earth— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e25600">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>— Hold, Royal Sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e25630">
            <speaker>Vand. </speaker>
            <l>I wish my Death might cause that Peace within </l>
            <l>Your Royal Breast, which I must banish thence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e25670">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>A Gothish Prince! whence dropt he? from the Clouds? </l>
            <l>Or is the Mushroom sprung up in a night? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e25720">
            <speaker>Vand. </speaker>
            <l>The late suppos'd Valdaura is declar'd </l>
            <l>Ambiomer, th' Heir Male to Rhadagaise. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e25790">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>What wondrous transformation dost thou talk of? </l>
            <l>Valdaura turn'd into Ambiomer! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e25850">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>A most surprizing Secret! as important </l>
            <l>As that I've kept so long.— </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e25890">Aside, </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e25900">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— But that I know </l>
            <pb n="37" xml:id="ep000458-023-b"/>
            <l>Thou ever hast been held discreet and honest, </l>
            <l>Thy Life had been a forfeit to my Rage. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e25950">
            <speaker>Vand. </speaker>
            <l>And let it still be so if what I say </l>
            <l>Prove in one tittle false.— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e25990">The King muses. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e26000">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— Now Briomer's </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e26040">To Rod. and Alm. </stage>
            <l>Great Secret is disclos'd, the next is mine; </l>
            <l>But though he finds the Gothish Prince, he ne'er </l>
            <l>Shall find the Ravisher.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e26110">
            <speaker>Rod. </speaker>
            <l>— He sooner shall </l>
            <l>Reach up to Heav'n.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e26150">
            <speaker>Alm. </speaker>
            <l>— Or fathom Hell.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e26180">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— Indeed, </l>
            <l>Valdaura still appear'd too rough and haughty </l>
            <l>For that soft Sex; her Spirit seem'd to threaten </l>
            <l>Something above a Woman's heart.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e26250">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>— 'Tis true. </l>
            <l>How often has my watchful Genius </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e26290">Aside. </stage>
            <l>Prompted my Soul, to what my foolish Mercy </l>
            <l>Rejected then as cruel: Had I follow'd </l>
            <l>That faithful Councellour, she long ago </l>
            <l>Had perish'd as Valdaura, and not liv'd </l>
            <l>To act Ambiomer.— </l>
            <l>— Well suppose this were </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e26380">To them. </stage>
            <l>The Gothish Heir; why should they chuse this time </l>
            <l>To broach the mighty Secret? By this Match </l>
            <l>Their Party ev'ry day and hour had gain'd </l>
            <l>New Strength and Vigour; and their doubtful Game </l>
            <l>Might have been play'd with greater hopes of winning. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e26450">
            <speaker>Vand. </speaker>
            <l>The cause of such a quick discovery </l>
            <l>Is yet behind, and 'tis a dismal part </l>
            <l>Of my too dreadful Story. Fair Eurione, </l>
            <l>Destin'd this day for Agilmond, last night </l>
            <l>Was in her private walk surpriz'd, and rifl'd </l>
            <l>Of all her Virgin Treasure.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e26550">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— Ha! what Ravish'd! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e26580">
            <speaker>Vand. </speaker>
            <l>It is too true.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e26610">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— Oh horrid Villany! </l>
            <l>What Hellish Furies have been busie here </l>
            <l>To fill Mankind with Rage beyond their own? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e26660">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>Ah, sweet Eurione! my Heart weeps Tears </l>
            <l>Of Blood for thee.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e26710">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>Just Gods, could ye behold </l>
            <l>So vile a Crime, and keep your Thunder in? </l>
            <l>But your Vicegerent shall perform the part </l>
            <l>You have reserv'd for him. By you I swear, </l>
            <l>Let me but know the Fiend, and he shall live </l>
            <l>Whole years in Torment, roaring out for Death. </l>
            <pb n="38" xml:id="ep000458-024-a"/>
            <l>But what's all this to Agilmond's Confinement? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e26810">
            <speaker>Vand. </speaker>
            <l>There are so many pregnant Circumstances, </l>
            <l>To fix the Guilt of this upon the Prince, </l>
            <l>As caus'd his Seizure; and the sudden Publishing </l>
            <l>Of what their Prudence longer had conceal'd, </l>
            <l>But for this sad Conjuncture.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e26880">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>— How! the Prince! </l>
            <l>Believe him not; 'tis all Imposture, Sir. </l>
            <l>My Son! my Agilmond! It is impossible: </l>
            <l>She was to be his Bride.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e26950">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— 'Tis true, she was; </l>
            <l>Nor could he have so furious a Passion, </l>
            <l>Where he had shewn so much aversion still, </l>
            <l>That I with greatest difficulty wrought him </l>
            <l>To a consent of Marriage.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e27020">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>— You have reason. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e27050">
            <speaker>Vand. </speaker>
            <l>The Gods can witness what I say is true. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e27080">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>Perhaps he scorn'd to make a Captive Princess </l>
            <l>The Partner of his Bed; yet he's not proud. </l>
            <l>Perhaps his hatred to her made him find </l>
            <l>This only way to break the Marriage off. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e27140">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>Can you suspect such wicked Subtlety </l>
            <l>Shou'd dwell with so much Youth and Innocence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e27180">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>My thoughts are in a mist, I am confounded; </l>
            <l>'Tis time must clear up all. But for the new </l>
            <l>Ambiomer, and his Confederate Rebels, </l>
            <l>My swiftest Vengeance shall o'ertake their fault. </l>
            <l>Shall Gunderic endure to be out-brav'd </l>
            <l>By a smooth Boy that scarce knows how to act </l>
            <l>The Manly part his fear so long conceal'd? </l>
            <l>Then let my numerous Conquests be forgotten, </l>
            <l>And my vast Fame shrink to the basest Titles </l>
            <l>Of Slave and Coward. Let us face the Traitors; </l>
            <l>We'll not allow them time to hatch new Treasons, </l>
            <l>But crush them in the Shell Genselaric, </l>
            <l>Get my old Troops together: Ferrismond, </l>
            <l>Draw out the Guards: you Rodoric and Almeric, </l>
            <l>Go raise the City-Bands, and lead them hither. </l>
            <l>By Heav'n! I'll see if this Ambiomer </l>
            <l>Have ought that's worthy of his Valiant Father. </l>
            <l>Make haste, my Lords, we'll gain the Cittadel </l>
            <l>E're night, or bury it and them in Ruins. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e27460">Exeunt. </stage>
        </div>
        <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000458-e27470">
          <pb n="39" xml:id="ep000458-024-b"/>
          <head>SCENE the Cittadel. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e27500">Enter <hi>Ambiomer, Rhadegonda, Briomer, Albimer, Gothish </hi>Lords, &amp;c. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e27520">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>Though all our present hopes seem small and cramp'd </l>
            <l>Within these narrow Walls, yet know, my Lords, </l>
            <l>The mightiest Empires had the same beginning: </l>
            <l>Imperial Rome her self in one poor Hamlet </l>
            <l>Took her first rise, and from that single spot </l>
            <l>O'er-ran the Conquer'd World.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e27610">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>— If Hearts as good, </l>
            <l>And a much better Cause than theirs, can promise </l>
            <l>Equal Success; we need not doubt but Fate </l>
            <l>Will give to our just Arms as ample Progress. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e27670">
            <speaker>Rhad. </speaker>
            <l>The Valiant Vinderic, who for thirty years </l>
            <l>Successfully did fight your Father's Battles, </l>
            <l>Though silver'd o'er with Age. yet tempts again </l>
            <l>War's doubtful hazard: and to assist your Cause, </l>
            <l>Before to Morrow's Sun has touch'd the West, </l>
            <l>Will at the head of thirty thousand Goths </l>
            <l>Come to receive your Orders.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e27780">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— His Arrival </l>
            <l>Will make us strong enough to quit this Fortress </l>
            <l>And take the Field. Gods! how I long to meet </l>
            <l>The haughty Vandal! and with equal Arms </l>
            <l>Retrieve th' immortal Honour of our Name, </l>
            <l>Lost by my slaughter'd Father! Albimer, </l>
            <l>How fares the Captive Prince! does the young Lion </l>
            <l>Struggle, and bite his Chain?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e27900">
            <speaker>Alb. </speaker>
            <l>— My Lord, he bears it </l>
            <l>With as much calmness, as the Soul endures </l>
            <l>The Prison of the Body: he expresses </l>
            <l>Some Sorrow, but no Anger.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e27960">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— When you carry'd him </l>
            <l>To see the Ravish'd Princess, could he brook </l>
            <l>The sight of her unmov'd?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e28010">
            <speaker>Rhad. </speaker>
            <l>— Let me resolve you, </l>
            <l>For I was present then. Soon as he enter'd </l>
            <l>And view'd her in her solemn Pomp of Grief, </l>
            <l>He melted into tears; but when he heard us </l>
            <l>Reproach him as the Author of her Ruine, </l>
            <l>Unable to reply, he deeply sigh'd, </l>
            <l>And fainted in the Arms of Albimer: </l>
            <l>When, by his care reviv'd, he round him cast </l>
            <l>A wild, disorder'd look, then fix'd his eyes </l>
            <pb n="40" xml:id="ep000458-025-a"/>
            <l>Upon Eurione, and softly told her, </l>
            <l>He never had the Will, and had he that, </l>
            <l>He wanted Pow'r to wrong her; there he stop'd, </l>
            <l>And struggled with himself, as if he labour'd </l>
            <l>With something sit for us to know, and yet </l>
            <l>Unfit for him to tell.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e28200">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— His inward guilt </l>
            <l>Then stuck him to the quick, and prompted him </l>
            <l>To make a free Discovery; but the danger </l>
            <l>Which threaten'd that proceeding, stifled it, </l>
            <l>And kept him silent still.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e28270">
            <speaker>Rhad. </speaker>
            <l>— If he be guilty, </l>
            <l>(As I can neither yet condemn nor quit him) </l>
            <l>Never did any Guilt wear such a Mask </l>
            <l>Of well-dissembled Innocence.— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e28330">Enter a Goth. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e28350">
            <speaker>Goth. </speaker>
            <l>— My Lord, </l>
            <l>The Captain of the Guards, sent by the King, </l>
            <l>Desires admittance.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e28400">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— Let him have it. Briomer, </l>
            <l>Conduct him in: Now, Madam, we shall hear </l>
            <l>How Gunderic resents our bold Attempt: </l>
            <l>I know it grates his haughty Soul, to find </l>
            <l>A Rival Prince, that dares affront and brave him </l>
            <l>Just at his Palace Gates.— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e28500">Enter Ferrismond and Briomer. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e28530">
            <speaker>Fer. </speaker>
            <l>— My Royal Master, </l>
            <l>Not knowing yet which 'tis more fit to call </l>
            <l>The new-found Prince, Valdaura or Ambiomer, </l>
            <l>Commands me, Madam, to demand of you, </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e28610">To Rhad. </stage>
            <l>Why on this solemn day, design'd to make </l>
            <l>You and your Nation happy, you attempt </l>
            <l>To frustrate and abuse his good intentions; </l>
            <l>To seize the Sacred Person of his Son; </l>
            <l>Shut up his Royal Cittadel; disturb </l>
            <l>The common Peace; and with rebellious Arms </l>
            <l>Provoke the Indignation of a Prince, </l>
            <l>Who sixteen years has nourish'd you and yours </l>
            <l>With tenderness and love?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e28720">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— Yes as a Guardian, </l>
            <l>That flaunts and revels with his Ward's Estate, </l>
            <l>But keeps him bare and scanty. Royal Madam, </l>
            <l>Permit me, if you please, to give an Answer </l>
            <l>To this so lofty Message. Tell your Master, </l>
            <l>My slaughter'd Father, and my ravish'd Sister, </l>
            <l>Call both for just Revenge; the one on him, </l>
            <l>The other on his Son: My Royal Birth, </l>
            <l>And Rhadagaise's Great Example, prompt me </l>
            <l>Rather to dye a King, than live a Slave: </l>
            <pb n="41" xml:id="ep000458-025-b"/>
            <l>This Fatal Day, which blushes to set off </l>
            <l>The yearly Pride of Gunderic, calls on me </l>
            <l>To rescue it from such a shameful Office, </l>
            <l>And make it shine again in Gothish Annals, </l>
            <l>Stamp'd with the glorious Mark of Regain'd Liberty. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e28920">
            <speaker>Fer. </speaker>
            <l>For fair Eurione's lamented Fate, </l>
            <l>My King vies Sorrow with you; and engages </l>
            <l>His Royal Word, to punish that Offence, </l>
            <l>Where-ever prov'd, tho' on the Prince himself; </l>
            <l>With utmost rigour; this his love to Justice, </l>
            <l>And pity of her injur'd Innocence, </l>
            <l>Oblige him to perform.— For you, my Lord, </l>
            <l>And those whom your Example or Perswasions </l>
            <l>Have in your Guilt involv'd, thus he ordains, </l>
            <l>Give up the Cittadel, and jointly try </l>
            <l>With humble Duty to appease his Anger, </l>
            <l>And he'll impute this rash and heedless Action </l>
            <l>To Heat of Youth, and to the sudden Passion </l>
            <l>Caus'd by your Sister's Wrongs. If you refuse, </l>
            <l>He comes prepar'd to force you to Obedience, </l>
            <l>And crush you with his Vengeance.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e29110">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— Sure he thinks </l>
            <l>I am Valdaura still; and that my Soul </l>
            <l>Is of the Female Stamp; he would not else </l>
            <l>Propose such servile Terms, as feeble Women </l>
            <l>Would almost blush to stoop to. Let him not </l>
            <l>Despise me, that some years my Manly Limbs </l>
            <l>Were clad in Female Weeds; so was Achilles, </l>
            <l>And from less glorious Motives. Tell your Master, </l>
            <l>Ambiomer will ne're submit the Cause </l>
            <l>Of his wrong'd Sister to such partial Justice, </l>
            <l>But will himself Examine and Revenge it: </l>
            <l>Say, I was born a King, and scorn to dye </l>
            <l>With any meaner Title: For his Threats </l>
            <l>I heed them as I ought; when e'er he dares </l>
            <l>Attempt our Strength, we dare oppose his Fury, </l>
            <l>And with Superiour Force and Valour break </l>
            <l>His weak Efforts. Return this Answer to him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e29330">
            <speaker>Fer. </speaker>
            <l>Since you refuse to taste his Royal Clemency, </l>
            <l>Prepare to meet his Vengeance.— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e29370">Ex. Ferrism. and Briom. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e29400">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— Wait him forth. </l>
            <l>My Lords, we must expect to be assail'd, </l>
            <l>And speedily; the Rage of Gunderic </l>
            <l>Will, like a sudden Whirl-wind, drive him hither: </l>
            <l>Prepare to give the rugged Visitant </l>
            <l>Such Entertainment as his Visit merits. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e29490">Exeunt. </stage>
        </div>
        <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000458-e29500">
          <pb n="42" xml:id="ep000458-026-a"/>
          <head>SCENE a Chamber in the Cittadel. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e29530">Enter Agilmond. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e29550">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>Death, which at distance seems so terrible, </l>
            <l>View'd nearer looks less dreadful; and to me </l>
            <l>Has in it more to be desir'd than fear'd: </l>
            <l>But to be Executed as a Ravisher, </l>
            <l>Is something worse than death, 'tis death of Fame: </l>
            <l>Yet even that Fate carries this Comfort with it, </l>
            <l>The fatal Secret of my Sex dies with me, </l>
            <l>And leaves the Queen in safety. Tho' I cannot </l>
            <l>Be so unjust to my own Innocence, </l>
            <l>To own so black a Guilt; yet since my death </l>
            <l>Secures my Royal Mother, I'll suppress </l>
            <l>The certain Means to clear me, and submit </l>
            <l>To what the Gods and Fate have order'd for me. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e29700">Enter Ambiomer. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e29720">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>See! there he stands, calm and compos'd; nor does </l>
            <l>One line in all that lovely Face, denote him </l>
            <l>Lustful or Ravisher: When-e're I see him, </l>
            <l>Something within me strongly pleads, and tells me </l>
            <l>He must be innocent. If he be guilty, </l>
            <l>The Gods themselves are faulty too, in giving him </l>
            <l>So foul a Heart, and such a Face to hide it. </l>
            <l>I must not let him know how much my thoughts </l>
            <l>Are chang'd in favour of him. Solitude </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e29830">To him. </stage>
            <l>And close Retirement often hold the Glass </l>
            <l>To guilty Minds, and make them see their Faults </l>
            <l>In their true ugly Colours; have they had </l>
            <l>The same effect on you?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e29880">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— A guilty Solitude </l>
            <l>May have Effects like these; but Innocence </l>
            <l>Is always best, when suffer'd to enjoy </l>
            <l>The prospect of it self.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e29940">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— Then you still stand </l>
            <l>Upon your first Defence?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e29980">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— I cannot alter: </l>
            <l>Falsehood is almost infinite, but Truth </l>
            <l>Is still the same.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e30030">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— So very willingly </l>
            <l>I would believe him, that I scarce can urge </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e30070">Aside. </stage>
            <l>A Reason to disprove him. What occasion </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e30090">To him. </stage>
            <l>Led you so late into the Palace Walks, </l>
            <pb n="43" xml:id="ep000458-026-b"/>
            <l>And brought you back so hastily?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e30120">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— Desire </l>
            <l>To meet the lovely Princess led me thither; </l>
            <l>And, tho I blush to own it, 'twas my Fear </l>
            <l>That brought me back so soon.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e30180">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— Your Fear! of what? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e30210">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>I thought, as I advanc'd, I heard some shrieks, </l>
            <l>Which robb'd the Night of all its former stillness, </l>
            <l>And gave it greater horrour: Much amaz'd, </l>
            <l>I durst not venture on, but soon return'd </l>
            <l>Without one Moment's stay.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e30280">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— This free account </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e30310">Aside▪ </stage>
            <l>Looks so like Truth, I cannot disbelieve it. </l>
            <l>This is your Dagger, yesternight you drop'd it; </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e30340">To him. </stage>
            <l>Can you remember where?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e30360">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— Nor where, nor when: </l>
            <l>Only thus much I know, I mist it first </l>
            <l>When from your Royal Mother I retir'd </l>
            <l>With Gunderic.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e30430">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— Now on a Prince's Word, </l>
            <l>Which ought to be as sacred as the Oaths </l>
            <l>Of Vulgar Souls, answer me truly; did you </l>
            <l>Then miss your Dagger when you say, nor had it </l>
            <l>In your possession since?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e30500">
            <speaker>Agil. </speaker>
            <l>— By all my Hopes </l>
            <l>Of Happiness, I never view'd it since, </l>
            <l>Till you produc'd it now.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e30550">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— My Lord, your words </l>
            <l>Have stagger'd my Belief, and make me doubt </l>
            <l>I have been led by false Appearances: </l>
            <l>But till I'm more resolv'd, I must detain you </l>
            <l>A Prisoner still: If you are Innocent, </l>
            <l>That Knowledge will compose and calm your thoughts▪ </l>
            <l>What pity 'tis, ye Gods, we seldom find </l>
            <l>A just Resemblance of the Face and Mind! </l>
            <l>Could we but read the Hearts of Men, like you, </l>
            <l>What God-like Justice might we Monarchs do! </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e30670">Exeunt severally. </stage>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="ep000458-e30680">
        <pb n="44" xml:id="ep000458-027-a"/>
        <head>ACT V. </head>
        <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000458-e30700">
          <head>SCENE a Chamber-Royal. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e30730">Enter Gunderic and Amalazontha. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e30760">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>THat Love by which you urge me to a grant, </l>
            <l>Denies your strange request; Why should you tempt </l>
            <l>Unnecessary hazards? your soft Sex, </l>
            <l>In safety plac'd, should leave to us the dangers </l>
            <l>And drudgery of War.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e30830">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>— There is no danger: </l>
            <l>Or were it ne'er so great, I ought to share it </l>
            <l>As well as your Success; besides, my Agilmond </l>
            <l>Is now at stake; and every doubtful minute, </l>
            <l>By leaving me uncertain of his Fate, </l>
            <l>Will give me many Deaths.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e30920">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— You shall o'ercome: </l>
            <l>But lest some fatal Dart should rob me of you, </l>
            <l>I'll once more offer Mercy, and my self </l>
            <l>In Person treat with them.— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e30980">Enter Ferrismond. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e31000">
            <speaker>Fer. </speaker>
            <l>— My Lord, your Forces </l>
            <l>Are all drawn up, and wait for your Commands. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e31040">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>Let them advance, and tell them, Ferrismond, </l>
            <l>My Queen and I will head them. This rash Boy </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e31090">Exit Ferrismond. </stage>
            <l>Has by this vain Attempt giv'n me fair warning </l>
            <l>To make sure work; and I with little pains </l>
            <l>May quash this young Rebellion.— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e31140">Enter a Vandal. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e31160">
            <speaker>Vandal. </speaker>
            <l>— Pardon, Sir, </l>
            <l>The luckless Bearer of unwelcome news: </l>
            <l>Old Vinderic, the Gothish General, </l>
            <l>Is at the head of thirty thousand Rebels </l>
            <l>Advancing hither.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e31250">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— Then we shall have work </l>
            <l>More tough than I expected. How near are they? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e31290">
            <speaker>Vandal. </speaker>
            <l>Last Night they quarter'd seven Leagues off, to Morrow </l>
            <l>Expect to see them here.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e31330">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— I'm satisfi'd; </l>
            <l>We shall have time enough to finish here </l>
            <l>Before they can arrive. O Agilmond, </l>
            <l>Thy Guilt, if prov'd, will more distract my Soul, </l>
            <l>Than the united Force of all my Enemies. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e31410">Exeunt. </stage>
        </div>
        <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000458-e31420">
          <pb n="45" xml:id="ep000458-027-b"/>
          <head>SCENE, the Cittadel. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e31450">Enter <hi>Ambiomer, Briomer, Albimer, Gothish </hi>Lords, &amp;c. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e31470">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>Though long Experience join'd with daring Valour, </l>
            <l>Are met in Gunderic, to make up an Enemy </l>
            <l>Too great to be despis'd; yet your known Courage, </l>
            <l>And our just Cause do give me full Assurance </l>
            <l>Of wish'd Success: I feel an inward joy, </l>
            <l>Which tells me this important Day will crown </l>
            <l>Our forward hopes with vast Advantages. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e31570">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>May all those hopes prove true! or only fail </l>
            <l>In promising less than your Fate performs! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e31610">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord, I thank you: Gunderic, I hear, </l>
            <l>Whose fiery temper hates the dull delay </l>
            <l>Of formally Besieging, has resolv'd </l>
            <l>To carry us by Storm; we must prepare </l>
            <l>To give him a sharp welcome. Hark! his Drums! </l>
            <l>He's advancing towards us; let us all </l>
            <l>Attend our several Charges. Come, my Lords, </l>
            <l>Now let us shew the ancient Gothish Courage, </l>
            <l>Which made the Romans tremble. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e31750">Exeunt. </stage>
        </div>
        <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000458-e31760">
          <head>SCENE A large Space before the Cittadel. Drums beat a March. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e31790">Enter <hi>Gunderic, Amalazontha, Genselaric, Ferrismond, Rodoric, Almeric, </hi>&amp;c. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e31810">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>Though with our Arms in Hand 'tis much below us </l>
            <l>To treat with Rebels, yet since you, my Queen </l>
            <l>May be expos'd to some unlucky Arrow, </l>
            <l>We'll condescend to parly. Let our Drums </l>
            <l>Declare our pleasure to them.— </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e31880">Drums beat a Parly, then <hi>Ambiomer, Briomer</hi>, &amp;c. appear on the Walls. </stage>
            <l>— Which is he </l>
            <l>You call Ambiomer, the new-found Prince? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e31930">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>I am Ambiomer, King of the Goths, </l>
            <l>And rightful Owner of those large Dominions </l>
            <l>Possess'd by Rhadagaise, my Royal Father. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e32010">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>To me he lost them; by this Arm he fell, </l>
            <l>And with him fell his Kingdom.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e32050">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— You then claim </l>
            <l>By right of Conquest only; and if I </l>
            <l>By Strength of Arms can pluck that Title from you, </l>
            <pb n="46" xml:id="ep000458-028-a"/>
            <l>The right again is mine.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e32110">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— O! never hope it: </l>
            <l>As soon you may from the avenging Pow'rs </l>
            <l>Snatch their dread Bolts of Fury, as from me, </l>
            <l>That which my Sword made mine. But listen now </l>
            <l>To what my Pity of your Youth inclines me. </l>
            <l>So well I love the Brave, that though this Action </l>
            <l>Does savour more of Rrashness, or Despair, </l>
            <l>Than prudent Valour; yet, release the Prince, </l>
            <l>Give up the Fortress, and return again </l>
            <l>To your forsaken Duty, and your Fault </l>
            <l>Shall die forgotten, like an idle Dream </l>
            <l>That pass'd unheeded by.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e32250">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>—— Such Dreams as these </l>
            <l>Carry vast moment with them, and oft-times </l>
            <l>Portend the fall of Monarchs. Think not, Gunderic, </l>
            <l>That this attempt is like a short-liv'd Blazo </l>
            <l>That dies as soon as kindl'd: no, the Justice </l>
            <l>On which our Cause is built, though we should perish, </l>
            <l>Would from the midst of your own Subjects raise </l>
            <l>Some Valiant Spirit to redress our Wrongs, </l>
            <l>And bravely strike to right a Ravish'd Virgin. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e32370">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>Be witness for me, Gods, how much I loath </l>
            <l>A Villany like that! How much my Heart </l>
            <l>Deplores with Tears of Blood the Virtuous Princess! </l>
            <l>And if the Prince be Guilty, not your self </l>
            <l>Should run more greedily to just Revenge </l>
            <l>Than I; no more I'll own him for my Son, </l>
            <l>But blot him from my Memory for ever, </l>
            <l>And give him up to Justice.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e32470">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— 'Tis not safe </l>
            <l>To venture so the Honour of our Race </l>
            <l>Upon the partial Justice of a Father: </l>
            <l>The soundest Proofs against so strong a Prejudice </l>
            <l>Will weigh but little.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e32540">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— How have I descended </l>
            <l>Below my self, to bandy words with Rebels, </l>
            <l>And in return, meet nothing but Contempt! </l>
            <l>But I will rowze my sleeping Majesty, </l>
            <l>And speak in Thunder to them.— Hear me you </l>
            <l>That try beneath the Prince to shroud the Traitor, </l>
            <l>Hear what your King commands. Deliver up </l>
            <l>The Fortress straight, and with a quick Submission </l>
            <l>Implore the Pardon you so proudly slighted, </l>
            <l>Or the Revenge which I will take, shall stand </l>
            <l>To after times exemplary and dreadful. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e32670">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>Threats cannot frighten Men: now hear me, Gunderic. </l>
            <pb n="47" xml:id="ep000458-028-b"/>
            <l>Not that I doubt the Issue, or despair </l>
            <l>Of wish'd Success; but that I may not leave </l>
            <l>To chance, a thing of such vast consequence </l>
            <l>As is our House's Honour, which would suffer </l>
            <l>In wanting just Revenge; soon as your Forces </l>
            <l>Attempt our Strengths, the Head of Agilmond, </l>
            <l>Reeking with Blood, shall be thrown over to you: </l>
            <l>And the first hour of your Assault shall be </l>
            <l>His last of Life.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e32810">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>— The Head of Agilmond! </l>
            <l>Forbid it, Heav'n! rather let me disclose, <stage xml:id="ep000458-e32860">Aside. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>With hazard of my Life, the fatal Secret </l>
            <l>Which has so long lain hid!— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e32890">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— You dare not act </l>
            <l>What you would seem to threaten.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e32930">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— Let my daring </l>
            <l>Be put to tryal, and you soon will find </l>
            <l>How much I dare, or little.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e32980">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— Now, by Heav'ns, </l>
            <l>He mocks my Anger, the insulting Boy! </l>
            <l>And dallies with my Rage. But let me live </l>
            <l>Branded with the base Names of Slave and Coward, </l>
            <l>If any tame results of Blood or Nature </l>
            <l>With-hold my just Revenge. Genselaric, </l>
            <l>Begin th' Assault. Perish ten thousand Sons, </l>
            <l>Rather than I'll endure Affronts like these: </l>
            <l>Though Agilmond should fall, my Noble Vengeance </l>
            <l>Shall, like another Son, keep up my Fame, </l>
            <l>And make my Name Immortal.— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e33130">Is going, Amalazontha holds him. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e33150">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>— Stay! O stay! </l>
            <l>My Royal Husband; and before you go </l>
            <l>To this most fatal Conflict, give one Moment </l>
            <l>To the sad Transports of a mourning Mother: </l>
            <l>And you Ambiomer, attend a while, </l>
            <l>For I have mighty Wonders to disclose. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e33240">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>What means the Woman? Can you have ought to say </l>
            <l>That may at such a time as this be worth </l>
            <l>One Moment's stop?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e33290">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>— Yes, my lov'd Lord, I have. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e33320">Kneeling. </stage>
            <l>But first unbend your Brow, whilst on my Knees </l>
            <l>I humbly beg your Pardon, that I durst </l>
            <l>Thus long deceive you: Agilmond is not </l>
            <l>What he appears, nor could commit a Rape </l>
            <l>On fair Eurione.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e33400">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— You speak in Riddles; </l>
            <l>Explain your mystick meaning, and dispatch us. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e33440">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>Let me not lose your Love for ever, when </l>
            <pb n="48" xml:id="ep000458-029-a"/>
            <l>I tell you he's a Woman.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e33480">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— Ha! a Woman! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e33510">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>Ye Gods! can this be true?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e33540">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>— Put off your wonder, </l>
            <l>Whilst I unfold the mighty Mystery. </l>
            <l>When you, my Lord, went to the Gothish War, </l>
            <l>You left me pregnant; </l>
            <l>And your impatient wishes for a Son </l>
            <l>Forc'd out a Solemn Vow, that if my Issue </l>
            <l>Prov'd Female, it should die.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e33640">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— 'Tis true, I did so; </l>
            <l>And though the Vow was rash, yet being made, </l>
            <l>I had not fail'd to keep it.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e33690">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>— Too well I know it; </l>
            <l>And therefore many doubtful Conflicts pass'd </l>
            <l>'Twixt a Wife's Duty, and a Mother's tenderness: </l>
            <l>Nature at last o'recame, and made me venture </l>
            <l>What most I fear'd, your Anger, nay, your Hatred, </l>
            <l>To save a harmless Babe. My time drew near; </l>
            <l>And I, assisted by two faithful Servants, </l>
            <l>Dispos'd all things with privacy and care </l>
            <l>To favour the deceit: My pangs were short, </l>
            <l>And soon rewarded with the happy Birth </l>
            <l>Of a most lovely Child, but as my fears </l>
            <l>Too truly had suggested, of that Sex </l>
            <l>Which you had doom'd to Death. I then resolv'd </l>
            <l>To put in practice what I long design'd, </l>
            <l>And bred it as a Male.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e33860">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— 'Tis wondrous strange! </l>
            <l>How could you blind the piercing eyes of those </l>
            <l>Whom I at my departure had appointed </l>
            <l>To pry into its Sex?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e33920">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>— A new born Male </l>
            <l>Was by my Faithful Confidents prepar'd; </l>
            <l>Which hid within the Bed, and drawn from thence, </l>
            <l>Confirm'd them all that I had born a Son: </l>
            <l>My Infant Daughter was for some few Weeks, </l>
            <l>Under pretence of Sickness, bred in private; </l>
            <l>And for her real Name of Elismonda, </l>
            <l>Took that of Agilmond.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e34040">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— The strange Events </l>
            <l>Of this amazing day have been so wonderful, </l>
            <l>Methinks I stand prepar'd to credit firmly </l>
            <l>The most unlikely News. 'Tis you, ye Gods, </l>
            <l>Whose over-ruling Providence contriv'd </l>
            <l>This Maze of Fate! and Kings, though Gods on Earth </l>
            <l>Must not contest with you! Nor have I lost </l>
            <pb n="49" xml:id="ep000458-029-b"/>
            <l>By this Exchange; since for a Son, whose weakness </l>
            <l>Has often made me blush, I gain a Daughter </l>
            <l>Well worth the owning. Madam, rise; and let </l>
            <l>This strict Embrace attone for all the troubles </l>
            <l>Which my rash Vow has caus'd you.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e34180">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>— Let me thus </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e34210">Kneeling again. </stage>
            <l>Receive the mighty Blessing.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e34230">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— Now, Ambiomer, </l>
            <l>You see the rash Mistakes to which your Passion </l>
            <l>Has led you Blindfold: Agilmond, you find, </l>
            <l>Cannot be guilty of that horrid Rape </l>
            <l>Of which he stands accus'd.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e34320">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— My Lord, I know it; </l>
            <l>And 'tis with wondrous shame that I reflect </l>
            <l>On the unworthy treatment I have given </l>
            <l>That injur'd Princess: But it is not yet </l>
            <l>Too late to make amends, and my Repentance </l>
            <l>Shall move with winged haste. Madam, I go </l>
            <l>To send you that lov'd Daughter, which has been </l>
            <l>So much the Care of Heav'n. But oh! my Sister! </l>
            <l>Where shall we find the Lustful Villain now, </l>
            <l>That robb'd thee of thy Honour?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e34440">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— Stay, Ambiomer, </l>
            <l>And hear me speak; I see so much of Honour </l>
            <l>Break through your gusts of Passion, that at once </l>
            <l>I pity and esteem you; and to shew it, </l>
            <l>Invite you to come forth: On a King's Word, </l>
            <l>(And he who trusts my Honour, never shall </l>
            <l>Have reason to repent him) you shall meet </l>
            <l>With Honourable Usage. Fate and I </l>
            <l>Have mighty thinks in store for your advantage, </l>
            <l>Unless your own Distrust of both defeat them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e34570">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>Consider, Sir, e'er you consent too easily, </l>
            <l>That the whole Fortune of the Gothish Nation </l>
            <l>Depends upon your Conduct. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e34630">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>I will answer </l>
            <l>For the Success of what I now design: </l>
            <l>I see his aim, nor will I doubt his Honour. </l>
            <l>My Lord, I am resolv'd to trust your Honour, </l>
            <l>And wait the Princess home: But first be pleas'd </l>
            <l>To draw your Forces off, that my Surrender </l>
            <l>May have no shew of Fear.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e34720">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— Genselaric, </l>
            <l>Conduct them off; come, my Amalazontha, </l>
            <l>The Triumphs which were destin'd for this day </l>
            <l>Shall yet go on, and, tho thus cross'd, shall join </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e34790">Drums beating, Trumpets sounding. </stage>
            <l>A double Crown for ever in our Line. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e34810">Exeunt Gund. &amp;c. below, Ambiomer, &amp;c. above. </stage>
        </div>
        <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000458-e34840">
          <pb n="50" xml:id="ep000458-030-a"/>
          <head>SCENE, A Chamber in the Cittadel. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e34870">Enter Ambiomer and Briomer. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e34900">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>You know, my Lord, 'twas always my Opinion, </l>
            <l>That Agilmond was Innocent; and once </l>
            <l>I hinted to you, my suspitions tended </l>
            <l>Another way; they're now so much confirm'd, </l>
            <l>I dare impart them to you.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e34980">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— Good my Lord, </l>
            <l>Inform me quickly, that my Rage may find </l>
            <l>A lawful Object, and my Breast be quieted </l>
            <l>With Hopes of just Revenge for my wrong'd Sister. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e35040">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>As it appear'd unlikely, that the Prince </l>
            <l>Should snatch by force what the succeeding night </l>
            <l>Had giv'n him freely; so it seem'd to me </l>
            <l>Most probable, that some despairing Lover, </l>
            <l>Cut off from all his Hopes, should force the Joy, </l>
            <l>Which otherwise he was to lose for ever: </l>
            <l>This made me doubt the General; with whose love </l>
            <l>To fair Eurione I'm well acquainted, </l>
            <l>And had it from himself.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e35160">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— His love to her </l>
            <l>The Queen inform'd me of; but that alone </l>
            <l>Seems much too weak a ground to judge him Guilty. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e35210">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>I grant, my Lord, it is; and therefore this </l>
            <l>Did but awake my Doubts: What shock'd me more, </l>
            <l>Was that I learn'd he had not been at home </l>
            <l>During that dismal Night.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e35270">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— I must confess </l>
            <l>Such an unusual absence look'd suspicious. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e35310">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>But that which most confirms me that he was </l>
            <l>The Ravisher, is the Confusion visible </l>
            <l>In him and his upon the late Discovery </l>
            <l>Of Agilmond's true Sex; for I my Eyes </l>
            <l>Did rivet to their Faces, and observ'd </l>
            <l>More than Surprise, Vexation, Grief, and Care, </l>
            <l>With frequent Whispers, and such cloudy Looks </l>
            <l>As Guilty Men can never well put off. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e35420">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>Continue, my dear Briomer, to make </l>
            <l>Your Observations still. </l>
            <l>But I will yet be calm, and when our Doubts </l>
            <l>Are grown up into Certainties, fall on him </l>
            <l>With unresisted Fury.— Is the Princess </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e35500">Enter Albimer. </stage>
            <l>Yet ready to depart?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e35530">
            <speaker>Albi. </speaker>
            <l>— My Lord, she is; </l>
            <pb n="51" xml:id="ep000458-030-b"/>
            <l>And in her Female Habit looks so lovely, </l>
            <l>That none, except the fair Eurione, </l>
            <l>Can vie with her for Beauty.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e35600">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— When she pass'd </l>
            <l>For Agilmond, her Features and Complexion </l>
            <l>Were much too delicate for what she seem'd. </l>
            <l>My Lords, let all attend her to the Palace; </l>
            <l>The King, though cruel, has a generous Soul, </l>
            <l>And will not wrong our Trust. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e35690">Exeunt. </stage>
        </div>
        <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000458-e35700">
          <head>SCENE a rich Hall in the Palace. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e35730">Enter <hi>Gunderic, Amalazontha, Genselaric, Ferrismond, Rodoric, Almeric, </hi>Guards and Attendants. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e35750">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>How strange are all the turns of Providence! </l>
            <l>And by what secret steps does Heav'n advance </l>
            <l>Its own designs, and mock our humane Prudence! </l>
            <l>Yet where it means to bless, it makes us happy </l>
            <l>By Methods hid from us: This day's design </l>
            <l>Was to unite in Bands of lasting Friendship </l>
            <l>The Vandals and the Goths, and join by Marriage </l>
            <l>The double Royal Line; and that intent </l>
            <l>This happy day will finish, but by ways </l>
            <l>Unthought of, unforeseen: a Male and Female </l>
            <l>Are on each side discover'd, long conceal'd </l>
            <l>For Reasons almost equal; Fate has match'd them, </l>
            <l>And the agreeing course of both their lives </l>
            <l>Has mark'd them each for other.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e35930">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>— 'Tis so visible, </l>
            <l>That to oppose it were to fight with Heav'n, </l>
            <l>And counterplot the Wisdom of the Gods. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e35980">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>I long to see the new found Elismonda </l>
            <l>Drest in her Sex's Habit; if she bears </l>
            <l>Her change as well as young Ambiomer, </l>
            <l>I shall not much regret the loss of Agilmond. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e36070">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>He has, indeed, a charming Manly Beauty, </l>
            <l>Which challenges at once, Respect and Love. </l>
            <l>But hark! your Subjects joy proclaim their coming; </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e36120">Shouts within. </stage>
            <l>And see, they're here already— </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e36140">Enter <hi>Ambiomer, Elismonda </hi>in her own habit, <hi>Briomer, Albimer, Gothish </hi>Lords, &amp;c. </stage>
            <l>— O! my Daughter; </l>
            <l>Is it then giv'n me to embrace you thus? </l>
            <l>To call you Elismonda? and behold you </l>
            <l>Confess'd what Nature meant you?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e36220">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>Accept, my Daughter, </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e36250">Embracing her. </stage>
            <pb n="52" xml:id="ep000458-031-a"/>
            <l>A Father's Penitence, who ne'er had pass'd </l>
            <l>So harsh a Doom upon your Infant State, </l>
            <l>Could he have then foreseen the mighty Joys </l>
            <l>Your riper Years have brought him.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e36300">
            <speaker>Elis. </speaker>
            <l>— Royal Sir, </l>
            <l>Excuse a Criminal that dar'd to live </l>
            <l>When doom'd to death by you.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e36350">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— Let us blot out </l>
            <l>Those sad Remembrances, and turn our thoughts </l>
            <l>To Scenes of welcome Joy.— To you, brave Prince, </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e36400">To Amb. </stage>
            <l>And your mistaken Zeal, we owe the blest </l>
            <l>Discov'ry of this Secret; and your firm </l>
            <l>Reliance on my Honour, has engag'd </l>
            <l>My grateful Soul to make you large Returns; </l>
            <l>Nor shall they be delay'd: but where's the Queen </l>
            <l>Your Royal Mother?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e36480">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— With my mourning Sister. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e36510">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>Alas! poor injur'd Innocence! How I lov'd her, </l>
            <l>My late design of matching her with Agilmond </l>
            <l>Sufficiently exprest; how now I pity her, </l>
            <l>My dire Revenge upon the lustful Villain, </l>
            <l>Whene'er found out, that robb'd her of her Honour, </l>
            <l>Shall loudly prove. But say, Ambiomer, </l>
            <l>On what strange ground did your Suspicion work, </l>
            <l>To six the Guilt of such an horrid Action </l>
            <l>On the supposed Agilmond?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e36650">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— I never </l>
            <l>Should dare to look upon this injur'd Princess </l>
            <l>Had I not gone upon the strongest Circumstances </l>
            <l>That could engage Belief. Your Majesty </l>
            <l>Well knows this Dagger; in the very place </l>
            <l>Where that foul Villany was done, I found it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e36730">
            <speaker>Elis. </speaker>
            <l>I know not where I lost it, but I guess, </l>
            <l>'Twas in the Gothish Queen's Apartment.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e36780">
            <speaker>Fer. </speaker>
            <l>— Madam, </l>
            <l>I saw you drop it there; and I remember </l>
            <l>I stoop'd to take it up, but was prevented </l>
            <l>By Rodoric.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e36850">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>— My Lord, observ'd you that? </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e36880">To Amb. aside, </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e36900">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>By Rodoric? He then must needs be able </l>
            <l>To give us some account of this dire action. </l>
            <l>Come hither, Rodoric; you know that Dagger? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e36970">
            <speaker>Rod. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord, I think I oft have seen it worn </l>
            <l>By our fair Princess.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e37010">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— Had you it of late </l>
            <l>In your Possession? Speak.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e37050">
            <speaker>Rod. </speaker>
            <l>— No, Royal Sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e37080">
            <pb n="53" xml:id="ep000458-031-b"/>
            <speaker>Fer. </speaker>
            <l>Sure you forget; I saw you take it up </l>
            <l>But Yesterday.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e37120">
            <speaker>Rod. </speaker>
            <l>— 'Tis true, indeed, I did; </l>
            <l>But lost it soon.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e37160">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— It must be so, he falters: </l>
            <l>By all my hopes of Glory, he's the Villain. </l>
            <l>My Guards, there, seize and bear him hence to Torture; </l>
            <l>We'll see what Sense the Rack will force from him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e37220">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>So much I hate a Crime so black as his, </l>
            <l>I'll see him rack'd my self, and bring your Majesty </l>
            <l>A just account.— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e37270">Briomer <hi>whispers the King</hi>. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e37290">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— My Lord, you much amaze me: </l>
            <l>But nought shall be omitted, that may serve </l>
            <l>To solve this fatal Riddle. Seize the General. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e37340">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>Me! Royal Sir?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e37370">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— I will not hear him speak. </l>
            <l>Intreat the Queen and Ravish'd Princess hither. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e37410">Exit Briomer </stage>
            <l>Now bear that Villain forth. You, Ferrismond, </l>
            <l>Go see him rack'd, and bring me an account </l>
            <l>Of what he shall discover.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e37470">
            <speaker>Rod. </speaker>
            <l>In vain you seek what you must never find; </l>
            <l>An Innocence like mine can laugh at Torments. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e37510">Is carried off, Ferrismond attends, &amp;c. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e37530">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— Now, Ambiomer, </l>
            <l>Prepare to see what just Revenge I'll take </l>
            <l>Upon the Lustful Slave that durst pollute </l>
            <l>The Sacred Blood of Kings.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e37600">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— This Royal Justice </l>
            <l>For ever makes me yours.— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e37640">Enter <hi>Rhadegonda, Eurione </hi>in Mourning, and Briomer. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e37670">
            <speaker>Eur. </speaker>
            <l>Ah! whither do you lead me, cruel Briomer? </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e37710">Eurione <hi>draws back</hi>. </stage>
            <l>Let me for ever hide my Face in Darkness: </l>
            <l>I am not sit for Light; a stain like mine </l>
            <l>Should seek for Everlasting Night to cover it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e37760">
            <speaker>Brio. </speaker>
            <l>Madam, the King invites you to assist </l>
            <l>In the discovery of the cursed Ravisher, </l>
            <l>And then to taste the Pleasure of just Vengeance. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e37810">
            <speaker>Eur. </speaker>
            <l>Vengeance? will that restore my Ravish'd Honour? </l>
            <l>I cannot bear their eyes; already see </l>
            <l>All turn and gaze, as if they saw a Monster. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e37860">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>Approach, fair Sufferer; and suspend a while </l>
            <l>Your cruel Griefs, to entertain a Joy </l>
            <l>The Gods themselves are fond of, just Revenge. </l>
            <l>View this supposed Criminal; not my Blood </l>
            <l>Which flows within his Veins, shall priviledge him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e37930">
            <pb n="54" xml:id="ep000458-032-a"/>
            <speaker>Eur. </speaker>
            <l>Oh I have seen enough: the Ring! the Ring! </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e37960">Swoons away, they chafe her, she recovers. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e37970">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>What means my best lov'd Sister?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e38000">
            <speaker>Eur. </speaker>
            <l>— O that Ring! </l>
            <l>It was impossible so black a Crime </l>
            <l>Should be conceal'd for ever. That bright Jewel, </l>
            <l>Worn by the Lustful Villain, glitter'd then </l>
            <l>Through all the shades of Night, and now reveals </l>
            <l>The cursed Ravisher.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e38080">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— O ye just Gods, </l>
            <l>By what amazing ways you make the Guilty </l>
            <l>Meet their just Vengeance!— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e38130">Enter Ferrismond. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e38150">
            <speaker>Fer. </speaker>
            <l>— Rodoric, Royal Sir, </l>
            <l>Has on the Rack accus'd Genselaric </l>
            <l>To be the Actor of this horrid Rape, </l>
            <l>And that himself and Almeric assisted him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e38240">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>Secure that other Villain! How was I </l>
            <l>Mistaken in this Monster! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e38280">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— Speak, foul Ravisher, </l>
            <l>What Devil prompted you to such an Action </l>
            <l>As Fiends would blush to own? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e38330">
            <speaker>Gen. </speaker>
            <l>— 'Twas Love, or Lust, </l>
            <l>Give it which name you will. The mighty Pleasure </l>
            <l>I then receiv'd, will scarce be bought too dear </l>
            <l>By all that I can suffer. Rodoric </l>
            <l>Can tell you more: For me, I vow to keep </l>
            <l>An Everlasting silence.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e38420">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— Force of Torture </l>
            <l>Shall break your wilful silence, and compel you </l>
            <l>To Groan, if not to speak.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e38470">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— My Royal Lord, </l>
            <l>When first I found this Weapon, I vow'd solemnly, </l>
            <l>That my sad Soul should never taste of Quiet, </l>
            <l>Till in the lustful Villain's Blood I drench'd </l>
            <l>The thirsty Blade.— Thus I perform my Vow. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e38540">Stabs Gen. </stage>
            <l>And though the foulness of a Guilt like yours </l>
            <l>Deserves the common Hangman to avenge it; </l>
            <l>Yet since the Royal Blood of Gunderic </l>
            <l>Flows in your Veins, die by a Prince's hand. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e38610">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>Young Man, you are too rash.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e38640">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— Thus low I beg </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e38670">Kneeling. </stage>
            <l>Your Royal Pardon, and submit my self </l>
            <l>To what your justly kindled Rage ordains. </l>
            <l>I hearken'd to my wrongs; and they allow'd me </l>
            <l>No leisure to consult with due respect. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e38720">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>Rise up, brave Prince; I only grieve he met </l>
            <l>A Fate so Noble. Fair Eurione, </l>
            <pb n="55" xml:id="ep000458-032-b"/>
            <l>This Virgin will endeavour to divert you, </l>
            <l>And make you lose your Sorrows.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e38790">
            <speaker>Eur. </speaker>
            <l>— Royal Sir, </l>
            <l>Could my lost state admit of any Comfort, </l>
            <l>I sure, should find it there. But Life has nothing </l>
            <l>That I can relish now. Blest opportunity! </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e38850">Aside. </stage>
            <l>I see the friendly means to end my Sorrow, </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e38870">Sees the Dagger. </stage>
            <l>And make my Fame Immortal; </l>
            <l>But shall I mix my Blood with such a Villain's? </l>
            <l>Stain'd and polluted as it is, 'tis fit </l>
            <l>To mingle with no other. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e38920">Snatches the Dagger, and stabs her self. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e38930">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— Hold, Eurione! </l>
            <l>What has despairing Sorrow forc'd you to? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e38980">
            <speaker>Eur. </speaker>
            <l>To seek the only cure for that distemper </l>
            <l>Which I have labour'd under. Nor had I wav'd </l>
            <l>This Remedy so long, but that I waited </l>
            <l>To see my injur'd Honour first reveng'd. </l>
            <l>What farther use of Life can I propose? </l>
            <l>Since nothing more is to be lost or gain'd; </l>
            <l>My Honour gone, and my Revenge obtain'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e39070">Dies. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e39080">
            <speaker>Rhad. </speaker>
            <l>Alas! my Daughter! </l>
            <l>The Gods must have in store mighty Reserves </l>
            <l>Of Happiness, to make you just amends </l>
            <l>For what you suffer'd here.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e39140">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— O Royal Victim! </l>
            <l>How does the Soul of our Immortal Father </l>
            <l>Look down with Joy upon his dying Offspring, </l>
            <l>And bless his Noble Issue.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e39200">
            <speaker>Amal. </speaker>
            <l>Let not unprofitable Sorrow, Madam, </l>
            <l>Make you insensible of solid Joys; </l>
            <l>Eurione has gain'd a Fame by dying, </l>
            <l>Which the most happy life may envy.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e39270">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>— Madam, </l>
            <l>You mourn a Daughter lost, to fill her room </l>
            <l>Accept this Maid, the only Prop and Comfort </l>
            <l>Of my declining Age; in gaining her </l>
            <l>I lost a Son; but shall be much o'erpaid, </l>
            <l>If this brave Prince will take his empty place, </l>
            <l>And let me call him mine.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e39360">
            <speaker>Rhad. </speaker>
            <l>— What vast returns </l>
            <l>Of Gratitude am I oblig'd to make </l>
            <l>For such a mighty Present?— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e39410">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>— Let me thus </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000458-e39440">Kneeling. </stage>
            <l>Low on my Knees receive the glorious Fortune </l>
            <l>Your Goodness has design'd me. If you, Madam, </l>
            <l>Consent to favour my aspiring hopes </l>
            <l>The Blessing will be infinite. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e39490">
            <pb n="56" xml:id="ep000458-033-a"/>
            <speaker>Elis. </speaker>
            <l>— The King commands, </l>
            <l>And I must ne'er dispute his Royal Will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e39530">
            <speaker>Gund. </speaker>
            <l>Draw near Ambiomer and Elismonda; </l>
            <l>Thus I unite your hands, and may this be </l>
            <l>A Match of Nations, whilst the Goths and Vandals </l>
            <l>Link'd in a firm Alliance look on you </l>
            <l>As on their double Pledge of mutual Friendship. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000458-e39640">
            <speaker>Amb. </speaker>
            <l>All my past Griefs are swallow'd up and lost </l>
            <l>In this vast tide of Joy: and Fate has given </l>
            <l>More than my most aspiring hopes could aim at. </l>
            <l>Come, beauteous Elismonda, let's prepare </l>
            <l>To meet Love's richest Joys: And from our Fate </l>
            <l>The World may learn this Lesson, that the Gods, </l>
            <l>While Human Policy contends in vain, </l>
            <l>Will their own Ends by their own Ways obtain. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000458-e39750">Exeunt omnes. </stage>
        </div>
      </div>
      <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
