<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Landgartha</title>
        <author>
<!--Burnell, Henry-->
          <persName>
            <forename>Henry</forename>
            <surname>Burnell</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <idno type="dracor" xml:base="https://dracor.org/id/">ep000471</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A30315.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull n="TCP source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">Landgartha a tragie-comedy as it was presented in the new theater in Dublin with good applause, being an ancient story / written by H.B.</title>
                <author>H. B. (Henry Burnell), fl. 1641.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>41 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
                <date>2011 April (TCP phase 2)</date>
                <idno type="marc">11276859</idno>
                <idno type="stc">Wing B5751.</idno>
                <idno type="vid">47257</idno>
                <idno type="DLPS">A30315</idno>
                <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2240942592</idno>
                <availability>
                  <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
                </availability>
              </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
            <biblFull n="printed source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">Landgartha a tragie-comedy as it was presented in the new theater in Dublin with good applause, being an ancient story / written by H.B.</title>
                <author>H. B. (Henry Burnell), fl. 1641.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>73 p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Printed at Dublin :</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication_date">1641.</date>
                <date type="creation_date">1641</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>
                  <p>Pages 11-16 repeated.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</p>
                </note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1639">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000471-e100030">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000471-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000471-001-b"/>
        <p>Landgartha. </p>
        <p>A Tragie-Comedy, as it was presented in the new Theater in Dublin, with good applause, being an Ancient story, </p>
        <p>Written by H. B. </p>
        <quote>
          <bibl>HORAT. </bibl>
          <p>Hunc socci cepere pedem, grandesque cothurni. </p>
        </quote>
        <p>Printed at Dublin Anno 1641. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="ep000471-e100110">
        <pb xml:id="ep000471-002-a"/>
        <head>The persons of the Play. </head>
        <list>
          <item>Frollo King of Sweland and conqueror of Norway. </item>
          <item>Hasmond and Gotar, two courtiers to Frollo. </item>
          <item>Landgartha, a Norwegian Lady. </item>
          <item>Scania, sister to Landgartha. </item>
          <item>Elsinora Aunt to both. </item>
          <item>Fatyma, cousin to Land. &amp; Scan. </item>
          <item>Marfisa, an humorous gentlewoman, cousin to Fatyma. </item>
          <item>Fredericke and Wermond, two noble men of Norway. </item>
          <item>Reyner King of Denmarke. </item>
          <item>Valdemar, neer cousin to Reyner. </item>
          <item>Inguar, a Danish noble man. </item>
          <item>Hubba, an humorous merry Danish Captaine. </item>
          <item>Cowsell and Radgee, two foolish Coxcombes. </item>
          <item>Rolfo, a Drawer. </item>
          <item>Harrold, a competitor for Denmarke. </item>
          <item>Eric, his brother. </item>
          <item>Lothaire, a German noble man. </item>
          <item>Vraca, daughter to Frollo. </item>
          <item>Two posts, a Scout, &amp; two Gentl, </item>
          <item>Phoebus, Pallas, Pryam, Hector. </item>
          <item>Achylles, and Satyres, in a maske: which may be Acted by the forenam'd persons. </item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000471-e100340">
        <pb xml:id="ep000471-002-b"/>
        <head>THE EPISTLE Dedicatorie. </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>To all faire, indifferent faire, vertuous, that are not faire and magnanimous Ladies. </salute>
        </opener>
        <p>I Have here plac'd a patterne, yea, more then one (Ladies) for you to imitate Chastity and other vertues joyn'd to beauty, vertue single and manly fortitude in the female Sexe, doe here present themselves unto you. What you cannot reach one way take another: &amp; know that the form &amp; faculties of the minde, doe farre excell in worth those of the body. Yet, both joyn'd (as in Landgartha) is of all the most excellent: in regard that that externall beauty allures (nay commands) the minde of man (that affects visible objects) to the love of vertue, which it selfe do's possesse, and suffers (as most coveted) greater combats in the resisting of vice. Bodily force too in a woman (were it but to defend it's owne Fort) is a perfection; though it cannot be expected but from a few of you, it will be sufficient, that you never fall willingly, but in the way of honour. <pb xml:id="ep000471-003-a"/>If I have not draw'n this faire visage, as a chiefe Arts man: I hope yet (you will say) that I have made it indifferent handsome, and that my good will to effect it after the best fashion for your sakes: will notwithstanding my weaknesse, purchase an excuse at least for my boldnesse, both in undertaking the worke and in offering of it (in part a poore braine borne Infant of mine, that covets to looke at the light) to be cherish'd by such hands as yours, to kneele at the feete of your pietie. Whatsoever it be, or whosoever got it: let it be yours, as is </p>
        <closer>
          <signed>The affectionate honourer of your perfections Henry Burnell. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div cert="high"
              type="encomium"
              xml:id="ep000471-e100400"
              xml:lang="lat">
        <pb xml:id="ep000471-003-b"/>
        <head>Patri suo Charissimo operis Encomium. </head>
        <lg>
          <l>MUltiplici ratione, sator, mea carmina (quamvis </l>
          <l>Non limata) tuis jungo; nempe ipse petisti, </l>
          <l>Cui teneor parere libens; formosa virago </l>
          <l>Huc me vestra movet, virtutis dotibus exors, </l>
          <l>In fraecte potius carnis qua compede solvi </l>
          <l>Certa fuit, foedat a foret quam crimine; cujus </l>
          <l>Iactatis Pyrrhae decus immortale resurgit </l>
          <l>Nobilitus gestis; ad quod praecordia magna </l>
          <l>Laetitia diffufa mihi, quando auribus hausi </l>
          <l>Arrectis (genitor) te (per quem essentia, &amp; à quo </l>
          <l>Impetrata mihi, fruor &amp; quibus, omnia) culte, </l>
          <l>Consulto, graviter, cum suavitate, venuste, </l>
          <l>Praegnantem causam peragisse. Sed indere amoris </l>
          <l>Non probo delicias: quod te fecisse sequntum </l>
          <l>Historia; belle, sciteque jocantem </l>
          <l>Latificando alios, non te, mens certa revolvit. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <head>Aliud. </head>
          <l>Melpomena tua tela (parens) contexta Thalia et, </l>
          <l>judicio quamvis non trutinanda meo est: </l>
          <l>Me tua sed certam solers facundia, verax </l>
          <l>expertorum hominum &amp; fama diurna facit, </l>
          <l>Te nullis potuisse tuis errare, decorum </l>
          <l>omnimodo Scenis, sed tennisse triplex; </l>
          <l>Nempe modum retinendo (docent ut scripta sagacit </l>
          <l>Flacci) personae, temporis, atque loci. </l>
          <l>Ad te à Invernis flexit victoria vatem. </l>
          <l>partibus his cedunt Brutiginaeque tibi. </l>
          <l>Fama quidem tendet, quacunque auratus Apollo </l>
          <l>se tua: tu vives dum vehet amnis aquas. </l>
          <l>Tu pater Aenio deducens vertice musas, </l>
          <l>gloria (non fallor) posteritatis eris. </l>
          <l>Terra tuas certum est exhauriet extera laudes; </l>
          <l>clarescet scriptis insula nostra tuis. </l>
        </lg>
        <closer>
          <signed>Eleonora Burnell. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000471-e100770">
        <pb xml:id="ep000471-004-a"/>
        <head>To his worthy to be much honoured Cousin Henry Burnell Esq. on this his Tragie-Comedy, &amp;c. </head>
        <l>THough my prayse cannot adde ought here: Yet, give </l>
        <l>Me leave (Cousin) to rayse my selfe, and live </l>
        <l>Past time with thee; for, what thou writ'st is fine, </l>
        <l>Pleasant, profound, chaste, morall, and divine; </l>
        <l>Beyond the childish flashes of this age, </l>
        <l>Affected non-sence, and Canarian rage; </l>
        <l>Or Garagantuan foppery. Not one word </l>
        <l>That's immateriall do'st thou affoord, </l>
        <l>Vaine, or superfiuous. Thy phrase is good; </l>
        <l>Nay, strong, and elegant, though understood </l>
        <l>Not by light-headed ignorance that do's admire </l>
        <l>Strange language only. Wave, vote, flames, and fire, </l>
        <l>Tempests and whirlewinds, Scorpions, and Hags, </l>
        <l>Are stuffe that take such, though indeed but rags, </l>
        <l>Base rags that they patch on, and thou do'st scorne; </l>
        <l>Or any dialect that is much worne, </l>
        <l>Though by the best; thy words thou mak'st to fit </l>
        <l>(Not contrary) th' Conceptions of thy wit. </l>
        <l>And, though thou England never saw'st: Yet, this </l>
        <l>(Let others boast of their owne faculties, </l>
        <l>Or being Sonne to Iohnson) I dare say, </l>
        <l>That thou art farre more like to Ben then they </l>
        <l>That lay clayme as heires to him, wrongfully: </l>
        <l>For he survives now only, but in thee </l>
        <l>And his owne lines; the rest degenerate. </l>
        <l>Nay, I can more affirme (and truly) that </l>
        <l>In some things thou do'st passe him: being more sweet, </l>
        <l>More modest, mylde, lesse tedious; Thy owne feer </l>
        <l>Goe thou on stoutly then: if thou proceed, </l>
        <l>Him (though 't be much) in all points thou'lt exceed. </l>
        <closer>
          <signed>Io. Bermingham. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div cert="high"
              type="encomium"
              xml:id="ep000471-e101100"
              xml:lang="lat">
        <pb xml:id="ep000471-004-b"/>
        <head>Ad nobilissimum ingeniosissimum, dissertissimumque suum amicum Dominum Henricum Burnellum operis Elogium. </head>
        <l>VEllera laturus signorum principis, anceps </l>
        <l>Ausonides lecto milite cepit iter: </l>
        <l>Mox longos tentare sinus, votoque potiri, </l>
        <l>Aeolios cives, Ioniumque domans. </l>
        <l>Mascula, casta, decens, suavisque, (Henrice) virago </l>
        <l>Sola tibi invicta pubis ad instar adest. </l>
        <l>Ergo procellosae Niseidis, atque Charibdis </l>
        <l>Securus turbae, carbasa pande Notis. </l>
        <l>Pande palam cedro tua digna volumina, Meci, </l>
        <l>Multorumque prius pensa bilance virûm. </l>
        <l>Pande nihil mancum: nil non laudabile: nil, quod </l>
        <l>Sympathicum non est, symmetriaeque tenor. </l>
        <l>Currum Phoebus equis sic, sic robusta Bootes </l>
        <l>Septem concordi plaustra Trione regit. </l>
        <l>Magnes gnarorum: in rabiem Marpesia cautes, </l>
        <l>Quorum Cerberea toxica fauce sluunt. </l>
        <l>Carmine sublimi morum icon, stilus honesti, </l>
        <l>Calcar virtuti es, criminibusque jugum. </l>
        <l>Per●g Minervali tutus munimine: fiet </l>
        <l>Nobilior studijs gens tua clara tuis. </l>
        <l>Munera, vive, tibi fulvo mage grata metallo, </l>
        <l>Aequora dum biberint proxima signa polo. </l>
        <closer>
          <signed>Philippus Patricius </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="prologue" xml:id="ep000471-e101360">
        <pb xml:id="ep000471-005-a"/>
        <head>Prologue delivered by an Amazon with a Battle-Axe in her hand. </head>
        <l>THe best of English Poets for the Stage </l>
        <l>(Such was the envie, nicenesse, and the rage </l>
        <l>Of pettish weakelings, and detracting fooles, </l>
        <l>That could prayse no man; and, I' th' muddie pooles </l>
        <l>Of their owne vices, were o'rwhelm'd) was faine </l>
        <l>An armed Prologue to produce, on paine </l>
        <l>Of being tongue-strucke Therefore, marvell not </l>
        <l>The present author (having not forgot </l>
        <l>How in 's first Play, he met with too much spite) </l>
        <l>Sho'd send an armed Amazon, t' invite </l>
        <l>(If it be possible) all minds to affect </l>
        <l>What of himselfe, he could not well expect </l>
        <l>From his detractors: Or, to let those know, </l>
        <l>He cares not each of them prove still a foe. </l>
        <l>Yet, this his second (as that first) he made </l>
        <l>To please you, not for Money; to invade </l>
        <l>Your wills for your owne profit. For, if his minde </l>
        <l>He had sought by it to content, you'd finde </l>
        <l>Another method in't; and not a word </l>
        <l>Of any mirth or love wo'd he afford </l>
        <l>To make you laugh or languish. All, rich stuffe </l>
        <l>(Though not so pleasing) he'd expose, to cuffe </l>
        <l>(And generally too) the monster vice; </l>
        <l>Which he performes but gently, in this piece. </l>
        <l>Yet, it's beleev'd 't will please the most and best, </l>
        <l>In all the passages; and for the rest, </l>
        <l>Let 'em (if they will needs) in pudles swim: </l>
        <l>For, he sleights them more, then they can wrong him. </l>
      </div>
      <div type="body_of_play" xml:id="ep000471-e101650">
        <pb xml:id="ep000471-005-b"/>
        <head>Landgartha. </head>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="ep000471-e101660">
          <head>The first Act. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e101670">Enter Fredericke and Wermond. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e101680">
            <speaker>Fred. </speaker>
            <l>IT's a noble, noble act! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-wermond" xml:id="ep000471-e101700">
            <speaker>Wer. </speaker>
            <l>And cannot </l>
            <l>But vex the bloudy usurper, let him put </l>
            <l>Ever so good a face on't, though they were </l>
            <l>But women only, that conspire against him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e101750">
            <speaker>Fred. </speaker>
            <l>It stirs him not: for since his conquest made </l>
            <l>On us, and murdring of our lawfull Prince, </l>
            <l>Things have succeeded so to all his wishes, </l>
            <l>That he's grow'n carelesse: nay blindly besotted </l>
            <l>By security, and selfe-perswasion, </l>
            <l>Lock'd by the tempest of his lust; so as </l>
            <l>He feares no force of man; much lesse weake women, </l>
            <l>As he is pleasd to tearme 'em; he minds nothing </l>
            <l>But whom to kill, or foulely ravish: and </l>
            <l>The conversation of his Bawds, and Spintries. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-wermond" xml:id="ep000471-e101860">
            <speaker>Wer. </speaker>
            <l>Is't possible, he sho'd be so secure, </l>
            <l>And passe away in such a dying slumber? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e101890">
            <speaker>Fred. </speaker>
            <l>He thinkes the gods doe slumber too, or winke </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-006-a"/>
            <l>At what he do's, or rather snore supinely; </l>
            <l>Or that there are no gods, and what's spoke of 'em </l>
            <l>Is but a meere foolish fable; He'll beleeve </l>
            <l>No mans intelligence, not his owne spyes, </l>
            <l>That this fleet of Denmarke, now lanch'd forth, sho'd move </l>
            <l>Against him hither. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-wermond" xml:id="ep000471-e101970">
            <speaker>Wer. </speaker>
            <l>It's not all the power, </l>
            <l>He for the present can command that will </l>
            <l>Resist it, if it doe; joyn'd to the valiant </l>
            <l>Landgartha, with her faire sock'd troope of Ladies: <stage xml:id="ep000471-e102020">Musicke of Recorders. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>But, let's be silent; here the wretch himselfe comes. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e102040">Enter Frollo leading a weeping Lady, Hasmond and Gotar. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e102050">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Come my pretty sweet-heart, dry up those pleasing </l>
            <l>Eyes; this liquor's too precious to be spilt </l>
            <l>In such a cause, for a lost Maydenhead, </l>
            <l>And to a King that will become thy slave for't, </l>
            <l>And for more of that sport: who to please thee </l>
            <l>In that, and whatsoever else thou canst conceive, </l>
            <l>To rayse content to thee, and varri'd to thought, </l>
            <l>Will ransacke Kingdomes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-lady" xml:id="ep000471-e102140">
            <speaker>Lady, </speaker>
            <l>Leave me yet blacke Devill, <stage xml:id="ep000471-e102160">Breakes from him </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Thy words sound farre worse than the voyce of Hell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e102180">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Some kicke the Spyder out at the Court gates; </l>
            <l>An angry scratching Cat. We wold not be </l>
            <l>So vex'd another night with such a foole. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e102220">Exeunt Fred. and Wer. with the Lady. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-gotax" xml:id="ep000471-e102230">
            <speaker>Got. </speaker>
            <l>She'll soone repent Sir, and turne backe, to offer </l>
            <l>Her dainty body to your mylder usage. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hasmond" xml:id="ep000471-e102260">
            <speaker>Hasm. </speaker>
            <l>I rather thinke, she'll to the mad Langartha; </l>
            <l>And there make one among her furious troope </l>
            <l>Of Furies, that will yet endure no horsing, </l>
            <l>Though they manage bravely. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e102310">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>There's a Wench indeed, </l>
            <l>What lucke had I, never to lay my hands </l>
            <l>On her? They say she's very faire and handsome. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hasmond" xml:id="ep000471-e102350">
            <speaker>Hasm. </speaker>
            <l>The clappers of mens tongues proclayme that; and </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-006-b"/>
            <l>Speake strange things of her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e102380">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>We shall finde'em (the best </l>
            <l>Is of it) altogether, to make a royall </l>
            <l>Choyce. We meane to single forty at least, </l>
            <l>Of the most buxome (of which she shall be </l>
            <l>Chiefe generall, as now she is) for our </l>
            <l>Owne private pallat. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hasmond" xml:id="ep000471-e102450">
            <speaker>Hasm. </speaker>
            <l>I may hope (Sir) you'll grant </l>
            <l>Me halfe the number, with her wise and modest </l>
            <l>Aunt Elsinora, to precede: Or her fine </l>
            <l>Valorous sister Scania, for I must </l>
            <l>Imitate your manly vertue, Sir, as neere </l>
            <l>As I can. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e102520">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Marke we'l what I say now: for thy </l>
            <l>Good service as my honest smocke Atturney </l>
            <l>(Though sometime, yet thou did'st begin to us, thou'lt say </l>
            <l>For feare they'd beene diseas'd:) thou shalt not have </l>
            <l>One woman (wert thou e'er so willing) more </l>
            <l>Or lesse than thirty. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hasmond" xml:id="ep000471-e102590">
            <speaker>Hasm. </speaker>
            <l>O Prodigious! <stage xml:id="ep000471-e102610">Ieeringly. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>I doe beseech you, Sir, to heare me speake, </l>
            <l>Like so many Basilisks (with angry shots </l>
            <l>From their sharpe venom'd eyes) they'd strike me dead: </l>
            <l>Or (as the Porcupyne) send fether'd arrowes </l>
            <l>At me, for my slacknesse. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e102670">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>You must have thirty, </l>
            <l>Or none. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hasmond" xml:id="ep000471-e102700">
            <speaker>Hasm. </speaker>
            <l>Nay, If I must, I shall: and that's </l>
            <l>As bad. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-gotax" xml:id="ep000471-e102730">
            <speaker>Got. </speaker>
            <l>You will not (Sir) be altogether <stage xml:id="ep000471-e102750">Solemnely. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Unmindefull of my good endeavours. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e102770">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>By no meanes, good Sir, thou shalt possesse for thy </l>
            <l>Share, twenty five; with the pretty smugge Fatyma, </l>
            <l>To leade'em. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-gotax" xml:id="ep000471-e102810">
            <speaker>Gotar. </speaker>
            <l>I humbly thanke your grace, though I </l>
            <l>Sho'd not covet so many desperate femals: </l>
            <l>Yet, with the assistance of my kindest friends, </l>
            <l>I shall be strongly back'd. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e102860">Enter Wermond. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000471-007-a"/>
          <sp who="A30315-wermond" xml:id="ep000471-e102870">
            <speaker>Wermond. </speaker>
            <l>May it please you, Sir, </l>
            <l>Here are arriv'd two posts at once, all full </l>
            <l>Of sweat and durt; and bring bad newes, it's fear'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e102910">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Curse on thy feares, Goe, send 'em hither to us; <stage xml:id="ep000471-e102930">Exit. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>It's but these women that affright fooles thus. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e102950">Enter first post. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>What newes? be briefe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-gotax" xml:id="ep000471-e102970">
            <speaker>Gotar. </speaker>
            <l>He's full of durt, indeed! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-yyyy_1" xml:id="ep000471-e102990">
            <speaker>1. Post. </speaker>
            <l>Landgartha with a mighty troope of women, </l>
            <l>Gatherd to her from all the parts of Norway, </l>
            <l>Make havocke of your souldiers, sir; and killing </l>
            <l>All the Swedes they light vpon, they likewise threaten, </l>
            <l>They will grant you (ere long) no better quarter. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e103050">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>My Sweds and I will make some, here in Norway, </l>
            <l>Pay dearely for that vant. Come, doe thou croake too <stage xml:id="ep000471-e103080">Enter 2. post. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>The worst tale thou canst. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-yyyy_2" xml:id="ep000471-e103100">
            <speaker>2. Post. </speaker>
            <l>You had neede, Sir, make quicke </l>
            <l>Resistance, or shift for your selfe: for, the King </l>
            <l>Of Denmarke, with a mighty fleete, has now </l>
            <l>Put in at Mastrand; and begins to land </l>
            <l>His forces, to joyne with Landgartha's: who </l>
            <l>With maine speede, marches to meete him thither. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e103170">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Which he shall soone repent, and so shall that </l>
            <l>Male-harted Traytresse, withall the curll'd knot </l>
            <l>Of rebels that attend her; We are not </l>
            <l>So unprovided, as they doe suppose yet, </l>
            <l>Fly therefore Hasmomd, gather thou our troopes </l>
            <l>Within and neere the Citie. Gotar, thou </l>
            <l>Haste to the quarters further of; and with </l>
            <l>All possible speed draw unto us. Away </l>
            <l>When need compels, men must use no delay. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e103270">Exeunt omnes: </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e103280">A march, then enter Landgartha, Scania, Elsinora, Fatyma, and one or two Ladies more, all attyr'd like Amazons, wtih Battle-axes in their hands and Swords on. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e103290">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>We now (sweet Ladies and deare sisters) march not </l>
            <l>Against th'intemperate Frollo: but ascend </l>
            <l>The milkie way, that leads to immortall fame, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-007-b"/>
            <l>Not to be rank'd among the starre-made harlots: </l>
            <l>But stated in the high'st Empyrcall heaven, </l>
            <l>To side the gods, where Pallas and chast Phoebe </l>
            <l>(Arm'd chiefely with the weapons of their vertues) </l>
            <l>Keepe all the Masculin deities in awe. </l>
            <l>This our designe may well exalt us thither, </l>
            <l>As their good deeds did them: that in defence </l>
            <l>Of that all sho'd hold dearest, our honours, Ladies, </l>
            <l>Doe now expose our selves to death, and what </l>
            <l>A cruell, vicious, revengefull Tyrant </l>
            <l>May inflict on us, if vanquish'd. Yet, this act </l>
            <l>Of ours we must not vainely boast of: for, </l>
            <l>The little birds will (with their beaks and wings) </l>
            <l>Offend the ravishers of their young issue. </l>
            <l>What then should we performe thinke you, that farre </l>
            <l>Passe these? yeild up your bodies basely to </l>
            <l>Foule rape and lust, and so to infamie </l>
            <l>For ever? No, no: farre be this from us </l>
            <l>Honour'd virgins, that have such armes to wield </l>
            <l>These cutting weapons, being (too) to fight authoriz'd, </l>
            <l>By the examples of the noblest women, </l>
            <l>Semiramis, Zenobia, faire Cinana </l>
            <l>Sister unto great Macedon, stout Alvilda, </l>
            <l>Cumilla, and the Amazonian Queenes, </l>
            <l>Great Mithridates Queene, and severall others, </l>
            <l>Are patterns now for us to imitate; </l>
            <l>O most brave patterns! Yet this we may say, </l>
            <l>That our chast glories shall passe theirs, as farre </l>
            <l>As th' worth of our intentions doth exceed </l>
            <l>The cause they undertooke: nor ought you doubt it. </l>
            <l>Let then the King of Denmarke fight where he list: </l>
            <l>We will pursue no other than our worst </l>
            <l>And strongest adversary in's owne squadron; </l>
            <l>Where I, as first, will loose my life, or give </l>
            <l>A suddaine end to his blacke purposes, </l>
            <l>That fought a conquest on our chastities. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-elsinora" xml:id="ep000471-e103690">
            <speaker>Elsinor. </speaker>
            <l>Thy vertues and example, Neece: that are not </l>
            <l>To be reach'd by any imitation </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-008-a"/>
            <l>(At least of our endeavours) doe farre more </l>
            <l>Excite our courages, then Hermes could, </l>
            <l>Were he now here, to play the Orator: </l>
            <l>Lead on then; you shall find us no bad seconds. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e103760">
            <speaker>Scania. </speaker>
            <l>I have more than a womans longing to begin. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e103780">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>I know Fatyma, though she be not great, </l>
            <l>Has not the least desire to fight among us. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-fatyma" xml:id="ep000471-e103810">
            <speaker>Fatyma. </speaker>
            <l>Stay till you see me knocke some great ones downe; </l>
            <l>Untill when, I shall well remit your prayses. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e103840">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>Then follow me; and as you see me wooe </l>
            <l>The Swedish King, to his doe you so too. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e103870">Exeunt. A march. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e103880">Enter Reyner, Valdemar, Inguar, Hubba, and one or two or more Souldiers with Axes. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e103890">
            <speaker>Reyner. </speaker>
            <l>It's my chiefe comfort, noble Cymbrians, </l>
            <l>Subjects and friends, to be your guide to day, </l>
            <l>Against a valiant, wicked adversary; </l>
            <l>And for our right, th' inheritance of this kingdome, </l>
            <l>To shew that vertue and the cause, doe more </l>
            <l>Prevayle than any humane fortitude, </l>
            <l>Or setl'd Councels, when they're joyn'd to vice; </l>
            <l>And by injustice seeke to advance their states: </l>
            <l>Which wisely our forefathers mask'd beneath </l>
            <l>The fables of the Titans 'gainst the gods. </l>
            <l>But it sho'd seeme the vertue of our foes </l>
            <l>(Wisedome and valour) has forsooke'em, by </l>
            <l>Their palliardise, by ease, and hourely ryot; </l>
            <l>This kingdome being more fatall unto them, </l>
            <l>Then Capua was to Hannibal: and therefore, </l>
            <l>Not worth your meanest feares: I must not then </l>
            <l>Inlarge my selfe in words too farre, because </l>
            <l>You need 'em not; nor need you be beholding, </l>
            <l>Unto the fames of your brave Ancestors, </l>
            <l>Those valiant Cymbrians, that almost gave </l>
            <l>An end to Rome, the Mistris of the world, </l>
            <l>And not in her declyning dayes, when her </l>
            <l>Owne vices had confounded her; as when </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-008-b"/>
            <l>The Gothes and Vandals (now our enemies) </l>
            <l>Did trample on her, being downe before. </l>
            <l>She liv'd full man, when great King Beleus </l>
            <l>Did (on the borders of rich Jtaly) </l>
            <l>Vanquish three of her bravest Generals, </l>
            <l>Sylanus, Coepio, and Manilius. </l>
            <l>This (if you please) you may consider; and </l>
            <l>That our foes are more famous for their whoredomes, </l>
            <l>Than conquering of Norway. Reflect also </l>
            <l>How for this cause, we are assisted by </l>
            <l>An Angel troope, of chast and noble Ladies: </l>
            <l>Whom neyther losse of life, or other evils </l>
            <l>Can fright, from seeking to revenge the wrongs </l>
            <l>Done to their Sex, their parents, and their friends. </l>
            <l>Then, let's not shame our selves now in their presence, </l>
            <l>Or to posteritie: by being out-gone </l>
            <l>By women in a battle. Lastly, consider </l>
            <l>The everlasting honour due to vertue; </l>
            <l>Of which we now shall make a glorious purchase. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e104320">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>I am affraid you will consider (sir,) </l>
            <l>So long of these women; untill you forget </l>
            <l>What you applaud so feelingly, your vertue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e104360">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Thou'rt alwayes merry, Hubba, honest withall; </l>
            <l>And from my heart I wish, that each man here </l>
            <l>Performe a Souldiers parts, no worse than thou; </l>
            <l>We shall not then be beaten. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e104410">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>Let's march on, sir: </l>
            <l>And you shall quickly find the meanest of 'em, </l>
            <l>Valiant and strong to purchase what's your birth-right. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e104450">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Then let us move; and prosper too, as we </l>
            <l>Affect injustice, or impietie. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e104480">Exeunt. A march </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e104490">Enter Frollo, Hasmond, Gotar, and two or three more with Axes. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-frollo" xml:id="ep000471-e104500">
            <speaker>Frollo. </speaker>
            <l>We must not loose our confidence, brave Warriors, </l>
            <l>Though we be taken somewhat tardy, by </l>
            <l>A sort of raw fresh-water souldiers, weake </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-009-a"/>
            <l>Unmartiall women fitter for night encounters, </l>
            <l>And some poore fugitive Norwegian rebels, </l>
            <l>Conquer'd and beaten oft by us before. </l>
            <l>What then although our numbers be the lesse? </l>
            <l>Yet not by much: the glory of the adventure, </l>
            <l>Would not be worth the paines we under tooke else. </l>
            <l>Besides, if we consider what our Ancestors </l>
            <l>Have (by their never-equall'd vallors) oft </l>
            <l>Perform'd against the noblest nations of </l>
            <l>The world, this our designe is nothing: nothing </l>
            <l>To what they did: What we have done our selves, </l>
            <l>And meane to doe hereafter. Notwithstanding, </l>
            <l>Let me commend unto your memories, </l>
            <l>After a generall fashion (for now </l>
            <l>The time exacts deeds more than words) what some </l>
            <l>Of their large conquests were, not onely in </l>
            <l>Europe, Which was all theirs a most: but in </l>
            <l>Affricke, a third and richest part of th'world; </l>
            <l>Which from the Ocean unto Nyle they won; </l>
            <l>And from the Mid-land Sea, to the torrid Zone. </l>
            <l>Great Rome her selfe (that wisedome boasted most, </l>
            <l>And next her vallor) was by our fathers taken, </l>
            <l>Pillag'd, and burnt foure times at least; and her </l>
            <l>Large Empyre brought to nothing. She master'd all: </l>
            <l>We master'd her; </l>
            <l>And will not now degenerate first of ours. </l>
            <l>What though men say, we are not religious? </l>
            <l>Religion is but a toy, and first invented </l>
            <l>By politicke States, to keepe fooles in awe; </l>
            <l>And of all men observed least by themselves, </l>
            <l>If she but thwart the least of their intendments. </l>
            <l>They glorifie her much for their owne ends; </l>
            <l>And that's even almost all: and so may we. </l>
            <l>Yet, honour by warre, riches, and our pleasure, </l>
            <l>Shall be the Altars, and the gods we'll bow to </l>
            <l>In our free mindes; and what we gaine we'l keepe. </l>
            <l>King Reyner therefore was not wise, in seeking </l>
            <l>To dispossesse the bravest Nation breathing, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-009-b"/>
            <l>Of what they have atchiev'd by the right of conquest; </l>
            <l>And shall (I hope) in snatching at our Crowne, </l>
            <l>By your more pow'rfull armes, soone misse his own. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e104950">Ex. Allarums. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e104960">A good while after the allarums are begun, Enter Frolle and a gentleman. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-frollo" xml:id="ep000471-e104970">
            <speaker>Frol. </speaker>
            <l>Furies and plagues: these wild, wild bloudy whores, </l>
            <l>Fight like so many Tygers: without the least </l>
            <l>Apprehension of feare, or any kind </l>
            <l>Of mercy: the pursie Danes come nothing neere 'em. </l>
            <l>Having cut off our vauntgard, and right wing, </l>
            <l>They presse on our maine battle too; and force </l>
            <l>It to give ground. Goe, fly thou: and charge Hasmond </l>
            <l>To fetch the reare with speed up; that we may <stage xml:id="ep000471-e105060">Exit gentl. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>(There being no other hope for safety left us) </l>
            <l>Upon one desperat onslaught hazard all. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e105090">Enter Scania. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e105100">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>I am glad I've met you, sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frollo" xml:id="ep000471-e105120">
            <speaker>Frol. </speaker>
            <l>A pretty fine peece, <stage xml:id="ep000471-e105140">aside. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>I wo'd faine save this. I sho'd preferre </l>
            <l>Thy beautie, unto ought that's ours; prove kind </l>
            <l>And gentle unto thee, sweet-heart: if thou'lt </l>
            <l>But yeeld— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e105190">
            <speaker>Scania. </speaker>
            <l>To thy imbraces, that must 'a' had </l>
            <l>My sister, me and forty more. We now </l>
            <l>Shall see what you can doe 'gainst one. Come quickly </l>
            <l>Then, vnto your guard sir: or I shall soone send forth </l>
            <l>Your too hot bloud, to coole your lustfull heart. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frollo" xml:id="ep000471-e105250">
            <speaker>Frol. </speaker>
            <l>Plague on you for a company of spitefull, </l>
            <l>Venomous tong'd bitches. Ye had rather lye </l>
            <l>With the worst Hynde of your owne, than the best of us. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e105290">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>Villaine, I'll answer thee another way. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e105310">Offers to fight on which Land. enters. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e105320">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>Hold sister. This must only be my mate: </l>
            <l>Goe, seeke you out another somewhere else? <stage xml:id="ep000471-e105350">Exit Scania. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frollo" xml:id="ep000471-e105360">
            <speaker>Frol. </speaker>
            <l>Art thou Landgartha? or some supernall goddesse, </l>
            <l>Descended in her fairer shape, to make </l>
            <l>A conquest now on Frollo, that must yeeld </l>
            <l>Himselfe thy captive? </l>
          </sp>
          <pb subtype="duplicate" type="blank" xml:id="ep000471-010-a"/>
          <pb subtype="duplicate" type="blank" xml:id="ep000471-010-b"/>
          <pb subtype="duplicate" type="blank" xml:id="ep000471-011-a"/>
          <pb subtype="duplicate" type="blank" xml:id="ep000471-011-b"/>
          <pb subtype="duplicate" type="blank" xml:id="ep000471-012-a"/>
          <pb subtype="duplicate" type="blank" xml:id="ep000471-012-b"/>
          <pb xml:id="ep000471-013-a"/>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e105410">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>Thou once call'dst me subject; </l>
            <l>And I am come to tender my alleageance, </l>
            <l>To your ungracious wickednesse, thus— <stage xml:id="ep000471-e105450">stricks at him. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frollo" xml:id="ep000471-e105460">
            <speaker>Frol. </speaker>
            <l>Hold, for heavens sake hold, and patiently </l>
            <l>But take my faithfull vow. Doe thou withdraw </l>
            <l>Thy troopes from our defeat: and by the Olympian </l>
            <l>Gods, I shall no sooner </l>
            <l>Have strucke King Reyner with his punie Danes, </l>
            <l>But I'll make thee my Queene. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e105530">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>Thy Concubyne. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frollo" xml:id="ep000471-e105550">
            <speaker>Frol. </speaker>
            <l>All miseries light on me then for ever; </l>
            <l>Or if I ever mixe with woman but </l>
            <l>Thy selfe: for thou art worthy of a Mars. </l>
            <l>A Hercules, or Iupiter. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e105600">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>And have </l>
            <l>Fully resolv'd never to kisse any man, </l>
            <l>But him that shall first master me in fight: </l>
            <l>You are best therefore looke well to your selfe, sir; </l>
            <l>Or I shall quickly marry your hearts bloud </l>
            <l>To this weapon. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e105670">They fight &amp; he's hurt. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frollo" xml:id="ep000471-e105680">
            <speaker>Frol. </speaker>
            <l>I bleed you see: let which </l>
            <l>Serve as an offering, to appease thy wrath </l>
            <l>Conceiv'd against a wretch, that now repents <stage xml:id="ep000471-e105720">Here Rey. Vald. Inguar. &amp; Hubb. are discovered. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>(Unfainedly) his former evill life. </l>
            <l>May the gods chiefe attribute then (mercy) </l>
            <l>Find roome for me (a Convertite) in thy </l>
            <l>Noble and vertuous soule: and I shall still </l>
            <l>Become thy pious imitator: be </l>
            <l>Govern'd by thee in all thing, and thy husband, </l>
            <l>By heaven and all, I will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e105800">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>But I hope you shall not: </l>
            <l>For I must try your manhood once againe. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e105830">They fight, and she strikes him downe. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e105840">
            <speaker>Reyn. </speaker>
            <l>O brave mayde! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frollo" xml:id="ep000471-e105860">
            <speaker>Frol. </speaker>
            <l>Faire Furie, thou hast kill'd me, </l>
            <l>Hell take thee for 't my love is now cool'd indeed. </l>
            <l>But I will be reveng'd. I cannot, cannot rise: </l>
            <l>The losse of bloud, and paine, strike faint my pow'rs: </l>
            <l>That I were now on high transform'd Atlas: </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-013-b"/>
            <l>This being no fable, but a truth: that I </l>
            <l>Might cut the axle-tree of heaven in two: </l>
            <l>And tumble downe the gods, and breake their necks, </l>
            <l>Proud gods, if such there be. Then, like Enceladus </l>
            <l>(Loaden with flaming Etna) I sho'd turne, </l>
            <l>And shake out all the starres: The sunne, and with </l>
            <l>That fire, burne all to cinders. Thus I'd turne: </l>
            <l>O divels, I cannot: but doe feele a pitchy </l>
            <l>Cloud (darker than night) hang o'r my drowsie temples: </l>
            <l>And must (there is no remedy) descend, to stalke </l>
            <l>A long th'infernall waves, or wafted over, </l>
            <l>Grapple with the damned Furies, receive my soule </l>
            <l>You beastly Hags, then: that shall torment you more, </l>
            <l>Than you can any. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e106060">Dyes. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e106070">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>The gods are now reveng'd </l>
            <l>On thee, by me, libidinous Woolfe, foule Tyrant. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e106100">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>And rid me (worthy Lady,) of a dangerous </l>
            <l>Adversary. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e106130">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>I doe beseech, sir: <stage xml:id="ep000471-e106150">Kneels on one knee. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>As my duty onely to receive that, </l>
            <l>Vnto them and your grace, though a woman. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e106180">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>This to me (Madame) is too great an honour. </l>
            <l>Pray stand up. I should rather kneele to you, </l>
            <l>Whose beauty and incomparable vertues, </l>
            <l>Exact no slender adoration, </l>
            <l>From all those that love goodnesse; or the image </l>
            <l>Of heaven in your face. We must acknowledge, </l>
            <l>Notwithstanding our right to the crowne of Norway, </l>
            <l>What pow'r soe'r we have in't, gain'd and confirm'd </l>
            <l>Chiefly by you, that are our strongest friend. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e106280">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>Your poore and humble vassall, that desires </l>
            <l>No other recompence for her small service, </l>
            <l>Than your Kingly licence, to remaine </l>
            <l>(When your foes are wholly vanquish'd) from all </l>
            <l>Imployment sever'd: to leade a solitary </l>
            <l>Quiet life, being compell'd (in the defence </l>
            <l>Of what I ever most esteemed) to match </l>
            <l>Thus amongst men; which I did not covet, but </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-014-a"/>
            <l>The contrary. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e106380">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>You will not wrong the world </l>
            <l>(The race of man, sweet Lady,) so to robb it </l>
            <l>Of such lustre: nay of all light, by </l>
            <l>Dedicating of what is onely good in't, </l>
            <l>Your selfe, to solitude. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e106440">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>I must no be </l>
            <l>Compell'd to any state of life, sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e106470">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>You cannot </l>
            <l>Madame, I see that; and (by your force my foes </l>
            <l>Now put to flight) I shall continue alwayes, </l>
            <l>Not onely a meere servant, but for ever </l>
            <l>Your bondman; not to offend you i' th' least thought. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e106530">Enter Scania, Elsinora, &amp; Fat. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e106540">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>Here be other noble friends (sir) to whom you </l>
            <l>Stand bound in no small summes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-elsinora" xml:id="ep000471-e106570">
            <speaker>Elsinor. </speaker>
            <l>Of Princely favour </l>
            <l>Onely. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e106600">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Rise faire Ladies, you shall command </l>
            <l>Vs, being your creature. Hub. they're delicate fine wenches, pretty youths. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e106630">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>You are now, sir </l>
            <l>To consider, how to use your victory. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e106660">
            <speaker>Scania. </speaker>
            <l>For us, we shall hereafter (we doubt not) </l>
            <l>Partake the fruits of your most Royall bounty, </l>
            <l>Which we shall begge more, for the generall </l>
            <l>Good, than our particular interests, sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e106710">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>You shall be the Law-makers, to your selves: </l>
            <l>For those, by whom we raigne, shall be our guides: </l>
            <l>In the meane time, thou Valdemar and Inguar, </l>
            <l>Pursue the flying foe, but most with mercie, </l>
            <l>Not of circumspection; yet, least th' Van </l>
            <l>Turne by some accident, by us not thought on; </l>
            <l>Save all that yeeld, whom we doe meane to send </l>
            <l>Home ransomelesse; to see if that benefit </l>
            <l>May worke a peace betwixt us. If it doe not, </l>
            <l>We shall the next time be the more excus'd, </l>
            <l>In our extending of severitie. </l>
            <l>Come Ladies, we'll to counsell to conclude </l>
            <l>Concerning what we have (by you) subdu'd. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="ep000471-e106850">
          <pb xml:id="ep000471-014-b"/>
          <head>The second Act. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e106860">Enter Valdemar, and Jnguar. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e106870">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>It's a strange humor that has seaz'd upon him; </l>
            <l>whatsoever the cause be. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e106900">
            <speaker>Inguar. </speaker>
            <l>When you are </l>
            <l>Ignorant of it, all others must be so. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e106930">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>He discovers nothing to me save onely </l>
            <l>That he is full (and that he often sayes) </l>
            <l>Of griefe and heavinesse; and sometimes sicke. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e106970">
            <speaker>Ing. </speaker>
            <l>His sicknesse may (in time) prove dangerous, </l>
            <l>If some fit remedy be not apply'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-unassigned" xml:id="ep000471-e107000">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>He'll heare of none; I urg'd his Physitians, </l>
            <l>At which he storm'd, and bad me leave him to </l>
            <l>Himselfe; and since I dare not come in sight. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e107040">
            <speaker>Ingar. </speaker>
            <l>It's a deadly malady, that will admit </l>
            <l>Of no cure We are best put Captaine Hubba, </l>
            <l>Or the wise Cowsell on him: for the wit </l>
            <l>Of the one and th'others folly may remove </l>
            <l>More of that griefe he speaks on, than good counsell. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e107100">Enter Rey. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e107110">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>Here comes the man himselfe, in his usuall </l>
            <l>Meditation: and therefore let's away. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e107140">Exeunt ambo, </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e107150">
            <speaker>Reyn. </speaker>
            <l>She is divinely faire, and in her mind </l>
            <l>The noblest vertues keepe their residence, </l>
            <l>As in their loveli'st habitation, </l>
            <l>Being all in love with her, I thinke, as I am, </l>
            <l>From my sad heart warme teares (teares of affliction) </l>
            <l>The fire of my affection doth send up </l>
            <l>Into my eyes, that thence distill in streames, </l>
            <l>Which yet to me, are torrents of sweet joyes, </l>
            <l>Ioyes, that this is for her, my griefe proceeds </l>
            <l>From a profound feare I shall never gaine her, </l>
            <l>Injoy that unpeer'd modell of perfection. </l>
            <l>There is no way but one to pull the fruit </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-015-a"/>
            <l>Jove would turne Goose, taste: she's so reserv'd </l>
            <l>To the least vicious acts; Wretch, that hope </l>
            <l>Is not (yet) left thee: For, being nobly borne </l>
            <l>(Though she no fit match be for us, in lieu </l>
            <l>Of worldly substance, being in her selfe </l>
            <l>An ample dowry for a richer Prince) </l>
            <l>We sho'd (and gladly) sue to be her husband. </l>
            <l>But a report goes, she will joyne with no man, </l>
            <l>In such an obligation, which (that she </l>
            <l>Will not at all have me) is that which striks </l>
            <l>A blacke despaire into my soule, and will </l>
            <l>(Vnlesse I meete some comfort) quickly kill me; </l>
            <l>Being sicke in body, as in mind already. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e107410">Enter Hub &amp; Cowsell. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e107420">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>See, where he stalks. Doe you but put him out </l>
            <l>Of his sad humor; and thou sha't have— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e107450">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>O Captaine, </l>
            <l>I am afraid, for he looks sowre upon't. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e107480">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>No matter: feare you nothing, but proceed; </l>
            <l>And care not what you say, so you say something; </l>
            <l>It's your fooles fashion, and you now must seeme one. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e107520">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>But hearke, you, Captaine. How sho'd I begin? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e107540">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>Say that you come from the Ladies: so I leave you. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e107560">Exit Hub. &amp; peeps. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e107570">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Sirra, what make you here? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e107590">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>Come from the Ladies. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e107610">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Well sayd, speake that againe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e107630">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>Come from the Ladies. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e107650">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Very good, and what of them? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e107670">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>Come from the Ladies. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e107690">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>What, againe. Pray tell me, what did occasion </l>
            <l>Your so kind friendly visit to the Ladies? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e107720">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>I went thither (being some two myle of) </l>
            <l>To be joviall with a new acquaintance </l>
            <l>Of mine, my brother Radger. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e107760">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Some such wise man, </l>
            <l>As thou art. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e107790">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>He's a very honest man. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e107810">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>And takes his cup soundly, I warrant. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e107830">
            <speaker>Cowsell. </speaker>
            <l>So </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-015-b"/>
            <l>Doe many honest men beside him; and </l>
            <l>Keepe wenches too, that's more. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e107870">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>And yet are honest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e107890">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>'s honest and faire-condition'd gentlemen, </l>
            <l>As live, I know severall of 'em, my selfe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e107920">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>The Ladies are well. How did they use thee? tell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e107940">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>They're all exceeding well: and us'd me kindly </l>
            <l>For your sake; gave me a banquet, strawberries </l>
            <l>And creame; we drunke helter-skelter too; the Ladies </l>
            <l>Tooke your health themselves, and ask'd me how you did; </l>
            <l>Landgartha say'd, you were a good man, and that </l>
            <l>She lov'd you with all her heart. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e108010">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Let me imbrace <stage xml:id="ep000471-e108030">Jmbraces him. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Thee from my heart for that good newes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e108050">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>Sweet King, </l>
            <l>Have I found your malady? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e108080">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>O kind Prince! <stage xml:id="ep000471-e108100">Aside. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e108110">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>What sayest? are they not delicate fine creatures? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e108130">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>Indifferent handsome, passable, and so forth— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e108150">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>You'll with a knocke be sent forth, I see that. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e108170">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>I was not from thy want of wit, to expect </l>
            <l>Any true censure. But yet, tell me truely: </l>
            <l>Which of 'em all dost thou thinke is the fairest? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e108210">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>The Lady Elsinora in my opinion, </l>
            <l>Is th' rich Pearle amongst 'em; Landgartha to her </l>
            <l>Is but a meere milkemayde. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e108250">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>He makes me sicke, </l>
            <l>A dunce to wrong the worlds chiefe ornament. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e108280">Kicks, &amp; beats him. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e108290">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>Oh, oh my bum! my bum! <stage xml:id="ep000471-e108310">Exit, and enter Hubba. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e108320">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>I perceive I must </l>
            <l>Venture a beating too. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e108350">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Thou mett'st a foole </l>
            <l>Going out that way. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e108380">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>And he complaines of something </l>
            <l>Vnder favour. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e108410">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>We gave some cause for 't, but </l>
            <l>Doe now repent it. Prethee Hubba call him; </l>
            <l>He sayd some at of the Ladies. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000471-016-a"/>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e108450">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>I can tell </l>
            <l>You more of 'em than he: for, I was lately too </l>
            <l>Where they (like a companie of fine ducklings) </l>
            <l>Wag together. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e108500">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Thy words are base. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e108520">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>What wo'd </l>
            <l>You have me say? they are all very valiant; </l>
            <l>And made King Frollo pay for seeking (and </l>
            <l>But in's good will) to domineere a little </l>
            <l>Over 'em; he lost his life and kingdomes by 't. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e108580">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>We therefore ought the better to love them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e108600">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>As your subjects onely, sir, but not to cast </l>
            <l>Vnder you on a bed, couch, or cleane mat; </l>
            <l>You know what fine Furies they are, if you vex 'em. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e108640">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>We are not so unwise, as to consult </l>
            <l>Of their dishonour. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e108670">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>Nor so farre (I hope) </l>
            <l>Mistaken to marry any of 'em. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e108700">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Why Hubba? are they not faire and vertuous, </l>
            <l>Think'st thou? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e108730">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>I doe admire, sir you sho'd talke </l>
            <l>So much of vertue: a thing th'arrantest Asse </l>
            <l>Will scorne, if Money be not joyn'd to it; </l>
            <l>And then (although he hate it, and the possessor </l>
            <l>Of it) he will prayse 't. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e108790">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Thou'rt now in thy old humors. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e108810">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>Besides, you thinke Landgartha faire: but I say, </l>
            <l>Th' Emperors daughter's worth a thousand of her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e108840">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>I 'de loathly beat thee Hubba: yet, I tell thee; </l>
            <l>Were Charlemaine (the Emperors father) now </l>
            <l>Alive, and in his Pryme of youth and glory, </l>
            <l>Landgartha (being his Paralell in vallor; </l>
            <l>By vertue much more) were a wise enough good </l>
            <l>For him; were she not neere so faire as she is. </l>
            <l>But all, all being joyn'd Hubba; I suppose </l>
            <l>He wo'd esteeme her his chiefe eat thy blessing. </l>
            <l>I, I, and more, a Paradise on earth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e108940">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>Were she ten times better: you cannot have her. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000471-016-b"/>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e108960">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Thou shoot'st a suddaine feare (colder then death) </l>
            <l>Into me; You were best give no bad reason, </l>
            <l>For what you say. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e109000">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>She has vow'd Chastity, </l>
            <l>Unto the gods: which bond though you sho'd be </l>
            <l>Content to forfeyt, it is sure she will not. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e109040">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>The strongest poyson could not sincke me deader, </l>
            <l>Then thy sad tongue has. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e109070">Exit. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e109080">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>Flunge away in a rage: </l>
            <l>Well; I was to blame to tell him, what I was not </l>
            <l>Sure on: For now I truely doe conceive </l>
            <l>There is no plaster but one, that can cure him; </l>
            <l>And that the faire Landgartha must apply too; </l>
            <l>No garden hearbs will doe it, any one </l>
            <l>That has as much braine as a Wood-cocke, may now </l>
            <l>Finde that, that knowes what his disease is. He's worse </l>
            <l>Then horne-mad already; I 'll therefore after him, </l>
            <l>And what betwixt lyes and true tales, I shall goe very neere </l>
            <l>To fetch him to himselfe, and hope againe. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e109200">Exit. </stage>
            </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000471-e109210">Enter Inguar in the middle. </stage>
            <l>The King stretch'd on his Couch, strangely distemper'd, </l>
            <l>And most unlike himselfe (his courage lost) </l>
            <l>He pules and whynes most pitifully: Good heaven, </l>
            <l>What strange disease sho'd render so devicted </l>
            <l>Such a man? So valiant? So each way noble? </l>
            <l>We see no outward cause, that sho'd distract him; </l>
            <l>Sho'd it be love? <stage xml:id="ep000471-e109290">Enter Vald. to Inguar. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e109300">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>Lord Inguar, I have newes </l>
            <l>For you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e109330">
            <speaker>Ing. </speaker>
            <l>I long to heare'em: For your count'nance </l>
            <l>(Showing alacrity) speaks comfort to the King. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e109360">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>Did you never heare of a little blind </l>
            <l>Boy, that wounded many a proper man? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e109390">
            <speaker>Ing. </speaker>
            <l>Has Cupid shot his Highnesse? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e109410">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>No mortall man, </l>
            <l>Nor god so deepe, 't will be proclaym'd in open </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-017-a"/>
            <l>Market shortly. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e109450">
            <speaker>Inguar. </speaker>
            <l>Who should the object be? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e109470">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>Who but Volsca de gente Camilla? </l>
            <l>Th'fairest and best of women, brave, Landgartha </l>
            <l>Hubba is sent (on paine of his best joynt) </l>
            <l>To fetch her hither: from whence ere she part, </l>
            <l>Her duty and th'Kings gracious affection </l>
            <l>Consider'd, she may be glad to yeeld to his </l>
            <l>Commands; as I hope her sister will, to my </l>
            <l>Intreaties to serve her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e109560">
            <speaker>Inguar. </speaker>
            <l>I beleeve, you 'ill finde </l>
            <l>Your selfe mistaken in those vertuous Ladies. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000471-e109590">Enter the foure Ladies in womans apparell with Swords on, and Hubba. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e109600">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>The gods defend so good, and mercifull </l>
            <l>A Prince; I know it's but a cold that troubles </l>
            <l>His grace. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e109640">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>Not so (Madame) I can assure you; </l>
            <l>His disease proceeds rather of heate. He burnes </l>
            <l>Extreamely; and its thought by some, that his </l>
            <l>Physitians cannot cure him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e109690">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>I hope </l>
            <l>They are deceiv'd that thinke so. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e109720">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>Welcome to Court, </l>
            <l>Faire Ladies, Which, till now (that you lighten it </l>
            <l>With the divine splendor of your beauties) </l>
            <l>Was darker than a dungeon: and but a Hell </l>
            <l>Compar'd unto the Paradise of the Campe, </l>
            <l>Where in the fruition of your pleasing'st </l>
            <l>Conversations, being rapt beyond our selves </l>
            <l>With hope of future favours, we in you </l>
            <l>Plac'd the whole summe of our felicities. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e109820">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>You are merrily dispos'd it seemes, sir, </l>
            <l>Which (to be plaine) becomes you but most foulely, </l>
            <l>The King being sicke, when all (and chiefly you) </l>
            <l>Sho'd (and not for ceremony onely) put </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-017-b"/>
            <l>A darke face of sorrow on; and contayne </l>
            <l>Their slippery tongues, from talking over-idlely; </l>
            <l>Some may conceive your mirth proceeds, from being </l>
            <l>Next heire to him in bloud. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e109910">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>It rather springs </l>
            <l>(Sweet Lady) from your comming now to cure him </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e109940">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>Which, with a joyfull heart, I sho'd performe </l>
            <l>If I knew how: Pray you therefore, kind sir, </l>
            <l>Be somewhat cleerer in what you conceive. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e109980">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>'tis quickly learnt; nature will teach you Madame, </l>
            <l>His grace will shew you too; you will not prove <stage xml:id="ep000471-e110010">Ieeringly. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Perverse. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e110030">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>Are you so blinde a Goate, to forget <stage xml:id="ep000471-e110050">Gives him a box, on which all draw, and Scania steps in. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Frollo so soone? to open your eyes take that. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e110070">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>Pray sister hold. What doe you meane to quarell </l>
            <l>On a surmise? I know the Lord Valdemars </l>
            <l>Intents are noble, and much more the Kings. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-elsinora" xml:id="ep000471-e110110">
            <speaker>Elsin. </speaker>
            <l>Y'are to blame, Neece, to be so suddaine in such </l>
            <l>A fond conceit. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e110140">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>Doe we come to be abus'd? </l>
            <l>I'll backe agen. For your part sir, you shall <stage xml:id="ep000471-e110170">Exit, and the other three follow her. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Not fayle to meete me, when and where you list. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e110190">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>His grace will now run mad indeed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e110210">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>Lord Inguar, </l>
            <l>As you love me, follow that severe Lady; </l>
            <l>And reduce her (if ever you did ought for </l>
            <l>A friend) to mildnesse, and this way backe; or I </l>
            <l>Am lost for ever to the King and people: <stage xml:id="ep000471-e110270">Exit Inguar </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Captaine, goe thou too once more, for my sake. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e110290">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>And as you meane to doe, forsweare my selfe </l>
            <l>That you meant no hurt. I have already told her </l>
            <l>A hundred lyes at least; and am now o' th' faith, </l>
            <l>That double the number will scarce serve to quiet her; </l>
            <l>It's such another untoward piece of flesh <stage xml:id="ep000471-e110350">Exit Hub. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e110360">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>She is an excellent Mistris, and has taught <stage xml:id="ep000471-e110380">Ieeringly. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Me such a Lesson, I have cause to thanke her: </l>
            <l>For she has given me patience, and wisedome; </l>
            <l>Honesty too I thinke. The flat truth is </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-018-a"/>
            <l>She has wrought strangely with me, very strangely, </l>
            <l>The ravishing notes of a Cycilian Cyren, </l>
            <l>Could not so have taken my Eare (and from thence </l>
            <l>My heart) with a most alluring kinde of </l>
            <l>Delight, as the smart-touch of her white hand has: </l>
            <l>It strucke into me such a love, </l>
            <l>To her sister I meane, that came so kindly </l>
            <l>Betwixt us, as I doe now account my selfe, </l>
            <l>A gainer by the blow; in hope to gaine </l>
            <l>What I now love so much, and nobly too. </l>
            <l>Well, they will come backe this way againe, I know; </l>
            <l>And I must sing a very dolefull ditty, </l>
            <l>A Palinode; or pray, where they may see me, </l>
            <l>Being a thing I 've onely done but twice </l>
            <l>These seven yeares: once, that I went to sea: </l>
            <l>Secondly and lastly, before the last battle. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e110580">Exit. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e110590">Reyner is discover'd on a Couch, and a gentleman with him. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e110600">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Are th' Ladies come yet to Court? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-gentleman" xml:id="ep000471-e110620">
            <speaker>Gent. </speaker>
            <l>They are sir, </l>
            <l>And will soone be here. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e110650">Enter Inguar &amp; Hubb. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e110660">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Whos's that? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-gentleman" xml:id="ep000471-e110680">
            <speaker>Gent. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord Inguar. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e110700">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Where have you left the Ladies? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e110720">
            <speaker>Ing. </speaker>
            <l>Comming after (Sir,) </l>
            <l>Sad and much troubl'd for your want of health. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e110750">Enter the 4. Ladies. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e110760">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>You'll be extreamely hated, if you use </l>
            <l>So much exception, on so little cause. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e110790">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>If he accost me any more, with his </l>
            <l>Base jeering countenance, and whorish language; </l>
            <l>My sword shall (for such kindnesse) kisse his middrisse. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-fatyma" xml:id="ep000471-e110830">
            <speaker>Fat. </speaker>
            <l>Pray pacifie your minde, you need not stand </l>
            <l>At so much distance. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e110860">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Are not they come yet? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e110880">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>They now are here, by much adoe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e110900">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Good Inguar, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-018-b"/>
            <l>Intreat 'em to approach. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e110930">
            <speaker>Inguar. </speaker>
            <l>Madame, the King </l>
            <l>Desires you wo'd be pleas'd to draw neerer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e110960">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>You honour me, sweet Ladies, in this visit: </l>
            <l>Which, beyond expression adds comfort </l>
            <l>Vnto a wretched sickely man. Chayres there, </l>
            <l>Pray you sit downe; y'are all exceeding welcome. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e111010">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>Our duty charg'd us (sir,) to obey your summons: </l>
            <l>Yet, our affection to your grace's welfare, </l>
            <l>And to that depends of it (the generall good </l>
            <l>Of the republicke) were the chiefe motives </l>
            <l>To our journey. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e111070">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>And being able (sir,) to stead you </l>
            <l>In loving wishes onely, we must expect </l>
            <l>(With griefe to see his weaknesse, whose good health </l>
            <l>We most desire) your highnesse royall pleasure. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e111120">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Thankes worthy Ladies. We must also pay </l>
            <l>You in good wishes; being otherwise </l>
            <l>Too indigent to cancell what we are </l>
            <l>Ingag'd to you for many wayes. </l>
            <l>We have beene still opprest since your departure </l>
            <l>From us (whose vertuous presence, was all </l>
            <l>The comfort we had) with a heavy sadnesse, </l>
            <l>Nourish'd by griefe; nor doe we ever hope </l>
            <l>To see the Sunne againe, but at a window. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e111220">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>The gods defend you (sir,) from giving way </l>
            <l>To such despayre. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e111250">Enter Vald. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e111260">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>I follow after (like </l>
            <l>A Theefe) aloofe, to see what good successe </l>
            <l>The King has in his love suite; and to venter </l>
            <l>For my particular, as he makes his voyage. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e111310">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>Your Majestie must never entertayne </l>
            <l>Darke melancholy thoughts, but quite cashire 'em. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e111340">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>Her voyce sounds sweeter, then the celestiall spheres, </l>
            <l>In their harmonious motion. I am more </l>
            <l>Then ravish'd when I heare it; and thinke I shall </l>
            <l>Fall sicke too, or runne franticke, ere 't belong. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-fatyma" xml:id="ep000471-e111390">
            <speaker>Fat. </speaker>
            <l>I heard no meane Physitian often say, Sir, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-019-a"/>
            <l>That Musicke and mirth were good for sickely men. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e111420">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Bid the Boy sing the Song we made of Love. </l>
          </sp>
          <lg type="song">
            <head>Song. </head>
            <l>Love's farre more pow'rfull than a King, </l>
            <l>And wiser then most Statesmen are: </l>
            <l>For it commands him, and doth spring </l>
            <l>In them strange thoughts; in both much care </l>
            <l>(Beside th'affaires o' th' Common-wealth) </l>
            <l>To crouch and to obey. Nay more; </l>
            <l>It makes 'em loose all joy and health, </l>
            <l>And not be the men they were before; </l>
            <l>Vntill wise love, all pow'rfull love, </l>
            <l>The gracious Physitian prove. </l>
          </lg>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e111550">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>This is a very loving song, </l>
            <l>Your grace made: but the contents of it, not </l>
            <l>To be apply'd to you sir, that may command </l>
            <l>(If pow'r and person can compell) the best </l>
            <l>And fairest Lady i' th'world to be yours, </l>
            <l>In a noble way; and otherwise your vertue forbids it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e111620">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>It does indeed forbid us what is vicious. </l>
            <l>And seeing we doe not hope for life, we must </l>
            <l>Crave your kinde pardon now, to heare us tell </l>
            <l>Th'occasion of our sicknesse, briefly thus: </l>
            <l>You are the onely cause on't. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e111680">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>How? I my liege? </l>
            <l>My knowledge sayes not so. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e111710">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Your beautie, vallor, </l>
            <l>And all the perfections (parted to others, </l>
            <l>But) in you conjoyn'd, protest it: and I </l>
            <l>For one can sweare it. But, being repell'd </l>
            <l>By a severely-awing rigor from your brow </l>
            <l>(Yet sweet withall, though killing) and being told </l>
            <l>Of a sad purpose y' have, never to marry; </l>
            <l>We now are fall'n thus low, beneath the Center </l>
            <l>Of deepe despaire and sorrow: and desire, </l>
            <l>You will say something, eyther to hasten our death, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-019-b"/>
            <l>Or to recall it by a loving sentence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e111830">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>I must take sometime then to deliberate </l>
            <l>Aside. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e111860">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Being yours, in that you may command us. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e111880">She goes aside &amp; the Ladies with her. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e111890">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>We expected no such entertaynment. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-elsinora" xml:id="ep000471-e111910">
            <speaker>Elsin. </speaker>
            <l>My minde foretold me still of some disaster. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e111930">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>Notwithstanding your resolution, </l>
            <l>Not to marry: you have not vow'd against </l>
            <l>Obedience to a man, in that friendly </l>
            <l>Yoake of Wedlocke. The Kings sound affection </l>
            <l>Is not then to be rejected, if you ever </l>
            <l>Take any. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e112000">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>If I doe, he shall be the man. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-fatyma" xml:id="ep000471-e112020">
            <speaker>Fatyma. </speaker>
            <l>You must not study now long for some answer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-elsinora" xml:id="ep000471-e112040">
            <speaker>Elsin. </speaker>
            <l>He's desperatly ill: and if you sho'd </l>
            <l>Give him a flat deniall, we might be </l>
            <l>All seazed on heere at Court, and some villanie </l>
            <l>Committed on us; being to defend our selves, </l>
            <l>Too few by many. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e112100">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>They shall take our lives, </l>
            <l>Ere we'll endure to be defil'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-fatyma" xml:id="ep000471-e112130">
            <speaker>Fatyma. </speaker>
            <l>And with </l>
            <l>The losse of some of theirs. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e112160">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Have you consider'd </l>
            <l>Yet, of the doome y'are to pronounce? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-elsinora" xml:id="ep000471-e112190">
            <speaker>Elsinora. </speaker>
            <l>All stand </l>
            <l>Warily on their guard. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e112220">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>Your poore subjects (sir) </l>
            <l>Must rather expect (in duty) your commands. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e112250">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Nay sweet Lady. Doe not increase my torment, </l>
            <l>By adding affliction to misery, </l>
            <l>With a complement: but something say, that </l>
            <l>May appertaine to th' matter, to rid me </l>
            <l>Quickely of my paine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e112310">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>It's sure; I have not </l>
            <l>(Although I ever meant it) bound my selfe, </l>
            <l>Unto a single life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e112350">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Then dearest Lady, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-020-a"/>
            <l>Consider who I am; and what I now am, </l>
            <l>Lodg'd thus: for though I clayme you not as by desert, </l>
            <l>Or dutie: Yet, being your Prince, you owe me </l>
            <l>Some regard; and all, I e'r must glory in, </l>
            <l>Shall be to make you Queene of what is ours. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e112420">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>May it please you, Sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e112440">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Pray you sit and speake; </l>
            <l>Or I must rise, if weakenesse will permit. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e112470">She sits, and the rest stand. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e112480">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>Had I beene ambitious, when you were not </l>
            <l>Crown'd King of Norway: I could then perchance </l>
            <l>Have written Queene, unto your prejudice. </l>
            <l>But, for that Frollo once intended foulely, </l>
            <l>I (that could not affect vice) did refuse </l>
            <l>What he with earnestnesse, and many Oathes </l>
            <l>Sought to confirme; and was his bane at last, </l>
            <l>Though I beleev'd that what he said, he meant. </l>
            <l>Now therefore (Sir,) your affection (grounded </l>
            <l>In way of honour, without taint of basenesse; </l>
            <l>With such exterior signes too, of deepe love </l>
            <l>To me, unworthy of so great a Prince:) </l>
            <l>I cannot (nor will my heart permit it) but </l>
            <l>In way of gratefulnesse, reciprocally </l>
            <l>Requite with love againe, as dutie binds; </l>
            <l>Nay, more then so. But yet, gracious Sir, </l>
            <l>I (that am meane and poore to be your Consort; </l>
            <l>And that things of this kinde are oft repented) </l>
            <l>Doe now beseech you, to decline a while </l>
            <l>The vehemencie of your fleete desires; </l>
            <l>And take full time to thinke on what you doe: </l>
            <l>Were 't but to take a neerer view of me, </l>
            <l>And that in all points. For know sir, the honour </l>
            <l>You now affoord me, compar'd to th'infamie </l>
            <l>That would redound to both of us, and to others </l>
            <l>(By whom you are to be advis'd) if ought </l>
            <l>Sho'd chance amisse, when things were consumate, </l>
            <l>Is nothing: would but heighten your disgrace. </l>
            <l>Your wise demurre too, I shall take as full payment </l>
            <l>For all my services; and rest devoted </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-020-b"/>
            <l>More deepely yours: and evermore continue </l>
            <l>Your loyall subject onely, sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e112810">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>I was sure </l>
            <l>(Noblest and best of Ladies:) That your words </l>
            <l>(Being such as now they are) could not but worke </l>
            <l>A cure upon me. See, I can stand up: </l>
            <l>Nay, goe; I 'll throw my Cap off too. Some of you </l>
            <l>Give me a Hat; I will walke with you forth </l>
            <l>Into the Gallery, and tell you there, </l>
            <l>I have consider'd so much what you are, </l>
            <l>Though not to your full value this being </l>
            <l>Impossible: that if you thinke me not </l>
            <l>Unworthy (as indeed I am for you) </l>
            <l>We shall soone be Man and Wife. To morrow </l>
            <l>I 'll wayte on you further, into the Garden. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e112950">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>And there (in one of the little bawdy houses) <stage xml:id="ep000471-e112970">Aside. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Seale the Covenant, if it be receiv'd, </l>
            <l>Though he were sure to die in an houre after. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-elsinora" xml:id="ep000471-e113000">
            <speaker>Elsin. </speaker>
            <l>I see she does affect him in good earnest. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e113020">Aside. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>But wisedome bids be silent; This poore kingdome </l>
            <l>Being already torne too much, by tyrannie and troubles. </l>
            <l>Things past our helpe, with patience must be borne, </l>
            <l>Untill a fit time. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e113070">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Lady Elsinora, </l>
            <l>Me thinkes you doe not signe our loving motion, </l>
            <l>With a friendly countenance. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-elsinora" xml:id="ep000471-e113110">
            <speaker>Elsin. </speaker>
            <l>I hope, great Sir, </l>
            <l>You will be pleased to entertayne farre better thoughts </l>
            <l>Of your humblest hand-mayd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e113150">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>I hope we shall. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e113170">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>In licensing our departure, for some small time </l>
            <l>(Dayes five or sixe, and for a private Cause:) </l>
            <l>You will for ever bind us (sir) to your commands; </l>
            <l>And to returne with all convenient speed, </l>
            <l>To obey your Highnesse pleasure in all points. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e113230">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>That ask'd agen, would throw me on my Couch; </l>
            <l>Never to rise. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e113260">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>Madame, I sho'd make bold </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-021-a"/>
            <l>To stop your journey, though the King were pleas'd </l>
            <l>To grant his licence: for you (I must say </l>
            <l>Somewhat roughly) saluted my left eare </l>
            <l>With your right hand, as these can witnesse for me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e113320">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>For which, you are resolv'd to challenge me: </l>
            <l>But not to be your wife; I gave you no </l>
            <l>Such promise. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e113360">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>I must have satisfaction. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e113380">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>You may declare what that is, when you list. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e113400">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>Nay, you shall know it now; and thus it sounds: </l>
            <l>That you perswade this Lady, to become <stage xml:id="ep000471-e113430">Takes Scan. by the hand. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>My second. For, love has strucke me too, so sore </l>
            <l>A cuffe (caus'd by her beautie, and what else </l>
            <l>Is good in her, in my opinion </l>
            <l>Superlatively:) that I shall ne'r be rid </l>
            <l>O' th' paine on't; unlesse you that are like to be </l>
            <l>My Cossen, advance me higher, to the honour </l>
            <l>To be your brother. We shall then be kind friends. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e113510">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>She is not my warde; and may take whom she fancies; </l>
            <l>I may my selfe repent, to be perswaded. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e113540">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Speake Ladie, doe you like the man? He is </l>
            <l>As good a Gentleman as We are: Say, </l>
            <l>Will you have him? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e113580">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>You make me blush (sir,) to aske </l>
            <l>Me such a question. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e113610">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>Nay then, it's granted. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e113630">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>I will not grant at first; nor shall you say </l>
            <l>Hereafter I deceiv'd you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-fatyma" xml:id="ep000471-e113660">
            <speaker>Fat. </speaker>
            <l>You deceive </l>
            <l>Your selfe. Well Madame, I perceive we two <stage xml:id="ep000471-e113690">To Elsin. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Must matelesse home to prove the Vestals. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e113710">
            <speaker>Ing. </speaker>
            <l>Not, sweet Lady, if you'll daigne to grace me, with </l>
            <l>The title husband. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-fatyma" xml:id="ep000471-e113740">
            <speaker>Fat. </speaker>
            <l>For your good will, sir, </l>
            <l>I thanke you: but will heare of no more coupling. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e113770">
            <speaker>Ing. </speaker>
            <l>I yet must love you still. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e113790">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Then let's from hence, </l>
            <l>To entertayne heavens happy influence. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e113820">Exeunt. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="ep000471-e113830">
          <pb xml:id="ep000471-021-b"/>
          <head>The third Act. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e113840">Enter Fredericke and a Servant at the dore. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e113850">
            <speaker>Fred. </speaker>
            <l>Let 'em not presse so fast in, to behold </l>
            <l>A semi-maske; for now 't can be no more, </l>
            <l>For want of fitting Actors here at Court; </l>
            <l>The Warre and want of Money, is the cause on't. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-servant" xml:id="ep000471-e113900">
            <speaker>Serv. </speaker>
            <l>Stand further off, my masters, or I shall— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e113920">
            <speaker>Fred. </speaker>
            <l>Let fly amongst 'em. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e113940">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>Pray you my Lord, have a care <stage xml:id="ep000471-e113960">Enter Vald. and Lady. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>(For my sake) of this Lady; a kins-woman </l>
            <l>Of my wives. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e113990">
            <speaker>Fred. </speaker>
            <l>(I know you are Vxorious.) </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e114010">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>He shall not need: for I will have a care </l>
            <l>Of my selfe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e114040">
            <speaker>Fred. </speaker>
            <l>I sho'd gladly serve your Highnesse: </l>
            <l>But can hardly yet from hence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e114070">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>Come Cousin, </l>
            <l>I will be your Gentleman usher my selfe. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e114100">Exeunt ambo. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Cowsell within, make roome I say there, for me and my brother. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e114120">
            <speaker>Fred. </speaker>
            <l>What kinde Cossens are those? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-servant" xml:id="ep000471-e114140">
            <speaker>Serv. </speaker>
            <l>A payre of Coxcombes, </l>
            <l>So individuall by the littlenesse </l>
            <l>Of their understandings, they cannot be parted. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e114180">Enter Cow. &amp; Rad. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e114190">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>Come away brother Radgar, we'd need make haste, </l>
            <l>To take our places. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e114220">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>I shall be proud brother, </l>
            <l>To be seated after you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e114250">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>And I fortunate </l>
            <l>To sit next before you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e114280">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>It shall be my ambition brother, to </l>
            <l>Be still (as now) your most humble servant, </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000471-022-a"/>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e114310">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>It must be all my study then, brother; To </l>
            <l>Command things onely pleasing: for marke you </l>
            <l>Deere brother. I must strive chiefly to precede, </l>
            <l>But— in my affection. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e114360">
            <speaker>Fred. </speaker>
            <l>A pretty Antimasque: </l>
            <l>I will sit downe, and heare what it concludes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e114390">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>But hearke you now, brother. Shall we have any </l>
            <l>Drinke, Banquets, or so— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e114420">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>Not a drop betwixt meales, brother, </l>
            <l>That's but a simple Countrey fashion. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e114450">
            <speaker>Fred. </speaker>
            <l>Are they already fall'n from complement? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e114470">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>Yet, me thinkes brother, 't were n't amisse to lay </l>
            <l>The pots hard by; and let him drinke that wo'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e114500">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>I sho'd a part keepe with you, in that Catch </l>
            <l>brother, but now (with griefe enough) I say 't </l>
            <l>(Wo'd I co'd not say 't:) I cannot now (being puff'd </l>
            <l>Vp here for want of ayre) drinke nere as much, </l>
            <l>As when I liv'd abroad i' th' Countrie; nor eate </l>
            <l>The quarter quantitie. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e114570">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>That must be beleev'd </l>
            <l>Generally, as a Maxime infallible: </l>
            <l>For to day brother, the stinke of your perfum'd </l>
            <l>And stuffing meates, tooke my stomacke quite away </l>
            <l>From me. Yet, we drunke pretty well you know. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e114630">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>It's certaine (brother,) those that cannot eate, </l>
            <l>Must drinke, and I can drinke indifferent well still </l>
            <l>But, time there was I could 'a' payde it soundly. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e114670">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>As, how much? Pray sweet brother. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e114690">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>It is scarce </l>
            <l>Credible, I now shall tell you: at one short </l>
            <l>Sitting, I'd a drunke you of Wine sixe Flaggons, </l>
            <l>And two dozen of Beere at least, all at eight draughts; </l>
            <l>And never 'a' seene the colour of my face, </l>
            <l>In a Chamber pot; or sought ease, by visiting </l>
            <l>My kind friend Aiax. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e114770">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>That's more by a little, </l>
            <l>Then I ever could vent the right way. But yet, </l>
            <l>I dare speake it brother, we are very neere </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-022-b"/>
            <l>As good drinkers, as you be here i' th' Citie: </l>
            <l>For you see, when we come to Towne, we doe </l>
            <l>Nothing but runne from Taverne, to Taverne; </l>
            <l>Oft to blind Ale-houses, to visit the fine </l>
            <l>Wenches, of purpose there plac'd, to draw custome; </l>
            <l>Now and then to see a Play, when we want </l>
            <l>Other exercise; and once a weeke (upon </l>
            <l>A holy day, when all doores are shut up) </l>
            <l>To a godly exhortation, and sleepe out </l>
            <l>(At least) three parts on't. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e114910">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>Especially if you </l>
            <l>Take your liquor before hand. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e114940">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>Right brother, but </l>
            <l>To morrow we will both from hence, to th' Countrey. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e114970">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>Wo'd this night were over once. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e114990">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>We've excellent Mayds with us, </l>
            <l>And while my Ladies dance and feast it here, </l>
            <l>Both night and day: We both will keepe Court there; </l>
            <l>Throw out the house at th' windowes, and fetch in </l>
            <l>All our Towne-fidlers, with all the young fellowes </l>
            <l>In fifteene villages about us; is 't not good? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e115060">
            <speaker>Fred. </speaker>
            <l>O rare! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e115080">
            <speaker>Fred. </speaker>
            <l>I' th' meane time Sir, let me perswade you </l>
            <l>To conduct your brother to a place: For I </l>
            <l>Am weary of your company. Cow, 'thanke your Lordship. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e115120">Exeunt ambo. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Hubba within, give way there. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e115140">
            <speaker>Fred. </speaker>
            <l>What lusty Gentleman's that? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-servant" xml:id="ep000471-e115160">
            <speaker>Serv. </speaker>
            <l>Mad Captaine Hubba, and as lusty a </l>
            <l>Virago with him. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e115190">Enter Hubba and Marfisa in an Irish Gowne tuck'd up to mid-legge, with a broad basket-hilt Sword on, hanging in a great Belt, Broags on her feet, her hayre dishevell'd, and a payre of long neck'd big-rowll'd Spurs on her heels. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e115200">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>Come my brave Marfisa, </l>
            <l>You are but just now come to Towne you say? </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000471-023-a"/>
          <sp who="A30315-marfisa" xml:id="ep000471-e115230">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>That you may well perceive sir, by my spurs. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e115250">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Here's handsome Cheese and Butter, and a Sword. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e115270">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>They're a payre of excellent ginglers, but pray </l>
            <l>Tell me: Did you ride sideling, or like a man? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-marfisa" xml:id="ep000471-e115300">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>Howsoever, there shall ne'r a Dane ride i' my Saddle. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e115320">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>What? not i' the way of honesty? as you love me, </l>
            <l>Say not so; I hope you'll be pleas'd to thinke of my service. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-marfisa" xml:id="ep000471-e115350">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>I sho'd rejoyce to be well pleas'd i' th' way </l>
            <l>Of honesty: Yet, your faire words shall not </l>
            <l>Deceive me. As first try, then take on liking. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e115390">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>But, with your favour I thinke 't were better try: </l>
            <l>Least you sho'd chance repent too late hereafter. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-marfisa" xml:id="ep000471-e115420">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>You will not put me sir, to use my Sword: <stage xml:id="ep000471-e115440">Puts hand to her sword. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>If you doe, you must first begin at that. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e115460">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>I thinke she meanes to make him marry her </l>
            <l>Perforce; I shall have my part o' th' Maske here. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e115490">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>Pray Lady, take patience along with you; </l>
            <l>I am fairely yours. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e115520">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>You had (on my knowledge) </l>
            <l>But need to say so, if she be in earnest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-marfisa" xml:id="ep000471-e115550">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>Then leade me to some honest place, where I may </l>
            <l>Unspurre, untucke my Gowne, wash, and so forth— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e115580">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>Most willingly, my faire Marfisa, thou sha't </l>
            <l>Have a looking-glasse too; I ever tooke </l>
            <l>A strange liking to thee, since first I saw </l>
            <l>Thee fight i' th' battle like a Lyonesse. </l>
            <l>Y'are Coffen-german to th' Lady Fatyma? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-marfisa" xml:id="ep000471-e115640">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>Her selfe dare not deny it, sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e115660">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>I doe not <stage xml:id="ep000471-e115680">Goes about her. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Onely marke your sweet face, but all things else </l>
            <l>About you. Y' have a fine legge. The fashion </l>
            <l>Of this Gowne, likes me well too; I thinke you had </l>
            <l>The patterne on't from us, as we from Ireland. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-marfisa" xml:id="ep000471-e115730">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>That I know not, but am sure a handsome woman </l>
            <l>Lookes as well in 't, as in any dresse, or habit </l>
            <l>Whatsoever. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e115770">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>So it seemes by thee, my </l>
            <l>Beautifull Mistris: For by that name, I must </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-023-b"/>
            <l>Stile you henceforth. Come, let your loving squire </l>
            <l>Conduct you. Mar, on before, I'll follow. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e115820">Exeunt ambo. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Lowd Musicke. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e115840">Enter Reyner, Landgartha, Valdemar, Scania, Elsinora, Inguar, and Fatyma. The Ladies attir'd like women onely </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e115850">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>My Queene and I, Valdemar, are much bound </l>
            <l>To thy free Genius, for this thy second Maske </l>
            <l>After our nuptials; She more: but most </l>
            <l>Of all, thy owne Lady. For, it's for her sake </l>
            <l>Thou so affect'st both us. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e115910">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>I could not wish </l>
            <l>To 'a' met a kinder man. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e115940">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>His kindnesse makes </l>
            <l>You oft asham'd, you say; nor wo'd I have </l>
            <l>The King so over fond of me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e115980">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>You stand </l>
            <l>Confirm'd, Madame, in the pow'r your merits </l>
            <l>Hold, to charme his faculties to your obeysance. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e116020">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>You deliver that, sir, to picke a thanke from </l>
            <l>My Sister; at whom you point in that language. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e116050">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>I doe beleeve he does: which yet, must be </l>
            <l>Conceiv'd onely to proceed, from his ill-plac'd </l>
            <l>Affection; not my desert to answer </l>
            <l>His; much lesse your perfections: being </l>
            <l>But a poore Pigmie, compar'd to the greatnesse </l>
            <l>Of the worth in you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e116120">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>This friendly Complement </l>
            <l>We will passe over: and now Valdemar, <ref target="A30315-e116150-b"/>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A30315-e116150-a" place="margin">Heere they take their places, but the King and the Queene under a Canopie. </note>
            </l>
            <l>To apt our apprehensions the more </l>
            <l>To the true understanding of your Maske: </l>
            <l>You may tell us somewhat of your scope in 't. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e116190">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>That is sufficiently inform'd i' the thing </l>
            <l>It selfe; though lame it be. The matter (being </l>
            <l>All propheticall) I found in an old </l>
            <l>Worme-eaten Booke, in the Lady Elsinora's </l>
            <l>Library. And I sho'd wrong your judgement; </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-024-a"/>
            <l>And my owne labour, though of little value, </l>
            <l>By staling of it before hand. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e116270">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>It's a fine tale; </l>
            <l>And cannot but please, unlesse it meet such minds, </l>
            <l>As are not to be pleas'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-elsinora" xml:id="ep000471-e116310">
            <speaker>Elsin. </speaker>
            <l>There is no Fustian, </l>
            <l>Non sense, Winde, or fopperie in't. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e116340">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>It matters not </l>
            <l>What some odd envious foole sayes; that grieves most </l>
            <l>At th' goodnesse of what he disprayses: and wo'd </l>
            <l>Be glad 't were worse. We despise affected stuffe; </l>
            <l>Or a strayn'd kind of Eloquence; being the smoake </l>
            <l>And fruits or a vaineglorious, and an empty braine, </l>
            <l>No flattery dwels we know in this. Let it begin. </l>
            <l>The Maske. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e116430">First enter six Satyrs and dance a short nimble anticke to no Musicke, or at most to a single Violine: at the end of which enter Phoebus with Bow and Arrowes. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-phoebus" xml:id="ep000471-e116440">
            <speaker>Phoeb. </speaker>
            <l>A way unmanner'd deities, though hope </l>
            <l>Rayse you unto this mirth, for Troy: Your scope </l>
            <l>In 't (form'd at the counsell of the higher gods) </l>
            <l>Makes not the issue of their Periods, </l>
            <l>So fortunate as you doe now suppose </l>
            <l>(In your inferior knowledges) to dispose </l>
            <l>For Hectors safetie: whom Aracides </l>
            <l>(Madded for his lov'd Menetiades) </l>
            <l>Flyes to destroy. Nor can the Fates divert, </l>
            <l>But that fierce horrid man, will soone convert </l>
            <l>All unto sad destruction; unlesse </l>
            <l>We the pryme gods and demi-gods suppresse </l>
            <l>His force, not otherwise to be resisted. </l>
            <l>Get you away from hence then, and in stead </l>
            <l>Of frisk, in these pleasant vales of Ide, </l>
            <l>Expose your aydes (to th' utmost can be try'd) </l>
            <l>For Pryam and his issue, ne'r till now </l>
            <l>In danger of an utter overthrow. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-024-b"/>
            <l>And my owne labour, though of little value, </l>
            <l>By staling of it before hand. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-frederick" xml:id="ep000471-e116650">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>It's a fine tale; </l>
            <l>And cannot but please, unlesse it meet such minds, </l>
            <l>As are not to be pleas'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-elsinora" xml:id="ep000471-e116690">
            <speaker>Elsin. </speaker>
            <l>There is no Fustian, </l>
            <l>Non sense, Winde, or fopperie in't. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e116720">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>It matters not </l>
            <l>What some odd envious foole sayes; that grieves most </l>
            <l>At th' goodnesse of what he disprayses: and wo'd </l>
            <l>Be glad 't were worse. We despise affected stuffe; </l>
            <l>Or astrayn'd kind of Eloquence; being the smoake </l>
            <l>And fruits of a vaineglorious, and an empty braine, </l>
            <l>No flattery dwels we know in this. Let it begin. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e116800">The Maske. First enter six Satyrs and dance a short nimble anticke to no Musicke, or at most to a single Violine: at the end of which enter Phoebus with Bow and Arrowes. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-phoebus" xml:id="ep000471-e116810">
            <speaker>Phoeb. </speaker>
            <l>Away unmanner'd deities though hope </l>
            <l>Rayse you unto this mirth, for Troy: Your scope </l>
            <l>In 't (form'd at the counsell of the higher gods) </l>
            <l>Makes not the issue of their Periods, </l>
            <l>So fortunate as you doe now suppose </l>
            <l>(In your inferior knowledges) to dispose </l>
            <l>For Hectors safetie: whom Aracides </l>
            <l>(Madded for his lov'd Menetiades) </l>
            <l>Flyes to destroy. Nor can the Fates divert, </l>
            <l>But that fierce horrid man, will soone convert </l>
            <l>All unto sad destruction; unlesse </l>
            <l>We the pryme gods and demi-gods suppresse </l>
            <l>His force, not otherwise to be resisted. </l>
            <l>Get you away from hence then. and instead </l>
            <l>Of frisk, in these pleasant vales of Ide, </l>
            <l>Expose your aydes (to th' utmost can be try'd) </l>
            <l>For Pryam and his issue, ne'r till now </l>
            <l>In danger of an utter overthrow. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000471-025-a"/>
          <lg type="song">
            <head>Song. </head>
            <l>Though Hector now be dead, his name </l>
            <l>And memory shall last, while fame </l>
            <l>Sounds her low'd Trumpet, lov'd, admir'd; </l>
            <l>By his example shall be fir'd </l>
            <l>To acts heroicke, future ages: </l>
            <l>And Prophets (sacred in their rages) </l>
            <l>Shall by his vertues be install'd; </l>
            <l>And he by all a worthy call'd. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e117090">Hectors body is taken away about the middle of the Song: after the end of it, Enter Phoebus and Pryam. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-phoebus" xml:id="ep000471-e117100">
            <speaker>Phoeb. </speaker>
            <l>Much honour'd and deere old man, did'st not heare, </l>
            <l>How the Jdalian deities forbeare </l>
            <l>Not (sacred loving Nymphs, and griev'd like thee) </l>
            <l>To chant a mirthfull pleasing melody? </l>
            <l>Glad for the future glory of thy sonne, </l>
            <l>Reason sho'd governe: and a faire fame wonne, </l>
            <l>Is of mans humane life the chiefest part, </l>
            <l>Chiefest in Hector, and shall not depart </l>
            <l>From thy for-ever-most-fam'd house: For, know </l>
            <l>Th' gods on thy line (of Dardunus) will bestow </l>
            <l>The largest Empyres; which to thee I'll now </l>
            <l>Show for thy comfort: that thou sho'dst not bow </l>
            <l>(Too much dejected in thy minde) to what </l>
            <l>They in their Counsels doe predestinate. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-pryam" xml:id="ep000471-e117250">
            <speaker>Pry. </speaker>
            <l>Heavens brightest eye, I 'll doe what lyes in me, </l>
            <l>To obey thy will, and my sowre destinie. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-phoebus" xml:id="ep000471-e117280">
            <speaker>Phoeb. </speaker>
            <l>My tale in two parts, I doe thus impart: </l>
            <l>A Prince from Troy hereafter shall depart, </l>
            <l>When Troy takes end (as all dominion. </l>
            <l>Of mortals must:) whose chance will fetch him on </l>
            <l>The Lybian shores, and upon Latium next. </l>
            <l>Before which time and after, though oft vex'd </l>
            <l>By the high-minded Juno, for her hates </l>
            <l>Conceiv'd against the Troians: Yet, the Fates </l>
            <l>Have destin'd him that throne of Latium, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-025-b"/>
            <l>Marrying the daughter of its King. From him </l>
            <l>(The Royall seate first chang'd to Alba) shall </l>
            <l>Descend two Princes, twins; for which, a fall </l>
            <l>Their mother takes from Mars, a votresse she, </l>
            <l>Compell'd unto that state. Impietie </l>
            <l>In an ambitious kinsman, to be drown'd </l>
            <l>Sends both the Infants: who (sav'd by chance) are found </l>
            <l>Of a she-woolfe, and nourish'd with her Teats; </l>
            <l>Till by a sheepheard found, and by brave feats </l>
            <l>Made know'n to be themselves, they build a Towne </l>
            <l>Which shall be call'd Rome; and shall weare the Crowne </l>
            <l>Of the worlds Monarchy, hundreds of yeares. </l>
            <l>This is the first part of my tale. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-pryam" xml:id="ep000471-e117510">
            <speaker>Pry. </speaker>
            <l>My feares </l>
            <l>And sorrow (which till now I did suppose </l>
            <l>Could not be done) th' hast heal'd. Disclose </l>
            <l>The other part (deare god) that's left untould. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-phoebus" xml:id="ep000471-e117560">
            <speaker>Phoeb. </speaker>
            <l>Which (in no obscure termes) I doe unfould: </l>
            <l>A Prince call'd Brutus (of the Troian race) </l>
            <l>Third to the first spoke of, being in the chace </l>
            <l>Of wild beasts, by unlucky fate he kils </l>
            <l>Sylvius his Father, with the shaft he drils </l>
            <l>At other game: Which fact, so much doth bend </l>
            <l>The Latines against Brutus, him they send </l>
            <l>To sad exile. Who (after a time) arrives </l>
            <l>At a brave spatious Iland (that derives </l>
            <l>Her name from white rocks, being a little world) </l>
            <l>With other Troians before met, and hurl'd </l>
            <l>Too on misfortunes. A towne call'd new Troy </l>
            <l>He builds here th' Land cals Brutaine: doth enjoy </l>
            <l>The whole as King; and his posteritie </l>
            <l>For many ages, shall raigne there, as he. </l>
            <l>Sometimes (in pow'r and plentie) conquering </l>
            <l>The neighbor Nations: sometimes these (for nothing </l>
            <l>But 's subject unto change on earth) afflict </l>
            <l>Againe Troy's Brutaines, in their owne district. </l>
            <l>Of which a certaine people, and call'd Danes </l>
            <l>(Cymbrians by some) will prove their worst of banes. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-026-a"/>
            <l>But shall be beaten backe; not without paine. </l>
            <l>At length (in processe of much time) shall raigne </l>
            <l>In this faire Ile, a Prince (one way descended </l>
            <l>Of Troian race: I' th' other side extended </l>
            <l>Vp by the Royall bloud of Danes, unto </l>
            <l>A warlike King call'd Reyner, that shall wooe </l>
            <l>And wed a Lady Amazonian, </l>
            <l>Landgartha nam'd) which Prince shall be the man </l>
            <l>(Having his subjects in their loves combyn'd; </l>
            <l>Who shall to evils onely be confin'd </l>
            <l>By their owne sad dissentions, being of all </l>
            <l>Earths men, the properest and most martiall) </l>
            <l>To exalt thy bloud. He shall (by 's right) enjoy </l>
            <l>The Land of Danes; and in this place where Troy </l>
            <l>Now stands, shall Conquer, and build it againe. </l>
            <l>Will also Conquer Greece, and there restrayne </l>
            <l>Th' impieties of wicked men. Thus, Fate </l>
            <l>I have layd ope 'to thee, to consolate </l>
            <l>Thy selfe and sad Queene; Now I must away: </l>
            <l>For, from the gods I've made too long a stay. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e117980">Exeunt ambo. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e117990">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>Your Majesties have now seene all; even as </l>
            <l>I found recorded in the foresayd Booke: </l>
            <l>How true heaven onely knowes. Yet, all may prove true </l>
            <l>(Being not impossible) if men be wise. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e118040">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>And not destroy themselves, as it's there spoke. </l>
            <l>Our part on't has hit right; and so may that. </l>
            <l>And now (Valdemar) to requite thy love, <stage xml:id="ep000471-e118080">All rise. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>My Queene and I will make your Maske compleate, </l>
            <l>By being your dancers. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e118110">Enter Hub. &amp; Marf. without her sword, &amp; her Gowne untuck'd. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e118120">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>I must first beg your </l>
            <l>Pardon, to leade the measure, sir, for I have </l>
            <l>Brought a fine friendly dancer with me; and </l>
            <l>We will so foot it— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e118170">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Hubba, thou alwayes comm'st in pudding time. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e118190">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>Let's stand; I long to see Marfisa dance. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e118210">Here Hubba and Marfisa Dance the whip of Donboyne merrily. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e118220">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>This was excellent. We shall but shame ourselves, </l>
            <l>In following of you; Come let us begin. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e118250">
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-026-b"/>Here they dance the grand Dance in foure Couple, Reyner and Landgartha, Valdemar and Scania, Fredericke and Elsinora, Inguar and Fatyma. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e118260">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>So Cousin, we have made you some amends, </l>
            <l>For your part of the Maske: and now you shall </l>
            <l>(Being so kinde a husband) conduct your Lady </l>
            <l>Unto her Chamber; and there use her kindly </l>
            <l>Too as she deserves. Our Aunt and Cousin may </l>
            <l>(After all this noyse) also retyre; and say </l>
            <l>(In solitude and silence) th' many prayers </l>
            <l>They have omitted all the day. As for </l>
            <l>The Queenes grace: she must give me leave, </l>
            <l>To usher her to bed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e118370">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>Must That, in such </l>
            <l>A servant, were too peremptory. But </l>
            <l>If you plead your title King; I'll answer </l>
            <l>That I know how to fight: and have ere now </l>
            <l>Stoop'd a too hasty Prince. Therefore, good sir, </l>
            <l>You are best speake me faire; or I may put you </l>
            <l>Beside your sweet hopes; </l>
            <l>And give you some what of the sowre to taste. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e118460">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>That, and to kill me, were all one: For which, </l>
            <l>I now (and ever will) humbly intreat, </l>
            <l>As a poore suppliant with you to treat. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e118500">Exeunt omnes. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="ep000471-e118510">
          <head>The fourth Act. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e118520">Enter Reyner musing at one doore, and Hubba to him at the other. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e118530">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Is Inguar yet return'd from th' Fleet? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e118550">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>Not yet sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e118570">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Let him be quickly sent for then: be gone. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e118590">Exit Hubba. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>A poore gentlewoman, an ordinary </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-027-a"/>
            <l>Noble mans daughter, to have catch'd me thus; </l>
            <l>Whom Cesar would rejoyce, to have made his sonne, </l>
            <l>Some horrid plague confound her modesty, </l>
            <l>And her for me, for now I care not for her; </l>
            <l>Though I dissemble it: because I dare not </l>
            <l>(She is so damn'd valiant) doe otherwise </l>
            <l>Till I have got from hence: For she (being </l>
            <l>So belov'd too of the Norwegians) might </l>
            <l>Cut short my life and passage. But yet, Reyner, </l>
            <l>Thinke how exceeding worthy she is of love; </l>
            <l>And of a Prince: thinke of her vertue, doe: </l>
            <l>Thinke of her beautie, myldnesse, vallor, and </l>
            <l>What else: no, no, I will not; will not love her: </l>
            <l>For I have tooke enough of what I most lov'd; </l>
            <l>Which, I confesse could not but please my Palat <stage xml:id="ep000471-e118760">Enter Vald. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>But here comes Valdemar, who like an Asse </l>
            <l>Still dotes on his wife, I 'll not therefore trust him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e118790">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>Your resolution to be gone for Denmarke, </l>
            <l>Men doe admire; and I must tell you, sir, </l>
            <l>(Seeing you will needs be constant, in so bad </l>
            <l>A purpose) some doe feare your projects are </l>
            <l>Ignoble. I then (as one that lov'd you once; </l>
            <l>And will doe still, unlesse you forfeyte your selfe) </l>
            <l>Wo'd be your adviser, if you dare take advice. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e118870">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Y'are too sawcie; and what I have resolv'd on, </l>
            <l>I will not alter. Must we be curb'd by you, </l>
            <l>In tendering the welfare of our subjects? </l>
            <l>Shall Denmarke be still forgotten? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e118920">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>That colour </l>
            <l>Dyes but very poorely; though you stalke with it. </l>
            <l>The fall of your obstreperous passion, to </l>
            <l>Your Queene (sir) people take notice of: though she, </l>
            <l>Poore Lady, (asham'd to be deceiv'd or scorn'd) </l>
            <l>Say nothing of it; restrayn'd too, by her love </l>
            <l>To you. But, we that are your Countriemen </l>
            <l>(Whom you mainely dishonour in't) can have </l>
            <l>No such patience. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e119020">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Our affection to our </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-027-b"/>
            <l>Lov'd faire Consort (though you be pleas'd to doubt it) </l>
            <l>Will not be question'd, but by your slanderous tongue </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-unassigned" xml:id="ep000471-e119060">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>You cannot, sir. Nay shall not, maske your blacke </l>
            <l>Intentions so from me; they doe appeare </l>
            <l>Too many. And she whom you most wrong, is more </l>
            <l>Then worthy of you; had you but the wisedome </l>
            <l>And grace to thinke so still. But be assur'd </l>
            <l>(When she is rid o' th' burthen she now carries) </l>
            <l>She'll be reveng'd at full for her dishonour; </l>
            <l>And snatch the Crownes you weare from of your trech'rous Temples. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e119150">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>You will not play the Traytor, in </l>
            <l>Conspiring with her? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e119180">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>Though I sho'd not, sir, </l>
            <l>You need not doubt but Harrolld will; who thinkes </l>
            <l>His right to Denmarke, as good as yours to Norway. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e119220">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>That Christian dogshead and yours too, had beene </l>
            <l>chopt off ere this, had I not beene a foole. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e119250">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>If you durst (you make me now beleeve) that had </l>
            <l>Beene so. But I'll make shift to save one of 's; <stage xml:id="ep000471-e119280">Enter Ing. &amp; Hubba. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>And thinke you'll hardly save your selfe from t' other. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e119300">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>You may doe what you lift; and so will I, </l>
            <l>Are all the Shipping ready? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e119330">
            <speaker>Ing. </speaker>
            <l>They are sir, but— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e119350">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Come, spare your breath; I know what you wo'd say. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e119370">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>Wo'd all the Cables and Sayles were burnt: </l>
            <l>You brought us hither with the hazard of our lives, </l>
            <l>To gaine this kingdome for you; and now you have it, </l>
            <l>You'll wisely gi' 't away; and fetch 'em all </l>
            <l>Upon our backes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e119430">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Who made you a Counseller? </l>
            <l>There's your reward. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e119460">strikes him. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e119470">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>I shall take more then this </l>
            <l>Ere long if I sticke to you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e119500">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>You doe well </l>
            <l>To practise before hand. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e119530">Offers to draw, so does Vald. &amp; Ing. steps in. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e119540">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Traytor, doe you upbrayd us? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e119560">
            <speaker>Ing. </speaker>
            <l>I beseech you sir, to suppresse your passion; </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-028-a"/>
            <l>And not to rayse a tumult here: knowing </l>
            <l>How truely-loyall the Prince Valdemar, </l>
            <l>Has ever beene to you, sir, and now pleads </l>
            <l>Strongly against himselfe; in seeking to </l>
            <l>Detaine you, with your gracious noble Queene. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e119630">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>He accounts his friends, his neerest enemies, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e119650">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>We take heaven to witnesse, we are wrong'd. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e119670">Enter Land, with Childe and Scania not so. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>But peace; here she comes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e119690">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>Will you needs be gone, sir, </l>
            <l>And leave me thus? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e119720">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>It is but two houres sayling, </l>
            <l>In a faire day; and we shall soone be backe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e119750">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>I doe not use to weepe: But now I must; <stage xml:id="ep000471-e119770">Weeps. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>My heavy minde fore-speakes some future evill. </l>
            <l>Death (which shall be welcome) I know 's not farre from me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e119800">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>May the gods grant to hasten it. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e119820">Aside. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e119830">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>The time was </l>
            <l>When shee, sir, could with a nod a' forc'd your fancie, </l>
            <l>In a farre greater matter, then your stay </l>
            <l>For some small time. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e119880">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>And shall againe sweet Sister, </l>
            <l>But the meere necessitie of our departure, </l>
            <l>Is such: that we must needs away, at this </l>
            <l>Very instant. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e119930">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>Then give me leave (deare sir,) </l>
            <l>To share the worst may happen in your voyage. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e119960">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>So to indanger your life, we'd loose ours first, </l>
            <l>You shall by no meanes stirre, my only soule, Come: </l>
            <l>We will conduct you to your Chamber, and there </l>
            <l>Leave you (with your friends and mine) to be guided </l>
            <l>By your accustomed vertue, and strong heart. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e120020">Exeunt. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e120030">Enter Cowsell and Radger. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e120040">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>O brother, brother, I know the very griefe on't, </l>
            <l>Will kill me out right, as dead as a Herring. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e120070">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>O deare, loving brother. I shall fare no better, </l>
            <l>I'm sure o' that; wo'd I had never seene you. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000471-028-b"/>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e120100">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>Besides brother, I tooke such an affection </l>
            <l>To the women, fine, courteous, honest cre'tures. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e120130">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>And we to you brother, and to all the Danes. </l>
            <l>You came not to pray on's, but to deliver </l>
            <l>Us from the Swedes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e120170">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>We ought to love each other, </l>
            <l>Brother, being so neere neighbors, and friends. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e120200">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>So we doe, deare brother, all those are good and honest. </l>
            <l>Who wo'd 'a' thought his grace sho'd leave the Queene </l>
            <l>So abruptly, i' the latter end of her time too? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e120240">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>Hard against our wils: but sayes, he'll soone be backe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e120260">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>I' th' meane time brother, and before we part, </l>
            <l>We are best take t' other cup. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e120290">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>I thought to 'a' </l>
            <l>Made that now my motion brother, we shall </l>
            <l>Remember you in Denmarke. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e120330">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>And when we </l>
            <l>Forget you brother, may the gods forget us. </l>
            <l>Ho! drawer, Rolfo, </l>
            <l>Within, Anon anon sir. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e120380">Enter Rolfo. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e120390">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>Honest Rolfo, one flaggon more of that </l>
            <l>You gave us last, the very same I charge thee, </l>
            <l>Without tricks or mixture. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-rolfo" xml:id="ep000471-e120430">
            <speaker>Rol. </speaker>
            <l>By Love sir, you shall: </l>
            <l>What? Doe you thinke I 'll use you like a stranger? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e120460">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>Prithee kinde Rolfo, let not us be forc'd </l>
            <l>To knocke agen. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e120490">Exit Rolfo. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e120500">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>Captaine Hubba (as I </l>
            <l>Conceive brother) goes not along with you; </l>
            <l>I met him spurring to our house, as I came. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e120540">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>The Princesse Scania, by much intreatie </l>
            <l>Got leave of the Lord Inguar, his Coronell, </l>
            <l>To stay onely two dayes; and he is gone </l>
            <l>A visit to his Mistris. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e120590">Enter Rolfo. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e120600">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>Welcome Rolfo. </l>
            <l>Come, give it me: for we shall need no glasses. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e120630">They drinke at the Lines. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Here worthy brother, halfe to your good journey </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e120650">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>Let me see brother, <ref target="A30315-e120670-b">* </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A30315-e120670-a" n="*" place="bottom">* Peeps into the pot. </note>you have drunke the full halfe— </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-029-a"/>
            <l>Here Rolfo, fill 't agen. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e120690">Exit Rolfo. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e120700">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>O sweet brother, that you co'd stay all night, </l>
            <l>I sho'd never be weary of your company. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e120730">Enter Rolfo. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e120740">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>Nor I of yours brother, and now from the deepe </l>
            <l>Bottome of my heart to th' wide mouth of my stomacke </l>
            <l>I speake it dearest brother, here's a whole one, </l>
            <l>To our next merry meeting— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e120790">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>Quickely Rolfo, <stage xml:id="ep000471-e120810">Exit Rolfo. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Fetch it, and be honest. O sweet brother, </l>
            <l>That I co'd imbrace you thus for ever, ever. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e120840">They imbrace. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e120850">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>I must kisse at parting. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e120870">They kisse. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-rolfo" xml:id="ep000471-e120880">
            <speaker>Rolf. </speaker>
            <l>Y'are a couple of th' arrantest kind gentlemen. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e120900">Ent. Rolf. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e120910">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>Give me the pot: I ne'r drunke i' my life </l>
            <l>With more sorrow, and a better desire.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e120940">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>Here, take Money Rolfo, my brother payd last, </l>
            <l>I must kisse thee too Rolfo, </l>
            <l>Within, Rolfo. Rogue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-rolfo" xml:id="ep000471-e120980">
            <speaker>Rolfo. </speaker>
            <l>Anon, anon, sir. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e121000">As they kisse. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e121010">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>Nay Rolfo, for all </l>
            <l>Your haste: I must (for my brothers sake) take </l>
            <l>Off that kisse, from thy now sweet (though greasie) lips. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e121050">They kisse </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e121060">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>And now farewell, but not for ever, my dearest </l>
            <l>And best of friends. Rad. we'll part at t'other Taverne. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e121090">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>Then arme in arme let 's march, most worthy brother. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e121110">Exeunt. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e121120">Enter Hubba and Marfisa. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e121130">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>I could not otherwise chuse, Mistris (though </l>
            <l>Your distrust of my unfayn'd affection, </l>
            <l>Kept me thus long from injoying, what I </l>
            <l>Most desir'd in a noble way) but come </l>
            <l>(Vrg'd by that love, that ever shall remaine </l>
            <l>With me, wheresoe'r I goe) to tender </l>
            <l>The duty of a servant, in taking leave </l>
            <l>Of you, before my suddaine departure. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-marfisa" xml:id="ep000471-e121220">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>It 's indeed too suddaine: and I doe now </l>
            <l>Repent the not imbracing, what I was not </l>
            <l>Enough good to accept, your love. For, I confesse </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-029-b"/>
            <l>Though somewhat late, I lov'd you more then you </l>
            <l>Did me; and ever shall unlesse the fault </l>
            <l>Be onely yours, in proving (which I doe </l>
            <l>Not yet suspect) a changling. I shall for </l>
            <l>My part, punish severely in my selfe, </l>
            <l>Th' offence of not being yours, by a continu'd </l>
            <l>Sadnesse and griefe, till once agen I see you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e121330">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>And though I have beene too much noted for </l>
            <l>My mirth (which yet, was never sawe'd with spite, </l>
            <l>Or other bad condition:) I promise </l>
            <l>(Por my misfortune in thus missing of you) </l>
            <l>Not to laugh once (unlesse against my will, </l>
            <l>At some unlucky chance) till I possesse </l>
            <l>The treasure I most covet. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-marfisa" xml:id="ep000471-e121410">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>That (if you </l>
            <l>Meane me) shall be yours when we meete next, and </l>
            <l>Safely kept for you, untill then. I' th' meane time, </l>
            <l>I shall charily preserve (though but a poore </l>
            <l>Satisfaction for you) your image in </l>
            <l>Th' interior of my minde. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e121480">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>Which overpay's, </l>
            <l>With much advantage, all my services. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-marfisa" xml:id="ep000471-e121510">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>'t was a strange resolution of the King, </l>
            <l>To leave his Queene, she being so much against it; </l>
            <l>And he so strangely fond of her at first: </l>
            <l>Which she deserv'd, being a Lady the world </l>
            <l>Cannot match. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e121570">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>He is these thirtie houres in Denmarke: </l>
            <l>Where if he prove unkinde to her, that cannot </l>
            <l>(In true judgement) condemne others, that like not </l>
            <l>Such proceeding. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-marfisa" xml:id="ep000471-e121620">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>He had neede be circumspect </l>
            <l>In what he do's; or he may soone repent it, </l>
            <l>And perchance, </l>
            <l>When matters prove past remedy to him, </l>
            <l>Yet, while I find you sound: no alien faults </l>
            <l>Shall make me hate, what once I so affected, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e121690">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>Resting on that assurance, I must now </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-030-a"/>
            <l>Crave the kind, favour of a parting kisse. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-marfisa" xml:id="ep000471-e121720">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>That you shall have <ref target="A30315-e121740-b">* </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A30315-e121740-a" n="*" place="margin">* they kisse </note>and halfe a dozen more, </l>
            <l>When you come to your Ship: For, so farre I </l>
            <l>Will with you; and wo'd along to Denmarke, but to try </l>
            <l>If I may build upon your constancie. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e121780">Exeunt. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e121790">Enter Harold and Eric. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-harrold" xml:id="ep000471-e121800">
            <speaker>Har. </speaker>
            <l>It's now but need, we both looke to our selves: </l>
            <l>Or we may pay the forfeyt of our slackenesse </l>
            <l>(With the losse of both our heads) upon a Scaffold. </l>
            <l>For, Reyner having cast the faire Landgartha </l>
            <l>Off, (of whom he was not worthy:) and by </l>
            <l>A dreadfull precipice, fall'n from much goodnesse: </l>
            <l>He will not stop at his first fault. But (hurri'd </l>
            <l>By the guiltinesse of his Conscience) </l>
            <l>Runne headlong downe the hill, upon the rocke </l>
            <l>Of dangerous mischiefe; to which he 's now ingag'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-eric" xml:id="ep000471-e121910">
            <speaker>Eric. </speaker>
            <l>She is a Lady of so stout a heart, </l>
            <l>That when she finds him base (although she lov'd him </l>
            <l>Exceedingly) shee cannot but be reveng'd </l>
            <l>For her repudiation, and disgrace. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-harrold" xml:id="ep000471-e121960">
            <speaker>Har. </speaker>
            <l>And may prove our strong friend to ruine him; </l>
            <l>That has threatned (and that not privatly) </l>
            <l>To rid himselfe on us. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-eric" xml:id="ep000471-e122000">
            <speaker>Eric. </speaker>
            <l>And will, if he can: </l>
            <l>You may by his death then, that wo'd be yours, </l>
            <l>Settle your selfe securely in his kingdomes, </l>
            <l>By matching and partaking now with her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-harrold" xml:id="ep000471-e122050">
            <speaker>Har. </speaker>
            <l>Brother, the man whose deitie we adore </l>
            <l>(And who to give us rest, still liv'd without it) </l>
            <l>Can witnesse for me, could I but perswade </l>
            <l>My minde by any probabilitie, </l>
            <l>'t were possible, for me to live in peace here, </l>
            <l>And not have my throat cut: although my right </l>
            <l>Unto the Crowne of Denmarke be apparant, </l>
            <l>My title while I slept or wak'd, sho'd sleepe; </l>
            <l>As when King Reyner liv'd a vertuous kind man. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-030-b"/>
            <l>For I delight not in th' expence of bloud; </l>
            <l>Though I feare not to spend my owne in a </l>
            <l>Iust cause. But seeing all rest is deni'd me: </l>
            <l>As the strong law of nature binds, I must </l>
            <l>Shift for my selfe, the best I may. Which shall not </l>
            <l>Be effected by base trechery, or murder. </l>
            <l>Nor doe I chiefly yet meane to rely </l>
            <l>On th' brave Landgartha's assistance; whom the </l>
            <l>Love of a wife, and hope of reconcilement, </l>
            <l>May urge beyond all spirit of revenge. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-eric" xml:id="ep000471-e122250">
            <speaker>Eric. </speaker>
            <l>What is 't you meane to plot then for our safetie? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-harrold" xml:id="ep000471-e122270">
            <speaker>Har. </speaker>
            <l>We'll to the pious Christian Emperor, </l>
            <l>Lewis the Debonaire; who (as you know) </l>
            <l>Do's oft solicite me to plead my right </l>
            <l>To th' Crowne, by dent of sword; that being the best </l>
            <l>(Nay onely) Patent, Reyner has to show for 't. </l>
            <l>Though he from 's father got it: which doth lessen </l>
            <l>Much his guilt. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-eric" xml:id="ep000471-e122350">
            <speaker>Eric. </speaker>
            <l>It's not his guilt that now most troubles him; </l>
            <l>But by more sinne to guard it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-harrold" xml:id="ep000471-e122380">
            <speaker>Har. </speaker>
            <l>Twelve thousand. </l>
            <l>Expert Souldiers (that lye neere here, o' th' borders </l>
            <l>Of Germany) I may have when I list; </l>
            <l>To adde (with all speed) to our owne sure friends. </l>
            <l>And unto others that will fall in troopes, </l>
            <l>From now dishonour'd Reyner, for his base </l>
            <l>Adultery intended with Vraca, </l>
            <l>To strengthen himselfe against his wife and me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-eric" xml:id="ep000471-e122470">
            <speaker>Eric. </speaker>
            <l>Vnheard of madnesse, so vilely to betray </l>
            <l>(And to 's owne ruine) a poore and vertuous Lady; </l>
            <l>That but for him, and his damn'd shamelesse lyes, </l>
            <l>Had never marry'd any. Being withall </l>
            <l>(As 't is reported) most extreamely faire, </l>
            <l>Farre, farre beyond the other, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-harrold" xml:id="ep000471-e122540">
            <speaker>Har. </speaker>
            <l>Such are the follies </l>
            <l>Of humane nature, when it is forsaken </l>
            <l>Of him that made it: But we'll now make use on't. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-eric" xml:id="ep000471-e122580">
            <speaker>Eric. </speaker>
            <l>You sho'd be suddaine, least we be layd hold on; </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-031-a"/>
            <l>And to take him unprepar'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-harrold" xml:id="ep000471-e122610">
            <speaker>Har. </speaker>
            <l>When night ascends </l>
            <l>Her sable charyot, we will both of us </l>
            <l>(Mounted on our best horses) post away; </l>
            <l>And be (I hope) ere we be miss'd, pass'd danger. </l>
            <l>Come, let us therefore in, and loose no time: </l>
            <l>Which, in necessitie 's a fatall crime. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e122680">Exeunt. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="ep000471-e122690">
          <head>The fift Act. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e122700">Enter Valdomar and Jnguar. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e122710">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>You are happy beyond expectation </l>
            <l>In your Embassage: for all men did conceive </l>
            <l>(And very probably) the Queene would ayde </l>
            <l>With th' utmost of her pow'r, Harrold in his </l>
            <l>Designe for Denmarke. But, she noble Lady, </l>
            <l>(Although in outward show, she have not granted </l>
            <l>What you demand) I know (such is her vertue </l>
            <l>And loving nature) is comming in her minde, </l>
            <l>Now to assist your most ungracious King. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e122810">
            <speaker>Ing. </speaker>
            <l>For which in chiefe he is to you beholding; </l>
            <l>Though he deserv'd it not, at his departure. </l>
            <l>But now, Contrition has wipt off his guilt, </l>
            <l>Though not the punishment, before the gods. </l>
            <l>Nor is there any hope left us on earth, </l>
            <l>But what we now may gaine here by your meanes </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e122880">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>Had you but beene a witnesse of her griefes </l>
            <l>(Able to rive a heart of steele) you had </l>
            <l>Melted (as we almost did) into teares: </l>
            <l>Especially when she heard of th' infamous </l>
            <l>Marryage, with Swealands daughter (told her by </l>
            <l>A whispering flatterer:) how then she tore </l>
            <l>Her golden hayre, and us'd such cruelty </l>
            <l>On her faire limmes, which had wellneere ended her </l>
            <l>(Notwithstanding what we could doe to hinder 't:) </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-031-b"/>
            <l>Cursing the time when she e'r saw a Dane; </l>
            <l>Not for her husbands renogading most: </l>
            <l>But the losse of her virginitie, and foule </l>
            <l>Disgrace. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e123020">
            <speaker>Ing. </speaker>
            <l>We heard of all: Yet, were compell'd </l>
            <l>By strong necessitie (perforce) to build </l>
            <l>On her heroicke goodnesse, and your worth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e123060">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>'t was well conceiv'd; and better put to tryall, </l>
            <l>That compulsion may worke peace agen. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e123090">
            <speaker>Ing. </speaker>
            <l>Here the divine Lady comes (her selfe) unto us. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e123110">Enter Landgartha, Scania, Elsinora, Fatyma, &amp; Marfisa in womans apparell with Swords on. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e123120">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>Although (Lord Inguar,) your soveraigne, and my </l>
            <l>Unkind husband, were rather to expect </l>
            <l>Sharpe warre and hate then any ayde from me </l>
            <l>In his distresse: having (as farre as 't lay </l>
            <l>In him) disgrac'd me by his flight; and as </l>
            <l>I'd us'd false play with others: yet, my love </l>
            <l>To him (deepely engraven in my heart.) </l>
            <l>Ioyn'd to my owne innocence and merit, has </l>
            <l>(As all may see) got the upper-hand; and stopt </l>
            <l>My once intended course of strict revenge; </l>
            <l>Though he enjoy another wife, now the Mistris </l>
            <l>Of what is mine by bond. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e123250">
            <speaker>Ing. </speaker>
            <l>Most gracious Queene, </l>
            <l>I can say nothing, to excuse his guilt; </l>
            <l>Or lessen it: but that your vertue shines </l>
            <l>The brighter for his deepe ingratitude, </l>
            <l>Which now 's the greatest Corrosive to himselfe, </l>
            <l>And cause of all his evils, by the losse </l>
            <l>Of in a manner all was his before: </l>
            <l>And that his act, has render'd both of you </l>
            <l>Famous to all the world, in different manners: </l>
            <l>You as the glorious mirrour of all worth, </l>
            <l>But him (with griefe I speake it) for 's offence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e123370">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>Which now (deare Madame) as it is repented, </l>
            <l>Exacts your mercy more then punishment. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-elsinora" xml:id="ep000471-e123400">
            <speaker>Elsin. </speaker>
            <l>To prove a lasting Pyramid to all </l>
            <l>Succeeding times, of such a noble act. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e123430">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>It can yeeld you no benefit to ruine </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-032-a"/>
            <l>Him and his poore subjects, being also yours; </l>
            <l>And in their loves, they're yours. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-fatyma" xml:id="ep000471-e123470">
            <speaker>Fat. </speaker>
            <l>Much more then his </l>
            <l>I doe beleeve. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e123500">
            <speaker>Ing. </speaker>
            <l>Madame. I can depose it. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e123520">To Fatyma. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>And that they 've ever deem'd it their chiefe glory, </l>
            <l>To have had her for their Queene; their hearts he lost, </l>
            <l>When he lost her: nor is there ought can rayse </l>
            <l>The minds o' th' few, that now sticke to him, but her </l>
            <l>Strong assistance, and the try'd vallor of the </l>
            <l>Norwegian Ladies, that before </l>
            <l>Gave us the victory against the Swedes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e123600">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>King Reyner and your selfe (Lord Inguar) have </l>
            <l>Too many friends here, to be deni'd in what </l>
            <l>Our pow'r may stead him, or you demand. </l>
            <l>And I'm the more induc'd to pardon his fault, </l>
            <l>That I acknowledge my selfe faultie too </l>
            <l>(And which my heart has oft accus'd me for, </l>
            <l>With no small griefe) in granting that to him </l>
            <l>Vnder the flattering title of marryage, which I </l>
            <l>Resolv'd ne'r to 'a' lost; and which he durst not </l>
            <l>Seeke to have forc'd from me. But it 's now past helpe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e123710">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>There 's one way yet left (Madame) to helpe all. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e123730">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>He then transported, by his fierce desire, </l>
            <l>Which slav'd him: by craft (I'll give it no worse </l>
            <l>A name) did that wrong to my modestie, </l>
            <l>Which I (being not so deepe in passion) </l>
            <l>Might well have hinder'd; and by yeelding to it, </l>
            <l>Have given scope for others to condemne me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e123800">
            <speaker>Ing. </speaker>
            <l>Which none can justly doe: For, I'm assur'd, </l>
            <l>Madame (though you have cause not to beleeve it) </l>
            <l>That his intents to your grace, were sincere </l>
            <l>At first, as now they are: and therefore (deare Queene,) </l>
            <l>You are to meete his past ill, with your goodnesse. </l>
            <l>Which, if you doe not speedily: there will be </l>
            <l>No time, nor meanes hereafter, left for you </l>
            <l>To exercise your vallor in this cause. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e123890">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>When we behold our neighbors house on fire, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-032-b"/>
            <l>The Proverbe sayes we ought looke to our owne: </l>
            <l>This you conceive; and I suppose you are </l>
            <l>Inform'd by these that love you, that we have </l>
            <l>As many valiant men and women, in </l>
            <l>A readinesse, as may, if heaven be pleas'd </l>
            <l>(For we are pleas'd in 't) reinthrone your King; </l>
            <l>And chase those rebels that now urge his flight. </l>
            <l>Let then my brother (the Prince Valdemar) </l>
            <l>And you, make all the haste you can before us; </l>
            <l>With newes of our approach. And, one thing more </l>
            <l>I must intreat you doe for me: which is </l>
            <l>To deliver this Letter, unto him that </l>
            <l>Caus'd my sorrow; and left me great with child. </l>
            <l>Which fruit of his, he shall soone looke on, young Frideslaus. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e124050">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>He sho'd 'a' stayd, to have got </l>
            <l>Such another. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e124080">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>In honesty, he could </l>
            <l>Have done no lesse. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e124110">
            <speaker>Ing. </speaker>
            <l>Your graces Letter, I hope </l>
            <l>Within these three houres, he shall reade at furthest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e124140">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>You'll give me leave to goe before, to provide </l>
            <l>A lodging for you? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e124170">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>Yes: for I meane to be </l>
            <l>Your bedfellow to morrow night. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e124200">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>And I shall strayne my selfe, to bid you welcome. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e124220">
            <speaker>Ing. </speaker>
            <l>The King will doe as much too, for your Highnesse. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e124240">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>Fy, not so soone man, that were a shame indeed, </l>
            <l>People wo'd then say, that I went to aske it. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e124270">smilingly </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Nor does he neede me; having one (at least) </l>
            <l>Already to keepe him warme. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e124300">
            <speaker>Ing. </speaker>
            <l>He thinkes of none, </l>
            <l>But your Grace. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e124330">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>We must be now abrupt in our </l>
            <l>Leave taking? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e124360">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>Be gone Scania, fare you well. Inguar, may all </l>
            <l>The gods be your guides. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e124390">Exeunt ambo. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e124400">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>And now Marfisa. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-033-a"/>
            <l>Silence declares with you, how gladly your heart </l>
            <l>Consents, to goe for Denmarke. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-marfisa" xml:id="ep000471-e124440">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>I meane to doe </l>
            <l>Your Majestie some service there, now that </l>
            <l>You measure my affection by your owne. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e124480">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>But what, if you come to weare the Willow garland, </l>
            <l>By the inconstancie of Captaine Hubba? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-marfisa" xml:id="ep000471-e124510">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>Not (doe as the Queene did) forgive the offence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-fatyma" xml:id="ep000471-e124530">
            <speaker>Fat. </speaker>
            <l>No lesse then 's life would satisfie your anger. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-marfisa" xml:id="ep000471-e124550">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>Doe you make doubt on't? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-elsinora" xml:id="ep000471-e124570">
            <speaker>Elsin. </speaker>
            <l>I beleeve him honest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e124590">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>What is your owne opinion? Marfisa. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-marfisa" xml:id="ep000471-e124610">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>I still suppose the best. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e124630">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>Then wayte upon </l>
            <l>My cousin Fatyma: and both of you make haste </l>
            <l>To summon with all speede (on paine of death) </l>
            <l>All our troops (both men and women) in Anstoy, </l>
            <l>Saltsburge, and thereabouts. Our Sister and Aunt </l>
            <l>Shall to the neerer quarters; whilst I prepare </l>
            <l>Here all things requisite for our departure. </l>
            <l>And as we once made no small haste to meete </l>
            <l>King Reyner, when he brought us ayde against </l>
            <l>Our foes: let's doe the same in gratitude </l>
            <l>(And with more honour) now, in assisting of him. </l>
            <l>Those which we leave, will keepe safe here. Away. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-fatyma" xml:id="ep000471-e124760">
            <speaker>Fat. </speaker>
            <l>The trust impos'd on us, we'll not betray. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e124780">Exeunt omnes severally. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e124790">A march. Then enter Harrold, Eric, and Lothaire arm'd. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-harrold" xml:id="ep000471-e124800">
            <speaker>Har. </speaker>
            <l>We must make haste, Lord Lothaire, (now that by </l>
            <l>The helpe of heaven, for which we chiefly move: </l>
            <l>And the assistance which you Lord and ours, </l>
            <l>The noble Emperor Lewis, true inheritor </l>
            <l>Of his great fathers vertues did afford us, </l>
            <l>We are ascended to what is our right, </l>
            <l>Being thereto lifted by your manly worth too) </l>
            <l>To make all sure, by joyning our last issue </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-033-b"/>
            <l>With Reyner, ere the brave Landgartha come </l>
            <l>(Whom he once more thinkes to deceive:) For, where </l>
            <l>Shee leads, all goes to wracke i' th' other side. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-lothaire" xml:id="ep000471-e124920">
            <speaker>Loth. </speaker>
            <l>It 's strange so stout a minde as hers, sho'd ever </l>
            <l>Yeeld love or obedience to a man that has </l>
            <l>So basely dealt to her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-eric" xml:id="ep000471-e124960">
            <speaker>Eric. </speaker>
            <l>She squares all her </l>
            <l>Actions by the rule of goodnesse, not </l>
            <l>Of passion; and thinkes this deede of hers, </l>
            <l>A very gratefull offering to her gods, </l>
            <l>Yet, we doe hope to send (before she land here: </l>
            <l>Her husbands rancke soule, to great Belzebub. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-harrold" xml:id="ep000471-e125030">
            <speaker>Har. </speaker>
            <l>Then let's march on with speede; and trust our cause </l>
            <l>To him, that only gives life by his lawes. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e125060">Exeunt a march. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e125070">After the march, Enter Reyner and Hubba. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e125080">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Heare you no newes from Inguar (Hubba) yet </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e125100">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>Not a word: But a ship is now on entring </l>
            <l>In at the haven; and we hope it 's his. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e125130">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>No, no. We are of all the world forsaken, </l>
            <l>But most of heaven: For, we have deserv'd it, </l>
            <l>And our repentance now comes too too late. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e125170">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>I doe beseech you sir, not to yeeld to </l>
            <l>Such weake, unmanly diffidence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e125200">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>We wrong'd </l>
            <l>Thee (Hubba) too; and now thy loyaltie </l>
            <l>And kindnesse wounds our soule deeper, then if thou hadst </l>
            <l>Prov'd false, all turnes to my confusion. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e125250">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>It was your passion and not you, strucke me, sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e125270">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Would I were quickly dead, or never borne, </l>
            <l>To see the evils which I have occasion'd, </l>
            <l>And must needs feele, if I but live a while. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e125310">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>Your noble Queene Landgartha, will I doubt not </l>
            <l>(If i' th' meane time sir, you doe what lyes in you, </l>
            <l>With patience) soone rid you of those feares; </l>
            <l>And State you as before; and in her love too. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e125360">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>I ne'r shall see that Halcyon day againe, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-034-a"/>
            <l>To see her, Hubba, though you all suppose </l>
            <l>The contrary; and caus'd me send to move </l>
            <l>Her goodnesse. She is too magnanimous </l>
            <l>Ever to looke at such a wretch as I am, </l>
            <l>That deceiv'd her once so foulely. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e125430">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>You'll finde </l>
            <l>Your selfe deceiv'd, I hope sir, in that ere long. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e125460">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Had I but faithfull prov'd to her, as she </l>
            <l>Deserv'd (thou know's it Hubba,) I might then </l>
            <l>'a' playd at stoole-ball with young children, or </l>
            <l>Have wasted time more idlely, if I'd listed; </l>
            <l>And have my estate multiply'd to many </l>
            <l>Kingdomes. Now, thou seest, we are not worth one </l>
            <l>Province, Stricke me heaven. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e125540">Enter Valdemar and Inguar. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e125550">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>Honest Captaine, I </l>
            <l>Am glad to meete you alive. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e125580">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>Your Highnesse poore servant. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e125600">
            <speaker>Ing. </speaker>
            <l>The King walkes strangely sad. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-hubba" xml:id="ep000471-e125620">
            <speaker>Hub. </speaker>
            <l>He's not himselfe: and therefore, whatsoever </l>
            <l>Newes you bring; y' had neede use your accustomed </l>
            <l>Discretion in the relating of it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e125660">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>You are both as welcome hither, as my </l>
            <l>Distraction will give me leave to bid you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e125690">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>I never knew you (sir) too much exalted </l>
            <l>At flatt'ring Fortunes smiles, or when you Conquer'd: </l>
            <l>And (now she frownes) you still ought to preserve </l>
            <l>A valiant indifferencie. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e125740">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Healthy men </l>
            <l>Know how t' afford good counsell unto others, </l>
            <l>Whose forces being too weake, to beare the blowes </l>
            <l>Of their diseases, yeeld and languish under </l>
            <l>The waight that 's insupportable. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e125800">
            <speaker>Jng. </speaker>
            <l>The weaker </l>
            <l>Their minds are, the more they yeeld; beyond </l>
            <l>Necessitie: and thereby become chiefe Actors </l>
            <l>In their owne Tragedies. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e125850">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>I know you speake this, </l>
            <l>To prepare my minde, for the bad newes you bring. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000471-034-b"/>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e125880">
            <speaker>Ing. </speaker>
            <l>Your vertue will now most consist, in not </l>
            <l>Being over joy'd, when you read this Letter, </l>
            <l>Written and sent by her, that sayes she loves you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e125920">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Let me see 't. I know the hand, it's hers, </l>
            <l>O let me, let me kisse it, kisse it still, <stage xml:id="ep000471-e125950">Kisses the Letter. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>And not presume to looke what it contaynes, </l>
            <l>To plague my guiltie conscience. Vald. reade and be rul'd. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000471-e125980">Reyner opens and Reads. </stage>
            <floatingText type="letter">
              <body>
                <p>If this my second duty, may prove as happy in the recovery of thy kingdomes, as my first was against a Tyrant; yet honouring thee with the victory; J shall account my travell well bestow'd. Make head bravely (as wisedome permits) against the enemie: for I am comming with all speed, to let him know, that Landgartha (being thy Queenne and only lawfull Wife) is a warrior: and will prove so to his prejudice, and thy advantage: having from her heart (notwithstanding thy unkindnesse) absolv'd thee of all the wrongs thou did'st her. </p>
                <closer>
                  <signed>Landgartha, </signed>
                </closer>
              </body>
            </floatingText>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e126040">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>A gracious language! O you gods defend me, </l>
            <l>From turning altogether foole at this. For, my </l>
            <l>Frayle vessell is not able to contayne, </l>
            <l>The forcible excesse of this sweet comfort. </l>
            <l>My soule results so strangely, mounts, mounts up, </l>
            <l>That I have much adoe, to keepe from dancing: </l>
            <l>My nimble spirit elevats my body, </l>
            <l>And my very life (I thinke) will now with joy </l>
            <l>Forsake me, fly away. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e126140">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>Be not in extreames, </l>
            <l>So like a meere franticke Pray recall your wits, </l>
            <l>Before she comes, you may loose all; your selfe, and us. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e126180">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Excuse me, worthy Cousin, you feele not </l>
            <l>The force of my impulsion. Yet, I confesse </l>
            <l>I'm (but as others are) a poore weake man; </l>
            <l>Subject to many changes 'gainst my will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e126230">
            <speaker>Ing. </speaker>
            <l>Collect your selfe, were 't but in obedience <stage xml:id="ep000471-e126250">Enter scout. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>To your wise and noble Queene. What newes with you? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scout" xml:id="ep000471-e126270">
            <speaker>Scout. </speaker>
            <l>That Harrold and his brother Eric, with </l>
            <l>A mighty pow'r of Danes and Germans, march </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-035-a"/>
            <l>Hither with speed, doubtlesse to force a battle. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e126310">
            <speaker>Ing. </speaker>
            <l>Which we must decline, till our best souldier </l>
            <l>Come: and then we are for 'em. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e126340">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>Lead us from hence, </l>
            <l>To guard your works; and doe not now forget </l>
            <l>(Your wish'd ayde being so neere you) your old vallor; </l>
            <l>And judgement to command. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e126390">
            <speaker>Ray. </speaker>
            <l>I hope we shall not. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e126410">Exeunt. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e126420">A march. Enter Harrold, Eric, Lothaire, and one or two more with Battle-axes. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-harrold" xml:id="ep000471-e126430">
            <speaker>Har. </speaker>
            <l>Our foes have fortifi'd themselves so strongly, </l>
            <l>With Waggons, Carts, huge tymber, and deepe trenches: </l>
            <l>As 'tis impossible almost to force 'em. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-eric" xml:id="ep000471-e126470">
            <speaker>Eric. </speaker>
            <l>Which if you doe not, you'll finde it a worse taske, </l>
            <l>To quayle Landgartha; whose fleet's now at sea; </l>
            <l>Nay hard on landing. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-lothaire" xml:id="ep000471-e126510">
            <speaker>Loth. </speaker>
            <l>Th' present attempt will not </l>
            <l>Perchance, prove so dangerous, as to th' eye </l>
            <l>It seemes; if we valiantly ingage </l>
            <l>Our selves in th' onset. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-harrold" xml:id="ep000471-e126560">
            <speaker>Har. </speaker>
            <l>Let us boldly on then; </l>
            <l>And to conclude what hitherto, we have </l>
            <l>So prosperously atchiev'd. I will beginne: </l>
            <l>And die, rather then loose what I have wonne. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e126610">Exeunt. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e126620">Allarums, A while after which is begun, enter Reyner and Valdemar with Battle-axes. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e126630">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>All 's lost beyond recoverie, they are broke </l>
            <l>Vpon us in, and fight like hungry Lyons, </l>
            <l>Tearing our men to peeces, that now leave, </l>
            <l>In foule disorder. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e126680">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>Doe you (whil'st I charge up, </l>
            <l>To give some stop unto their furie) rally </l>
            <l>And hearten yours, the best you may. For, if </l>
            <l>We can hold out, but one full houre: the noble </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-035-b"/>
            <l>Landgartha (that with speed incredible, </l>
            <l>Has almost landed all her forces) will be </l>
            <l>With us, to mend all agen. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e126760">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>She shall never meet me flying. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e126780">Exeunt. allarums. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e126790">Enter Landgartha, Scania, Elsinora, Fatyma, and Marfisa: The foure Ladies, like Amazons. Marfisa with her Gowne tuck'd to th' midleg, spurs, &amp;c. As in the first of the third Act; Battle-axes withall. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e126800">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>You heare this Musicke, Ladies, and perceive </l>
            <l>What need our friends have of our swift assistance. </l>
            <l>We are not therefore now, to insist upon <stage xml:id="ep000471-e126840">Here the Allarums sound as farre off. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>A tedious consultation; or on words </l>
            <l>By me deliver'd, to encourage those </l>
            <l>Whose worths I know already. Doe you Aunt </l>
            <l>(Assisted by Fatyma and Marfisa) </l>
            <l>Lead halfe our Armie: and wheele round about </l>
            <l>(With speed and silence) to charge strongly home, </l>
            <l>Upon our enemies backes. My sister and I </l>
            <l>Will to our Husbands, that are hardly prest; </l>
            <l>Their men all routed, and a number slaine. </l>
            <l>Farewell, I hope that we shall meete againe. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e126950">Exeunt sverally allarums. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e126960">Allarums. Then enter Reyner at one doore, and Harold at the other. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e126970">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Stand Traytor! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-harrold" xml:id="ep000471-e126990">
            <speaker>Har. </speaker>
            <l>Thou usurper, I will stand; </l>
            <l>And could afford you other glorious titles: </l>
            <l>But that I meane not (having met you) to </l>
            <l>Waste time in words, untill your foolish sweet-heart </l>
            <l>(Whom you wo'd still deceive) come to your rescue. </l>
            <l>But now, I hope you never shall enjoy her, </l>
            <l>You know how. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e127070">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>You shall know somewhat from me, howsoever. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e127090">
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-036-a"/>Here they fight, and Harrold beats Reyner under him; on which Landgartha enters, beats in Harrold and returns. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e127100">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>Is it you? I were not beholding, to <stage xml:id="ep000471-e127120">Land. Exit. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Have done this for you now. Goe, look to your selfe &amp; people. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e127140">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Deare heaven, where am I? or, is this a dream? <stage xml:id="ep000471-e127160">Reyner rises as she beats in Harrold. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>It was Landgartha sure. O no, it was not, </l>
            <l>That glory and great miracle of the world, </l>
            <l>Could not afford such grace to me, the meere </l>
            <l>Fall'n dregs of villanie. But yet, 't was she, </l>
            <l>The figure of her heavenly face, was once </l>
            <l>(And still is) so imprinted in my soule, </l>
            <l>As 't is impossible I sho'd forget her, </l>
            <l>Therefore you gods, heape all those mountaynes on me, </l>
            <l>Which the impious Gyants lifted against you, </l>
            <l>Or sincke me downe into the very Center, </l>
            <l>That I may ne'r behold her any more, </l>
            <l>That is so like you, both in shape and goodnesse. </l>
            <l>For, both I have contemn'd, and my most base </l>
            <l>Ingratitude, never appear'd at full; </l>
            <l>Till now. O Iove, pownd pownd me with thy thunder, </l>
            <l>For, my confusion is the worst of torments. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e127330">Enter Scania and Valdemar. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e127340">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>The King 's in danger; and we had need make haste </l>
            <l>To disingage him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e127370">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>That 's done (I hope) already. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e127390">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Welcome deare Sister, I am asham'd to looke </l>
            <l>You in the face. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e127420">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>We heard (sir) you were in danger. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e127440">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>I was: But now may (when I list) goe take </l>
            <l>A nap. Wo'd the infernall dogs would teare </l>
            <l>My limbs to callops: or adde some worse torment </l>
            <l>Unto my minds affliction. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e127490">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>You neede not </l>
            <l>Afflict your selfe so much, for ought we see: </l>
            <l>For, now the wheele is turn'd to your advantage; </l>
            <l>My Sister is friends with you too, sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e127540">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>She say'd </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-036-b"/>
            <l>My life, when I was downe; and ready to </l>
            <l>Receive the last (and mortall) blow. But then, </l>
            <l>Gave me so sad a looke, O loving Sister, </l>
            <l>That life which is her gift, if I must keepe </l>
            <l>In her displeasure, is much worse then death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e127610">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>Sir, if you will be rul'd by me, you must not </l>
            <l>Expresse too much, those vehement affections: </l>
            <l>For, she's acquainted but too well already, </l>
            <l>With your sad passion, and the continuance of it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e127660">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Seeing you (deare Lady,) in love and wisedome, </l>
            <l>Esteeme that my best course: I shall be dumbe </l>
            <l>As night, calme as the calm'st evening after </l>
            <l>A stormy day. Scania, let's follow, where she went then. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e127710">Exeunt. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e127720">Enter Harrold and Eric. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-harrold" xml:id="ep000471-e127730">
            <speaker>Har. </speaker>
            <l>After our losse and watching these two nights, </l>
            <l>I cannot brother (the toyle of our journey, </l>
            <l>Lying so heavy too, on my tyr'd body) </l>
            <l>But sleepe a little, though it be dangerous. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-eric" xml:id="ep000471-e127780">
            <speaker>Eric. </speaker>
            <l>My neede's no lesse; a little sleepe will serve. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-harrold" xml:id="ep000471-e127800">
            <speaker>Har. </speaker>
            <l>Let's take it here then, the place being solitary. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e127820">They sleepe, and a sweet solemne Musicke of Recorders is heard, then enter an Angel. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-angel" xml:id="ep000471-e127830">
            <speaker>Ang. </speaker>
            <l>Heaven has decreed, another day </l>
            <l>Shall gaine what you have lost. Your way </l>
            <l>Take both (as you were forc'd before) </l>
            <l>Unto the pious Emperor. </l>
            <l>One of you shall be King: whose seed </l>
            <l>Shall be so too, untill 't all bleed. </l>
            <l>Then (when that issue is extinct) </l>
            <l>Norway and Denmarkes whole precinct </l>
            <l>Shall be rul'd by Landgartha's line, </l>
            <l>And Reyners. Her the pow'rs divine </l>
            <l>Will (for her Morall vertues) turne </l>
            <l>A Christian, ere she come to th' Urne: </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-037-a"/>
            <l>Yeeld faith to this: For, without doubt, </l>
            <l>What I have sayd shall come about. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e127980">Exit Ang. then Eric stirs and wakes Har. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-eric" xml:id="ep000471-e127990">
            <speaker>Eric. </speaker>
            <l>Sir, you sleepe exceeding soundly: Pray wake. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-harrold" xml:id="ep000471-e128010">
            <speaker>Har. </speaker>
            <l>I now am fresh enough; Come let's be gone. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-eric" xml:id="ep000471-e128030">
            <speaker>Eric. </speaker>
            <l>Dream't you nothing, while you slept? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-harrold" xml:id="ep000471-e128050">
            <speaker>Har. </speaker>
            <l>No, did you? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-eric" xml:id="ep000471-e128070">
            <speaker>Eric. </speaker>
            <l>Me thought I heard a most heavenly Musicke; </l>
            <l>And that an Angel did appeare: and wish'd us, </l>
            <l>Betake our selves againe to th' Emperor, </l>
            <l>That what we lost, another day sho'd purchase; </l>
            <l>And that the faire Landgartha (as the reward </l>
            <l>Of her Morall vertues) would be made Christian, </l>
            <l>Before she di'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-harrold" xml:id="ep000471-e128150">
            <speaker>Har. </speaker>
            <l>Though we afford no credit </l>
            <l>Vnto such dreames: Yet, we must steere our course </l>
            <l>That way; there being (after so great a losse) </l>
            <l>No comfort left, where our foes are so strong. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-eric" xml:id="ep000471-e128200">
            <speaker>Eric. </speaker>
            <l>Heaven will in time (I hope) revenge our wrong. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e128220">Exeunt </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e128230">Enter Cowsell and Radgee. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e128240">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>Come brother Radgee, it is now concluded, </l>
            <l>We shall never part agen. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e128270">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>O deare brother, </l>
            <l>I never had a good day on't (much lesse </l>
            <l>A good night) since (being barr'd the comfort of your </l>
            <l>Sweet conversation) you parted from me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e128320">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>Nay brother, I can howle the same sad Madrigall </l>
            <l>Too: For looke you brother, we were all so frighted </l>
            <l>By those fat-foggy Germans (who men say </l>
            <l>Are nothing but flesh and belly:) that we durst </l>
            <l>Allow no time for mirth and drinking. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e128380">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>Very </l>
            <l>Strange that brother. For, they say themselves are </l>
            <l>Exceeding good fellowes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e128420">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>Iust of that seize. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e128440">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>I'll tell you more what I heard spoken of 'em, </l>
            <l>Brother, they're sowre: and never worth the trusting, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-037-b"/>
            <l>Or honest i' their bargaines, untill they </l>
            <l>Be drunke, or at least halfe drunke. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e128490">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>That's as true, </l>
            <l>Brother, as that you and I drunke halfe a score </l>
            <l>Flaggons yesternight a peece. The North winde </l>
            <l>Is not so bitter in a morning, till he </l>
            <l>Has tooke a buttrum, or his Wine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e128550">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>And then, </l>
            <l>Makes as good Musicke, as a Bag-pipe when it's </l>
            <l>Full blow'n. What doe you thinke of the Swedes? brother? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e128590">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>They are not (yet) altogether so good drinkers, </l>
            <l>As th' Germans are: but well fall'n to 't of late. </l>
            <l>Which makes me suppose, brother, they'll be beaten </l>
            <l>Out too. For besides, the King will no more kisse </l>
            <l>The Queene Vraca, as't is spoken: But sticke </l>
            <l>To 's owne old Camrade, being indeed the fairer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e128660">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>Yet, in my opinion brother: his Grace </l>
            <l>Being marry'd to both, sho'd doe exceeding well, </l>
            <l>To keepe both still: Sleepe betwixt both 'a' nights. </l>
            <l>And imbrace both by turnes. What say you brother? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e128710">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>What? But to concurre with you? and for many </l>
            <l>Good, and convincing reasons. 's for example: </l>
            <l>The King being kept so warme on both sides, by </l>
            <l>Two such delicate cre'tures, 't were impossible </l>
            <l>He sho'd catch cold; I, or perchance be troubl'd </l>
            <l>With Coughs, Scyaticas, or other bone-ach; </l>
            <l>And to have Swealand and Norway at command, </l>
            <l>Were a matter of no small importance, </l>
            <l>You conceive me, brother. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e128810">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>Few wise men better, </l>
            <l>In part. But, stand aside: themselves are comming. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e128840">Florish. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e128850">Enter Reyner, Landgartha, Valdemar, Vraca, Scania, Inguar, Elsinora Fatyma, Hubba and Marfisa; the Norwegian Ladies in womans apparell, with Swords on; Marfisa with her Gown untuck'd and sword on. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e128860">
            <speaker>Ing. </speaker>
            <l>You will not (gracious Madame) thus deceive </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-038-a"/>
            <l>The expectations of your poore, and loving </l>
            <l>People: whose whole hopes, comfort, safetie (nay all </l>
            <l>We can for the present, or hereafter call ours) </l>
            <l>Are but benefits deriv'd from the fountaine </l>
            <l>Of your warme bountie; at whose goodnesse yet, </l>
            <l>We most rejoyce. Doe not then (deare Empresse,) strike </l>
            <l>Sorrow to our lately bleeding hearts; that still </l>
            <l>Pant (and not slowly) by our former feares; </l>
            <l>And the sore stripes we tooke: Which, but for you, </l>
            <l>For ever were incurable; and now </l>
            <l>By your forsaking of us, will fester worse </l>
            <l>Then before. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e129000">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>That you neede not feare, Lord Inguar. </l>
            <l>For, I shall ne'r be wanting in my care, </l>
            <l>And love unto this Nation. Leaving here </l>
            <l>The best halfe of our Army, now behinde us; </l>
            <l>To prevent all future mischiefes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e129060">
            <speaker>Jng. </speaker>
            <l>Our dishonour </l>
            <l>In your departure, we shall ne'r recover. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e129090">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>My offence (which now 's my worst affliction, </l>
            <l>With what it does occasion) all may see, </l>
            <l>Tooke origen and issue, more of humane </l>
            <l>Frayltie, and foolish pride: then want of love </l>
            <l>To you; or of desert in you, to merit </l>
            <l>A better and more pow'rfull man then I am; </l>
            <l>Th' worlds onely Monarch, if there were but one, </l>
            <l>For which, I (without your mercie to restore me </l>
            <l>Once more unto your heart, as to my kingdomes) </l>
            <l>Must spend my dayes (which shall not then be many) </l>
            <l>Like to a sickely beast without a soule. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e129210">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>My heart shall still receive you: But, on my word, </l>
            <l>Th' rest of my body you shall not enjoy, sir, </l>
            <l>I now am gaunt you see, </l>
            <l>All though you must not have a feeling of it; </l>
            <l>And if I doe play false, my belly will show't </l>
            <l>Questionlesse: For, I am fruitfull if </l>
            <l>I sho'd be touch'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e129290">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>Although but weakly, Madame. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-039-a"/>
            <l>On you, and this your kinde friend: but that I wav'd </l>
            <l>Him for my husband, that despis'd me as </l>
            <l>His honest Mate; and wo'd 'a' lov'd me for </l>
            <l>By-blowes. Therefore, enjoy him still: for, I suppose </l>
            <l>You are a Hen, that must be trod. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-uraca" xml:id="ep000471-e129360">
            <speaker>Vrac. </speaker>
            <l>That 's more then you know; or I hope shall finde. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e129380">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>She shall ne'r enjoy me; nor has not </l>
            <l>Of a long time I'll sweare, if that will serve. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e129410">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>It shall not sir) beleeve it. Yet, ne'r feare </l>
            <l>You shall be arm'd i' th' front by me; which is </l>
            <l>A wrong this other Lady cannot doe you, </l>
            <l>If she wo'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-uraca" xml:id="ep000471-e129460">
            <speaker>Vrac. </speaker>
            <l>I'll leave that now for you, that have </l>
            <l>The abler bodie. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e129490">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>And you the frayler minde. </l>
            <l>But if you chop words with me thus, or insult: </l>
            <l>I may (for a farwell) cracke your birds necke, </l>
            <l>Before we part. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-uraca" xml:id="ep000471-e129540">
            <speaker>Vrac. </speaker>
            <l>I must not stand so neere </l>
            <l>You then. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e129570">She steps behinde Reyner, and holds him betwixt Langartha and her selfe. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e129580">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Nor I prove any safeguard for you. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e129600">Steps from betwixt them. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>But sho'd take part with her, whom I love best; </l>
            <l>And has best right unto me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-unassigned" xml:id="ep000471-e129630">
            <speaker>Urac. </speaker>
            <l>That you say </l>
            <l>To flatter her, and for meere feare. But if </l>
            <l>I had you in private, I know what you </l>
            <l>Wo'd sing; and play too, if I sho'd but yeeld. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e129680">Land. runs at her, and Elsinora steps in. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-elsinora" xml:id="ep000471-e129690">
            <speaker>Elsin. </speaker>
            <l>What doe you meane? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e129710">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>That I will ne'r have him, </l>
            <l>That is resolv'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-elsinora" xml:id="ep000471-e129740">
            <speaker>Elsin. </speaker>
            <l>Your resolution </l>
            <l>(I must say) in that, is worse then madnesse. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e129770">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>I'll not quarrell with you, Aunt. Yet, doe admire </l>
            <l>A Lady of your know'n modestie, should be </l>
            <l>So farre mistaken, and in such a cause. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-elsinora" xml:id="ep000471-e129810">
            <speaker>Elsin. </speaker>
            <l>It's you that are mistaken: I confesse. </l>
            <l>I was at first an opposit in your love </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-039-b"/>
            <l>Vnto the King: but, seeing you would needs </l>
            <l>Yeeld (then) your virgin Forte unto his Hignesse: </l>
            <l>I now wo'd have you take what wives doe use; </l>
            <l>And let me still live chaste, that doe professe it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e129880">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>My Aunt sayes more (to me I am sure she did:) </l>
            <l>All ought to live according their vocation. </l>
            <l>And not preposterously prove aliens to it. </l>
            <l>Nor will it serve to say he tore the bond, </l>
            <l>Now that he's sorry for't: For, still the generall good </l>
            <l>Must be preferr'd to all particular </l>
            <l>Merit; or that devotion that may </l>
            <l>By foolish zeale, prove a too great offence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-landgartha" xml:id="ep000471-e129970">
            <speaker>Land. </speaker>
            <l>I must heare more opinions, ere I part </l>
            <l>From my strong purpose: therefore sir, adieu. </l>
            <l>Be mercifull in chiefe, unto your subjects; </l>
            <l>To allure their hearts, by love: that being the tye </l>
            <l>That will hold strongest; never can be broken, </l>
            <l>Vnlesse by fooles, or mad men. For, that partie </l>
            <l>That sho'd tend any mischiefe, 'gainst a good Prince: </l>
            <l>Were first to kill all his subjects, being the Kings friends; </l>
            <l>Or perish himselfe, by his fatall and bad </l>
            <l>Purpose. Be just and vertuous, and you neede not </l>
            <l>Feare poyson, poynards, or conspiracie. </l>
            <l>To end: Norway shall be preserv'd for your young sonne; </l>
            <l>And as for me (though yours:) I'll end my life, </l>
            <l>An honest widdow, or forsaken wife: <stage xml:id="ep000471-e130120">Exit with Elsinora, Fatyma, &amp; Marfisa </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-valdemar" xml:id="ep000471-e130130">
            <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
            <l>I must take leave too. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e130150">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Farewell, worthiest Cousin. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-scania" xml:id="ep000471-e130170">
            <speaker>Scan. </speaker>
            <l>You know the way to Norway, Sir, and if </l>
            <l>I might advise so wise a King to follow </l>
            <l>Us thither, and not slowly: that honourable </l>
            <l>Obligation would so bind your Queene </l>
            <l>(Being seconded by us your friends, and reason) </l>
            <l>That I beleeve what now she does denie, </l>
            <l>She wo'd then grant; especially, when she </l>
            <l>Perceives you constant in your vow'd affection: </l>
            <l>For this perchance she do's to tempt and try you. </l>
            <l>Nay, I am sure she do's; and that she will be </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000471-040-a"/>
            <l>Yours againe, if you persever in your love to her, </l>
            <l>In the meane time, I shall not fayle to prove, </l>
            <l>Your grace's faithfull, loving advocate. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e130310">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>In you the anchor of my trust lyes only fix'd, </l>
            <l>Deare sister. I must follow your advise. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e130340">kisses her. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000471-e130350">Exit Scania &amp; Valdemar. </stage>
          <sp who="A30315-radgee" xml:id="ep000471-e130360">
            <speaker>Rad. </speaker>
            <l>O brother, brother: must we part at last? <stage xml:id="ep000471-e130380">They imbrace. Exeunt Cow. &amp; Radgee. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-cowsell" xml:id="ep000471-e130390">
            <speaker>Cow. </speaker>
            <l>No, no: get afore; I'll steale along with you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e130410">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Inguar, Did'st thinke our hopes sho'd end in this? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-inguar" xml:id="ep000471-e130430">
            <speaker>Ing. </speaker>
            <l>It may prove better; and I hope it will sit. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-reyner" xml:id="ep000471-e130450">
            <speaker>Rey. </speaker>
            <l>Accursed Fate of man, of foolish man, </l>
            <l>That cannot prize a Iewell while he has it, </l>
            <l>Till it be lost, and then his griefe is vaine, </l>
            <l>Vaine and unprofitable, when no hope </l>
            <l>Is left to finde it, which I feare's my case; </l>
            <l>Our miserie the mirror's made, by which </l>
            <l>We onely see our faults, our dangerous wounds. </l>
            <l>Which likely then can never be recur'd: </l>
            <l>Being Gangreene filthy sores, that doe Corrode </l>
            <l>So farre into the very soule of man, </l>
            <l>That they hale to sad desperation. </l>
            <l>To which point I'm almost arriv'd, the Gemme </l>
            <l>I lost, being so rich, as all earths Potentates </l>
            <l>A richer could not boast. Which if I finde not </l>
            <l>(Strucke with my dyre misfortune) my owne hand </l>
            <l>Shall send my spirit to the Stygian strand. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e130620">Exit with Ing. &amp; Hub. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A30315-uraca" xml:id="ep000471-e130630">
            <speaker>Vrac. </speaker>
            <l>And seeing I've walk'd astray, I will from hence: </l>
            <l>By future good to expiate my offence. <stage xml:id="ep000471-e130660">Exit in the middle. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
      <div type="epilogue" xml:id="ep000471-e130680">
        <pb xml:id="ep000471-040-b"/>
        <head>EPILOGVE. </head>
        <head type="sub">Scania (that spoke the Prologue) now delivers the Epilogue, apparelled as in the last Scene, with her Sword and Belt in her hand. </head>
        <l>THough our Author cares not, how his Play may take: </l>
        <l>Yet, cause he purposes not to forsake </l>
        <l>In his affection, any Worthy here; </l>
        <l>He hath sent me 'fore the Court breake up, to appeare </l>
        <l>For him agen; to see how it hath pleas'd: </l>
        <l>For, notwithstanding he meanes to be eas'd; </l>
        <l>For ever of th' like taske: Yet, from his heart </l>
        <l>He wishes, you and he sho'd fairely part. </l>
        <l>And this he more (for him) desir'd me say: </l>
        <l>Where others spend a yeare about a Play </l>
        <l>(Picking a sentence here, a word from thence) </l>
        <l>This Tragie-Comedy with the expence </l>
        <l>Of lesse then two Moneths time he pen'd: For he </l>
        <l>'s not too ambitious of the dignitie </l>
        <l>Of a prime Poet; which he needs must know, </l>
        <l>The Muses chiefe (Apollo) doth bestow </l>
        <l>But very rarely. Himselfe he knowes too </l>
        <l>Better i' th' Art, then some that to be so </l>
        <l>Thought worthy, maligne him. If this please you, </l>
        <l>It's all he'll aske of Hellicon: Adieu. </l>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="supplied_by_editor">
        <head>Notes, typically marginal, from the original text</head>
        <div corresp="A30315-e101650" xml:id="ep000471-e101650-n">
          <head>Notes for div A30315-e101650</head>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="author_s_note" xml:id="ep000471-e130900">
        <pb xml:id="ep000471-041-a"/>
        <p>Some (but not of best judgements) were offended at the Conclusion of this Play, in regard Landgartha tooke not then, what she was perswaded to by so many, the Kings kind night-imbraces. To which kind of people (that know not what they say) I answer (omitting all other reasons:) that a Tragie-Comedy sho'd neither end Comically or Tragically, but betwixt both: which Decorum I did my best to observe, not to goe against Art, to please the over-amorous. To the rest of bablers, I despise any answer. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="license" xml:id="ep000471-e130920">
        <p>This Play was first Acted on S. Patricks day, 1639. with the allowance of the Master of Revels. </p>
        <pb xml:id="ep000471-041-b"/>
      </div>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist">
        <head>Machine-generated castlist</head>
        <list n="164-A30315">
          <item n="107">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-reyner</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">107</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="61">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-landgartha</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">61</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="47">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-valdemar</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">47</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="46">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-hubba</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">46</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="44">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-cowsell</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">44</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="30">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-inguar</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">30</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="28">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-frederick</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">28</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="27">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-radgee</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">27</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="27">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-scania</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">27</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="17">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-harrold</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">17</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="16">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-marfisa</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">16</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="15">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-elsinora</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">15</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="13">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-eric</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">13</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="10">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-fatyma</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">10</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="9">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-frollo</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="5">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-phoebus</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="5">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-hasmond</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="4">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-uraca</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="4">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-wermond</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="4">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-gotax</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="3">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-rolfo</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="3">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-unassigned</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="3">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-servant</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="2">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-gentleman</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="2">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-lothaire</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="2">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-pryam</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="1">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-scout</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="1">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-angel</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="1">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-yyyy_2</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="1">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-lady</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="1">
            <seg type="character_name">A30315-yyyy_1</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
          </item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-digit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber. A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a keyword in context.</p>
        <note target="A30315-003-b-0070">
          <label>c4ato-003-b-0070</label>
          <sic>MƲltiplici</sic>
          <seg/>
          <corr>MUltiplici</corr>
          <seg>ratione , sator , mea carmina ( quamvis</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-003-b-0080">
          <label>c4ato-003-b-0080</label>
          <sic>rations</sic>
          <seg>MUltiplici</seg>
          <corr>ratione</corr>
          <seg>, sator , mea carmina ( quamvis Non limata</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-003-b-1260">
          <label>c4ato-003-b-1260</label>
          <sic>Histori●normam</sic>
          <seg>probo delicias : quod te fecisse sequntum</seg>
          <corr>Historia</corr>
          <seg>; belle , sciteque jocantem Latificando</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-003-b-1330">
          <label>c4ato-003-b-1330</label>
          <sic>alie●</sic>
          <seg>Historia ; belle , sciteque jocantem Latificando</seg>
          <corr>alios</corr>
          <seg>, non te , mens certa revolvit .</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-004-a-0820">
          <label>c4ato-004-a-0820</label>
          <sic>soppery</sic>
          <seg>non-sence , and Canarian rage ; Or Garagantuan</seg>
          <corr>foppery</corr>
          <seg>. Not one word That's immateriall do'st</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-004-b-0960">
          <label>c4ato-004-b-0960</label>
          <sic>uil</sic>
          <seg>Pande nihil mancum : nil non laudabile :</seg>
          <corr>nil</corr>
          <seg>, quod Sympathicum non est , symmetriaeque</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-005-a-1880">
          <label>c4ato-005-a-1880</label>
          <sic>you ' d</sic>
          <seg>his minde He had sought by it to content ,</seg>
          <corr>you'd</corr>
          <seg>finde Another method in't ; and not a word</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-005-b-1550">
          <label>c4ato-005-b-1550</label>
          <sic>hesho'd</sic>
          <seg>Is't possible ,</seg>
          <corr>he sho'd</corr>
          <seg>be so secure , And passe away in such</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-006-a-2850">
          <label>c4ato-006-a-2850</label>
          <sic>she●ll</sic>
          <seg>I rather thinke ,</seg>
          <corr>she'll</corr>
          <seg>to the mad Langartha ; And there make one</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-007-a-1120">
          <label>c4ato-007-a-1120</label>
          <sic>Swed●</sic>
          <seg>your souldiers , sir ; and killing All the</seg>
          <corr>Swedes</corr>
          <seg>they light vpon , they likewise threaten</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-009-b-2070">
          <label>c4ato-009-b-2070</label>
          <sic>thou ' lt</sic>
          <seg>kind And gentle unto thee , sweet-heart : if</seg>
          <corr>thou'lt</corr>
          <seg>But yeeld —</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-016-b-1640">
          <label>c4ato-016-b-1640</label>
          <sic>I 'll</sic>
          <seg>is . He's worse Then horne-mad already ;</seg>
          <corr>I'll</corr>
          <seg>therefore after him , And what betwixt lyes</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-017-a-0960">
          <label>c4ato-017-a-0960</label>
          <sic>thosse</sic>
          <seg>, you ' ill finde Your selfe mistaken in</seg>
          <corr>those</corr>
          <seg>vertuous Ladies .</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-017-a-2640">
          <label>c4ato-017-a-2640</label>
          <sic>dispos ' itd</sic>
          <seg>You are merrily</seg>
          <corr>dispos'd</corr>
          <seg>it seemes , sir , Which ( to be plaine )</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-017-a-2650">
          <label>c4ato-017-a-2650</label>
          <sic>itd</sic>
          <seg>You are merrily dispos'd</seg>
          <corr>it</corr>
          <seg>seemes , sir , Which ( to be plaine ) becomes</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-018-b-0800">
          <label>c4ato-018-b-0800</label>
          <sic>grac's</sic>
          <seg>your summons : Yet , our affection to your</seg>
          <corr>grace's</corr>
          <seg>welfare , And to that depends of it ( the</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-018-b-3010">
          <label>c4ato-018-b-3010</label>
          <sic>founds</sic>
          <seg>Her voyce</seg>
          <corr>sounds</corr>
          <seg>sweeter , then the celestiall spheres ,</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-020-b-0590">
          <label>c4ato-020-b-0590</label>
          <sic>I 'll</sic>
          <seg>upon me . See , I can stand up : Nay , goe ;</seg>
          <corr>I'll</corr>
          <seg>throw my Cap off too . Some of you Give</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-020-b-1320">
          <label>c4ato-020-b-1320</label>
          <sic>I 'll</sic>
          <seg>We shall soone be Man and Wife . To morrow</seg>
          <corr>I'll</corr>
          <seg>wayte on you further , into the Garden .</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-020-b-2570">
          <label>c4ato-020-b-2570</label>
          <sic>pleas●d</sic>
          <seg>I hope , great Sir , You will be</seg>
          <corr>pleased</corr>
          <seg>to entertayne farre better thoughts Of your</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-023-a-2600">
          <label>c4ato-023-a-2600</label>
          <sic>Gowue</sic>
          <seg>place , where I may Unspurre , untucke my</seg>
          <corr>Gowne</corr>
          <seg>, wash , and so forth —</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-024-a-2800">
          <label>c4ato-024-a-2800</label>
          <sic>▪</sic>
          <seg>be resisted . Get you away from hence then</seg>
          <corr>,</corr>
          <seg>and in stead Of frisk , in these pleasant</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-024-b-0930">
          <label>c4ato-024-b-0930</label>
          <sic>st●ffe</sic>
          <seg>glad 't were worse . We despise affected</seg>
          <corr>stuffe</corr>
          <seg>; Or astrayn'd kind of Eloquence ; being</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-024-b-1510">
          <label>c4ato-024-b-1510</label>
          <sic>▪</sic>
          <seg>Musicke , or at most to a single Violine</seg>
          <corr>:</corr>
          <seg>at the end of which enter Phoebus with Bow</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-025-a-2110">
          <label>c4ato-025-a-2110</label>
          <sic>predestinat</sic>
          <seg>minde ) to what They in their Counsels doe</seg>
          <corr>predestinate</corr>
          <seg>.</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-025-a-2190">
          <label>c4ato-025-a-2190</label>
          <sic>I 'll</sic>
          <seg>Heavens brightest eye ,</seg>
          <corr>I'll</corr>
          <seg>doe what lyes in me , To obey thy will ,</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-026-a-1940">
          <label>c4ato-026-a-1940</label>
          <sic>amb●</sic>
          <seg>Exeunt</seg>
          <corr>ambo</corr>
          <seg>.</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-026-b-2580">
          <label>c4ato-026-b-2580</label>
          <sic>Jnguar</sic>
          <seg>Is</seg>
          <corr>Inguar</corr>
          <seg>yet return'd from th' Fleet ?</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-027-a-1770">
          <label>c4ato-027-a-1770</label>
          <sic>I 'll</sic>
          <seg>who like an Asse Still dotes on his wife ,</seg>
          <corr>I'll</corr>
          <seg>not therefore trust him .</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-027-a-3370">
          <label>c4ato-027-a-3370</label>
          <sic>a sliam'd</sic>
          <seg>take notice of : though she , Poore Lady , (</seg>
          <corr>asham'd</corr>
          <seg>to be deceiv'd or scorn'd ) Say</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-027-b-1610">
          <label>c4ato-027-b-1610</label>
          <sic>dog-shead</sic>
          <seg>That Christian</seg>
          <corr>dogshead</corr>
          <seg>and yours too , had beene chopt off ere</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-028-b-0340">
          <label>c4ato-028-b-0340</label>
          <sic>Daues</sic>
          <seg>And we to you brother , and to all the</seg>
          <corr>Danes</corr>
          <seg>. You came not to pray on's , but to deliver</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-028-b-2370">
          <label>c4ato-028-b-2370</label>
          <sic>I 'll</sic>
          <seg>Love sir , you shall : What ? Doe you thinke</seg>
          <corr>I'll</corr>
          <seg>use you like a stranger ?</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-031-a-0370">
          <label>c4ato-031-a-0370</label>
          <sic>cre</sic>
          <seg>best horses ) post away ; And be ( I hope )</seg>
          <corr>ere</corr>
          <seg>we be miss'd , pass'd danger . Come , let</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A30315-031-b-1600">
          <label>c4ato-031-b-1600</label>
          <sic>I ' d</sic>
          <seg>him ) disgrac'd me by his flight ; and as</seg>
          <corr>I'd</corr>
          <seg>us'd false play with others : yet , my love</seg>
        </note>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
