<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000573" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Pluto furens &amp; vinctus, or, The raging devil bound a modern farse / Per Philocomicum.</title>
        <author>
<!--Carr, William-->
          <persName>
            <forename>William</forename>
            <surname>Carr</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A40946.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <p>
            This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is available for reuse, according to the terms of
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>
            . The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
          </p>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull>
              <titleStmt>
                <title>Pluto furens &amp; vinctus, or, The raging devil bound a modern farse / Per Philocomicum.</title>
                <author>Carr, William.</author>
                <author>Fitton, Alexander, Sir, d. 1699.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[22], 44, [2] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>in usum theatri amstelredemensis,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Amstelodami [i.e. Londini?] :</pubPlace>
                <date>1669.</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>Imprint probably false.</note>
                <note>Epistle dedicatory signed: C.F.</note>
                <note>Perhaps written with assistance of Sir Alexander Fitton; for discussion of authorship, see H.G. Platt in Modern language notes, XLV (1930), p. 507-510.</note>
                <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                <note>A satire on Charles Gerard.</note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000573-e10">
        <pb xml:id="ep000573-001-a"/>
        <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000573-001-b"/>
        <p>PLUTO <foreign xml:lang="lat">Furens &amp; Vinctus</foreign>; OR, The Raging Devil BOUND. </p>
        <p>A Modern Farse. </p>
        <p>Per Philocomicum. First Edition. </p>
        <q>Is legibus nocens, &amp; falsi damnatus, inter alia belli mala ordinem Senatorium recipe raverat— Serendae invidiae in alios artifex discordiis, &amp; seditionibus potens, raptor largitor, pace pessimus, bell● non spernendus <bibl>C. Tac. </bibl>
        </q>
        <p>AMSTELODAMI; In usum Theatri Amstelredemensis, 1669. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000573-e90">
        <pb xml:id="ep000573-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000573-002-b"/>
        <head>To Sir <hi>John James</hi>, Sir <hi>Will. Greene</hi>, Sir <hi>Sam. Starlyn</hi>, Sir <hi>John Forth </hi>Sheriff of London; <hi>John Breden, John Bucknall</hi>, Aldermen; <hi>Emery Hill</hi>, Esq; with the rest of the Worshipful Corporation of Brewers. </head>
        <p>HAaving lately an Occasion that called me into the Country about a small Affair, relating to a Member of your Company, I there accidentally had an opportunity to behold the Great Houses of Charity belonging to your Corporation; amongst the rest, I visited two Almes-Houses, and two Schools, in which Schools I found many expert <pb xml:id="ep000573-003-a"/>and witty Boyes, and very oppertunely came to be a Spectator of a Play Acted by the Boyes of one of the Schools, which was performed beyond belief, for such Actors whose business is not Playes; and then beholding the good Order and Method of the Government of the Schoole and Almes-Houses, and the decent provision for the Poor; and then reflected back, and beheld the Sterne that guided them, (which are you Worthy Gentl men) and there I found not onely your Care to preserve the Ancient and Noble Acts of Charity of your Predecessors, even in the worst of Times, but observed your great Industry, Wisdom, and Discretion in making Additions daily for the relief of your Poor, and adding greater strength to your Corporation, as you lately have done by renewing your Charter; nor are you onely prudent amongst your selves, but are thought <pb xml:id="ep000573-003-b"/>fit Ministers to be intrusted by State of a great Branch of his Majesties Revenue, which is so discreetly managed, that your Burden is thought light, to former Vndertakers; and that Clamour hath seased, which was wont to be heard in the Streets. And such is your Loyalty, that in great straits, who more ready are to advance Money from your thriving Banks; neither can I forget your former Activeness to advance the Kings Restauration, when by your Politick and hazardous Vndertaking, you stopt all the Excise Duty, which was the ruine both of <hi>Lambert, Army</hi>, and <hi>Committee of Safety</hi>, which purchased a Prison to some of you, and others great trouble; but I fear I am to blame to undertake to sifter out your Worth, and therefore onely beg the favour, that your Boyes may accept my Piece of Play, which is the first that ere I writ, <pb xml:id="ep000573-004-a"/>and being near Christmas Holidaies, I hope their Master will give them leave to Act it; until my other Play be finished, which is now on the Stocks, and will be quickly Printed, until then I take my leave, and subscribe my self, </p>
        <closer>
          <signed>Your Old Servant, C. F. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="authors_note" xml:id="ep000573-e250">
        <pb xml:id="ep000573-004-b"/>
        <head>TO THE READER. </head>
        <p>IT hath always been observed, that the Maxims of Reason are in themselves coherent; and that the Methods of Fortune in her several progresses, have been as varying as the vicissitudes of humane Affairs in themselves; from whence we may conclude <seg xml:lang="unk">〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 </seg>ill Fortune (taking her still as a Goddess) never crushed any man whom <seg xml:lang="unk">〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 </seg>the good Goddess had not first deceived: I therefore advise thee (my Friend) never to give a credit to those smiles which are primarily deceitful; for, although they pretend friendship and peace, yet whatever proceeds thence, are but temporary advantages, that with Proteus, change face every <pb xml:id="ep000573-005-a"/>minute: but if thou canst so place them, as to be willing upon demand to surrender the same without troubling thy quiet, or otherwise to keep such a distance between her and thy self, that thou canst answer all perversnesses with an <hi>Omnia mea mecum porto</hi>; then thou wilt at least seem <hi>plusquam victor</hi>, more then a Conquerer. He knows not his own strength who never tried it; Adversity brings us into the Ring to wrestle, and makes us, in defence of our Reputation, shew all we can: And if our endeavours prove too weak, Hercules will help, Heaven prepares good men with Crosses which are <foreign xml:lang="lat">mala per accidens</foreign>, but <foreign xml:lang="lat">malum in se</foreign>, evil quatenus evil never happened to a good man. Contraries can never be reconciled, yet lose of their strictness by variety of tempers, for what happens to one, may chance to another, and it is as well in his humour as Reason, what he accounts it, and will make it. </p>
        <p>That there is an indispensable Fate that hurries every man to his end, even beyond his own intention; there is uncertainty in Wisdom as well as Folly, for all is Vanity. When a man deviseth by policy to save himself, that very policy leads him to ruine. Decrees are past upon us, and our own wit often hunts us into the <pb xml:id="ep000573-005-b"/>snares that we would above all things avoid: what we suspect and would fly, that we cannot: what now is an Asylum, proves anon a Prison: we design that for a means of our preservation, which proves our destruction; and what we thought our greatest disadvantage, proves our safety: So that man is the Tenice-ball of Time, sometimes taken from the Plough, to the Throne; and thence again, on a sudden, dejected to the Prison and a Halter, as if there were such an Aequilibrium between Felicity and Misery, that no man could avoid being wretched or happy, or both. But not admitting that, yet supposing our selves possessed of Fortunatus his Cap, whereby we might enjoy the ful accomplishment of our desires, who would be more miserable then he that should cull out his own wayes? What a specious shew carried Mydas his wish with it, and how it paid him at last with ruine? Though God in the Creation of man called a Council Faciamus, yet ever since in all things he will work alone, and man must not be of his Council. I have within the small compass of my few years seen matters so unexpectedly fall out, that they have tutored me in all Affairs, neither to despair, nor presume. </p>
        <pb xml:id="ep000573-006-a"/>
        <p>It is said of Martius, That one day made him Emperour, the second saw him Rule, and the third shewed him Slain by his Souldiers: see here the slippery estate of even the greatest persons; however, I will not despair, because I have a God; nor dare I presume, because I am but a man. Take Seneca's counsel. </p>
        <q>
          <lg>
            <l>Nemo confidat nimium secundis </l>
            <l>Nemo desperet, meliora lapsus, </l>
            <l>Miscet hae illis prohibetque Clothe </l>
            <l>Stare Fortunum. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Let none fall in despair to rise, </l>
            <l>Nor trust too great Prosperities; </l>
            <l>Clotho so mingling both commands, </l>
            <l>That neither stands. </l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>Therefore, my old Friend, when I pondered your other days discourse, wherein you blamed my miscarriages and misfortunes, reflecting upon my imprisonment and necessities, despising poverty, and a mean estate; I looking upon your famous Buildings, and great undertakings in the World, I cast my eye backwards to former Ages, and there beheld with pity and admiration those stupendious Mausoleums the <pb xml:id="ep000573-006-b"/>Heroes of that time built for the honour of their Names, and eaten up by the steely Teeth of Time, or else rest but as Monuments of their Pride and Luxury. What is become of Caligula's Bridge over the Bajae, or the Bituminated Wall of Babylon? No Fortifications can hold against the cruel devastations of Time: Who would have thought, that when Scanderbeg was laid in his Tomb, the Turks should afterwards rifle it, and wear his Bones as precious Relicks, or Jewels to support their Valour? We are so far from leaving any thing certain to Posterity, that we are not sure to enjoy what we have while we live. Nay, sometimes we live to see greater changes in our own time, then we could ever imagine to happen to our Off-spring for the future, according to that of the Poet. </p>
        <q>
          <l>Who hath not heard of Croesus heaps of Gold, </l>
          <l>Yet knows his Foe did him a Pris'ner hold? </l>
          <l>He that once awed Sycilia's proud extent, </l>
          <l>By a poor Art could Famine scarce prevent? </l>
        </q>
        <p>Have you not seen strange things happen of late years? who durst within less then a Lustrum <pb xml:id="ep000573-007-a"/>have told the late Lord Chancellor, that he should be forced to abscond himself from the peoples rage? or that Brunkard should have fled for so heinous miscarriages? Were they not both great and shining, not to say Stars, but Meteors? Who, till of late, durst have walked the Exchange, and reported, that the three Brothers B—'s would be Prisoners in the Kings Bench, with many other Aldermen, some of them England's Croessusses, as they were thought, for their great Wealth? Who would have thought such a destroying Plague, mischievous War, and calcining Fire, should not have awakened our sinful Nation? but all these have prevailed nothing. </p>
        <p>To begin therefore a Reformation, let us (my Dear Friend) advance it in our selves, and so <foreign xml:lang="lat">ex particularibus generalia</foreign>, by uniting Particulars we shall make it General. For my own part, I am resolved by the assistance from above, to preferre honest Adversity, before undue Prosperity. Although <foreign xml:lang="lat">Prosperum &amp; foelix nefas virtus vocatur, &amp; Probitas laudatur &amp; alget, </foreign>however the titulary honour of Prosperous Villany hath not prevailed against the withering Laurel of Praised Honesty; for from hence it comes to pass, that wise men chose goodness, <pb xml:id="ep000573-007-b"/>and Vertue attended with Affliction, and the burthens of unpleasing Accidents, rather then Vice waited on, and garlanded with all the soft demulsions of a present contentment. Hereof might be produced many Examples, one only I will name, which is of Socrates, who being committed to custody by Publick Authority (though unjustly) would neither attempt to break Prison, nor offer any violence, or indignity to Justice, to purchase his Life or Liberty. The rules of Vertue are not perfectly to be learned without a severe Tutor: The Rod of Discipline, and the Fire of Affliction can onely scour us from our dross, and burn off all our rust; and hereby the faithful learn all those other excellent perfections, accompanied with other glorious Graces. </p>
        <p>I confess this, <hi>rara avis</hi>, a great novelty to see a Rich or Potent man Religious, for Religion (<hi>a religando</hi>) binds up, and restrains, whereas Riches tempt and prompt to licentious Libertinism. Our Saviours Parable of a Camel passing a Needles Eye, was <foreign xml:lang="lat">durus sermo</foreign>, but himself explained the Text. When wealth abounds, men seldom come by sufferings to be sober; they buy out their penance, and <pb xml:id="ep000573-008-a"/>cast over-board those Considerations that should make them serious. They are so swelled by the slavish humorings of their Attendants, and so elated by the crouchings of all about them, that inveloped with sensuality, they not only miss of knowing themselves, but others; and by the pravity of their weak Nature, are so set on the solaces of this life, that they seldome have time to think of another, or better. There is most commonly a Worm in the fairest Fruit, which makes it decay. The best inclinations of humane Nature are vitiated by Pride, which sooner seiseth the Peacock with his beautiful Traine, then the lean bald-Coot. Old Jacob begged but only Food and Rayment, and Agar prayeth directly against Plenty; and though Solomon was so wise as not to ask it, yet we see, when he had it, it had well-nigh eaten out all his wisdom. But, there is one thing in wealth which fascinates beyond all these, in that it is apt to seduce a man into a <seg xml:lang="unk">〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>, a love of himself, and a self-conceit of his wisdom; whence haply it might be, that when Simonides was asked which was best for man, Wealth or Wisdom, he made a scruple, as doubting what answer to give; and the reason was, as he said, <hi>That he had often observed wise men wait <pb xml:id="ep000573-008-b"/>and attend at the houses of rich men: </hi>but alas, if waiting in this age were all, it would be excusable; but the pride of our Great Ones is so exorbitant, that after a tedious attendance, at last comes an answer indeed, but so ful of disdain and tyranny, that would affright the hearer. And this might be the cause of what one said, <hi>That a rich Tyrant is the worst of all wild Beasts; and a rich Christian, one of Christs Wonders. Nihil honestius, </hi>saith <foreign xml:lang="lat">Seneca, magnificentiusque quam pecunias contemnere si non habeas, ad beneficentiam libertatemque conferre</foreign>; If we have not wealth, 'tis Noble and Princely not to be fond after it; but far more Heroick, if we have it, to sow it into Charity and Benificence: but, whether so or no, 'tis the custom of the World, to magnifie the wealthy man, though of never so mean parts; whereas poverty must be despised, though attended with never so many vertuous Qualities; so that to be Rich, is to be three parts of the way onward to perfection, while Poverty is a pavement for the high-minded man to tread on: Gold is the only Cover-led of Imperfections, is Follies Curtain to hide all defects from the World. VVe in these Times differ from the Ancient Heathen, they <pb xml:id="ep000573-009-a"/>made Jupiter their chief Deity, but we have crowned Pluto, on whom wait the mellisonant Muses, and worthy Graces for hire; Mercury is his Messenger; Mars musters under his Banner for pay; Venus becomes his Prostitute; and Cupid himself, that blind, but powerful Numen, yet can do no feats, but with his Golden-headed Arrow. 'Tis Money makes a Gentleman, an Alderman, or Poet Laureat, as may be read in witty Sir <hi>John Sucklin </hi>his Session of the Poets; as also excellently well described by Petronius. </p>
        <q>
          <l>The money'd man can safely sail all Seas, </l>
          <l>And make his Fortune as himself shall please; </l>
          <l>He can wed Danae, and command that now </l>
          <l>Acrisius self that fatal match allow; </l>
          <l>He can declaim, chide, censure, Verses write, </l>
          <l>And do all things better than Cato might; </l>
          <l>He knows the Law, and rules it; hath, and is </l>
          <l>Whole Servius, and what Labeo would possess: </l>
          <l>In brief, Let rich men wish, what ere they love </l>
          <l>Will come: they in a lock't Chest keep a Jove. </l>
        </q>
        <p>Now is the time whereof Diogenes foretold, when he gave a reason why he would be buried groveling, We have made the Earths bottom powerful to the lofty skie, <pb xml:id="ep000573-009-b"/>Gold that lay buried in the lowest parts, is now made the head of all our enterprises; yet after all, I for my own part look upon wealth without worth, but as a rich saddle upon an Asses back. </p>
        <p>As to my Restraint, which is another Joynt whereon you insisted, I am almost of Cicero's opinion, <foreign xml:lang="lat">Non nobis solum, sed ad decus &amp; libertatem nati sumus. </foreign>The greatest Prince that ever was produced by Woman, comes into the World insanguined, and is a poor resistless Slave to the first Arms he falls into. Imprisonment is not such a mischief as the World ignorantly reputes it: the greatest of it is, in that the Eye is debarred from the delight of the Worlds variety; yet is not this total, but in part and local only; for to a good man, a prison is no more then a place of retiring and sequestration from the world, which many both of the wisest and greatest have voluntarily taken upon themselves, witness, <hi>Demosthenes, Dioclesian, Charles </hi>the Fifth, &amp;c. besides many other, whose Examples would be without number. Now, although by this kind of pleading, we alleviate the cruelty of Fate, yet Nature pleads for Liberty; and though Command may be easie, yet sometimes <pb xml:id="ep000573-010-a"/>they grate and gall; yet still if we appeal to the mind of man, it will affirm, That it is better being a King, though in a Tub, then to be a Slave in a Palace roofed with Gold. If then I have Liberty (which is so generally esteemed) I will rest in the Priviledges that accrue by it: And if I want it, yet will I satisfie my self with the benefits that attend that want, so that in either estate, I will make Content my fellow. </p>
        <p>Dear Friend, give me leave to hope for this Liberty, although haply, you will say, hope many times falls short, and therein proves a mans greatest Enemy, according to that of the Wise Man, Hope deferred maketh the heart sick; yet is it not to be denied, that this very Hope is the miserable and afflicted mars chiefest refuge and shelter, which doth in the hardest gripe of Calamity never faile to yield him beams of Comfort. How many had sunk and perished under the pressure of their troubles, had not Hope sustained them? Nay, who surrounded with Calamities would not despair, if smiling Hope did not chear him with expectation of deliverance. To this purpose is an ingenious Epigram of Tibullus. </p>
        <q>
          <pb xml:id="ep000573-010-b"/>
          <l>Hope Flatters life, and sayes shee'l stil bequeath </l>
          <l>Better, else I had cur'd all ills by death; </l>
          <l>Through this the Farmer doth his Grain commit </l>
          <l>To earth, which with large use replentieth it. </l>
          <l>The Snares, the Birds, and Fishes as they glide, </l>
          <l>Catch at smal hooks, that cozening baits do hide. </l>
          <l>Hope cheers the shackled Pris'ner, who while's thigh </l>
          <l>Rings with his Chain, yet works and sings on high. </l>
        </q>
        <p>Sir, I will end this Discourse; only first, I must put you in remembrance of your unkindness of upbraiding me of your Favours done to me since my Troubles; If Love (as the word of Truth affirms) will cover a multitude of Sins; Friendship, which is the perfect growth of Love, ought, without peradventure much more to hide infirmities. Whoever doeth a Courtesie to another, and after upbraids him with it, expecting a return, is certainly kind only to himself: who looks for a requital, serves himself, not me: If he often recount the Favours he hath done me, thereby he cancels the debt I owed him, files off the chains that kept me his Prisoner, and with his Tongue unlooseth the fetters his hands had put on If I be able to do a courtesie, I rebate it by repeating, and blot it out when I go about to Text it; and the Receiver <pb xml:id="ep000573-011-a"/>becomes unworthy of it, if he forget it. It was thus long since declared by the sententious <foreign xml:lang="lat">Seneca, Beneficii inter duos lex est, alter statim oblivisci debet dati, alter accepti nunquam; Qui dedit beneficium taceat, narret qui accepit</foreign>; Between two Friends it is the Law of Kindness, That he that doth it forgets it presently; but, he that doth receive it, never: Let him that bestows it, be silent; but, let him that takes it, speak thereof: He that blows a Trumpet at his Alms-giving is a Pharisee in Friendship, and intitleth himself to the check which Martial bestowes on talking Posthumus, (wherewith I will conclude) </p>
        <l>What, Posthumus, thou hast done, I'le nere forget, </l>
        <l>Why should I smother't, when thou trumpetst it? </l>
        <l>When I to any do thy gifts relate, </l>
        <l>He presently replyes, I heard Him say't; </l>
        <l>Some things become not two, here one may serve; </l>
        <l>If I must tell, do thou thy self reserve. </l>
        <l>Believe me, Posthume, though thy gifts be vast, </l>
        <l>They perish, when the Authors Tongue runs wast. </l>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="ep000573-e1540">
        <pb xml:id="ep000573-011-b"/>
        <head>Drammatis Personae. </head>
        <list>
          <item>PLuto. </item>
          <item>Proserpine. </item>
          <item>Sir Edward Lack-Latine. </item>
          <item>Size Ace. </item>
          <item>Pitt-fall. </item>
          <item>Instrument. </item>
          <item>Shackels. </item>
          <item>Capt. Brandy. </item>
          <item>Cape. Bub. </item>
          <item>Want-Practise. </item>
          <item>Ordinary or Bishop. </item>
          <item>Intelligence. </item>
          <item>Tipstaff. </item>
          <item>Sir Foulmouth unlearned. </item>
          <item>Surribus. </item>
          <item>Capt. Honesty. </item>
          <item>Lieut. Well-meaning. </item>
          <item>Mr. Meerly-drawn-in. </item>
          <item>High Constable. </item>
          <item>Magna Charta. </item>
          <item>Mrs. Sorrow. </item>
          <item>Sir Empty-Scull <hi>Fore-man of the Jury. Juror. </hi>
          </item>
          <item>Capt. Bluster. Juror. </item>
          <item>Capt. Want-Credit. Juror. </item>
          <item>Col. Plunder. Juror. </item>
          <item>Capt. Tripan. Juror. </item>
          <item>Capt. Bulysany. Juror. </item>
          <item>Capt. Indigent. Juror. </item>
          <item>Capt. Kick-a-Tan. Juror. </item>
          <item>Capt. Priviledge. Juror. </item>
          <item>Capt. Spunge. Juror. </item>
          <item>Capt. Ignorance. Juror. </item>
          <item>Capt. Flutterer. Juror. </item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="prologue" xml:id="ep000573-e2250">
        <pb xml:id="ep000573-012-a"/>
        <head>Prologue. </head>
        <l>WHat need our Work <hi>a Prologue</hi>? shall it </l>
        <l>Be deck'd, when none knows what to call it? </l>
        <l>It is, you may be bold to say, </l>
        <l>No Tragy-Comedie, no Play; </l>
        <l>For none but Pluto's Courtiers are </l>
        <l>Vilians and Tripans Act it here: </l>
        <l>Nor yet a Farse you can it call, </l>
        <l>That hides, but this uncovers all; </l>
        <l>Cruel Lust the good man kills, </l>
        <l>Fraud the Court-Triumphant fills; </l>
        <l>And they hate even those they kiss; </l>
        <l>Good men ill rewarded is; </l>
        <l>And the Chaste are poor, while Vice </l>
        <l>Lords it by Adulteries: </l>
        <l>And when they have performed this Play, </l>
        <l>Our Poet will work the other day; </l>
        <l>And he'l once more betray their Guiles, </l>
        <l>And Counter-plot their chiefest Wiles. </l>
        <l>Yet, truly Friends, I've no intent </l>
        <l>Yet to be held a <hi>Fool in Print</hi>. </l>
      </div>
      <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="ep000573-e2600">
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000573-e2610">
          <pb n="1" xml:id="ep000573-012-b"/>
          <head>Actus I. Scen. I. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e2630">Enter Shackles, Cap. Brandy, and Cap. Bub. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e2670">
            <speaker>Shac. </speaker>
            <p>NOw you Rogues, here is like to be brave times, the Sword, the Sword; and Liberty. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e2700">
            <speaker>Bub. </speaker>
            <p>What Sword? what Liberty? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e2730">
            <speaker>Shac. </speaker>
            <p>Why Sirrah, to lie with thy Wife, or Brandy's Wife: here is my Commission, you sons of sinners; read, I am, in short, Marshal General by Commission from— </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e2770">
            <speaker>Bub. </speaker>
            <p>No body: Pox on't, Brandy le●'s be gone, this is a Brandynian lie or Commission; wee'l not venture hanging under such a preheminenc, Priviledge and Profit. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e2820">
            <speaker>Bran. </speaker>
            <p>If this be your great preferment, I have the same, it cost me Five Pounds when I first marched under Pluto; you told me there was a new Court to be erected, and that Coff, Philo's House should be plundred. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e2870">
            <speaker>Shac. </speaker>
            <p>Peace you thick scull'd slave, look who's there: even Pluto himself with his Privy Councel. <hi>Let us withdraw</hi>. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e2920">Exeunt. </stage>
          <pb n="2" xml:id="ep000573-013-a"/>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e2930">Enter Pluto, Sir Foulmouth unlearned, Lack-Latine, or Law-Practice, and Instrument. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e2990">
            <speaker>Pluto, </speaker>
            <p>By your favour, Sir Foulmouth, I am for your Westminster-Hall Dammee. Do you think that I will be a bubble to your hooks: my Sword ever hated a damned English Jury. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e3040">
            <speaker>Sir Foulmouth, </speaker>
            <p>Give me leave to give you your 200 l. and I am gone; I wish I could as well part with my Dub, as I can give you your 200 l. I would never be for you more: yet be rul'd, and I will put you in a kind of an Arbitrary way. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e3100">
            <speaker>Pluto, </speaker>
            <p>As much as you can: but give me my 200 l. again, then go drink all night, and the next morning forget 'tis a Hall-day, Lose your Clyents Cause, 'tis not the first time you took a Fee, when you did not understand your breviate. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e3150">
            <speaker>Sir Foulmouth. </speaker>
            <p>Then farewel Pluto. I believe you will find rhe bold Britain at Grays-Inn of my mind— <stage xml:id="ep000573-e3220">Exit. </stage>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e3230">
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>He is gone; and now he is gone, what is he but a blackmouthed bawling senseless fellow, one that can only throw dirt on an honest Witness without Cavere? Law he hath none: but why do I rage? I am resolved to take thy counsel, Dear Lack-Latine and Practice, and you Instrument will be a great advancer of our design, therefore let us go in and settle our Affairs. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e3300">Exeunt. </stage>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="ep000573-e3310">
          <pb n="3" xml:id="ep000573-013-b"/>
          <head>Scen. II. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e3330">Enter Sice-Ace, and Pitfal. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e3360">
            <speaker>Sice-Ace. </speaker>
            <p>Truly Sister Pitfal, I did not like Proserpines last nights discourse, I know her birth, she was Sweet-Scents daughter, and you were born in Cheshire out of Saltpeter, and my self of the old Charcole's Family in Staffordshire; and I pray mingle us together, and we are as good as Gun-powder, and have been as soon Fired and Blown up as her Highness was:— But I will no longer endure her French tricks: Do you mark how she cogs a Die? O she outstrips you far, Pitfal! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e3480">
            <speaker>Pitfal. </speaker>
            <p>And I always lose on Sice-Ace. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e3520">Exeunt. </stage>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="ep000573-e3530">
          <head>Scen. III. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e3550">Enter Cap. Bluster, Cap. Plunder, Cap. Ignorance, with the rest of the Jurors. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e3590">
            <speaker>Blust. </speaker>
            <p>What in his own name? I mean the Devils name, I must speak plain to you Cap. Ignorance; I say again, what? doth Pluto intend by our Summons to make us Jury-men? Be it, I am resolved to do nothing without a fat Buck out of <hi>Enfield Chace</hi>, and 20 pieces beside: Who do you think is like to be Foreman, marry, Sir <hi>Confident Empty-Scull</hi>, a meer plain Ale Rogue? O, I hate a Rogue that will be drunk with Ale; besides he can neither Write nor Read, neither has wit to know how to say agreed. But hold, here is <hi>Tipst aff </hi>coming, I think, look about you. We shall, I warrant you receive Orders from Pluto's Court. </p>
          </sp>
          <pb n="4" xml:id="ep000573-014-a"/>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e3680">Enter Tipstaff, with a Warrant, which he reads to them. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e3700">
            <speaker>Tip. </speaker>
            <p>
              <q>You Gentlemen Hecks of the Jury are to make your personal appearance to morrow at 8 a clock in the forenoon exactly at Pluto's Court; and I am to desire you, that you will neither drink, nor go to Sodom this night, because weighty affairs require your more than ordinary courage: and after your Verdict is delivered, you shall find Pluto's Cooks dressing you a good Dinner under the Sun next to <hi>Hell Gate</hi>. </q>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e3790">
            <speaker>Cap. Spunge. </speaker>
            <p>Well Tipstaff, is this all? what, nothing in hand? then I shall be sick in the morning: I would his Highness had sent Bub or Brandy, we might have held out with them 6 or 7 hours. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e3860">
            <speaker>Tipst. </speaker>
            <p>Farewel VVorthies of matter of Fact. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e3890">
            <speaker>Cap. Plunder. </speaker>
            <p>Well brother Jurors you remember eight a clock to morrow. Wee'l not be long upon the Evidence; for Pluto's Dinner may then be spoyl'd: me thinks I see Col. Judgement and Want-Credit, knuckle deep in Venison Pasties: in the interim lets loose no time: I am for the Sack shop: Farewel. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e3970">
            <speaker>Omnes. </speaker>
            <p>Farewel and be hang'd, that's twice God b'w'y ' </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e4000">Exeunt. </stage>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="ep000573-e4010">
          <head>Scen. IV. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e4030">Enter <hi>Pluto, Lack-Latine, Practice, Instrument, Shackles, Tipstaff, Bub, Brandy </hi>and Surribus. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e4060">
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>Let us sit down, and hear the Commission read. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e4090">
            <speaker>Instrument. </speaker>
            <p>Do you read it, and then my dear friends you will thereby understand what Officers and Instruments are designed for you. </p>
          </sp>
          <pb n="5" xml:id="ep000573-014-b"/>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e4120">Enter Proserpine. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e4140">
            <speaker>Proserp. </speaker>
            <p>What Treason's this black Council of the Deep? Do you intend without my knowledge here to settle your selves, and leave me out? am not I (as the Diverb says) the Grey Mare? what if I lost the other night 200 l. in Sice-Ace's company, which by the clack of Caerion Pitfall's everflitting tongue came to my Pluto's ears? did I abate ought of my grandeur, or let fall my Pride? And shall I now admit— </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e4220">
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>Patience Proserpine, if you'l a while withdraw, you shall find things done answerable to your mind, Side— </p>
            <p>But friends, are you willing that Proserpine shall be joyned with you in the Commission of Oyer and Terminer? she may do us good service, for she has a notable Head, though at Play her luck be naught, but that Peccadillo I have forgiven: speak Gentlemen, are you willing she shall be joyned? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e4320">
            <speaker>Latine for all. </speaker>
            <p>Yes so, if it please your Highness. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e4350">
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>Then interline her name, and let her sit as one of Us. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e4380">
            <speaker>Bishop. </speaker>
            <p>I first desire to be heard one word, that is, if her Highness offer to speak French, there are 2 or 3 damn'd English Jury-men that will be yery cross, and spoil the Verdict, your Highness therefore must engage her to leave off that while she sits in Court. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e4410">
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>Well moved, and like a Bishop or Ordinary. </p>
            <p>Call Proserpine in— You are welcom Madam, pray sit quiet till the Commission be read. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e4460">
            <speaker>Proserp. </speaker>
            <p>Tell not me of quiets, before I'le be oblig'd to that, I'le know how I stand in the Commission, or else you shall keep no quiet Sessions here: you know I made a disturbance at a greater meeting than this. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e4490">
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>Stop a Pin there. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e4520">
            <speaker>Proserp. </speaker>
            <p>What, because you and I were out of favour for it. But proceed to Read if you will. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e4550">
            <pb n="6" xml:id="ep000573-015-a"/>
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>You Rascal Cryer, must you be call'd on to do your duty. Make an <hi>O yes</hi>, and proclaim silence. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e4590">Silence being made, the Cryer reads the Commission, as follows. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e4600">
            <speaker>Cryer. </speaker>
            <p>
              <q>Pluto and Proserpine, Lord and Lady of the Deeds of the under world, &amp;c. send greeting: To our Right Trusty and well beloved Sir <hi>Edward Lack-Latine </hi>my Recorder, <hi>Post Practice </hi>my Solliciter General, <hi>Dick Instrument </hi>my Remembrancer, and to our Trusty Shackles our Jailor, Cap. Bub, and Cap. Brandy Setting-Dogs, and Turn keys to Shackles, with <hi>Tipstaff, Surribus, Want-Practice</hi>, &amp;c. Know Ye, That forasmuch as <hi>Truth, Virtue</hi>, and a <hi>Quiet Life </hi>is like to be promoted against the Interest of our selves by a damn'd Turk named Coffo-Philo. We of our Princely Grace and Favour do Authorise you to meet, whereof 3 of you to be a Quorum, and that you cause Jurors to come before you. to enquire the best way to destroy the growth of this <hi>Coffo Filo</hi>, for Reasons best known to our selves.— </q>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e4810">
            <speaker>Proserp. </speaker>
            <p>Read no further. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e4840">
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>Why? are you pleased Madam? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e4870">
            <speaker>Pros. </speaker>
            <p>No. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e4900">
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>What is the Reason? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e4930">
            <speaker>Pros. </speaker>
            <p>Because all our Titles are not in the Front of the Commission, as Captain General— </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e4960">
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>Prethee, Wife, Peace, that Title I dare not own. Mum for that—— But M. Recorder tell the Court your opinion, what is the best way to stifle this Heresie of <hi>Coffo Philo.</hi>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e5010">
            <speaker>Sir Edw. </speaker>
            <p>May it please your Highness, I desire to be truly informed whether you will take an Arbitrary way, or what way. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e5050">
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>Any way to do my business. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e5080">
            <speaker>S. Edw. </speaker>
            <p>Would your Highness have him so stopt, that he shall never appear. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e5120">
            <pb n="7" xml:id="ep000573-015-b"/>
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>Pish, I tell you S. Edward I would have him stock'd up by the Roots; for if any branches be left, they may first grow to overtop me, and then make me shorter by the Head. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e5160">
            <speaker>Pract. </speaker>
            <p>Let me advise your Highness to Indict him in 17 Indictments, some for his Life, and others for Forgery, &amp;c. But you must have some witnesses to swear. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e5200">
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>Why, I my self will swear, who swears more? Dammmee I never heard such a question; You Shackles, S. Edward, and Bub, and Brandy will all swear: yea and there is Instrument an excellent swearer; you know how diligent he was to get and suborn swearers in wronged M. Fitton's Cause. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e5290">
            <speaker>S. Edw. </speaker>
            <p>Spare me a word: what if Shackles, with <hi>Bub, Brandy</hi>, and others go to Coffo-Philo's house, and rifle his Closet, seize his goods, and frighten his wife and children; in this attempt you must be sure to send Coffo-Philo's Brothers to Shackle's house; and when you have entred, you must send some of your Troop to keep Guard there, under pretence of Authority, I will swear he ows me 500 l. and that will colour the work. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e5390">
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>O most excellent S. Edw. no more of Dub, and 200 l. for a Fee, thou deservest 2000 l. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e5460">
            <speaker>Pract. </speaker>
            <p>Besides, I advise your Highness to imploy Shackles with his setting-dogs at a close scent upon Coffo-Philo himself; however, enter 13 Actions in your own Court, make use of any bodies name, 'tis no matter, this will hinder his growth. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e5510">
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>Bravely moved Post-practice. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e5550">
            <speaker>Instrum. </speaker>
            <p>I humbly move that the Warrant may be signed, and Shackles sent about his work. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e5590">
            <speaker>Tipstaff. </speaker>
            <p>The Jurors are at the door, and are impatient to be gone under the Sun next to Hell, to their dinner. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e5640">
            <speaker>S. Edw. </speaker>
            <p>Call in the Fore-man, and then discharge them till to morrow; hang a little charge, Coffo-Philo shall pay all at last. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e5690">Exeunt. </stage>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="ep000573-e5700">
          <pb n="8" xml:id="ep000573-016-a"/>
          <head>Scen. V. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e5720">Enter <hi>Sice-Ace, Pitfal</hi>, and the 4 Tryers. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e5750">
            <speaker>Sice-Ace. </speaker>
            <p>Sister Pitfal, what do you think is the meaning of the Court, that it sits so long? I do mightily want S. Edw. and am undone at play with these Tryers. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e5810">
            <speaker>Pitfal. </speaker>
            <p>Gentlemen, I hope you will have us to a Play to day, for our Husbands are so buisie grown, that we have nothing from them either night or day, but starts in their sleeps; you were telling me Sister how your Husband starts in his sleep. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e5840">
            <speaker>Sice-Ace. </speaker>
            <p>True it is; for he not only starts, but cries out— O Conscience! Here I could have you Coffo-Philo: run him through, and then we shall be quiet. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e5880">
            <speaker>Pitfal. </speaker>
            <p>Alas dear sister; And my Husband 'tother night cryed out, <hi>I am Damned, I will kill </hi>Pluto <hi>that is the cause of it: Poor </hi>Coffo-Philo, <hi>I ask thee forgiveness</hi>.— But hear me sister Sice-Ace, and you Gentlemen Tryers; VVhen I kept a Semstress shop in the Strand, but more particularly, when I was an Actress at the Play-house in Vere-Street, I was in bed with a Man. (This was before I was marryed) who laying hold of me, cryed out, <hi>You damn'd Whore </hi>'tis <hi>you have undone me</hi>; and alas, I never lay with him but that night, and thus— </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e6000">
            <speaker>Sice-Ace. </speaker>
            <p>Fie sister, Did you let out your Salt-pit before marriage? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e6040">
            <speaker>Pitfal. </speaker>
            <p>Why Madam, do not I know your good Ladiship? but you dare not say so much before your Gallant, the pitiful shabbed Tryer. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e6080">
            <speaker>Tryer </speaker>
            <p>Peace Ladies, Hark! we are called for into Court. </p>
          </sp>
          <pb n="9" xml:id="ep000573-016-b"/>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e6110">Enter at one door Pluto, with Attendants; at the other, <hi>Shackles, Bub, Brandy</hi>, and the 4 Tryers. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e6150">
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>There is your Warrant Shackles, use your dexterity and art; I know there is Bub, and Brandy, and all those <hi>Four Gentlemen </hi>will do their parts— I was a dreamed Gentlemen, that just such an honest fellow as Shackles and you Gentlemen, were imployed to take Coffo-Philo; and, methoughts, one of you did cunningly run his Sword into his Belly, so that he dyed; this was so slily done, that it was no hard matter to make it Accident: It cannot be termed Murder by any Law, nor so much as Manslaughter; for as our mortal enemy, if he be killed cunningly or foolishly, I can get— you know what I mean: you most excellent friends, farewel, and try what can be done for a friend. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e6250">Tipstaff sends for the Jury to come to the Bar. Tipstaff goes out, and presently returns with the Jury. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e6280">
            <speaker>S. Edward. </speaker>
            <p>May it please your Highness to have the Jury sworn? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e6320">
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>Yes, give them their Oaths. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e6350">
            <speaker>Tipstaff. </speaker>
            <p>S. <hi>Confident Empty-Skull</hi>, come to the Book. </p>
            <p>
              <q>You shall well, but not truly try the matter in question named in the Indictments between our L. Pluto, and Coffo-Philo; and such a Verdict give, as may take away his Life and Goods, &amp;c. and destroy him root and branch. <hi>So help you </hi>Pluto. </q>Kiss this Carbine and Belt. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e6450">
            <speaker>Cap. Bluster. Cap. Want-credit. Col. Plunder. Cap. Trapan. </speaker>
            <p>Is not here inough at a time? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e6520">
            <pb n="10" xml:id="ep000573-017-a"/>
            <speaker>S. Edw. </speaker>
            <p>No, all to the Book at once. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e6560">Tipstaff. Cap. Bully-Sany. Col. Indigent. Cap. Kickt-a-Lan. Cap. Priviledge. Cap. Spunge. Cap. Ignorance, and Cap. Flutterer. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e6650">
            <speaker>S. Edw. </speaker>
            <p>
              <q>The same Oath your Fore-man hath taken, you for your parts shall well and truly keep. <hi>So help you </hi>Pluto, <hi>or a </hi>Pay-day. </q>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e6720">
            <speaker>Pract. </speaker>
            <p>
              <q>Gentlemen Hecks of the Jury, Coffo-Philo stands here Indicted for that he being no Soldier, nor in Pay, nor Roll, departed from his Colours against the Statute Anno tertio Hen. 8. cap. 5. We will prove him guilty of that Statute, no matter for his being in the Roll, or being no Soldier, or not in pay: To prove this, his Highness swears, and Instrument, and many others. </q>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e6790">
            <speaker>S. Edw. </speaker>
            <p>Give his Highness the Book. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e6830">
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>
              <hi>Damme 'tis true</hi>; what is it you mean? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e6870">
            <speaker>S. Edw. </speaker>
            <p>Now swear Instrument. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e6920">
            <speaker>Instr. </speaker>
            <p>I do swear, (because I dare do no other) that his Highness swears true. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e6950">
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>Gentlemen of the Jury, I desire to take a General Oath to all the Indictments at once, and S. Edw. and Instrum. will do the like. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e7000">
            <speaker>Iury. </speaker>
            <p>That shall serve, for 'tis past twelve. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e7030">
            <speaker>Cap. Blust. </speaker>
            <p>And I have taken but 4 pipes of Tobacco to day. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e7070">The Oath. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e7080">
            <speaker>Pluto <hi>, S. </hi>Edw. and Instr. </speaker>
            <stage xml:id="ep000573-e7120">swear. </stage>
            <p>
              <q>We do swear, </q>that the whole contents of these 17 Indictments are true. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e7150">
            <speaker>Fore-man of the Iury. </speaker>
            <p>We have evidence enough, let us deliver our Verdict. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e7190">
            <pb n="11" xml:id="ep000573-017-b"/>
            <speaker>Jury. </speaker>
            <p>Agreed. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e7220">
            <speaker>Tipstaff. </speaker>
            <p>A Verdict. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e7260">
            <speaker>Cap. Want. </speaker>
            <p>Hold M. Fore-man, who pays the Jury? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e7300">
            <speaker>Cap. Indig. </speaker>
            <p>I will be paid, before I agree to deliver the Verdict. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e7350">
            <speaker>Cap. Bluster. </speaker>
            <p>Verdict not me, for I'le no Verdict till after Dinner, and Money. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e7410">
            <speaker>The rest of the Iury. </speaker>
            <p>And so we say all, except our Fore-man Empty-skull. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e7450">
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>You are very bold with the Court; either deliver your Verdict, or I'le send you to Shackles </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e7500">
            <speaker>Proserp. </speaker>
            <p>I, do Husband, <hi>fort bone fet mon Dieu, mon Dieu Cockeu d'Angletere. </hi>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e7540">
            <speaker>Cap. Priv. </speaker>
            <p>Madam, what is that you say, <hi>Dieu Gwin Cuckol</hi>? I am half a Britain; I do say you curse us in down-right stark <hi>Welch: Dieu Gwin</hi>, is <hi>White God</hi>; but as you pronounce it, it is <hi>Rogue in White; Grave </hi>and Cocken, is a <hi>meer Cuckold of the Mountains</hi>: give me the price of the Whisk I gave your Ladiship when I gave 5 l. to boot, besides 12 l. 10 s. for Belt, Hoose, and Feathers, and I will quit the Troop presently: I observed when we were sworn, it was on a Carbine belt; I knew, and told some of my fellows then, we should have a French exaction on us. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e7710">
            <speaker>Cap. Ignorance. </speaker>
            <p>I protest when I saw it, I began to think— </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e7750">
            <speaker>Cap. Want-credit. </speaker>
            <p>Madam, as brisk as you call us in French, you will give us leave to ask our own in English: Pray Madam, give me the Diamond Ring that was my Grand-mothers, which I gave you to come into the Troop, and I will quit it presently. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e7810">
            <speaker>Cap. Flutter. </speaker>
            <p>Then Madam, let me speak too; for I gave 50 l. besides riding six months for nothing, and yet paid for my preheminencies, profits, and priviledges, Belt, Hooses, and Feathers, and Arms to the Adjutant. Give me but my 50 l. and I will say such a prayer, which I will leave in charge to my posterity; it shall be but short, these 3 or 4 words, <pb n="12" xml:id="ep000573-018-a"/>from being under the Command of Pluto, and his Emissaries, Goodness Defend us. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e7880">
            <speaker>Proserp. </speaker>
            <p>My Husband, <hi>sela set un frepone</hi>. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e7920">
            <speaker>Col. Plund. </speaker>
            <p>Ha Madam! have I caught you, calling us names in <hi>Irish? Hone</hi>, is <hi>mutinous Rogue</hi>; I do speak in behalf of some of my brother Jurors, pay us but the 18 Months we rid in the Troop for nothing, wee'l never trouble you more; then we say <hi>furr tutor</hi>; or <hi>furr futre</hi>, French Madam: I think I have plundred you of some of your French. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e8010">
            <speaker>Cap. Kick-a-tan. </speaker>
            <p>Well concluded brother Plunder, and in your own name too. That's most like an old Jury-man, as much as to say, I could Kick— you may imagine, and— tan were he either Pluto or Pan. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e8100">
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>Jurors withdraw. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e8130">
            <speaker>Cap. Blust. </speaker>
            <p>You mean for altogether sure; Farewel: well this— Imployment makes good the old Proverb, If the Devil set at work, he will pay wages too. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e8170">
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>Jurors withdraw. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e8200">
            <speaker>Cap. Bluster. </speaker>
            <p>You mean for ever; for I find the Proverb good, as I said before, the Devils wages! As for my dear Brother Hecks, and Jury-men, do but observe, now his turn is served, he cares not for us, we may go hang ourselves. I am sure honest men will not keep us company, they know how we have forsworn our selves; I hope Coffo-Philo will undo all we have done, and at last will destroy this ill-founded Arbitrary Court; but since it is so, come, let's go and wait the good hour. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e8250">Enter <hi>Shackles, Bub, Brandy</hi>, coming into Court almost out of breath. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e8270">
            <speaker>Shackles. </speaker>
            <p>May it please your Highness, we have taken Coffo-Philo's Books, seized his Goods, and left a Guard in his house. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e8310">
            <pb n="13" xml:id="ep000573-018-b"/>
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>Well done, but who have you left there besides? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e8340">
            <speaker>Shackles. </speaker>
            <p>Mrs. Sorrow, and her Children. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e8390">
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>Damme, have ye not turn'd them out? 'twill prove a mischief; run and do it now, or else we shall lose all. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e8420">
            <speaker>Shackles. </speaker>
            <p>Wee'l go; But Sir, we mist narrowly of him: for had it been but dark, or no body present but my Comrades, it had been done, you know what I mean— I, alas I laugh at Man-slaughter, <stage xml:id="ep000573-e8450">(shews his hand.) </stage>Come, away, away. </p>
          </sp>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="ep000573-e8460">
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000573-e8470">
          <head>Actus II. Scen. I. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e8490">Enter Shackles, with Brandy, and Soldiers, into Coffo-Philo's Closet, while Mrs. Sorrow, and her Children were crying in the same room. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e8540">
            <speaker>Mrs. Sorrow. </speaker>
            <p>Pray Gentlemen give me leave to take such Papers as belong to other men. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e8570">
            <speaker>Shackles. </speaker>
            <p>Damn you, and your bawling Imps: touch a Paper, and I will run this Sword into your belly. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e8600">
            <speaker>Brandy. </speaker>
            <p>What great book is that, Dammee I will have it? who hath your Husband's Cloak and Perriwig? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e8630">
            <speaker>M. Sorrow. </speaker>
            <p>You, for any thing I know. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e8670">
            <speaker>Shac. </speaker>
            <p>You lye, I have them not; for Instrument hath the Cloak, and S. <hi>Edw. Lack-Latine </hi>hath the Perriwig. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e8720">
            <speaker>M. Sorrow. </speaker>
            <p>By what Authority do you act this, Gentlemen? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e8760">
            <speaker>Shackles. </speaker>
            <p>Go look, Is it not enough that Pluto sent us? behold our carriage, by that you may know whom we serve. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e8800">
            <pb n="14" xml:id="ep000573-019-a"/>
            <speaker>Serv. </speaker>
            <stage xml:id="ep000573-e8820">to M. Sorrow. </stage>
            <p>Mrs here is a Gentleman at the dore desires to speak with you. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e8850">
            <speaker>M. Sorrow. </speaker>
            <p>I come to him </p>
            <stage xml:id="ep000573-e8890">(she goes out). </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000573-e8900">Enter M. Sor. with the Gentleman. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e8920">
            <speaker>M. Sorrow. </speaker>
            <p>Here is a Gentleman that hath been with my L. General, who believes your breaking into my house, and behaviour there, is contrary to Law. This will be examined one day. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e8960">
            <speaker>Shack. </speaker>
            <p>Go hang your self till then: we serve a Captain General. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e8990">
            <speaker>M. Sorrow. </speaker>
            <p>However, pray M. Shackles, let me have a Bed for my Children. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e9040">
            <speaker>Shac. </speaker>
            <p>Not to save your life, I had rather be hanging you, as I must your Husband. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e9070">
            <speaker>M. Sorrow. </speaker>
            <p>Then take off the Soldiers that keep Guard in my house, and burn out wastfully my Fire and Candles. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e9110">
            <speaker>Shac. </speaker>
            <p>Speak such another word, and I will turn your neck round, you damn'd-bitch-whore.! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e9140">
            <speaker>M. Sorrow. </speaker>
            <p>O unheard, but condemn'd Innocence! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e9180">
            <speaker>Shac. </speaker>
            <p>You Brandy, and the rest, look to the Books and Papers, and take them all up, dispatch, send for Porters and Carts, and carry them all away to Pluto's Court; and for you Brandy, after I am gone, I will get a Guard constantly to be kept in the house, you shall overlook them: your chief diligence must be to dog Sorrow's Children, and by that means take Coffo-Philo. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e9260">
            <speaker>Brandy. </speaker>
            <p>Bravely contrived Seignior Shac. </p>
            <stage xml:id="ep000573-e9300">Exit Shackles. </stage>
            <p>Well Gentlemen, I must have one Quartern and a Pipe. </p>
            <p>I'le but step. There are the Keys, see that nothing be stirred. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e9330">
            <speaker>Cap. Honesty a soldier. </speaker>
            <p>Poor woman, here is my self, and Lieutenant Well-meaning; as also Ms. <hi>Meerly drawn in</hi>, are heartily sorry that the Rogue Shackles useth you thus: Nor is his baseness in words and threats all; for if ought come <pb n="15" xml:id="ep000573-019-b"/>in his way, he will stuff his breeches full of Linnen, and one thing or other every time he goes home sticks to his Lime-twig Fingers. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e9400">
            <speaker>Lt. Well-meaning. </speaker>
            <p>That Rogue Shackles will be hanged, so will Brandy. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e9460">
            <speaker>M. Sor. </speaker>
            <p>Pray Gentlemen, as you seem to be civil, get me but my great Bible, and my Childrens cloaths out, and I will hold my self much engaged to you for your kind Charity. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e9500">
            <speaker>Cap. Honesty. </speaker>
            <p>Mist. your Childrens cloaths were carryed away last night; I must tell you, I see two of Pluto's friends with Practice, take Hangings and Pewter. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e9560">
            <speaker>M. Sor. </speaker>
            <p>Thank you Gentlemen— but I hear Shac. his voice. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e9610">Enter Shackles. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e9630">
            <speaker>Shackles. </speaker>
            <p>Gent. we have taken Coffo-Philo, and his Brother, we fetcht them out of London by Pluto's only Power; but a pox take him, the Judge hath taken Bail, and things go cross, neither power above nor below can hurt him, he is so clear from what he is Indicted for: what then will become of the brave swearing against— I would I had the 200 l. I gave Proserpine for my Shackles. I have brought my self doubly into trouble, for I kept Coffo-Philo's Brother in my house Prisoner 24 hours: but this is my comfort, the Court is now sitting, where they are going on with such unheard of ways, that I am sure we shall master this great Hogan— but I would fain have him dead or banished, And it shall not want for swearing if that will do. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e9740">
            <speaker>Tip. </speaker>
            <p>Here is Cap. Swear-at-all would speak with the <hi>Court▪ </hi>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e9790">
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>Call him in. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e9820">
            <speaker>Cap. Swear-at. </speaker>
            <p>May it please your Highness, Coffo-Philo and his brother are taken, and are bailed. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e9870">
            <pb n="16" xml:id="ep000573-020-a"/>
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>Damn ye for a fool, I would not have had it known that he was Bailed: hang your self and your news, get you out of the Court. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e9900">
            <speaker>Cap. Swear. </speaker>
            <p>Damn me? damn you, and your Actions; is this all I have for my news? </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e9940">Exit. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e9950">
            <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
            <p>We must clog this Coffo-philo and his Brother with faigned Actions. Now, Practice, and <hi>Lack-Latine, Instrum</hi>. and all to work, and use your wits. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e10010">
            <speaker>S. Lack. </speaker>
            <p>I will presently make an Oath in the Dutchy that he ows me 50 l. and I will make it such a Debt as shall colour our seizure of his Goods and House. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e10070">Enter Tipstaff, with a High-Constable. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e10100">
            <speaker>Tipst. </speaker>
            <p>Mr. Constable, this is the place of the unlawful Assembly, which my Mr. told you of, and according to your Warrant, pray disperse this Arbitrary Court: if you w'ont help, M. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Posse Comitatus </foreign>is now passing his green wax Roll before 4 of my Ms. Stewards. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e10150">
            <speaker>Const. </speaker>
            <p>Sir I will first knock at the Court dore, and send in my business by one of their own Officers: and if I receive any opposition, then I will trouble M. <foreign xml:lang="lat">posse Comitatus</foreign>. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e10190">
            <speaker>Tipstaff. </speaker>
            <p>Knock then. <stage xml:id="ep000573-e10220">Constable Knocks. </stage>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e10230">
            <speaker>Surribus. </speaker>
            <p>Who are you Sir, that are so rude by knocking to disturb our Court? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e10260">
            <speaker>Const. </speaker>
            <p>I take you to be rude to ask me such an impertinent question, I must tell you and your upstart Court, I am come from my Master, and I am a sworn Servant to his Honour, and have in my Hundred, 50 sworn Servants under me: but why do I trouble my self with giving you an account? I tell you my Masters name is <foreign xml:lang="lat">MAGNA CHARTA</foreign>, and if you will but look out into the street, you shall see what a goodly, strong, well composed Gentleman he is. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e10300">
            <pb n="17" xml:id="ep000573-020-b"/>
            <speaker>Surribus. </speaker>
            <p>Pray Sir, give me leave to look out and take a view of him, for I would be glad to know your Master, that I may give an account to the Court of his Quality and Train. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e10330">
            <speaker>Const. </speaker>
            <p>Do then, and tell the Court I stay without, and expect to be called in. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e10360">Surribus goes, and looks out at the dore, and presently as affrighted returns. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000573-e10370">
            <speaker>Surribus. </speaker>
            <p>Pluto, defend me, what do I see! why, on my Conscience our Pluto, with all his Train, is but a <hi>French Mushrom </hi>to this goodly sight, I have enough, O the presence of that man, I pray Heaven it sets not an end to our Rule. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000573-e10430">Exit with all the rest. </stage>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="ep000573-e10440">
        <head>Act. III. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000573-e10460">The Stage being prepared, and the Court sitting, Enter Surribus almost out of breath. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e10480">
          <speaker>Surribus. </speaker>
          <p>Oh, Oh, O me!— May it please your Highness, yonder are without 2 surly fellows, and into the Court they will come: one's name is Tip-tip-the-Staff, and the other a downright blunt fellow, I think they call him <hi>Constable of Height</hi>, and he says he is a sworn servant to M. Carter, and Ms. Magna! pox on't 'tis a hard name his Mast. is call'd by; but may it please you, and as I suppose it will not be very pleasing to your Highness, He stands in the street, whither I looked and saw him, a pox on him, he almost frighted me; Carter call you his name, bless me! I tremble to think on him; and he hath with him another like himself, I think they call him M. <hi>Petition of right</hi>: I am sure I am not mistaken in his name. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e10570">
          <pb n="18" xml:id="ep000573-021-a"/>
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Damn thee for a dull Rogue, thou tellest us an imperfect story without head or tail: nay, thou art so shallow, that thou canst not remember his name; Carter, a plague on him, what Carter dares be thus bold? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e10620">
          <speaker>Surribus. </speaker>
          <p>Sir, you interrupt me; there are with this M. Magnus or M. Carter, twelve grave and well countenanced Men wrapt in Lambskins or Furr; and besides, there were I know not how many more in Quoifes like my Grand-mother, and such a number of men in black long robes, that I wondred what they were; and thrusting them, I perceived some of them had Pens and Inckhorns by their girdles, others were taking Notes, and all addressed themselves to this longnamed man, who has 30 odd additions to his name, some call them Chapters, as 12th. 7th. 29th. &amp;c. I hearkened to their Language, and by and by in another place one repeated Anno 9. Hen. 3. another read tertio and quinto of Edw. 3. the hearing of this (for I took them for Conjurers) has almost frighmen me out of my wits: And I assure you, that one of the Gentlemen in Furr is as like that troublesom fellow that sent me to the University of Newgate to commence, for beating my Shoomaker that was so bold as to ask me for money, he lent me to pay my Dr. that cured me of a Clap; but I am sure for one of those Furred Gentlemen, I have seen the Constables beat away the Coaches and Car-men out of his way in the street; Nay, I am sure he is the man that sent Cap. <hi>Bub, Brandy </hi>and Bluster to Newgate, for hunting on the high-way near Barnet. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e10800">
          <speaker>Shac. </speaker>
          <p>By your favour, Surribus, it was neither Bub nor Brandy that was sent, 'twas Cap. C. and Cap. A. and they poor hearts were hanged: but poor Bluster was wronged in that business, for I was the man; Only I took his horse, and thence grew the mistake: but I was glad the Rogues did not peach me, and my Dan cropt Nag: O sweet Hounslow-Heath. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e10900">
          <pb n="9" xml:id="ep000573-021-b"/>
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>My freinds, no differences now, for every one must help: I smell a Rat, and therefore be loving, and build up one another, else our Kingdom is short-liv'd. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e10930">
          <speaker>Proserp. </speaker>
          <p>Who to take this man to be, that this long imperfect story is told of, I know not, I begin now to be affraid. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e10960">
          <speaker>Plut. </speaker>
          <p>Pox damn him, 'tis that fart of a fellow, old troublesom <foreign xml:lang="lat">Magna Charta</foreign>, We are bound to see the worst of it; Call in the Constable— but be sure no difference appear, nor any altering of Countenance— Throw out a <hi>Demy Oath </hi>or two, look fierce and big, and shake your Swords and Carbines now and then— Call him in, call him in. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000573-e11040">Shackles goes, and returning, Enter with him Constable, and Tipstaff. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e11080">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Friends, if I may so call you, what is your business, and the reason of your haste? you see we are Arm'd, and do you think with those two wooden sticks, and your hasty words, to frighten us? Let your Mast. be who he will, dammee he is but a clown, he is not <hi>a-la-mode, per ma foy, parle vous Francols. </hi>
          </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e11120">
          <speaker>Constab. </speaker>
          <p>Sir, I care not for your high words, nor your Conquered Nations <hi>Gibble Gabble</hi>, my Mast. will be hard enough for you at any Language; for several of his Attendants are clad in French and Latine, which he will force you to understand, though you could neither Write nor Read: But Sir, in plain English, in my Mast. name, from whom I am come, and by his Authority to me committed, I Adjourn your Court, with all its Arbitrary proceedings, for ever and a day. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e11180">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>You Adjourn my Court, your Mast. can have no Cognizance of what I do. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e11210">
          <pb n="20" xml:id="ep000573-022-a"/>
          <speaker>Const. </speaker>
          <p>Yes Sir, but he has, and will take Cognizance of you, and your Actions; for Coffo-Philo hath delivered him a Petition, which was the cause of his sending me. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e11250">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Damn Coffo-Philo, and your Mast. too: Gentlemen, stand to your Arms, We will not be surprized. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e11290">
          <speaker>Proserp. </speaker>
          <p>Pray, hold, Pluto, let us hear who his Mast. is, you are the most passionate— that ever was. Sir,— M. Const. pray tell me the name of your Mast. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e11340">
          <speaker>Const. </speaker>
          <p>Why, Madam, so I would; but Pluto plunders my meaning before I speak, as friends and foes were plundred in Britain— Welch for that. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e11400">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Dammee Rascal, do you speak of Oxford or Newark? Sirrah, be your Mast. what he will, he durst not then have stirred, I have hanged as good men as you, a High-Constable or two in a morning for not— dogs, must I hear this, and wear a Sword? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e11470">
          <speaker>Pros. </speaker>
          <p>Constable, Go on, pray go on. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e11510">
          <speaker>Const. </speaker>
          <p>I say, my Mast. is <foreign xml:lang="lat">Magna Charta</foreign>, a very old man. He was born in Nono of Henry the 3d. and then Christned: his Godfathers were the <hi>King, Lords</hi>, and Commons: thirty Parliaments have since that been Witnesses of his Confirmation, and attested his birth and power; he hath such a trick in Nature, that every Parliament gives and adds strength to his days: And I must tell you here of this pretended Court, that my Mast. hath a small Officer called <foreign xml:lang="lat">Posse Comitatus </foreign>belonging to him, that will fall foul with you, and disperse you, if you resist his Power: besides, his Children the Commons love him so dearly, that they will raise Money, Men, Armies, and all to preserve him, and keep his Honour inviolable. </p>
        </sp>
        <pb n="21" xml:id="ep000573-022-b"/>
        <stage xml:id="ep000573-e11610">Enter <foreign xml:lang="lat">Venire Facias</foreign>. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e11630">
          <speaker>Ven. Fac. </speaker>
          <p>
            <q>
              <hi>Pluto, Pros</hi>. and you the rest of the black Instruments of darkness, I am come to cite you to appear in <hi>Mens. Michael</hi>. before my Mast. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Magna Charta</foreign>, in his great Hall at Westminster, to answer Coffo-Philo, and 500 younger brothers, with Pierce-heart, Sir <hi>John Morley</hi>, old Cicel our neighbour at Enfield, with many others; as the <hi>Military ground men</hi>, and Fitton:— where you are to answer for many Riots, wrongs, and high misdemeanors. And therefore Constable dis-arm them. </q>
          </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e11790">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>You M. Troublesome, I will have <hi>l'argent per ma foy</hi>, or else I'le not part with my Sword. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000573-e11840">He resists, and there arises a bustle, and in the hurly burly <hi>Exeunt Ven. Fa. Const</hi>. and Tipstaff. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e11870">
          <speaker>Proserp. </speaker>
          <p>Now these vexatious varlets are fled, Pray Husband get what money you can, I do not like this <foreign xml:lang="lat">Magna Charta</foreign>; for I have heard Haly the first, and worst say, that <foreign xml:lang="lat">Magna Charta </foreign>cares no more for a Lord, or Great Man, than you do for a <hi>petit frepone de la Guard</hi>: Nay, he says, That he has prosecuted the highest Subjects, and somtimes hanged them, as <hi>Empson, Dudley</hi>, and 100 more of his Infringers: I'de have you for avoiding danger, to buy a Bashaws place in Turky; for methinks I could make a rare Bashaw's wife; There is no <foreign xml:lang="lat">Magna Charta</foreign>. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e11990">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Pox damn it, there is a kind of little <foreign xml:lang="lat">Magna Charta</foreign>, that is the Alcoran, and <hi>Bow strings</hi>, and I hate choaking; besides, the Janisaries are as mutinous as our common Soldiers, and often knock their Visier on the head; Nay, the Grand-Seignior, if a General do but cheat him in his Muster-Roll, sends him a Bow-string; and then— he may go hang himself. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e12110">
          <pb n="22" xml:id="ep000573-023-a"/>
          <speaker>Proserp. </speaker>
          <p>Is it possible? <hi>fer futre la Gran Seigner</hi>; what then will you do with this damn'd English <foreign xml:lang="lat">Magna Charta</foreign>? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e12160">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>S. <hi>Edw. Lack. </hi>now we know it is <foreign xml:lang="lat">Magna Charta </foreign>that takes Coffo-Philo's part, we had best while we are together to examine our own strengths and weaknesses. And therefore Wife I beg your silence, till we have examined Cap. Intelligence, who is ready to make Report, are you not Captain? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e12230">
          <speaker>Cap. Intel. </speaker>
          <p>Yes Sir, but I cannot give an account to the Court of all: for one of Shack. setting dogs, with M. Want-Practice, sit close at Coffo-Philo, whence in a little time you will know much more; in the mean time, I must beg all the Honourable persons of this Court, that they will take no exceptions till I have told out my tale. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e12300">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>You shall not be interrupted. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e12330">
          <speaker>Cap. Intel. </speaker>
          <p>Then first; for you S. <hi>Edw. Lack. </hi>there is a man here in Town that knows you ever since your Mother sold Ale: and that after you came to be M. Harper's boy at Chester, you made Practice, which since you have well improved— I— and he knows of the Letter that got you your Barr-Gown, and the occasion: and told all the story of your contrivance with Granger, and the false Oath you made against C— to get his Goods: yours is too long a story to relate, therefore here is your black Bill of Fare in writing, signed and examined by <hi>Alex. Fitton, Carr</hi>, and <hi>Percival Hart</hi>, but transcribed by Coffo-Philo. </p>
          <p>For your part M. Practice, your name is like an infectious disease— honest men never use your name, but they do as the Papists, at the name of the Devil, sign themselves with the Cross, or God bless me from that Knave in grain M. Practice. </p>
          <p>As to you M. Instrument, you are known in Cheshire, ever since you led your Fathers Pack-horse that carryed his Pedlers Ware; but known better by the name of <hi>Engine Dick</hi>, that informed against the Cavaliers in S. Geor. Booth's business: <pb n="23" xml:id="ep000573-023-b"/>and then, as your Father was made a Sequestrator, so you had 3 <foreign xml:lang="lat">s. per diem </foreign>allowed you by those Usurpers, to attend the Sequestrator; yet they held you but for a silly fellow: and S. <hi>Edw. Lack. </hi>for 20 s. preferred you to be his Instrumant. </p>
          <p>But for you Shackles, you are called in <hi>London, lying, broken Dick, </hi>who cousened all your Creditors, and to the great disgrace of the Guards sheltred your self from your just Debts: but to hear Coffo-Philo tell the story of your life, how often imprisoned, and how you were condemned to be boyled alive in Oyl for a Coyner, would make one wonder: in a word, you are hated even amongst your own Comrades. </p>
          <p>For you Brandy, your life is generally scandalous and infamous for beating your Wife, although she often— deserves admonition, or something else, or her Neighbours do her wrong: but laying aside a bushel of ill qualities, that which S. <hi>Edw. Massey </hi>tells of you, is unpardonable, how you would have killed him when he declared for the King at Glocester; and was the last man of the Soldiers that opposed Gen. Monk in Glocester: the story is too large to relate, therefore take S. Edw. Massey's own Certificate. </p>
          <p>For you Bub, you are looked upon as a poor spirited fellow; that for a dinner, bub, and ease, will swear any thing: the most empty-scul'd, cock-brain'd fellow that ever was made a Cuckold: your Neighbours call you <hi>foul mouth</hi>, and <hi>blew. lips</hi>. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e12730">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Pray, Cap. hold a little, what do they say of my Wife? speak freely, (<hi>Wife you shall not be angry.</hi>) </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e12770">
          <speaker>Cap. Intel. </speaker>
          <p>They say, that Proserp. though the grey mare is the better horse, and wears the breeches, playing away her money freely, many an undone younger brother hath been set at <hi>Humber, Picquet </hi>in a night. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e12830">
          <pb n="24" xml:id="ep000573-024-a"/>
          <speaker>Proserp. </speaker>
          <p>Pray Husband let me speak a word; you did allow me the selling of 5 or 6 places in a year, and then I had 300 l. a year for my allowance, besides other ways of progging for money, therefore I may afford to Play, 'tis my own: only, I confess I owe <hi>Coffo Philo </hi>300 l. which I borrowed on my Jewels, as you have heard. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e12890">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Pray where is my Charge, Cap. Intelligence? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e12930">
          <speaker>Cap. Intell. </speaker>
          <p>There it is in writing, take it, with a comment upon it, and a many great Authorities against all your unjust Arbitrary proceedings; and I have put you to the cost of one copie of the Statute of <foreign xml:lang="lat">Anno tertio Car. </foreign>and the reason why I brought it, is, because your Highness is much blamed for sending your two Daughters into France to be bred Papists in a Nunnerie, where your eldest daughter Charnock, torments her self, and cries out, she will be a Protestant, or else she will destroy her self, to the great admiration and pitie of Sir <hi>Thom. Arpe</hi>, who hath sent to have the poor young Ladie sent for away to England.— </p>
          <p>Nay Sir, should I have paid for all the copies of the Charge against you, my 4 s. a day would not have held out: but I must have a dead pay for what I have done alreadie, or else you may— go look. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e13040">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Dear Cap. Intell. read them to me, and then we will Adjourn the Court, or else this foolish troublesome fellow <foreign xml:lang="lat">Magna Charta </foreign>will secure us all under his Shackles. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e13090">
          <speaker>Pract. </speaker>
          <p>Give me the papers I will read them. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e13120">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Prithee do, and I would have you Sir <hi>Edw. Lack. </hi>to make notes on what you have read. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e13160">
          <pb n="25" xml:id="ep000573-024-b"/>
          <speaker>Pract. </speaker>
          <p>Anno 9. H. 3. Cap. 29. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Magna Charta </foreign>runs thus. </p>
          <q>
            <p>No Free-man shall be taken or Imprisoned, or be disseized of his Free-hold, or Liberties, or Free-Customs, or be Outlawed or Eriled, or any other ways destroyed: Nor We will not pass upon him, nor condemn him, but by lawful Judgement of his Peers, or by Law of the Land; We will sell to no man, We will not deny or defer to any man either Justice or Right. </p>
          </q>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e13230">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Read no further of that, which is the next? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e13260">
          <speaker>Pract. </speaker>
          <p>Sir there are so many more, that it would be too tedious a work to read all: but if you please I will read the Conference between the Lords and Commons, concerning this great liberty of the Commons. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e13290">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Pray do, but if there be any Latine, pray English it as you read, because of Sir Edw. and my self. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e13330">
          <speaker>Pract. </speaker>
          <p>I will read it. </p>
          <q>
            <p>The Commons having taken into their serious consideration the matter of personal Liberty, and after long debate thereof an divers days, aswel by solemn Arguments, as single Propositions of Doubts and Answers, to the end no scruple might remain in any mans breast unsatisfyed; they have upon a full search, and clear understanding of all things pertinent to the Question, unanimously declared. </p>
            <p>That no Free-man ought to be committed or detained in Prison, or otherwise restrained by the Command of the King or Privy Council, or any other, unless some cause of the commitment, detainer or restraint be expressed, for which by Law he ought to be committed, detained or restrained. </p>
          </q>
          <p>And they have sent me with others of their Members, to represent unto your Lordships the true grounds of such their Resolution, and have charged me particularly, leaving the <pb n="26" xml:id="ep000573-025-a"/>reasons of Law and Presidents for others to give your Lordships satisfaction, that this Liberty is established and confirmed by the whole State, the King, the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, by several Acts of Parliament; the Authority whereof is so great, that it can receive no Answer: save by Interpretation or Repeal by future Statutes; and those that I shall mind your Lordships of, are so direct to the point, that they can bear no other exposition at all, and sure I am they are still in force. </p>
          <p>The first of them is, the Grand Charter of the Liberties of England, first granted in the seaventeenth year of King John, and renewed in the ninth year of King Henry the Third, and since confirmed in Parliament above thirty times; The words are thus, Cap. 29. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Nullus Liber homo Capiatur vel Imprisonetur, aut Dissesietur de Libero Tenemento suo, vel libertatibus, vel Liberis consuetudinibus suis, aut utlegatur, aut exuletur, aut aliquo modo destruatur, nec super eum ibimus, nec super eum mittemus, nisi per Legale Judicium Parium suorum vel per Legem Terrae. </foreign>These words, <foreign xml:lang="lat">Nullus Liber homo</foreign>, &amp;c. are express enough, yet it is remarkable that <hi>Matthew Paris</hi>, an Author of special credit doth observe Fol. 432, that the Charter of 9. Hen. 3. was the very same as of the 17 of King John (<hi>in nullo dissimilis</hi>, are his words,) and that of King John he setteth down verbatim, Fol. 342, and there the words are directly, <hi>Nec eum in carcerem mittemus</hi>; And such a corruption as is now in the print, might easily happen 'twixt 9. H. 3. and 28. E. 1. when this Charter was first exemplified; but certainly there is sufficient left in that which is extant to decide this question, For the words are, <hi>That no Free-man shall be taken or Imorisoned, but by the lawful Judgement of his Peers, which is by Jury Peers for Peers, ordinary Jurors for others who are their Peers, or by the Law of the Land, which words (Law of the Land) </hi>must of necessity be understood in this notion, to be by due Process of the Law, <pb n="27" xml:id="ep000573-025-b"/>and not the Law of the Land generally, otherwise it would comprehend Bond-men (whom we call Villains) who are excluded by the word Liber; for the general Law of the Land doth allow their Lords to Imprison them at pleasure without Cause; wherein they only differ from the Free-men in respect of their persons, who cannot be Imprisoned without a cause: And that this is the true understanding of those words (<foreign xml:lang="lat">per Legem Terrae</foreign>) will more plainly appear by divers other Statutes that I shall use which do expound the same accordingly; And though the words of this grand Charter be spoken in the third person, yet they are not to be understood of Suits betwixt party and party, at least not of them alone, but even of the King's Suits against his Subjects, as will appear by the occasion of the getting of that Charter, which was by reason of the difference betwixt those Kings and their People, and therefore properly to be applyed unto their power over them, and not to ordinary questions betwixt Subject and Subject. Secondly, the words <hi>Per Legale judicum parium suorum</hi>, immediately preceding the other of <foreign xml:lang="lat">Per Legem Terrae</foreign>, are meant of Tryals at the King's Suit, and not at the prosecution of a Subject; And therefore if a Peer of the Realm be Arraigned at the Suit of the King upon an Indictment of Murder, he shall be Tryed by his Peers, that is Nobles, but if he be appealed of Murder by a Subject, his Tryal shall be by an ordinary Jury of Twelve Free-holders, as appeareth in 10. E. 4. 6. 33. H. 8. Brook titl. Tryals 142. Stamford Pleas of the Crown, lib. 3. cap. 1 folio 152. And in the 10. E. 4. it is said, such is the meaning of <foreign xml:lang="lat">Magna Charta</foreign>, by the same reason therefore as <hi>per judicium parium suorum</hi>, extends to the King's Suit, so shall these words <foreign xml:lang="lat">per Legem Terrae</foreign>. And in 8. E. 2. <hi>Rot. Parliament. memb</hi>. 7. There is a Petition that a Writt under the Privy Seal went to the Guardians of the great Seal, to cause Lands to be seized into the King's hands; By force of which there went a Writt out of the Chancery to the Escheater to seize against the form of the <pb n="28" xml:id="ep000573-026-a"/>grand Charter, that the King nor his Ministers shall out no man of Free-hold without reasonable Judgement; and the party was restored to his Land, which sheweth the Statute did extend to the King. There was no invasion upon this personal Liberty, till the time of King Edward the Third, which was eftsoons resented by the Subjects; for in 5 Edw. 3. cap. 9. it is ordained in these words; </p>
          <p>
            <q>It is Enacted, That no man from henceforth shall be attached by any accusation, nor forejudged of life or limb, nor his lands, tenements, goods, nor chattels seised into the Kings hands, against the form of the grrat Charter, and the Law of the Land. </q>
          </p>
          <p>25 E. 3. cap. 4. Is more full, and doth expound the words of the grand Charter: And thus; </p>
          <p>
            <q>Whereas it is contained in the great Charter of the Franchises of England, that none shall be imprisoned, nor put out of his Freehold, nor of his Franchises, nor Free Custom, unless it be by the Law of the Land: 〈◊〉 is accorded, assented and established, That from henceforth none shall be taken by petition, or suggestion made to our Lord the King, or to his Council, unless it be by Indictment, or Presentment of his good and lawful people of the same Neighbourhood, where such deeds be done in due manner, or by process made by Writ Original at the Common Law; nor that none be out of his Franchises, nor of his Free-holds, unless he be duly brought in answer, and forejudged of the same by the course of the Law: And if any thing be done against the same, it shall be redressed, and holden for none. </q>
          </p>
          <pb n="29" xml:id="ep000573-026-b"/>
          <p>Out of this Statute I observe, that what in <foreign xml:lang="lat">Magna Charta</foreign>, and the Preamble of the Statute is termed by the Law of the Land, is in the body of this Act expounded to be by process made by Writ Original at the Common Law, which is a plain interpretation of the words (<hi>Law of the Land</hi>) in the grand Charter. And I note, that this law was made upon the Commitment of divers to the Tower, no man yet knoweth for what. </p>
          <p>28 E. 3. cap. 3. is yet more direct (this Liberty being followed with fresh suit by the Subject) where the words are not many, but very full and significant. </p>
          <p>
            <q>That no man of estate or condition that he be, shall be put out of his lands, nor tenement, nor taken nor imprisoned, nor disherited, nor put to death, without he be brought in answer by due process of the Law. </q>
          </p>
          <p>Here your Lordships see the usual words of the law of the land are rendered by due process of the Law. </p>
          <p>36 E. 3. <hi>Rot. Parl. n. </hi>9. Amongst the Petitions of the Commons, one of them being translated into English out of French, is thus; </p>
          <p>
            <q>First, That the great Charter, and the Charter of the Forrest, and the other Statutes made in his time, and in the time of his Progenitors, for the profit of him, and his Commonalty, be well and firmly kept, and put in due execution, without putting disturbance, or making arrest contrary to them by special command, or in other manner. </q>
          </p>
          <p>The Answer to the Petition, which makes it an Act of Parliament, is, </p>
          <p>
            <q>
              <pb n="30" xml:id="ep000573-027-a"/>Our Lord the King by the assent of the Prelates, Dukes, Earls, Barons, and the Commonalty, hath ordained and established, That the said Charters and Statutes be held, and put in execution according to the said Petition. </q>
          </p>
          <p>It is observable, that the statutes were to be put in execution, according to the said Petition, which is, that no arrest should be made contrary to the statutes by special command. This concludes the question, and is of as great force, as if it were Printed; for the Parliament Roll is the true warrant of an Act, and many are omitted out of the Books that are extant. </p>
          <p>36 E. 3. <hi>Rot. Parl. n. </hi>20. explaineth it further, for there the Petition is: </p>
          <p>
            <q>Item, As it is contained in the Grand Charter, and other Statutes, that no man be taken, nor imprisoned by special Command without Indictment, or other due process to be made by the Law, and oftentimes it hath been, and yet is, that many are hindered, taken and imprisoned without Indictment, or other process made by the Law upon them, as well of things done out of the Forrest of the King, as for other things, that it would please our said Lord, to command those to be delivered which are so taken by special Command, against the form of the Charters and Statutes aforesaid. </q>
          </p>
          <p>The Answer is, </p>
          <p>
            <q>The King is pleased, That if any man find himself agrieved, that he come and make his complaint, and right shall be done unto him. </q>
          </p>
          <pb n="31" xml:id="ep000573-027-b"/>
          <p>42 E. 3. cap. 18. agreeth in substance, when it saith, <q>Though that it be contained in the Great Charter; that no man be taken, nor imprisoned, nor put out of his Free-hold, without process of the Law; nevertheless divers people make false suggestion to the King himself, as well for malice, as otherwise, whereof the King is often grieved, and divers of the Realm put in damage, against the form of the same Charter; Wherefore it is ordained, That all they which make suggestions, wall be sent with the same suggestions before the Chancellor Treasurer, and his grand Council, aud that they there find Sureties to pursue their suggestions, and incurre the same pain that the other should have had, if he were attainted, in case that his suggestion be found evil: And that then process of the Law be made against them without being taken and imprisoned against the form of the said Charter and other Statutes. </q>
          </p>
          <p>Here the Law of the Land in the grand Charter is explained to be without process of the Law. </p>
          <p>
            <q>
              <bibl>37 <hi>E. cap. </hi>3. </bibl>At the request of the Commons by their Petitions put forth in this Parliament; To eschew mischief and damage done to divers of the Commons by false accusers which oftentimes have made their accusation more for revenge and singular benefit, than for the profit of the King, or of his people; which accused persons, some have been taken, and sometime caused to come before the Kings Council by Writ, and otherwise upon grievous pain against the Law: It is assented and accorded for the good governance of the Commons, That no man be <pb n="32" xml:id="ep000573-028-a"/>put to answer without presentment before Iustices, or matter of Record, or by due Process and Writ Original, according to the old Law of the Land. And if any thing from henceforth be done to the contrary, it shall be void in the Law, and holden for Error. </q>
          </p>
          <p>But this is better in the Parliament Roll, where the Petition and Answer which makes the Act, are set down at large. </p>
          <p>42 E. 3 <hi>Rot. n. </hi>12. The Petition. </p>
          <p>
            <q>Item, Because that many of your Commons are hurt and destroyed by false Accusers, who make their accusations more for their revenge and particular gain, then for the profit of the King, or his people; and these that are accused by them, some have been taken, and others are made to come before the Kings Council by Writ, or other Commandment of the King, upon grievous pains, contrary to the Law: That it would please our Lord the King, and his good Council, for the Iust government of his people to ordain, That if hereafter any accuser purpose any matter for the profit of the King, that the same matter be sent to the Justices of the one Bench, or the other, or the Assizes, to be enquired and determined according to the Law: And if it concern the accuser or party, that he take his suit at the Common Law; and that no man be put to answer without presentment before Iustices, or matter of Record, or by due Process, and original Writ, according to the antient Law of the Land; And if any thing hence forward be done to the contrary, that it be void in Law, and held for Error. </q>
          </p>
          <pb n="33" xml:id="ep000573-028-b"/>
          <p>Here by due Process and Original Writ, according to the ancient Law of the Land, is meant the same thing, as, <foreign xml:lang="lat">Per Legem Terrae in Magna Charta</foreign>; and the abuse was, That they were put to answer by Commandment of the King. </p>
          <p>The Kings Answer is thus: </p>
          <p>
            <q>Because that this Article is an Article of the Grand Charter, the King will that this be done as the Petition doth demand. </q>
          </p>
          <p>By this appeareth, that <foreign xml:lang="lat">Per Legem Terrae in Magna Charta, </foreign>is meant by due Process of the Law. </p>
          <p>Thus your Lordships have heard Acts of Parliament in the point; but the Statute of <hi>Westminster the first, cap. </hi>15. is urged to disprove this opinion, where it is expresly said, That a man is not Replevisable, who is committed by the command of the King; therefore the Command of the King without any cause shewed, is sufficient to commit a man to prison. And because the strength of the Argument may appear, and the Answer be better understood, I shall read the words of that Statute, which are thus: </p>
          <p>
            <q>And forasmuch as Sheriffs and others which have taken and kept in prison persons detected of felony, and oftentimes have let out by Replevin such as were not Replevisable, and have kept in prison such as were Replevisable; because they would gain of the one party, and grieve the other. And forasmuch as before this time it was not certainly determined what persons were repleviable, and what not: but only those that were taken for the death of a man, or by Commandment of the King, or of his Iustices, or for the Forrest. It is provided, and by the <pb n="34" xml:id="ep000573-029-a"/>King commanded, that such prisoners as before were outlawed; and they which have abjured the Realm, provors, and such as be taken with the manner, and those which have broken the Kings Prison, Thieves openly defamed and known, and such as be appealed by provors, so long as the provors be living, if they be not of good name, and such as be taken for burning of houses feloniously done, or for false money, or for counterfeiting the Kings Seal, or persons excommunicate taken at the request of the Bishop, or for manifest offences, or for Treason touching the King himself, shall be in no wise Replevisable by Common Writ, or without Writ; but such as be indicted of Larceny by Inquests taken before Sheriffs or Bayliffs by their office, or of light suspition, or for petty Larceny, that amounteth not above the value of twelve pence, if they were not guilty of some other Larceny aforetime, or guilty of receipt of felons, or of commandment, or force, or aid in felony done, or guilty of some other trespasses, for which one ought not to lose life or member; And a man appealed by a provor, after the death of the provor, if he be no common thief, nor defamed, shall from henceforth be let out by sufficient Surety, whereof the Sheriff will be answerable, and that without giving ought of their goods. And if the Sheriff or any other let any go at large by Surety, that is not Replevisable, if he be Sheriff or Constable, or any other Bayliff of Fee which hath keeping of Prisons, and thereof be attainted he shall lose his Fee and Office for ever. And if the under-Sheriff, Constable, or Bayliff of such as hath Fee for keeping of Prisons, do it contrary to the will of his Lord, or <pb n="35" xml:id="ep000573-029-b"/>any other Bayliff being not of Fee, they shall have three years imprisonment, and make a Fine at the Kings pleasure: And if any withhold prisoners Replevisable, after that they have offered sufficient Surety, he shall pay a grievous Amerciament to the King; And if he take any reward for the deliverance of such, he shall pay double to the prisoner, and also shall be in the great mercy of the King. </q>
          </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e14340">
          <speaker>Pluto </speaker>
          <p>Dam me, this is a damn'd Argument, I do not like it; for by this I find I have run into a Praemunire, for keeping Coffophilo and his Brother in Prison under Shackles, and keeping guard in his house: neither can you, Gentlemen, keep your plunder by this Argument to try by Peers: Why, there was never the peer of this. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e14400">
          <speaker>Shackles. </speaker>
          <p>Pray Sir, who shall Captain Bub, and Brandy, and my self keep harmless? I find the Proverb true, <hi>He that is born to be hang'd, shall never be boyl'd in Oyl. </hi>
          </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e14460">
          <speaker>Brandy. </speaker>
          <p>Will swearing do no good to hang this Coffo-philo? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e14500">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Peace, Gentlemen, we shall have need of all your swearing: Oh that a Jury would believe! here are arrant Knights— of the Post: stand to it Shackles, you shall all swear and be d— </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e14540">
          <speaker>Bub. </speaker>
          <p>Tis true: <hi>Post Practice </hi>you swore home to hang your Country-men, when they were for the King, at the rising in Lincolnshire. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e14590">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>No rubbing of old sores, Gentlemen, here is a new Ulcer will want curing. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e14620">
          <speaker>Bishop. </speaker>
          <p>Do not quarrel, Gentlemen, I'le teach you your Neck-verse. Would to Heaven I might have the favour to read mine. Such of you as are without benefit of my Function, as some of you are, and therefore I will make you Paper Wills, that shall last seventeen year in the lining of a doublet. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e14650">
          <pb n="36" xml:id="ep000573-030-a"/>
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Practise, Pray read that damn'd Statute against Captains cousening and defrauding their Prince and Souldiers, there is two of them, read them both; the one of Henry the Seventh, and the other of Henry the Eighth. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e14710">
          <speaker>Pract. </speaker>
          <p>I will. </p>
          <p>
            <q>
              <bibl>
                <foreign xml:lang="lat">Anno tertio Hen. </foreign>8 cap. 5. </bibl>
              <p>Forasmuch as the King our Soveraign Lord intendeth, by the grace of God, to send over the ●…a a great Army, trusting thereby, not only to preserve this his Realm in its ancient ●ante and honour, etc. </p>
              <p>Howbeit, many times by the inordinate covetousness of Captains retained with Princes, afore this time, Great part of the number of Souldiers for whom such Captains have indented with Princes at time of need, have lacked of the number of Souldiers; whereby great jeopardy hath insued, &amp; inrecuperable damages may insue, if remedy therefore be not seen and had; Be it therefore ordained by Authority of this present Parliament, That if any Captain be retained, or hereafter shall be, to serve the King upon the Sea, or beyond the Sea, or in feat of War, which have not his or their whole and perfect number of Men and Souldiers, according as he shall bee retained with the King, or give not them their full wages, without abridgement, as he shall receive of the King for them; he shall for such default, forfeit to the King all his goods and Chattels, and his body to the prison; and that every Captain and petit Captain, and all other, having under them retinue of Souldiers at the Kings wages, shall, upon the pain aforesaid, pay to the retinue of the Souldiers, and every of <pb n="37" xml:id="ep000573-030-b"/>them tho wages rateably, as is allowed unto them, by the King our Soveraign Lord, or the Treasurer of his Wars, without lessing, or withdrawing any part thereof, &amp;c. </p>
            </q>
          </p>
          <p>The Statute of <foreign xml:lang="lat">Anno septimo H </foreign>7. cap. 1. is also very strict against your Highness; but, Sir, I will read one Statute more to this particular. </p>
          <p>
            <q>
              <bibl>
                <foreign xml:lang="lat">Anno secundo &amp; tertio Edwardi sext. Cap. </foreign>2. </bibl>And be it also Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That if any Captain, or any other before named, having the Order of any number of Souldiers serving as is aforesaid, upon the Sea or Land, do at any time after the first day of April, demand, receive, or take of the Kings Highness, or any of his Treasurers, any wages for any more Souldiers, then served in such manner and form, as the wages was paid for, sr for any more days, then such Souldiers served, and do not note the day of every Souldiers entry into wages, and day of his death, and departure, and deliver the same in writing to such Treasurers as shall pay the wages, &amp;c. </q>
          </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e14890">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Hold, this is worse and worse. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e14920">
          <speaker>Pract. </speaker>
          <p>Give me leave to read but one Statute more, and that is against sending Children to be bred beyond Sea in Papist houses. </p>
          <p>
            <q>
              <bibl>
                <foreign xml:lang="lat">Anno tertio Caroli Regis, cap. </foreign>2. </bibl>
              <p>Forasmuch as divers ill-affected persons to the true Religion established within this Realm, have sent their Children into forraign parts, to be bred up in Popery, &amp;c. </p>
              <p>Be it Enacted, etc. That in case that any person or persons, <pb n="38" xml:id="ep000573-031-a"/>under the obedience of the King, his Heirs and Successors, at any time after the end of this Session of Parliament, shall pass, or go, or shall convey, or send, or cause to be sent or conveyed any Child, or other person, out of any of the Kings Dominions, into any the parts beyond the Seas out of the Kings Obedience, to the intent and purpose to enter into, or be resident, or trained up in any Priory, Abbey, Nunnery, Popish Vniversity, Colledge, or School, or House of Iesuites, Priests, or in any private Popish Family, and shall be there by any Iesuite, Seminary Priest, Friar, Monk, or other Popish Person, instructed, &amp;c. being thereof lawfully convicted, in, or upon any Information, Presentment, or Indictment as aforesaid, shall be distnabled from thenceforth to sue, or use any Action, Bill, Plaint, or Information in course of Law, or to prosecute any suit in any Court of Equity, or to be committed to any Ward, or Executor, or Administrator, or any person capable of any Legacy, or Deed of Gift, or to bear any Office within the Realm, and shall lose and forfeit all his Goods and Chattels, and shall forfeit all his Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments, Rents, Annuities, Offices, and Estates of Free-hold, for and during his natural life, &amp;c. </p>
            </q>
          </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15010">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Read no further, I am guilty of all these Statutes, and many more; and therefore Proserpine, I will immediately make my Will. Call the Ordinary, he hath a rare faculty in making Wills in Paper, to last seventeen years in the lining of a Doublet. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15050">
          <speaker>Pract. </speaker>
          <p>I have not half done, give me leave to read all. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15080">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Read all and be damn'd. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15110">
          <pb n="39" xml:id="ep000573-031-b"/>
          <speaker>Pract. </speaker>
          <p>Hen. 3. Anno 9. cap. 30. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Magna Charta </foreign>runs thus: </p>
          <p>
            <q>No Freeman shall be taken, or imprisoned, or be disseised of his Freehold, or Liberties, or Free Customs, or be outlawed, or exiled, or any otherwise distroyed, nor we will not pass upon him, nor condemn him, but by lawful Iudgement of his Peers, or by the Law of the Land; we will sell to no man, we will not deny, or deferre to any man either Iustice, or Right. </q>
          </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15200">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Read no further of that, which is next? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15230">
          <speaker>Pract. </speaker>
          <p>The next is the Learned Conference in <hi>Caroli primo</hi>, between the Lords and Commons, concerning the Great Liberties of the Commons. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15270">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Prithee read, but when you come to Latine, English it as you go, because of Sir Edward and my Self. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000573-e15310">All the Stage being cleared, Enters Pluto, Sir <hi>Edward Lack Latine, Bishop, Post Practice </hi>and Instrument. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15350">
          <speaker>POst Practice. </speaker>
          <p>Sir, I am not satisfied, that your Highness should make your will yet, for Sir Edward and I have lately consulted; and fain would be at the other touch. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15390">
          <speaker>Sir Edw. </speaker>
          <p>Right; I am resolved to venter my Neck after my Ears, 'tis but a venture; and now you have money good stood store, you do not know, but Coffophilo may either die, or be tired out for want of money. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15430">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Well, let me hear which way now, Gentlemen, <pb n="40" xml:id="ep000573-032-a"/>how many Actions is now against him? and how many have been tryed? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15460">
          <speaker>Practice. </speaker>
          <p>We have tryed in all seventeen, and there yet remains five more. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15490">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>How many hath he cast us in? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15520">
          <speaker>Sir Edw. </speaker>
          <p>All. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15550">
          <speaker>Bishop. </speaker>
          <p>I am for no more Tryals, till my Trial be over for my Perjury. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15580">
          <speaker>Instrum. </speaker>
          <p>Bishop, let me tell you, your Parishioners are now totally your enemies, since they heard you was such a Knave, to plead the Ingagement, in Barre to a poor Cavalier-Minister, that sued you in the late Times for money; his name was Green, a poor sequestered Minister, whose Conscience was not free to take the Ingagement: and thus the poor Gentleman lost his suit. Your Wife may well be mad, if half be true, as I was told by one of your Parish, the child sent in the basket— </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15620">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Hold, no more. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000573-e15650">Enter Shackells with a Note from Pluto's Council. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15680">
          <speaker>Shackel. </speaker>
          <p>SIr, pray read this. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15710">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>What is't Shackel? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15750">
          <speaker>Shackel. </speaker>
          <p>'Tis Latine. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15780">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Read it. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15810">
          <speaker>Sir Edw. Lack-Lat. </speaker>
          <p>Practice, give it me, <hi>Carol. secund. Dei gratia</hi>: How! what this attach the body of Pluto?— </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15870">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>O me Good Behaviour! I am a Peer. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15900">
          <speaker>Instrum. </speaker>
          <p>I, there is not the Peer of your Highness: now, what's to be done? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15930">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Did not Proserpine tell us that <foreign xml:lang="lat">Magna Charta </foreign>cared <pb n="41" xml:id="ep000573-032-b"/>no shore for a Great man, then if he were <hi>petete frepone de la gard </hi>in a just cause. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e15990">
          <speaker>Sir Edw. </speaker>
          <p>May it please your Highness, I would have you remove Carr by Writ to the Fleet, by this means it may be done; First, enter three great Actions against him and his Brother in the Exchequer; next, file two Bills in Chancery, and take out five other Writs to torment him if he stir abroad: This will do his business. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e16040">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>How, in my own name, or his Lawyers? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e16070">
          <speaker>Sir Edw. Lack. </speaker>
          <p>There is <hi>Monsieur Francois Pembertonia</hi>, he that pick'd the hole in your evidence against Coffophilo; next, <hi>Seignior Francisco, alias </hi>honest, just, and able Viningtoniences, and Honourable stout Colmaneburg, Grave, and as honest Symsoniack. Lastly, <hi>Seignior Ofley Lego</hi>. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e16170">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Damme that— he— Lego is down right a name of War— Lego— Leiger, a Town besieged; I will send these five Hectors of the Barre, five Tryers, or five Hecks will they fight? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e16230">
          <speaker>Sir Edw. </speaker>
          <p>O no Sir. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e16260">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Damme, I will send for French Lawyers— sons of the little French Lawyer, they shall both fight them, and carry the Judge a Challenge too, if need require. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e16290">
          <speaker>Pract. </speaker>
          <p>Pray send your Dub to fight one of them. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e16320">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>How do you mean? at Law? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e16350">
          <speaker>Instrum. </speaker>
          <p>Pox on him, he is rotten; give him Sack and Tobacco, and he'l make a shift to bawl; but Law, as Pluto observed, he hath none. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e16390">
          <speaker>Bishop </speaker>
          <p>Gentlemen, all's to no purpose, let us fall to making of Wills, for I see that what we intended against Coffophilo, hath overtaken us, as the Poet hath it. </p>
          <p>
            <q>
              <l>
                <foreign xml:lang="lat">Fallite fallentes ex magna parte profanum </foreign>
              </l>
              <l>
                <foreign xml:lang="lat">Sunt genus: in laqueos, quos posuere cadent. </foreign>
              </l>
              <l>Cousen the Couseners; commonly they be </l>
              <l>Profane: let their own snare their ruine be. </l>
            </q>
          </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e16510">
          <pb n="42" xml:id="ep000573-033-a"/>
          <speaker>Ordinary. </speaker>
          <p>Tell me Sir, what you would have done, and I will use my uttermost skill. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e16540">
          <speaker>Pluto, </speaker>
          <p>Write there: <hi>Whereas I </hi>Pluto <hi>being surprized with an infectious Disease, arising by frights, from the breath of </hi>Westminster-Hall, <hi>and finding my courage not sufficient to bear my Distempers, though once I thought I could have hush't Death, and silenced, or at least outbrav'd </hi>Magna Charta, <hi>do make this my last Will and Testament in manner following: </hi>
          </p>
          <p>Imprimis, <hi>I give to </hi>Fitton <hi>all his Estate, hoping he will let you, my Doctor, be Parson of </hi>Gansworth, <hi>and also suffer Sir </hi>Edward Lack-Latine, Edward Dicket, <hi>and both the </hi>Hollingsheads <hi>to enjoy their Leases I gave them for their good Services: you know Sir, they will stick at a mark, if swearing will do it, as well as </hi>Instrument. </p>
          <p>Item, <hi>I give Mr. </hi>Blundall <hi>his Estate, but the Rogue that betray'd him a Halter. </hi>
          </p>
          <p>Item, <hi>I give </hi>Delamere Forrest <hi>to the Commoners and right Owners, onely I cannot forget the damn'd Clowns that rose against us, when we went to enclose their Common. </hi>
          </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e16730">
          <speaker>Ordinary, </speaker>
          <p>Pray Sir be not disturb'd, but go on. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e16760">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Item, <hi>I giue the Military Ground and House to the Military Company; but for their Goods <pb n="43" xml:id="ep000573-033-b"/>and Library, they'r gone— Gentlemen, you all shar'd in that plunder, but you </hi>Instrument <hi>more especially</hi>. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e16810">
          <speaker>Ordinary. </speaker>
          <p>Pray be not in passion, but go on. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000573-e16840">
          <speaker>Pluto. </speaker>
          <p>Item, <hi>I give Sir </hi>John Morley <hi>the Grant of </hi>Newcastle, <hi>with the Honors, because his Grant is older then mine, and the Country doth not love me. </hi>
          </p>
          <p>Item. <hi>I give fat </hi>Will Loven <hi>his project of getting the </hi>Harringtons <hi>Estate, forfeited for Treason, and relapsed to the Crown ever since </hi>Hen. 7. and Hen 8.. <hi>If I had gone on with that design, I should have added to all my other wickedness, the ruine of many Families. </hi>
          </p>
          <p>Item, <hi>I give </hi>Percival Hart <hi>his Estate, because that damn'd blockhead </hi>Ward, <hi>together with you </hi>Lack-Latine and Instrument <hi>put me upon so open a design. </hi>
          </p>
          <p>Item, I give Enfield Chase <hi>to the right Owner old </hi>Salisbury, <hi>because he hath two Lives in the Chase before me. </hi>
          </p>
          <p>I <hi>would give </hi>Halsall <hi>to satisfie the Mortgage, and pay my Fathers debts, but Damme, </hi>Proserpine <hi>will want Tools for Cards and Dice. </hi>
          </p>
          <p>
            <hi>For that Rogue </hi>Coffophilo, Magna Charta <hi>threatens he will Administer, as chiefest Creditor, and pay </hi>Coffophilo <hi>his damages</hi>. </p>
          <p>
            <hi>And now my worthy Friends of the Sword and <pb n="44" xml:id="ep000573-034-a"/>the Law, and the rest of the Faculties, I do desire your excuses, for I am spent, and do not find any surplusage of Estate, which will remain as Assets to bequeath to you, only I give you free leave either to hang, drown, or poyson your selves, any way to speed and hasten your passage to our Infernal Kingdom. </hi>
          </p>
          <p>
            <hi>And lastly, for you my Dear </hi>Proserpine, <hi>I am glad I took thy counsel, and sold my Place, for reany money will do thee good when I am gone; and if this </hi>Coffophilo <hi>were by thy industrious Art knockt on the head, peradventure our </hi>Tragy-Comedie <hi>would never come upon the Stage: But alas! it nippeth my Soul to think, that Mortals shall Act thy Part and mine on their Stage, with the Worlds Applause, to our eternal Infamy. </hi>
          </p>
        </sp>
      </div>
      <div type="epilogue" xml:id="ep000573-e17210">
        <pb xml:id="ep000573-034-b"/>
        <head>Epilogue. </head>
        <l>SPectators, is it your desire to find </l>
        <l>Such <hi>Witty Jests </hi>as please a joyful mind? </l>
        <l>Go seek them where th'are, sure th'are to be had, </l>
        <l>'Tis not VVits recreation to be sad. </l>
        <l>VVit must avaunt, with all its Levities, </l>
        <l>VVhere heaviness becomes the Obsequies: </l>
        <l>For, if't be true, sad Objects do require </l>
        <l>Sad Thoughts, sad VVords, and sad Attire. </l>
        <l>Then do not (pray) my Muse for dulness tax, </l>
        <l>Since lighter Phansies sute not with her blacks. </l>
        <l>But, stay my Muse, thy Lines let PLUTO read, </l>
        <l>They will conduct him to a Grave or Bed; </l>
        <l>VVhere, when the Curtain's drawn, each active part </l>
        <l>will move, without instructions from Black Art; </l>
        <l>His nature motive is, in quest of ill, </l>
        <l>Stated in mischief, all his ablest skill; </l>
        <l>Neither know right from wrong, til wrong be done </l>
        <l>Fix Nature will, to condemn'd Customs run: </l>
        <l>Unchangedly, who to his sins can set. </l>
        <l>A certain end, when hath he never met </l>
        <l>Blushes once from his hardned forehead thrown, </l>
        <l>VVho is it sins, and is content with one? </l>
        <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000573-035-a"/>
        <l>No, no, our PLUTO hath mauy in store, </l>
        <l>And longs to Act them ore and ore: </l>
        <l>But <foreign xml:lang="lat">Magna Charta </foreign>stopp'd his intent, </l>
        <l>By a late Attachment, which he sent. </l>
        <l>Unto Sheriff— to execute, </l>
        <l>VVhich makes the Devil very mute; </l>
        <l>And now stands bound unto his good behavior </l>
        <l>And must neither kick, nor strike, nor swager: </l>
        <l>And therefore now, since Pluto is in bands, </l>
        <l>Let each with me rejoyce, and <hi>Clap their hands</hi>. </l>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
