<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eng000267" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Mariam, the Fair Queen of Jewry</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Elizabeth</forename>
            <surname>Cary</surname>
          </persName>
          <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q331855</idno>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A17956.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
        </bibl>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The tragedie of Mariam, the faire queene of Iewry. VVritten by that learned, vertuous, and truly noble ladie, E.C.</title>
            <author>Cary, Elizabeth, Lady, 1585 or 6-1639.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>36 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 January (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99843181</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 4613.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 308.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">7894</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17956</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2240952461</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The tragedie of Mariam, the faire queene of Iewry. VVritten by that learned, vertuous, and truly noble ladie, E.C.</title>
            <title type="alt">Mariam</title>
            <title type="alt">Mariam.</title>
            <title type="alt">Tragedie of Mariam, the faire queene of Jewry.</title>
            <author>Cary, Elizabeth, Lady, 1585 or 6-1639.</author>
            <author>Berkeley, Elizabeth, 1575-1635,</author>
            <author>Carey, Elizabeth, d. 1618,</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[70] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by Thomas Creede, for Richard Hawkins, and are to be solde at his shoppe in Chancery Lane, neere vnto Sargeants Inne,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date type="publication_date">1613.</date>
            <date type="creation_date">1604</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>E.C. = Elizabeth Cary, Viscountess Falkland. Also sometimes attributed to Lady Elizabeth Berkeley (nee Carey) and to her mother, Lady Elizabeth Carey.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: pi2 A4 (-A1) B-H4 I2.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The first leaf is blank.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>A1, originally with a dedication, is cancelled in most copies. Variant: A1 present.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <person xml:id="eng000267-mariam" sex="FEMALE">
            <persName>Mariam</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000267-alexandra" sex="FEMALE">
            <persName>Alexandra</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000267-nuntius" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Nuntius</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000267-salome" sex="FEMALE">
            <persName>Salome</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000267-silleus" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Silleus</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000267-constabarus" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Constabarus</persName>
          </person>
          <personGrp xml:id="eng000267-chorus" sex="UNKNOWN">
            <name>Chorus</name>
          </personGrp>
          <person xml:id="eng000267-pheroras" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Pheroras</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000267-graphina" sex="FEMALE">
            <persName>Graphina</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000267-babus_son_1" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Babus Son 1</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000267-babus_son_2" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Babus Son 2</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000267-doris" sex="FEMALE">
            <persName>Doris</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000267-antipater" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Antipater</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000267-ananell" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Ananell</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000267-servant" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Servant to Silleus</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000267-sohemus" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Sohemus</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000267-herod" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Herod</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="eng000267-butler" sex="MALE">
            <persName>Butler</persName>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
      <textClass>
        <classCode scheme="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q80930</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange>
        <change when="2022-06-16">(Luca Giovannini) fixed speaker tags and particDesc</change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1602">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
    <listRelation>
      <relation name="wikidata"
                   active="https://dracor.org/entity/eng000267"
                   passive="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q7769853"/>
    </listRelation>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="eng000267-e100030">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="eng000267-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="eng000267-001-b"/>
        <p>THE TRAGEDIE OF MARIAM, THE FAIRE Queene of Iewry. </p>
        <p>Written by that learned, vertuous, and truly noble Ladie, E. C. </p>
        <p>LONDON. Printed by Thomas Creede, for Richard Hawkins, and are to be solde at his shoppe in Chancery Lane, neere vnto Sargeants Inne. 1613. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="eng000267-e100070">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="eng000267-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="eng000267-002-b"/>
        <head>TO DIANAES EARTHLIE DEPVTESSE, and my worthy Sister, Mistris Elizabeth Carye. </head>
        <lg>
          <l>WHen cheerfull Phoebus his full course hath run, </l>
          <l>His sisters fainter beams our harts doth cheere: </l>
          <l>So your faire Brother is to mee the Sunne, </l>
          <l>And you his Sister as my Moone appeere. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>You are my next belou'd, my second Friend, </l>
          <l>For when my Phoebus absence makes it Night, </l>
          <l>Whilst to th'Antipodes his beames do bend, </l>
          <l>From you my Phoebe, shines my second Light. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Hee like to SOL, cleare-sighted, constant, free, </l>
          <l>You LVNA-like, vnspotted, chast, diuine: </l>
          <l>Hee shone on Sicily, you destin'd bee, </l>
          <l>T'illumine the now obscurde Palestine. </l>
          <l>My first was consecrated to Apollo, </l>
          <l>My second to DIANA now shall follow. </l>
        </lg>
        <signed>E. C. </signed>
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="eng000267-003-a"/>
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="eng000267-003-b"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="eng000267-e100270">
        <pb xml:id="eng000267-004-a"/>
        <head>The names of the Speakers. </head>
        <list>
          <item>Herod, King of Iudea. </item>
          <item>Doris, his first Wife. </item>
          <item>Mariam, his second Wife. </item>
          <item>Salome, Herods Sister. </item>
          <item>Antipater his sonne by Salome. </item>
          <item>Alexandra, Mariams mother. </item>
          <item>Sillius, Prince of Arabia. </item>
          <item>Constabarus, husband to Salome. </item>
          <item>Phaeroras, Herods Brother. </item>
          <item>Graphina, his Loue. </item>
          <item>Babus first Sonne. </item>
          <item>Babus second Sonne. </item>
          <item>Annanell, the high Priest. </item>
          <item>Sohemus, a counsellor to Herod. </item>
          <item>Nuntis. </item>
          <item>Bu. another Messenger. </item>
          <item>Chorus, a Companie of Iewes. </item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="argument" xml:id="eng000267-e100460">
        <pb xml:id="eng000267-004-b"/>
        <head>The Argument. </head>
        <p>HErod the sonne of Antipater (an Idumean,) hauing crept by the fauor of the Romanes, into the Iewish Monarchie, married Mariam the daughter of Hircanus, the rightfull King and Priest, and for her (besides her high blood, being of singular beautie) hee reputiated Doris, his former Wife, by whome hee had Children. </p>
        <p>This Mariam had a Brother called Aristobolus, and next him and Hircanus his Graund-father, Herod in his Wiues right had the best title. Therefore to remooue them, he charged the first with treason: and put him to death; and drowned the second vnder colour of sport. Alexandra, Daughter to the one, and Mother to the other, accused him for their deaths before Anthony. </p>
        <p>So when hee was forc'te to goe answere this Accusation at Rome, he left the custodie of his wife to Iosephus his Vncle, that had married his Sister Salome, and cut of a violent affection (vnwilling any should enioy her after him) hee gaue strict and priuate commaundement, that if hee were slaine, shee should be put to death. But he returned with much honour, yet found his Wife extreamely discontented, to whom Iosephus had (meaning it for the best, to proue Herod loued her) reuealed his charge. </p>
        <p>So by Salomes accusation hee put Iosephus to death, but was reconciled to Mariam, who still bare the death of her Friends exceeding hardly. </p>
        <p>In this meane time Herod was againe necessarily to reuisite Rome, for Caesar hauing ouerthrowne Anthony his <pb xml:id="eng000267-005-a"/>great friend, was likely to make an alteration of his Fortune. </p>
        <p>In his absence, newes came to Ierusalem that Caesar had put him to death, their willingnes it should be so, together with the likelyhood, gaue this Rumor so good credit, as Sohemus that had suceeded Iosephus charge, succeeded him likewise in reuealing it. So at Herods returne which was speedy and vnexpected, he found Mariam so farre from ioye, that she shewed apparant signes of sorrow. Hee still desiring to winne her to a better humour, she being very vnable to conceale her passion, fell to vpbraiding him with her Brothers death. As they were thus debating, came in a fellow with a Cuppe of Wine, who hired by Salome, saide first, it was a Loue potion, which Mariam desired to deliuer to the King: but afterwards he affirmed that it was a poyson, and that Sohemus had tolde her somewhat, which procured the vehement hate in her. </p>
        <p>The King hearing this, more moued with Iealousie of Sohemus, then with this intent of poyson, sent her away, and presently after by the instigation of Salome, she was beheaded. Which rashnes was afterward punished in him, with an intollerable and almost Frantike passion for her death. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="eng000267-e100540">
        <pb xml:id="eng000267-005-b"/>
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="eng000267-e100550">
          <head>Actus primus. Scoena prima. </head>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e100560">
            <speaker>Mariam sola. </speaker>
            <l>HOw oft haue I with publike voyce runne on? </l>
            <l>To censure Romes last Hero for deceit: </l>
            <l>Because he wept when Pompeis life was gone, </l>
            <l>Yet when he liu'd, hee thought his Name too great. </l>
            <l>But now I doe recant, and Roman Lord </l>
            <l>Excuse too rash a judgement in a woman: </l>
            <l>My Sexe pleads pardon, pardon then afford, </l>
            <l>Mistaking is with vs, but too too common. </l>
            <l>Now doe I finde by selfe Experience taught, </l>
            <l>One Object yeelds both griefe and ioy: </l>
            <l>You wept indeed, when on his worth you thought, </l>
            <l>But ioyd that slaughter did your Foe destroy. </l>
            <l>So at his death your Eyes true droppes did raine </l>
            <l>Whom dead, you did not wish aliue againe. </l>
            <l>When Herod liu'd, that now is done to death, </l>
            <l>Oft haue I wisht that I from him were free: </l>
            <l>Oft haue I wisht that he might lose his breath, </l>
            <l>Oft haue I wisht his Carkas dead to see. </l>
            <l>Then Rage and Scorne had put my loue to flight, </l>
            <l>That Loue which once on him was firmely set: </l>
            <l>Hate hid his true affection from my sight, </l>
            <l>And kept my heart from paying him his debt. </l>
            <l>And blame me not, for Herods Iealousie </l>
            <l>Had power euen constancie it selfe to change: </l>
            <l>For hee by barring me from libertie, </l>
            <l>To shunne my ranging, taught me first to range. </l>
            <l>But yet too chast a Scholler was my hart, </l>
            <l>To learne to loue another then my Lord: </l>
            <l>To leaue his Loue, my lessons former part, </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-006-a"/>
            <l>I quickly learn'd, the other I abhord. </l>
            <l>But now his death to memorie doth call, </l>
            <l>The tender loue, that he to Mariam bare: </l>
            <l>And mine to him, this makes those riuers fall, </l>
            <l>Which by an other thought vnmoistned are. </l>
            <l>For Aristobolus the lowlyest youth </l>
            <l>That euer did in Angels shape appeare: </l>
            <l>The cruell Herod was not mou'd to ruth, </l>
            <l>Then why grieues Mariam Herods death to heare? </l>
            <l>Why ioy I not the tongue no more shall speake, </l>
            <l>That yeelded forth my brothers latest dome: </l>
            <l>Both youth and beautie might thy furie breake, </l>
            <l>And both in him did ill befit a Tombe. </l>
            <l>And worthy Grandsire ill did he requite, </l>
            <l>His high Assent alone by thee procur'd, </l>
            <l>Except he murdred thee to free the spright </l>
            <l>Which still he thought on earth too long immur'd. </l>
            <l>How happie was it that Sohemus minde </l>
            <l>Was mou'd to pittie my distrest estate? </l>
            <l>Might Herods life a trustie seruant finde, </l>
            <l>My death to his had bene vnseparate. </l>
            <l>These thoughts haue power, his death to make me beare, </l>
            <l>Nay more, to wish the newes may firmely hold: </l>
            <l>Yet cannot this repulse some falling teare, </l>
            <l>That will against my will some griefe vnfold. </l>
            <l>And more I owe him for his loue to me, </l>
            <l>The deepest loue that euer yet was seene: </l>
            <l>Yet had I rather much a milke-maide bee, </l>
            <l>Then be the Monarke of Iudeas Queene. </l>
            <l>It was for nought but loue, he wisht his end </l>
            <l>Might to my death, but the vaunt-currier proue: </l>
            <l>But I had rather still be foe then friend, </l>
            <l>To him that saues for hate, and kills for loue. </l>
            <l>Hard-hearted Mariam, at thy discontent, </l>
            <l>What flouds of teares haue drencht his manly face? </l>
            <l>How canst thou then so faintly now lament, </l>
            <l>Thy truest louers death, a deaths disgrace: </l>
            <l>I now mine eyes you do begin to right </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-006-b"/>
            <l>The wrongs of your admirers. And my Lord, </l>
            <l>Long since you should haue put your smiles to flight, </l>
            <l>Ill doth a widowed eye with ioy accord. </l>
            <l>Why now me thinkes the loue I bare him then, </l>
            <l>When virgin freedome left me vnrestraind: </l>
            <l>Doth to my heart begin to creepe agen, </l>
            <l>My passion now is far from being faind. </l>
            <l>But teares flie backe, and hide you in your bankes, </l>
            <l>You must not be to Alexandra seene: </l>
            <l>For if my mone be spide, but little thankes </l>
            <l>Shall Mariam haue, from that incensed Queene. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="eng000267-e101350">
          <head>Actus primus: Scoena Secunda. </head>
          <stage xml:id="eng000267-e101360">Mariam. Alexandra. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000267-alexandra" xml:id="eng000267-e101370">
            <speaker>Alex: </speaker>
            <l>WHat meanes these teares? my Mariam doth mistake, </l>
            <l>The newes we heard did tell the Tyrants end: </l>
            <l>What weepst thou for thy brothers murthers sake, </l>
            <l>Will euer wight a teare for Herod spend? </l>
            <l>My curse pursue his breathles trunke and spirit, </l>
            <l>Base Edomite the damned Esaus heire: </l>
            <l>Must he ere Iacobs child the crowne inherit? </l>
            <l>Must he vile wretch be set in Dauids chaire? </l>
            <l>No Dauids soule within the bosome plac'te, </l>
            <l>Of our forefather Abram was asham'd: </l>
            <l>To see his seat with such a toade disgrac'te, </l>
            <l>That seat that hath by Iudas race bene fain'd. </l>
            <l>Thou fatall enemie to royall blood, </l>
            <l>Did not the murther of my boy suffice, </l>
            <l>To stop thy cruell mouth that gaping stood? </l>
            <l>But must thou dim the milde Hercanus eyes? </l>
            <l>My gratious father, whose too readie hand </l>
            <l>Did lift this Idumean from the dust: </l>
            <l>And he vngratefull catiffe did withstand, </l>
            <l>The man that did in him most friendly trust. </l>
            <l>What kingdomes right could cruell Herod claime, </l>
            <l>Was he not Esaus Issue, heyre of hell? </l>
            <l>Then what succession can he haue but shame? </l>
            <l>Did not his Ancestor his birth-right sell? </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-007-a"/>
            <l>O yes, he doth from Edoms name deriue, </l>
            <l>His cruell nature which with blood is fed: </l>
            <l>That made him me of Sire and sonne depriue, </l>
            <l>He euer thirsts for blood, and blood is red. </l>
            <l>Weepst thou because his loue to thee was bent? </l>
            <l>And readst thou loue in crimson caracters? </l>
            <l>Slew he thy friends to worke thy hearts content? </l>
            <l>No: hate may Iustly call that action hers. </l>
            <l>He gaue the sacred Priesthood for thy sake, </l>
            <l>To Aristobolus. Yet doomde him dead: </l>
            <l>Before his backe the Ephod warme could make, </l>
            <l>And ere the Myter setled on his head. </l>
            <l>Oh had he giuen my boy no lesse then right, </l>
            <l>The double oyle should to his forehead bring: </l>
            <l>A double honour, shining doubly bright, </l>
            <l>His birth annoynted him both Priest and King. </l>
            <l>And say my father, and my sonne he slewe, </l>
            <l>To royalize by right your Prince borne breath: </l>
            <l>Was loue the cause, can Mariam deeme it true, </l>
            <l>That Mariam gaue commandment for her death? </l>
            <l>I know by fits, he shewd some signes of loue, </l>
            <l>And yet not loue, but raging lunacie: </l>
            <l>And this his hate to thee may iustly proue, </l>
            <l>That sure he hates Hercanus familie. </l>
            <l>Who knowes if he vnconstant wauering Lord, </l>
            <l>His loue to Doris had renew'd againe? </l>
            <l>And that he might his bed to her afford, </l>
            <l>Perchance he wisht that Mariam might be slaine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-nuntius" xml:id="eng000267-e101900">
            <speaker>Nun: </speaker>
            <l>Doris, Alas her time of loue was past, </l>
            <l>Those coales were rakte in embers long agoe: </l>
            <l>If Mariams loue and she was now disgrast, </l>
            <l>Nor did I glorie in her ouerthrowe. </l>
            <l>He not a whit his first borne sonne esteem'd, </l>
            <l>Because as well as his he was not mine: </l>
            <l>My children onely for his owne he deem'd, </l>
            <l>These boyes that did descend from royall line. </l>
            <l>These did he stile his heyres to Dauids throne, </l>
            <l>My Alexander if he liue, shall sit </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-007-b"/>
            <l>In the Maiesticke seat of Salamon, </l>
            <l>To will it so, did Herod thinke it fit. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-alexandra" xml:id="eng000267-e102030">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Why? who can claime from Alexanders brood </l>
            <l>That Gold adorned Lyon-guarded Chaire? </l>
            <l>Was Alexander not of Dauids blood? </l>
            <l>And was not Mariam Alexanders heire? </l>
            <l>What more then right could Herod then bestow, </l>
            <l>And who will thinke except for more then right, </l>
            <l>He did not raise them, for they were not low, </l>
            <l>But borne to weare the Crowne in his despight: </l>
            <l>Then send those teares away that are not sent </l>
            <l>To thee by reason, but by passions power: </l>
            <l>Thine eyes to cheere, thy cheekes to smiles be bent, </l>
            <l>And entertaine with ioy this happy houre. </l>
            <l>Felicitie, if when shee comes, she findes </l>
            <l>A mourning habite, and a cheerlesse looke, </l>
            <l>Will thinke she is not welcome to thy minde, </l>
            <l>And so perchance her lodging will not brooke. </l>
            <l>Oh keepe her whilest thou hast her, if she goe </l>
            <l>She will not easily returne againe: </l>
            <l>Full many a yeere haue I indur'd in woe, </l>
            <l>Yet still haue sude her presence to obtaine: </l>
            <l>And did not I to her as presents send </l>
            <l>A Table, that best Art did beautifie </l>
            <l>Of two, to whom Heauen did best feature lend, </l>
            <l>To woe her loue by winning Anthony: </l>
            <l>For when a Princes fauour we doe craue, </l>
            <l>We first their Mynions loues do seeke to winne: </l>
            <l>So I, that sought Felicitie to haue, </l>
            <l>Did with her Mynion Anthony beginne, </l>
            <l>With double slight I sought to captiuate </l>
            <l>The warlike louer, but I did not right: </l>
            <l>For if my gift had borne but halfe the rate, </l>
            <l>The Roman had beene ouer-taken quite. </l>
            <l>But now he fared like a hungry guest, </l>
            <l>That to some plenteous festiuall is gone, </l>
            <l>Now this, now that, hee deems to eate were best, </l>
            <l>Such choice doth make him let them all alone. </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-008-a"/>
            <l>The boyes large forehead first did fayrest seeme </l>
            <l>Then glaunst his eye vpon my Mariams cheeke: </l>
            <l>And that without comparison did deeme, </l>
            <l>What was in eyther but he most did leeke. </l>
            <l>And thus distracted, eythers beauties might </l>
            <l>Within the others excellence was drown'd: </l>
            <l>Too much delight did bare him from delight, </l>
            <l>For eithers loue, the others did confound. </l>
            <l>Where if thy portraiture had onely gone, </l>
            <l>His life from Herod, Anthony had taken: </l>
            <l>He would haue loued thee, and thee alone, </l>
            <l>And left the browne Egyptian cleane forsaken. </l>
            <l>And Cleopatra then to seeke had bene, </l>
            <l>So firme a louer of her wayned face: </l>
            <l>Then great Anthonius fall we had not seene, </l>
            <l>By her that fled to haue him holde the chase. </l>
            <l>Then Mariam in a Romans Chariot set, </l>
            <l>In place of Cleopatra might haue showne: </l>
            <l>A mart of Beauties in her visage met, </l>
            <l>And part in this, that they were all her owne. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e102600">
            <speaker>Ma. </speaker>
            <l>Not to be Emprise of aspiring Rome, </l>
            <l>Would Mariam like to Cleopatra liue: </l>
            <l>With purest body will I presse my Toome, </l>
            <l>And wish no fauours Anthony could giue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-alexandra" xml:id="eng000267-e102650">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Let vs retire vs, that we may resolue </l>
            <l>How now to deale in this reuersed state: </l>
            <l>Great are th'affaires that we must now reuolue, </l>
            <l>And great affaires must not be taken late. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="eng000267-e102700">
          <head>Actus primus. Scoena tertia. </head>
          <stage xml:id="eng000267-e102710">Mariam. Alexandra. Salome. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e102720">
            <speaker>Salome. </speaker>
            <l>MOre plotting yet? Why? now you haue the thing </l>
            <l>For which so oft you spent your supliant breath: </l>
            <l>And Mariam hopes to haue another King, </l>
            <l>Her eyes doe sparkle ioy for Herods death. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="eng000267-008-b"/>
          <sp who="#eng000267-alexandra" xml:id="eng000267-e102770">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>If she desir'd another King to haue, </l>
            <l>She might before she came in Herods bed </l>
            <l>Haue had her wish. More Kings then one did craue, </l>
            <l>For leaue to set a Crowne vpon her head. </l>
            <l>I thinke with more then reason she laments, </l>
            <l>That she is freed from such a sad annoy: </l>
            <l>Who ist will weepe to part from discontent, </l>
            <l>And if she ioy, she did not causelesse ioy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e102860">
            <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
            <l>You durst not thus haue giuen your tongue the raine, </l>
            <l>If noble Herod still remaind in life: </l>
            <l>Your daughters betters farre I dare maintaine, </l>
            <l>Might haue reioyc'd to be my brothers wife. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e102910">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>My betters farre, base woman t'is vntrue, </l>
            <l>You scarce haue euer my superiors seene: </l>
            <l>For Mariams seruants were as good as you, </l>
            <l>Before she came to be Iudeas Queene. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e102960">
            <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
            <l>Now stirs the tongue that is so quickly mou'd, </l>
            <l>But more then once your collor haue I borne: </l>
            <l>Your fumish words are sooner sayd then prou'd, </l>
            <l>And Salomes reply is onely scorne. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e103010">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>Scorne those that are for thy companions held, </l>
            <l>Though I thy brothers face had neuer seene, </l>
            <l>My birth, thy baser birth so farre exceld, </l>
            <l>I had to both of you the Princesse bene. </l>
            <l>Thou party Iew, and party Edomite, </l>
            <l>Thou Mongrell: issu'd from reiected race, </l>
            <l>Thy Ancestors against the Heauens did fight, </l>
            <l>And thou like them wilt heauenly birth disgrace. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e103100">
            <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
            <l>Still twit you me with nothing but my birth, </l>
            <l>What ods betwixt your ancesters and mine? </l>
            <l>Both borne of Adam, both were made of Earth, </l>
            <l>And both did come from holy Abrahams line. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e103150">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>I fauour thee when nothing else I say, </l>
            <l>With thy blacke acts ile not pollute my breath: </l>
            <l>Else to thy charge I might full iustly lay </l>
            <l>A shamefull life, besides a husbands death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e103200">
            <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
            <l>Tis true indeed, I did the plots reueale, </l>
            <l>That past betwixt your fauorites and you: </l>
            <l>I ment not I, a traytor to conceale. </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-009-a"/>
            <l>Thus Salome your Mynion Ioseph slue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e103250">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>Heauen, dost thou meane this Infamy to smother? </l>
            <l>Let slandred Mariam ope thy closed eare: </l>
            <l>Selfe guilt hath euer bene suspitious mother, </l>
            <l>And therefore I this speech with patience beare. </l>
            <l>No, had not Salomes vnstedfast heart, </l>
            <l>In Iosephus stead her Constabarus plast, </l>
            <l>To free her selfe, she had not vsde the art, </l>
            <l>To slander haplesse Mariam for vnchast. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-alexandra" xml:id="eng000267-e103340">
            <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
            <l>Come Mariam, let vs goe: it is no boote </l>
            <l>To let the head contend against the foote. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="eng000267-e103370">
          <head>Actus primus. Scoena quarta. </head>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e103380">
            <speaker>Salome, Sola. </speaker>
            <l>LIues Salome, to get so base a stile </l>
            <l>As foote, to the proud Mariam Herods spirit: </l>
            <l>In happy time for her endured exile, </l>
            <l>For did he liue she should not misse her merit: </l>
            <l>But he is dead: and though he were my Brother, </l>
            <l>His death such store of Cinders cannot cast </l>
            <l>My Coales of loue to quench: for though they smother </l>
            <l>The flames a while, yet will they out at last. </l>
            <l>Oh blest Arabia, in best climate plast, </l>
            <l>I by the Fruit will censure of the Tree: </l>
            <l>Tis not in vaine, thy happy name thou hast, </l>
            <l>If all Arabians like Silleus bee: </l>
            <l>Had not my Fate bene too too contrary, </l>
            <l>When I on Constabarus first did gaze, </l>
            <l>Silleus had beene obiect to mine eye: </l>
            <l>Whose lookes and personage must allyes amaze. </l>
            <l>But now ill Fated Salome, thy tongue </l>
            <l>To Constabarus by it selfe is tide: </l>
            <l>And now except I doe the Ebrew wrong </l>
            <l>I cannot be the faire Arabian Bride: </l>
            <l>What childish lets are these? Why stand I now </l>
            <l>On honourable points? Tis long agoe </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-009-b"/>
            <l>Since shame was written on my tainted brow: </l>
            <l>And certaine tis, that shame is honours foe. </l>
            <l>Had I vpon my reputation stood, </l>
            <l>Had I affected an vnspotted life, </l>
            <l>Iosephus vaines had still bene stuft with blood, </l>
            <l>And I to him had liu'd a sober wife. </l>
            <l>Then had I neuer cast an eye of loue, </l>
            <l>On Constabarus now detested face, </l>
            <l>Then had I kept my thoughts without remoue </l>
            <l>And blusht at motion of the least disgrace: </l>
            <l>But shame is gone, and honour wipt away, </l>
            <l>And Impudencie on my forehead sits: </l>
            <l>She bids me worke my will without delay, </l>
            <l>And for my will I will imploy my wits. </l>
            <l>He loues, I loue; what then can be the cause, </l>
            <l>Keepes me for being the Arabians wife? </l>
            <l>It is the principles of Moses lawes, </l>
            <l>For Contabarus still remaines in life, </l>
            <l>If he to me did beare as Earnest hate, </l>
            <l>As I to him, for him there were an ease, </l>
            <l>A separating bill might free his fate: </l>
            <l>From such a yoke that did so much displease. </l>
            <l>Why should such priuiledge to man be giuen? </l>
            <l>Or giuen to them, why bard from women then? </l>
            <l>Are men then we in greater grace with Heauen? </l>
            <l>Or cannot women hate as well as men? </l>
            <l>Ile be the custome-breaker: and beginne </l>
            <l>To shew my Sexe the way to freedomes doore, </l>
            <l>And with an offring will I purge my sinne, </l>
            <l>The lawe was made for none but who are poore. </l>
            <l>If Herod had liu'd, I might to him accuse </l>
            <l>My present Lord. But for the futures sake </l>
            <l>Then would I tell the King he did refuse </l>
            <l>The sonnes of Baba in his power to take. </l>
            <l>But now I must diuorse him from my bed, </l>
            <l>That my Silleus may possesse his roome: </l>
            <l>Had I not begd his life he had bene dead, </l>
            <l>I curse my tongue the hindrer of his doome, </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-010-a"/>
            <l>But then my wandring heart to him was fast, </l>
            <l>Nor did I dreame of chaunge: Silleus said, </l>
            <l>He would be here, and see he comes at last, </l>
            <l>Had I not nam'd him longer had he staid. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="eng000267-e104030">
          <head>Actus primus. Scena quinta. </head>
          <stage xml:id="eng000267-e104040">Salome, Silleus. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000267-silleus" xml:id="eng000267-e104050">
            <speaker>Silleus. </speaker>
            <l>WEll found faire Salome Iudaeas pride, </l>
            <l>Hath thy innated wisedome found the way </l>
            <l>To make Silleus deeme him deified, </l>
            <l>By gaining thee a more then precious pray? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e104100">
            <speaker>Salo. </speaker>
            <l>I haue deuisde the best I can deuise, </l>
            <l>A more imperfect meanes was neuer found: </l>
            <l>But what cares Salome, it doth suffice </l>
            <l>If our indeuours with their end be crown'd. </l>
            <l>In this our land we haue an ancient vse, </l>
            <l>Permitted first by our law-giuers head: </l>
            <l>Who hates his wife, though for no iust abuse, </l>
            <l>May with a bill diuorce her from his bed. </l>
            <l>But in this custome women are not free, </l>
            <l>Yet I for once will wrest it, blame not thou </l>
            <l>The ill I doe, since what I do'es for thee, </l>
            <l>Though others blame, Silleus should allow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-silleus" xml:id="eng000267-e104230">
            <speaker>Solleus. </speaker>
            <l>Thinkes Salome, Silleus hath a tongue </l>
            <l>To censure her faire actions: let my blood </l>
            <l>Bedash my proper brow, for such a wrong, </l>
            <l>The being yours, can make euen vices good: </l>
            <l>Arabia ioy, prepare thy earth with greene, </l>
            <l>Thou neuer happie wert indeed till now: </l>
            <l>Now shall thy ground be trod by beauties Queene, </l>
            <l>Her foote is destin'd to depresse thy brow. </l>
            <l>Thou shalt faire Salome commaund as much </l>
            <l>As if the royall ornament were thine: </l>
            <l>The weaknes of Arabias King is such, </l>
            <l>The kingdome is not his so much as mine. </l>
            <l>My mouth is our Obodas oracle, </l>
            <l>Who thinkes not ought but what Silleus will? </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-010-b"/>
            <l>And thou rare creature. Asias miracle, </l>
            <l>Shalt be to me as It: Obodas still. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e104400">
            <speaker>Salome. </speaker>
            <l>Tis not for glory I thy loue accept, </l>
            <l>Iudea yeelds me honours worthy store: </l>
            <l>Had not affection in my bosome crept, </l>
            <l>My natiue country should my life deplore. </l>
            <l>Were not Silleus he with home I goe, </l>
            <l>I would not change my Palastine for Rome: </l>
            <l>Much lesse would I a glorious state to shew, </l>
            <l>Goe far to purchase an Arabian roome. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-silleus" xml:id="eng000267-e104490">
            <speaker>Silleus. </speaker>
            <l>Far be it from Silleus so to thinke, </l>
            <l>I know it is thy gratitude requites </l>
            <l>The loue that is in me, and shall not shrinke </l>
            <l>Till death doe seuer me from earths delights. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e104540">
            <speaker>Salom. </speaker>
            <l>But whist; me thinkes the wolfe is in our talke, </l>
            <l>Be gone Silleus, who doth here arriue? </l>
            <l>Tis Constabarus that doth hither walke, </l>
            <l>Ile find a quarrell, him from me to driue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-silleus" xml:id="eng000267-e104590">
            <speaker>Sille. </speaker>
            <l>Farewell, but were it not for thy commaund, </l>
            <l>In his despight Silleus here would stand. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="6" type="scene" xml:id="eng000267-e104620">
          <head>Actus primus: Scena Sexta </head>
          <stage xml:id="eng000267-e104630">Salome: Constabarus. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000267-constabarus" xml:id="eng000267-e104640">
            <speaker>Const: </speaker>
            <l>OH Salome, how much you wrong your name, </l>
            <l>Your race, your country, and your husband most? </l>
            <l>A straungers priuate conference is shame, </l>
            <l>I blush for you, that haue your blushing lost. </l>
            <l>Oft haue I found, and found you to my griefe, </l>
            <l>Consorted with this base Arabian heere: </l>
            <l>Heauen knowes that you haue bin my comfort chiefe, </l>
            <l>Then doe not now my greater plague appeare. </l>
            <l>Now by the stately Carued edifice </l>
            <l>That on Mount Sion makes so faire a show, </l>
            <l>And by the Altar fit for sacrifice, </l>
            <l>I loue thee more then thou thy selfe doest know. </l>
            <l>Oft with a silent sorrow haue I heard </l>
            <l>How ill Iudeas mouth doth censure thee: </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-011-a"/>
            <l>And did I not thine honour much regard, </l>
            <l>Thou shouldst not be exhorted thus for mee. </l>
            <l>Didst thou but know the worth of honest fame, </l>
            <l>How much a vertuous woman is esteem'd, </l>
            <l>Thou wouldest like hell eschew deserued shame, </l>
            <l>And seeke to be both chast and chastly deem'd. </l>
            <l>Our wisest Prince did say, and true he said, </l>
            <l>A vertuous woman crownes her husbands head. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e104870">
            <speaker>Salome. </speaker>
            <l>Did I for this, vpreare thy lowe estate? </l>
            <l>Did I for this requitall begge thy life, </l>
            <l>That thou hadst forfeited haples fate? </l>
            <l>To be to such a thankles wretch the wife. </l>
            <l>This hand of mine hath lifted vp thy head, </l>
            <l>Which many a day agoe had falne full lowe, </l>
            <l>Because the sonnes of Baba are not dead, </l>
            <l>To me thou doest both life and fortune owe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-constabarus" xml:id="eng000267-e104960">
            <speaker>Const. </speaker>
            <l>You haue my patience often exercisde, </l>
            <l>Vse make my choller keepe within the bankes: </l>
            <l>Yet boast no more, but be by me aduisde. </l>
            <l>A benefit vpbraided, forfeits thankes: </l>
            <l>I prethy Salome dismisse this mood, </l>
            <l>Thou doest not know how ill it fits thy place: </l>
            <l>My words were all intended for thy good, </l>
            <l>To raise thine honour and to stop disgrace. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e105050">
            <speaker>Sa. </speaker>
            <l>To stop disgrace? take thou no care for mee, </l>
            <l>Nay do thy worst, thy worst I set not by: </l>
            <l>No shame of mine is like to light on thee, </l>
            <l>Thy loue and admonitions I defie. </l>
            <l>Thou shalt no hower longer call me wife, </l>
            <l>Thy Iealousie procures my hate so deepe: </l>
            <l>That I from thee doe meane to free my life, </l>
            <l>By a diuorcing bill before I sleepe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-constabarus" xml:id="eng000267-e105140">
            <speaker>Const. </speaker>
            <l>Are Hebrew women now transform'd to men? </l>
            <l>Why do you not as well our battels fight, </l>
            <l>And weare our armour? suffer this, and then </l>
            <l>Let all the world be topsie turued quite. </l>
            <l>Let fishes graze, beastes, swine, and birds descend, </l>
            <l>Let fire burne downewarde whilst the earth aspires: </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-011-b"/>
            <l>Let Winters heat and Summers cold offend, </l>
            <l>Let Thistels growe on Vines, and Grapes on Briers, </l>
            <l>Set vs to Spinne or Sowe, or at the best </l>
            <l>Make vs Wood-hewers, Waters-bearing wights: </l>
            <l>For sacred seruice let vs take no rest, </l>
            <l>Vse vs as Ioshua did the Gibonites. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e105270">
            <speaker>Salom. </speaker>
            <l>Hold on your talke, till it be time to end, </l>
            <l>For me I am resolu'd it shall be so: </l>
            <l>Though I be first that to this course do bend, </l>
            <l>I shall not be the last full well I know. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-constabarus" xml:id="eng000267-e105320">
            <speaker>Const. </speaker>
            <l>Why then be witnesse Heau'n, the Iudge of sinnes, </l>
            <l>Be witnesse Spirits that eschew the darke: </l>
            <l>Be witnesse Angels, witnesse Cherubins, </l>
            <l>Whose semblance sits vpon the holy Arke: </l>
            <l>Be witnesse earth, be witnesse Palestine, </l>
            <l>Be witnesse Dauids Citie, if my heart </l>
            <l>Did euer merit such an act of thine: </l>
            <l>Or if the fault be mine that makes vs part, </l>
            <l>Since mildest Moses friend vnto the Lord, </l>
            <l>Did worke his wonders in the land of Ham, </l>
            <l>And slew the first-borne Babes without a sword, </l>
            <l>In signe whereof we eate the holy Lambe: </l>
            <l>Till now that foureteene hundred yeeres are past, </l>
            <l>Since first the Law with vs hath beene in force: </l>
            <l>You are the first, and will I hope, be last, </l>
            <l>That euer sought her husband to diuorce. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e105490">
            <speaker>Salom. </speaker>
            <l>I meane not to be led by president, </l>
            <l>My will shall be to me in stead of Law. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-constabarus" xml:id="eng000267-e105520">
            <speaker>Const. </speaker>
            <l>I feare me much you will too late repent, </l>
            <l>That you haue euer liu'd so void of awe: </l>
            <l>This is Silleus loue that makes you thus </l>
            <l>Reuerse all order: you must next be his. </l>
            <l>But if my thoughts aright the cause discusse, </l>
            <l>In winning you, he gaines no lasting blisse, </l>
            <l>I was Silleus and not long agoe </l>
            <l>Iosephus then was Constabarus now: </l>
            <l>When you became my friend you prou'd his foe, </l>
            <l>As now for him you breake to me your vowd. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="eng000267-012-a"/>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e105630">
            <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
            <l>If once I lou'd you, greater is your debt: </l>
            <l>For certaine tis that you deserued it not. </l>
            <l>And vndeserued loue we soone forget, </l>
            <l>And therefore that to me can be no blot. </l>
            <l>But now fare ill my once beloued Lord, </l>
            <l>Yet neuer more belou'd then now abhord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-constabarus" xml:id="eng000267-e105700">
            <speaker>Const. </speaker>
            <l>Yet Constabarus biddeth thee farewell. </l>
            <l>Farewell light creature. Heauen forgiue thy sinne: </l>
            <l>My prophecying spirit doth foretell </l>
            <l>Thy wauering thoughts doe yet but new beginne. </l>
            <l>Yet I haue better scap'd then Ioseph did, </l>
            <l>But if our Herods death had bene delayd, </l>
            <l>The valiant youths that I so long haue hid, </l>
            <l>Had bene by her, and I for them betrayd. </l>
            <l>Therefore in happy houre did Caesar giue </l>
            <l>The fatall blow to wanton Anthony. </l>
            <l>For had he liued, our Herod then should liue, </l>
            <l>But great Anthonius death made Herod dye. </l>
            <l>Had he enioyed his breath, not I alone </l>
            <l>Had beene in danger of a deadly fall: </l>
            <l>But Mariam had the way of perill gone, </l>
            <l>Though by the Tyrant most belou'd of all. </l>
            <l>The sweet fac'd Mariam as free from guilt </l>
            <l>As Heauen from spots, yet had her Lord come backe </l>
            <l>Her purest blood had bene vniustly spilt. </l>
            <l>And Salome it was would worke her wracke. </l>
            <l>Though all Iudea yeeld her innocent, </l>
            <l>She often hath bene neere to punishment. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-chorus" xml:id="eng000267-e105930">
            <speaker>Chorus. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>THose mindes that wholy dote vpon delight, </l>
              <l>Except they onely ioy in inward good: </l>
              <l>Still hope at last to hop vpon the right, </l>
              <l>And so from Sand they leape in loathsome mud. </l>
              <l>Fond wretches, seeking what they cannot finde, </l>
              <l>For no content attends a wauering minde. </l>
              <l>If wealth they doe desire, and wealth attaine, </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000267-012-b"/>
              <l>Then wondrous faine would they to honor lep: </l>
              <l>Of meane degree they doe in honor gaine, </l>
              <l>They would but wish a little higher step. </l>
              <l>Thus step to step, and wealth to wealth they ad, </l>
              <l>Yet cannot all their plenty make them glad. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Yet oft we see that some in humble state, </l>
              <l>Are cheerfull, pleasant, happy, and content: </l>
              <l>When those indeed that are of higher state, </l>
              <l>With vaine additions do their thoughts torment. </l>
              <l>Th'one would to his minde his fortune binde, </l>
              <l>T'hother to his fortune frames his minde. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>To wish varietie is signe of griefe, </l>
              <l>For if you like your state as now it is, </l>
              <l>Why should an alteration bring reliefe? </l>
              <l>Nay change would then be fear'd as losse of blis. </l>
              <l>That man is onely happy in his Fate, </l>
              <l>That is delighted in a setled state. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Still Mariam wisht she from her Lord were free, </l>
              <l>For expectation of varietie: </l>
              <l>Yet now she sees her wishes prosperous bee, </l>
              <l>She grieues, because her Lord so soone did die. </l>
              <l>Who can those vast imaginations feede, </l>
              <l>Where in a propertie, contempt doth breede? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Were Herod now perchance to liue againe, </l>
              <l>She would againe as much be grieued at that: </l>
              <l>All that she may, she euer doth disdaine, </l>
              <l>Her wishes guide her to she knowes not what. </l>
              <l>And sad must be their lookes, their honor sower, </l>
              <l>That care for nothing being in their power. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="eng000267-e106360">
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="eng000267-e106370">
          <head>Actus secundus. Scoena prima. </head>
          <stage xml:id="eng000267-e106380">Pheroras and Graphina. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000267-pheroras" xml:id="eng000267-e106390">
            <speaker>Pher. </speaker>
            <l>TIs true Graphina, now the time drawes nye </l>
            <l>Wherin the holy Priest with hallowed right, </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-013-a"/>
            <l>The happy long desired knot shall tie, </l>
            <l>Pheroras and Graphina to vnite: </l>
            <l>How oft haue I with lifted hands implor'd </l>
            <l>This blessed houre, till now implord in vaine, </l>
            <l>Which hath my wished libertie restor'd, </l>
            <l>And made my subiect selfe my owne againe. </l>
            <l>Thy loue faire Mayd vpon mine eye doth sit, </l>
            <l>Whose nature hot doth dry the moysture all, </l>
            <l>Which were in nature, and in reason fit </l>
            <l>For my monachall Brothers death to fall: </l>
            <l>Had Herod liu'd, he would haue pluckt my hand </l>
            <l>From faire Graphinas Palme perforce: and tide </l>
            <l>The same in hatefull and despised band, </l>
            <l>For I had had a Baby to my Bride: </l>
            <l>Scarce can her Infant tongue with easie voice </l>
            <l>Her name distinguish to anothers eare: </l>
            <l>Yet had he liu'd, his power, and not my choise </l>
            <l>Had made me solembly the contract sweare. </l>
            <l>Haue I not cause in such a change to ioy? </l>
            <l>What? though she be my Neece, a Princesse borne: </l>
            <l>Neere bloods without respect: high birth a toy. </l>
            <l>Since Loue can teach blood and kindreds scorne. </l>
            <l>What booted it that he did raise my head, </l>
            <l>To be his Realmes Copartner, Kingdomes mate, </l>
            <l>Withall, he kept Graphina from my bed, </l>
            <l>More wisht by me then thrice Iudeas state. </l>
            <l>Oh, could not he be skilfull Iudge in loue, </l>
            <l>That doted so vpon his Mariams face? </l>
            <l>He, for his passion, Doris did remoue. </l>
            <l>I needed not a lawfull Wife displace, </l>
            <l>It could not be but he had power to iudge, </l>
            <l>But he that neuer grudg'd a Kingdomes share, </l>
            <l>This well knowne happinesse to me did grudge: </l>
            <l>And ment to be therein without compare. </l>
            <l>Else had I bene his equall in loues hoast, </l>
            <l>For though the Diadem on Mariams head </l>
            <l>Corrupt the vulgar iudgements, I will boast </l>
            <l>Graphina: brow's as white, her cheekes as red. </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-013-b"/>
            <l>Why speaks thou not faire creature? moue thy tongue, </l>
            <l>For Silence is a signe of discontent: </l>
            <l>It were to both our loues too great a wrong </l>
            <l>If now this hower do find thee sadly bent. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-graphina" xml:id="eng000267-e106840">
            <speaker>Graph. </speaker>
            <l>Mistake me not my Lord, too oft haue I </l>
            <l>Desir'd this time to come with winged feete, </l>
            <l>To be inwrapt with griefe when tis too nie, </l>
            <l>You know my wishes euer yours did meete: </l>
            <l>If I be silent, tis no more but feare </l>
            <l>That I should say too little when I speake: </l>
            <l>But since you will my imperfections beare, </l>
            <l>In spight of doubt I will my silence breake: </l>
            <l>Yet might amazement tie my mouing tongue, </l>
            <l>But that I know before Pheroras minde, </l>
            <l>I haue admired your affection long: </l>
            <l>And cannot yet therein a reason finde. </l>
            <l>Your hand hath lifted me from lowest state, </l>
            <l>To highest eminencie wondrous grace, </l>
            <l>And me your hand-maid haue you made your mate, </l>
            <l>Though all but you alone doe count me base. </l>
            <l>You haue preserued me pure at my request, </l>
            <l>Though you so weake a vassaile might constraine </l>
            <l>To yeeld to your high will, then last not best </l>
            <l>In my respect a Princesse you disdaine, </l>
            <l>Then need not all these fauours studie craue, </l>
            <l>To be requited by a simple maide: </l>
            <l>And studie still you know must silence haue, </l>
            <l>Then be my cause for silence iustly waide, </l>
            <l>But studie cannot boote nor I requite, </l>
            <l>Except your lowly hand-maides steadfast loue </l>
            <l>And fast obedience may your mind delight, </l>
            <l>I will not promise more then I can proue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-pheroras" xml:id="eng000267-e107130">
            <speaker>Phero. </speaker>
            <l>That studie needs not let Graphina smile, </l>
            <l>And I desire no greater recompence: </l>
            <l>I cannot vaunt me in a glorious stile, </l>
            <l>Nor shew my loue in far-fetcht eloquence: </l>
            <l>But this beleeue me, neuer Herods heart </l>
            <l>Hath held his Prince-borne beautie famed wife </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-014-a"/>
            <l>In neerer place then thou faire virgin art, </l>
            <l>To him that holds the glory of his life. </l>
            <l>Should Herods body leaue the Sepulcher, </l>
            <l>And entertaine the seuer'd ghost againe: </l>
            <l>He should not be my nuptiall hinderer, </l>
            <l>Except he hindred it with dying paine. </l>
            <l>Come faire Graphina, let vs goe in state, </l>
            <l>This wish-indeered time to celebrate. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="eng000267-e107280">
          <head>Actus 2. Scena. 2. </head>
          <stage xml:id="eng000267-e107290">Constabarus and Babus Sonnes. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000267-babus_son_1" xml:id="eng000267-e107300">
            <speaker>Babus. 1. Sonne. </speaker>
            <l>NOw valiant friend you haue our liues redeem'd, </l>
            <l>Which liues as sau'd by you, to you are due: </l>
            <l>Command and you shall see your selfe esteem'd, </l>
            <l>Our liues and liberties belong to you. </l>
            <l>This twice sixe yeares with hazard of your life, </l>
            <l>You haue conceal'd vs from the tyrants sword: </l>
            <l>Though cruell Herods sister were your wife, </l>
            <l>You durst in scorne of feare this grace afford. </l>
            <l>In recompence we know not what to say, </l>
            <l>A poore reward were thankes for such a merit, </l>
            <l>Our truest friendship at your feete we lay, </l>
            <l>The best requitall to a noble spirit. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-constabarus" xml:id="eng000267-e107430">
            <speaker>Const. </speaker>
            <l>Oh how you wrong our friendship valiant youth, </l>
            <l>With friends there is not such a word as det: </l>
            <l>Where amitie is tide with bond of truth, </l>
            <l>All benefits are there in common set. </l>
            <l>Then is the golden age with them renew'd, </l>
            <l>All names of properties are banisht quite: </l>
            <l>Diuision, and distinction, are eschew'd: </l>
            <l>Each hath to what belongs to others right. </l>
            <l>And tis not sure so full a benefit, </l>
            <l>Freely to giue, as freely to require: </l>
            <l>A bountious act hath glory following it, </l>
            <l>They cause the glory that the act desire. </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-014-b"/>
            <l>All friendship should the patterne imitate, </l>
            <l>Of Iesses Sonne and valiant Ionathans </l>
            <l>For neither Soueraignes nor fathers hate, </l>
            <l>A friendship fixt on vertue seuer can. </l>
            <l>Too much of this, tis written in the heart, </l>
            <l>And need no amplifying with the tongue: </l>
            <l>Now may you from your liuing tombe depart, </l>
            <l>Where Herods life hath kept you ouer long. </l>
            <l>Too great an iniury to a noble minde, </l>
            <l>To be quicke buried, you had purchast fame, </l>
            <l>Some yeares a goe, but that you were confinde. </l>
            <l>While thousand meaner did aduance their name. </l>
            <l>Your best of life the prime of all your yeares, </l>
            <l>Your time of action is from you bereft. </l>
            <l>Twelue winters haue you operpast in feares: </l>
            <l>Yet if you vse it well, enough is left. </l>
            <l>And who can doubt but you will vse it well? </l>
            <l>The sonnes of Babus haue it by descent: </l>
            <l>In all their thoughts each action to excell, </l>
            <l>Boldly to act, and wisely to inuent. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-babus_son_2" xml:id="eng000267-e107760">
            <speaker>Babus 2. Sonne. </speaker>
            <l>Had it not like the hatefull cuckoe beene, </l>
            <l>Whose riper age his infant nurse doth kill: </l>
            <l>So long we had not kept our selues vnseene, </l>
            <l>But Constabarus safely crost our will: </l>
            <l>For had the Tyrant fixt his cruell eye, </l>
            <l>On our concealed faces wrath had swaide </l>
            <l>His Iustice so, that he had forst vs die. </l>
            <l>And dearer price then life we should haue paid, </l>
            <l>For you our truest friend had falne with vs: </l>
            <l>And we much like a house on pillers set, </l>
            <l>Had cleane deprest our prop, and therefore thus </l>
            <l>Our readie will with our concealement met. </l>
            <l>But now that you faire Lord are daungerlesse, </l>
            <l>The Sonnes of Baba shall their rigor show: </l>
            <l>And proue it was not basenes did oppresse </l>
            <l>Our hearts so long, but honour kept them low. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-babus_son_1" xml:id="eng000267-e107930">
            <speaker>Ba. 1. Sonne. </speaker>
            <l>Yet do I feare this tale of Herods death, </l>
            <l>At last will proue a very tale indeed: </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-015-a"/>
            <l>It giues me strongly in my minde, his breath </l>
            <l>Will be preseru'd to make a number bleed: </l>
            <l>I wish not therefore to be set at large, </l>
            <l>Yet perill to my selfe I do not feare: </l>
            <l>Let vs for some daies longer be your charge, </l>
            <l>Till we of Herods state the truth do heare. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-constabarus" xml:id="eng000267-e108020">
            <speaker>Const. </speaker>
            <l>What art thou turn'd a coward noble youth, </l>
            <l>That thou beginst to doubt, vndoubted truth? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-babus_son_1" xml:id="eng000267-e108050">
            <speaker>Babus. 1. Son. </speaker>
            <l>Were it my brothers tongue that cast this doubt, </l>
            <l>I from his hart would haue the question out: </l>
            <l>With this keene fauchion, but tis you my Lord </l>
            <l>Against whose head I must not lift a sword: </l>
            <l>I am so tide in gratitude Const. belieue </l>
            <l>You haue no cause to take it ill, </l>
            <l>If any word of mine your heart did grieue </l>
            <l>The word discented from the speakers will, </l>
            <l>I know it was not feare the doubt begun, </l>
            <l>But rather valour and your care of me, </l>
            <l>A coward could not be your fathers sonne, </l>
            <l>Yet know I doubts vnnecessarie be: </l>
            <l>For who can thinke that in Anthonius fall, </l>
            <l>Herod his bosome friend should scape vnbrusde: </l>
            <l>Then Caesar we might thee an idiot call, </l>
            <l>If thou by him should'st be so farre abusde. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-babus_son_2" xml:id="eng000267-e108220">
            <speaker>Babus. 2. Sonne. </speaker>
            <l>Lord Constab: let me tell you this, </l>
            <l>Vpon submission Caesar will forgiue: </l>
            <l>And therefore though the tyrant did amisse, </l>
            <l>It may fall out that he will let him liue. </l>
            <l>Not many yeares agone it is since I </l>
            <l>Directed thither by my fathers care, </l>
            <l>In famous Rome for twice twelue monthes did liue, </l>
            <l>My life from Hebrewes crueltie to spare, </l>
            <l>There though I were but yet of boyish age, </l>
            <l>I bent mine eye to marke, mine eares to heare. </l>
            <l>Where I did see Octauious then a page, </l>
            <l>When first he did to Iulions sight appeare: </l>
            <l>Me thought I saw such mildnes in his face, </l>
            <l>And such a sweetnes in his lookes did grow, </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-015-b"/>
            <l>Withall, commixt with so maiesticke grace, </l>
            <l>His Phisnomy his Fortune did foreshow: </l>
            <l>For this I am indebted to mine eye, </l>
            <l>But then mine eare receiu'd more euidence, </l>
            <l>By that I knew his loue to clemency, </l>
            <l>How he with hottest choller could dispence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-constabarus" xml:id="eng000267-e108430">
            <speaker>Const. </speaker>
            <l>But we haue more then barely heard the news, </l>
            <l>It hath bin twice confirm'd. And though some tongue </l>
            <l>Might be so false, with false report t'abuse, </l>
            <l>A false report hath neuer lasted long. </l>
            <l>But be it so that Herod haue his life, </l>
            <l>Concealement would not then a whit auaile: </l>
            <l>For certaine t'is, that she that was my wife, </l>
            <l>Would not to set her accusation faile. </l>
            <l>And therefore now as good the venture giue, </l>
            <l>And free our selues from blot of cowardise: </l>
            <l>As show a pittifull desire to liue, </l>
            <l>For, who can pittie but they must despise? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-babus_son_1" xml:id="eng000267-e108560">
            <speaker>Babus first sonne. </speaker>
            <l>I yeeld, but to necessitie I yeeld, </l>
            <l>I dare vpon this doubt ingage mine arme: </l>
            <l>That Herod shall againe this kingdome weeld, </l>
            <l>And proue his death to be a false alarme. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-babus_son_2" xml:id="eng000267-e108610">
            <speaker>Babus second sonne. </speaker>
            <l>I doubt it too: God grant it be an error, </l>
            <l>Tis best without a cause to be in terror: </l>
            <l>And rather had I, though my soule be mine, </l>
            <l>My soule should lie, then proue a true diuine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-constabarus" xml:id="eng000267-e108660">
            <speaker>Const. </speaker>
            <l>Come, come, let feare goe seeke a dastards nest, </l>
            <l>Vndanted courage lies in a noble brest. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="eng000267-e108690">
          <head>Actus 2. Scoena 3. </head>
          <stage xml:id="eng000267-e108700">Doris and Antipater. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000267-doris" xml:id="eng000267-e108710">
            <speaker>Dor. </speaker>
            <l>YOur royall buildings bow your loftie side, </l>
            <l>And scope to her that is by right your Queen: </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-016-a"/>
            <l>Let your humilitie vpbraid the pride </l>
            <l>Of those in whom no due respect is seene: </l>
            <l>Nine times haue we with Trumpets haughtie sound, </l>
            <l>And banishing sow'r Leauen from our taste: </l>
            <l>Obseru'd the feast that takes the fruit from ground. </l>
            <l>Since I faire Citie did behold thee last, </l>
            <l>So long it is since Mariams purer cheeke </l>
            <l>Did rob from mine the glory. And so long </l>
            <l>Since I returnd my natiue Towne to seeke: </l>
            <l>And with me nothing but the sense of wrong. </l>
            <l>And thee my Boy, whose birth though great it were, </l>
            <l>Yet haue thy after fortunes prou'd but poore: </l>
            <l>When thou wert borne how little did I feare </l>
            <l>Thou shouldst be thrust from forth thy Fathers doore. </l>
            <l>Art thou not Herods right begotten Sonne? </l>
            <l>Was not the haples Doris, Herods wife? </l>
            <l>Yes: ere he had the Hebrew kingdome wonne, </l>
            <l>I was companion to his priuate life. </l>
            <l>Was I not faire enough to be a Queene? </l>
            <l>Why ere thou wert to me false Monarch tide, </l>
            <l>My lake of beauty might as well be seene, </l>
            <l>As after I had liu'd fiue yeeres thy Bride. </l>
            <l>Yet then thine oath came powring like the raine, </l>
            <l>Which all affirm'd my face without compare: </l>
            <l>And that if thou might'st Doris loue obtaine, </l>
            <l>For all the world besides thou didst not care. </l>
            <l>Then was I yong, and rich, and nobly borne, </l>
            <l>And therefore worthy to be Herods mate: </l>
            <l>Yet thou vngratefull cast me off with scorne, </l>
            <l>When Heauens purpose raisd your meaner fate. </l>
            <l>Oft haue I begd for vengeance for this fact, </l>
            <l>And with deiected knees, aspiring hands </l>
            <l>Haue prayd the highest power to inact </l>
            <l>The fall of her that on my Trophee stands. </l>
            <l>Reuenge I haue according to my will, </l>
            <l>Yet where I wisht this vengeance did not light: </l>
            <l>I wisht it should high-hearted Mariam kill. </l>
            <l>But it against my whilome Lord did fight </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-016-b"/>
            <l>With thee sweet Boy I came, and came to try </l>
            <l>If thou before his bastards might be plac'd </l>
            <l>In Herods royall seat and dignitie. </l>
            <l>But Mariams infants here are onely grac'd, </l>
            <l>And now for vs there doth no hope remaine: </l>
            <l>Yet we will not returne till Herods end </l>
            <l>Be more confirmd, perchance he is not slaine. </l>
            <l>So glorious Fortunes may my Boy attend, </l>
            <l>For if he liue, hee'll thinke it doth suffice, </l>
            <l>That he to Doris shows such crueltie: </l>
            <l>For as he did my wretched life dispise, </l>
            <l>So doe I know I shall despised die. </l>
            <l>Let him but proue as naturall to thee, </l>
            <l>As cruell to thy miserable mother: </l>
            <l>His crueltie shall not vpbraided bee </l>
            <l>But in thy fortunes. I his faults will smother. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-antipater" xml:id="eng000267-e109280">
            <speaker>Antipat. </speaker>
            <l>Each mouth within the Citie loudly cries </l>
            <l>That Herods death is certaine: therefore wee </l>
            <l>Had best some subtill hidden plot deuise, </l>
            <l>That Mariams children might subuerted bee, </l>
            <l>By poisons drinke, or else by murtherous Knife, </l>
            <l>So we may be aduanc'd, it skils not how: </l>
            <l>They are but Bastards, you were Herods wife, </l>
            <l>And foule adultery blotteth Mariams brow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-doris" xml:id="eng000267-e109370">
            <speaker>Doris. </speaker>
            <l>They are too strong to be by vs remou'd, </l>
            <l>Or else reuenges foulest spotted face: </l>
            <l>By our detested wrongs might be approu'd, </l>
            <l>But weakenesse must to greater power giue place. </l>
            <l>But let vs now retire to grieue alone, </l>
            <l>For solitarines best fitteth mone. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="eng000267-e109440">
          <head>Actus secundus. Scoena 4. </head>
          <stage xml:id="eng000267-e109450">Silleus and Constabarus. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000267-silleus" xml:id="eng000267-e109460">
            <speaker>Silleus. </speaker>
            <l>WEll met Iudean Lord, the onely wight </l>
            <l>Silleus wisht to see. I am to call </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-017-a"/>
            <l>Thy tongue to strict account. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-constabarus" xml:id="eng000267-e109500">
            <speaker>Const. </speaker>
            <l>For what despight </l>
            <l>I ready am to heare, and answere all. </l>
            <l>But if directly at the cause I gesse </l>
            <l>That breeds this challenge, you must pardon me: </l>
            <l>And now some other ground of fight professe, </l>
            <l>For I haue vow'd, vowes must vnbroken be. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-silleus" xml:id="eng000267-e109570">
            <speaker>Sill. </speaker>
            <l>What may be your expectation? let me know. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-constabarus" xml:id="eng000267-e109590">
            <speaker>Const. </speaker>
            <l>Why? ought concerning Salom, my sword </l>
            <l>Shall not be welded for a cause so low, </l>
            <l>A blow for her my arme will scorne t'afford. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-silleus" xml:id="eng000267-e109630">
            <speaker>Sill. </speaker>
            <l>It is for slandering her vnspotted name, </l>
            <l>And I will make thee in thy vowes despight, </l>
            <l>Sucke vp the breath that did my Mistris blame, </l>
            <l>And swallow it againe to doe her right. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-constabarus" xml:id="eng000267-e109680">
            <speaker>Const. </speaker>
            <l>I prethee giue some other quarrell ground </l>
            <l>To finde beginning, raile against my name: </l>
            <l>Or strike me first, or let some scarlet wound </l>
            <l>Inflame my courage, giue me words of shame, </l>
            <l>Doe thou our Moses sacred Lawes disgrace, </l>
            <l>Depraue our nation, doe me some despight: </l>
            <l>I'm apt enough to fight in any case, </l>
            <l>But yet for Salome I will not fight. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-silleus" xml:id="eng000267-e109770">
            <speaker>Sill. </speaker>
            <l>Nor I for ought but Salome: My sword </l>
            <l>That owes his seruice to her sacred name: </l>
            <l>Will not an edge for other cause afford, </l>
            <l>In other fight I am not sure of fame. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-constabarus" xml:id="eng000267-e109820">
            <speaker>Const. </speaker>
            <l>For her, I pitty thee enough already, </l>
            <l>For her, I therefore will not mangle thee: </l>
            <l>A woman with a heart so most vnsteady, </l>
            <l>Will of her selfe sufficient torture bee. </l>
            <l>I cannot enuy for so light a gaine, </l>
            <l>Her minde with such vnconstancie doth runne: </l>
            <l>As with a word thou didst her loue obtaine, </l>
            <l>So with a word she will from thee be wonne. </l>
            <l>So light as her possessions for most day </l>
            <l>Is her affections lost, to me tis knowne: </l>
            <l>As good goe hold the winde as make her stay, </l>
            <l>Shee neuer loues, but till she call her owne. </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-017-b"/>
            <l>She meerly is a painted sepulcher, </l>
            <l>That is both faire, and vilely foule at once: </l>
            <l>Though on her out-side graces garnish her, </l>
            <l>Her mind is fild with worse then rotten bones. </l>
            <l>And euer readie lifted is her hand, </l>
            <l>To aime destruction at a husbands throat: </l>
            <l>For proofes, Iosephus and my selfe do stand, </l>
            <l>Though once on both of vs, she seem'd to do at. </l>
            <l>Her mouth though serpent-like it neuer hisses, </l>
            <l>Yet like a Serpent, poysons where it kisses. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-silleus" xml:id="eng000267-e110050">
            <speaker>Silleus. </speaker>
            <l>Well Hebrew well, thou bark'st, but wilt not bite. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-constabarus" xml:id="eng000267-e110070">
            <speaker>Const. </speaker>
            <l>I tell thee still for her I will not fight. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-silleus" xml:id="eng000267-e110090">
            <speaker>Sille: </speaker>
            <l>Why then I call thee coward. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-constabarus" xml:id="eng000267-e110110">
            <speaker>Const: </speaker>
            <l>From my heart </l>
            <l>I giue thee thankes. A cowards hatefull name, </l>
            <l>Cannot to valiant mindes a blot impart, </l>
            <l>And therefore I with ioy receiue the same. </l>
            <l>Thou know'st I am no coward: thou wert by </l>
            <l>At the Arabian battaile th'other day: </l>
            <l>And saw'st my sword with daring valiancy, </l>
            <l>Amongst the faint Arabians cut my way. </l>
            <l>The blood of foes no more could let it shine, </l>
            <l>And twas inameled with some of thine. </l>
            <l>But now haue at thee, not for Salome </l>
            <l>I fight: but to discharge a cowards stile: </l>
            <l>Here gins the fight that shall not parted be, </l>
            <l>Before a soule or two indure exile. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-silleus" xml:id="eng000267-e110260">
            <speaker>Silleus. </speaker>
            <l>Thy sword hath made some windowes for my blood, </l>
            <l>To shew a horred crimson phisnomie: </l>
            <l>To breath for both of vs me thinkes twere good, </l>
            <l>The day will giue vs time enough to die. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-constabarus" xml:id="eng000267-e110310">
            <speaker>Const: </speaker>
            <l>With all my hart take breath, thou shalt haue time, </l>
            <l>And if thou list a twelue month, let vs end: </l>
            <l>Into thy cheekes there doth a palenes clime, </l>
            <l>Thou canst not from my sword thy selfe defend. </l>
            <l>What needest thou for Salome to fight, </l>
            <l>Thou hast her, and may'st keepe her, none striues for her: </l>
            <l>I willingly to thee resigne my right, </l>
            <l>For in my very soule I do abhorre her. </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-018-a"/>
            <l>Thou seest that I am fresh, vnwounded yet, </l>
            <l>Then not for feare I do this offer make: </l>
            <l>Thou art with losse of blood, to fight vnfit, </l>
            <l>For here is one, and there another take. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-silleus" xml:id="eng000267-e110440">
            <speaker>Silleus. </speaker>
            <l>I will not leaue as long as breath remaines </l>
            <l>Within my wounded body: spare your words, </l>
            <l>My heart in bloods stead, courage entertaines, </l>
            <l>Salomes loue no place for feare affords. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-constabarus" xml:id="eng000267-e110490">
            <speaker>Const: </speaker>
            <l>Oh could thy soule but prophesie like mine, </l>
            <l>I would not wonder thou should'st long to die: </l>
            <l>For Salome if I aright diuine </l>
            <l>Will be then death a greater miserie. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-silleus" xml:id="eng000267-e110540">
            <speaker>Sille. </speaker>
            <l>Then list, Ile breath no longer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-constabarus" xml:id="eng000267-e110560">
            <speaker>Const: </speaker>
            <l>Do thy will, </l>
            <l>I hateles fight, and charitably kill. I, I, they fight, </l>
            <l>Pittie thy selfe Silleus, let not death </l>
            <l>Intru'd before his time into thy hart: </l>
            <l>Alas it is too late to feare, his breath </l>
            <l>Is from his body now about to part. </l>
            <l>How far'st thou braue Arabian? Silleus very well, </l>
            <l>My legge is hurt, I can no longer fight: </l>
            <l>It onely grieues me, that so soone I fell, </l>
            <l>Before faire Salomes wrongs I came to right. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-constabarus" xml:id="eng000267-e110670">
            <speaker>Const: </speaker>
            <l>Thy wounds are lesse then mortall. Neuer feare, </l>
            <l>Thou shalt a safe and quicke recouerie finde: </l>
            <l>Come, I will thee vnto my lodging beare, </l>
            <l>I hate thy body, but I loue thy minde. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-silleus" xml:id="eng000267-e110720">
            <speaker>Silleus. </speaker>
            <l>Thankes noble Iew, I see a courtious foe, </l>
            <l>Sterne enmitie to friendship can no art: </l>
            <l>Had not my heart and tongue engagde me so, </l>
            <l>I would from thee no foe, but friend depart. </l>
            <l>My heart to Salome is tide so fast, </l>
            <l>To leaue her loue for friendship, yet my skill </l>
            <l>Shall be imploy'd to make you fauour last, </l>
            <l>And I will honour Constabarus still. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-constabarus" xml:id="eng000267-e110810">
            <speaker>Const: </speaker>
            <l>I ope my bosome to thee, and will take </l>
            <l>Thee in, as friend, and grieue for thy complaint: </l>
            <l>But if we doe not expedition make, </l>
            <l>Thy losse of blood I feare will make thee faint. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-chorus" xml:id="eng000267-e110860">
            <speaker>
              <pb xml:id="eng000267-018-b"/>Chorus. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>TO heare a tale with eares preiudicate, </l>
              <l>It spoiles the iudgement, and corrupts the sence: </l>
              <l>That humane error giuen to euery state, </l>
              <l>Is greater enemie to innocence. </l>
              <l>It makes vs foolish, heddy, rash, vniust, </l>
              <l>It makes vs neuer try before we trust. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>It will confound the meaning change the words, </l>
              <l>For it our sence of hearing much deceiues: </l>
              <l>Besides no time to Iudgement it affords, </l>
              <l>To way the circumstance our eare receiues. </l>
              <l>The ground of accidents it neuer tries, </l>
              <l>But makes vs take for truth ten thousand lies. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Our eares and hearts are apt to hold for good, </l>
              <l>That we our selues doe most desire to bee: </l>
              <l>And then we drowne obiections in the flood </l>
              <l>Of partialitie, tis that we see </l>
              <l>That makes false rumours long with credit past, </l>
              <l>Though they like rumours must conclude at last. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>The greatest part of vs preiudicate, </l>
              <l>With wishing Herods death do hold it true: </l>
              <l>The being once deluded doth not bate, </l>
              <l>The credit to a better likelihood due. </l>
              <l>Those few that wish it not the multitude, </l>
              <l>Doe carrie headlong, so they doubts conclude. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>They not obiect the weake vncertaine ground, </l>
              <l>Whereon they built this tale of Herods end: </l>
              <l>Whereof the Author scarcely can be found, </l>
              <l>And all because their wishes that way bend. </l>
              <l>They thinke not of the perill that ensu'th, </l>
              <l>If this should proue the contrary to truth. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000267-019-a"/>
              <l>On this same doubt, on this so light a breath, </l>
              <l>They pawne their liues, and fortunes. For they all </l>
              <l>Behaue them as the newes of Herods death, </l>
              <l>They did of most vndoubted credit call: </l>
              <l>But if their actions now doe rightly hit, </l>
              <l>Let them commend their fortune, not their wit. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="eng000267-e111290">
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="eng000267-e111300">
          <head>Actus tertius: Scoena prima. </head>
          <stage xml:id="eng000267-e111310">Pheroras: Salome. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000267-pheroras" xml:id="eng000267-e111320">
            <speaker>Phero. </speaker>
            <l>VRge me no more Graphina to forsake, </l>
            <l>Not twelue howers since I married her for loue: </l>
            <l>And doe you thinke a sisters power cane mak </l>
            <l>A resolute decree, so soone remoue? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e111370">
            <speaker>Salome. </speaker>
            <l>Poore minds they are that honour not affects. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-pheroras" xml:id="eng000267-e111390">
            <speaker>Phero: </speaker>
            <l>Who hunts for honour, happines neglects. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e111410">
            <speaker>Salom. </speaker>
            <l>You might haue bene both of felicitie, </l>
            <l>And honour too in equall measure seasde. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-pheroras" xml:id="eng000267-e111440">
            <speaker>Phero: </speaker>
            <l>It is not you can tell so well as I, </l>
            <l>What tis can make me happie, or displeasde. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e111470">
            <speaker>Salome. </speaker>
            <l>To match for neither beautie nor respects </l>
            <l>One meane of birth, but yet of meaner minde, </l>
            <l>A woman full of naturall defects, </l>
            <l>I wonder what your eye in her could finde. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-pheroras" xml:id="eng000267-e111520">
            <speaker>Phero: </speaker>
            <l>Mine eye found louelines, mine eare found wit, </l>
            <l>To please the one, and to enchant the other: </l>
            <l>Grace on her eye, mirth on her tongue doth sit, </l>
            <l>In lookes a child, in wisedomes house a mother. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e111570">
            <speaker>Salom: </speaker>
            <l>But say you thought her faire, as none thinks else, </l>
            <l>Knowes not Pheroras, beautie is a blast: </l>
            <l>Much like this flower which to day excels, </l>
            <l>But longer then a day it will not last. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-pheroras" xml:id="eng000267-e111620">
            <speaker>Phero: </speaker>
            <l>Her wit exceeds her beautie, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e111640">
            <speaker>Salo: </speaker>
            <l>Wit may show </l>
            <l>The way to ill, as well as good you know. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-pheroras" xml:id="eng000267-e111670">
            <speaker>Phero: </speaker>
            <l>But wisedome is the porter of her head, </l>
            <l>And bares all wicked words from issuing thence. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="eng000267-019-b"/>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e111700">
            <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
            <l>But of a porter, better were you sped, </l>
            <l>If she against their entrance made defence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-pheroras" xml:id="eng000267-e111730">
            <speaker>Phero. </speaker>
            <l>But wherefore comes the sacred Ananell, </l>
            <l>That hitherward his hastie steppes doth bend? </l>
            <l>Great sacrificer y'are arriued well, </l>
            <l>Ill newes from holy mouth I not attend. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="eng000267-e111780">
          <head>Actus tertius. Scoena 2. </head>
          <stage xml:id="eng000267-e111790">Pheroras. Salome. Ananell. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000267-ananell" xml:id="eng000267-e111800">
            <speaker>Ananell. </speaker>
            <l>MY lippes, my sonne, with peacefull tidings blest, </l>
            <l>Shall vtter Honey to your listning eare: </l>
            <l>A word of death comes not from Priestly brest, </l>
            <l>I speake of life: in life there is no feare. </l>
            <l>And for the newes I did the Heauens salute, </l>
            <l>And fill'd the Temple with my thankfull voice: </l>
            <l>For though that mourning may not me pollute, </l>
            <l>At pleasing accidents I may reioyce. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-pheroras" xml:id="eng000267-e111890">
            <speaker>Pheror. </speaker>
            <l>Is Herod then reuiu'd from certaine death? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e111910">
            <speaker>Sall. </speaker>
            <l>What? can your news restore my brothers breath? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-ananell" xml:id="eng000267-e111930">
            <speaker>Ana. </speaker>
            <l>Both so, and so, the King is safe and sound, </l>
            <l>And did such grace in royall Caesar meet: </l>
            <l>That he with larger stile then euer crownd, </l>
            <l>Within this houre Ierusalem will greet. </l>
            <l>I did but come to tell you, and must backe </l>
            <l>To make preparatiues for sacrifice: </l>
            <l>I knew his death, your hearts like mine did racke, </l>
            <l>Though to conceale it, prou'd you wise. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e112020">
            <speaker>Salom. </speaker>
            <l>How can my ioy sufficiently appeare? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-pheroras" xml:id="eng000267-e112040">
            <speaker>Phero. </speaker>
            <l>A heauier tale did neuer pierce mine eare. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e112060">
            <speaker>Salo. </speaker>
            <l>Now Salome of happinesse may boast. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-pheroras" xml:id="eng000267-e112080">
            <speaker>Pheror. </speaker>
            <l>But now Pheroras is in danger most. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e112100">
            <speaker>Salom. </speaker>
            <l>I shall enioy the comfort of my life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-pheroras" xml:id="eng000267-e112120">
            <speaker>Pheror. </speaker>
            <l>And I shall loose it, loosing of my wife. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="eng000267-020-a"/>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e112140">
            <speaker>Salom. </speaker>
            <l>Ioy heart, for Constan: shall be slaine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-pheroras" xml:id="eng000267-e112160">
            <speaker>Phero. </speaker>
            <l>Grieue soule, Graphina shall from me be tane. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e112180">
            <speaker>Salom. </speaker>
            <l>Smile cheekes, the faire Silleus shall be mine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-pheroras" xml:id="eng000267-e112200">
            <speaker>Phero. </speaker>
            <l>Weepe eyes, for I must with a child combine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e112220">
            <speaker>Salom. </speaker>
            <l>Well brother, cease your mones, on one condition </l>
            <l>He vndertake to winne the Kings consent: </l>
            <l>Graphina still shall be in your tuition, </l>
            <l>And her with you be nere the lesse content. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-pheroras" xml:id="eng000267-e112270">
            <speaker>Phero. </speaker>
            <l>What's the condition? let me quickly know, </l>
            <l>That I as quickly your command may act: </l>
            <l>Were it to see what Hearbs in Ophir grow, </l>
            <l>Or that the lofty Tyrus might be sackt. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e112320">
            <speaker>Salom. </speaker>
            <l>Tis no so hard a taske: It is no more, </l>
            <l>But tell the King that Consta: hid </l>
            <l>The sonnes of Baba, done to death before: </l>
            <l>And tis no more then Consta. did. </l>
            <l>And tell him more that he for Herods sake, </l>
            <l>Not able to endure his brothers foe: </l>
            <l>Did with a bill our separation make, </l>
            <l>Though loth from Consta: else to goe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-pheroras" xml:id="eng000267-e112410">
            <speaker>Phero. </speaker>
            <l>Beleeue this tale for told, Ile goe from hence, </l>
            <l>In Herods eare the Hebrew to deface: </l>
            <l>And I that neuer studied eloquence, </l>
            <l>Doe meane with eloquence this tale to grace. <stage xml:id="eng000267-e112460">Exit. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e112470">
            <speaker>Salom. </speaker>
            <l>This will be Constabarus quicke dispatch, </l>
            <l>Which from my mouth would lesser credit finde: </l>
            <l>Yet shall he not decease without a match, </l>
            <l>For Mariam shall not linger long behinde. </l>
            <l>First Iealousie, if that auaile not, feare </l>
            <l>Shalbe my minister to worke her end: </l>
            <l>A common error moues not Herods eare, </l>
            <l>Which doth so firmly to his Mariam bend. </l>
            <l>She shall be charged with so horrid crime, </l>
            <l>As Herods feare shall turne his loue to hate: </l>
            <l>He make some sweare that she desires to clime, </l>
            <l>And seekes to poyson him for his estate. </l>
            <l>I scorne that she should liue my birth t'vpbraid, </l>
            <l>To call me base and hungry Edomite: </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-020-b"/>
            <l>With patient show her choller I betrayd, </l>
            <l>And watcht the time to be reueng'd by slite. </l>
            <l>Now tongue of mine with scandall load her name, </l>
            <l>Turne hers to fountaines, Herods eyes to flame: </l>
            <l>Yet first I will begin Pheroras suite, </l>
            <l>That he my earnest businesse may effect: </l>
            <l>And I of Mariam will keepe me mute, </l>
            <l>Till first some other doth her name detect. </l>
            <l>Who's there, Silleus man? How fares your Lord? </l>
            <l>That your aspects doe beare the badge of sorrow? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-servant" xml:id="eng000267-e112720">
            <speaker>Silleus man. </speaker>
            <l>He hath the marks of Constabarus sword, </l>
            <l>And for a while desires your sight to borrow </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e112750">
            <speaker>Salom. </speaker>
            <l>My heauy curse the hatefull sword pursue, </l>
            <l>My heauier curse on the more hatefull arme </l>
            <l>That wounded my Silleus. But renew </l>
            <l>Your tale againe. Hath he no mortall harme? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-servant" xml:id="eng000267-e112800">
            <speaker>Silleus man. </speaker>
            <l>No signe of danger doth in him appeare, </l>
            <l>Nor are his wounds in place of perill seene: </l>
            <l>Hee bides you be assured you need not feare, </l>
            <l>He hopes to make you yet Arabias Queene. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e112850">
            <speaker>Salom. </speaker>
            <l>Commend my heart to be Silleus charge, </l>
            <l>Tell him, my brothers suddaine comming now: </l>
            <l>Will giue my foote no roome to walke at large, </l>
            <l>But I will see him yet ere night I vow. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="eng000267-e112900">
          <head>Actus 3. Scoena 3. </head>
          <stage xml:id="eng000267-e112910">Mariam and Sohemus. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e112920">
            <speaker>Mariam. </speaker>
            <l>SOhemus, tell me what the newes may he </l>
            <l>That makes your eyes so full, your cheeks so blew? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-sohemus" xml:id="eng000267-e112950">
            <speaker>Sohem. </speaker>
            <l>I know not how to call them. Ill for me </l>
            <l>Tis sure they are: not so I hope for you. </l>
            <l>Herod. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e112990">
            <speaker>Mari. </speaker>
            <l>Oh, what of Herod? Sohem. Herod liues. </l>
            <l>How! liues? What in some Caue or forrest hid? </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="eng000267-021-a"/>
          <sp who="#eng000267-sohemus" xml:id="eng000267-e113020">
            <speaker>Sohem. </speaker>
            <l>Nay, backe return'd with honor. Caesar giues </l>
            <l>Him greater grace then ere Anthonius did. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e113050">
            <speaker>Mari. </speaker>
            <l>Foretell the ruine of my family, </l>
            <l>Tell me that I shall see our Citie burnd: </l>
            <l>Tell me I shall a death disgracefull die, </l>
            <l>But tell me not that Herod is returnd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-sohemus" xml:id="eng000267-e113100">
            <speaker>Sohem. </speaker>
            <l>Be not impatient Madam, be but milde, </l>
            <l>His loue to you againe will soone be bred: </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e113130">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>I will not to his loue be reconcilde, </l>
            <l>With solemne vowes I haue forsworne his Bed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-sohemus" xml:id="eng000267-e113160">
            <speaker>Sohem. </speaker>
            <l>But you must breake those vowes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e113180">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>Ile rather breake </l>
            <l>The heart of Mariam. Cursed is my Fate: </l>
            <l>But speake no more to me, in vaine ye speake </l>
            <l>To liue with him I so profoundly hate. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-sohemus" xml:id="eng000267-e113230">
            <speaker>Sohem. </speaker>
            <l>Great Queene, you must to me your pardon giue, </l>
            <l>Sohemus cannot now your will obey: </l>
            <l>If your command should me to silence driue, </l>
            <l>It were not to obey, but to betray. </l>
            <l>Reiect, and slight my speeches, mocke my faith, </l>
            <l>Scorne my obseruance, call my counsell nought: </l>
            <l>Though you regard not what Sohemus saith, </l>
            <l>Yet will I euer freely speake my thought. </l>
            <l>I feare ere long I shall faire Mariam see </l>
            <l>In wofull state, and by her selfe vndone: </l>
            <l>Yet for your issues sake more temp'rate bee, </l>
            <l>The heart by affabilitie is wonne. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e113360">
            <speaker>Mari. </speaker>
            <l>And must I to my Prison turne againe? </l>
            <l>Oh, now I see I was an hypocrite: </l>
            <l>I did this morning for his death complaine, </l>
            <l>And yet doe mourne, because he liues ere night. </l>
            <l>When I his death beleeu'd, compassion wrought, </l>
            <l>And was the stickler twixt my heart and him: </l>
            <l>But now that Curtaine's drawne from off my thought, </l>
            <l>Hate doth appeare againe with visage grim: </l>
            <l>And paints the face of Herod in my heart, </l>
            <l>In horred colours with detested looke: </l>
            <l>Then feare would come, but scorne doth play her part, </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-021-b"/>
            <l>And saith that scorne with feare can neuer brooke. </l>
            <l>I now I could inchaine him with a smile: </l>
            <l>And lead him captiue with a gentle word, </l>
            <l>Scorne my looke should euer man beguile, </l>
            <l>or other speech, then meaning to afford. </l>
            <l>Else Salome in vaine might spend her winde, </l>
            <l>In vaine might Herods mother whet her tongue: </l>
            <l>In vaine had they complotted and combinde, </l>
            <l>For I could ouerthrow them all ere long. </l>
            <l>Oh what a shelter is mine innocence, </l>
            <l>To shield me from the pangs of inward griefe: </l>
            <l>Gainst all mishaps it is my faire defence, </l>
            <l>And to my sorrowes yeelds a large reliefe. </l>
            <l>To be commandresse of the triple earth, </l>
            <l>And sit in safetie from a fall secure: </l>
            <l>To haue all nations celebrate my birth, </l>
            <l>I would not that my spirit were impure. </l>
            <l>Let my distressed state vnpittied bee, </l>
            <l>Mine innocence is hope enough for mee. <stage xml:id="eng000267-e113670">Exit. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-sohemus" xml:id="eng000267-e113680">
            <speaker>Sohem: </speaker>
            <l>Poore guiltles Queene. Oh that my wish might place </l>
            <l>A little temper now about thy heart: </l>
            <l>Vnbridled speech is Mariams worst disgrace, </l>
            <l>And will indanger her without desart. </l>
            <l>I am in greater hazard. O're my head, </l>
            <l>The fattall axe doth hang vnstedily: </l>
            <l>My disobedience once discouered, </l>
            <l>Will shake it downe: Sohemus so shall die. </l>
            <l>For when the King shall find, we thought his death </l>
            <l>Had bene as certaine as we see his life: </l>
            <l>And markes withall I slighted so his breath, </l>
            <l>As to preserue aliue his matchles wife. </l>
            <l>Nay more, to giue to Alexanders hand </l>
            <l>The regall dignitie. The soueraigne power, </l>
            <l>How I had yeelded vp at her command, </l>
            <l>The strength of all the citie, Dauids Tower. </l>
            <l>What more then common death may I expect, </l>
            <l>Since I too well do know his crueltie: </l>
            <l>Twere death, a word of Herods to neglect, </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-022-a"/>
            <l>What then to doe directly contrarie? </l>
            <l>Yet life I quite thee with a willing spirit, </l>
            <l>And thinke thou could'st not better be imploi'd: </l>
            <l>I forfeit thee for her that more doth merit, </l>
            <l>Ten such were better dead then she destroi'd. </l>
            <l>But fare thee well chast Queene, well may I see </l>
            <l>The darknes palpable, and riuers part: </l>
            <l>The sunne stand still: Nay more retorted bee, </l>
            <l>But neuer woman with so pure a heart. </l>
            <l>Thine eyes graue maiestie keepes all in awe, </l>
            <l>And cuts the winges of euery loose desire: </l>
            <l>Thy brow is table to the modest lawe, </l>
            <l>Yet though we dare not loue, we may admire. </l>
            <l>And if I die, it shall my soule content, </l>
            <l>My breath in Mariams seruice shall be spent. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-chorus" xml:id="eng000267-e114030">
            <speaker>Chorus. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>TIs not enough for one that is a wife </l>
              <l>To keepe her spotles from an act of ill: </l>
              <l>But from suspition she should free her life, </l>
              <l>And bare her selfe of power as well as will. </l>
              <l>Tis not so glorious for her to be free, </l>
              <l>As by her proper selfe restrain'd to bee. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>When she hath spatious ground to walke vpon, </l>
              <l>Why on the ridge should she desire to goe? </l>
              <l>It is no glory to forbeare alone, </l>
              <l>Those things that may her honour ouerthrowe. </l>
              <l>But tis thanke-worthy, if she will not take </l>
              <l>All lawfull liberties for honours sake. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>That wife her hand against her fame doth reare, </l>
              <l>That more then to her Lord alone will giue </l>
              <l>A priuate word to any second eare, </l>
              <l>And though she may with reputation liue. </l>
              <l>Yet though most chast, she doth her glory blot, </l>
              <l>And wounds her honour, though she killes it not. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000267-022-b"/>
              <l>When to their Husbands they themselues doe bind, </l>
              <l>Doe they not wholy giue themselues away? </l>
              <l>Or giue they but their body not their mind, </l>
              <l>Reseruing that though best, for others pray? </l>
              <l>No sure, their thoughts no more can be their owne, </l>
              <l>And therefore should to none but one be knowne. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Then she vsurpes vpon anothers right, </l>
              <l>That seekes to be by publike language grac't: </l>
              <l>And though her thoughts reflect with purest light, </l>
              <l>Her mind if not peculiar is not chast. </l>
              <l>For in a wife it is no worse to finde, </l>
              <l>A common body, then a common minde. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And euery mind though free from thought of ill, </l>
              <l>That out of glory seekes a worth to show: </l>
              <l>When any's eares but one therewith they fill, </l>
              <l>Doth in a sort her purenes ouerthrow. </l>
              <l>Now Mariam had, (but that to this she bent) </l>
              <l>Beene free from feare, as well as innocent. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="eng000267-e114460">
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="eng000267-e114470">
          <head>Actus quartus: Scoena prima. </head>
          <stage xml:id="eng000267-e114480">Enter Herod and his attendants. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e114490">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>HAile happie citie, happie in thy store, </l>
            <l>And happy that thy buildings such we see: </l>
            <l>More happie in the Temple where w'adore, </l>
            <l>But most of all that Mariam liues in thee. </l>
            <l>Art thou return'd? how fares my Mariam? <stage xml:id="eng000267-e114550">Enter Nutio. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-nuntius" xml:id="eng000267-e114560">
            <speaker>Nutio. </speaker>
            <l>She's well my Lord, and will anon be here </l>
            <l>As you commanded. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e114590">
            <speaker>Her: </speaker>
            <l>Muffle vp thy browe </l>
            <l>Thou daies darke taper. Mariam will appeare. </l>
            <l>And where she shines, we need not thy dimme light, </l>
            <l>Oh hast thy steps rare creature, speed thy pace: </l>
            <l>And let thy presence make the day more bright, </l>
            <l>And cheere the heart of Herod with thy face. </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-023-a"/>
            <l>It is an age since I from Mariam went, </l>
            <l>Me thinkes our parting was in Dauids daies: </l>
            <l>The houres are so increast by discontent, </l>
            <l>Deepe sorrow, Iosua like the season staies: </l>
            <l>But when I am with Mariam, time runnes on, </l>
            <l>Her sight, can make months, minutes, daies of weekes </l>
            <l>An hower is then no sooner come then gon. </l>
            <l>When in her face mine eye for wonders seekes. </l>
            <l>You world commanding citie, Europes grace, </l>
            <l>Twice hath my curious eye your streets suruai'd, </l>
            <l>And I haue seene the statue filled place, </l>
            <l>That once if not for griefe had bene betrai'd. </l>
            <l>I all your Roman beauties haue beheld, </l>
            <l>And seene the showes your Ediles did prepare, </l>
            <l>I saw the sum of what in you exceld, </l>
            <l>Yet saw no miracle like Mariam rare. </l>
            <l>The faire and famous Liuia, Caesars loue, </l>
            <l>The worlds commaunding Mistresse did I see: </l>
            <l>Whose beauties both the world and Rome approue, </l>
            <l>Yet Mariam: Liuia is not like to thee. </l>
            <l>Be patient but a little, while mine eyes </l>
            <l>Within your compast limits be contain'd: </l>
            <l>That obiect straight shall your desires suffice, </l>
            <l>From which you were so long a while restrain'd. </l>
            <l>How wisely Mariam doth the time delay, </l>
            <l>Least suddaine ioy my sence should suffocate: </l>
            <l>I am prepar'd, thou needst no longer stay: </l>
            <l>Whos's there, my Mariam, more then happie fate? </l>
            <l>Oh no, it is Pheroras, welcome Brother, </l>
            <l>Now for a while, I must my passion smother. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="eng000267-e114960">
          <head>Actus quartus. Scoena secunda. </head>
          <stage xml:id="eng000267-e114970">Herod. Pheroras. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000267-pheroras" xml:id="eng000267-e114980">
            <speaker>Pheroras. </speaker>
            <l>ALl health and safetie waite vpon my Lord, </l>
            <l>And may you long in prosperous fortunes liue </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-023-b"/>
            <l>With Rome commanding Caesar; at accord, </l>
            <l>And haue all honors that the world can giue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e115030">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Oh brother, now thou speakst not from thy hart, </l>
            <l>No, thou hast strooke a blow at Herods loue: </l>
            <l>That cannot quickly from my memory part, </l>
            <l>Though Salome did me to pardon moue. </l>
            <l>Valiant Phasaelus, now to thee farewell, </l>
            <l>Thou wert my kinde and honorable brother: </l>
            <l>Oh haples houre, when you selfe striken fell, </l>
            <l>Thou fathers Image, glory of thy mother. </l>
            <l>Had I desir'd a greater sute of thee, </l>
            <l>Then to withhold thee from a harlots bed, </l>
            <l>Thou wouldst haue granted it: but now I see </l>
            <l>All are not like that in a wombe are bred. </l>
            <l>Thou wouldst not, hadst thou heard of Herods death, </l>
            <l>Haue made his buriall time, thy bridall houre: </l>
            <l>Thou wouldst with clamours, not with ioyfull breath, </l>
            <l>Haue show'd the newes to be not sweet but soure. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-pheroras" xml:id="eng000267-e115200">
            <speaker>Phero. </speaker>
            <l>Phasaelus great worth I know did staine </l>
            <l>Pheroras petty valour: but they lie </l>
            <l>(Excepting you your selfe) that dare maintaine, </l>
            <l>That he did honor Herod more then I. </l>
            <l>For what I showd, loues power constraind me show, </l>
            <l>And pardon louing faults for Mariams sake. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e115270">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Mariam, where is she? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-pheroras" xml:id="eng000267-e115290">
            <speaker>Phero. </speaker>
            <l>Nay, I do not know, </l>
            <l>But absent vse of her faire name I make: </l>
            <l>You haue forgiuen greater faults then this, </l>
            <l>For Constabarus that against you will </l>
            <l>Preseru'd the sonnes of Baba, liues in blisse, </l>
            <l>Though you commanded him the youths to kill. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e115360">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Goe, take a present order for his death, </l>
            <l>And let those traytors feele the worst of feares: </l>
            <l>Now Salome will whine to begge his breath, </l>
            <l>But Ile be deafe to prayers: and blind to teares. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-pheroras" xml:id="eng000267-e115410">
            <speaker>Phero. </speaker>
            <l>He is my Lord from Salom diuorst, </l>
            <l>Though her affection did to leaue him grieue: </l>
            <l>Yet was she by her loue to you inforst, </l>
            <l>To leaue the man that would your foes relieue. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="eng000267-024-a"/>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e115460">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Then haste them to their death. I will requite </l>
            <l>Thee gentle Mariam. Salom I meane </l>
            <l>The thought of Mariam doth so steale my spirit, </l>
            <l>My mouth from speech of her I cannot weane. <stage xml:id="eng000267-e115510">Exit. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="eng000267-e115520">
          <head>Actus 4. Scoena 3. </head>
          <stage xml:id="eng000267-e115530">Herod. Mariam. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e115540">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>ANd heere she comes indeed: happily met </l>
            <l>My best, and deerest halfe: what ailes my deare? </l>
            <l>Thou doest the difference certainly forget </l>
            <l>Twixt Duskey habits, and a time so cleare. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e115590">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord, I suit my garment to my minde, </l>
            <l>And there no cheerfull colours can I finde. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e115620">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Is this my welcome? haue I longd so much </l>
            <l>To see my dearest Mariam discontent? </l>
            <l>What ist that is the cause thy heart to touch? </l>
            <l>Oh speake, that I thy sorrow may preuent. </l>
            <l>Art thou not Iuries Queene, and Herods too? </l>
            <l>Be my Commandres, be my Soueraigne guide: </l>
            <l>To be by thee directed I will woo, </l>
            <l>For in thy pleasure lies my highest pride. </l>
            <l>Or if thou thinke Iudaeas narrow bound, </l>
            <l>Too strict a limit for thy great command: </l>
            <l>Thou shalt be Empresse of Arabia crownd, </l>
            <l>For thou shalt rule, and I will winne the Land. </l>
            <l>Ile robbe the holy Dauids Sepulcher </l>
            <l>To giue thee wealth, if thou for wealth do care: </l>
            <l>Thou shalt haue all, they did with him inter, </l>
            <l>And I for thee will make the Temple bare. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e115790">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>I neither haue of power not riches want, </l>
            <l>I haue enough, nor doe I wish for more: </l>
            <l>Your offers to my heart no ease can grant, </l>
            <l>Except they could my brothers life restore. </l>
            <l>No, had you wisht the wretched Mariam glad, </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-024-b"/>
            <l>Or had your loue to her bene truly tide: </l>
            <l>Nay, had you not desir'd to make her sad, </l>
            <l>My brother nor my Grandsyre had not dide. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e115880">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Wilt thou beleeue no oathes to cleere thy Lord? </l>
            <l>How oft haue I with execration sworne: </l>
            <l>Thou art by me belou'd, by me ador'd, </l>
            <l>Yet are my protestations heard with scorne. </l>
            <l>Hercanus plotted to depriue my head </l>
            <l>Of this long setled honor that I weare: </l>
            <l>And therefore I did iustly doome him dead, </l>
            <l>To rid the Realme from perill, me from feare. </l>
            <l>Yet I for Mariams sake doe so repent </l>
            <l>The death of one: whose blood she did inherit: </l>
            <l>I wish I had a Kingdomes treasure spent, </l>
            <l>So I had nere expeld Hercanus spirit. </l>
            <l>As I affected that same noble youth, </l>
            <l>In lasting infamie my name inrole: </l>
            <l>If I not mournd his death with heartie truth. </l>
            <l>Did I not shew to him my earnest loue, </l>
            <l>When I to him the Priesthood did restore? </l>
            <l>And did for him a liuing Priest remoue, </l>
            <l>Which neuer had bene done but once before. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e116080">
            <speaker>Mariam. </speaker>
            <l>I know that mou'd by importunitie, </l>
            <l>You made him Priest, and shortly after die. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e116110">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>I will not speake, vnles to be beleeu'd, </l>
            <l>This froward humor will not doe you good: </l>
            <l>It hath too much already Herod grieu'd, </l>
            <l>To thinke that you on termes of hate haue stood. </l>
            <l>Yet smile my dearest Mariam, doe but smile, </l>
            <l>And I will all vnkind conceits exile. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e116180">
            <speaker>Mari. </speaker>
            <l>I cannot frame disguise, nor neuer taught </l>
            <l>My face a looke dissenting from my thought. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e116210">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>By heau'n you vexe me, build not on my loue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e116230">
            <speaker>Mari. </speaker>
            <l>I wil not build on so vnstable ground. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e116250">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Nought is so fixt, but peeuishnes may moue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e116270">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>Tis better sleightest cause then none were found. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e116290">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Be iudge your selfe, if euer Herod sought </l>
            <l>Or would be mou'd a cause of change to finde: </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-025-a"/>
            <l>Yet let your looke declare a milder thought, </l>
            <l>My heart againe you shall to Mariam binde. </l>
            <l>How oft did I for you my Mother chide, </l>
            <l>Reuile my Sister, and my brother rate: </l>
            <l>And tell them all my Mariam they belide, </l>
            <l>Distrust me still, if these be signes of hate. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="eng000267-e116380">
          <head>Actus 4. Scoena 4. </head>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e116390">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>WHat hast thou here? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-butler" xml:id="eng000267-e116410">
            <speaker>Bu. </speaker>
            <l>A drinke procuring loue, </l>
            <l>The Queene desir'd me to deliuer it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e116440">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>Did I: some hatefull practise this will proue, </l>
            <l>Yet can it be no worse then Heauens permit. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e116470">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Confesse the truth thou wicked instrument, </l>
            <l>To her outragious will, tis passion sure: </l>
            <l>Tell true, and thou shalt scape the punishment, </l>
            <l>Which if thou doe conceale thou shalt endure. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-butler" xml:id="eng000267-e116520">
            <speaker>Bu. </speaker>
            <l>I know not, but I doubt it be no lesse, </l>
            <l>Long since the hate of you her heart did cease. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e116550">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Know'st thou the cause thereof? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-butler" xml:id="eng000267-e116570">
            <speaker>Bu. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord I gesse, </l>
            <l>Sohemus told the tale that did displease. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e116600">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Oh Heauen! Sohemus false! Goe let him die, </l>
            <l>Stay not to suffer him to speake a word: </l>
            <l>Oh damned villaine, did he falsifie </l>
            <l>The oath he swore eu'n of his owne accord? </l>
            <l>Now doe I know thy falshood, painted Diuill </l>
            <l>Thou white Inchantres. Oh thou art so foule, </l>
            <l>That Ysop cannot clense thee worst of euill. </l>
            <l>A beautious body hides a loathsome soule, </l>
            <l>Your loue Sohemus mou'd by his affection, </l>
            <l>Though he haue euer heretofore bene true: </l>
            <l>Did blab forsooth, that I did giue direction, </l>
            <l>If we were put to death to slaughter you. </l>
            <l>And you in blacke reuenge attended now </l>
            <l>To adde a murther to your breach of vow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e116750">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>Is this a dream? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e116770">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Oh Heauen, that t'were no more, </l>
            <l>Ile giue my Realme to who can proue it so: </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-025-b"/>
            <l>I would I were like any begger poore, </l>
            <l>So I for false my Mariam did not know. </l>
            <l>Foule pith contain'd in the fairest rinde, </l>
            <l>That euer grac'd a Caedar. Oh thine eye </l>
            <l>Is pure as heauen, but impure thy minde, </l>
            <l>And for impuritie shall Mariam die. </l>
            <l>Why didst thou loue Sohemus? Mar: they can tell </l>
            <l>That say I lou'd him, Mariam saies not so. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e116880">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Oh cannot impudence the coales expell, </l>
            <l>That for thy loue in Herods bosome glowe: </l>
            <l>It is as plaine as water, and deniall </l>
            <l>Makes of thy falsehood but a greater triall. </l>
            <l>Hast thou beheld thy selfe, and couldst thou staine </l>
            <l>So rare perfection: euen for loue of thee </l>
            <l>I doe profoundly hate thee. Wert thou plaine, </l>
            <l>Thou shoul'dst the wonder of Iudea bee. </l>
            <l>But oh thou art not. Hell it selfe lies hid </l>
            <l>Beneath thy heauenly show. Yet neuer wert thou chast: </l>
            <l>Thou might'st exalt, pull downe, command, forbid, </l>
            <l>And be aboue the wheele of fortune plast. </l>
            <l>Hadst thou complotted Herods massacre, </l>
            <l>That so thy sonne a Monarch might be stilde, </l>
            <l>Not halfe so grieuous such an action were, </l>
            <l>As once to thinke, that Mariam is defilde. </l>
            <l>Bright workmanship of nature sulli'd ore, </l>
            <l>With pitched darknes now thine end shall bee: </l>
            <l>Thou shalt not liue faire fiend to cozen more, </l>
            <l>With heauy semblance, as thou cousnedst mee. </l>
            <l>Yet must I loue thee in despight of death, </l>
            <l>And thou shalt die in the dispight of loue: </l>
            <l>For neither shall my loue prolong thy breath, </l>
            <l>Nor shall thy losse of breath my loue remoue. </l>
            <l>I might haue seene thy falsehood in thy face, </l>
            <l>Where coul'dst thou get thy stares that seru'd for eyes? </l>
            <l>Except by theft, and theft is foule disgrace: </l>
            <l>This had appear'd before were Herod wise, </l>
            <l>But I'me a sot, a very sot, no better: </l>
            <l>My wisedome long agoe a wandring fell, </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-026-a"/>
            <l>Thy face incountring it, my wit did fetter, </l>
            <l>And made me for delight my freedome sell. </l>
            <l>Giue me my heart false creature, tis a wrong, </l>
            <l>My guiltles heart should now with thine be slaine: </l>
            <l>Thou hadst no right to looke it vp so long, </l>
            <l>And with usurper name I Mariam staine. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000267-e117250">Enter Bu: </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e117260">
            <speaker>He: </speaker>
            <l>Haue you design'd Sohemus to his end? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-butler" xml:id="eng000267-e117280">
            <speaker>Bu: </speaker>
            <l>I haue my Lord Herod: Then call our royall guard </l>
            <l>To doe as much for Mariam, they offend </l>
            <l>Leaue ill vnblam'd, or good without reward. </l>
            <l>Here take her to her death Come backe, come backe, </l>
            <l>What ment I to depriue the world of light: </l>
            <l>To muffle Iury in the foulest blacke, </l>
            <l>That euer was an opposite to white. </l>
            <l>Why whither would you carrie her: Sould: you bad </l>
            <l>We should conduct her to her death my Lord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e117380">
            <speaker>Hero: </speaker>
            <l>Wie sure I did not, Herod was not mad, </l>
            <l>Why should she feele the furie of the sword? </l>
            <l>Oh now the griefe returnes into my heart, </l>
            <l>And pulles me peecemeale: loue and hate doe fight: </l>
            <l>And now hath boue acquir'd the greater part, </l>
            <l>Yet now hath hate, affection conquer'd quite. </l>
            <l>And therefore beare her hence: and Hebrew why </l>
            <l>Seaze you with Lyons pawes the fairest lam </l>
            <l>Of all the flocke? she must not, shall not, die, </l>
            <l>Without her I most miserable am. </l>
            <l>And with her more then most, away, away, </l>
            <l>But beare her but to prison not to death: </l>
            <l>And is she gon indeed, stay villaines stay, </l>
            <l>Her lookes alone preseru'd your Soueraignes breath. </l>
            <l>Well let her goe, but yet she shall not die, </l>
            <l>I cannot thinke she ment to poison me: </l>
            <l>But certaine tis she liu'd too wantonly, </l>
            <l>And therefore shall she neuer more be free. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="eng000267-e117570">
          <pb xml:id="eng000267-026-b"/>
          <head>Actus 4. Scoena 5. </head>
          <sp who="#eng000267-butler" xml:id="eng000267-e117580">
            <speaker>Bu. </speaker>
            <l>FOule villaine, can thy pitchie coloured soule </l>
            <l>Permit thine eare to heare her caules doome? </l>
            <l>And not inforce thy tongue that tale controule, </l>
            <l>That must vniustly bring her to her too me. </l>
            <l>Oh Salome thou hast thy selfe repaid, </l>
            <l>For all the benefits that thou hast done: </l>
            <l>Thou art the cause I haue the queene betraid, </l>
            <l>Thou hast my hart to darkest false-hood wonne. </l>
            <l>I am condemn'd, heau'n gaue me not my tongue </l>
            <l>To slander innocents, to lie, deceiue: </l>
            <l>To be the hatefull instrument to wrong, </l>
            <l>The earth of greatest glory to bereaue. </l>
            <l>My sinne ascends and doth to heau'n crie, </l>
            <l>It is the blackest deed that euer was: </l>
            <l>And there doth sit an Angell notarie, </l>
            <l>That doth record it downe in leaues of brasse. </l>
            <l>Oh how my heart doth quake: Achitophel, </l>
            <l>Thou founds a meanes thy selfe from shame to free: </l>
            <l>And sure my soule approues thou didst not well, </l>
            <l>All follow some, and I will follow thee. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="6" type="scene" xml:id="eng000267-e117790">
          <head>Actus 4. Scoena 6. </head>
          <stage xml:id="eng000267-e117800">Constabarus, Babus Sonnes, and their guard. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000267-constabarus" xml:id="eng000267-e117810">
            <speaker>Const: </speaker>
            <l>NOw here we step our last, the way to death, </l>
            <l>We must not tread this way a second time: </l>
            <l>Yet let vs resolutely yeeld our breath, </l>
            <l>Death is the onely ladder, Heau'n to clime. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-babus_son_1" xml:id="eng000267-e117860">
            <speaker>Babus 1. Sonne. </speaker>
            <l>With willing mind I could my selfe resigne, </l>
            <l>But yet it grieues me with a griefe vntold: </l>
            <l>Our death should be accompani'd with thine, </l>
            <l>Our friendship we to thee haue dearely sold. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="eng000267-027-a"/>
          <sp who="#eng000267-constabarus" xml:id="eng000267-e117910">
            <speaker>Const. </speaker>
            <l>Still wilt thou wrong the sacred name of friend? </l>
            <l>Then should'st thou neuer stile it friendship more: </l>
            <l>But base mechanicke traffique that doth lend, </l>
            <l>Yet will be sure they shall the debt restore. </l>
            <l>I could with needlesse complement returne, </l>
            <l>Tis for thy ceremonie I could say: </l>
            <l>Tis I that made the fire your house to burne, </l>
            <l>For but for me she would not you betray. </l>
            <l>Had not the damned woman sought mine end, </l>
            <l>You had not bene the subiect of her hate: </l>
            <l>You neuer did her hatefull minde offend, </l>
            <l>Nor could your deaths haue freed your nuptiall fate. </l>
            <l>Therefore faire friends, though you were still vnborne, </l>
            <l>Some other subtiltie deuisde should bee: </l>
            <l>Were by my life, though guiltles should be torne, </l>
            <l>Thus haue I prou'd, tis you that die for mee. </l>
            <l>And therefore should I weakely now lament, </l>
            <l>You haue but done your duties, friends should die: </l>
            <l>Alone their friends disaster to preuent, </l>
            <l>Though not compeld by strong necessitie. </l>
            <l>But now farewell faire citie, neuer more </l>
            <l>Shall I behold your beautie shining bright: </l>
            <l>Farewell of Iewish men the worthy store, </l>
            <l>But no farewell to any female wight. </l>
            <l>You wauering crue: my curse to you I leaue, </l>
            <l>You had but one to giue you any grace: </l>
            <l>And you your selues will Mariams life bereaue, </l>
            <l>Your common-wealth doth innocencie chase. </l>
            <l>You creatures made to be the humane curse, </l>
            <l>You Tygers, Lyonesses, hungry Beares, </l>
            <l>Teare massacring Hienas: nay far worse, </l>
            <l>For they for pray doe shed their fained teares. </l>
            <l>But you will weepe, (you creatures crosse to good) </l>
            <l>For your vnquenched thirst of humane blood: </l>
            <l>You were the Angels cast from heaue'n for pride, </l>
            <l>And still doe keepe your Angels outward show, </l>
            <l>But none of you are inly beautifide, </l>
            <l>For still your heau'n depriuing pride doth grow. </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-027-b"/>
            <l>Did not the sinnes of many require a scourge, </l>
            <l>Your place on earth had bene by this withstood: </l>
            <l>But since a flood no more the world must purge, </l>
            <l>You staid in office of a second flood. </l>
            <l>You giddy creatures, sowers of debate, </l>
            <l>You'll loue to day, and for no other cause, </l>
            <l>But for you yesterday did deply hate, </l>
            <l>You are the wreake of order, breach of lawes. </l>
            <l>You best, are foolish, froward, wanton, vaine, </l>
            <l>Your worst adulterous, murderous, cunning, proud </l>
            <l>And Salome attends the latter traine, </l>
            <l>Or rather he their leader is allowd. </l>
            <l>I do the sottishnesse of men bewaile, </l>
            <l>That doe with following you inhance your pride: </l>
            <l>T'were better that the humane race should faile, </l>
            <l>Then be by such a mischiefe multiplide. </l>
            <l>Chams seruile curse to all your sexe was giuen, </l>
            <l>Because in Paradise you did offend: </l>
            <l>Then doe we not resist the will of Heauen, </l>
            <l>When on your willes like seruants we attend? </l>
            <l>You are to nothing constant but to ill, </l>
            <l>You are with nought but wickednesse indude: </l>
            <l>Your loues are set on nothing but your will, </l>
            <l>And thus my censure I of you conclude. </l>
            <l>You are the least of goods, the worst of euils, </l>
            <l>Your best are worse then men: your worst then diuels. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-babus_son_2" xml:id="eng000267-e118560">
            <speaker>Babus second sonne. </speaker>
            <l>Come let vs to our death: are we not blest? </l>
            <l>Our death will freedome from these creatures giue: </l>
            <l>Those trouble quiet sowers of vnrest, </l>
            <l>And this I vow that had I leaue to liue, </l>
            <l>I would for euer leade a single life, </l>
            <l>And neuer venter on a diuellish wife. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="7" type="scene" xml:id="eng000267-e118630">
          <pb xml:id="eng000267-028-a"/>
          <head>Actus 4. Scoena 7. </head>
          <stage xml:id="eng000267-e118640">Herod and Salome. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e118650">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>NAy, she shall die. Die quoth you, that she shall: </l>
            <l>But for the meanes. The meanes! Me thinks tis hard </l>
            <l>To finde a meanes to murther her withall, </l>
            <l>Therefore I am resolu'd she shall be spar'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e118700">
            <speaker>Salom. </speaker>
            <l>Why? let her be beheaded. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e118720">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>That were well, </l>
            <l>Thinke you that swords are miracles like you: </l>
            <l>Her skinne will eu'ry Curtlax edge refell, </l>
            <l>And then your enterprise you well may rue. </l>
            <l>What if the fierce Arabian notice take, </l>
            <l>Of this your wretched weaponlesse estate: </l>
            <l>They answere when we bid resistance make, </l>
            <l>That Mariams skinne their fanchions did rebate. </l>
            <l>Beware of this, you make a goodly hand, </l>
            <l>If you of weapons doe depriue our Land. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e118830">
            <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
            <l>Why drowne her then. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e118850">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Indeed a sweet deuice, </l>
            <l>Why? would not eu'ry Riuer turne her course </l>
            <l>Rather then doe her beautie preiudice? </l>
            <l>And be reuerted to the proper sourse. </l>
            <l>So not a drop of water should be found </l>
            <l>In all Iudeas quondam firtill ground. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e118920">
            <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
            <l>Then let the fire deuoure her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e118940">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>T'will not bee: </l>
            <l>Flame is from her deriu'd into my heart: </l>
            <l>Thou nursest flame, flame will not murther thee, </l>
            <l>My fairest Mariam, fullest of desert. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e118990">
            <speaker>Salom. </speaker>
            <l>Then let her liue for me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e119010">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Nay, she shall die: </l>
            <l>But can you liue without her? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e119040">
            <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
            <l>doubt you that? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e119060">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>I'me sure I cannot, I beseech you trie: </l>
            <l>I haue experience but I know not what. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e119090">
            <speaker>Salom. </speaker>
            <l>How should I try? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e119110">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Why let my loue be slaine, </l>
            <l>But if we cannot liue without her sight </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-028-b"/>
            <l>Youle finde the meanes to make her breathe againe, </l>
            <l>Or else you will bereaue my comfort quite. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e119160">
            <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
            <l>Oh I: I warrant you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e119180">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>What is she gone? </l>
            <l>And gone to bid the world be ouerthrowne: </l>
            <l>What? is her hearts composure hardest stone? </l>
            <l>To what a passe are cruell women growne? </l>
            <l>She is return'd already: haue you done? </l>
            <l>Ist possible you can command so soone? </l>
            <l>A creatures heart to quench the flaming Sunne, </l>
            <l>Or from the skie to wipe away the Moone. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e119270">
            <speaker>Salo. </speaker>
            <l>If Mariam be the Sunne and Moone, it is: </l>
            <l>For I already haue commanded this. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e119300">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>But haue you seene her cheek? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e119320">
            <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
            <l>A thousand times. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e119340">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>But did you marke it too? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e119360">
            <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
            <l>I very well. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e119380">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>What ist? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e119400">
            <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
            <l>A Crimson bush, that euer limes </l>
            <l>The soule whose foresight doth not much excell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e119430">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Send word she shall not dye. Her cheek a bush, </l>
            <l>Nay, then I see indeed you markt it not. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e119460">
            <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
            <l>Tis very faire, but yet will neuer blush, </l>
            <l>Though foule dishonors do her forehead blot. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e119490">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Then let her die, tis very true indeed, </l>
            <l>And for this fault alone shall Mariam bleed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e119520">
            <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
            <l>What fault my Lord? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e119540">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>What fault ist? you that aske: </l>
            <l>If you be ignorant I know of none, </l>
            <l>To call her backe from death shall be your taske, </l>
            <l>I'm glad that she for innocent is knowne. </l>
            <l>For on the brow of Mariam hangs a Fleece, </l>
            <l>Whose slenderest twine is strong enough to binde </l>
            <l>The hearts of Kings, the pride and shame of Greece, </l>
            <l>Troy flaming Helens not so fairely shinde. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e119630">
            <speaker>Salom. </speaker>
            <l>Tis true indeed, she layes them out for nets, </l>
            <l>To catch the hearts that doe not shune a baite: </l>
            <l>Tis time to speake: for Herod sure forgets </l>
            <l>That Mariams very tresses hide deceit. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e119680">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Oh doe they so? nay, then you doe but well, </l>
            <l>Insooth I thought it had beene haire: </l>
            <l>Nets call you them? Lord, how they doe excell, </l>
            <l>I neuer saw a net that show'd so faire. </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-029-a"/>
            <l>But haue you heard her speake? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e119740">
            <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
            <l>You know I haue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e119760">
            <speaker>Her: </speaker>
            <l>And were you not amaz'd? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e119780">
            <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
            <l>No, not a whit. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e119800">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Then t'was not her you heard, her life Ile saue, </l>
            <l>For Mariam hath a world amazing wit. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e119830">
            <speaker>Salo. </speaker>
            <l>She speaks a beautious language, but within </l>
            <l>Her heart is false as powder: and her tongue </l>
            <l>Doth but allure the auditors to sinne, </l>
            <l>And is the instrument to doe you wrong. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e119880">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>It may be so: nay, tis so: shee's vnchaste, </l>
            <l>Her mouth will ope to eu'ry strangers eare: </l>
            <l>Then let the executioner make haste, </l>
            <l>Lest she inchant him, if her words he heare. </l>
            <l>Let him be deafe, lest she do him surprise </l>
            <l>That shall to free her spirit be assignde: </l>
            <l>Yet what boots deafenes if he haue his eyes, </l>
            <l>Her murtherer must be both deafe and blinde. </l>
            <l>For if he see, he needs must see the starres </l>
            <l>That shine on eyther side of Mariams face: </l>
            <l>Whose sweet aspect will terminate the warres, </l>
            <l>Wherewith he should a soule so precious chase. </l>
            <l>Her eyes can speake, and in their speaking moue, </l>
            <l>Oft did my heart with reuerence receiue </l>
            <l>The worlds mandates. Pretty tales of loue </l>
            <l>They vtter, which can humane bondage weaue. </l>
            <l>But shall I let this heauens modell dye? </l>
            <l>Which for a small selfe-portraiture she drew: </l>
            <l>Her eyes like starres, her forehead like the skie, </l>
            <l>She is like Heauen, and must be heauenly true. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e120090">
            <speaker>Salom. </speaker>
            <l>Your thoughts do raue with doating on the Queen, </l>
            <l>Her eyes are ebon hewde, and you'll confesse: </l>
            <l>A sable starre hath beene but seldome seene, </l>
            <l>Then speake of reason more, of Mariam lesse. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e120140">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Your selfe are held a goodly creature heere, </l>
            <l>Yet so vnlike my Mariam in your shape: </l>
            <l>That when to her you haue approached neere, </l>
            <l>My selfe hath often tane you for an Ape. </l>
            <l>And yet you prate of beautie: goe your waies, </l>
            <l>You are to her a Sun burnt Blackamore: </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-029-b"/>
            <l>Your paintings cannot equall Mariams praise, </l>
            <l>Her nature is so rich, you are so poore. </l>
            <l>Let her be staide from death, for if she die, </l>
            <l>We do we know not what to stop her breath: </l>
            <l>A world cannot another Mariam buy, </l>
            <l>Why stay you lingring? countermaund her death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e120270">
            <speaker>Salo. </speaker>
            <l>Then youle no more remember what hath past, </l>
            <l>Sohemus loue, and hers shall be forgot: </l>
            <l>Tis well in truth: that fault may be her last, </l>
            <l>And she may mend, though yet she loue you not. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e120320">
            <speaker>Her: </speaker>
            <l>Oh God: tis true. Sohemus: earth and heau'n, </l>
            <l>Why did you both conspire to make me curst: </l>
            <l>In cousning me with showes, and proofes vneu'n? </l>
            <l>She show'd the best, and yet did proue the worst. </l>
            <l>Her show was such, as had our singing king </l>
            <l>The holy Dauid, Mariams beautie seene: </l>
            <l>The Hittits had then felt no deadly sting, </l>
            <l>Nor Bethsabe had neuer bene a Queene. </l>
            <l>Or had his sonne the wisest man of men, </l>
            <l>Whose fond delight did most consist in change: </l>
            <l>Beheld her face, he had bene staid agen, </l>
            <l>No creature hauing her, can wish to range. </l>
            <l>Had Asuerus seene my Mariams brow, </l>
            <l>The humble Iewe, she might haue walkt alone: </l>
            <l>Her beautious vertue should haue staid below, </l>
            <l>Whiles Mariam mounted to the Persian throne. </l>
            <l>But what auailes it all: for in the waight </l>
            <l>She is deceitfull, light as vanitie: </l>
            <l>Oh she was made for nothing but a bait, </l>
            <l>To traine some haples man to miserie. </l>
            <l>I am the haples man that haue bene trainde, </l>
            <l>To endles bondage. I will see her yet: </l>
            <l>Me thinkes I should discerne her if she fainde, </l>
            <l>Can humane eyes be dazde by womans wit? </l>
            <l>Once more these eyes of mine with hers shall meet, </l>
            <l>Before the headsman doe her life bereaue: </l>
            <l>Shall I for euer part from thee my sweet? </l>
            <l>Without the taking of my latest leaue. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="eng000267-030-a"/>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e120610">
            <speaker>Salo: </speaker>
            <l>You had as good resolue to saue her now, </l>
            <l>Ile stay her death, tis well determined: </l>
            <l>For sure she neuer more will breake her vow, </l>
            <l>Sohemus and Iosephus both are dead. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e120660">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>She shall not liue, nor will I see her face, </l>
            <l>A long heald wound, a second time doth bleed: </l>
            <l>With Ioseph I remember her disgrace, </l>
            <l>A shamefull end ensues a shamefull deed. </l>
            <l>Oh that I had not cald to minde anew, </l>
            <l>The discontent of Mariams wauering hart: </l>
            <l>Twas you: you foule mouth'd Ate, none but you, </l>
            <l>That did the thought hereof to me impart. </l>
            <l>Hence from my sight, my blacke tormenter hence, </l>
            <l>For hadst not thou made Herod vnsecure: </l>
            <l>I had not doubted Mariams innocence, </l>
            <l>But still had held her in my heart for pure. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-salome" xml:id="eng000267-e120790">
            <speaker>Salo: </speaker>
            <l>Ile leaue you to your passion: tis no time </l>
            <l>To purge me now, though of a guiltles crime. <stage xml:id="eng000267-e120820">Exit. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e120830">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Destruction take thee: thou hast made my hart </l>
            <l>As heauie as reuenge, I am so dull, </l>
            <l>Me thinkes I am not sensible of smart, </l>
            <l>Though hiddious horrors at my bosome pull. </l>
            <l>My head waies downwards: therefore will I goe </l>
            <l>To try if I can sleepe away my woe. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="8" type="scene" xml:id="eng000267-e120900">
          <head>Actus 4. Scoena. 8. </head>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e120910">
            <speaker>Mariam. </speaker>
            <l>AM I the Mariam that presum'd so much, </l>
            <l>And deem'd my face must needes preserue my breath? </l>
            <l>I, I it was that thought my beautie such, </l>
            <l>At it alone could countermaund my death. </l>
            <l>Now death will reach me: he can pale aswell </l>
            <l>A cheeke of roses, as a cheeke lesse bright: </l>
            <l>And dim an eye whose shine doth most excell, </l>
            <l>Assoone as one that casts a meaner light. </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-030-b"/>
            <l>Had not my selfe against my selfe conspirde, </l>
            <l>No plot: no aduersarie from without </l>
            <l>Could Herods loue from Mariam haue retirde, </l>
            <l>Or from his heart haue thrust my semblance out. </l>
            <l>The wanton Queene that neuer lou'd for loue, </l>
            <l>False Cleopatra, wholly set on gaine: </l>
            <l>With all her slights did proue: yet vainly proue, </l>
            <l>For her the loue of Herod to obtaine. </l>
            <l>Yet her allurements, all her courtly guile, </l>
            <l>Her smiles, her fauours, and her smooth deceit: </l>
            <l>Could not my face from Herods minde exile, </l>
            <l>But were with him of lesse then little weight. </l>
            <l>That face and person that in Asia late </l>
            <l>For beauties Goddesse Paphos Queene was tane: </l>
            <l>That face that did captiue great Iulius fate, </l>
            <l>That very face that was Anthonius bane. </l>
            <l>That face that to be Egipts pride was borne, </l>
            <l>That face that all the world esteem'd so rare: </l>
            <l>Did Herod hate, despise, neglect, and scorne, </l>
            <l>When with the same, he Mariams did compare. </l>
            <l>This made that I improuidently wrought, </l>
            <l>And on the wager euen my life did pawne: </l>
            <l>Because I thought, and yet but truly thought, </l>
            <l>That Herods loue could not from me be drawne. </l>
            <l>But now though out of time, I plainly see </l>
            <l>It could be drawne, though neuer drawne from me: </l>
            <l>Had I but with humilitie bene grac'te, </l>
            <l>As well as faire I might haue prou'd me wise: </l>
            <l>But I did thinke because I knew me chaste, </l>
            <l>One vertue for a woman, might suffice. </l>
            <l>That mind for glory of our sexe might stand, </l>
            <l>Wherein humilitie and chastitie </l>
            <l>Doth march with equall paces hand in hand, </l>
            <l>But one it single seene, who setteth by? </l>
            <l>And I had single one, but tis my ioy, </l>
            <l>That I was euer innocent, though sower: </l>
            <l>And therefore can they but my life destroy, </l>
            <l>My Soule is free from aduersaries power.) <stage xml:id="eng000267-e121380">Enter Doris. </stage>
            </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-031-a"/>
            <l>You Princes great in power, and high in birth, </l>
            <l>Be great and high, I enuy not your hap: </l>
            <l>Your birth must be from dust: your power on earth, </l>
            <l>In heau'n shall Mariam sit in Saraes lap. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-doris" xml:id="eng000267-e121430">
            <speaker>Doris. </speaker>
            <l>I heau'n, your beautie cannot bring you thither, </l>
            <l>Your soule is blacke and spotted, full of sinne: </l>
            <l>You in adultry liu'd nine yeare together, </l>
            <l>And heau'n will neuer let adultry in. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e121480">
            <speaker>Mar: </speaker>
            <l>What art thou that dost poore Mariam pursue? </l>
            <l>Some spirit sent to driue me to dispaire: </l>
            <l>Who sees for truth that Mariam is vntrue, </l>
            <l>If faire she be, she is as chaste as faire. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-doris" xml:id="eng000267-e121530">
            <speaker>Doris. </speaker>
            <l>I am that Doris that was once belou'd, </l>
            <l>Belou'd by Herod: Herods lawfull wife: </l>
            <l>Twas you that Doris from his side remou'd, </l>
            <l>And rob'd from me the glory of my life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e121580">
            <speaker>Mar: </speaker>
            <l>Was that adultry: did not Moses say, </l>
            <l>That he that being matcht did deadly hate: </l>
            <l>Might by permission put his wife away, </l>
            <l>And take a more belou'd to be his mate? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-doris" xml:id="eng000267-e121630">
            <speaker>Doris. </speaker>
            <l>What did he hate me for: for simple truth? </l>
            <l>For bringing beautious babes for loue to him: </l>
            <l>For riches: noble birth, or tender youth, </l>
            <l>Or for no staine did Doris honour dim? </l>
            <l>Oh tell me Mariam, tell me if you knowe, </l>
            <l>Which fault of these made Herod Doris foe. </l>
            <l>These thrice three yeares haue I with hands held vp, </l>
            <l>And bowed knees fast nailed to the ground: </l>
            <l>Besought for thee the dreggs of that same cup, </l>
            <l>That cup of wrath that is for sinners found. </l>
            <l>And now thou art to drinke it: Doris curse, </l>
            <l>Vpon thy selfe did all this while attend, </l>
            <l>But now it shall pursue thy children worse. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e121770">
            <speaker>Mar: </speaker>
            <l>Oh Doris now to thee my knees I bend, </l>
            <l>That hart that neuer bow'd to thee doth bow: </l>
            <l>Curse not mine infants, let it thee suffice, </l>
            <l>That Heau'n doth punishment to me allow. </l>
            <l>Thy curse is cause that guiltles Mariam dies. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="eng000267-031-b"/>
          <sp who="#eng000267-doris" xml:id="eng000267-e121830">
            <speaker>Doris. </speaker>
            <l>Had I ten thousand tongues, and eu'ry tongue </l>
            <l>Inflam'd with poisons power, and steept in gall: </l>
            <l>My curses would not answere for my wrong, </l>
            <l>Though I in cursing thee imployd them all. </l>
            <l>Heare thou that didst mount Gerarim command, </l>
            <l>To be a place whereon with cause to curse: </l>
            <l>Stretch thy reuenging arme: thrust forth thy hand, </l>
            <l>And plague the mother much: the children worse. </l>
            <l>Throw flaming fire vpon the baseborne heads </l>
            <l>That were begotten in vnlawfull beds. </l>
            <l>But let them liue till they haue sence to know </l>
            <l>What tis to be in miserable state: </l>
            <l>Then be their neerest friends their ouerthrow, </l>
            <l>Attended be they by suspitious hate. </l>
            <l>And Mariam, I doe hope this boy of mine </l>
            <l>Shall one day come to be the death of thine. <stage xml:id="eng000267-e122000">Exit. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-mariam" xml:id="eng000267-e122010">
            <speaker>Mariam. </speaker>
            <l>Oh! Heauen forbid. I hope the world shall see, </l>
            <l>This curse of thine shall be return'd on thee: </l>
            <l>Now earth farewell, though I be yet but yong, </l>
            <l>Yet I, me thinks, haue knowne thee too too long. <stage xml:id="eng000267-e122060">Exit. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-chorus" xml:id="eng000267-e122070">
            <speaker>Chorus. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>THe fairest action of our humane life, </l>
              <l>Is scorning to reuenge an iniurie: </l>
              <l>For who forgiues without a further strife, </l>
              <l>His aduersaries heart to him doth tie. </l>
              <l>And tis a firmer conquest truely sed, </l>
              <l>To winne the heart, then ouerthrow the head. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>If we a worthy enemie doe finde, </l>
              <l>To yeeld to worth, it must be nobly done: </l>
              <l>But if of baser mettall be his minde, </l>
              <l>In base reuenge there is no honor wonne. </l>
              <l>Who would a worthy courage ouerthrow, </l>
              <l>And who would wrastle with a worthles foe? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="eng000267-032-a"/>
              <l>We say our hearts are great and cannot yeeld, </l>
              <l>Because they cannot yeeld it proues them poore: </l>
              <l>Great hearts are task't beyond their power, but seld </l>
              <l>The weakest Lyon will the lowdest roare. </l>
              <l>Truths schoole for certaine doth this same allow, </l>
              <l>High hartednes doth sometimes teach to bow. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>A noble heart doth teach a vertuous scorne, </l>
              <l>To scorne to owe a dutie ouer-long: </l>
              <l>To scorne to be for benefits forborne, </l>
              <l>To scorne to lie, to scorne to doe a wrong. </l>
              <l>To scorne to beare an iniurie in minde, </l>
              <l>To scorne a free-borne heart slaue-like to binde. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>But if for wrongs we needs reuenge must haue, </l>
              <l>Then be our vengeance of the noblest kinde: </l>
              <l>Doe we his body from our furie saue, </l>
              <l>And let our hate preuaile against our minde? </l>
              <l>What can gainst him a greater vengeance bee, </l>
              <l>Then make his foe more worthy farre then hee? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Had Mariam scorn'd to leaue a due vnpaide, </l>
              <l>Shee would to Herod then haue paid her loue: </l>
              <l>And not haue bene by sullen passion swaide </l>
              <l>To fixe her thoughts all iniurie aboue </l>
              <l>Is vertuous pride. Had Mariam thus bene prou'd, </l>
              <l>Long famous life to her had bene allowd. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="eng000267-e122500">
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="eng000267-e122510">
          <head>Actus quintus. Scoena prima. </head>
          <sp who="#eng000267-nuntius" xml:id="eng000267-e122520">
            <speaker>Nuntio. </speaker>
            <l>WHen, sweetest friend, did I so farre offend </l>
            <l>Your heauenly selfe: that you my fault to quit </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-032-b"/>
            <l>Haue made me now relator of her end, </l>
            <l>The end of beautie? Chastitie and wit, </l>
            <l>Was none so haples in the fatall place, </l>
            <l>But I, most wretched, for the Queene t'chuse, </l>
            <l>Tis certaine I haue some ill boding face </l>
            <l>That made me culd to tell this luckles newes. </l>
            <l>And yet no news to Herod: were it new, </l>
            <l>To him vnhappy t'had not bene at all: </l>
            <l>Yet doe I long to come within his vew, </l>
            <l>That he may know his wife did guiltles fall: </l>
            <l>And heere he comes. Your Mariam greets you well. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="eng000267-e122660">Enter Herod. </stage>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e122670">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>What? liues my Mariam? ioy, exceeding ioy. </l>
            <l>She shall not die. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-nuntius" xml:id="eng000267-e122700">
            <speaker>Nun. </speaker>
            <l>Heau'n doth your will repell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e122720">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Oh doe not with thy words my life destroy, </l>
            <l>I prethy tell no dying-tale: thine eye </l>
            <l>Without thy tongue doth tell but too too much: </l>
            <l>Yet let thy tongues addition make me die, </l>
            <l>Death welcome, comes to him whose griefe is such. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-nuntius" xml:id="eng000267-e122780">
            <speaker>Nunti. </speaker>
            <l>I went amongst the curious gazing troope, </l>
            <l>To see the last of her that was the best: </l>
            <l>To see if death had hart to make her stoope, </l>
            <l>To see the Sunne admiring Phoenix nest. </l>
            <l>When there I came, vpon the way I saw </l>
            <l>The stately Mariam not debas'd by feare: </l>
            <l>Her looke did seeme to keepe the world in awe, </l>
            <l>Yet mildly did her face this fortune beare. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e122870">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Thou dost vsurpe my right, my tongue was fram'd </l>
            <l>To be the instrument of Mariams praise: </l>
            <l>Yet speake: she cannot be too often fam'd: </l>
            <l>All tongues suffice not her sweet name to raise. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-nuntius" xml:id="eng000267-e122920">
            <speaker>Nun. </speaker>
            <l>But as she came she Alexandra met, </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-033-a"/>
            <l>Who did her death (sweet Queene) no whit bewaile, </l>
            <l>But as if nature she did quite forget, </l>
            <l>She did vpon her daughter loudly raile. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e122970">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Why stopt you not her mouth? where had she words </l>
            <l>To darke that, that Heauen made so bright? </l>
            <l>Our sacred tongue no Epithite affords, </l>
            <l>To call her other then the worlds delight. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-nuntius" xml:id="eng000267-e123020">
            <speaker>Nun. </speaker>
            <l>Shee told her that her death was too too good, </l>
            <l>And that already she had liu'd too long: </l>
            <l>She said, she sham'd to haue a part in blood </l>
            <l>Of her that did the princely Herod wrong. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e123070">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Base picke-thanke Diuell. Shame, twas all her glory, </l>
            <l>That she to noble Mariam was the mother: </l>
            <l>But neuer shall it liue in any storie </l>
            <l>Her name, except to infamy ile smother. </l>
            <l>What answere did her princely daughter make? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-nuntius" xml:id="eng000267-e123130">
            <speaker>Nun. </speaker>
            <l>She made no answere, but she lookt the while, </l>
            <l>As if thereof she scarce did notice take, </l>
            <l>Yet smilde, a dutifull, though scornefull smile. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e123170">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Sweet creature, I that looke to mind doe call, </l>
            <l>Full oft hath Herod bene amaz'd withall. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-nuntius" xml:id="eng000267-e123200">
            <speaker>Nun. </speaker>
            <l>Go on, she came vnmou'd with pleasant grace, </l>
            <l>As if to triumph her arriuall were: </l>
            <l>In stately habite, and with cheerfull face: </l>
            <l>Yet eu'ry eye was moyst, but Mariams there. </l>
            <l>When iustly opposite to me she came, </l>
            <l>She pickt me out from all the crue: </l>
            <l>She beckned to me, cald me by my name, </l>
            <l>For she my name, my birth, and fortune knew. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e123290">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>What did she name thee? happy, happy man, </l>
            <l>Wilt thou not euer loue that name the better? </l>
            <l>But what sweet tune did this faire dying Swan </l>
            <l>Afford thine care: tell all, omit no letter. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-nuntius" xml:id="eng000267-e123340">
            <speaker>Nun. </speaker>
            <l>Tell thou my Lord, said she. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e123360">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Mee, ment flie mee? </l>
            <l>Ist true, the more my shame: I was her Lord, </l>
            <l>Were I not made her Lord, I still should bee: </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-033-b"/>
            <l>But now her name must be by me adord. </l>
            <l>Oh say, what said she more? each word she sed </l>
            <l>Shall be the food whereon my heart is fed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-nuntius" xml:id="eng000267-e123430">
            <speaker>Nun: </speaker>
            <l>Tell thou my Lord thou saw'st me loose my breath. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e123450">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Oh that I could that sentence now controule. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-nuntius" xml:id="eng000267-e123470">
            <speaker>Nun. </speaker>
            <l>If guiltily eternall be my death, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e123490">
            <speaker>Her: </speaker>
            <l>I hold her chast eu'n in my inmost soule. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-nuntius" xml:id="eng000267-e123510">
            <speaker>Nun: </speaker>
            <l>By three daies hence if wishes could reuiue, </l>
            <l>I know himselfe would make me oft aliue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e123540">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Three daies: three houres, three minutes, not so much, </l>
            <l>A minute in a thousand parts diuided, </l>
            <l>My penitencie for her death is such, </l>
            <l>As in the first I wisht she had not died. </l>
            <l>But forward in thy tale. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-nuntius" xml:id="eng000267-e123600">
            <speaker>Nun: </speaker>
            <l>Why on she went, </l>
            <l>And after she some silent praier had sed: </l>
            <l>She did as if to die she were content, </l>
            <l>And thus to heau'n her heau'nly soule is fled. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e123650">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>But art thou sure there doth no life remaine? </l>
            <l>Ist possible my Mariam should be dead, </l>
            <l>Is there no tricke to make her breathe againe? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-nuntius" xml:id="eng000267-e123690">
            <speaker>Nun: </speaker>
            <l>Her body is diuided from her head. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e123710">
            <speaker>Her: </speaker>
            <l>Why yet me thinkes there might be found by art, </l>
            <l>Strange waies of cure, tis sure rare things are don: </l>
            <l>By an inuentiue head, and willing heart. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-nuntius" xml:id="eng000267-e123750">
            <speaker>Nun: </speaker>
            <l>Let not my Lord your fancies idlely run. </l>
            <l>It is as possible it should be seen. </l>
            <l>That we should make the holy Abraham liue, </l>
            <l>Though he intomb'd two thousand yeares had bene, </l>
            <l>As breath againe to slaughtred Mariam giue. </l>
            <l>But now for more assaults prepare your eares, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e123820">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>There cannot be a further cause of mone, </l>
            <l>This accident shall shelter me from feares: </l>
            <l>What can I feare? already Mariams gone. </l>
            <l>Yet tell eu'n what you will: </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-nuntius" xml:id="eng000267-e123870">
            <speaker>Nun: </speaker>
            <l>As I came by, </l>
            <l>From Mariams death I saw vpon a tree, </l>
            <l>A man that to his necke a cord did tie: </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-034-a"/>
            <l>Which cord he had designd his end to bee, </l>
            <l>When me he once discern'd, he downwards bow'd, </l>
            <l>And thus with fearefull voyce she cride alowd, </l>
            <l>Goe tell the King he trusted ere he tride, </l>
            <l>I am the cause that Mariam causeles dide. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e123960">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Damnation take him, for it was the slaue </l>
            <l>That said she ment with poisons deadly force </l>
            <l>To end my life that she the Crowne might haue: </l>
            <l>Which tale did Mariam from her selfe diuorce. </l>
            <l>Oh pardon me thou pure vnspotted Ghost, </l>
            <l>My punishment must needes sufficient bee, </l>
            <l>In missing that content I valued most: </l>
            <l>Which was thy admirable face to see. </l>
            <l>I had but one inestimable Iewell, </l>
            <l>Yet one I had no monarch had the like, </l>
            <l>And therefore may I curse my selfe as cruell: </l>
            <l>Twas broken by a blowe my selfe did strike. </l>
            <l>I gaz'd thereon and neuer thought me blest, </l>
            <l>But when on it my dazled eye might rest: </l>
            <l>A pretious Mirror made by wonderous art, </l>
            <l>I prizd it ten times dearer then my Crowne, </l>
            <l>And laide it vp fast foulded in my heart: </l>
            <l>Yet I in suddaine choler cast it downe. </l>
            <l>And pasht it all to peeces: twas no foe, </l>
            <l>That robd me of it; no Arabian host, </l>
            <l>Nor no Armenian guide hath vsde me so: </l>
            <l>But Herods wretched selfe hath Herod crost. </l>
            <l>She was my gracefull moytie, me accurst, </l>
            <l>To slay my better halfe and saue my worst. </l>
            <l>But sure she is not dead you did but iest, </l>
            <l>To put me in perplexitie a while, </l>
            <l>Twere well indeed if I could so be drest: </l>
            <l>I see she is aliue, me thinkes you smile. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-nuntius" xml:id="eng000267-e124250">
            <speaker>Nun: </speaker>
            <l>If sainted Abel yet deceased bee, </l>
            <l>Tis certaine Mariam is as dead as hee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e124280">
            <speaker>Her: </speaker>
            <l>Why then goe call her to me, bid her now </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-034-b"/>
            <l>Put on faire habite, stately ornament: </l>
            <l>And let no frowne ore shade her smoothest brow, </l>
            <l>In her doth Herod place his whole content. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-nuntius" xml:id="eng000267-e124330">
            <speaker>Nun: </speaker>
            <l>Sheel come in stately weedes to please your sence, </l>
            <l>If now she come attirde in robe of heauen: </l>
            <l>Remember you your selfe did send her hence, </l>
            <l>And now to you she can no more be giuen. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e124380">
            <speaker>Herod. </speaker>
            <l>Shee's dead, hell take her murderers, she was faire, </l>
            <l>Oh what a hand she had, it was so white, </l>
            <l>It did the whitenes of the snowe impaire: </l>
            <l>I neuer more shall see so sweet a sight. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-nuntius" xml:id="eng000267-e124430">
            <speaker>Nun: </speaker>
            <l>Tis true, her hand was rare. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-herod" xml:id="eng000267-e124450">
            <speaker>Her: </speaker>
            <l>her hand? her hands; </l>
            <l>She had not singly one of beautie rare, </l>
            <l>But such a paire as heere where Herod stands, </l>
            <l>He dares the world to make to both compare. </l>
            <l>Accursed Salome, hadst thou bene still, </l>
            <l>My Mariam had bene breathing by my side: </l>
            <l>Oh neuer had I: had I had my will, </l>
            <l>Sent forth command, that Mariam should haue dide. </l>
            <l>But Salome thou didst with enuy vexe, </l>
            <l>To see thy selfe out-matched in thy sexe: </l>
            <l>Vpon your sexes forehead Mariam sat, </l>
            <l>To grace you all like an imperiall crowne, </l>
            <l>But you fond foole haue rudely pusht thereat, </l>
            <l>And proudly puld your proper glory downe. </l>
            <l>One smile of hers: Nay, not so much a: looke </l>
            <l>Was worth a hundred thousand such as you, </l>
            <l>Iudea how canst thou the wretches brooke, </l>
            <l>That robd from thee the fairest of the crew? </l>
            <l>You dwellers in the now depriued land, </l>
            <l>Wherein the matchles Mariam was bred: </l>
            <l>Why graspe not each of you a sword in hand, </l>
            <l>To ayme at me your cruell Soueraignes head. </l>
            <l>Oh when you thinke of Herod as your King, </l>
            <l>And owner of the pride of Palestine: </l>
            <l>This act to your remembrance likewise bring, </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-035-a"/>
            <l>Tis I haue ouerthrowne your royall line. </l>
            <l>Within her purer vaines the blood did run, </l>
            <l>That from her Grandam Sara she deriu'd, </l>
            <l>Whose beldame age the loue of Kings hath wonne, </l>
            <l>Oh that her issue had as long bene li'ud. </l>
            <l>But can her eye be made by death obscure? </l>
            <l>I cannot thinke but it must sparkle still: </l>
            <l>Foule sacriledge to rob those lights so pure, </l>
            <l>From out a Temple made by heau'nly skill. </l>
            <l>I am the Villaine that haue done the deed, </l>
            <l>The cruell deed, though by anothers hand, </l>
            <l>My word though not my sword made Mariam bleed, </l>
            <l>Hircanus Grandchild did at my command. </l>
            <l>That Mariam that I once did loue so deare, </l>
            <l>The partner of my now detested bed, </l>
            <l>Why shine you sun with an aspect so cleare? </l>
            <l>I tell you once againe my Mariams dead. </l>
            <l>You could but shine, if some Egiptian blows, </l>
            <l>Or AEthiopian doudy lose her life: </l>
            <l>This was, then wherefore bend you not your brows, </l>
            <l>The King of Iuries faire and spotles wife. </l>
            <l>Denie thy beames, and Moone refuse thy light, </l>
            <l>Let all the starres be darke, let Iuries eye </l>
            <l>No more distinguish which is day and night: </l>
            <l>Since her best birth did in her bosome die. </l>
            <l>Those fond Idolaters the men of Greece, </l>
            <l>Maintaine these orbes are safely gouerned: </l>
            <l>That each within themselues haue Gods a peece, </l>
            <l>By whom their stedfast course is iustly led. </l>
            <l>But were it so, as so it cannot bee, </l>
            <l>They all would put their mourning garments on: </l>
            <l>Not one of them would yeeld a light to mee, </l>
            <l>To me that is the cause that Mariams gon. </l>
            <l>For though they fame their Saturne melancholy, </l>
            <l>Of sowre behauiours, and of angry moode: </l>
            <l>They fame him likewise to be iust and holy, </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-035-b"/>
            <l>And iustice needes must seeke reuenge for blood, </l>
            <l>Their Ioue, if Ioue he were, would sure desire, </l>
            <l>To punish him that slew so faire a lasse: </l>
            <l>For Laedaes beautie set his heart on fire, </l>
            <l>Yet she not halfe so faire as Mariam was. </l>
            <l>And Mars would deeme his Venus had bene slaine, </l>
            <l>Sol to recouer her would neuer sticke: </l>
            <l>For if he want the power her life to gaine: </l>
            <l>Then Physicks God is but an Empericke. </l>
            <l>The Queene of loue would storme for beauties sake, </l>
            <l>And Hermes too, since he bestow'd her wit, </l>
            <l>The nights pale light for angrie griefe would shake, </l>
            <l>To see chast Mariam die in age vnfit. </l>
            <l>But oh I am deceiu'd, she past them all </l>
            <l>In euery gift, in euery propertie: </l>
            <l>Her Excellencies wrought her timeles fall, </l>
            <l>And they reioyc'd, not grieu'd to see her die. </l>
            <l>The Paphian Goddesse did repent her wast, </l>
            <l>When she to one such beautie did allow: </l>
            <l>Mercurius thought her wit his wit surpast, </l>
            <l>And Cinthia enui'd Mariams brighter brow. </l>
            <l>But these are fictions, they are void of sence, </l>
            <l>The Greekes but dreame, and dreaming falsehoods tell: </l>
            <l>They neither can offend nor giue defence, </l>
            <l>And not by them it was my Mariam fell. </l>
            <l>If she had bene like an Egiptian blacke, </l>
            <l>And not so faire, she had bene longer liude: </l>
            <l>Her ouerflow of beautie turned backe, </l>
            <l>And drownde the spring from whence it was deriude. </l>
            <l>Her heau'nly beautie twas that made me thinke </l>
            <l>That it with chastitie could neuer dwell: </l>
            <l>But now I see that heau'n in her did linke, </l>
            <l>A spirit and a person to excell. </l>
            <l>Ile muffle vp my selfe in endles night, </l>
            <l>And neuer let mine eyes behold the light. </l>
            <l>Retire thy selfe vile monster, worse then hee </l>
            <pb xml:id="eng000267-036-a"/>
            <l>That staind the virgin earth with brothers blood, </l>
            <l>Still in some vault or denne inclosed bee, </l>
            <l>Where with thy teares thou maist beget a flood, </l>
            <l>Which flood in time may drowne thee: happie day </l>
            <l>When thou at once shalt die and finde a graue, </l>
            <l>A stone vpon the vault, some one shall lay, </l>
            <l>Which monument shall an inscription haue. </l>
            <l>And these shall be the words it shall containe, </l>
            <l>Heere Herod lies, that hath his Mariam slaine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#eng000267-chorus" xml:id="eng000267-e125520">
            <speaker>Chorus. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>WHo euer hath beheld with steadfast eye, </l>
              <l>The strange euents of this one onely day: </l>
              <l>How many were deceiu'd? How many die, </l>
              <l>That once to day did grounds of safetie lay? </l>
              <l>It will from them all certaintie bereue, </l>
              <l>Since twice sixe houres so many can deceiue. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>This morning Herod held for surely dead, </l>
              <l>And all the Iewes on Mariam did attend: </l>
              <l>And Constabarus rise from Saloms bed, </l>
              <l>And neither dreamd of a diuorce or end. </l>
              <l>Pheroras ioyd that he might haue his wife, </l>
              <l>And Babus sonnes for safetie of their life. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>To night our Herod doth aliue remaine, </l>
              <l>The guiltles Mariam is depriu'd of breath: </l>
              <l>Stout Constabarus both diuorst and slaine, </l>
              <l>The valiant sonnes of Baba haue their death. </l>
              <l>Pheroras sure his loue to be bereft, </l>
              <l>If Salome her sute vnmade had left. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Herod this morning did expect with ioy, </l>
              <l>To see his Mariams much beloued face: </l>
              <l>And yet ere night he did her life destroy, </l>
              <pb xml:id="eng000267-036-b"/>
              <l>And surely thought she did her name disgrace. </l>
              <l>Yet now againe so short do humors last, </l>
              <l>He both repents her death and knowes her chast. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Had he with wisedome now her death delaide, </l>
              <l>He at his pleasure might command her death: </l>
              <l>But now he hath his power so much betraide, </l>
              <l>As all his woes cannot restore her breath. </l>
              <l>Now doth he strangely lunatickly raue, </l>
              <l>Because his Mariams life he cannot saue. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>This daies euents were certainly ordainde, </l>
              <l>To be the warning to posteritie: </l>
              <l>So many changes are therein containde, </l>
              <l>So admirablie strange varietie. </l>
              <l>This day alone, our sagest Hebrewes shall </l>
              <l>In after times the schoole of wisedome call. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back></back>
  </text>
</TEI>
