<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000338" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Masque of the Middle Temple and Lincoln's Inn</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>George</forename>
            <surname>Chapman</surname>
          </persName>
          <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q342720</idno>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A18416.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="A18416-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull n="TCP source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">The memorable maske of the two honorable houses or Innes of Court; the Middle Temple, and Lyncolns Inne. As it was performd before the King, at White-Hall on Shroue Munday at night; being the 15. of February. 1613. At the princely celebration of the most royall nuptialls of the Palsgraue, and his thrice gratious Princesse Elizabeth. &amp;c. With a description of their whole show; in the manner of their march on horse-backe to the Court from the Maister of the Rolls his house: with all their right noble consorts, and most showfull attendants. Inuented, and fashioned, with the ground, and speciall structure of the whole worke: by our kingdomes most artfull and ingenious architect Innigo Iones. Supplied, aplied, digested, and written, by Geo: Chapman.</title>
                <author>Chapman, George, 1559?-1634.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>28 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
                <date>2003 January (TCP phase 1)</date>
                <idno type="marc">99843391</idno>
                <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 4981.</idno>
                <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 310(a).</idno>
                <idno type="vid">8121</idno>
                <idno type="DLPS">A18416</idno>
                <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2240896215</idno>
                <availability>
                  <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
                </availability>
              </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
            <biblFull n="printed source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">The memorable maske of the two honorable houses or Innes of Court; the Middle Temple, and Lyncolns Inne. As it was performd before the King, at White-Hall on Shroue Munday at night; being the 15. of February. 1613. At the princely celebration of the most royall nuptialls of the Palsgraue, and his thrice gratious Princesse Elizabeth. &amp;c. With a description of their whole show; in the manner of their march on horse-backe to the Court from the Maister of the Rolls his house: with all their right noble consorts, and most showfull attendants. Inuented, and fashioned, with the ground, and speciall structure of the whole worke: by our kingdomes most artfull and ingenious architect Innigo Iones. Supplied, aplied, digested, and written, by Geo: Chapman.</title>
                <title type="alt">Masque of the middle Temple, and Lincolns Inne.</title>
                <author>Chapman, George, 1559?-1634.</author>
                <author>Jones, Inigo, 1573-1652.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[56] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Printed by G. Eld, for George Norton, and are to be sould at his shoppe neere Temple-bar,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication_date">[1613]</date>
                <date type="creation_date">1613</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>
                  <p>Publication date from STC.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Signatures: [par.]2 A4 a4 B-E4 F2.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>The last leaf is blank.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Running title reads: The masque of the middle Temple, and Lincolns Inne.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Leaf a4r has errata. Variant: a4r lacks errata; the argument in a different setting.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Reproduction of the original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</p>
                </note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <person xml:id="ep000338-plutus">
            <persName>Plutus</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000338-capriccio">
            <persName>Capriccio</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000338-eun">
            <persName>Eun</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000338-honour">
            <persName>Honour</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000338-herald">
            <persName>Herald</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000338-chorus">
            <persName>Chorus</persName>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1613">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
    <listRelation>
      <relation name="wikidata"
                   active="https://dracor.org/entity/ep000338"
                   passive="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q7750957"/>
    </listRelation>
  </standOff>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000338-e100030">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000338-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-001-b"/>
        <p>THE MEMORABLE MASKE of the two Honorable Houses or Inns of Court; the Middle Temple, and Lyncolns Inne. </p>
        <p>As it was performd before the King, at White-Hall on Shroue Munday at night; being the 15. of February. 1613. </p>
        <p>At the Princely celebration of the most Royall Nuptialls of the palsgrave, and his thrice gratious Princesse Elizabeth. &amp;c. </p>
        <p>With a description of their whole show; in the manner of their march on horse-backe to the Court from the Maister of the Rolls his house: with all their right Noble consorts, and most showfull attendants. </p>
        <p>Inuented, and fashioned, with the ground, and speciall structure of the whole worke, </p>
        <p>By our Kingdomes most Artfull and Ingenious Architect INNIGO IONES. </p>
        <p>Supplied, Aplied, Digested, and written, By GEO: CHAPMAN. </p>
        <p>AT LONDON, Printed by G. Eld, for George Norton and are to be sould at his shoppe neere Temple-bar. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000338-e100120">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000338-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-002-b"/>
        <head>TO THE MOST NOble, and constant Combiner of Honor, and Vertue, Sir EDWARD PHILIPS, Knight, Mr. of the Rolls. </head>
        <p>THis Noble and Magnificent performance, renewing the ancient spirit, and Honor of the Innes of Court; being especially furthered and followed by your most laborious and honored endeuors, (for his Maiesties seruice; and honour of the all-grace-deseruing Nuptialls, of the thrice gracious Princesse Elizabeth, his Highness daughter) deserues especially to be in this sort consecrate, to your worthy memory and honor. Honor, hauing neuer her faire hand more freely and nobly giuen to Riches (being a fit particle of this Inuention) then by yours, at this Nuptiall solemnity. To which assisted, and <pb xml:id="ep000338-003-a"/>memorable ceremony; the ioin'd hand and industry, of the worthely honour'd Knight, Sir H. Hubberd, his Maiesties Atturny generall, deseruing, in good part, a ioint memory with yours; I have submitted it freely to his noble acceptance. The poore paines I added to this Royall seruice, being wholly chosen, and commanded by your most constant, and free fauour; I hope will now appeare nothing neglectiue of their expected duties. Hearty wil, and care enough, I am assured was employ'd in me; and the onely ingenuous will, being first and principall step to vertue; I beseech you let it stand for the performing vertue it selfe. In which addition of your euer-honour'd fauours, you shall euer binde all my future seruice to your most wished Commandement. </p>
        <p>God send you long health, and your Vertues will endue you with honor enough, </p>
        <closer>
          <signed>By your free merits euer vow'd honorer, and most vnfainedly affectionate Obseruant. GEO. CHAPMAN. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="text" xml:id="ep000338-e100170">
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-003-b"/>
        <head>THE MASKE OF THE Gentlemen of the two combin'd houses, or Inns of Court, the Middle-Temple, and Lincolns Inne. </head>
        <p>AT the house of the most worthely honour'd preferrer and gracer of all honorable Actions, and vertues, (Sir Edward Philips Knight, Master of the Rolls) al the Performers and their Assistents made their Rendesvous, prepar'd to their performance, and thus set forth. </p>
        <p>Fiftie Gentlemen, richly attirde, and as gallantly mounted, with Foot-men perticularly attending, made the noble vant-guarde of these Nuptiall forces. Next (a fit distance obseru'd betweene them) marcht a mock-Maske <pb xml:id="ep000338-004-a"/>of Baboons, attir'd like fantasticall Trauailers, in Neapolitane sutes, and great ruffes, all horst with Asses; and dwarfe Palfries, with yellow foot-cloathes, and casting Cockle-demois about, in courtesie, by way of lardges; Torches boarn on either hand of them; lighting their state as ridiculously, as the rest Nobly. After them were sorted two Carrs Triumphall, adornd with great Maske heads, Festones, scroules, and antick leaues, euery part inricht with siluer and golde. These were through-varied with different inuention, and in them aduanc't, the choice Musitions of our Kingdome, sixe in each; attir'd like Virginean Priests, by whom the Sun is there ador'd; and therfore called the Phoebades. Their Robes were tuckt vp before; strange Hoods of feathers, and scallops about their neckes, and on their heads turbants, stucke with seuerall colour'd feathers, spotted with wings of Flies, of extraordinary bignesse; like those of their countrie: And about them march't two ranks of Torches. Then rode the chiefe Maskers, in Indian <pb xml:id="ep000338-004-b"/>habits, all of a resemblance: the ground cloath of siluer, richly embroidered, with golden Sunns, and about euery Sunne, ran a traile of gold, imitating Indian worke,: their bases of the same stuffe and work, but betwixt euery pane of embroidery, went a rowe of white Estridge feathers, mingled with sprigs of golde plate; vnder their breasts, they woare bawdricks of golde, embroidered high with purle, and about their neckes, Ruffes of feathers, spangled with pearle and siluer. On their heads high sprig'd-feathers, compast in Coronets, like the Virginian Princes they presented. Betwixt euery set of feathers, and about their browes, in the vnder-part of their Coronets, shin'd Sunnes of golde plate, sprinkled with pearle; from whence sprung rayes of the like plate, that mixing with the motion of the feathers, shew'd exceedingly delightfull, and gracious. Their legges were adorn'd, with close long white silke-stockings: curiously embroidered with golde to the Middelegge. </p>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-005-a"/>
        <p>And ouer these (being on horse backe) they drew greaues or buskins embrodered with gould, &amp; enterlac't with rewes of fethers; Altogether estrangfull, and Indian like. </p>
        <p>In their Hands (set in seueral postures as they rode) they brandisht cane darts of the finest gould. Their vizerds of oliue collour; but pleasingly visag'd: their hayre, blacke and lardge, wauing downe to their shoulders. </p>
        <p>Their Horse, for rich show, equalld the Maskers them-selues; all their caparisons being enchac't with sunnes of Gould and Ornamentall Iewells. To euery one of which, was tackt a Scarffing of Siluer; that ran sinnuousely in workes ouer the whole caparison, euen to the daseling of the admiring spectators. </p>
        <p>Their heads, no lesse gracefully and properly deckt with the like light skarffing that hung about their eares wantonly dangling. </p>
        <p>Euery one of these horse, had two Moores, attir'd like Indian slaues, that for state sided them; with swelling wreaths of gould, and watshed on their heads, which arose in all to <pb xml:id="ep000338-005-b"/>the number of a hundred. </p>
        <p>The Torch-bearers habits were likewise of the Indian garb, but more strauagant then those of the Maskers; all showfully garnisht with seueral-hewd fethers. The humble variety whereof, stucke off the more amplie, the Maskers high beauties, shining in the habits of themselues; and reflected in their kinde, a new and delightfully-varied radiance on the beholders. </p>
        <p>All these sustaind torches of Virgine wax, whose staues were great canes al ouer gilded; And these (as the rest) had euery Man his Moore, attending his horse. </p>
        <p>The Maskers, riding single; had euery Masker, his Torch-bearer mounted before him. </p>
        <p>The last Charriot, which was most of all adornd; had his whole frame fill'd with moulded worke; mixt all with paintings, and glittering scarffings of siluer; ouer which was cast a Canopie of golde, boarne vp with antick figures, and all compos'd a la Grotesea. Before this in the seate of it, as the Chariotere; <pb xml:id="ep000338-006-a"/>was aduanc't a strange person, and as strangely habited, half French, halfe Swizz; his name Capriccio; wearing on his head a paire of golden Bellowes, a guilt spurre in one hand, and with the other mannaging the reignes of the fowre Horses that drewe it: </p>
        <p>On a seate of the same Chariot, a little more eleuate, sate Eunomia, the Virgine Priest of the Goddesse Honor, together with Phemis, her Herald: The habite of her Priest, was a Robe of white silke, gathered about the necke; a pentacle of siluered stuffe about her shoulders, hanging foldedly downe, both before and behind. </p>
        <p>A vestall vaile on her head of Tiffany, strip't with siluer, hanging with a trayne, to the earth. </p>
        <p>The Herrald was attyr'd in an Antique Curace of siluer stuffe, with labells at the wings and basses; a short gowne of gould stuffe; with wide sleeues, cut in panes: A wreath of gould on his head, and a Rod of gould in his hand. </p>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-006-b"/>
        <p>Highest of all in the most eminent seate of the Tryumphall sat, side to side, the coelestiall Goddesse, Honour; and the earthy Deity, Plutus; or Riches. His attire; a short robe of gould, frindg'd; his wide sleeues turn'd vp, and out-showd his naked armes: his Head and Beard sprinckl'd with showrs of gould: his Buskins, clinckant, as his other attire. The Ornaments of Honor were these: a rich full robe of blew silke girt about her, a mantle of siluer worne ouer-thwart, ful gathered, and descending in folds behind: a vaile of netlawne, enbrodered with Oos and Spangl'd; her tresses in tucks, braided with siluer: The hinder part shadowing in waues her shoulders. </p>
        <p>These, thus perticularly, and with proprietie adorn'd, were strongly attended with a full Guard of two hundred Halbardiers: two Marshals (being choice Gentlemen, of either house) Commaunder-like attir'd, to and fro coursing, to keepe all in their orders. </p>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-007-a"/>
        <p>A showe at all parts so nouell, conceitfull and glorious, as hath not in this land, (to the proper vse and obiect it had porpos'd) beene euer before beheld. Nor did those honorable Inns of Court, at any time in that kinde, such acceptable seruice to the sacred Maiesty of this kingdome, nor were return'd by many degrees, with so thrice gratious, and royall entertainment and honor. But, (as aboue sayd) all these so marching to the Court at White Hall, the King, Bride, &amp; Bridegroom, with all the Lords of the most honord priuy Councel, and our chief Nobility, stood in the Gallery before the Tilt-yeard, to behold their arriuall; who, for the more ful satisfaction of his Maiesties view, made one turn about the yeard, and dismounted: being then honorably attended through the Gallery to a Chamber appointed, where they were to make ready for their performance in the Hall, &amp;c. </p>
        <p>The King beeing come forth, the Maskers ascended vnseene to their scoene. Then for the works. </p>
        <p>First there appear'd at the lower end of the <pb xml:id="ep000338-007-b"/>Hall, an Artificiall Rock, whose top was neere as high as the hall it selfe. This Rock, was in the vndermost part craggy, and full of hollow places, in whose concaues were contriv'd, two winding paire of staires, by whose greeces the Persons aboue might make their descents, and all the way be seene: all this Rocke grew by degrees vp into a gold-colour; and was run quite through, with veines of golde: On the one side whereof, eminently raised on a faire hill, was erected a siluer Temple of an octangle figure, whose Pillars were of a compos'd order, and bore vp an Architraue, Freese, and Cornish: Ouer which stood a continued Plinthe; whereon were aduaunc't Statues of siluer: Aboue this, was placed a bastarde Order of Architecture, wherein were keru'd Compartements: In one of which was written in great golde Capitalls, HONORIS FANVM: Aboue all, was a Coupolo, or Type, which seem'd to be scal'd with siluer Plates. </p>
        <p>For finishing, of all, vpon a Pedistall, was fixt a round stone of siluer, from which grew a paire of golden wings, both faign'd to bee <pb xml:id="ep000338-008-a"/>Fortunes: the round stone (when her feet trod it) euer affirm'd to be rouling; figuring her inconstancy: the golden wings, denoting those nimble Powres, that pompously beare her about the world; On that Temple (erected to her daughter, Honor; and figuring this kingdome) put off by her, and fixt, for assured signe she would neuer forsake it. </p>
        <p>About this Temple, hung Festones wreath'd with siluer from one Pillars head to another. Besides, the Freese was enricht with keruings, all shewing Greatnes and Magnificence. </p>
        <p>On the other side of the Rocke, grewe a Groue, in whose vtmost part appear'd a vast, wither'd, and hollow Tree, being the bare receptacle of the Baboonerie. </p>
        <p>These following should in duty haue had their proper places, after euery fitted speech of the Actors; but being preuented by the vnexpected haste of the Printer, which he neuer let me know, and neuer sending me a proofe, till he had past those speeches; I had no reason to imagine hee could haue been so forward. His fault is therfore to be supplied by the obseruation, <pb xml:id="ep000338-008-b"/>and reference of the Reader, who will easily perceiue, where they were to bee inserted. </p>
        <p>After the speech of Plutus (who as you may see after, first entred) the middle part of the Rocke began to moue, and being come some fiue paces vp towards the King, it split in peeces with a great crack; and our brake Capriccio, as before described. The peeces of the Rocke vanisht and he spake as in his place. </p>
        <p>At the singing of the first Song, full, which was sung by the Virginian Priests; called the Phoebades, to sixe Lutes (being vsed as an Orphean vertue, for the state of the Mines opening): the vpper part of the Rock was sodainly turn'd to a Cloude, discouering a rich and refulgent Mine of golde; in which the twelue Maskers were triumphantly seated: their Torch-bearers attending before them. All the lights beeing so ordred, that though none were seen, yet had their lustre such vertue, that by it, the least spangle or spark of the Maskers rich habites, might with ease and cleerenesse be discerned as far off as the seate. </p>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-009-a"/>
        <p>Ouer this golden Mine, in an Euening sky, the ruddy Sunne was seen ready to be set; and behind the tops of certaine white Cliffes, by degrees descended, casting vp a banke of Cloudes; in which, a while hee was hidden: but then gloriously shining, gaue that vsually-obseru'd good Omen, of succeeding faire weather. </p>
        <p>Before he was fully set, the Phoebades (shewing the custome of the Indians to adore the Sunne setting) began their obseruance with the Song, to whose place, wee must referre you for the manner and words; All the time they were singing; the Torch-bearers holding vp their Torches to the Sun; to whome the Priests themselues, and the rest, did as they sung obeisance: Which was answred by other Musique and voices, at the commandement of Honor, with all' obseruances vs'd to the King &amp;c. As in the following places. </p>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-009-b"/>
        <p>TO answer certaine insolent obiections made against the length of my speeches, and narrations; being (for the probability of all accidents, rising from the inuention of this Maske; and their aplication, to the persons, and places: for whome, and by whome it was presented) not conuenient, but necessary; I am enforct to affirme this; That: as there is no Poem nor Oration so generall; but hath his one perticular proposition; Nor no riuer so extrauagantly ample, but hath his neuer-so-narrow fountaine, worthy to be namd; so all these courtly, and honoring inuentions (hauing Poesie, and Oration in them, and a fountaine, to be exprest, from whence their Riuers flow) should expressiuely-arise; out of the places, and persons for; and by whome they are presented; without which limits, they are luxurious, and paine. But what rules soeuer are set downe, to any Art, or Act (though, without their obseruation; No Art, nor Act, is true, and worthy) yet are they nothing the more followd; or those few that follow them credited. Euery vulgarly-esteemd vpstart; dares breake the dreadfull dignity of antient and autenticall Poesie: and presume Luciforously, to proclame in place thereof, repugnant precepts of their owne spaune. Truth, and Worth, haue no faces, to enamour the Lycentious, but vaine-glory, and humor. The same body: the same beauty, a thousand men seeing: Onely the man whose bloud is fitted, hath that which hee calls his soule, enamourd. And this, out of infallible cause; for, men vnderstand not these of Maenander— est morbus <pb xml:id="ep000338-010-a"/>oportunitas </p>
        <quote>Animae, quodictus, vulnus accipit graue. </quote>
        <p>But the cause of all Mens being enamourd with Truth. And of her slight respect, in others; is the diuine Freedom; one touching with his aprehensiue finger, the other, passing. The Hill of the Muses (which all men must clime in the regular way, to Truth) is said of ould, to be forcked. And the two points of it, parting at the Top; are Insania, and, diuinus furor. Insania, is that which euery Ranck-brainde writer; and iudge of Poeticall writing, is rapt withal; when hee presumes either to write or censure the height of Poesie; and that transports him with humor, vaine-glory and pride, most prophane and sacrilegious: when diuinus furor; makes gentle, and noble, the neuer so truly inspired writer— </p>
        <quote>Emollit mores nec sinit esse feros. </quote>
        <p>And the mild beames of the most holy inflamer; easely, and sweetly enter, with all vnderstanding sharpenesse, the soft, and sincerely humane; but with no Time; No Study; No meanes vnder heauen: any arrogant, all-occupation deuourer (that will Chandler-like set vp with all wares; selling, Poesies Nectar and Ambrosia; as wel as musterd, and vineagar.) The chast and restraind beames of humble truth will euer enter; but onely grase, and glaunce at them: and the further fly them. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="argument" xml:id="ep000338-e100500">
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-010-b"/>
        <head>The aplicable argument of the Maske. </head>
        <p>HOnor, is so much respected, and ador'd; that shee hath a Temple erected to her, like a Goddesse; a Virgine Priest consecrated to her (which is Eunomia, or Lawe; since none should dare accesse to Honor, but by Vertue; of which Lawe being the rule, must needes be a chiefe) and a Herrald (call'd Phemis, or Fame) to proclame her institutions, and commandements. To amplefie yet more the diuine graces of this Goddesse; Plutus, (or Riches) being by Aristophanes, Lucian. &amp;c. presented naturally blind, deformd, and dull witted; is here by his loue of Honor, made see, made sightly, made ingenious; made liberall: And all this conuerted and consecrate to the most worthy celebration of these sacred Nuptialls; all issuing (to conclude the necessary application) from an honorable Temple. &amp;c. <quote>
            <l>Non est certa fides, quam non Iniuria versat. </l>
            <l>— Fallit portus &amp; ipse fidem. </l>
          </quote>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="errata" xml:id="ep000338-e100550">
        <head>Errata. </head>
        <p>In Capri. first speech, for many, read maine, in c. 1. for Pot, re. post. in c. 3. for answer, re. austerity, for purposes, re. purses, in c. 3. for seemingly, re. securely, in d. 2. for law, and vertue, re. loue and beauty, in the first stance of the second song, for this re. his. for sweet deuotions, re. fit deuotions. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="ep000338-e100580">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000338-011-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-011-b"/>
        <head>THE NAMES OF THE SPEAKERS. </head>
        <list>
          <item>Honour, a Goddesse. </item>
          <item>Plutus, (or Riches) a God. </item>
          <item>Eunomia (or law) Priest of honor. </item>
          <item>Phemis, Honors Herrald. </item>
          <item>Capriccio, a man of wit, &amp;c. </item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="play" xml:id="ep000338-e100650">
        <head>THE PRESENTMENT. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000338-e100660">Plutus appear'd suruaying the worke with this speech. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e100670">
          <speaker>PLVTVS. </speaker>
          <p>ROckes? Nothing but Rockes in these masking deuices? Is Inuention so poore shee must needes euer dwell amongst Rocks? But it may worthily haue chaunc'd (being so often <pb xml:id="ep000338-012-a"/>presented) that their vaine Custome is now become the necessarie hand of heauen, transforming into Rocks, some stonie hearted Ladies, courted in former masks; for whose loues, some of their repulst seruants haue perisht: or perhaps some of my flintie-hearted Vsurers haue beene heere metamorphosed; betwixt whom and Ladies, there is resemblance enough: Ladies vsing to take interest, besides their principall, as much as Vsurers. See, it is so; and now is the time of restoring them to their naturall shapes: It moues, opens, excellent! This metamorphosis I intend to over-heare. </p>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-012-b"/>
        <stage xml:id="ep000338-e100690">A ROCK, MOOVING and breaking with a cracke about Capriccio, he enters with a payre of Bellows on his head, a spur in one hand, and a peece of golde Ore in the other, &amp;c. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000338-e100700">He speakes, vt sequitur. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000338-capriccio" xml:id="ep000338-e100710">
          <speaker>CAPRICCIO. </speaker>
          <p>HOw hard this world is to a man of wit? hee must eate through manie Rockes for his food, or fast; a restles and tormenting stone, his wit is to him: the very stone of Sisyphus in hell; nay, the Philosophers stone, makes not a man more wretched: A man must be a second Proteus, and turne himselfe into all shapes (like Vlisses) to winde through the straites of this pinching vale of miserie; I haue turn'd my selfe into a Tailor, a Man, a Gentleman, a Nobleman, a Worthy man; but had neuer the witte to turne my selfe into an Alder-man. There are manie shapes to perish in, but one to liue in, and tha's an Aldermans: <pb xml:id="ep000338-013-a"/>Tis not for a man of wit to take any rich Figure vpon him: your bould, proud, ignorant, that's braue and clinkant, that findes crownes put into his shooes euery morning by the Fayries and will neuer tell; whose Wit is humor, whose Iudgement is fashion, whose Pride is emptinesse, Birth his full man, that is in all things something, in Sum totall, nothing. He shall liue in the land of Spruce, milke and hony flowing into his mouth sleeping. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e100730">
          <speaker>PLVTVS. </speaker>
          <p>This is no transformation, but an intrusion into my golden mines: I will heare him-further. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-capriccio" xml:id="ep000338-e100750">
          <speaker>CAPRIC. </speaker>
          <p>This breach of Rockes I haue made, in needy pursuite of the blind Deity, Riches: who is myraculously ariued here. For (according to our rare men of wit) heauen standing, and earth mouing, her motion (being circular) hath brought one of the most remote <pb xml:id="ep000338-013-b"/>parts of the world, to touch at this all-exceeding Iland: which a man of wit would imagine must needs moue circularly with the rest of the world, and so euer maintaine an equal distance. But, Poets (our chiefe men of wit) answere that point directly; most ingeniously affirming: That this Ile is (for the excellency of it) diuided from the world (diuisus ab orbe Britannus) and that though the whole World besides moues; yet this Ile stands fixt on her owne feete, and defies the Worlds mutability, which this rare accident of the arriuall of Riches, in one of his furthest-off-scituate dominions, most demonstratiuely proues. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e100770">
          <speaker>PLVTVS. </speaker>
          <p>This is a man of wit indeede, and knows of all our arriuals. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-capriccio" xml:id="ep000338-e100790">
          <speaker>CAPRIC. </speaker>
          <p>With this dull Deity Riches, a rich Iland lying in the South-sea, called Poeana, (of the Poeans (or songs) sung to the Sun, whom they <pb xml:id="ep000338-014-a"/>there adore (being for strength and riches, called the Nauill of that South-sea) is by earths round motion mou'd neere this Brittan Shore. In which Island (beeing yet in command of the Virginian continent.) A troupe of the noblest Virginians inhabiting; attended hether the God of Riches, all triumphantly shyning in a Mine of gould. For hearing of the most royal solemnity, of these sacred Nuptialls; they crost the Ocean in their honor, and are here arriu'd. A poore snatch at some of the goulden Ore, that the feete of riches haue turnd vp as he trod here, my poore hand hath purchast; and hope the Remainder of a greater worke, wilbe shortly extant. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e100810">
          <speaker>PLVT. </speaker>
          <p>You Sir, that are miching about my goulden Mines here. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-capriccio" xml:id="ep000338-e100830">
          <speaker>CAPR. </speaker>
          <p>What, can you see Sir? you haue heretofore beene presented blinde: like your Mother <pb xml:id="ep000338-014-b"/>Fortune; and your Brother Loue. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e100850">
          <speaker>PLVT. </speaker>
          <p>But now Sir, you see I see. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-capriccio" xml:id="ep000338-e100870">
          <speaker>CAPR. </speaker>
          <p>By what good meanes, I beseech you Sir. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e100890">
          <speaker>PLVT. </speaker>
          <p>That meanes, I may vouchsafe you hereafter; meane space, what are you? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-capriccio" xml:id="ep000338-e100910">
          <speaker>CAPR. </speaker>
          <p>I am Sir a kinde of Man; A Man of wit: with whom your worship has nothing to do I thinke. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e100930">
          <speaker>PLVT. </speaker>
          <p>No Sir, nor will haue any thing to doe with him: A Man of wit? whats that? A Begger. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-capriccio" xml:id="ep000338-e100950">
          <speaker>CAPR. </speaker>
          <p>And yet no Diuell Sir. </p>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-015-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e100970">
          <speaker>PLV. </speaker>
          <p>As I am, you meane. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-capriccio" xml:id="ep000338-e100990">
          <speaker>CAPR. </speaker>
          <p>Indeede sir your Kingdome is vnder the Earth. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e101010">
          <speaker>PLVT. </speaker>
          <p>That's true; for Riches is the Atlas that holdes it vp, it would sinke else. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-capriccio" xml:id="ep000338-e101030">
          <speaker>CAPR. </speaker>
          <p>Tis rather a wonder, it sinks not with you Sir, y'are so sinfully, and damnably heauy. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e101050">
          <speaker>PLVT. </speaker>
          <p>Sinfull? and damnable? what a Puritane? These Bellowes you weare on your head, shew with what matter your braine is pufft vp Sir: A Religion-forger I see you are, and presume of inspiration from these Bellowes; with which yee study to blow vp the setled gouernments of kingdomes. </p>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-015-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000338-capriccio" xml:id="ep000338-e101070">
          <speaker>CAPR. </speaker>
          <p>Your worship knockes at a wrong dore Sir, I dwell farre from the person you speak of. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e101090">
          <speaker>PLVT. </speaker>
          <p>What may you be then, beeing a man of wit? a Buffon, a Iester. Before I would take vpon mee the title of a man of wit, and bee baffl'd by euery man of wisedome for a Buffon; I would turne Banckrout, or let vp a Tobacco shop, change clokes with an Alchemist, or serue an Vsurer, bee a watering pot for euery Groome; stand the push of euery rascall wit; enter lifts of iests with trencher-fooles, and bee foold downe by them, or (which is worse) put them downe in fooling: are these the qualities a man of wit should run proud of? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-capriccio" xml:id="ep000338-e101110">
          <speaker>CAPR. </speaker>
          <p>Your worship I see has obtaind wit, with sight, which I hope yet my poor wit wil well be able to answer; for touching my iesting, I <pb xml:id="ep000338-016-a"/>haue heard of some Courtiers, that haue run themselues out of their states with Iusting; and why may not I then raise my selfe in the State with iesting? An honest Shoomaker, (in in a liberall Kings time) was knighted for making a cleane boote, and is it impossible, that I for breaking a cleane Iest, should bee aduaunct in Court, or Counsaile? or at least, serued out for an Ambassador to a dull Climate? Iests, and Merriments are but wild weedes in a rank soile, which being well manured, yield the wholesom crop of wisdome and discretion at time ath' yeare. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e101130">
          <speaker>PLV. </speaker>
          <p>Nay, nay, I commend thy iudgement for cutting thy cote so iust to the bredth of thy shoulders; he that cannot be a courser in the field, let him learne to play the Iack-an-Apes in the Chamber, hee that cannot personate the wise-man well amongst wisards, let him learne to play the foole well amongst dizzards. </p>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-016-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000338-capriccio" xml:id="ep000338-e101150">
          <speaker>CAPR. </speaker>
          <p>Tis passing miraculous, that your dul and blind worship should so sodainly turne both sightfull, and witfull. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e101170">
          <speaker>PLVT. </speaker>
          <p>The Riddle of that myracle, I may chance dissolue to you in sequell; meane time, what name sustain'st thou? and what toies are these thou bear'st so phantastically about thee? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-capriccio" xml:id="ep000338-e101190">
          <speaker>CAPR. </speaker>
          <p>These, toies Sir, are the Ensignes that discouer my name and qualitie: my name being Capriccio, and I weare these Bellowes on my head, to shew I can pusse vp with glory all those that affect mee: and besides, beare this spurre, to shew I can spur gall, euen the best that contemne me. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e101210">
          <speaker>PLVT. </speaker>
          <p>A dangerous fellowe, But what makest thou (poore man of wit) at these pompous Nuptials; </p>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-017-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000338-capriccio" xml:id="ep000338-e101230">
          <speaker>CAPRIC. </speaker>
          <p>Sir, I come hether with a charge; To doe these Nuptialls, I hope, very acceptable seruice; And my charge is; A company of accomplisht Trauailers; that are excellent at Antemaskes; and will tender a tast of their quallity, if your worship please. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e101250">
          <speaker>PLVT. </speaker>
          <p>Excellent well pleasd; of what vertue are they besides. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-capriccio" xml:id="ep000338-e101270">
          <speaker>CAPR. </speaker>
          <p>Passing graue Sir, yet exceeding acute: witty, yet not ridiculous; neuer laugh at their owne iests: laborious yet not base, hauing cut out the skirts of the whole world, in amorous quest of your gould and siluer. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e101290">
          <speaker>PLVT. </speaker>
          <p>They shal haue enough; cal them: I beseech thee call them: how farre hence abide they? </p>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-017-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000338-capriccio" xml:id="ep000338-e101310">
          <speaker>CAPR. </speaker>
          <p>Sir (being by another eminent qualitie the admired souldiers of the world) in contempt of softnes, and delicacie, they lie on the naturally hard boords of that naked tree; and will your worship assure them rewards fit for persons of their freight. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e101330">
          <speaker>PLVT. </speaker>
          <p>Dost thou doubt my reward beeing pleased? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-capriccio" xml:id="ep000338-e101350">
          <speaker>CAPR. </speaker>
          <p>I know Sir, a man may sooner win your reward, for pleasing you, then deseruing you. But you great wise persons, haue a fetch of State; to employ with countenance, and encouragement, but reward with answer and disgrace, saue your purposes, and lose your honours. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e101370">
          <speaker>PLVT. </speaker>
          <p>To assure thee of reward, I will now satisfie <pb xml:id="ep000338-018-a"/>thee touching the miraculous cause, both of my sight and wit, and which consequently moues mee to humanity, and bounty; And all is, onely this; my late being in loue, with the louely Goddesse Honor. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-capriccio" xml:id="ep000338-e101390">
          <speaker>CAPRIC. </speaker>
          <p>If your Worshipp loue Honor, indeed, Sir you must needes be bountifull. But where is the rare Goddesse you speake of to be seene? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e101410">
          <speaker>PLVTVS. </speaker>
          <p>In that Rich Temple, where Fortune fixt those her goulden wings, thou seest; And that rowling stone she vs'd to tread vpon, for signe shee would neuer for-sake this Kingdome; There is ador'd, the worthy Goddesse Honor. The swetnesse of whose voice, when I first heard her perswasions, both to my self, and the Virginian Princes arriu'd here, to doe honor and homage, to these heauenly Nuptialls, so most powerfully enamour'd mee, that the fire of my loue flew vp to the sight <pb xml:id="ep000338-018-b"/>of mine eyes: that haue lighted within mee a whole firmament of Bounty, which may semingly assure the, thy reward is certaine: &amp; therefore call thy accomplisht company to their Antemaske. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-capriccio" xml:id="ep000338-e101430">
          <speaker>CAPRIC. </speaker>
          <p>See Sir, The time, set for their apperance, being expir'd; they appeere to their seruice of them-selues. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000338-e101450">Enter the Baboones after whose dance, being Anticke, and delightful, they returned to their Tree, when Plutus spake to Capriccius. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e101460">
          <speaker>PLVTVS. </speaker>
          <p>Gramercy now Capriccio, take thy men of complement, and trauaile with them to other marriages. My Riches to thy Wit; they will get something some-where. </p>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-019-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000338-capriccio" xml:id="ep000338-e101480">
          <speaker>CAPR. </speaker>
          <p>Whats this? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e101500">
          <speaker>PLVT. </speaker>
          <p>A straine of Wit beyond a Man of Wit. I haue imployd you, and the grace of that, is reward enough; hence; packe, with your complemental Fardle: The sight of an attendant for reward, is abominable in the eyes of a turne-seru'd Politician, and I feare, will strike me blinde againe. I can not abide these bellowes of thy head, they and thy men of wit haue melted my Mines with them, and consum'd me, yet take thy life and be gone. Neptune let thy predecessor, Vlysses, liue after all his slaine companions, but to make him die more miserably liuing; gaue him vp to ship wracks, enchantments; men of wit are but enchanted, there is no such thing as wit in this world. So, take a tree, inure thy souldiers to hardnes, tis honorable, though not clinkant. </p>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-019-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000338-capriccio" xml:id="ep000338-e101520">
          <speaker>CAPR. </speaker>
          <p>Can this be possible? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e101540">
          <speaker>PLVT. </speaker>
          <p>Alas! poore man of wit, how want of reward daunts thy vertue? But because I must send none away discontented, from these all-pleasing Nuptials; take this wedge of golde, and wedge thy selfe into the world with it, renouncing that loose wit of thine, t'will spoile thy complexion. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-capriccio" xml:id="ep000338-e101560">
          <speaker>CAPR. </speaker>
          <p>Honor, and all Argus eyes, to Earths all-commaunding Riches. Pluto etiam cedit Iupiter </p>
          <stage xml:id="ep000338-e101580">Exit Capr. </stage>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-020-a"/>
        <stage xml:id="ep000338-e101590">After this lowe Induction, by these succeeding degrees, the chiefe Maskers were aduanc't to their discouerie </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e101600">
          <speaker>PLVTVS. </speaker>
          <l>These humble obiects can no high eyes drawe, <ref target="A18416-e101620-b"/>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A18416-e101620-a" place="margin">Plutus, cals to Eunomia. </note>
          </l>
          <l>Eunomia? (or the sacred power of Lawe) </l>
          <l>Daughter of Ioue, and Goddesse Honors Priest; </l>
          <l>Appeare to Plutus, and his loue assist. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-eun" xml:id="ep000338-e101660">
          <speaker>EVN. </speaker>
          <l>What would the god of Riches? <ref target="A18416-e101680-b"/>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A18416-e101680-a" place="margin">Eunomia in the Temple gates. </note>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e101690">
          <speaker>PLVT. </speaker>
          <l>Ioine with Honor: </l>
          <l>In purpos'd grace of these great Nuptials; </l>
          <l>And since to Honor none should dare accesse, </l>
          <l>But helpt by vertues hand (thy selfe, chaste Loue </l>
          <l>Being Vertues Rule, and her directfull light) </l>
          <l>Help me to th'honor of her speech and sight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-eun" xml:id="ep000338-e101760">
          <speaker>EVN. </speaker>
          <l>Thy will shal straight be honour'd; all that seek </l>
          <l>Accesse to Honor, by cleer virtues beame, </l>
          <l>Her grace preuents their pains, and comes to them. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-020-b"/>
        <stage xml:id="ep000338-e101800">Loud Musick, and Honor appears, descending with her Herrald Phemis, and Eunomia (her Priest) before her. The Musique ceasing Plutus spake. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e101810">
          <speaker>PLVT. </speaker>
          <l>Crowne of all merit, Goddess, and my Loue; </l>
          <l>Tis now high time, that th'end for which we come </l>
          <l>Should be endeuor'd in our vtmost right, </l>
          <l>Done to the sweetnes of this Nuptiall night. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-honour" xml:id="ep000338-e101860">
          <speaker>HON. </speaker>
          <l>Plutus? The Princes of the Virgine land, </l>
          <l>Whom I made crosse the Britan Ocean </l>
          <l>To this most famed Ile, of all the world, </l>
          <l>To do due homage to the sacred Nuptials </l>
          <l>Of Lawe, and Vertue, celebrated here, </l>
          <l>By this Howre of the holy Eeuen I know, </l>
          <l>Are ready to performe the rites they owe </l>
          <l>To setting Phoebus; which (for greater State </l>
          <l>To their apparance) their first act aduances. </l>
          <l>And with songs Vshers their succeeding dances, </l>
          <l>Herrald! giue summons to the Virgine Knights, </l>
          <l>No longer to delay their purpos'd Rites. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-herald" xml:id="ep000338-e101990">
          <speaker>HER. </speaker>
          <l>Knights of the Virgine Land, whom bewties lights </l>
          <l>Would glorifie with their inflaming sights; </l>
          <l>Keep now obscur'd no more your faire intent, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000338-021-a"/>
          <l>To adde your Beames to this nights ornament, </l>
          <l>The golden-winged Howre strikes now a Plaine, </l>
          <l>And calls out all the pompe ye entertaine; </l>
          <l>The Princely Bride-groome, and the Brides bright eyes, </l>
          <l>Sparkle with grace to your discoueries. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000338-e102080">At these words, the Phoebades (or Priests of the Sunne) appear'd first with sixe Lutes, and sixe voices, and sung to the opening of the Mine and Maskers discouery, this sul Song. </stage>
        <floatingText>
          <body>
            <div type="song" xml:id="ep000338-e102110">
              <head>The first Song. </head>
              <l>OPe Earth thy wombe of golde, </l>
              <l>Shew Heauen thy cope of starres. </l>
              <l>All glad Aspects vnfolde, </l>
              <l>Shine out, and cleere our Cares: </l>
              <l>Kisse Heauen and Earth, and so combine </l>
              <l>In all mixt ioy our Nuptiall Twine. </l>
            </div>
          </body>
        </floatingText>
        <stage xml:id="ep000338-e102180">This Song ended, a Mount opened, and spred like a Skie, in which appear'd a Sunne setting; beneath which, sate the twelue Maskers, in a Mine of golde; twelue Torch-bearers holding their torches before them, after which Honor, &amp;c. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000338-honour" xml:id="ep000338-e102190">
          <speaker>HON. </speaker>
          <l>Se now the setting Sun, casts vp his bank, </l>
          <l>And showes his bright head at his Seas repaire, </l>
          <l>For signe that all daies future shall be faire. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-021-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e102230">
          <speaker>PLVT. </speaker>
          <l>May he that rules the nightes &amp; dayes confirme it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-honour" xml:id="ep000338-e102250">
          <speaker>HON. </speaker>
          <l>Behold the Sunnes faire Preists the Phaebades, </l>
          <l>Their euening seruice in an Hymne addresse </l>
          <l>To Phoebus setting; which we now shall heare, </l>
          <l>And see the formes of their deuotions there. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000338-e102300">The Phoehades sing the first Stance of the second song, vt sequitur. </stage>
        <lg>
          <head>One alone 1. </head>
          <l>Descend (faire Sun) and sweetly rest, </l>
          <l>In Tethis Cristal armes, thy toyle, </l>
          <l>Fall burning on her Marble brest, </l>
          <l>And make with Loue her billowes boyle. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <head>Another alone. 2. </head>
          <l>Blow blow, sweet windes, O blow away, </l>
          <l>Al vapours from the fined ayre: </l>
          <l>That to this golden head no Ray, </l>
          <l>May languish with the least empaire. </l>
        </lg>
        <sp who="#ep000338-chorus" xml:id="ep000338-e102410">
          <speaker>CHO. </speaker>
          <l>Dance Tethis, and thy loues red beames, </l>
          <l>Embrace with Ioy he now discends: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000338-022-a"/>
          <l>Burnes burnes with loue to drinke thy streames, </l>
          <l>and on him endles youth attends. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000338-e102460">After this Stance, Honor &amp;c. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000338-honour" xml:id="ep000338-e102470">
          <speaker>HON. </speaker>
          <l>This superstitious Hymne, sung to the Sunne, </l>
          <l>Let vs encounter with fit duties done </l>
          <l>To our cleere Phoebus; whose true piety, </l>
          <l>Enioyes from heaven an earthly deity. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000338-e102520">Other Musique, and voyces; and this second Stance was sung, directing their obseruance to the King. </stage>
        <lg>
          <head>One alone 1. </head>
          <l>Rise, rise O Phoebus, euer rise, </l>
          <l>descend not to th'inconstant streame, </l>
          <l>But grace with endles light, our skyes, </l>
          <l>to thee that Sun is but a beame. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <head>Another 2. </head>
          <l>Dance Ladies in our Sunnes bright rayes, </l>
          <l>in which the Bride and Bridegroome shine: </l>
          <l>Cleere sable night with your eyes dayes, </l>
          <l>and set firme lights on Hymens shrine. </l>
        </lg>
        <sp who="#ep000338-chorus" xml:id="ep000338-e102630">
          <speaker>CHO. </speaker>
          <l>O may our Sun not set before, </l>
          <l>he sees his endles seed arise: </l>
          <l>And deck his triple crowned shore, </l>
          <l>with springs of humane Deities. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000338-e102680">
          <pb xml:id="ep000338-022-b"/>This ended the Phoebades sung the third Stance. </stage>
        <lg n="1">
          <l>1. Set Set (great Sun) our rising loue </l>
          <l>shall euer celebrate thy grace: </l>
          <l>Whom entring the high court of Ioue, </l>
          <l>each God greetes rising from his place. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg n="2">
          <l>2. When thow thy siluer bow dost bend, </l>
          <l>all start aside and dread thy draughtes: </l>
          <l>How can we thee enough commend, </l>
          <l>commanding all worlds with the shafts? </l>
        </lg>
        <sp who="#ep000338-chorus" xml:id="ep000338-e102790">
          <speaker>CHO. </speaker>
          <l>Blest was thy mother bearing thee, </l>
          <l>and Phoebe that delights in darts: </l>
          <l>Thou artful Songes dost set; and shee </l>
          <l>winds horns, loues hounds, &amp; high pallmd harts </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000338-e102840">After this Honor. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000338-honour" xml:id="ep000338-e102850">
          <speaker>HON. </speaker>
          <l>Againe our Musique and conclude this Song, </l>
          <l>To him, to whom all Phoebus beames belong: </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000338-e102880">The other voyces sung to other Musike the third stance. </stage>
        <lg n="1">
          <l>1 Rise stil (cleere Sun) and neuer set, </l>
          <l>but be to Earth her only light: </l>
          <l>All other Kings in thy beames met, </l>
          <l>are cloudes and darke effects of night. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg n="2">
          <pb xml:id="ep000338-023-a"/>
          <head>2. </head>
          <l>As when the Rosie Morne doth rise, </l>
          <l>Like Mists, all giue thy wisedome waie; </l>
          <l>A learned King, is, as in skies, </l>
          <l>To poore dimme stars, the flaming day. </l>
        </lg>
        <sp who="#ep000338-chorus" xml:id="ep000338-e102990">
          <speaker>CHO. </speaker>
          <l>Blest was thy Mother, bearing Thee, </l>
          <l>Thee only Relick of her Race, </l>
          <l>Made by thy vertues beames a Tree, </l>
          <l>Whose armes shall all the Earth embrace. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000338-e103040">This done Eunomia spake to the Maskers set yet aboue. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000338-eun" xml:id="ep000338-e103050">
          <speaker>EVN. </speaker>
          <l>Virginian Princes, ye must now renounce </l>
          <l>Your superstitious worship of these Sunnes, </l>
          <l>Subiect to cloudy darknings and descents, </l>
          <l>And of your sweet deuotions, turne the euents </l>
          <l>To this our Britan Phoebus, whose bright skie </l>
          <l>(Enlightned with a Christian Piety) </l>
          <l>Is neuer subiect to black Errors night, </l>
          <l>And hath already offer'd heauens true light, </l>
          <l>To your darke Region, which acknowledge now; </l>
          <l>Descend, and to him all your homage vow. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000338-e103160">
            <pb xml:id="ep000338-023-b"/>With this the Torch-bearers descended, and performed another Antemaske, dancing with Torches lighted at both ends; which done, the Maskers descended, and fell into their dances, two of which being past, and others with the Ladies. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000338-e103170">Honor spake. </stage>
          <l>Musiquely our voyces, now tune sweet and hie, </l>
          <l>And singe the Nuptiall Hymn of Loue, <ref target="A18416-e103200-b"/>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A18416-e103200-a" place="margin">The Bride and Bride groome were figured in Loue and Beauty. </note>and Beauty. </l>
          <l>Twinns, as of one age, so to one desire </l>
          <l>May both their bloods giue, an vnparted fire. </l>
          <l>And as those twinns that Fame giues all her prise, </l>
          <l>Combind their lifes power in such Symphathies; <ref target="A18416-e103250-b"/>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A18416-e103250-a" place="margin">Twinns of which Hippocrates speakes. </note>
          </l>
          <l>That one being merry; mirth the other grac't: </l>
          <l>If one felt sorrow, th' other griefe embrac't. </l>
          <l>If one were healthfull; Health the other pleasd: </l>
          <l>If one were sicke: the other was diseasd; </l>
          <l>And all waies ioynd in such a constant troth </l>
          <l>That one like cause had like effect in both, </l>
          <l>So may these Nuptiall Twynnes, <ref target="A18416-e103330-b"/>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A18416-e103330-a" place="margin">Called Twynns being both of an Age. </note>their whole liues store, </l>
          <l>Spend in such euen parts, neuer grieuing more, </l>
          <l>Then may the more set off their ioyes diuine; </l>
          <l>As after clouds, the Sunne, doth clerest shine. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-024-a"/>
        <stage xml:id="ep000338-e103370">This sayd, this Song of Loue, and Bewty was sung; single. </stage>
        <l>Bright Panthaea borne to Pan, </l>
        <l>Of the Noblest Race of Man, </l>
        <l>Her white hand to Eros giuing, </l>
        <l>With a kisse, ioin'd Heauen to Earth </l>
        <l>And begot so faire a birth, </l>
        <l>As yet neuer grac't the liuing. </l>
        <sp who="#ep000338-chorus" xml:id="ep000338-e103440">
          <speaker>CHO. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>A Twinne that all worlds did adorne, </l>
            <l>For so were Loue and Bewty borne. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg n="1">
            <head>2. </head>
            <l>Both so lou'd, they did contend </l>
            <l>Which the other should transcend, </l>
            <l>Doing either, grace, and kindnes; </l>
            <l>Loue from Bewty did remoue, </l>
            <l>Lightnes call'd her staine in loue, </l>
            <l>Bewtie took from Loue his blindness. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-024-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000338-chorus" xml:id="ep000338-e103550">
          <speaker>CHO. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Loue sparks made flames in Bewties skie, </l>
            <l>And Bewtie blew vp Loue as hie. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg n="2">
            <head>3 </head>
            <l>Virtue then commixt her fire; </l>
            <l>To which Bountie did aspire, </l>
            <l>Innocence a Crowne conferring; </l>
            <l>Mine, and Thine, were then vnusde, </l>
            <l>All things common: Nought abusde, </l>
            <l>Freely earth her frutage bearing. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000338-chorus" xml:id="ep000338-e103660">
          <speaker>CHO. </speaker>
          <l>Nought then was car'd for, that could fade, </l>
          <l>And thus the golden world was made. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000338-e103690">This sung, the Maskers danc't againe with the Ladies, after which Honor. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000338-honour" xml:id="ep000338-e103700">
          <speaker>HON. </speaker>
          <l>Now may the blessings of the golden age, </l>
          <l>Swimme in these Nuptials, euen to holy rage, </l>
          <l>A Hymn to Sleep prefer, and all the ioyes </l>
          <l>That in his Empire are of dearest choice, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000338-025-a"/>
          <l>Betwixt his golden slumbers euer flow, </l>
          <l>In these; And Theirs, in Springs as endless growe. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000338-e103770">This sayd, the last Song was sung full. </stage>
        <floatingText>
          <body>
            <div type="song" xml:id="ep000338-e103800">
              <head>The last Song. </head>
              <l>Now sleepe, binde fast, the flood of Ayre, </l>
              <l>strike all things dumb and deafe, </l>
              <l>And, to disturbbe our Nuptiall paire, </l>
              <l>Let stir no Aspen leafe. </l>
              <l>Send flocks of golden Dreames </l>
              <l>That all true ioyes presage, </l>
              <l>Bring, in thy oyly streames, </l>
              <l>The milke and hony Age. </l>
              <l>Now close the world-round sphere of blisse, </l>
              <l>And fill it with a heauenly kisse. </l>
            </div>
          </body>
        </floatingText>
        <stage xml:id="ep000338-e103910">After this Plutus to the Maskers. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000338-plutus" xml:id="ep000338-e103920">
          <speaker>PLVT. </speaker>
          <l>Come Virgine Knights, the homage ye haue done, </l>
          <l>To Loue and Bewty, and our Britan Sun, </l>
          <l>Kinde Honor, will requite with holy feasts </l>
          <l>In her faire Temple; and her loued Guests, </l>
          <l>Giues mee the grace t'inuite, when she and I </l>
          <l>(Honor and Riches) will eternally </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000338-025-b"/>
          <l>A league in fauour of this night combine, </l>
          <l>In which Loues second hallowed Tapers shine; </l>
          <l>Whose Ioies, may Heauen &amp; Earth as highly please </l>
          <l>As those two nights that got great Hercules. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000338-e104030">The speech ended; they concluded with a dance, that brought them off; Plutus, with Honor and the rest conducting them vp to the Temple of Honor. </stage>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
      <div type="hymn" xml:id="ep000338-e104050">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000338-026-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-026-b"/>
        <head>A Hymne to Hymen for the most timefitted Nuptialls of our thrice gracious Princesse Elizabeth &amp;c. </head>
        <l>SInge, Singe a Rapture to all Nuptial eares, </l>
        <l>Bright Hymens torches, drunke vp Parcaes tears: </l>
        <l>Sweete Hymen; Hymen, Mightiest of Gods, </l>
        <l>Attoning of all-taming blood the odds; </l>
        <l>Two into One, contracting; One to Two </l>
        <l>Dilating, which no other God can doe. </l>
        <l>Mak'st sure, with change, and lett'st the married try, </l>
        <l>Of Man and woman, the Variety. </l>
        <l>And as a flower, halfe scorcht with daies long heate Simil. </l>
        <l>Thirsts for refreshing, with Nights cooling sweate, </l>
        <l>The wings of Zephire, fanning still her face, </l>
        <l>No chere can ad to her heart-thirsty grace; </l>
        <l>Yet weares she gainst those fires that make her fade, </l>
        <l>Her thicke hayrs proofe, al hyd, in Midnights shade; </l>
        <l>Her Helth, is all in dews; Hope, all in showres, </l>
        <l>Whose want bewailde, she pines in all her powres: </l>
        <l>So Loue-scorch't Virgines, nourish quenchles fires; </l>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-027-a"/>
        <l>The Fathers cares; the Mothers kind desires. </l>
        <l>Their Gould, and Garments, of the newest guise, </l>
        <l>Can nothing comfort their scorcht Phantasies, </l>
        <l>But, taken rauish't vp, in Hymens armes, </l>
        <l>His Circkle holds, for all their anguish, charms: </l>
        <l>Then, <ref target="A18416-e104290-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A18416-e104290-a" place="margin">Simil. ad eandem explicat. </note>as a glad Graft, in the spring Sunne shines, </l>
        <l>That all the helps, of Earth, &amp; Heauen combines </l>
        <l>In Her sweet grouth: Puts in the Morning on </l>
        <l>Her cherefull ayres; the Sunnes rich fires, at Noone; </l>
        <l>At Euen the sweete deaws, and at Night with starrs, </l>
        <l>In all their vertuous influences shares; </l>
        <l>So, in the Bridegroomes sweet embrace; the Bride, </l>
        <l>All varied Ioies tasts, in their naked pride: </l>
        <l>To which the richest weedes: are weedes, to flowres; </l>
        <l>Come Hymen then; com close these Nuptial howres </l>
        <l>With all yeares comforts. Come; each virgin keepes </l>
        <l>Her odorous kisses for thee; Goulden sleepes </l>
        <l>Will, in their humors, neuer steepe an eie, </l>
        <l>Till thou inuit'st them with thy Harmony. </l>
        <l>Why staiest thou? see each Virgin doth prepare </l>
        <l>Embraces for thee; Her white brests laies bare </l>
        <l>To tempt thy soft hand; let's such glances flie </l>
        <l>As make starres shoote, to imitate her eye. </l>
        <l>Puts Arts attires on, that put Natures doune: </l>
        <l>Singes, Dances, sets on euery foote a Crowne, </l>
        <l>Sighes, in her songs, and dances; kisseth Ayre </l>
        <l>Till Rites, and words past, thou in deedes repaire; </l>
        <l>The whole court Io sings: Io the Ayre: </l>
        <l>Io, the flouds, and fields: Io, most faire, </l>
        <l>Most sweet, most happy Hymen; Come: away; </l>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-027-b"/>
        <l>With all thy Comforts come; old Matrons pray, </l>
        <l>With young Maides Languors; Birds bill, build, and breed </l>
        <l>To teach thee thy kinde, euery flowre and weed </l>
        <l>Looks vp to gratulate thy long'd for fruites; </l>
        <l>Thrice giuen, are free, and timely-granted suites: </l>
        <l>There is a seed by thee now to be sowne, </l>
        <l>In whose fruit Earth, shall see her glories show'n, </l>
        <l>At all parts perfect; and must therfore loose </l>
        <l>No minutes time; from times vse all fruite flowes; </l>
        <l>And as the tender Hyacinth, that growes </l>
        <l>Where Phoebus <ref target="A18416-e104650-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A18416-e104650-a" place="margin">Simil. </note>most his golden beames bestowes, </l>
        <l>Is propt with care; is water'd euery howre; </l>
        <l>The sweet windes adding their encreasing powre, </l>
        <l>The scattered drops of Nights refreshing dew, </l>
        <l>Hasting the full grace, of his glorious hew, </l>
        <l>Which once disclosing, must be gatherd straight, </l>
        <l>Or hew, and Odor both, will lose their height; </l>
        <l>So, of a Virgine, high, and richly kept, </l>
        <l>The grace and sweetnes full growne must be reap't, </l>
        <l>Or, forth her spirits fly, in empty Ayre; </l>
        <l>The sooner fading; the more sweete and faire. </l>
        <l>Gentle, O Gentle Hymen, be not then </l>
        <l>Cruell, That kindest arts to Maids, and Men; </l>
        <l>These two, One Twynn are; and their mutuall blisse, </l>
        <l>Not in thy beames, but in thy Bosome is. </l>
        <l>Nor can their hands fast, their harts ioyes make sweet; </l>
        <l>Their harts, in brests are; and their Brests must meete. </l>
        <l>Let, there be Peace, yet Murmur: and that noise, </l>
        <l>Beget of peace, the Nuptiall battailes ioyes. </l>
        <l>Let Peace grow cruell, and take wrake of all, </l>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-028-a"/>
        <l>The warrs delay brought thy full Festiuall. </l>
        <l>Harke, harke, O now the sweete Twyn murmur sounds; </l>
        <l>Hymen is come, and all his heate abounds; </l>
        <l>Shut all Dores; None, but Hymens lights aduance. </l>
        <l>No sound styr; let, dumb Ioy, enioy a trance. </l>
        <l>Sing, sing a Rapture to all Nuptiall eares, </l>
        <l>Bright Hymens Torches drunke vp Parcaes teares. </l>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
        <pb xml:id="ep000338-028-b"/>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="supplied_by_editor">
        <head>Notes, typically marginal, from the original text</head>
        <div corresp="A18416-e100650" xml:id="ep000338-e100650-n">
          <head>Notes for div A18416-e100650</head>
        </div>
        <div corresp="A18416-e104050" xml:id="ep000338-e104050-n">
          <head>Notes for div A18416-e104050</head>
        </div>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
