<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000352" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Cid</title>
        <author>
<!--Corneille, Pierre-->
          <persName>
            <forename>Pierre</forename>
            <surname>Corneille</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A19346.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull n="TCP source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">The Cid a tragicomedy, out of French made English: and acted before their Majesties at court, and on the Cock-pit stage in Drury-lane by the servants to both their Majesties.</title>
                <author>Corneille, Pierre, 1606-1684.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>42 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
                <date>2007 October (TCP phase 1)</date>
                <idno type="marc">99844350</idno>
                <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 5770.</idno>
                <idno type="stc">Greg, II, 525(a).</idno>
                <idno type="vid">9154</idno>
                <idno type="DLPS">A19346</idno>
                <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2240901389</idno>
                <availability>
                  <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
                </availability>
              </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
            <biblFull n="printed source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">The Cid a tragicomedy, out of French made English: and acted before their Majesties at court, and on the Cock-pit stage in Drury-lane by the servants to both their Majesties.</title>
                <title type="alt">Cid. English</title>
                <title type="alt">Le Cid.</title>
                <author>Corneille, Pierre, 1606-1684.</author>
                <author>J. R. fl. 1635-1640,</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[84] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Printed by Iohn Haviland for Thomas Walkly, and are to be sold at his shop at the Flying Horse neare Yorke house,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication_date">1637.</date>
                <date type="creation_date">1637</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>
                  <p>A translation of: Corneille, Pierre. Le Cid.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Translator's dedication signed: Rutter.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Signatures: A-C12 D6.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>With a final imprimatur leaf; the last leaf is blank.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
                </note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <person xml:id="ep000352-elvira">
            <persName>Elvira</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000352-count">
            <persName>Count</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000352-cimena">
            <persName>Cimena</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000352-infanta">
            <persName>Infanta</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000352-leonora">
            <persName>Leonora</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000352-page">
            <persName>Page</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000352-diego">
            <persName>Diego</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000352-roderigo">
            <persName>Roderigo</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000352-arias">
            <persName>Arias</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000352-boy">
            <persName>Boy</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000352-king">
            <persName>King</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000352-sancho">
            <persName>Sancho</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000352-alonso">
            <persName>Alonso</persName>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
      <textClass>
        <classCode scheme="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q192881</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1637">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000352-e100030">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000352-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000352-001-b"/>
        <p>The Cid, A TRAGICOMEDY, out of French made English: And acted before their Majesties at Court, and on the Cock-pit Stage in Drury-lane, by the servants to both their Majesties. </p>
        <p>
          <figure/>
        </p>
        <p>LONDON, Printed by John Haviland for Thomas Walkly, and are to be sold at his shop at the Flying Horse neare Yorke house, 1637. </p>
      </div>
      <div cert="high"
              type="frontispiece"
              xml:id="ep000352-e100080"
              xml:lang="fr">
        <pb xml:id="ep000352-002-a"/>
        <p>
          <figure>
            <p>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENCE. </p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000352-e100120">
        <pb xml:id="ep000352-002-b"/>
        <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, my singular good Lord and Master, EDWARD, Earle of Dorset, Lord Chamberlaine to the Queene, Councellour of Estate to his Majesty, and Knight of the most noble order of the Garter. </head>
        <p>TO give your Lordship a testimony of my readinesse to obey you, I no sooner was commanded by you to translate this Poem than I went about it. And certainly your commands gave life to the worke, which else despaire of performance, or the consideration to whom it must be presented, would ave stifled in its first birth. For how could I hope any thing from mine owne sufficiencie, being little exercised in the French tongue, and <pb xml:id="ep000352-003-a"/>finding such a contumacy in their phrase to our manner of speaking; or how should I not feare such a Judge as your Lordship, who are not onley a perfect understander, but an exact speaker of both languages. So that what we with much labour compasse, is your daily exercise. For if that which Augustus attributed to Vinicius, that he had Solus ingenium in numerato, can snit with any man, it does with your Lordship, whose wit we have so often seene ready told out, and fit for any emanation: and with which you have justly purchased every mans wonder and astonishment. It was therefore aptly and truly said by a noble man of your owne ranke and order, that when you spoke in any businesse you imposed oblivion on what was said before you, and silence on any man that should speake after you. It behooves me then (since I must feare your judgement) to flie to that sweetnesse of your disposition (the temper of your vertues) with which you use to receive the offers that come from a gratefull heart. Un lesse I should presume to thinke that your Lord ship cannot without delight survey the person of D. Roderigo in this play, with whom you life has held some proportion, for like him you have ever preferr'd your honour to your affections, and your King and Countrey to an thing besides: which you did not so much, because <pb xml:id="ep000352-003-b"/>the place you are in requires it, but out of an in-bred affection delivered to you from your Ancestors, who with their happy counsailes have no lesse confirm'd this kingdome than D. Diego is here said by his armes to have supported Castile. In fine, my Lord, I hope you will looke with more content upon this Peece, when you shall reade there some places of my Lords your sonnes translation, from whose attendance, if I have borrowed this time, I must account it upon your Lordships service, from whom I have received all I have, which is the glory to be esteemed, </p>
        <closer>
          <salute>My Lord, </salute>
          <signed>Your honours most faithfull most obedient servant. RUTTER. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="to_the_reader" xml:id="ep000352-e100170">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000352-004-a"/>
        <head>
          <pb xml:id="ep000352-004-b"/>To the Reader. </head>
        <p>THe place of a Prologue let this leafe take up; which would gently advise you to suspend your censure of this translation, till you be skilled in both the languages; for from the ignorant in either I may suffer. Some places in the Originall I have changed, but not many: two Scenes I have left out, as being soliloquies and little pertinent to the businesse: some things I have added, but scarce discernable: where he would give me leave, I have followed close both the sense &amp; words of the Author, but many things are received wit in one tongue which are not in another. The Play it selfe, being a true history, though like a Romance (since this age consists of such Play-seers) I would willingly propose to be imitated of our undertakers in the like kinde, I meane for the conveyance, and (as I may call it) the Oeconomy of it: for what concernes the wit and naturall expressions in it; I know I speak to deafe people, whose <pb xml:id="ep000352-005-a"/>tares have beene furr'd with 'so many Hyperboles, which it the wit in fashion, though the same in <ref target="A19346-e100190-b">* </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A19346-e100190-a" n="*" place="margin">* Sen. Rhet. sua 1. sub finem. </note>Seneca's dayes, were accounted madnesse. But if they knew how dissenting with a right care any affected speech is, they would rather trespasse the other way, and not straine nature beyond what we finde it commonly is. But this is no fit Porch for the Temple of love, Ile shut it up, and open you the pleasant way, into which you had rather enter. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="ep000352-e100200">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000352-005-b"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000352-006-a"/>
        <p>
          <list>
            <head>The names of the Actors. </head>
            <item>D. FERNANDO the first King of Castile. </item>
            <item>D. URRACA the Infanta of Castile. </item>
            <item>D. DIEGO the father of RODERIGO. </item>
            <item>D. GOMES the Count of Gormas, father to CIMENA. </item>
            <item>D. RODERIGO the lover of CIMENA. </item>
            <item>D. SANCHO in love with CIMENA. </item>
            <item>
              <list>
                <head>Courtiers. </head>
                <item>D. ARIAS </item>
                <item>D. ALONSO </item>
              </list>
            </item>
            <item>CIMENA D. ROD. and D. SAN. Mistresse. </item>
            <item>LEONORA Governesse to the Infanta. </item>
            <item>ELVIRA servant to CIMENA. </item>
            <item>A Page. </item>
            <item>Attendants. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>The Scene </p>
        <p>SEVILLE. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="play" xml:id="ep000352-e100410">
        <pb xml:id="ep000352-006-b"/>
        <head>A Tragicomedy. </head>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="ep000352-e100420">
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000352-e100430">
            <head>ACT I. SCENE I. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e100440">COUNT. ELVIRA. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e100450">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>MOngst all the youthfull lovers which adore </l>
              <l>Your daughters beauty, and implore my aid, </l>
              <l>Don Roderigo and Don Sancho strive </l>
              <l>Who shall shew most the fire her beauties rais'd. </l>
              <l>But yet Cimena is indifferent </l>
              <l>To both their loves, and with an equall eye </l>
              <l>Beholds them both, nor does she take away </l>
              <l>Or adde ought to their hopes, but still expects </l>
              <l>A husband from your choice alone design'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e100550">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>She does her duty, both of them deserve her, </l>
              <l>Both sprung from brave and noble families, </l>
              <l>Both young, yet such as in their faces shew </l>
              <l>Th' illustrious vertue of their Ancestors, </l>
              <l>But above all, in Roderigo's face </l>
              <l>There's not a line which speaks not a brave man; </l>
              <l>His family has been fruitfull still in souldiers, </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-007-a"/>
              <l>As if they had beene borne ith' midst of lawrels. </l>
              <l>His fathers valour, in his time, unequall'd, </l>
              <l>(Whil'st his strength lasted) was a prodigie. </l>
              <l>The furrowes in his fore-head seeme to be </l>
              <l>Th' ingravements of his noble actions, </l>
              <l>And Roderigo's person seemes to promise </l>
              <l>The vertues of his father. In conclusion, </l>
              <l>My daughter if she love him shall please me; </l>
              <l>Goe entertaine her with it, but be sure </l>
              <l>You hide m' intentions, and discover hers, </l>
              <l>At my returne wee'le speake of it together, </l>
              <l>Time cals me now to wait upon the Councell, </l>
              <l>Where the King meanes to chuse a Governour </l>
              <l>Unto the Prince his sonne, or rather seat me </l>
              <l>In that high place of honour, for my merits </l>
              <l>Forbid me to expect an opposition. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="ep000352-e100790">
            <head>SCENE II. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e100800">ELVIRA. CIMENA. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e100810">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>HOw welcome newes will this be to our lovers? </l>
              <l>How fortune has provided, that all things </l>
              <l>Should sort to their contentment? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e100850">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>How now Elvira? </l>
              <l>What in conclusion must I hope or feare? </l>
              <l>What must become of me? what sayes my father? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e100890">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>Onely two words, enough to charme your senses, </l>
              <l>You cannot love Roderigo, more than he </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-007-b"/>
              <l>Does value him. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e100930">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Prithee speake truth Elvira, </l>
              <l>Th' excesse of this my happiness does stagger </l>
              <l>My faith in it; may I beleeve thy words? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e100970">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>Nay he went farther, he approves his love, </l>
              <l>And will command you meet with his desires, </l>
              <l>This you will finde 'soone as the Councell rises, </l>
              <l>And that Don Diego meeting time, and place </l>
              <l>Fit for his purpose, shall propose the businesse; </l>
              <l>Feare not but your desires will be contented. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e101040">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>I cannot tell, but yet me thinks my soule </l>
              <l>Does not receive this joy; but all confounded </l>
              <l>Expects what moment will present to me </l>
              <l>A divers face from this my happinesse, </l>
              <l>And crosse my present fortune. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e101100">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>You will finde </l>
              <l>This feare of yours most happily deceiv'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e101130">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Well, let us goe then, and attend the issue. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="ep000352-e101150">
            <head>SCENE III. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e101160">INFANTA. LEONORA. PAGE. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e101170">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>GOe boy, looke out Cimena, and from me </l>
              <l>Tell her, her presence was expected sooner, </l>
              <l>My friendship must complaine of this her sloth. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-008-a"/>
            <sp who="#ep000352-leonora" xml:id="ep000352-e101210">
              <speaker>LEONORA. </speaker>
              <l>I perceive, Madame, that all dayes alike </l>
              <l>You're sad and pensive, and the same desire </l>
              <l>To know how her love goes, still presses you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e101250">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>How should it not? when I my selfe have made her </l>
              <l>Receive the hurt wherewith her soule is wounded, </l>
              <l>She loves Don Roderigo by my meanes, </l>
              <l>And by my meanes he has vanquisht her disdaine, </l>
              <l>Then since to take 'um I have laid the snare, </l>
              <l>To free 'um unto me belongs the care. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-leonora" xml:id="ep000352-e101320">
              <speaker>LEONORA. </speaker>
              <l>And yet i'th midst of all their good successe </l>
              <l>One may perceive in you a kinde of sorrow; </l>
              <l>Why should that love which lifts them up with joy </l>
              <l>Weigh your great heart downe with a heavie sadnesse, </l>
              <l>And th' interest which you have in their love, </l>
              <l>Make you unhappy, when themselves are blest? </l>
              <l>But I'me too forward, and grow indiscreet. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e101400">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>To stifle it increases more my griefe! </l>
              <l>Leonora, thou shalt know it, and now heare </l>
              <l>What a strange conflict I have had within me, </l>
              <l>And when th' hast heard it, pittying my weaknesse, </l>
              <l>Admire my vertue, love is such a Tyrant </l>
              <l>As will spare none, this Gentleman, this lover </l>
              <l>Which I've bestow'd on her, I love my selfe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-leonora" xml:id="ep000352-e101480">
              <speaker>LEONORA. </speaker>
              <l>You Madame? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e101500">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>Lay thy hand upon my heart </l>
              <l>And feele now how it pants at th' hearing of </l>
              <l>The name of its owne Conquerour. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-leonora" xml:id="ep000352-e101540">
              <speaker>LEONORA. </speaker>
              <l>Pardon me, Madam, </l>
              <l>If blaming of your love, I doe forget </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-008-b"/>
              <l>My due respect; is he a match for you, </l>
              <l>A private Gentleman? can you a Princesse </l>
              <l>In a point of such consequence forget </l>
              <l>Whose child you are? what will the King say, think you? </l>
              <l>Doe you remember, Madam, whose you are? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e101620">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>Yes, yes, Leonora, and will rather die </l>
              <l>Than doe a thing unworthy of my birth: </l>
              <l>Though I could tell thee that in noble soules </l>
              <l>Merit alone ought to produce true love, </l>
              <l>And if my passion would flie to excuses, </l>
              <l>Many examples might authorize it, </l>
              <l>Yet I'le not follow that in which my honour </l>
              <l>Must be ingag'd. If I have much of love, </l>
              <l>I have much more of courage, and me thinks </l>
              <l>A noble true disdaine tels me that I, </l>
              <l>The daughter of a King, should deeme all others </l>
              <l>Below my love, unlesse it were a Monarch: </l>
              <l>But when I see my heart is not of force </l>
              <l>To make its owne defence, I give away </l>
              <l>That which I dare not take: 'stead of my selfe </l>
              <l>I put Cimena fast into his fetters, </l>
              <l>And kindle their fire to put out mine owne. </l>
              <l>Be not amaz'd then, if with distraction </l>
              <l>I still expect their marriage; you see </l>
              <l>All my repose onely depends on it, </l>
              <l>If love doe live on hope, it dies with it; </l>
              <l>'Tis a fire, that not nourish'd will goe out, </l>
              <l>And spight of my ill fortune, if Cimena </l>
              <l>Marry Don Roderigo, my long hopes </l>
              <l>Dying, my minde will be at ease; till then </l>
              <l>I'me still in torment; till his day of marriage </l>
              <l>Roderigo is my love, whom though I labour </l>
              <l>To lose, I cannot chuse but grieve to lose him; </l>
              <l>I finde my soule divided in two parts, </l>
              <l>My heart with honour fir'd as well as love: </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-009-a"/>
              <l>This Hymen's fatall, I both wish, and feare it. </l>
              <l>Nor can I hope for any perfect joy, </l>
              <l>Since whether he obtaine his love, or no, </l>
              <l>So many baits my love and honour have, </l>
              <l>In stead of comfort I must finde a grave. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-leonora" xml:id="ep000352-e101980">
              <speaker>LEONORA. </speaker>
              <l>After this, Madam, I have nought to say, </l>
              <l>Unlesse it be to grieve for your misfortunes, </l>
              <l>Before I blam'd you, now I pitty you: </l>
              <l>But since your vertue has made good it selfe, </l>
              <l>So strongly 'gainst the powerfull charmes and force </l>
              <l>Of love and honour, and beat backe th' assault </l>
              <l>Of this, and bait of that, in a short time </l>
              <l>'Twill give you ease of all, in the meane while </l>
              <l>Cast your firm hope on heaven, which has more justice </l>
              <l>Than to let virtue be a sufferer long. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e102090">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>My best of hopes is to cast off all hope. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-page" xml:id="ep000352-e102110">
              <speaker>PAGE. </speaker>
              <l>Madam, Cimena's come, as you commanded. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e102130">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>Goe, entertaine her in the Gallery. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-leonora" xml:id="ep000352-e102150">
              <speaker>LEONORA. </speaker>
              <l>But will you still remaine in these sad fancies? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e102170">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>No, I will 'spight of all my griefe, put on </l>
              <l>A face of gladnesse. Goe, I'le follow you. </l>
              <l>Just heaven, from whence I doe expect my aid, </l>
              <l>Put now at length some period to my evils; </l>
              <l>Assure mine honour with some ease of love, </l>
              <l>I seeke my happinesse in anothers blisse, </l>
              <l>To which give speed good heaven, or more strength </l>
              <l>To my yet feeble soule, which n'ere can be </l>
              <l>(Till Hymen have bound them) at liberty. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="ep000352-e102270">
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-009-b"/>
            <head>SCENE IV. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e102280">COUNT de GORMAS. D. DIEGO. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e102290">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>WEll sir, you have got the day, the Kings high favour </l>
              <l>Has lifted you to that which was my due, </l>
              <l>H' has made you governour to the Prince of Castile. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e102330">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>This honour which he has done my family, </l>
              <l>Shewes he is just, and knowes well how to pay </l>
              <l>With recompence, past services. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e102370">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>Though Kings </l>
              <l>Be great, they are like us, and as much subject </l>
              <l>To be deceiv'd, as we, and this his choice </l>
              <l>Makes us (which are his servants) see, how ill </l>
              <l>He recompences present services. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e102430">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>Pray let's no more of this: perhaps t' advance </l>
              <l>My businesse, favour did as much as merit: </l>
              <l>And happily you had beene the better choice, </l>
              <l>But yet the King thought me more fit for him: </l>
              <l>You may to th' honour which the King has done me </l>
              <l>Adde one more if you please, in joyning both </l>
              <l>Our families by sacred marriage. </l>
              <l>Roderigo loves your daughter, whom h' has made </l>
              <l>The chiefest object of's affections, </l>
              <l>Give your consent, and take him for your sonne. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e102540">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>O Sir, Roderigo must looke higher now, </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-010-a"/>
              <l>The splendor of this honour newly done you </l>
              <l>Ought to put greater thoughts into his heart. </l>
              <l>Looke to your office well; governe the Prince, </l>
              <l>Shew him the way how he may rule a Province, </l>
              <l>Make people every where obey his law, </l>
              <l>Teach him to love the good, to awe the bad, </l>
              <l>Adde to these vertues, those of a Generall, </l>
              <l>Instruct him how to harden his soft body </l>
              <l>With paine and travell, till he leave himselfe </l>
              <l>Without a Rivall in the art of Warre, </l>
              <l>To sit continued dayes and nights on horse-backe, </l>
              <l>To take his rest in's Armes: To force a Rampire, </l>
              <l>And not to owe a victorie but to himselfe, </l>
              <l>Shew him this by example, and remember </l>
              <l>You ought to represent what you would teach. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e102710">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>To instruct him by example, this I'le say </l>
              <l>In spight of envie, let him read my life, </l>
              <l>And by that story learne to tame fierce Nations. </l>
              <l>To set on any place, to range an Army, </l>
              <l>And lay his ground of honour on his actions. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e102770">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>Living examples move more forcibly </l>
              <l>Than books, in which a Prince scarce learnes his duty: </l>
              <l>But what I pray has all your long yeares done </l>
              <l>That one day of my actions has not equall'd? </l>
              <l>If you were valiant once, I still am so, </l>
              <l>This arm's the firme supporter of Castile, </l>
              <l>My sword once drawne has made Granado tremble, </l>
              <l>Arragon quake; without me other lawes </l>
              <l>You must have had, and other Princes serv'd: </l>
              <l>Each day, each instant, to my eternall glory, </l>
              <l>Has pil'd up victory on victory. </l>
              <l>The Prince to set an edge upon his valour, </l>
              <l>Marching by me shall be victorious, </l>
              <l>Farre from your cold instructions, he shall learne </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-010-b"/>
              <l>(Though to my valour they're prefer'd by some) </l>
              <l>In seeing my actions, how to overcome. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e102940">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>In vaine you tell me that I know already, </l>
              <l>I've seene you fight, and under me command. </l>
              <l>When age hath shrunke my sinewes up with cold, </l>
              <l>Your youth and valour have suppli'd my place. </l>
              <l>But not to make so many words of nothing, </l>
              <l>You are what I was once, and yet the King </l>
              <l>'Twixt our deserts has put a difference. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e103020">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>That which was my desert, you have obtain'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e103040">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>He that has got it, sure has best deserv'd it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e103060">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>He that can best discharge it, best deserves it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e103080">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis no good signe though to be put beside it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e103100">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>Like an old Courtier, by much suit you got it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e103120">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>My honourable actions stood for me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e103140">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>Come, come, the King thus honour'd your gray hairs </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e103160">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>He priz'd my valour, when he gave it me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e103180">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>If so, the honour had beene mine, not yours. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e103200">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>He that could not obtain't, did not deserve it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e103220">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>Not I deserve it, meane you? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e103240">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>No, not you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e103260">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>Take that, rash Dotard, for thy impudence. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-011-a"/>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e103280">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>Nay make it up, and after this affront. </l>
              <l>Take my life too. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e103310">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>What dost thou hope to doe thou feeble foole, </l>
              <l>Thy sword is mine, but yet I scorne to take it, </l>
              <l>Goe now and bid the Prince read o're thy life, </l>
              <l>And let him not omit this part of it, </l>
              <l>In which hee'le finde the just revenge I take </l>
              <l>Of this thine insolence, a faire example. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e103380">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>Will you then spare my life? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e103400">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>I'me satisfied; </l>
              <l>Mine eyes cry shame unto mine hands for this. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e103430">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>Then you doe scorne to take it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e103450">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>If I should, </l>
              <l>I did but cut the threed of three dayes lasting. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e103480">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>Rage and despaire! must I needs live thus long, </l>
              <l>To see this, one day of my infamy </l>
              <l>Blast all the Trophies of my former yeares, </l>
              <l>O fatall dignity! which art to me </l>
              <l>No other than a precipice, from whence </l>
              <l>Mine honour headlong fals unto the earth, </l>
              <l>Let him that has disarm'd me take the place </l>
              <l>Of Governour to the Prince, for I that am </l>
              <l>A man dishonour'd, am not fit for it. </l>
              <l>And thou my sword, that hang'st here for a shew, </l>
              <l>The glorious instrument of my actions past, </l>
              <l>But now the idle ornament of my age, </l>
              <l>Goe to his hands that can tell how to use thee, </l>
              <l>Be then my sonnes, who, if he be my owne, </l>
              <l>Cannot but have a sense of my dishonour, </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-011-b"/>
              <l>And though he love Cimena, yet 'tis fit </l>
              <l>His love give place to the more ardent fire </l>
              <l>Of valour, animated by an affront, </l>
              <l>Which, though it fell on me, did yet result </l>
              <l>On him: and see, he's here, Roderigo tell me, </l>
              <l>Hast th' any courage? </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="ep000352-e103700">
            <head>SCENE V. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e103710">RODERIGO. DIEGO. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e103720">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>ANy man but my father </l>
              <l>Should quickly finde I have. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e103750">
              <speaker>DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>Well said, my boy, </l>
              <l>I nowe perceive my bloud runnes in thy veines, </l>
              <l>This noble anger sayes thou art my sonne; </l>
              <l>My youth revives in me from this thy heat. </l>
              <l>Thou shalt revenge me sonne. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e103810">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Of what, or whom? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e103830">
              <speaker>DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>Of an affront so cruell, that our honours </l>
              <l>Suffer together in it. 'Twas, Roderigo, </l>
              <l>A box o'th eare, which on th'insolent giver </l>
              <l>I had reveng'd, but that my feeble age </l>
              <l>Fail'd my strong heart. This sword then, which my arme </l>
              <l>Knew not to weild, take thou, and with it punish </l>
              <l>The arrogant that wrong'd me, and be sure </l>
              <l>Thou kill, or die, for such a staine as this </l>
              <l>Is never washt, but in the offenders bloud. </l>
              <l>But let me tell thee, I doe send thee now </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-012-a"/>
              <l>To combat with a man whom I have seene </l>
              <l>All on a goare, in midst of a fought battell, </l>
              <l>Making himselfe a Rampire of slaine men. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e103970">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Pray Sir his Name, let him be what he will. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e103990">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>To tell thee more then; besides that he is </l>
              <l>The bravest souldier, and the best Commander </l>
              <l>That I have seene; he is— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e104030">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>For heavens sake what? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e104050">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>The father to Cimena. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e104070">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>The? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e104090">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>Reply not, </l>
              <l>I know thy love, but yet remember sonne, </l>
              <l>He that can live contemn'd, doth not deserve </l>
              <l>To breath an houre; thou know'st th' affront was given </l>
              <l>To me, to thee I leave the just revenge; </l>
              <l>The sense of honour, and the fire that springs </l>
              <l>From thence, should put out the lesse heat of love; </l>
              <l>Revenge me, and thy selfe, shew thy selfe worthy </l>
              <l>Of me thy father, now o're-borne with miseries, </l>
              <l>Which whilst I goe to moane, haste thou to punish. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="6" type="scene" xml:id="ep000352-e104200">
            <head>SCENE VI. </head>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e104210">
              <speaker>RODERIGO </speaker>
              <stage xml:id="ep000352-e104220">alone. </stage>
              <l>STrooke to the very heart, with a blow as fatall </l>
              <l>As un-foreseene; what shall I doe? I must </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-012-b"/>
              <l>Revenge my father, and provoke my mistresse, </l>
              <l>Either betray my honour, or my love, </l>
              <l>It were a better choice for me to die </l>
              <l>Than to doe either: </l>
              <l>If I revenge my father, I must lose </l>
              <l>My love; if not, I must live infamous; </l>
              <l>How can I live, having lost all I live for? </l>
              <l>But infamy pursues me after death. </l>
              <l>On then my soule, and rather chuse to die </l>
              <l>Losing thy love, than live ingloriously, </l>
              <l>And start not at the name of the offender, </l>
              <l>Because he is the father of thy mistresse, </l>
              <l>But rather thinke thine owne receiv'd the offence, </l>
              <l>And thou art bound to give the recompence. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="ep000352-e104390">
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000352-e104400">
            <head>ACT II. SCENE I. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e104410">Don ARIAS. The COUNT of Gormas. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e104420">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>I Must needs say, when I did give th' affront </l>
              <l>My bloud was over-heated, and my hand </l>
              <l>Somewhat too ready, but now who can help it? </l>
              <l>Since it is done, it cannot be recall'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-arias" xml:id="ep000352-e104470">
              <speaker>D. ARIAS. </speaker>
              <l>Faith, Let your courage stoope to the Kings will, </l>
              <l>He takes the businesse much to heart, and being </l>
              <l>So highly incens'd, beleeve it hee'le proceed </l>
              <l>With his full power, and then what defence </l>
              <l>Can you make for your selfe, when th' affront, </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-013-a"/>
              <l>And it's high quality shall be aggravated </l>
              <l>By the person of th' offended, and the place. </l>
              <l>These will require of you, my Lord, submissions </l>
              <l>Beyond all ordinary satisfaction. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e104570">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>Then let him take my life, 'tis in his power. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-arias" xml:id="ep000352-e104590">
              <speaker>D. ARIAS. </speaker>
              <l>Abate some of your heat, and heare what's reason, </l>
              <l>Will you not seeke to appease a Prince that loves you </l>
              <l>He sayes, I'le ha' this done, will not you doe it? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e104630">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, to preserve my honour, I cannot thinke </l>
              <l>'Tis such a crime, somewhat to disobey, </l>
              <l>But were it greater, what I've done for him, </l>
              <l>Would be more than enough to make my excuse. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-arias" xml:id="ep000352-e104680">
              <speaker>D. ARIAS. </speaker>
              <l>Suppose you've done all that a man can thinke </l>
              <l>In the Kings service: is he bound to thanke you? </l>
              <l>Can a Prince be beholding to a subject? </l>
              <l>You are too much o're-weening, you must know, </l>
              <l>He that best serves his King does but his duty, </l>
              <l>If you thinke otherwise, you are undone. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e104750">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>I shall beleeve you when I finde it so. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-arias" xml:id="ep000352-e104770">
              <speaker>D. ARIAS. </speaker>
              <l>Yout can't but feare the power of the King. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e104790">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>One day destroyes not such a man as I am. </l>
              <l>Let him arme all his power to punish me, </l>
              <l>The state shall rather perish, than I suffer. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-arias" xml:id="ep000352-e104830">
              <speaker>D. ARIAS. </speaker>
              <l>Doe you so little feare the soveraigne power? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e104850">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>What? of that Scepter? which if not for me </l>
              <l>Had ere now falne out of his hand: my person </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-013-b"/>
              <l>Is Sir, of so much consequence to the King, </l>
              <l>That if my head fall, his crowne cannot stand. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-arias" xml:id="ep000352-e104900">
              <speaker>D. ARIAS. </speaker>
              <l>My Lord, give reason leave to settle you, </l>
              <l>Thinke on't a little. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e104930">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>The thought's already taken. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-arias" xml:id="ep000352-e104950">
              <speaker>D. ARIAS. </speaker>
              <l>What shall I say then? I must give him an account. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e104970">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>This: that I know not how to give consent </l>
              <l>To mine owne shame. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-arias" xml:id="ep000352-e105000">
              <speaker>D. ARIAS. </speaker>
              <l>But my Lord imagine, </l>
              <l>Kings will be absolute. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e105030">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>Let 'um be so, </l>
              <l>The Die is cast Sir, let's talke no more on't. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-arias" xml:id="ep000352-e105060">
              <speaker>D. ARIAS. </speaker>
              <l>Then I must take my leave, since my perswasions </l>
              <l>Can doe no good: though you be cover'd o're </l>
              <l>with lawrels, yet my Lord, take heed of thunder. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e105100">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>I'le wait it without feare. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-arias" xml:id="ep000352-e105120">
              <speaker>D. ARIAS. </speaker>
              <l>It will come home. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e105140">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>If it doe, D. Diego's satisfied. </l>
              <l>How little am I scar'd with these poore threats? </l>
              <l>My honour once engag'd, a thousand deaths </l>
              <l>Presented to me in the most hideous formes, </l>
              <l>Cannot once startle me. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="ep000352-e105200">
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-014-a"/>
            <head>SCENE II. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e105210">RODERIGO. COUNT de GORMAS. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e105220">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>MY Lord a word. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e105240">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>Speake. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e105260">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Resolve me of a doubt, doe you know </l>
              <l>Don Diego well? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e105290">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>I doe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e105310">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>And that he was </l>
              <l>The spirit and the glory of his time, </l>
              <l>Doe you know this? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e105350">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>Perhaps he might be so. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e105370">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>And that this ardor which mine eyes doe beare, </l>
              <l>Doe you know it is his bloud it represents? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e105400">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>What's that to me? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e105420">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Some distance from this place </l>
              <l>I'le make you know it. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-014-b"/>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e105450">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>Presumptuous boy! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e105470">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Be not so hot, I know I'me young, but yet </l>
              <l>In noble soules, valour prevents their yeares. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e105500">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>But who has led thee to that vanity? </l>
              <l>To set thee upon me, thou that did'st never </l>
              <l>Beare armes, perhaps thou know'st not who I am. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e105540">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Yes: and I know a stouter man than I </l>
              <l>Would tremble at the hearing of thy name. </l>
              <l>Thy head is cover'd o're with lawrels, where </l>
              <l>Victory perches, and from thence reads to me </l>
              <l>The fate of my destruction: I doe challenge </l>
              <l>Like a rash youth, a man inur'd to conquest, </l>
              <l>Yet having heart enough, I shan't want strength, </l>
              <l>Or if I should, wearing my fathers cause </l>
              <l>Upon my sword and arme, they cannot faile me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e105640">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>This courage which appeares in thy discourse, </l>
              <l>I have beene long acquainted with, and hoping </l>
              <l>To see the honour of Castile in thee, </l>
              <l>'Twas in my thoughts to give my daughter to thee; </l>
              <l>I know thy love, and am amaz'd to see </l>
              <l>It's motions to give place unto thy honour, </l>
              <l>And meaning to finde out a perfect man, </l>
              <l>And compleat Cavalier for my sonne in law, </l>
              <l>I'me not mistaken in the choice I've made. </l>
              <l>But here my pitty intervenes, and though </l>
              <l>I wonder at thy courage, yet I grieve </l>
              <l>To see thy rashnesse: doe not seeke thy death, </l>
              <l>Prethee excuse my valour from a combat </l>
              <l>So farre unequall. If thou fall'st by me, </l>
              <l>'Twill be no honour to me. To o'recome </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-015-a"/>
              <l>Where there's no danger, will be a triumph </l>
              <l>Where there's no glory: for thou wilt be thought </l>
              <l>To have with ease beene ruin'd, and my selfe </l>
              <l>Shall alone feele the griefe that I have done it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e105840">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Th' hast seconded th' affront thou gav'st my father, </l>
              <l>With a pity worse than that, dar'st thou deprive me </l>
              <l>Of my honour, and yet fear'st to take my life? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e105880">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>Leave me good youth. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e105900">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Let's goe, and talke no more on't. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e105920">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>Art thou so weary of thy life? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e105940">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Art thou </l>
              <l>So afraid to die? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-count" xml:id="ep000352-e105970">
              <speaker>COUNT. </speaker>
              <l>Come then, thou do'st no more </l>
              <l>Than is thy duty, he's a degenerate sonne </l>
              <l>That will out-live one jot his fathers honour. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="ep000352-e106010">
            <head>SCENE III. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e106020">INFANTA. CIMENA. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e106030">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>BE not so griev'd, Cimena, dry thine eyes, </l>
              <l>Use now thy constancie in this misfortune, </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-015-b"/>
              <l>Thou'lt see't cleare up after a little tempest: </l>
              <l>Thy happinesse is but clouded for a while, </l>
              <l>And some small time will make thee no great loser. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e106090">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>What can I hope now, but continuall troubles, </l>
              <l>A storme so sudden comming o're this calme </l>
              <l>Threatens a certaine shipwracke to our loves: </l>
              <l>'Tis past all doubt, I perish in the haven. </l>
              <l>I lov'd, was lov'd againe, our friends agreed, </l>
              <l>And I no sooner had told you the newes, </l>
              <l>But in an ill houre sprung their fatall quarrell, </l>
              <l>Which when I heard, I knew my hopes were ruin'd: </l>
              <l>Cursed ambition, honour pittilesse, </l>
              <l>Under whose tyranny the bravest soules </l>
              <l>Doe ever suffer: how many teares and sighs </l>
              <l>Must I pay for you? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e106220">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>Thou hast no reason </l>
              <l>To feare their quarrell, which on a sudden borne, </l>
              <l>Will as soone die: there's too much noise of it </l>
              <l>To let it live. The King shall take it up, </l>
              <l>And for thy sake I'le see't shall goe no farther. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e106280">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>This businesse will admit no composition, </l>
              <l>Th' affronts to honour never are repair'd, </l>
              <l>Wisdome or power can prevaile little here; </l>
              <l>This wound will not be heal'd, it may be cover'd, </l>
              <l>And stifled hate nourishes secret fires </l>
              <l>Within the brest, but such as burne more fiercely. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e106350">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>But th' holy knot which shall once joyne Cimena </l>
              <l>To Roderigo, will dissolve the hatred </l>
              <l>Of both their fathers, and the bonds of love, </l>
              <l>As being more strong, will quickly stop their discord. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e106400">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>rather doe desire, than hope it, Madam, </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-016-a"/>
              <l>Don Diego is too haughty, and I know </l>
              <l>My father well, of what a spirit he is. </l>
              <l>I feele my teares runne, which I would retaine: </l>
              <l>What's past, torments me, and I feare the sequell. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e106460">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>Do'st thou feare what a weake old man can doe? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e106480">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Roderigo is not weake. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e106500">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>But he's too young. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e106520">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Valiant young men are ever very sudden. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e106540">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>But that thou need'st not feare. He loves thee too well </l>
              <l>To anger or displease thee, one poore word </l>
              <l>Out of thy mouth, will quickly stay his heat. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e106580">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>If he doe not obey, how great's my griefe? </l>
              <l>And if he doe, what will men say of him, </l>
              <l>That being a Gentleman, he could put up </l>
              <l>Such an affront? so that if he resist, </l>
              <l>Or else give way to his affection, </l>
              <l>I cannot but be troubled, or asham'd </l>
              <l>At his too much respect, or just deniall. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e106660">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>Cimena's generous, and though she be </l>
              <l>Ingag'd, she cannot suffer a base thought. </l>
              <l>But if I make a prisoner of this lover </l>
              <l>Untill this businesse be tane up betwixt them, </l>
              <l>Will not your love turne into jealousie? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e106720">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Ah, Madam, in this case I have no such thought. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e106740">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>Boy, looke out Roderigo, bring him hither. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-016-b"/>
            <sp who="#ep000352-boy" xml:id="ep000352-e106760">
              <speaker>BOY. </speaker>
              <l>He, and the Count of Gormas </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e106780">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Good God, I tremble! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e106800">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>Speake. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-boy" xml:id="ep000352-e106820">
              <speaker>BOY. </speaker>
              <l>Went out together. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e106840">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>Alone? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-boy" xml:id="ep000352-e106860">
              <speaker>BOY. </speaker>
              <l>Alone, and as it seem'd, they went to quarell. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e106880">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Ay me, my fear's, they're fighting by this time. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e106900">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>Let's spend no more time then, but goe looke um out. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="ep000352-e106920">
            <head>SCENE IV. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e106930">KING. D. ARIAS. D. ALONSO. D. SANCHO. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e106940">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>IS he so vaine, has he so little reason, </l>
              <l>That he dares thinke his crime yet pardonable? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-arias" xml:id="ep000352-e106970">
              <speaker>D. ARIAS. </speaker>
              <l>I treated long with him on your behalfe, </l>
              <l>I did (Sir) my devoir, but obtain'd nothing. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e107000">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>Just heaven! can a subject be so rash </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-017-a"/>
              <l>To have so little care to please his Master? </l>
              <l>H'as strucken Don Diego, scorn'd his King, </l>
              <l>In my owne Court he meanes to give me lawes: </l>
              <l>Be he ne're so good a souldier or commander, </l>
              <l>I'le make him know what 'tis to disobey. </l>
              <l>I would ha' treated him with all faire meanes, </l>
              <l>But since he has abus'd my patience, </l>
              <l>Goe some of you and looke him out, and whether </l>
              <l>He doe resist, or not, make sure of him. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-sancho" xml:id="ep000352-e107110">
              <speaker>D. SANCHO. </speaker>
              <l>Perhaps some little time will bring him in. </l>
              <l>He was taken boiling in his choller, Sir, </l>
              <l>And a stout heart will hardly yeeld to reason, </l>
              <l>In the first motion of its rage and heat. </l>
              <l>Here's no man, that not thinks he is to blame, </l>
              <l>But yet so high a spirit is not brought </l>
              <l>At first so easily to confesse his fault. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e107190">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>Don Sancho, hold your peace, and let me tell you, </l>
              <l>He that shall take his part is alike faulty. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-sancho" xml:id="ep000352-e107220">
              <speaker>D. SANCHO. </speaker>
              <l>I obey Sir, and am silent, but with favour, </l>
              <l>A word in his defence. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e107250">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>What can you say? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-sancho" xml:id="ep000352-e107270">
              <speaker>D. SANCHO. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, that a soule accustom'd to great actions, </l>
              <l>Cannot abase it selfe to low submissions. </l>
              <l>It knowes not how to doe it without shame, </l>
              <l>And that's the word which troubles most the Count. </l>
              <l>He finds it somewhat hard to doe his duty. </l>
              <l>He would obey if he had lesse of courage; </l>
              <l>If you'd command, that he being us'd to arms, </l>
              <l>Should with his sword repaire this injury, </l>
              <l>I'le undertake he shall make satisfaction. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-017-b"/>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e107370">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>You are too bold Sir, but your age I pardon, </l>
              <l>Thinking it to proceed from heat of youth. </l>
              <l>A prudent King knowes better how to husband </l>
              <l>His subjects bloud, then so to venture 'em. </l>
              <l>For mine, I meane my care shall still conserve 'um. </l>
              <l>As the head cares for th' members which doe serve it. </l>
              <l>You speake Sir, as a souldier, but I must </l>
              <l>Doe as a King, and whatsoere the Count </l>
              <l>Does say or thinke, I'me sure he cannot lose </l>
              <l>Ought of his honour in obeying me: </l>
              <l>Th' affront he did to him whom I have made </l>
              <l>Governour to my sonne, does touch me neerly, </l>
              <l>And this his insolence hath quarrell'd me, </l>
              <l>And th' choice I made: So if he doe submit, </l>
              <l>I am the man he satisfies. But no more, </l>
              <l>Don Arias, by an advice of late receiv'd, </l>
              <l>I heare the Moores meane shortly to supprise us. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-arias" xml:id="ep000352-e107550">
              <speaker>D. ARIAS. </speaker>
              <l>Dare the Moores stirre? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e107570">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>Their vessels are discover'd </l>
              <l>At the Rivers mouth, and you know how easily </l>
              <l>At a full Sea they may come up. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-arias" xml:id="ep000352-e107610">
              <speaker>D. ARIAS. </speaker>
              <l>The battailes </l>
              <l>They've lost already, should make 'um loose the heart </l>
              <l>To set on such a Conquerour as you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e107650">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>They cannot but with Jealouzy looke on, </l>
              <l>Seeing me rule in Andalouzia, </l>
              <l>And this faire Country, which I tooke from them, </l>
              <l>Keepes their designes awake. It is the reason, </l>
              <l>Why here in Sevill I have plac'd my Throne, </l>
              <l>That being neere'ee I may be more ready </l>
              <l>To meet with their attempts. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-018-a"/>
            <sp who="#ep000352-arias" xml:id="ep000352-e107730">
              <speaker>D. ARIAS. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, they have learnt, </l>
              <l>At the great charge of their owne heads by this time, </l>
              <l>How much your presence does assure your conquest, </l>
              <l>Y' have nothing Sir, to feare. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e107780">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>Nor to neglect: </l>
              <l>Too much assurance still drawes danger with it: </l>
              <l>The enemy which we now thinke to destroy, </l>
              <l>If he can take his time, may annoy us. </l>
              <l>But yet since I'me not certaine of my newes, </l>
              <l>I would not stirre up in my subjects hearts </l>
              <l>Vaine panique terrors, or this present night </l>
              <l>Affright the City with a false alarme: </l>
              <l>Let the haven be well guarded, and the wals, </l>
              <l>And for this night it shall suffice. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-alonso" xml:id="ep000352-e107890">
              <speaker>D. ALONSO </speaker>
              <stage xml:id="ep000352-e107900">enters againe. </stage>
              <l>Sir, the Count is dead, </l>
              <l>Roderigo's hand has satisfied his father. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e107930">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>I divin'd what would follow, when I first </l>
              <l>Heard of th' affront, and would ha' then prevented it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-alonso" xml:id="ep000352-e107960">
              <speaker>D. ALONSO. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, here's Cimena, who presents her griefe </l>
              <l>Upon her knees, with teares demanding justice. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e107990">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>Although my soule suffer with his misfortunes, </l>
              <l>Th' affront he did, deserv'd the punishment, </l>
              <l>Which though it were most just, yet can't I lose </l>
              <l>Without regret, a servant of his merit. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="ep000352-e108040">
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-018-b"/>
            <head>SCENE V. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e108050">KING. D. ARIAS. D. DIEGO. CIMENA. D. SANCHO. D. ALONSO. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e108060">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Justice, Sir, Justice, I aske it on my knees. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e108080">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>O Sir give eare to my defence. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e108100">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Revenge my fathers death. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e108120">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>Of him that punisht the highest insolence. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e108140">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Roderigo, Sir, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e108160">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>Has done the office of an honest man. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e108180">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Has kill'd my father. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e108200">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>Has reveng'd his owne. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e108220">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>A King owes justice to his subjects bloud. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e108240">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>A just revenge can feare no punishment. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e108260">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>Rise both of you, and speake without disturbance, </l>
              <l>I beare a part, Cimena, in thy sufferings. </l>
              <l>Trouble her not, when she has done, I'le heare you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e108300">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>My father's slaine, Sir, and these eyes have seene </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-019-a"/>
              <l>His bloud gush out in bubles; that deare bloud </l>
              <l>Which has so oft preserv'd your wals, so oft </l>
              <l>Been fir'd to gaine you battailes, and which yet </l>
              <l>Reakes with just anger, to have beene spilt for any </l>
              <l>But you the King, which war durst never draw, </l>
              <l>Roderigo in your Court has made to flow </l>
              <l>Upon the earth, and for his first essay, </l>
              <l>Has tane away the firme prop of your State, </l>
              <l>Breathlesse, and pale, I came unto the place, </l>
              <l>And found him dead! Dead! pardon Sir, my griefe, </l>
              <l>My voyce does faile mee, let my teares speake the rest. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e108430">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>Daughter, take comfort, and be confident </l>
              <l>Thou hast a King will be a Father to thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e108460">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>You'ave done my miseries, Sir, too much honour. </l>
              <l>Thither I came amaz'd, and found him dead, </l>
              <l>He spoke nought to me, but the more to move me, </l>
              <l>His spilt bloud wrote my duty on the dust. </l>
              <l>Rather his worth reduc'd to that poore State, </l>
              <l>Spoke to me through his wound and hasten'd me </l>
              <l>To this pursuite, and to be heard the better, </l>
              <l>Of the most just of Kings, borrow'd my voyce. </l>
              <l>Suffer not Sir, such rage to passe unpunisht </l>
              <l>Before your eyes, and let not heady youth, </l>
              <l>Lave themselves in the bloud of your best Souldiers, </l>
              <l>And brave their memories. If you permit it, </l>
              <l>You'le have, but few that will desire to serve you, </l>
              <l>In fine my Father's dead, I demaund justice </l>
              <l>Rather for yours, than my owne interest, </l>
              <l>You are ingag'd i' th' losse of such a man, </l>
              <l>Revenge it then, and require bloud for bloud. </l>
              <l>Sacrifice D. Diego, and his familie </l>
              <l>To your selfe, to the people, to Castile, </l>
              <l>What can be deare enough to satisfie </l>
              <l>For my dead Father? </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-019-b"/>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e108680">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>D. Diego answer. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e108700">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>How happy is the man Sir? </l>
              <l>Who parts no sooner with his strength than life, </l>
              <l>Since to the valiant, age is most unhappy </l>
              <l>Accompanied with weaknesse; I that have </l>
              <l>Gotten such glory by my former actions, </l>
              <l>Whom victory has ever wayted on </l>
              <l>See my selfe now, for having liv'd too long </l>
              <l>Affronted, and orecome. And that which neither </l>
              <l>Combat, nor siege, nor ambushes could doe, </l>
              <l>Nor all your enemies, nor mine to boot, </l>
              <l>The pride of one man in your Court has done </l>
              <l>Almost before your face, and sullied </l>
              <l>The reverence, and honour of my age, </l>
              <l>Advantag'd by his youth, and by my weaknesse, </l>
              <l>And so Sir, these my haires which have growne white </l>
              <l>Under my helmet, and my bloud, which has </l>
              <l>So oft for you been spent, should ha' descended </l>
              <l>Unto the grave with curelesse infamy. </l>
              <l>Had I not got a Sonne to save my honour, </l>
              <l>Who lending me his hand has slaine the Count. </l>
              <l>If to shew courage, and a sense of wrong, </l>
              <l>If to revenge a blow o'th face deserve </l>
              <l>Severely to be punisht, let it fall </l>
              <l>On me that tempest, what soer'e it be, </l>
              <l>For the armes fault, we punish oft the head, </l>
              <l>I am the head, Sir, he is but the arme, </l>
              <l>And if Cimena doe complaine that he </l>
              <l>Has slaine her Father, I must answer her, </l>
              <l>Had I beene able, he had never done it. </l>
              <l>Sacrifice then this head, which age will take, </l>
              <l>The arme Sir, may hereafter doe you service. </l>
              <l>And let Cimena's wrong be satisfied </l>
              <l>At my owne bloud's expence, and I shall be </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-020-a"/>
              <l>So farre from thinking it an uniust censure, </l>
              <l>That dying with mine honour, I shall die </l>
              <l>Withou t regret. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e109070">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>Th' affaire is of importance, </l>
              <l>And merits to be heard in a full Counsell. </l>
              <l>Don Sancho, wait upon Cimena home, </l>
              <l>Don Diego's word shall be his surety. </l>
              <l>Let his sonne be lookt out. I'le doe you justice. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e109130">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis just great Sir to cut off murderers. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e109150">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>Daughter, take truce a little with your griefes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e109170">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>To give them truce, is to increase them more. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="ep000352-e109190">
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000352-e109200">
            <head>ACT III. SCENE I. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e109210">D. RODERIGO. ELVIRA. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e109220">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>WHat meane you Roderigo? whither would you? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e109240">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>I would pursue the course of my sad fortune. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e109260">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>But this is a strange boldnesse, to appeare </l>
              <l>In the same place which you have fill'd with mourning, </l>
              <l>Come you t' affront the ghost of the dead Count? </l>
              <l>Have not you slaine him? </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-020-b"/>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e109310">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>His life was my disgrace, </l>
              <l>Mine honour at my hands requir'd dis death. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e109340">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>But in the house of death to looke for refuge, </l>
              <l>Did ever homicide make that his Asilum? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e109370">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Did never any murderer present </l>
              <l>Himselfe unto his Judge? ne're wonder at me, </l>
              <l>I come to seeke for that I gave another, </l>
              <l>That's death; my love Cimena is my Judge. </l>
              <l>When I deserv'd her hate, I deserv'd death, </l>
              <l>And for that cause I stand here to receive </l>
              <l>My sentence from her mouth, death from her hand. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e109450">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>Flie rather from her sight, and doe not meet </l>
              <l>With the first motions of her griefe and anger, </l>
              <l>Why, would you more enflame her present passion? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e109490">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>No, that deare object which I durst displease, </l>
              <l>To punish me cannot have too much passion; </l>
              <l>I should be happy if I could augment it, </l>
              <l>And hasten so my death from her faire hand. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e109540">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>Cimena's at the Court, bath'd in her teares, </l>
              <l>And will returne thence with much company. </l>
              <l>For heavens sake flie: what will mens censures say </l>
              <l>If y'are discover'd here? they must report </l>
              <l>Cimena t' have receiv'd into her house </l>
              <l>Th' Assassin of her father. Harke, she comes, </l>
              <l>It is her voice: at least, Roderigo, </l>
              <l>To save her reputation, hide your selfe. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="ep000352-e109630">
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-021-a"/>
            <head>SCENE II. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e109640">D. SANCHO. CIMENA. ELVIRA. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-sancho" xml:id="ep000352-e109650">
              <speaker>D. SANCHO. </speaker>
              <l>I Madame, never thinke of any other </l>
              <l>But bloudy sacrifices: your anger's just </l>
              <l>And your griefe lawfull, for my part Madame </l>
              <l>I'le neither goe about to pacifie </l>
              <l>Or comfort you; but if my present service </l>
              <l>Can be of use to you; imploy my Sword </l>
              <l>To cut out your revenge; from your commands </l>
              <l>My heart takes courage, and my arme its strength. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e109740">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>O me unfortunate! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-sancho" xml:id="ep000352-e109760">
              <speaker>D. SANCHO. </speaker>
              <l>Madame accept my service. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e109780">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>I shall offend the King then who has promis'd </l>
              <l>To doe me Justice. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-sancho" xml:id="ep000352-e109810">
              <speaker>D. SANCHO. </speaker>
              <l>But you know, justice </l>
              <l>Is so slow pac'd and languishing, that seldome </l>
              <l>It overtakes the crime; the wrong was done </l>
              <l>By th'sword, then let a Cavalier revenge it </l>
              <l>By the sword againe: It is the readiest way. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e109870">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis the last remedy, but if it must </l>
              <l>Arive at that, and this your noble pitty </l>
              <l>Of my misfortunes doe continue with you, </l>
              <l>I shall then give you the freedom you desire. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-021-b"/>
            <sp who="#ep000352-sancho" xml:id="ep000352-e109920">
              <speaker>D. SANCHO. </speaker>
              <l>It is the onely happinesse I wish, </l>
              <l>So having hopes to see't, I take my leave. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="ep000352-e109950">
            <head>SCENE III. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e109960">CIMENA. ELVIRA. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e109970">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>AT length I find I'me free to open to thee </l>
              <l>The sadnesse of my soule, and to give way </l>
              <l>to my deep sighs, which else would stifle me. </l>
              <l>My fathers dead, Eluira, the first sword </l>
              <l>That Roderigo us'd has cut his thred, </l>
              <l>Weepe, weepe mine eyes, melt into teares my braine </l>
              <l>Halfe of my life, the other halfe has slaine, </l>
              <l>And ty's me to revenge on what is left, </l>
              <l>That part of which by this I am bereft. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e110070">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>Quiet your selfe, sweet Madame. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e110090">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>How unfitly </l>
              <l>Thou bid'st me to be quiet, when at once </l>
              <l>I must bewaile my losse, and th'hand that made it, </l>
              <l>Or what is't I can hope for in this life </l>
              <l>But torments, neere to be redres'd by time, </l>
              <l>If loving th' Author, I pursue the crime. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e110160">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>Can you then love the man that kill'd your Father? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e110180">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Love him, Eluira? more than that I adore him, </l>
              <l>My love stands up against the sense, I should have </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-022-a"/>
              <l>Of a slaine father, and would quite o're-beare it. </l>
              <l>I finde my lover in mine enemie, </l>
              <l>And spight of all my anger, in my heart </l>
              <l>Roderigo makes his part good 'gainst my father: </l>
              <l>Yet though my love has these advantages, </l>
              <l>I'le not advise with it about my duty. </l>
              <l>Nothing is dearer to me than Roderigo, </l>
              <l>My heart would take his part, but then my honour </l>
              <l>Tels me I had a father, which he slew. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e110300">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>But doe you meane to prosecute him, Madam? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e110320">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>O cruell meaning! cruell prosecution! </l>
              <l>To which I'me forc'd. I aske his head, and yet </l>
              <l>Feare to obtaine it. I would ha him punish'd, </l>
              <l>And yet my death, I know, must wait on his. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e110370">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>Fie, Madam, quit this tragicall designe, </l>
              <l>Be not so cruell to your selfe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e110400">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Shall I see </l>
              <l>My father die betweene my armes? his bloud </l>
              <l>Crying vengeance to me, and shan't I heare him? </l>
              <l>Shall my heart thinke, because 'tis charm'd by love, </l>
              <l>That nothing's due unto a fathers death </l>
              <l>But childish teares? or shall I suffer love </l>
              <l>To steale into my heart, and thrust out honour? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e110480">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>Beleeve me, Madam, you may well be pardon'd, </l>
              <l>If you preserve unto your selfe a man </l>
              <l>You cannot paralell, and one you love. </l>
              <l>Y'have done enough to ha' beene with the King, </l>
              <l>Ne're presse it farther, be not obstinate. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e110540">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Then is my glory lost; no, it behoves </l>
              <l>I be reveng'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-022-b"/>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e110570">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>But you love Roderigo, </l>
              <l>He can't displease you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e110600">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>No I'le sweare he can't. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e110620">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>These things consider'd, Madam, what can you doe? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e110640">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>To save mine honour, and to put an end </l>
              <l>To all my griefes at once, I am resolv'd </l>
              <l>First to pursue him unto death, and then </l>
              <l>To die my selfe. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="ep000352-e110690">
            <head>SCENE IV. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e110700">RODERIGO to them. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e110710">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>TO save the trouble of </l>
              <l>Pursuing me, behold I'me here before you, </l>
              <l>Glut your selfe with the pleasure of my death. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e110750">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>What place is this, Elvira? who is this? </l>
              <l>Roderigo in my house! before my face! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e110780">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Spare not my bloud, but taste the sweetnesse of </l>
              <l>My death, and your revenge, without resistance. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e110810">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Aye me! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e110830">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Heare me Cimena. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-023-a"/>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e110850">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>I dye. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e110870">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>A word </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e110890">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Away and let me dye. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e110910">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>And afterwards </l>
              <l>Make me no answer but with this my sword. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e110940">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>That sword be smear'd with th' bloud of my dead father. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e110960">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>My Cimena </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e110980">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Fye, take away that object </l>
              <l>Which to myne eyes upbraids thy crime, and life. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e111010">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Looke on it rather to increase thy hate </l>
              <l>T'excite thine anger, and to speed my death. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e111040">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis dy'd in my owne bloud. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e111060">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Plunge it in mine, </l>
              <l>And make it lose the colour so of thine. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e111090">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>What cruelty is this, which in one day </l>
              <l>Father and daughter both deprives of life, </l>
              <l>One by the sword, the other by the sight? </l>
              <l>Remove that object of my hate, thy sword, </l>
              <l>Thou would'st be heard of her thou mean'st to kill. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e111150">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>I doe obey, yet with the same desire </l>
              <l>To dye by thee. For from my affection </l>
              <l>Never expect a cowardly repentance </l>
              <l>Of a good action, the box o'th eare </l>
              <l>Thy father gave, dishonor'd mine, thou know'st </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-023-b"/>
              <l>How home that touches any man of spirit, </l>
              <l>I shar'd in the affront and went to seeke </l>
              <l>The Author, having found him I reveng'd </l>
              <l>Mine and my fathers honor: wer't to doe </l>
              <l>Againe I'de do't, yet thinke not but thy love </l>
              <l>Held out against my father, and my selfe, </l>
              <l>A combat long enough, and made me doubt </l>
              <l>Whether I should displease thee or sit down </l>
              <l>By th' injury receav'd. I held my hand </l>
              <l>And blam'd my selfe for too much violence: </l>
              <l>And without doubt thy beauty had o're sway'd, </l>
              <l>Had I not cast in ballance, that a man </l>
              <l>Dishonor'd never could be worthy thee, </l>
              <l>That she who lov'd me when my fame stood cleare, </l>
              <l>Would hate me, stain'd with infamy. 'Tis true, </l>
              <l>I did thee an affront, and 'tis as true </l>
              <l>I ought to doe it both to save my honor </l>
              <l>And merit thee. But having thus acquitted </l>
              <l>My father and my selfe, 'tis onely you </l>
              <l>That I now come to satisfie, and make </l>
              <l>A present of my bloud. I know the thought </l>
              <l>Of a slaine father, armes thy hate against mee, </l>
              <l>Nor will I rob thee of thy sacrifice </l>
              <l>Here, offer to the blood already shed </l>
              <l>The blood of him, that glories to have shed it, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e111460">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>True Roderigo, (though thine enemy) </l>
              <l>That thou did'st shun disgrace, I cannot blame thee, </l>
              <l>And whatsoever face my griefes put on </l>
              <l>I not accuse thee, but my owne misfortune. </l>
              <l>I know what honour, after such an out rage, </l>
              <l>Demaund's of any brave and generous spirit. </l>
              <l>Thou did'st thy duty but in doeing it </l>
              <l>Thou taught'st me mine. The same regard thou had'st </l>
              <l>To vindicate thine owne, and fathers honor </l>
              <l>Fall's now one me, and the more t'afflict me </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-024-a"/>
              <l>Of thee I must require, what I have lost; </l>
              <l>It is thy interest makes me despaire, </l>
              <l>Had any other hand, or sad missortune </l>
              <l>Depriv'd me of my father, I had found </l>
              <l>My comfort in thy sight, the onely charme </l>
              <l>Against my griefes: When by so deare a hand </l>
              <l>My teares had beene wip'd off: but now I must </l>
              <l>Lose him and thee too, and what's more cruell, </l>
              <l>I'me bound my selfe to labour thy destruction, </l>
              <l>For never looke from my affection </l>
              <l>The least resentment for thy punishment; </l>
              <l>For though our love would speak in favour of thee, </l>
              <l>Mine honour yet must goe as high as thine; </l>
              <l>Thou in my wrong shewd'st thy selfe worthy me, </l>
              <l>I in thy death will appeare worthy thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e111720">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Never deferre then longer what your honour </l>
              <l>Requires of you. It demands my head, </l>
              <l>To stay till justice give't you, will delay </l>
              <l>As well your glory, as my punishment. </l>
              <l>I shall die happy, dying by your hand. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e111780">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Away, I'me thy accuser, not thy heads-man, </l>
              <l>Is't fit for me to take the head thou offer'st? </l>
              <l>'Tis of another that I must obtaine it; </l>
              <l>I must pursue thy crime, not punish it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e111830">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Though love speake to thee in my favour, yet </l>
              <l>The brav'ry of thy minde ought to answer mine, </l>
              <l>Which trust me (my Cimena) cannot be, </l>
              <l>If to revenge thou borrow'st other hands. </l>
              <l>For my revenge I us'd none but my owne, </l>
              <l>And thou for thine, must use thy hand alone. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e111900">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Cruell! to be so obstinate in this, </l>
              <l>If without helpe thou did'st revenge thy selfe, </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-024-b"/>
              <l>Why do'st thou offer't me? I'le follow thee, </l>
              <l>My courage is too great to let thee beare </l>
              <l>The least part in my glory, neither shall </l>
              <l>Mine, or my fathers honour stoop so low </l>
              <l>As to thy love, or thy despaire to owe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e111980">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Hard point of honour! can I by no way </l>
              <l>Obtaine this grace? punish me in the name </l>
              <l>Of thy dead father, or our dearest love, </l>
              <l>Either do't in revenge, or else in pity. </l>
              <l>'Twill to thy lover prove a gentler fate, </l>
              <l>To die thus by thy hand, than to live with thy hate. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e112050">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Away, I hate thee not. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e112070">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Thou ought'st to hate me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e112090">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>I can't. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e112110">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>But fear'st thou not the blame and scandall </l>
              <l>Which men will raise, when they shall know my crime, </l>
              <l>And the continuance of thy love; no, rather </l>
              <l>Force 'um to silence, and without more words, </l>
              <l>By my death give thy reputation life. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e112170">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>It will live better, if I let thee live; </l>
              <l>I'le ha' the voice of the most blacke mouth'd envie </l>
              <l>Admire my glory, and pitty my hard sufferings, </l>
              <l>When they shall know, that though I love thy person, </l>
              <l>I prosecute thy crime. Goe Roderigo, </l>
              <l>And let the darknesse of the night conceale </l>
              <l>Thy parting hence, mine honour cannot runne </l>
              <l>A greater hazzard, than if men shall know </l>
              <l>That I have kept thee company so long. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e112270">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis death to heare this. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-025-a"/>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e112290">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Away. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e112310">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>But what, are you resolv'd to doe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e112330">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Spight of this loving fire which would restraine </l>
              <l>That of my anger, I shall doe my best </l>
              <l>To have full vengeance for my fathers death, </l>
              <l>And yet in spight of this so cruell honor, </l>
              <l>My desire is to have my desires crost. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e112390">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>O miracle of love! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e112410">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>But heap'd with griefes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e112430">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>How many teares will these our fathers cost us? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e112450">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Who would ha' thought it Roderigo? </l>
              <l>Who </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e112480">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Cimena would ha' said it? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e112500">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>That our joyes </l>
              <l>Should be so nigh us and so quickly lost. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e112530">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>And that so neere the Port a suddaine storme </l>
              <l>Should shipwrack all our hopes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e112560">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Goe Roderigo, </l>
              <l>And thinke I cannot, dare not, heare thee longer. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e112590">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>I goe then to draw out a dying life, </l>
              <l>Till thy pursuit shall bring it to an end. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e112620">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>If I obtaine th' effect, I sadly vow </l>
              <l>Not to draw breath one minute after thee, </l>
              <l>Adieu, and have a care thou be not seene. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="ep000352-e112660">
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-025-b"/>
            <head>SCENE V. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e112670">D. DIEGO. D. RODERIGO. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e112680">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>AT length I see what all my industry </l>
              <l>Could not effect, chance offers to me, this </l>
              <l>Must be my Sonne. Roderigo, blest be Heaven </l>
              <l>That gives me leave to see thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e112730">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Ay me! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e112750">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>Doe not confound my joyes with these sad accents, </l>
              <l>But give me leave to praise thy early Valour, </l>
              <l>Which shewes the noble stock from which thou sprang'st </l>
              <l>The first stroke of thy sword, has equall'd all </l>
              <l>That mine could doe, and thy brave youthfull spirit, </l>
              <l>Has reach'd the glory of thy Ancestors. </l>
              <l>Prop of my age, and fulnesse of my joy, </l>
              <l>Touch these white hayres, whose honor thou hast sav'd, </l>
              <l>Come kisse this cheeke; and view the place which thou </l>
              <l>Being affronted, rescud'st from disgrace. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e112860">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>The honor's due to you, heaven be my witnesse </l>
              <l>That comming from you, I could doe no lesse, </l>
              <l>I hold my selfe most happy, that the first </l>
              <l>Triall of my poore valour should please him </l>
              <l>To whom I owe my life, but in these pleasures </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-026-a"/>
              <l>Have not a jealousie of me, because </l>
              <l>After you, I dare satisfie my selfe </l>
              <l>Give me leave to despaire; 'tis all I aske. </l>
              <l>Let not your praise flatter me out of that. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e112960">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>By, from so brave a heart banish this weaknesse, </l>
              <l>Thinke there are Mistrisses enough ith' world, </l>
              <l>But no more than one honour; love, is but </l>
              <l>A little pleasure, honour is a duty. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e113010">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>What say you, Sir? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e113030">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>That which thou ought'st to know. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e113050">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Would you then shame me with inconstancy, </l>
              <l>A coward Souldier, and a perjur'd Lover, </l>
              <l>Run the same course of infamy alike. </l>
              <l>Cannot I be thought generous unlesse </l>
              <l>I be perfidious. Alas my bonds </l>
              <l>Are too fast ty'd, to be so soone undone </l>
              <l>And since I can nor have, nor leave my love, </l>
              <l>The death I meane to seeke is my best comfort. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e113140">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>This is no time to seeke out death. Thy King, </l>
              <l>Thy Country needs thy aid, the Fleet wee fear'd </l>
              <l>That enter'd on the River, is now ready </l>
              <l>To take the City by surprise. The Moores </l>
              <l>Are come in silence almost to our wals, </l>
              <l>The Court is in an uproare, and the people </l>
              <l>Call to take armes. Nothing but cries are heard </l>
              <l>I'th mid'st of these calamities, my fortune </l>
              <l>Has favor'd me so much to let me see, </l>
              <l>Five hundred of my frinds, within my house, </l>
              <l>Who hearing of the affront was given me, </l>
              <l>Offer'd their lives to vindicate mine honour, </l>
              <l>Thou hast prevented them, but their brave valours </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-026-b"/>
              <l>Will better be imployed against the Moores; </l>
              <l>Goe march i'th head of them; where honour cals thee, </l>
              <l>Impeach the landing of the enemy. </l>
              <l>And if thou must seeke death, goe find it there; </l>
              <l>But rather Crown'd with victory returne, </l>
              <l>And by thy valour force ev'n justice selfe </l>
              <l>To pardon, and Cimena to be silent, </l>
              <l>If thou do'st love her, thinke thy comming home </l>
              <l>A Conquerour, must regaine her heart, or nothing. </l>
              <l>But time's too precious to be spent in talke, </l>
              <l>I stay thee in discourse, when thou should'st fly, </l>
              <l>Come follow mee to my house: Let the King see </l>
              <l>What he has lost ith' Count, he has found in thee. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="ep000352-e113410">
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000352-e113420">
            <head>ACT IV. SCENE I. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e113430">CIMENA. ELVIRA. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e113440">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>BUt is this true, Elvira? art thou sure on't? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e113460">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>How hard it is to beget faith in you, </l>
              <l>When every man extoll's the glorious actions </l>
              <l>Of this young Heros: The Moores before him </l>
              <l>Appear'd, but to their shame. They quickly landed, </l>
              <l>But quicker was their flight. Three houres fight </l>
              <l>Left to our men a victory intire, </l>
              <l>And two Kings prisoners. Their leaders valour </l>
              <l>Could meet with nothing durst stand in its way. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-027-a"/>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e113550">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>And was't Roderigo's hand that did these wonders. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e113570">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>The two Kings which he vanquish'd are his prize. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e113590">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Whence could'st thou gather this strange news, Elvira? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e113610">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>From those who sound his praises up and downe, </l>
              <l>The people, who with one voice doe salute him </l>
              <l>Their Guardian Angell, saver of their Countrey. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e113650">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>How does the King looke, upon this his valour? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e113670">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>Roderigo dares not yet appeare in Court, </l>
              <l>But Don Diego, in the Conquerours name, </l>
              <l>Has made a present of these Crowned Captives, </l>
              <l>And all he does demand, is, that the King </l>
              <l>Would daigne to see the hand that freed his Country. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e113730">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>But has he got no wound? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e113750">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>I know not that. </l>
              <l>Why change you colour so? resume your spirits. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e113780">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Let me resume my anger, which my love </l>
              <l>Has so enfeebled; must my care for him </l>
              <l>Make me forget my selfe? peace, peace my love, </l>
              <l>And let my anger worke; though he have vanquish'd </l>
              <l>Two kings, he has not overcome my duty. </l>
              <l>These mourning habits, where I read my miseries, </l>
              <l>Are the first fruits his valour did produce, </l>
              <l>And though all tongues should speake in his defence </l>
              <l>All objects here doe represent his crime. </l>
              <l>Veile, Cypres, and these blacks sad memories </l>
              <l>Of my dead Father, keepe a little up </l>
              <l>Mine honour 'gainst my passion, and when love </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-027-b"/>
              <l>Shall get the power of me, tell my heart </l>
              <l>I owe a duty to a Father slaine. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e113930">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>Be not transported so: The Infanta's here. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="ep000352-e113950">
            <head>SCENE II. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e113960">INFANTA. CIMENA. LEONORA. ELVIRA. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e113970">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>I Come not here, Cimena, with faint comforts </l>
              <l>To plead against thy griefe, but with sad sighs </l>
              <l>To mingle with thy teares. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e114010">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Nay rather, Madame, </l>
              <l>Share in the common joy, and fully taste </l>
              <l>The happinesse, kind heaven has sent to you, </l>
              <l>I only am design'd for grief; the dangers </l>
              <l>From which y'are rescu'd by Roderigo's hand, </l>
              <l>And all your safeties purchas'd by his armes. </l>
              <l>To me alone bequeath these teares and sighs, </l>
              <l>'Tis he has sav'd the Citty, serv'd his King, </l>
              <l>And onely ruin'd me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e114110">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis true, Cimena, </l>
              <l>He has done wonders. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-028-a"/>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e114140">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Yes the unwelcome newes, </l>
              <l>Has pierc'd my eares already, I can heare </l>
              <l>How the voyce goes, and that hee's fam'd no lesse </l>
              <l>A Valiant Souldier, than a lucklesse lover. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e114190">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>How comes this newes to be unwelcome to you? </l>
              <l>Was not the man they prais'd your servant once? </l>
              <l>And had not he your heart? in honouring him </l>
              <l>They honour much your choise. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e114240">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>I needs must say </l>
              <l>His honours are but due, and yet to me </l>
              <l>Each praise of him, is a new punishment, </l>
              <l>For I can't chose but know how great my losse is, </l>
              <l>Finding the value of the thing I lose </l>
              <l>The more his merit, and my love increases, </l>
              <l>The more my duty gets advantage of me, </l>
              <l>And spight of my affection puts me on </l>
              <l>To prosecute his crime. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e114340">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>But will you, Madam, </l>
              <l>Beleeve the counsell of a faithfull friend. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e114370">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Not to obey you were a sin unpardonable. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e114390">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>Though yesterday pursuing your revenge, </l>
              <l>You did so much that all the Court admir'd </l>
              <l>Your height of spirit, and bewaild your love; </l>
              <l>Yet the same way is not now to be taken. </l>
              <l>Roderigo's now the onely hope and stay </l>
              <l>Of all Castile. The terrour of the Mores. </l>
              <l>His valour has restor'd us what before </l>
              <l>It tooke away, in him your father seemes </l>
              <l>To live againe, and in a word pursuing </l>
              <l>His death, you goe about the publicke ruine, </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-028-b"/>
              <l>What? to revenge a father, is it lawfull </l>
              <l>To give your Country up to its Enemies? </l>
              <l>And are we to be punish'd for his fault? </l>
              <l>I say not this, that I would have you marry </l>
              <l>The man y'are bound to prosecute. I'de rather </l>
              <l>You should avoid that envy, and deprive </l>
              <l>Him of your love, but not us of his life. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e114570">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Ah, Madam, give my spirit its full course, </l>
              <l>Though my heart make a faction against me, </l>
              <l>Though he be lov'd by the King, ador'd by th' people, </l>
              <l>Though he be compass'd with the stoutest Souldiers, </l>
              <l>He overwhelme his Laurell, with my Cipresse. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e114630">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>I must confesse, it is a marke of spirit </l>
              <l>To prosecute the life you lov'd so dearely, </l>
              <l>Yet I should thinke, it were more noble fat </l>
              <l>To give up to the publick interest </l>
              <l>The private ones of bloud. For credit me, </l>
              <l>Cimena, 'tis enough, to leave to love him: </l>
              <l>Banish him from your heart and he will find </l>
              <l>A heavy punishment. Your Countries good </l>
              <l>Requires this, besides you must not thinke </l>
              <l>The King should grant you your request. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e114740">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>He may. </l>
              <l>Refuse me if he please, but I must speake. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e114770">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>Consider well, Cimena, what it is </l>
              <l>You goe about, and thinke of it at leasure. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="ep000352-e114800">
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-029-a"/>
            <head>SCENE III. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e114810">KING. D. DIEGO. D. ARIAS. D. RODERIGO. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e114820">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>THou brave descendent of a noble race, </l>
              <l>Who have been still supporters of my kingdome, </l>
              <l>(Who's valour the first proofe of thine has equall'd) </l>
              <l>My power is too narrow for thy merit. </l>
              <l>To free thy Country of so rude a foe </l>
              <l>As are the Moores, before my selfe could give </l>
              <l>Order for their repulse, is such an act </l>
              <l>As flies beyond all thought of recompence. </l>
              <l>But the two captiv'd Kings which thou hast taken, </l>
              <l>Shall give thee thy reward, they both have nam'd thee </l>
              <l>Their CID before me; which in their tongue sounds </l>
              <l>As much as Lord in ours, and this faire title </l>
              <l>I will not envy thee; from henceforth be </l>
              <l>Their CID, that at thy name the Moores may tremble. </l>
              <l>And that my Subjects hearing it may know </l>
              <l>Thy value, and how much to thee I owe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e114990">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Let not your Majesty confound your servant </l>
              <l>With too much shame, to set so high a prise </l>
              <l>Upon so poore a service. I must blush </l>
              <l>To see such honour done so slender merit. </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-029-b"/>
              <l>My debt to you, Sir, and my Country is </l>
              <l>The bloud I live by, and the aire I breath; </l>
              <l>And when I lose 'um for so faire an object, </l>
              <l>I doe, Sir, but the duty of a Subject. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e115080">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>Few of those whom their duty binds to serve me, </l>
              <l>Can so acquit themselves, as thou hast done, </l>
              <l>Suffer then thy just praises, and at full </l>
              <l>Relate the story of thy Victory. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e115130">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, you have heard how in this urgent danger, </l>
              <l>Which put the City in so great a tumult, </l>
              <l>A company of my friends met at my fathers, </l>
              <l>Mov'd me to goe upon this enterprize, </l>
              <l>But I crave pardon of your Majesty: </l>
              <l>For daring to imploy 'um without leave, </l>
              <l>The danger was at hand, So were my friends; </l>
              <l>The hazard of my head, made me I durst not </l>
              <l>Appeare at Court, and I had rather lose </l>
              <l>My life in the defence of the whole State, </l>
              <l>Than give it up unto Cimena's plaints. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e115250">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>I must excuse the heat of thy revenge, </l>
              <l>The State defended speakes in thy defence, </l>
              <l>Henceforth Cimena moves me but in vaine, </l>
              <l>Whom if I heare 'tis but to give her comfort; </l>
              <l>But on with your relation. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e115310">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Under me </l>
              <l>This troop advanc'd with such a confidence, </l>
              <l>And so good order, that where ere they pass'd </l>
              <l>They diffus'd courage through the lookers on, </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-030-a"/>
              <l>Which so much mov'd um that although at first </l>
              <l>We number'd but five hundred, ere we reacht </l>
              <l>The Port, we were increas'd into three thousand, </l>
              <l>Two thirds of these when I ariv'd, I hid </l>
              <l>Ith' bottom of our ships, which there I found, </l>
              <l>The rest, whose number every houre increas'd, </l>
              <l>Lay close to the ground, and in deep silence past </l>
              <l>The greatest part of that faire night away. </l>
              <l>To th' guard I gave commaund to doe the like, </l>
              <l>Affirming stoutly that I had your order, </l>
              <l>For what I did. At length the glimmering star light </l>
              <l>Made us discover thirty saile comming up </l>
              <l>With a full tide, for the swolne Sea at once </l>
              <l>Powr'd both it selfe, and them into our Haven, </l>
              <l>We let 'um passe discovering none of us </l>
              <l>Ith' haven, or the wals, and this our silence </l>
              <l>Made them so confident of our surprise, </l>
              <l>That presently they landed, fiercely running </l>
              <l>To meet the ruine which awaited them. </l>
              <l>Then rose we up, having receiv'd the signall </l>
              <l>From those within our ships; </l>
              <l>Who starting up in armes, did so confound </l>
              <l>The Moores, that they were frighted ere halfe landed. </l>
              <l>They came to pillage, but they met with War </l>
              <l>At Sea and Land, we bore 'um down before us, </l>
              <l>Many we slew ith' place before they could </l>
              <l>Fall into ranke or make the least resistance, </l>
              <l>When sudainly in spight of our endeavours, </l>
              <l>Their Princes rally'd their dispersed troops, </l>
              <l>And from a shame they felt, to dye so tamely, </l>
              <l>They tooke new courage, and restor'd their ranks, </l>
              <l>With their swords drawne, making their fight on foot, </l>
              <l>Then fell the bravest of our Souldiers </l>
              <l>Mixt with their Captains, the land, the water, </l>
              <l>Their Fleet, our Haven, seem'd a feild of slaughter </l>
              <l>Where death did onely triumph; blood, and darknesse </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-030-b"/>
              <l>Cover'd the place; what had their valour beene, </l>
              <l>Who fought thus in the darke, had they been seene. </l>
              <l>I, on all sides encourag'd our own men; </l>
              <l>Some I made fall upon the foe, and others </l>
              <l>I kept from falling from us, those that came </l>
              <l>I rang'd in order, put 'um on the places </l>
              <l>Which they were to make good; but what was done </l>
              <l>We had no meanes to know, 'till the first light </l>
              <l>Shew'd us our victory, and their losse. </l>
              <l>They seeing a new supply come to our aide, </l>
              <l>Fled now more fiercely, than before they fought. </l>
              <l>They got into their ships, and cut their cables, </l>
              <l>Disorderly retreating, and not minding </l>
              <l>Whether their Kings retir'd or stay'd behind, </l>
              <l>Feare more prevailing, made them lose their duty. </l>
              <l>They came in with the flood, and with the ebb. </l>
              <l>They went away. In the meane time their Kings, </l>
              <l>And some few of their men ingag'd amongst us, </l>
              <l>Sold their lives deare enough; I bid'um yeeld, </l>
              <l>But while they had a Sword to fight, they would not, </l>
              <l>Till seeing their Souldiers fall about their feet </l>
              <l>And that alone they must defend them selves, </l>
              <l>They ask'd who was our leader, I was nam'd, </l>
              <l>They yeild themselves to me. So was this Battaile </l>
              <l>Ended for want of men to fight it out. </l>
              <l>And thus, Sir, when we are about your service </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e115980">To them D. ALONSO. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-alonso" xml:id="ep000352-e115990">
              <speaker>D. ALONSO. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, here's Cimena come to aske you justice. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e116010">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>What shall I doe? I would not have her see thee, </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-031-a"/>
              <l>In stead of thankes I must dismisse thee from me, </l>
              <l>But ere thou leav'st the Court, returne againe </l>
              <l>Unto thy Kings embraces. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e116060">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis strange, she should </l>
              <l>Pursue the man thus, whom she faine would save. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e116090">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>I'me told she is in love with him. I'le try, </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000352-e116110">Cimena ent. </stage>
              <l>Make shew as you were sad. At length Cimena, </l>
              <l>Content your self, for your desires have met </l>
              <l>With their successe. Though Roderigo's valour </l>
              <l>Ha'got the better of the Moores. Himselfe </l>
              <l>Has perish'd with the wounds he there receiv'd, </l>
              <l>Give thankes to heaven that has given you vengeance; </l>
              <l>Her colour's chang'd already. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e116190">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>But, Sir, marke </l>
              <l>Her swoundings, and by them how she betrayes </l>
              <l>The secrets of her Soule, surely she loves him. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e116230">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Is Roderigo dead then? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e116250">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>No, no, he lives, </l>
              <l>And still remaines thy true, and constant lover, </l>
              <l>Thou shalt enjoy him, take thy mirth againe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e116290">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, we as often faint with joy as sadnesse, </l>
              <l>And when excesse of that surprizes us, </l>
              <l>It soone confounds our senses. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e116330">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>Thou would'st faine </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-031-b"/>
              <l>That to do thee a courtesie we should </l>
              <l>Beleeve impossibles; but here thy sadnesse </l>
              <l>Has shew'd it selfe too plain. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e116380">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Well, Sir, you may </l>
              <l>Adde this too, if you please, to my misfortunes, </l>
              <l>And call my swoundings the effects of griefe, </l>
              <l>I must confesse, I grieved to see my selfe </l>
              <l>Rob'd of the life I sue for. If he dye </l>
              <l>Of wounds he has receiv'd for 's Countries good, </l>
              <l>My vengeance is lost, and my designes betray'd, </l>
              <l>I aske his death, but not a glorious one; </l>
              <l>I would not have him dye ith' bed of honour, </l>
              <l>But on a Scaffold, that his name may rot, </l>
              <l>And his memoriall perish, 'Tis no shame </l>
              <l>To say I love his victory, by it </l>
              <l>He has assur'd the State, and render'd me </l>
              <l>A noble sacrifice, in stead of Flowers </l>
              <l>Crown'd with victorious baies, and such a one, </l>
              <l>As I'de have offer'd to my Fathers ghost. </l>
              <l>But why, alas, am I transported so? </l>
              <l>Roderigo needs not feare what I can doe. </l>
              <l>What can a Virgins teares despis'd and scorn'd. </l>
              <l>Your Kingdome is to him a place of free </l>
              <l>Security, and he shall triumph over me </l>
              <l>As 'ore his enemies, the bloud oth' Moores </l>
              <l>Shall choake up justice here, which must be made </l>
              <l>A Trophee to the Victors crimes; Whilest I </l>
              <l>Amongst the rest, adorne his victory. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e116640">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>Sweet heart y'are too much hurri'd with your passions. </l>
              <l>We, when we render Justice use to cast </l>
              <l>Each thing in ballance, Roderigo kill'd </l>
              <l>Thy Father, but he gave the first offence. </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-032-a"/>
              <l>Equity binds me then, to shew some sweetnesse </l>
              <l>To the first injur'd. But before thou accuse him, </l>
              <l>Aske counsaile of thy heart. Of which hee's master. </l>
              <l>I'me sure thy love, secretly thankes thy King, </l>
              <l>Whose favour keepes so brave a Lover for thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e116740">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>For me! my Enemy the Author of </l>
              <l>My miscries, the murderer of my father. </l>
              <l>Is my just suite so slighted that I'me thought </l>
              <l>To be oblig'd because I am not heard? </l>
              <l>Sir, since my teares cannot obtaine it of you, </l>
              <l>Let the sword, I beseech you, give me justice </l>
              <l>By that I'me injur'd and by that I crave </l>
              <l>To be reveng'd. Of all your Cavaliers </l>
              <l>I aske his head, to him that brings it me, </l>
              <l>As to the Conquerour I give my selfe, </l>
              <l>The Combat ended, he shall be my husband, </l>
              <l>This, I beseech your Majesty may be publish'd </l>
              <l>By your authority. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e116880">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>This Countries custome, </l>
              <l>More ancient than good, under the colour </l>
              <l>Of punishing unjust attempts, has rob'd </l>
              <l>The state of its best Souldiers, and often </l>
              <l>The successe does not answer the intent, </l>
              <l>The guilty scape, and kill the innocent; </l>
              <l>I must dispense with Roderigo's bloud, </l>
              <l>It is more pretious to me, than so slightly </l>
              <l>To be expos'd to hazard, though his spirit </l>
              <l>Forc'd him to doe an outrage, yet in freeing </l>
              <l>His Country from the Moores, h'has freed himselfe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e117000">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>How, Sir, for him must you reverse your lawes, </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-032-b"/>
              <l>Which have so often been observ'd? what will </l>
              <l>The people, or the tongue of envy say, </l>
              <l>Hearing he lives by your protection? </l>
              <l>And that it only serves him for a colour </l>
              <l>To hide his cowardise. These are favors, Sir, </l>
              <l>Which bring dishonor, with'um to the takers, </l>
              <l>The Count durst doe a wrong, my Sonne durst punish, </l>
              <l>Let him maintaine the honour hee has won. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e117100">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>Since you will have it so, let it be done, </l>
              <l>But if Roderigo be expos'd to all </l>
              <l>That will come in to fight for such a prize, </l>
              <l>He must be sure to want no enemies. </l>
              <l>I will have onely one t'incounter him. </l>
              <l>Choose whom you will, Cimena, and choose wisely, </l>
              <l>But after this, urge me to nothing farther. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-sancho" xml:id="ep000352-e117180">
              <speaker>D. SANCHO. </speaker>
              <l>An't please your Majesty to let the lists </l>
              <l>Be opened, I shall be th' undertaker; </l>
              <l>Madam, you know your promise, I beseech you </l>
              <l>Let me obtaine the grace to be your Champion. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e117230">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>What say you, Cimena, shall he be the Man? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e117250">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, I have promised him. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e117270">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>Be ready than to morrow. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e117290">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>Defer it not so long, Sir; </l>
              <l>A man of courage is at all times ready. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-033-a"/>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e117320">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>Shall he no sooner be returned from one, </l>
              <l>But he must enter on another fight? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e117350">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>He has tane breath, Sir, in recounting it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e117370">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>How ere, an houre or two let him repose, </l>
              <l>But lest I should be thought to countenance </l>
              <l>Proceedings of this bloudy nature, neither </l>
              <l>My selfe nor any of my Court shall see it perform'd, </l>
              <l>Doe you looke to it, and take care that both </l>
              <l>Present themselves, as befits men of armes, </l>
              <l>The Combat done, bring me the Conquerour, </l>
              <l>I meane my selfe to give him to Cimena. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e117460">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>That were t'impose too hard a law upon me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e117480">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>Thy love dares not avow this thy complaint, </l>
              <l>If Roderigo conquer, thou must have him, </l>
              <l>Never dispute my sentence or repine, </l>
              <l>Who ere is Victor, I will make him thine. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="ep000352-e117530">
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000352-e117540">
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-033-b"/>
            <head>ACT. V. SCENE I. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e117550">D. RODERIGO. CIMENA. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e117560">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>WHat Roderigo, in the open day! </l>
              <l>Whence comes this boldnesse? doe you meane t'undoe </l>
              <l>Mee, and mine honour? Fy, retire your selfe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e117600">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Madame, I goe to dye, and therefore come </l>
              <l>Before my death, to take my last farewell, </l>
              <l>My love does owe you this: and my thrall'd heart </l>
              <l>Dares not depart your Kingdome without leave. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e117650">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>You goe to dye? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e117670">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Nay, more, I run; as soone </l>
              <l>As I have tane my leave, the Count's reveng'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e117700">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>You goe to dye! And is Don Sancho then </l>
              <l>A man so terrible, that you need feare him? </l>
              <l>Who has made you so weake? or him so valiant? </l>
              <l>Roderigo goes to fight, and thinkes himselfe </l>
              <l>Already dead. He that nor fear'd the Moores, </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-034-a"/>
              <l>Nor yet my Father, going to encounter </l>
              <l>Don Sancho, trembles at it. Does your spirit </l>
              <l>Fayle you at greatest need? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e117790">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis not to the Combat </l>
              <l>That I goe now, but to my punishment. </l>
              <l>For when you seeke my death, my love cannot </l>
              <l>Defend a life against you. My heart is still </l>
              <l>The same, but not my arme, when it should guard </l>
              <l>That which displeases you. This night already </l>
              <l>Had beene my last, if for my private quarrell </l>
              <l>The fight had beene: But since 'twas for the King, </l>
              <l>His People, and my Countrye, had I left </l>
              <l>My selfe defencelesse, I'de betray'd them all: </l>
              <l>I must confesse, I did not hate my life </l>
              <l>So much as with false treachery to part from't. </l>
              <l>Now, since no interest but mine owne is in it, </l>
              <l>And you demaund my death, I accept your sentence, </l>
              <l>For which y'have made choise of another hand. </l>
              <l>(It seemes I not deserv'd to dye by yours) </l>
              <l>I shall not goe to exchange blow, for blow, </l>
              <l>I owe him more respect that fights for you </l>
              <l>And since it is your honour which hee fights for, </l>
              <l>I'le open him my brest, in his, adoring </l>
              <l>Your hand, from which I'le welcome my destruction. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e118010">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>If the just violence of a fatall duty, </l>
              <l>Which makes me to pursue thee 'gainst my will, </l>
              <l>Prescribe unto thy love so hard a law, </l>
              <l>That thou wilt not defend thy selfe 'gainst him </l>
              <l>That fights for me. Take head least thou forget </l>
              <l>That both thy life, and glory fall together, </l>
              <l>And howsoever Roderigo has liv'd </l>
              <l>Being slaine, he will be thought a vanquisht man. </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-034-b"/>
              <l>Honour was dearer once then I was to you, </l>
              <l>When in my Fathers bloud you imbru'd your hands, </l>
              <l>It made you then in spight of your affection </l>
              <l>Renounce the hope of ere injoying me; </l>
              <l>But now you value it so little that </l>
              <l>You care not who it is that conquers you. </l>
              <l>See how unseasonable your vertue is, </l>
              <l>Why were you valiant once &amp; are not now? </l>
              <l>Were you so onely to doe me an outrage? </l>
              <l>Or will you be so cruell to my father, </l>
              <l>That having conquer'd him, you will submit </l>
              <l>Your selfe to any hand. No Roderigo </l>
              <l>Defend thy honor, though thou slight thy life. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e118230">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Mine honor cannot need any defence </l>
              <l>More than it has already. He that could </l>
              <l>Defeat the Moores, and kill the Count of Gormas, </l>
              <l>Has not an enemy besides to feare. </l>
              <l>No, no, Roderigo know's what ere you thinke, </l>
              <l>How in this fight to die and save his honour, </l>
              <l>That none shall dare to thinke he wanted courage, </l>
              <l>Onely they'le say he did adore Cimena. </l>
              <l>He would not live, having deserv'd her hate, </l>
              <l>How he gave way unto the cruell fate </l>
              <l>which forc'd his Mistresse to pursue his death. </l>
              <l>Shee ask'd his head, and his great heart conceiv'd </l>
              <l>He should commit a crime, if he deny'd it. </l>
              <l>T'acquit his honour he renounc'd his love, </l>
              <l>T'acquit his Mistresse he renounc'd his life. </l>
              <l>Thus shall you see my glory in this Combat </l>
              <l>Shine more than ere it did. My willing death </l>
              <l>Shall have this honour, that no Man but I </l>
              <l>Could for the wrong done to you satisfy. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-035-a"/>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e118430">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Since nor thy love, nor honour can prevaile </l>
              <l>To hold thee from thy ruine, deare Roderigo, </l>
              <l>If ere I lov'd thee, I conjure thee now </l>
              <l>To doe thy best, if for no other end </l>
              <l>To free me from Don Sancho, let me not </l>
              <l>Be given up to th' object of my loathing. </l>
              <l>What shall I say more? goe defend thy selfe, </l>
              <l>And if thy love be not congeal'd to ice, </l>
              <l>Be Victor where Cimena is the price, </l>
              <l>Adieu! this last word makes me blush for shame. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e118540">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Is there an Enemy now, that I can feare? </l>
              <l>Moores, and Castilians, or what ere you be, </l>
              <l>Whom Aragon, or Spaine thinkes valiant, </l>
              <l>Appeare, and make one army of your selves, </l>
              <l>My soule encouraged thus shall throw me on you. </l>
              <l>For so sweet hopes, what is't I dare not meet with? </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="ep000352-e118610">
            <pb xml:id="ep000352-035-b"/>
            <head>SCENE II. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e118620">INFANTA. LEONORA. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e118630">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>IS it to me you come now Leonora? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-leonora" xml:id="ep000352-e118650">
              <speaker>LEONORA. </speaker>
              <l>Madame, I come to testifie the joy </l>
              <l>I feele, to see your heart at rest. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e118680">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>My heart? </l>
              <l>Can rest come to a heart that's fill'd with griefes? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-leonora" xml:id="ep000352-e118710">
              <speaker>LEONORA. </speaker>
              <l>If love doe live on hope, and dye with it, </l>
              <l>Roderigo cannot trouble you any longer, </l>
              <l>You know the Combat where he is ingag'd </l>
              <l>By his Cimena, there he must or dye, </l>
              <l>Or be her husband, but what ever happen, </l>
              <l>Whether he live, or dye, your hope is dead. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e118780">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>But how canst thou assure me it is dead, </l>
              <l>If upon these conditions Roderigo </l>
              <l>Doe entertaine the Combat, have not I </l>
              <l>Inventions enough to breake it off? </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-036-a"/>
              <l>Love the sweet Author of my punishment, </l>
              <l>Can teach the wits of lovers many slights. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-leonora" xml:id="ep000352-e118850">
              <speaker>LEONORA. </speaker>
              <l>Hope you to breed a discontent between'um, </l>
              <l>Which a Fathers death cannot. Cimena shewes </l>
              <l>By her conduct of this affaire, that hate </l>
              <l>Causes not her pursuite, 'tis true sh' has got </l>
              <l>The Combat graunted, but to take her part </l>
              <l>Whom has she chosen, not an expert man, </l>
              <l>Or one already famous for his actions. </l>
              <l>Don Sancho serves her turne, who till this time </l>
              <l>Did never put on armes; she loves in him </l>
              <l>His small experience. This her suddaine choise </l>
              <l>Must make you see, she sought for such a Combat </l>
              <l>As might enforce her duty to be silent, </l>
              <l>And yet assure Roderigo's conquest. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e118990">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>I see it well enough, and yet my heart </l>
              <l>Strives with Cimena's, who shal most adore him, </l>
              <l>What had I best resolve on, Leonora? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-leonora" xml:id="ep000352-e119030">
              <speaker>LEONORA. </speaker>
              <l>Madam, bethink your selfe of whom y'are borne, </l>
              <l>A King, heav'n owes you, and you love a subject. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e119060">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>No, no, my thoughts are off from their first object, </l>
              <l>I love not Roderigo as a Gentleman, </l>
              <l>Hee that I love now, is the Valiant CID, </l>
              <l>The Maister of two Kings. And yet I meane </l>
              <l>T'orecome my selfe, not for the feare of blame, </l>
              <l>But that I won't disturbe so faire a flame, </l>
              <l>And though they would now crown him, yet I should not </l>
              <l>Resume the guift which I have giv'n another </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-036-b"/>
              <l>Then since thou saist Roderigoe's Victory </l>
              <l>Is certaine, let's goe give him to Cimena. </l>
              <l>And thou that know'st how far my love has run, </l>
              <l>Come, see me finish what I have begun. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="ep000352-e119190">
            <head>SCENE III. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e119200">CIMENA. ELVIRA. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e119210">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>WHat shall I doe Elvira? all my hopes </l>
              <l>Are lost, and I have nothing left but feares, </l>
              <l>I dare not give consent to my owne wishes, </l>
              <l>I've caus'd two Rivals to take armes for me, </l>
              <l>What ever happens. Sorrow is my lot; </l>
              <l>For thinke the best, I can of fate obtaine, </l>
              <l>My Father's unreveng'd or lover slaine. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e119290">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>From both sides you will find reason of comfort, </l>
              <l>Either you have revenge or Roderigo </l>
              <l>How ever destiny disposes of you </l>
              <l>It saves your honour, and provides y'a husband. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e119340">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>What? the object of my hate, or of my anger? </l>
              <l>Roderigo's, or my Fathers murderer, </l>
              <l>From this or that, I must expect a husband </l>
              <l>Dy'd in the bloud of him I held most deare, </l>
              <l>I feare the issue worse than any death. </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-037-a"/>
              <l>Goe vengeance, or my love that troublest me, </l>
              <l>Thou hast not sweets I'me sure to make me amends, </l>
              <l>And thou the powerfull mover of that fate </l>
              <l>Which does me all this violence, determine </l>
              <l>This Combat equally, without advantage, </l>
              <l>That neither be the Victor, or the Vanquisht. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e119460">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>That were to handle you with too much cruelty, </l>
              <l>If when the fight were done, you should be bound </l>
              <l>A new to demand justice, and neare leave, </l>
              <l>With rigour to pursue the man you love. </l>
              <l>No, it were better that his unmatch'd valour </l>
              <l>Should get him victory, and silence you, </l>
              <l>And that the King, according to his law </l>
              <l>Should force you to comply with your owne wishes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e119550">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Doest thinke though he be Conquerour that I will </l>
              <l>Yeeld my selfe his? my duty is too strong, </l>
              <l>And my losse over great. He may o'recome </l>
              <l>Don Sancho easily, but not so soone </l>
              <l>The glory of Cimena. Though a Monarch </l>
              <l>Have promis'd me unto his victory </l>
              <l>Mine honour, (rather than I'le be his prize) </l>
              <l>Shall raise him up a thousand enemies. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e119640">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>Take heed, lest heav'n for this strange pride of yours </l>
              <l>Suffer you not to be reveng'd at all. </l>
              <l>What? meane you to refuse this happinesse </l>
              <l>That you may when you please sit down with honour? </l>
              <l>What is't you would pretend? what can you hope? </l>
              <l>Will your Lovers death restore your Father to you </l>
              <l>Or is your Fathers death so small a mischiefe, </l>
              <l>That you'd heape up losse on losse, griefe upon griefe. </l>
              <l>Well, doe, continue in this stubborne humour. </l>
              <l>You scarce deserve the man they 'ave destin'd for ye </l>
              <l>And heaven being weary of its too much favour, </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-037-b"/>
              <l>In stead of him, will wed you to Don Sancho. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e119770">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>The griefes Elvira, I sustaine already, </l>
              <l>Need not thy fatall augury to augment 'um, </l>
              <l>I would, if possible, avoid them both, </l>
              <l>If not, Roderigo has my best of wishes. </l>
              <l>Not that my love inclines me more to him, </l>
              <l>But lest he fayling, I should be Don Sancho's. </l>
              <l>The thought of that, makes me to wish him well. </l>
              <l>What's this Elvira? See 'tis done already. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="ep000352-e119860">
            <head>SCENE IV. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e119870">D. SANCHO. CIMENA. ELVIRA. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-sancho" xml:id="ep000352-e119880">
              <speaker>D. SANCHO. </speaker>
              <l>AT your feet, Madame, I present this sword. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e119900">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>What that yet reaking with Roderigo's bloud? </l>
              <l>Traytor, how dar'st thou come into my sight, </l>
              <l>When thou hast ravish'd from me, all I lov'd? </l>
              <l>Shine now at full my love, thou need'st not feare, </l>
              <l>My Father's satisfi'd. One onely blow, </l>
              <l>has to mine honour giv'n security, </l>
              <l>To my soule despaire, to my love liberty. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-sancho" xml:id="ep000352-e119980">
              <speaker>D. SANCHO. </speaker>
              <l>Heare me with better temper. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e120000">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Dar'st thou yet </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-038-a"/>
              <l>Speake to me? Cursed murderer of that Heros </l>
              <l>Which I doe most adore. Goe, thou hast slaine him </l>
              <l>Perfidiously, for otherwise that man </l>
              <l>Could never fall by such a hand as thine. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-elvira" xml:id="ep000352-e120060">
              <speaker>ELVIRA. </speaker>
              <l>But heare him, Madame. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e120080">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>What wouldst thou have me heare? </l>
              <l>Can I doubt, when my eyes are satisfied, </l>
              <l>I have obtain'd the mischiefe which I sought for, </l>
              <l>And my just suit has had too good successe, </l>
              <l>Pardon deare love, its bloudy cruelty. </l>
              <l>Thinke though a lover, yet I was a daughter. </l>
              <l>If on thy bloud I have reveng'd my Father. </l>
              <l>For thy revenge I will exhaust my owne, </l>
              <l>My soule has nothing now, that should retaine it, </l>
              <l>It shall goe after thine, to aske it pardon. </l>
              <l>And thou that think'st t'obtaine me by his death, </l>
              <l>Disloyall minister of my cruell fate, </l>
              <l>Hope nothing at my hands. Thou hast done me </l>
              <l>No service, onely hastned on my death. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-sancho" xml:id="ep000352-e120230">
              <speaker>D. SANCHO. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis a strange passion will not give me hearing. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e120250">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>What would'st thou have me heare thee, whilst with boasting </l>
              <l>Thou paint'st out to me my owne fatall crime, </l>
              <l>And his misfortunes, that thy cruell story </l>
              <l>May kill me in thy sight. No, I can dye </l>
              <l>Without thy help. My soule can find out death, </l>
              <l>Instructed by no ayd but her owne mischiefes. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e120320">
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-038-b"/>To them The KING. D. DIEGO. D. ARIAS. D. ALONSO. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e120330">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>SIr, I need not now dissemble any longer </l>
              <l>What never art of mine could hide from you </l>
              <l>I lov'd, you know, yet to revenge my Father </l>
              <l>I would proscribe the head I held so deare, </l>
              <l>By that your Majesty might easily see, </l>
              <l>I meant my love should give place to my duty. </l>
              <l>In fine Roderigoe's dead. His death has chang'd </l>
              <l>Her, who was once his mortall enemy </l>
              <l>To an afflicted lover. That revenge </l>
              <l>I to my Father ought, and to my love </l>
              <l>These teares which now I shed; Don Sancho has </l>
              <l>In taking of my part quite ruin'd me, </l>
              <l>And yet for doing so I'me made his prize. </l>
              <l>Sir, if kind pitty ever mov'd a King, </l>
              <l>Now of your grace revoke this cruell law, </l>
              <l>Though he have slaine the man I lov'd so dearely, </l>
              <l>I'le give him all I have for his reward, </l>
              <l>So he will leave me to my selfe, and that </l>
              <l>I may bewaile (the time I have to live) </l>
              <l>My Father, and my Lover, in a Cloister. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-diego" xml:id="ep000352-e120540">
              <speaker>D. DIEGO. </speaker>
              <l>Now you perceive she loves, Sir, and not thinkes </l>
              <l>'Tis such a crime t' a vow her lawfull love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e120570">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>Sweet heart mistake not, Roderigo lives </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-039-a"/>
              <l>Don Sancho has made thee a false report. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-sancho" xml:id="ep000352-e120600">
              <speaker>D. SANCHO. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, not by me, but by her too much heat </l>
              <l>Shee was deceiv'd: For had she given me leave; </l>
              <l>I should have told her, that her noble Lover, </l>
              <l>When he disarm'd me, bade me banish feare, </l>
              <l>For that (sai'd he) I'de rather leave the conquest </l>
              <l>Uncertaine, than I'de spill a drop of bloud </l>
              <l>That's ventur'd for Cimena, but since I </l>
              <l>Am by my duty call'd to attend the King, </l>
              <l>Goe you and entertaine her in my stead, </l>
              <l>And at her feet offer your life and sword. </l>
              <l>Which when I came to doe, the sword deceiv'd her, </l>
              <l>With which seeing me returne, she thought that I </l>
              <l>Had beene the Victor. Presently her anger </l>
              <l>Betray'd her love, with such impatience </l>
              <l>That I had not a minutes audience. </l>
              <l>For my part though I am a vanquish'd man, </l>
              <l>And though the interest of my love be great </l>
              <l>Yet I repute my selfe in this my losse </l>
              <l>To be a gainer, loving my distresse </l>
              <l>Which brings so faire a flame, so good successe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e120810">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>You must not be asham'd of such a love </l>
              <l>Cimena, or seeke meanes to disavow it, </l>
              <l>Your honour's disingag'd, your duty quitted, </l>
              <l>Your Father satisfied; what would you more? </l>
              <l>Must you still put Roderigo in new danger, </l>
              <l>You see heaven otherwise disposes of him. </l>
              <l>And since that it has done so much for him, </l>
              <l>Doe you too something for your selfe, and take </l>
              <l>Him for your husband that I offer you, </l>
              <l>And whom I know you love. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000352-e120920">
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-039-b"/>To them INFANTA. RODERIGO. LEONORA. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000352-infanta" xml:id="ep000352-e120930">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <l>COme Cimena, </l>
              <l>Drye thy eyes: And receive with a glad heart </l>
              <l>This noble Conquerour, from thy Princesse's hand. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e120970">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>Great Sir, be not offended if before you, </l>
              <l>The duty which I owe to love, doe cast me </l>
              <l>Here at her feet. I come not to demand </l>
              <l>The prize which I have won, but once more yet </l>
              <l>To offer you my life. My love shall not </l>
              <l>Or plead the combats law, or the Kings will, </l>
              <l>If all that's done cannot appease your anger, </l>
              <l>Tell me what meanes is left to satisfie. </l>
              <l>Must I encounter yet a thousand Rivals, </l>
              <l>Travaile from one end of the Earth to th' other </l>
              <l>Or force a Camp my selfe, or rout an Army, </l>
              <l>If at length I may expiate my crime, </l>
              <l>I shall attempt all this: But if your honour </l>
              <l>Be still inexorable, and nothing can </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-040-a"/>
              <l>Appease it but my death; Behold my head </l>
              <l>I cast it at your feet. Take it your selfe, </l>
              <l>And arme no other hand for your revenge, </l>
              <l>Since none but yours can do't. Yet let my death </l>
              <l>Be all my punishment, and let me not </l>
              <l>Be banish'd from your memory, but say </l>
              <l>If any time you call to mind my paine </l>
              <l>Had he not lov'd me, he had not been slaine, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-cimena" xml:id="ep000352-e121200">
              <speaker>CIMENA. </speaker>
              <l>Rise Roderigo. Sir, I must needs say </l>
              <l>My love has shew'd it selfe too much, for me </l>
              <l>Now to deny it. Roderigo has </l>
              <l>Such vertues, as I know not how to hate. </l>
              <l>And you're my King. I cannot but obey you, </l>
              <l>But is there here any appearance of </l>
              <l>A Marriage, if it be, it is a sad one, </l>
              <l>That one day should begin, and end my mourning, </l>
              <l>That having lay'd my Father in his grave, </l>
              <l>I should lay Roderigo in my bed: </l>
              <l>That were to hold intelligence with's murtherer, </l>
              <l>And soyle my honour with eternall shame. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e121330">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>Time often makes that lawfull, which at present </l>
              <l>Seemes not to be so. Roderigo, has won thee, </l>
              <l>And his thou must be. But though his valour </l>
              <l>Have made you his, yet I should doe you wrong </l>
              <l>So soone to give him the reward he fought for. </l>
              <l>Take if you will a yeare, to end your mourning. </l>
              <l>In the meane time Roderigo shall take armes, </l>
              <l>And having under his command my Army, </l>
              <l>Shall carry back the War unto the Moores </l>
              <l>Which they brought hither, that they all may tremble </l>
              <l>At this brave name of CID, which they have given thee </l>
              <l>They've call'd thee Lord already, and they would </l>
              <l>Make thee their King. But let not (Roderigo) </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000352-040-b"/>
              <l>Thy great exploits, take off thy loyalty; </l>
              <l>Returne, if possible, more worthy of her, </l>
              <l>And let thy deeds set such a price upon thee, </l>
              <l>That she may court thy Marriage as an honour. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-roderigo" xml:id="ep000352-e121510">
              <speaker>RODERIGO. </speaker>
              <l>For my Cimena, Sir, and for your service, </l>
              <l>What can you bid me doe I won't accomplish? </l>
              <l>And though I hardly can endure her absence, </l>
              <l>Yet are the hopes you give sufficient happinesse. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000352-king" xml:id="ep000352-e121560">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <l>Rely upon thy valour and my promise, </l>
              <l>And now thou hast thy Mistresse heart already, </l>
              <l>This point of honour (which is the last thing) </l>
              <l>Let time o're come, thy valour, and thy King. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="supplied_by_editor">
        <head>Notes, typically marginal, from the original text</head>
        <div corresp="A19346-e100170" xml:id="ep000352-e100170-n">
          <head>Notes for div A19346-e100170</head>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="license" xml:id="ep000352-e121630">
        <pb xml:id="ep000352-041-a"/>
        <p>THis Tragicomedy, called, The Valiant Cid, translated out of French, as it was acted before the King and Queene at Court, may be printed. </p>
        <closer>
          <signed>HENRY HERBERT. </signed>
          <dateline>
            <date>Janu. 12. 1637. </date>
          </dateline>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="imprimatur" xml:id="ep000352-e121690">
        <pb xml:id="ep000352-041-b"/>
        <p>Imprimatur. </p>
        <closer>
          <signed>THO. WYKES. </signed>
          <dateline>
            <date>Jan. 26. 1637. </date>
          </dateline>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div cert="high"
              type="illustration"
              xml:id="ep000352-e121750"
              xml:lang="fr">
        <pb xml:id="ep000352-042-a"/>
        <p>
          <figure>
            <p>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENCE </p>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <pb xml:id="ep000352-042-b"/>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
