<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000511" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Thyestes a tragedy acted at the Theatre-Royal by Their Majesties servants / written by Mr. Crown.</title>
        <author>
<!--Crowne, John-->
          <persName>
            <forename>John</forename>
            <surname>Crowne</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A35299.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <p>
            This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is available for reuse, according to the terms of
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>
            . The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
          </p>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull>
              <titleStmt>
                <title>Thyestes a tragedy acted at the Theatre-Royal by Their Majesties servants / written by Mr. Crown.</title>
                <author>Crown, Mr. (John), 1640?-1712.</author>
                <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus, ca. 4 B.C.-65 A.D. Thyestes.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[6], 56 p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Printed for R. Bently and M. Magnes ...,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                <date>1681.</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>An adaptation of Seneca's tragedy.</note>
                <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc/>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000511-e10">
        <pb xml:id="ep000511-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000511-001-b"/>
        <p>THYESTES A TRAGEDY. Acted at the Theatre-Royal, By their MAJESTIES SERVANTS </p>
        <p>Written by Mr. CROWN. </p>
        <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed for </hi>R. Bently and M. Magnes, in Russel-street, in Covent-Garden <hi>near the </hi>Piazza's, <foreign xml:lang="lat">Anno Domini, MDCLXXX </foreign>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="song" xml:id="ep000511-e120">
        <pb xml:id="ep000511-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000511-002-b"/>
        <head>The Song at Atreus his Banquet. </head>
        <lg n="1">
          <head>1. </head>
          <l>A Lovely pair endowed by Fate, </l>
          <l>With Loves and Beauties whole Estate; </l>
          <l>At the sweetest game have been, </l>
          <l>You know, you know what I mean; </l>
          <l>You know, you know what I mean. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg n="2">
          <head>2. </head>
          <l>For Kisses first the Lovers play'd, </l>
          <l>The pleasant sport provok'd the Maid </l>
          <l>To that height, she growing mad, </l>
          <l>Had almost play'd for all she had; </l>
          <l>But the Maid was not so mad. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg n="3">
          <head>3. </head>
          <l>She'll ask her Father's leave she swears, </l>
          <l>And then she'll play for what he dares, </l>
          <l>Leave is had, and to't they go; </l>
          <l>What I mean, you know, you know. </l>
          <l>What I mean, you know, you know. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg n="4">
          <head>4▪ </head>
          <l>To deeper Play, they now begin, </l>
          <l>The happy young man's hand is in, </l>
          <l>Both have stak'd down all their joys, </l>
          <l>But she loses, for she cryes: </l>
          <l>See! she cryes! oh! see she cryes! </l>
        </lg>
        <lg n="5">
          <head>5 </head>
          <l>But now the Bride, oh! tempting sight! </l>
          <l>Has won her lapful of delight, </l>
          <l>To deeper Play, she urges on; </l>
          <l>But, alas! his stakes are gone, </l>
          <l>But, alas! his stakes are gone. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg n="6">
          <head>6 </head>
          <l>And now she locks her Cabinet, </l>
          <l>But he'll play another set, </l>
          <l>When his hand again is in, </l>
          <l>You know, you know what I mean, </l>
          <l>You know, you know what I mean. </l>
        </lg>
        <pb xml:id="ep000511-003-a"/>
        <stage xml:id="ep000511-e560">A Chorus of Priests. </stage>
        <lg>
          <l>Goddess Minerva, Wise, Austere, </l>
          <l>Sober, Valiant, Chast, and Fair, </l>
          <l>We bring thee here, </l>
          <l>A Kind, a Young, a Lovely Pair; </l>
          <l>Who beg thy leave to joyn their hands, </l>
          <l>In Chast and Holy Marriage-bands. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>1 Pr. Oh! Let him be active Fire, </l>
          <l>Ever burning in desire, </l>
          <l>Ever free </l>
          <l>From any smoak of Jealousy. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Let her be water, soft to all his touches, </l>
          <l>Ever hot when he approaches, </l>
          <l>When he takes away his Eye, </l>
          <l>Even froze with Chastity: </l>
          <l>Long let love possess her heart, </l>
          <l>And ne're let Love and Beauty Part. </l>
        </lg>
        <stage xml:id="ep000511-e780">The First Chorus Sung over again. </stage>
      </div>
      <div type="prologue" xml:id="ep000511-e790">
        <pb xml:id="ep000511-003-b"/>
        <head>PROLOGUE. </head>
        <sp xml:id="ep000511-e810">
          <l>WHat cursed Planet o're this Play house raigns, </l>
          <l>Palsies, and Gouts, are all the Old mens gains; </l>
          <l>And we young men, e're we have learnt to speak, </l>
          <l>Have learnt the Old mens cursed trick, to Break. </l>
          <l>Some went to Scotland; they had cunning Plots </l>
          <l>Who went to sell the English wit to Scots. </l>
          <l>Scots in that traffique excell you I fear, </l>
          <l>Witness their Covenant they sold you so dear: </l>
          <l>So those young men are come as wealthy home, </l>
          <l>As they return devout who go for Rome: </l>
          <l>But still we are followed with a cursed blast, </l>
          <l>For in the harbours mouth we have split our Mast, </l>
          <l>And such Poetique Jewels perish here, </l>
          <l>As might be worn with pride in any Ear; </l>
          <l>Our massy treasure we shall ne're buy up. </l>
          <l>But live on poor slight stuff that floats atop. </l>
          <l>To day like cunning Romish Priests we try </l>
          <l>If we can awe you, with an antient lye. </l>
          <l>Some say you must not dare to pass a doom, </l>
          <l>On what has been admir'd by Greece and Rome. </l>
          <l>You upstart Sectaries of wit cry down </l>
          <l>What has for twenty ages had renown? </l>
          <l>The world will ask (in scorn of your dispraise) </l>
          <l>Where was your wit, Sirs, before Shakespears days? </l>
          <l>No matter where, we'l say y'have excellent sence; </l>
          <l>If you will please to let us get your pence. </l>
          <l>We like the Pope regard not much your praise, </l>
          <l>He Tickets sells for Heaven, and we for Plays; </l>
          <l>〈…〉 ll but to make advantage of the Keys; </l>
          <l>〈…〉 y for your Tickets, and go where you please. </l>
        </sp>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="ep000511-e1180">
        <pb xml:id="ep000511-004-a"/>
        <head>The Persons of the Tragedy. </head>
        <list>
          <item>ATreus King of Argos. </item>
          <item>Thyestes Brother of Atreus. </item>
          <item>Philisthenes Son to Thyestes, in love with Antigone. </item>
          <item>Peneus an old Philosopher, once Tutour and Governour to Atreus. </item>
          <item>Aerope Wife of Atreus. </item>
          <item>Antigone. his Daughter in love with Philisthenes. </item>
        </list>
        <p>SCENE Atreus his Court. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="play" xml:id="ep000511-e1430">
        <pb n="1" xml:id="ep000511-004-b"/>
        <head>THYESTES A TRAGEDY </head>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="ep000511-e1450">
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000511-e1460">
            <head>ACT I. SCENE I. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e1480">Thunder: The Ghost of <hi>Tantalus, Megaera. SCENE </hi>the Palace. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e1500">
              <speaker>Tan. </speaker>
              <l>THOU merciless, detested, horrid Fury: </l>
              <l>To what new Colonies of mocking Fruits, </l>
              <l>And vanishing false Streams, dost thou transplant </l>
              <l>The Hungry Thirsty Shade of Tantalus? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e1570">
              <speaker>Me. </speaker>
              <l>To Colonies, where thou shalt eat and drink </l>
              <l>Thy fill in quiet. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e1610">
              <speaker>Tan. </speaker>
              <l>Wilt thou clothe me then </l>
              <l>In Flesh and Blood again? For had I them </l>
              <l>Thou woud'st permit me to devour my self. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e1660">
              <speaker>Me. </speaker>
              <l>I lash thee hither, to devour thy self; </l>
              <l>Monsters I mean descended from thy self. </l>
              <l>Thou lazy Ghost hast done thy work by halves: </l>
              <l>I chas'd thee hither once, to fill thy House </l>
              <l>With Incest, Treason, Blood. Incest I see, </l>
              <l>Brother whor'd Brother's Wife: Treason I see, </l>
              <l>Brother depos'd his Brother from his Throne; </l>
              <l>But where's the Blood? I see no blood at all, </l>
              <l>Th' incestuous Traytour is in Exile safe. </l>
              <pb n="2" xml:id="ep000511-005-a"/>
              <l>Let me have Murders, such as all my Snakes </l>
              <l>May rear themselves to see, and hiss Applause. </l>
              <l>The Father eat the Nephew he begot; </l>
              <l>The Bastard Nephew go out of the World, </l>
              <l>A way more horrid than he came into it▪ </l>
              <l>Let the vast Villany of thy damn'd Race </l>
              <l>Reach, and confound the Heavens; make the Night </l>
              <l>Engender with the Day; the groaning Day </l>
              <l>Bring forth Gygantick darkness at full Noon, </l>
              <l>Such as for hours may pluck the Sun from Heaven. </l>
              <l>At this black Feast, I'le let thee be a Guest, </l>
              <l>Devour thy fill in quiet, when thy Cup </l>
              <l>Flowes with the Blood of thy incestuous Race, </l>
              <l>Nothing shall dare to snatch it from thy Lips. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e1910">
              <speaker>Tan. </speaker>
              <l>Return me to my dark dire Prison in Hell, </l>
              <l>And all you tortur'd Spirits hug your pains; </l>
              <l>Nor, might you be releas'd, return to Life; </l>
              <l>For Earth in Sin and Torment exceeds Hell: </l>
              <l>Finish thy execrable work thy self, </l>
              <l>The pain is more than I am bound to bear. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e1990">
              <speaker>Me. </speaker>
              <l>Look'st thou for Laws and Equity in Hell? </l>
              <l>Thy Sword was all thy Reason upon Earth, </l>
              <l>And this is ours. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e2040">
              <speaker>Tan. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! hold thy gnawing Whip, </l>
              <l>I will obey. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e2080">
              <speaker>Me. </speaker>
              <l>Enter the Palace then; </l>
              <l>Here with thy Son didst thou once feast thy Gods, </l>
              <l>With thy great Grand-Sons now Feast all the Furies. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e2130">[The Scene is drawn, Atreus asleep. </stage>
              <l>Behold a Shadow of thy pains in Hell </l>
              <l>Heir'd, by thy Grand-son Atreus upon Earth; </l>
              <l>Night seems to offer him her shady Fruit, </l>
              <l>And squeeze her Balmy slumbers in his Eyes, </l>
              <l>And when he catches at 'em, she pulls back, </l>
              <l>So from the Evening's Valley to the Morning Hill </l>
              <l>He rowls his time, as Sysiphus his Stone. </l>
              <l>The trembling Shade obeys, and pours himself </l>
              <l>Into the Palace, which shakes more than he. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e2260">
                <hi>[Ex. </hi>Tan. </stage>
              <l>Nature's diseas'd and scar'd at his approach; </l>
              <l>Trees shed their Leaves, as poyson'd men their Hair; </l>
              <pb n="3" xml:id="ep000511-005-b"/>
              <l>Streams crowd into their Mother-Fountain's Womb; </l>
              <l>The Seas that hung on the Corinthian Neck, </l>
              <l>Like Rival Queens in endless enterview, </l>
              <l>Swell'd with Convulsion Fits, run foaming back, </l>
              <l>Nor can be held by all their watry Train; </l>
              <l>And in their fright miscarry of new Isles. </l>
              <l>Winds scowre the Air like midnight Revellers, </l>
              <l>Mad with strong Spirits they ne're drunk before. </l>
              <l>Night us'd to Apparitions, sweats at this, </l>
              <l>And calls the Morning up, Morn dares not rise, </l>
              <l>But like a timerous Virgin lower creeps. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e2420">
                <hi>[Enter </hi>Tantalus. </stage>
              <l>The work is done!— Atreus begins to rise, </l>
              <l>And rising raves, descend damn'd Shade; the Earth </l>
              <l>Cannot support at once Atreus and thee; </l>
              <l>You both will break both Poles.— Descend to Hell. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e2500">[Tan. and Me. descend: Atreus rises. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e2540">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>All of the sudden quiet? is the Masque </l>
              <l>Concluded then, and Furies gone to rest? </l>
              <l>Then Furies may have rest, though I'm denyed: </l>
              <l>The Gods grudge me what they bestow on Hell. </l>
              <l>What Nights have I? Sure I mistake for Nights </l>
              <l>Whole pieces torn out of th' Infernal Blacks, </l>
              <l>To wrap the Furies whilst they sport themselves </l>
              <l>In this cold upper Air, by tort'ring me. </l>
              <l>Confound you Furies, why do you vex me? </l>
              <l>Is Earth grown good, that you want work below? </l>
              <l>I'm sure my share has wickedness enough, </l>
              <l>And find my Brother, and I'le fill your hands; </l>
              <l>Mean while torment me not with Nightly pains, </l>
              <l>Want of revenge is pain enough to me. </l>
              <l>Till revenge Crowns me, I am still depos'd, </l>
              <l>A Contemn'd, Artless, Nerveless, Spiritless Slave, </l>
              <l>A loaded emptyness, on which my Brother, </l>
              <l>Like a God, hangs an Universe of wrongs. </l>
              <l>Ho! there! </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e2750">[Enter a Waiter. </stage>
              <l>1. Your Royal Will. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e2770">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Thou fawning Dog! </l>
              <l>Thou lazy useless Cur, how long wilt thou </l>
              <l>And all thy fellow Curs, with flattering Tongues, </l>
              <l>Lye licking my wide Wounds, and not hunt out </l>
              <pb n="4" xml:id="ep000511-006-a"/>
              <l>The Savage Beast, from whom I had 'em all? </l>
              <l>My gaping aking wounds can ne're be cur'd, </l>
              <l>Till they are tented with his naked Bones. </l>
              <l>By Tantalus, my wicked Grandfather </l>
              <l>Who fear'd no Gods, by my more wicked self, </l>
              <l>Who have no fear of Gods, or Men, or Devils, </l>
              <l>Bring me Thyestes all to pieces torn, </l>
              <l>E're I be rack'd by one more restless Night, </l>
              <l>Or you, and all the Race of you shall dye; </l>
              <l>For I'le leave nothing upon Earth to groan </l>
              <l>For all your Deaths, but the o're-loaded Trees, </l>
              <l>On whose torn boughs in Clusters you shall hang. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e2970">[Enter a Second. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e2980">2. Sir, Tereus is return'd from the strict search Of Prince Thyestes. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e3010">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Ha! go bring him in. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e3040">Enter Tereus. </stage>
            <l>Now speak the Tydings, yet thou need'st not speak, </l>
            <l>Thy trembling Joints bow under evil news, </l>
            <l>Death fills thy Face, and stands as in the Door </l>
            <l>Ready to take possession of the House. </l>
            <l>Thy Eyes, like Evening-lights before their time </l>
            <l>Consum'd with Storms, are ready to go out, </l>
            <l>And let thy Soul in darkness scape away: </l>
            <l>But first I'le make it lay its burden down. </l>
            <l>Speak, can Thyestes yet be found? </l>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e3160">
              <speaker>Ter. </speaker>
              <l>Not yet. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e3190">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Then from this hour thou shalt be found no more. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e3220">1. Great Sir.— </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e3230">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Nor thou!— thus will I use you all; </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e3260">[Stabs both. </stage>
              <l>For you are Traytors all, hir'd Traytors, all </l>
              <l>Brib'd by Thyestes, you are all his Slaves, </l>
              <l>He governs here in Argos, and not I; </l>
              <l>I am his Slave, poor Slave; I have not Wealth </l>
              <l>Enough, to purchase from his Head one Hair; </l>
              <l>Yet he can buy my Peace, my Throne, my Wife, </l>
              <l>And after all can keep me on the Rack </l>
              <l>In my own Kingdom; in the midst of all </l>
              <l>My Slaves and Guards, a Slave can rack a King, </l>
              <pb n="5" xml:id="ep000511-006-b"/>
              <l>An exil'd Slave a King; so many Friends </l>
              <l>In Heaven, Earth, and Hell, has Villany. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e3400">Enter Antigone with Agamemnon and Menelaus, Infants. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e3450">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Now! what art thou? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e3480">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Antigone. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e3510">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>What's that? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e3540">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Your Daughter, Sir. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e3570">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>And are you sure o' that? </l>
              <l>By Heavens, thy Mother was so rank a Whore, </l>
              <l>That it is more than all the Gods can tell </l>
              <l>What share of thee is mine. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e3630">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>You have been pleas'd </l>
              <l>To think me all your own. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e3670">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>I have been pleas'd </l>
              <l>To be a Fool, and think thy Mother too </l>
              <l>Was all my own, and chaste. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e3720">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>So sure she was, </l>
              <l>Though any Chastity may be surpriz'd. </l>
              <l>However, Sir, we came— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e3770">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>To make me mad? </l>
              <l>Was it for that? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e3810">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>No, Sir, to make you Calm: </l>
              <l>You have been pleas'd sometimes to take delight </l>
              <l>In most unworthy me, and in these two </l>
              <l>Poor innocent young Princes, who did ne're </l>
              <l>Offend you yet. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e3880">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>How! not offend me yet? </l>
              <l>Then shou'd two flames, all of the sudden burst </l>
              <l>Out of the Hill, on which my Palace stands, </l>
              <l>The Hill upon whose brow by night I sleep, </l>
              <l>By day I take my prospects of my delight, </l>
              <l>The horrid flames wou'd not offend me? ha! </l>
              <l>By all the Gods, these damn'd incestuous Brats </l>
              <l>Are the irruptions of a burning Whore, </l>
              <l>More hot than Aetna. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e4000">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Sir! howe're my Mother sin'd of late, </l>
              <l>Yet I have heard your self sometimes confess </l>
              <l>You thought her innocent when we were born. </l>
              <pb n="6" xml:id="ep000511-007-a"/>
              <l>She never saw my wicked Uncle's Face </l>
              <l>Till after we were born. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e4070">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>And what o' that? </l>
              <l>Are there no men to sin withall but he? </l>
              <l>What a vast Monster dost thou make thy Mother? </l>
              <l>At the first minute of her Birth in Sin, </l>
              <l>To conquer Nature, cancel all her Laws, </l>
              <l>Do more than Fiends have done these thousand years? </l>
              <l>No, no, so well of her do I believe, </l>
              <l>I rather think she always was a Whore, </l>
              <l>And by degrees, ascended to this height: </l>
              <l>Oh! how I lov'd that Woman! oh! the Gods! </l>
              <l>Why in her stead was I not doom'd to love </l>
              <l>Some gastly, grim, devouring, Hellish Fury; </l>
              <l>Whose Hairs were Serpents, and her breath a plague; </l>
              <l>Whose Bones were Gibets, and her Nerves Iron Chains; </l>
              <l>Whose Eyes were Comets, and her Voice was Thunder, </l>
              <l>Whose Teeth were Hooks all gor'd with humane blood; </l>
              <l>Whose Flesh and Blood was a devouring bog, </l>
              <l>Compounded of all poysons in the world? </l>
              <l>In her abhor'd embrace I had not found </l>
              <l>So many Deaths and Hells as I do now. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e4290">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Gods! if my Mother sin'd against such love, </l>
              <l>And sin'd so foulely as some say she has; </l>
              <l>Pour all your vengeance on her impious head, </l>
              <l>And spare the injur'd King; his heavy wrongs </l>
              <l>Are sufferings great enough for all his sins. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e4360">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Gods! with what witchcraft did this woman deal? </l>
              <l>She has transform'd me to I know not what, </l>
              <l>I am a mingle of Fool, Tyrant, Devil, </l>
              <l>Madman, and Child, for by the Gods I weep, </l>
              <l>Who ne're did so in tender'st Infancy. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e4430">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Hard were the Heart that would not melt at this. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e4460">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>I am a madman too, I tear my self, </l>
              <l>Cause him ●ought to tear I cannot reach: </l>
              <l>I'm such a Tyrant, were he in my reach, </l>
              <l>I'd teach the Fur 〈…〉 to torment the damn'd. </l>
              <l>I was not always thus, this hellish mind </l>
              <l>Was the Creation of that cursed woman; </l>
              <l>Whom yet I love, so rank a Fool am I, </l>
              <l>And for her sake, her sin-begotten brood, </l>
              <pb n="7" xml:id="ep000511-007-b"/>
              <l>For which I loathe my self, away with 'em. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e4570">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Pray, Sir. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e4600">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>How now? Resist my will? Begone, </l>
              <l>Or on the floor I'le mingle ah your Brains▪ </l>
              <l>What hinders me from killing these lewd Brats? </l>
              <l>Sure it is Hell, which is afraid to lose </l>
              <l>Fruit of a Stock, the like was ne're before: </l>
              <l>Hence from my sight you Bastards, or my Guards </l>
              <l>Shall bear you hence upon their Holbard points. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e4690">Enter Peneus. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e4710">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Get you hence, Children; leave the King to me: </l>
              <l>Go, fair Antigone, your Planets lowr, </l>
              <l>I like 'em not; but Children your's shine out: </l>
              <l>Prince Agamemnon, Oracles agree, </l>
              <l>Shall lay a glorious Empire in the Dust, </l>
              <l>And Menelaus be the chiefest Cause. </l>
              <l>But yet no Oracle did utter this </l>
              <l>Without ill-boding sounds; then Children hence: </l>
              <l>Argos perhaps may perish by your Death, </l>
              <l>And that sad way the Oracle fulfill'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e4870">[Ex. An. Agam. Mene. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e4890">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>How now, old Dotard, what is thy business here? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e4920">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Business I have, or I wou'd ne're come here: </l>
              <l>A Court is not a place for an old man; </l>
              <l>'Specially if in dotage so far gone▪ </l>
              <l>As to be honest. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e4980">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Hence with thy old Cant; </l>
              <l>That was the unintelligible stuff </l>
              <l>Thou taught'st my foolish Youth; which now I find </l>
              <l>All non-sence, and not fit for Princes Courts? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e5040">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>What is not Vertue fit for Princes Courts? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e5070">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>No, 'tis an Art of washing o're false Coin, </l>
              <l>And stamping Images of Gods, on Knaves: </l>
              <l>Thou seem'st the humblest Creature in the World, </l>
              <l>The Fool that into flaming Aetna leapt, </l>
              <l>To be esteem'd a God, had not more pride. </l>
              <l>Thou fling'st thy self into the jaws of want, </l>
              <l>To be ador'd, and thought a Godlike man. </l>
              <l>He strove to disappear in Flame and Smoke, </l>
              <pb n="8" xml:id="ep000511-008-a"/>
              <l>And thou in cloudy words of good and wise. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e5190">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>I serv'd so faithfully your Royal House, </l>
              <l>Upwards of threescore years, that I believ'd </l>
              <l>I might assume the name of honest man, </l>
              <l>Since it was all the wages I desir'd. </l>
              <l>When did I ever wrong you in my life, </l>
              <l>That you shou'd throw this scandal on my age? </l>
              <l>I speak for Vertues sake, and not my own, </l>
              <l>Lest all men shou'd forsake her for a Cheat. </l>
              <l>I'le do her right, as I'm in Conscience bound, </l>
              <l>And boldly tell you, Vertue makes my Age </l>
              <l>More pleasant, than your Kingdom does your Youth. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e5320">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Thanks to Thyestes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e5360">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>He has wrong'd you indeed. </l>
              <l>But what have your obedient Subjects done? </l>
              <l>And you kill them; to save their lives I came. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e5410">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>They hide the Traytour. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e5440">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>I believe the Gods </l>
              <l>Hide him, lest you by death shou'd set him free </l>
              <l>From greater punishments which they inflict: </l>
              <l>Vengeance belongs to Gods, and they devour </l>
              <l>Their luscious Morsels of Revenge alone. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e5510">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>I'le find their Banquet out, and have my share, </l>
              <l>I care not what it cost me; let our fam'd </l>
              <l>Great House Pelops tumble on my head, </l>
              <l>So damn'd Thyestes perish under me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e5590">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>You'l make your self as odious as he; </l>
              <l>Almost as impious too. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e5630">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>I wou'd be more, </l>
              <l>I wou'd do all that Villany to him, </l>
              <l>That he can only wish were done to me, </l>
              <l>I have no other way to prove my self </l>
              <l>His Elder Brother, and a lawful King. </l>
              <l>For he of us that is the greatest Fiend </l>
              <l>Ought to be King of Argos, 'cause he gives </l>
              <l>The greatest proof of Tantalus his blood. </l>
              <l>And I'le appear no Bastard to the World. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e5760">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>What will your People say? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e5790">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>I'le make 'em say </l>
              <l>What I command. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e5830">
              <pb n="9" xml:id="ep000511-008-b"/>
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Falshoods perhaps you may. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e5860">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>That is the great Prerogative of Power, </l>
              <l>To tax the world for Praise as well as Coin; </l>
              <l>I'le make 'em praise my actions good or bad. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e5910">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Yes whilst you live you may, but when you are dead </l>
              <l>The world will curse you to Eternity. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e5950">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>My Name will live then to Eternity. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e5980">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>So will your Soul, but lost. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e6010">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Let 'em but live, </l>
              <l>No matter how. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e6050">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Fear you not Men or Gods? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e6080">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>The Fear of Gods ne're came in Pelops House. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e6120">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Think you there are no Gods? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e6150">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>I find all things </l>
              <l>So false, I'm sure of nothing but of wrongs. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e6190">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Then fear your injur'd Subjects, for the beams </l>
              <l>Of Vertue breed the Golden Mines of Praise; </l>
              <l>But Vice the Iron of Rebellion. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e6240">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Let them fear that! oh! I am mad, I burn, </l>
              <l>Furies with flaming brands are in my breast: </l>
              <l>Their Snakes with their own poyson almost burst; </l>
              <l>And every Vein o' mine contains a Snake. </l>
              <l>Ho! there! bid Mycenae get in Arms, </l>
              <l>I will pour all my Kingdom upon Greece. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e6340">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>And who shall guard your Cities then? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e6370">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>The Furies. </l>
              <l>They are their Temples, and belov'd abodes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e6410">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Sir! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e6440">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Away! or I will spurn thee hence; </l>
              <l>I am transported from my self— arm!— arm!— </l>
              <l>I'le do!— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e6490">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>What will you do? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e6520">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>I know not what, </l>
              <l>Something that all the Gods shall tremble at. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e6560">[Ex. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e6570">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>How miserable a thing is a great man? </l>
              <l>Take noysie vexing greatness they that please; </l>
              <l>Give me obscure, and safe, and silent ease: </l>
              <l>Acquaintaince and Commerce let me have none, </l>
              <l>With any powerful thing, but time alone: </l>
              <l>My rest let time be fearful to offend, </l>
              <pb n="10" xml:id="ep000511-009-a"/>
              <l>And creep by me, as by a slumb'ring Friend; </l>
              <l>Till with ease glutted, to my Grave I steal, </l>
              <l>As men to sleep after a plentious Meal. </l>
              <l>Oh! wretched he! who call'd abroad by power, </l>
              <l>To know himself can never find an hour. </l>
              <l>Strange to himself, but to all others known, </l>
              <l>Lends every one his Life, and uses none, </l>
              <l>So e're he tasted Life, to Death he goes, </l>
              <l>And himself loses, e're himself he knows. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e6740">[Exit. </stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="ep000511-e6750">
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="ep000511-e6760">
            <head>ACT II. SCENE II. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e6780">Philisthenes and Antigone meet. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e6790">SCENE the Mouth of a Cave in a Grove. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e6810">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>OH! my Philisthenes, sad news! sad news! </l>
              <l>My cruel Fathers Feaver of Revenge </l>
              <l>Grows on him every hour, night brings him all </l>
              <l>The restless shades of Hell, day all the Flames, </l>
              <l>He's ever calling for thy Fathers Blood: </l>
              <l>How greedily wou'd he drink thine more sweet? </l>
              <l>But do not fear; as soon as Night appears </l>
              <l>Away we'll fly from this accursed place, </l>
              <l>Devoted by our Fathers to all ill: </l>
              <l>By thine to Incest, and by mine to blood. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e6940">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Gods! what dreadful miseries must befall </l>
              <l>Th' unhappy Off-spring of two such bad men? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e6980">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Our Innocence and Love will guard us safe: </l>
              <l>I have prepar'd a Chariot for our flight </l>
              <l>To the Aegean Sea, and there a Boat </l>
              <l>Lies lock'd at Anchor, in a Creek so small, </l>
              <l>It seems a little Closet of the Sea, </l>
              <l>Where Mayden Calms lye hid from Ruffian Winds: </l>
              <l>The Creek appears a wrinkle made with age, </l>
              <l>In a high Promontories bending brow. </l>
              <l>The little Harbour is o're-look'd by all </l>
              <l>But a poor humble Fisherman, whose Hut </l>
              <pb n="11" xml:id="ep000511-009-b"/>
              <l>Is all the Castle that commands the Port: </l>
              <l>There needs no Porter where there is no Door. </l>
              <l>Nothing they think can creep out o' that Chink. </l>
              <l>The honest Fisherman expects us both </l>
              <l>E're Night be old; then let us fearless fly, </l>
              <l>We cannot lose our way, for we transport </l>
              <l>Our Journeys end along with us, our selves. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e7180">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>What Beauty, and Love, do I to Misery lead? </l>
              <l>Oh! Love! I lead thee from thy Fathers rage </l>
              <l>To a more cruel Tyrant, merciless want! </l>
              <l>My Fathers sins have press'd him down so low, </l>
              <l>He stoops to eat the Charitable Bread </l>
              <l>Of a poor aged Man, Peneus by Name. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e7270">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>I knew that man: oh! that's a good old man! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e7300">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Where he conceals my Father, I know not; </l>
              <l>He would not trust the secret with my Youth, </l>
              <l>For fear I shou'd be cheated by ill men; </l>
              <l>But from my Father oft he Presents brings, </l>
              <l>Such as his miserable Fortune yields: </l>
              <l>Their chiefest value is my Fathers Love. </l>
              <l>Now shall I steal thee from thy Fathers Court, </l>
              <l>And cannot give thee for it a poor Cave? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e7400">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>I foresaw this, and all my Jewels brought: </l>
              <l>Those with our Love will make a great Estate. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e7440">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! you kind Gods! which way have I deserv'd </l>
              <l>Such wondrous Love, from such a wondrous Maid? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e7480">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>What have I done with 'em?— I have 'em not— </l>
              <l>I have not lost 'em sure. </l>
              <l>I left 'em in my Chamber, I did ill, </l>
              <l>For I abhor to thrust my head again </l>
              <l>Within that cursed House, which is a Sink </l>
              <l>Where Jove throws all the scum of all ill stanes; </l>
              <l>And Furies watch'd my absence, I'm afraid, </l>
              <l>To set my Jewels in some baleful Charm: </l>
              <l>But I'le go fetch 'em; hide! oh! hide, my Dear! </l>
              <l>Down to the darkest corner of the Vault. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e7610">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! let me see thee, as long as e're I can. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e7640">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>No, no, 'tis dangerous, down, down, my Love! </l>
              <l>Oh! Cave, be faithful to thy precious trust, </l>
              <l>And all the youthful Lovers in the World, </l>
              <pb n="12" xml:id="ep000511-010-a"/>
              <l>With flowry Wreaths shall crown thy rocky brow, </l>
              <l>Shall make a Temple of thee, and adore </l>
              <l>Night's little Picture that adorns thy Walls, </l>
              <l>Night Lover's Goddess, and Eternal Friend. </l>
              <l>Farewell my Love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e7740">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Farewell my Dear!— my Eyes </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e7770">[Ex. Ant. </stage>
              <l>Are fastned to her steps, and I must look </l>
              <l>What-e're it cost me. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e7810">Enter a Captain of the Guard with a Guard, and seize Phil. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e7830">
              <speaker>Capt. </speaker>
              <l>And 'twill cost thee dear. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e7860">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Betray'd? ha! what are you? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e7890">
              <speaker>Capt. </speaker>
              <l>King Atreus Guard. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e7930">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! I am lost! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e7960">
              <speaker>Capt. </speaker>
              <l>Indeed young man, thou art </l>
              <l>So lost, I pity thee; and wou'd it cost </l>
              <l>No life but mine, by Heaven, I'd set thee free. </l>
              <l>But were it known, 'twou'd cost a thousand Lives; </l>
              <l>My single Life wou'd to the raging King </l>
              <l>Be but like a little Pillar to the Sea; </l>
              <l>Not stop the Waves, but make 'em foam the more. </l>
              <l>And that 'twill be discover'd is as sure </l>
              <l>As there are Spies and Villains in a Court. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e8070">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>What have I done, the King shou'd seek my Life? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e8100">
              <speaker>Capt. </speaker>
              <l>Thy Father sinn'd both for himself and thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e8130">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>I from my Father receive no Estate, </l>
              <l>'Tis hard I shou'd inherit all his Faults. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e8170">
              <speaker>Capt. </speaker>
              <l>May the King use thee as thou dost deserve. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e8200">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Since you have so much pity, I dare beg </l>
              <l>For my Dear Love; (whom I must see no more!) </l>
              <l>I know you over-heard our talk! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e8250">
              <speaker>Capt. </speaker>
              <l>We did. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e8280">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! spare her Life; and do not tell the King </l>
              <l>She loves unhappy me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e8320">
              <speaker>Capt. </speaker>
              <l>No, no, dear Youth, </l>
              <l>For our own sakes we'll hide it from the King: </l>
              <l>Small trust he'd put in us, if he shou'd find </l>
              <l>His daughter false. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e8380">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>She is not false; but Fate </l>
              <pb n="13" xml:id="ep000511-010-b"/>
              <l>Deals ill with her, to cast her Love on me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e8420">
              <speaker>Capt. </speaker>
              <l>Ah! cruel Chance, that brought me to this Cave, </l>
              <l>To ruine this unhappy lovely pair. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e8460">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Ah! poor Antigone! ah! wretched me!— </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e8500">Ex. Phi. with the Guard. At another Door enter Antigone. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e8530">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Methought complaining sounds came from the Cave; </l>
              <l>The sounds of differing Voices were compos'd; </l>
              <l>I'm in a horrid Agony with fear! </l>
              <l>I cannot stay, yet forward dare not go. </l>
              <l>Forward I must; how deadly cold I am, </l>
              <l>As if death stood between the Cave and me? </l>
              <l>If I meet not my Love, I shall with Death: </l>
              <l>He is not in the Cave; where is he wander'd?— </l>
              <l>My Love! Philisthenes— my Love, my Love! </l>
              <l>Where art thou hid? Come hither, I am here, </l>
              <l>Antigone is here!— my Love— My Love. </l>
              <l>Oh! nothing answers, he is seiz'd!— he's lost!— </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e8690">She falls in a Swoun. Enter Peneus. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e8710">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Ha! what is she, that sleeps in open Air? </l>
              <l>Indeed the place is far from any path, </l>
              <l>But what Conducts to melancholly thoughts; </l>
              <l>But those are beaten Roads about this Court. </l>
              <l>Her Habit calls her, noble Grecian Maid; </l>
              <l>But her sleep says she is a Stranger here. </l>
              <l>All Birds of Night build in this Court, but Sleep; </l>
              <l>And sleep is here made wild with loud Complaints, </l>
              <l>And flies away from all; I wonder how </l>
              <l>This Maid has brought it to her lure so tame. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e8840">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! my Philisthenes! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e8880">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>She wakes to moan; </l>
              <l>Ay! that's the proper Language of this place! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e8920">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>My Dear! my poor Philisthenes is seiz'd! </l>
              <l>I know 'tis so! oh! Horrour! Death! Hell!— oh! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e8970">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>I know her now, 'tis fair Antigone! </l>
              <l>The Daughter and the Darling of the King, </l>
              <l>This is the Lot of all this Family. </l>
              <pb n="14" xml:id="ep000511-011-a"/>
              <l>Beautious Antigone! thou know'st me well; </l>
              <l>I am old Peneus, one who threescore years </l>
              <l>Has lov'd and serv'd thy wretched Family, </l>
              <l>Impart thy sorrows to me, I perhaps </l>
              <l>In my wide Circle of Experience, </l>
              <l>May find some Counsel that may do me good. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e9110">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! good old man! how long have you been here? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e9140">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>I came but now. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e9170">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! did you see this way </l>
              <l>Poor young Philisthenes? you know him well. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e9220">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Thy Uncles Son? Thyestes eldest Son? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e9260">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>The same! the same! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e9290">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>No, all the Gods forbid </l>
              <l>I shou'd meet him so near thy Fathers Court. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e9330">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! he was here, one cursed minute past. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e9360">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>What brought him hither? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e9390">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Love to wretched me. </l>
              <l>Our warring Fathers never ventur'd more </l>
              <l>For bitter hate, than we for innocent Love. </l>
              <l>Here, but a minute past, the dear youth lay; </l>
              <l>Here in this brambly Cave lay in my Arms; </l>
              <l>And now he's seiz'd! oh! miserable me! </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e9470">[She tears her Hair. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e9480">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Why dost thou rend that Beautious Ornament? </l>
              <l>In what has it offended? hold thy hands. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e9520">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Father! go and plead for the poor Youth! </l>
              <l>No one dares speak to the fierce King but you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e9560">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>And no one near speaks more in vain than I; </l>
              <l>He spurns me from his presence like a Dog. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e9600">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! then— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e9630">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>She Faints! She Swouns!— I frightned her!— </l>
              <l>Oh! I spoke indiscreetly!— Daughter! Child! </l>
              <l>Antigone! I'le go!— indeed— I'le go!— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e9690">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>There is no help for me in Heaven or Earth. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e9720">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>There is, there is, despair not sorrowful Maid, </l>
              <l>All will be well— I'm going to the King, </l>
              <l>And will with powerful reasons bind his hands; </l>
              <l>And something in me says I shall prevail; </l>
              <l>But to whose care shall I leave thee mean while? </l>
              <l>For, oh! I dare not trust thee to thy grief. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e9800">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>I'le be dispos'd of, Father, as you please, </l>
              <pb n="15" xml:id="ep000511-011-b"/>
              <l>Till I receive the blest or dreadful doom. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e9840">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Then come, dear Daughter, lean upon my arm, </l>
              <l>Which old and weak is stronger yet than thine, </l>
              <l>Thy Youth has known more sorrow than my age. </l>
              <l>I never hear of grief, but when I'm here: </l>
              <l>But one days diet here of Sighs and Tears, </l>
              <l>Returns me elder home by many years. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e9920">
              <hi>[Ex. </hi>Pen. Ant. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e9940">SCENE the Court. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e9960">Enter Atreus, Captain of the Guard. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e9980">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Thyestes eldest Son fallen in my Hands? </l>
              <l>I find the Gods are tyr'd with holding up </l>
              <l>The ponderous Villain, long above my Sword, </l>
              <l>And mean to let him fall, in the mean while </l>
              <l>They fling his Race like Vipers from their hands. </l>
              <l>Bring in the Youth— </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e10070">Enter Guard with Philisthenes. </stage>
              <l>How now Boy? what Affair? </l>
              <l>What vast Affair, in value worth a Life, </l>
              <l>Made thee adventure to this dangerous place? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e10120">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Love to my native soyl; I came to see </l>
              <l>The Court and Kingdom of my Ancestors; </l>
              <l>And this great Palace where I had my birth: </l>
              <l>For I was told King Atreus was so good, </l>
              <l>He pardon'd and forgot his Brothers faults? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e10200">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>How bold and ready art thou in a lye? </l>
              <l>Who cou'd inform thee I had pardon'd faults </l>
              <l>Which cannot be forgiven by Men or Gods? </l>
              <l>To what strange thing didst thou believe me turn'd </l>
              <l>To a tame Beast? no Beast but loves Revenge: </l>
              <l>To a mild God? He cannot be a God </l>
              <l>That wants Revenge. 'Tis a Gods chief delight, </l>
              <l>They mark it for their own: what then a Tree? </l>
              <l>Alas! why did not thy good Father come </l>
              <l>And whore my Wife under my Bawdy Shade? </l>
              <l>So dumb a Husband need not have been fear'd, </l>
              <pb n="16" xml:id="ep000511-012-a"/>
              <l>Nor such a piece of Lumber of a King. </l>
              <l>And thou didst come to cut me down, in hopes. </l>
              <l>My Subjects were as weary of my Life, </l>
              <l>As thy lewd horrid Father has made me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e10370">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>I scorn an act so Villanous and base. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e10400">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>What crowd is this assembled in my Breast? </l>
              <l>My Soul's a Theatre with Furies fill'd. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e10440">[Asidè. </stage>
              <l>The Ghastly throng fling all their eager looks </l>
              <l>Upon a Table spread with mangled Limbs, </l>
              <l>And smoking bowls ore gorg'd with reeking blood; </l>
              <l>Their Eyes grow larger with the pleasing sight; </l>
              <l>And the deluded Guest, who eats his Son, </l>
              <l>Stamps all their Cheeks with a malicious smile </l>
              <l>The Vision takes! the Story's great and brave, </l>
              <l>I'le give it my Revenge to Copy out. </l>
              <l>Now with my Daughter I'le entice this Youth </l>
              <l>To cheat his Father with a proffer'd Crown. </l>
              <l>To meet a Crown, he'd rush on thundring Jove, </l>
              <l>Plunge in the Sea when Winds and Billows fight, </l>
              <l>Or on deep quicksands, that wou'd swallow hills; </l>
              <l>Nay, worse than all these joyn'd,— he wou'd meet me— </l>
              <l>Yes, and he shall— <hi>(Aside.) Philisthenes</hi>, bold Youth; </l>
              <l>Something in thee has made Friends in my heart, </l>
              <l>Who by plain force have master'd my Revenge, </l>
              <l>After a long and fierce and dubious fight, </l>
              <l>And make it bow to offer thee thy Life. </l>
              <l>What sayst thou, Youth? hast thou a mind to live? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e10670">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Let Nature answer for me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e10700">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>But to live </l>
              <l>On the ill terms of being Friends to me? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e10740">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>What God puts those good thoughts into your Soul? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e10770">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Thy own desert; I love thee, noble Youth. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e10800">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! I am overwhelm'd? </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e10830">[weeps and falls at the Kings Feet. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e10840">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>The sweet Youth weeps, </l>
              <l>And prostrates at my Feet; this must not be: </l>
              <l>Rise, rise, my own best blood, my own best self, </l>
              <l>The Hope and Pillar of our falling House: </l>
              <l>What wilt thou disobey my first command? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e10910">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Which of the best of Gods have done this good? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e10940">
              <pb n="17" xml:id="ep000511-012-b"/>
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Come to me, near my Heart, within my Heart. </l>
              <l>As soon as ever I beheld thy Eyes, </l>
              <l>Something flew from'em, like a Charming God, </l>
              <l>And bid the Furies leave my troubled Breast; </l>
              <l>They strugled hard, but now they are all gone; </l>
              <l>And now my heart is free for all my Friends. </l>
              <l>Oh! that I had thy Father in my Arms; </l>
              <l>In what perfection wou'd be my full joy? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e11040">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>And can you be so excellent to forgive </l>
              <l>My Father too? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e11080">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Ay! sooner than my self. </l>
              <l>My barb'rous Rage I never shall forgive. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e11120">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>How good are you? For you had been most kind, </l>
              <l>When you most heavily was wrong'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e11160">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>No more; </l>
              <l>Dear Youth, let all thy Fathers Errors dye; </l>
              <l>My mortal spite shall only be at them, </l>
              <l>And his too lasting hatred. Wou'd I knew </l>
              <l>Where my poor wandring exil'd Brother rov'd, </l>
              <l>That I might send, or rather go my self </l>
              <l>To Court him to my Arms, and to a Crown, </l>
              <l>To be my Friend, and be my King, his turn. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e11260">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>And do you mean it, Sir? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e11290">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>That is unkind! </l>
              <l>Dost thou suspect my Truth? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e11330">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>I do not, Sir; </l>
              <l>But I am so transported with my Joy, </l>
              <l>I know not what I think, or what I say. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e11380">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Then know'st thou where thy Father is, dear Youth? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e11410">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>I do not, Sir; but good old Peneus does. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e11450">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Does he indeed? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e11480">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Yes, my poor Father, Sir, </l>
              <l>Has all his bread from him. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e11520">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! false old Rogue!— </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e11550">[Aside. </stage>
              <l>Alas! poor Brother, art thou fall'n so low, </l>
              <l>To live upon old Servants broken Meat? </l>
              <l>But, good old Peneus, thou giv'st what thou hast, </l>
              <l>By all the Gods thou shalt have thy reward. </l>
              <l>See, here he comes! come hither pious man. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="18" xml:id="ep000511-013-a"/>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e11620">Enter Peneus. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e11640">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>What means this change?— </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e11670">[Aside. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e11680">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>I am to give thee thanks </l>
              <l>For my own innocence, my Brothers Life; </l>
              <l>It seems, 'tis thou, that hid him from my Rage, </l>
              <l>And given him Bread, and starv'd my fierce revenge. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e11740">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Who told you this? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e11770">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Nay, be not startled, Man; </l>
              <l>No other hurt is meant thee, than my Love; </l>
              <l>But I'm so bad a Man, men shun my Love, </l>
              <l>And think the Gods curse all whom I embrace. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e11830">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>I'm sure you once were good, but potent wrongs. </l>
              <l>To flaming vengeance grappled you so fast, </l>
              <l>I thought no Art or Strength cou'd set you free. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e11880">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>A thousand things conspir'd thy strong advice: </l>
              <l>The tempting sight of this most noble Youth; </l>
              <l>And last my Nature tyr'd with standing bent </l>
              <l>Always to ill, bowed down by force of wrongs, </l>
              <l>Starts up for ease, to its own posture, Love; </l>
              <l>Love of my Bother, this dear Youth his Son; </l>
              <l>And of my Sov'reign happiness, my Wife: </l>
              <l>What think you, Sirs, did I not love my Wife? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e11980">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Your passion for her hatred shew'd your Love; </l>
              <l>Though some believe she's wrong'd as much as you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e12020">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Faulty or not, so powerful was my Love, </l>
              <l>My wounded dying Love, had greater strength </l>
              <l>Than all my rage in its most vigorous Youth, </l>
              <l>And held me from her Life, that still she lives. </l>
              <l>'Tis true, in heavy sorrow, so she ought </l>
              <l>If she offended, as I fear she has, </l>
              <l>Her hardships though she owes to her own choice. </l>
              <l>I've often offer'd her my useless Couch; </l>
              <l>For what is it to me? I never sleep. </l>
              <l>But for her Bed, she chuses the hard floor. </l>
              <l>My Table is spread for her; I never eat: </l>
              <l>And she'll take nothing but what feeds her grief. </l>
              <l>Hair-cloth and Chains she wears, but by that means </l>
              <pb n="19" xml:id="ep000511-013-b"/>
              <l>She makes me wear'em, 'cause I feel her pains. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e12180">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! how Report has wrong'd this excellent King? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e12210">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>But now I've hopes to see my Brother's Face: </l>
              <l>My spacious Arms extend to Heaven and Hell; </l>
              <l>And I've the choice of both, which is soon made. </l>
              <l>Oh! Peneus! bring my Brother to my Arms, </l>
              <l>And greater joy shall lift the down-cast head </l>
              <l>Of Pelop's House, than ever it beheld. </l>
              <l>I'le give my Daughter to my Brother's Son, </l>
              <l>And then our joys are fastned at the root. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e12330">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>I shall run mad with Joy.— </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e12360">[Aside. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e12370">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Is not this Art? </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e12400">[Aside. </stage>
              <l>Methinks on this so fine Carv'd Pedestal, </l>
              <l>An Image with two Faces I discern. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e12430">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Dear Peneus, hasten on thy Embassy. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e12470">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>An Embassy that's worthy of a God; </l>
              <l>And wou'd I were a God, that I might find </l>
              <l>The wandring Prince, and finish this blest work. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e12520">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Know'st thou not where he is then? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e12550">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! yes, Sir! </l>
              <l>Ah! Peneus, why do you distrust the King? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e12600">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Ah! poor deluded Youth— </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e12630">[Aside. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e12640">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>He fears I'm false; </l>
              <l>I blame him not, for I am a bad man: </l>
              <l>I deserve all the wrongs I have indur'd; </l>
              <l>All I desire is leave to pardon wrongs. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e12700">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Father of my Father, thou whose great </l>
              <l>And pious Charity preserv'd his Life, </l>
              <l>Do not destroy us all by needless doubts. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e12750">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Gods! guide me in this doubtful Labyrinth. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e12780">[Aside. </stage>
              <l>Let me not be misguided by vain doubt, </l>
              <l>To be the death of seeming new-born joy: </l>
              <l>But if the King dissembles, (oh good Gods!) </l>
              <l>Let not my age, and this unknowing Youth, </l>
              <l>Be worse misguided both, to be the death </l>
              <l>Of his dear Father he, I of my Friend. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e12850">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>The wary wise old man distrusts me still. </l>
              <l>Oh! Brother, thou hast Friends, but I have none. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e12890">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Yes, I am, Sir, your Friend, as much as his: </l>
              <l>But more to Faith and Honesty than both▪ </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e12930">
              <pb n="20" xml:id="ep000511-014-a"/>
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Well, I will put my Kingdom in thy hands. </l>
              <l>Behind the Palace, in a sacred Field, </l>
              <l>Secur'd by twenty Walls, and watch'd by Guards, </l>
              <l>Rests all the Fortune of our Royal House. </l>
              <l>A shining Ram whose yellow Fleece is Gold; </l>
              <l>The Sands of Tagus are not half so rich; </l>
              <l>Whoever has possession of this Beast, </l>
              <l>Has all the Fortune of our House in pawn, </l>
              <l>An Hostage all our Gods cannot redeem, </l>
              <l>They are in perfect Friendship with that Prince </l>
              <l>To whom they send this Wealthy Minister; </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e13070">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>By long Experience, Sir, I know all this. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e13100">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Ho! there! go catch and bind the Sacred Ram. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e13130">A Field discover'd; a Golden Ram seen in the Head of a Flock of Sheep; a Guard round the Field; they bring the Ram to the King. </stage>
              <l>Peneus, this present to my Brother bear, </l>
              <l>As a rich Pledge of my Eternal Love. </l>
              <l>Give it to him, on no Condition, </l>
              <l>But that he come and take his turn to Reign. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e13190">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! good Gods! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e13220">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Still dost thou harbour doubt? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e13250">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Whether I Dream or no. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e13280">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! on my knees, </l>
              <l>I beg with Tears suspect the King no more; </l>
              <l>I've had no joy in all my Youth till now, </l>
              <l>And now good Fortune, like a Noon-day Sun, </l>
              <l>Breaks out upon me, if with Cloudy doubts </l>
              <l>You darken all again, I shall run mad. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e13360">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>I'le say no more; be witnesses ye Gods, </l>
              <l>If never Joy come more under this Roof, </l>
              <l>If it be any, any fault of mine. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e13410">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, I will bear you witness the short while </l>
              <l>My poor life lasts; which lies in Peneus's hands. </l>
              <l>If he will still keep up this wall of doubt </l>
              <l>'Tween joy and me; I'm at my Journeys end. </l>
              <l>Resolve me. Peneus, will you let me dye? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e13500">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>No: but I quickly shall, my feeble age. </l>
              <pb n="21" xml:id="ep000511-014-b"/>
              <l>Can never climb up this high hill of joy, </l>
              <l>But I shall faint before I reach the top; </l>
              <l>Howe're I'le go as far as e're I can: </l>
              <l>I'le send, for bring is too much joy for me </l>
              <l>(Most excellent King) your Brother to your Arms. </l>
              <l>But I go hence so surfeited with joy </l>
              <l>I shall not live to see you any more. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e13600">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! stay, thou richest blessing of our House; </l>
              <l>The dear Philisthenes shall go alone. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e13650">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>He is to his Father wonderfully dear; </l>
              <l>But he is young, his Father may distrust </l>
              <l>The weakness of his soft and easie youth. </l>
              <l>My wary faithful age he will not doubt; </l>
              <l>That I must go my self; farewell, good King. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e13720">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Farewell, thou pious, sacred, blest old man. </l>
              <l>Farewell sweet Youth, henceforwards my dear Son. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e13760">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, I wou'd call you,— cou'd I speak for Tears, </l>
              <l>Father,— and giver of my best new life. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e13800">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>My Dear Antigone shall know thy Love; </l>
              <l>I'le tell such Stories of thee, thou shalt find </l>
              <l>At thy return her Love exceeding thine. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e13860">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Peneus thy hand! I am so stun'd with joy, </l>
              <l>I cannot see my way. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e13910">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>My Chariot there! </l>
              <l>And Guards attend 'em— Farewell to you both, </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e13950">
                <hi>[Ex. </hi>Pen. Phi. </stage>
              <l>I think I've counterfeited rarely well. </l>
              <l>He who wou'd rule so damn'd a World as this, </l>
              <l>Where so many dissembling Villains dwell, </l>
              <l>Must cheat the Devil, and out-dissemble Hell. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e14010">[Ex. </stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="ep000511-e14020">
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="ep000511-e14030">
            <pb n="22" xml:id="ep000511-015-a"/>
            <head>ACT III. SCENE III. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e14050">Enter Antigone, attended by two Women. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e14060">SCENE the out-Gates of a Prison. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e14080">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>I'M torn! I'm torn! by Sorrow, Rage, Despair! </l>
              <l>No Tydings yet of my Philisthenes? </l>
              <l>I dare not, dare not ask, lest on my head </l>
              <l>I pull the Thunder of some dreadful news. </l>
              <l>Like a low Vale between two raging Seas, </l>
              <l>Of Fear and Hope, I lye, and hourly expect </l>
              <l>A deluge of delight, or of despair. </l>
              <l>But oh! the Seas rowl fastest from despair: </l>
              <l>For I like not this new and strange Command </l>
              <l>Sent from my Father, to come visit here, </l>
              <l>In her sad prison, the afflicted Queen. </l>
              <l>(For if she sinn'd as some believe, I hate </l>
              <l>To call her Mother) but of late she was </l>
              <l>A hated, out-cast, and forbidden thing. </l>
              <l>My Father wou'd not suffer to come near </l>
              <l>This doleful dwelling, any thing he lov'd. </l>
              <l>Then he has heard our Love, and is enrag'd; </l>
              <l>If so, my dear Philisthenes is dead, </l>
              <l>And with my Mother I'm condemn'd to dye. </l>
              <l>It must be so! I grow exceeding ill. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e14320">
              <speaker>1. Wom. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! help! the Princess! help! she faints away. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e14350">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>No matter what I do— let me alone!— </l>
              <l>Oh! my Philisthenes! 'twill not be long </l>
              <l>E're I be with thee!— Call the men that Guard </l>
              <l>The Queen, my wretched Mother. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e14420">
              <speaker>1. Wom. </speaker>
              <l>Ho! within! </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e14450">Enter a Keeper. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e14460">
              <speaker>Keep. </speaker>
              <l>Who calls? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e14490">
              <speaker>1. Wom. </speaker>
              <l>Come to the Princess. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e14520">
              <speaker>Keep. </speaker>
              <l>What's her will? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e14550">
              <pb n="23" xml:id="ep000511-015-b"/>
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Know you this Signet? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e14580">
              <speaker>Keep. </speaker>
              <l>Yes, it is the Kings. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e14610">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>I must have entrance here. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e14640">
              <speaker>Keep. </speaker>
              <l>Madam, you shall. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e14670">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Let the Queen know that by the Kings command </l>
              <l>I come to wait on her. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e14710">
              <speaker>Keep. </speaker>
              <l>I'le tell the Queen. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e14740">[Ex. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e14750">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Now Gods prepare me for th' afflicting fight. </l>
              <l>For if report be true, the alter'd Queen </l>
              <l>Is the most doleful Object in the World. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e14800">The Scene is drawn, the Queen in Hair-cloth, Chains at her Legs, she lies on the ground, a Lamp burning by her. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e14810">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>My Daughter see me by the Kings command? </l>
              <l>What does he mean? No good to us, I fear? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e14850">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Is that the Queen? Is that my Mother? oh! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e14880">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>My Daughter there? Antigone! my Child! </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e14920">[Rises and Embraces her. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e14930">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Ah! Mother! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e14960">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>Daughter! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e14990">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>O! my Tears! my Tears! </l>
              <l>I cannot speak! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e15030">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>Weep in my Bosom Child, </l>
              <l>And let thy poor sad Mother weep in thine. </l>
              <l>Come rest thy self, my Daughter, sit thee down </l>
              <l>On the hard Floor, thy Mothers only Bed; </l>
              <l>And hear the mournfull'st Story in the World. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e15100">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Mother! Mother! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e15130">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! my lov'd, my dear, </l>
              <l>My precious Comfort, dearer than my Life. </l>
              <l>My Life! What is my miserable Life? </l>
              <l>Dear as my Life was in my happy state. </l>
              <l>And happy! oh! too happy once I was; </l>
              <l>My Massy happiness tyr'd out my Fate, </l>
              <l>It cou'd not carry it to my lives end. </l>
              <l>Never did Woman love a Man more dear </l>
              <l>Than I once did, and still do love the King; </l>
              <l>Be witness all the Gods to what I say, </l>
              <l>And ne're was Woman more belov'd by man. </l>
              <pb n="23" xml:id="ep000511-016-a"/>
              <l>Than I was by the King,— until— oh! Child, </l>
              <l>I cannot speak how sadly I have been wrong'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e15280">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! my Dear Mother! I believe you indeed, </l>
              <l>All the Gods know I ne're thought otherwise. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e15320">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>Thyestes! (oh! Hell is in that Name▪) </l>
              <l>Me his own Brother's Wife, his dear lov'd Wife, </l>
              <l>Me whom his Brother trusted to his Care, </l>
              <l>Bruitishly forc'd— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e15390">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! horrid! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e15420">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>And then sought </l>
              <l>To get, by fraud, the Sacred Golden Fleece, </l>
              <l>The Monument and Instrument of Fate, </l>
              <l>To gain the Kingdom to secure his Sin, </l>
              <l>And retain me a Pris'ner for his Lust. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e15490">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>All this I've heard, and ever did believe; </l>
              <l>But no kind God wou'd e're conveigh this Faith </l>
              <l>Into my Fathers Soul. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e15540">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! no, my Child; </l>
              <l>Then think, oh! think, what are thy Mothers wrongs; </l>
              <l>And what her dismal alter'd sad Estate. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e15590">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Gods! was ever any thing so sad? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e15620">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! I have know the time, I'd not have let </l>
              <l>Such dirty Earth as this come near my Feet, </l>
              <l>Which now is all the Lodging that I have: </l>
              <l>I wou'd not once have vext my curious Eye </l>
              <l>With seeing such a Garment as I wear, </l>
              <l>Nor suffer'd to have come into my sight </l>
              <l>So vile a Creature as my self appears. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e15710">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>No more, no more, dear Mother. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e15740">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>O! my Child, </l>
              <l>These outward pains are pleasures, when compar'd </l>
              <l>With what I feel within me; for the loss </l>
              <l>Of all my honour and my Husbands Love. </l>
              <l>The Heavens are not so spotless as my Soul, </l>
              <l>Nor Gods so fond of Heaven as I of him; </l>
              <l>Yet am I thought a Strumper, nay a lew'd </l>
              <l>Incestuous monstrous Strumpet!— Furies— Hell— </l>
              <l>Stand from me, Child, for I shall do thee hurt; </l>
              <l>My Wits are going; when I think of this </l>
              <l>They always leave me— stand away dear Child. </l>
              <pb n="25" xml:id="ep000511-016-b"/>
              <l>Who says I am a Strumpet? is it thou? </l>
              <l>Lyar! 'tis well I have thee in my Arms, </l>
              <l>I'le throw thee piece-meal to the Furies— thus! </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e15900">[Tears her self. Ant. holds her Hands. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e15920">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Mother! Mother! 'tis your self you rend. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e15950">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>How now, contend with me? This is a Whore. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e15980">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Help, the Queen's mad!— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e16010">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>Ay! help me from a Whore </l>
              <l>That comes to get my Husband from my Arms: </l>
              <l>Oh! this is right the Picture of the Age, </l>
              <l>A shining Strumpet, and a tatter'd Wife. </l>
              <l>Indeed! and am I thus abus'd for thee? </l>
              <l>Some Water there! I'm burnt out o' my Bed, </l>
              <l>My Husbands Arms, by a hot flaming whore. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e16100">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Mother! Mother! I'm Antigone </l>
              <l>Your Daughter! oh! the Queen will kill me! help! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e16150">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>The Fire goes out! alloo! the ashes flye! </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e16180">[Pulls some loose Ornaments from Ant. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e16200">
              <l>So, now in the King's arms I will go sleep. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e16220">[Falls. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e16230">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Help! help the Queen! what are there none in call? </l>
              <l>Ha! her Heart strongly beats, breath comes and goes </l>
              <l>Upon Lifes errant, with no little force. </l>
              <l>Then all is well I hope! she sweetly sleeps. </l>
              <l>Her raving Spirit's in a wild uproar, </l>
              <l>Thrust her in tumults to the Vaults of sleep, </l>
              <l>Then shut the door with violence upon her. </l>
              <l>Sleep on, dear Mother, heal thy wounded mind </l>
              <l>With these sweet balmy slumbers; though, alas, </l>
              <l>'Tis only heal'd for new and deeper wounds. </l>
              <l>Oh! were there ever two so innocent; </l>
              <l>And yet so miserable as we are? </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e16370">Enter Keeper. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e16380">
              <speaker>Keep. </speaker>
              <l>Where is the Queen? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e16410">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Peace, peace, she's fallen asleep. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e16440">
              <speaker>Keep. </speaker>
              <l>The King is coming here to visit her. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e16470">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>The King? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e16500">
              <speaker>Keep. </speaker>
              <l>The King. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e16530">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>See in her Sleep she smiles, </l>
              <pb n="23" xml:id="ep000511-017-a"/>
              <gap extent="1" reason="duplicate" unit="pages"/>
              <pb n="25" xml:id="ep000511-017-b"/>
              <gap extent="1" reason="duplicate" unit="pages"/>
              <pb n="26" xml:id="ep000511-018-a"/>
              <l>Her Spirits rebound at mentioning a Name </l>
              <l>That has such sweet agreement with her Soul; </l>
              <l>As strings when tun'd alike, if one be touch'd </l>
              <l>The other leaps; and now she starts, as if </l>
              <l>She fain wou'd break through all the Gates of Sleep </l>
              <l>To meet the Voice that bears the pleasing sound; </l>
              <l>And now she wakes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e16670">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! I have had a sweet </l>
              <l>Reviving slumber; not these many months </l>
              <l>Have I been so refresh'd. Antigone! </l>
              <l>Now I perceive whence I had all my rest, </l>
              <l>From the delight my Soul did take in thee. </l>
              <l>But, oh! my Child! was I not very ill </l>
              <l>Before I slept? did I no hurt at all? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e16770">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Yes to your self I fear. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e16800">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>If that be all, </l>
              <l>It is no matter; 'tis as it shou'd be, </l>
              <l>I am the Center of all Miseries. </l>
              <l>What wander from me, leave their proper course. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e16860">Enter Women with a rich Role, and other Attires. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e16870">
              <speaker>Wom. </speaker>
              <l>Madam, the King— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e16900">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>The King, ha! what of him? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e16930">
              <speaker>Wom. </speaker>
              <l>Sends you these Robes, and begs you wou'd be pleas'd </l>
              <l>With these to hide your misery from his sight, </l>
              <l>And let the wondrous joy he means to take </l>
              <l>In seeing you, be pure from any grief. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e16990">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>Will he see me? and can the sight of me </l>
              <l>Be joy to him? Why does he tell me this? </l>
              <l>He does not well to make the miseries </l>
              <l>Of his poor ruin'd, injur'd Wife, his sport; </l>
              <l>I love him dearly, (witness all ye Gods) </l>
              <l>In spite of all my sufferings and wrongs. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e17070">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Mother! Mother! sudden beams of hope </l>
              <l>Shine out upon me; oh! there is a change! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e17110">
              <speaker>Wom. </speaker>
              <l>Madam, upon our lives we tell you truth, </l>
              <l>The stormd toss'd King is on the sudden calm▪ </l>
              <l>We know not what shou'd charm the billows down, </l>
              <l>Except the good old Peneus </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e17180">
              <pb n="27" xml:id="ep000511-018-b"/>
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! no doubt, </l>
              <l>It was the Wisdom of that wond'rous man. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e17220">Enter Keeper. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e17230">
              <speaker>Keep. </speaker>
              <l>The King is near. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e17260">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>Fling the Robe loosely o're; </l>
              <l>I never yet dissembled with the King; </l>
              <l>Nor hid from him was ever yet my heart: </l>
              <l>The wretch I am, let his own Eyes behold, </l>
              <l>I ne're deserv'd to be thus cast away. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e17330">Enter Atreus attended: The Queen kneels. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e17350">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Kneeling? this must not be!— Rise, Madam, rise. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e17380">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>I do not kneel, Sir, as a Criminal, </l>
              <l>But as an innocent poor Woman, thrown </l>
              <l>By grievous wrongs into a state unfit </l>
              <l>For you to see; I fall upon the Earth </l>
              <l>To hide my self, and save your generous heart </l>
              <l>From the affliction it must bear to see </l>
              <l>My woful change, whether deserv'd or not. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e17470">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Kneeling's a state I cannot bear to see. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e17500">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>You may be, Sir, assur'd I'le quit it then. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e17530">[Chairs brought. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e17540">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Now seat your self— Madam, I think you'l own </l>
              <l>I lov'd you well. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e17580">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>I were ungrateful else: </l>
              <l>And I lov'd you as dearly the Gods know, </l>
              <l>And I have ever been your faithful Wife, </l>
              <l>And ne're deserv'd to lose that glorious Name. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e17640">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Well, Madam, I will shew I love you still, </l>
              <l>If you have wrong'd me, be it to your self. </l>
              <l>The Gods forgive you freely, as I do: </l>
              <l>If not, Gods bring your innocence to light. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e17700">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Gods! good Gods! grant! grant! so good a prayer. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e17730">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>However, Madam, whatsoe're you be, </l>
              <l>All things are so forgot, as if the Gods </l>
              <l>Had made a Queen o' purpose for my Love, </l>
              <l>And you were newly come out of their hands, </l>
              <l>Just when they finish'd you, and said 'tis well, </l>
              <l>We cannot add one beauty to our work; </l>
              <pb n="28" xml:id="ep000511-019-a"/>
              <l>So I receive you to my arms and heart. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e17820">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! this is too much joy for me to bear, </l>
              <l>You build new Palaces on broken Walls. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e17860">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Madam, Eternal Gates are lock'd and bar'd </l>
              <l>On all past deeds, ne're to be open'd more, </l>
              <l>By this new happy meeting of our Lips, </l>
              <l>Which have been Strangers now these many Months; </l>
              <l>You are as dear to me, as when you came </l>
              <l>A fond young beautious Virgin to my Arms. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e17940">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>How bounteous are the Gods in the Rewards. </l>
              <l>Of suffering Innocence? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e17980">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! my dear Queen! </l>
              <l>Never admit past sufferings in thy thoughts, </l>
              <l>I'le have this joyful day without one Cloud. </l>
              <l>And joy shall shine through all my Family: </l>
              <l>Even my Brother shall not want his share. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e18050">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>Your Brother! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e18080">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Yes, I can forgive, even him; </l>
              <l>Nay, have invited him home to my Court, </l>
              <l>Both to receive my Pardon and my Love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e18130">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>Invite that wicked man home to your Court! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e18160">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>You do not know how dearly once we lov'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e18190">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>Nor you believe how much he injur'd me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e18220">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>I know his violent desires by mine; </l>
              <l>We were so one, one Fire must burn us both, </l>
              <l>And where Fire comes all things asunder fall; </l>
              <l>Our Union ruin'd us, but I'le build </l>
              <l>Our Friendship more magnificent than ever. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e18290">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>Then will my Life as wretched be as ever; </l>
              <l>The sight of him will like a Winter Cloud, </l>
              <l>Darken and Freeze the Joy I have in you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e18340">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>I send not home for him, who did you wrong, </l>
              <l>But him whose penitence has done you right, </l>
              <l>Wicked Thyestes you shall ne're see more, </l>
              <l>But new Thyestes so to goodness chang'd, </l>
              <l>You will know nothing of him but his Name. </l>
              <l>Oppose not then what all the Gods design, </l>
              <l>These breaches threaten ruine to our House; </l>
              <l>But the good Gods design our House shall stand. </l>
              <l>Did you ne're see a weather-beaten Wall </l>
              <pb n="29" xml:id="ep000511-019-b"/>
              <l>Breed up young Ivy to support its age? </l>
              <l>By Heavenly care from us bad men is sprung </l>
              <l>An excellent Race, to bind our Friendship close, </l>
              <l>And stop up all the breaches in our House. </l>
              <l>The Gods ne're made a more accomplish'd Youth, </l>
              <l>Than his sweet Eldest Son, Philisthenes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e18540">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Gods! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e18570">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>And I have sworn to marry him </l>
              <l>To my beloved Child, Antigone. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e18620">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>With all the pleasing wonder mixt with dread, </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e18650">[Aside. </stage>
              <l>A crowd behold a shining God descend, </l>
              <l>Have I been looking for this glorious news, </l>
              <l>'Tis lighted on me, and I'm overwhelm'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e18690">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Child, you have seen your noble Kinsman oft, </l>
              <l>What think you of him? Cou'd you love him? speak. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e18730">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>My thoughts are always in your keeping, Sir. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e18760">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Well answer'd, Daughter: Love your Kinsman then, </l>
              <l>Give him your Heart; but give him not such hold, </l>
              <l>But you may take it back, if ill shou'd chance, </l>
              <l>And ill may happen; I have sent the Youth </l>
              <l>With good old Peneus, to invite to Court </l>
              <l>My exil'd Brother; if he shou'd not come, </l>
              <l>I shou'd relapse into my grief again. </l>
              <l>The Noble Youth, at parting, left with me </l>
              <l>A wealthy Token for you, his dear Love: </l>
              <l>But you shall take no Presents from the Son, </l>
              <l>Unless the Father first accept of mine: </l>
              <l>Which for my Comfort beg of Heaven he may. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e18910">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! how devoutly will I make that Prayer? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e18940">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! wondrous goodness! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e18970">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Now my dearest Wife, </l>
              <l>And my Antigone, embrace me both. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e19020">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Sir! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e19050">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Father!— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e19080">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! my perfect joy, </l>
              <l>Come let our new-born pleasures breath sweet air; </l>
              <l>This Room's too vile a Cabinet for Gold. </l>
              <l>Then leave, for ever, Love, this doleful place, </l>
              <l>And leave behind thee all thy sorrows here, </l>
              <l>And dress thy self as this great day requires; </l>
              <pb n="30" xml:id="ep000511-020-a"/>
              <l>'Twill be thy Daughters Nuptials, and I dreamt </l>
              <l>The Sun himself wou'd be asham'd to come </l>
              <l>And be a Guest in his old tarnish'd Robe, </l>
              <l>But leave my Court t' enlighten all the Globe. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e19200">[Ex. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e19210">Enter Thyestes. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e19230">SCENE a Cave in a Desart. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e19250">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Astonishment! Confusion! how came I </l>
              <l>To be the horrid Villain that I was? </l>
              <l>I had it not from Nature; if I had, </l>
              <l>Why did it not break out in many years: </l>
              <l>How cou'd I carry such a load of sin </l>
              <l>And feel no pain? Did Custom dull my sence? </l>
              <l>No, for as soon as e're my greedy Eyes, </l>
              <l>Numbring the Treasures of my Brothers Bed, </l>
              <l>Had stoln more Appetite than I cou'd appease, </l>
              <l>I bowed beneath the weight, and cou'd not rest </l>
              <l>Till I had laid it on his Bed again. </l>
              <l>Perhaps I felt no sin, because I liv'd </l>
              <l>In th' Element of sin, my Brother's Court. </l>
              <l>Things in their Element lose all their weight; </l>
              <l>Water in water feels as light as Air. </l>
              <l>No, 'twas not that; I was the first that brought </l>
              <l>Incest and Treason to my Brother's Court. </l>
              <l>From my own self came all my Villany; </l>
              <l>Had I not been a Dunghill, Beauty might </l>
              <l>Have shin'd as wholesomely on me, as others. </l>
              <l>I loath, detest my self, and flye mankind, </l>
              <l>Counting the worst of men too good for me. </l>
              <l>Heark! I hear voices!— nay, and I see men; </l>
              <l>They're very near me too, I'le hide my head. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e19510">Thy goes into a Cavr. Enter Peneus and Philisthenes. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e19550">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Here dwells your Father. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e19580">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>In this Wilderness? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e19610">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Here in this Cave. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e19640">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Ah! lonely, poor abode. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e19670">
              <pb n="31" xml:id="ep000511-020-b"/>
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis his own choice: I proffer'd him my House, </l>
              <l>Where I had Rooms to hide, and ways to fly, </l>
              <l>In case of danger; but he rather chose </l>
              <l>This melancholly Desart, and this Cave. </l>
              <l>I'le call him out to you. Thyestes! ho! </l>
              <l>Ho! Prince Thyestes! know you not the Voice </l>
              <l>Of your old faithful Peneus? </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e19790">Enter Thyestes. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e19810">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Peneus here? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e19850">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Is that my Father? oh I how sadly chang'd? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e19880">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Who hast thou here, old Friend? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e19910">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>One you may trust, </l>
              <l>Half your own self, your Son Philisthenes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e19960">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>My Son? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e19990">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>My Father— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e20020">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Welcome to my arms, </l>
              <l>My Hope, my Comfort!— Time has rowld about </l>
              <l>Several Months since I have seen thy Face, </l>
              <l>And in its progress has done wond'rous things. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e20080">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Strange things indeed, to chase you to this sad </l>
              <l>Dismal abode, nay, and to Age I think. </l>
              <l>I see that Winter thrusting it self forth, </l>
              <l>Long, long, before its time, in Silver Hairs. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e20140">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>My fault, my Son, I wou'd be great and high; </l>
              <l>Snow lies in Summer on some Mountain tops. </l>
              <l>Ah! Son, I'm sorry for thy noble Youth, </l>
              <l>Thou hast so bad a Father; I'm afraid </l>
              <l>Fortune will quarrel with thee for my sake▪ </l>
              <l>Thou wilt derive unhappiness from me, </l>
              <l>Like an hereditary ill disease. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e20230">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, I was born when you were innocent, </l>
              <l>And all the ill you have contracted since, </l>
              <l>You have wrought out by painful penitence. </l>
              <l>For healthy joy returns to us again. </l>
              <l>Nay, a more vigorous joy than e're we had. </l>
              <l>Like one recover'd from a sad desease, </l>
              <l>Nature for dammage pays him double cost, </l>
              <l>And gives him fairer flesh than e're he had. </l>
              <pb n="32" xml:id="ep000511-021-a"/>
              <l>For a spoil'd Cottage, she bestows a Brief. </l>
              <l>On all her works, that doubles what he lost. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e20350">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Your Son Philisthenes, has told you truth: </l>
              <l>The King your Brother, by what God transform'd </l>
              <l>I cannot tell, is turn'd an excellent man. </l>
              <l>He has no memory of all Errours past, </l>
              <l>Except his own; the chief of which he counts </l>
              <l>His too immoderate passion for revenge. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e20440">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>And can this be? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e20470">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Will I not tell you truth? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e20500">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>By thy own goodness, art thou not deceiv'd? </l>
              <l>Thou d well'st in open truth, and when thou com'st </l>
              <l>Among dark men, thou knowst not what they are. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e20550">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Sir, my reason is not dim with age, </l>
              <l>What e're my Eyes are; time which steals our sight, </l>
              <l>Is for the Thievery by Nature fin'd, </l>
              <l>To make us recompence in inward light. </l>
              <l>Know, Sir, I did not lend your Brother Faith, </l>
              <l>Without a Pawn, as wealthy as his Crown; </l>
              <l>The Golden Ram, let this prevail, not I. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e20640">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>I stand amaz'd, for what wou'd this prevail? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e20670">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>To make you glorious in your Brothers Throne, </l>
              <l>Your Brother happy in the sight of You. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e20710">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>And me in the possession of my Love: </l>
              <l>I love his Daughter, fair Antigone, </l>
              <l>And he has sworn to place her in my Arms, </l>
              <l>When-ever to his Arms I can bring you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e20780">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>This is too much; a man that wou'd revive </l>
              <l>His famish'd Friend, wou'd never cram him thus: </l>
              <l>He choaks my Faith with gorging it too fast, </l>
              <l>And surfcits sickly Friendship with a Feast. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e20840">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Can you suspect, when you have such a pledge? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e20870">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>If the King be so good, 'twere a new Treason </l>
              <l>To blast him with my fight. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e20910">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Your penitence </l>
              <l>Restores intirely all your innocence, </l>
              <l>And now your presence wou'd restore your Joys. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e20960">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Things are miscall'd, I ne're was blest till now: </l>
              <l>When I was great, I had not one delight: </l>
              <l>Who needs a Taster has small joy in tastee. </l>
              <pb n="33" xml:id="ep000511-021-b"/>
              <l>Who needs a Guard for safety, ne're are safe▪ </l>
              <l>And who needs watching, has but little rest. </l>
              <l>What solitude so bad, as throngs of Knaves? </l>
              <l>What dwelling so uneasie as is his, </l>
              <l>Who in a thousand Rooms can take no rest, </l>
              <l>Till his proud Palace has beat back a Sea, </l>
              <l>And lifted up a Forrest on its brow? </l>
              <l>Say Poyson come not in a Princes Cup, </l>
              <l>Care will, and that's as bad; say Care shou'd not, </l>
              <l>Intemperance may, which is as bad as both; </l>
              <l>A lingring Poyson that consumes our time, </l>
              <l>Our Nights in drunkenness, our Days in sleep. </l>
              <l>Say he ne're see the bloody face of War, </l>
              <l>A thousand Dishes are a dangerous Camp, </l>
              <l>Where very often men have met with Death, </l>
              <l>Among those fair pretended Friends of Life; </l>
              <l>Nor is his rest the more for silent peace, </l>
              <l>In Calms of peace, when all without is still, </l>
              <l>Factions within will make a Kingdom rowl. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e21200">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>No doubt these Evils, and a thousand more, </l>
              <l>Attend on Royal greatness; but what then? </l>
              <l>Will you adventure nothing for your Friends? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e21250">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Father! humbly on my knees I beg, </l>
              <l>Go to the King, if for my sake alone. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e21290">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>For thy dear sake alone I fear to go, </l>
              <l>I fear to make thee guilty of my blood. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e21330">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>What reason have you to distrust the King? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e21360">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>He has had heavy wrongs, and no revenge. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e21390">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Is Poverty and Exile no revenge? </l>
              <l>Shame and Repentance is revenge enough </l>
              <l>To a good man. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e21440">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>It cannot be denyed. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e21470">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Can you not say he once was a good man? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e21500">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>The best of Kings, and Brothers? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e21530">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Did he e're </l>
              <l>Shew any hate to you, till you wrong'd him? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e21570">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! never! never! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e21600">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Did he then requite </l>
              <l>Your hate so ill, as you return'd his love? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e21640">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! no! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e21670">
              <pb n="34" xml:id="ep000511-022-a"/>
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Why judge you then of him so ill? </l>
              <l>Since you cou'd make him turn from good to ill, </l>
              <l>May not the Gods turn him from ill to good? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e21720">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>It cannot be deny'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e21750">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Are you not turn'd? </l>
              <l>Wou'd you fain act o're all your Crimes again? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e21790">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>I'd rather dye? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e21820">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Do you excell him so, </l>
              <l>That goodness shall be reconcil'd to you </l>
              <l>On easie terms, but on no terms with him? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e21870">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>I think him a much better man than I. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e21900">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Since you are chang'd, why may not he be so? </l>
              <l>I leave it to your choice, believe the King, </l>
              <l>And make up all the breaches of your House, </l>
              <l>Or begin new Confusions by your stay; </l>
              <l>Affront the King, and make him shed the blood </l>
              <l>Of your dear Son, and me your just old Friend, </l>
              <l>Hew Nations down to make his way to you, </l>
              <l>Whilst Curses in full cry shall hunt you out, </l>
              <l>As the great common mischief of the world: </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e22010">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>No more, no more, I'm overcome— I'le go— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e22040">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Gods! I thank you for so good success </l>
              <l>In my good Embassy. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e22080">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>And in my Love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e22110">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>You Divine Guardians of these innocent Woods, </l>
              <l>My only Friends of all the Heavenly Powers; </l>
              <l>Who here so faithfully have hid me long, </l>
              <l>And blest my mind with penitence and ease, </l>
              <l>If you can bear the wickedness of Courts, </l>
              <l>Go with us thither, and preserve us there: </l>
              <l>Not but my life to Justice is a debt; </l>
              <l>But let not my dear Son, and good old Friend, </l>
              <l>Prove guilty of shedding their own blood and mine, </l>
              <l>By undertaking such a good Design. </l>
              <l>For who will Vertue follow, and obey, </l>
              <l>If when she is their Guide, men lose their way? </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="ep000511-e22250">
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="ep000511-e22260">
            <pb n="35" xml:id="ep000511-022-b"/>
            <head>ACT IV. SCENE IV. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e22280">Enter Thyestes, Philisthenes, Peneus. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e22300">SCENE Mycenae▪ </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e22310">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>OH! wondrous pleasure to a banish'd man! </l>
              <l>I feel my lov'd, long look'd for Native Soyl; </l>
              <l>My former Incest (horrid to be nam'd) </l>
              <l>Gave me not greater pleasure, than this new </l>
              <l>Innocent Incest with my Mother Earth. </l>
              <l>And oh! my weary Eyes, that all the day </l>
              <l>Had from some Mountain travell'd toward this place, </l>
              <l>Now rest themselves upon the Royal Towers </l>
              <l>Of that great Palace where I had my birth. </l>
              <l>Oh! sacred Towers! sacred in your height, </l>
              <l>Mingling with Clouds, the Villa's of the Gods, </l>
              <l>Whither for secret pleasures they retire. </l>
              <l>Sacred, because you are the work of Gods; </l>
              <l>Your lofty looks boast your Divine descent, </l>
              <l>And the proud City which lies at your Feet, </l>
              <l>And wou'd give place to nothing but to you, </l>
              <l>Owns her Original is short of yours. </l>
              <l>And now a thousand Objects more ride fast </l>
              <l>On morning beams, and meet my Eyes in throngs. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e22520">[A shout. </stage>
              <l>And see all Argos meets me with loud shouts. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e22550">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! joyful sound. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e22580">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>But with them Atreus too. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e22620">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>What ails my Father, that he stops and shakes, </l>
              <l>And now retires? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e22660">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Return with me my Son, </l>
              <l>And old Friend Peneus, to the honest beasts </l>
              <l>And faithful desart, and well seated Caves; </l>
              <l>The Beasts declare their Natures without fraud: </l>
              <l>Trees shelter man, by whom they often dye, </l>
              <l>And never seek revenge; no Villany </l>
              <l>Lyes in the prospect of an humble Cave. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e22760">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Talk you of Villany, of Foes and Fraud? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e22790">
              <pb n="36" xml:id="ep000511-023-a"/>
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>I talk of Atreus. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e22830">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>What are these to him? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e22860">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Nearer than I am, for they are himself. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e22890">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Gods drive these impious thoughts out of your mind. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e22920">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>The Gods for all our safety put 'em there: </l>
              <l>Return, return with me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e22960">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Against our Oaths? </l>
              <l>I cannot stem the Vengeance of the Gods. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e23000">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Here are no Gods, they've left this dire abode. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e23030">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Father! Father! if not for my sake, </l>
              <l>For all our Family, all the Kingdoms sake, </l>
              <l>Bring your dear fellow Exiles peace and joy </l>
              <l>To Argos, who does Court'em with a Crown. </l>
              <l>Oh! look upon the Splendour of a Crown; </l>
              <l>See from the rising King it dawns this way; </l>
              <l>Oh! look upon it Father. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e23130">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Yes, I do, </l>
              <l>As I have often look'd upon the Sun, </l>
              <l>When I have seen him heave a thousand Waves </l>
              <l>In brimming Spouts, up to his Lips to drink, </l>
              <l>To spit 'em all in the Seas Face again, </l>
              <l>Or on some Desart, where they only serv'd </l>
              <l>To cool a while the thirst of burning Sands: </l>
              <l>So are we all by Royal splendour suck'd </l>
              <l>Up to the Clouds, to be let fall again </l>
              <l>Upon some dreadful unexpected Fate. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e23250">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>True Race of Tantalus! who Parent like </l>
              <l>Are doom'd in midst of plenty to be starv'd. </l>
              <l>His Hell and yours differ alone in this; </l>
              <l>When he wou'd catch at joys they fly from him, </l>
              <l>When Glories catch at you, you fly from them. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e23330">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>A fit Comparison; our joys and his </l>
              <l>Are lying Shadows, which to trust is Hell. </l>
              <l>What? Shall I trust my Brother and a Crown, </l>
              <l>Two the uncertain'st things, I was about </l>
              <l>To say, the falsest things in the whole world? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e23400">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>I must be wretched then. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e23430">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Well, for thy sake, </l>
              <l>Though I trust not the King, I'le trust the Gods. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="37" xml:id="ep000511-023-b"/>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e23470">Enter Atreus pompously attended. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e23490">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>The King is near,— and now his Eye is laid </l>
              <l>Firmly upon you, and has seiz'd you fast. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e23530">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>The beast is snar'd!— and I'm as fierce for prey, </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e23560">[Aside. </stage>
              <l>As the big Spartan Dog, when the fell Bore </l>
              <l>Laggs within reach of his long stretching neck. </l>
              <l>He breaks the Couples, from the Huntsman gets, </l>
              <l>And knows no Master but his love to bloud. </l>
              <l>My love to bloud will from my Fraud get loose: </l>
              <l>But what a thing he is? Exile and Grief </l>
              <l>Serve him so slovenly up to my Board, </l>
              <l>It palls my Stomach; but I'le garnish him </l>
              <l>With Princely Robes.— Oh! Brother! to my Arms— </l>
              <l>My Arms, dear Brother; render me your long </l>
              <l>Desir'd Embrace. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e23690">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! I have forseited </l>
              <l>The Title of your Brother; do not, Sir, </l>
              <l>Revile the honour'd Name, by giving it </l>
              <l>To me your humble penitent poor Slave. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e23750">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Away to everlasting. banishment </l>
              <l>The odious memory of all moments past, </l>
              <l>And all their Progeny. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e23800">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>I had prepar'd </l>
              <l>Excuses for my Crimes, and what were truth; </l>
              <l>But this amazing Piety and Love </l>
              <l>Render me past excuse, the worst of men. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e23860">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Must these dire thoughts, like Harpies, hover round </l>
              <l>Our Friendship still? Hence with 'em to abodes </l>
              <l>More hid from man, than those from whence you came. </l>
              <l>And rise! oh, rise to my embrace! what means </l>
              <l>This low unfitting posture? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e23940">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>It means more </l>
              <l>Than words can speak; I never kneel'd before: </l>
              <l>Then guess the honour I wou'd pay to you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e23990">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>I in the kindest manner take the sense, </l>
              <l>But do not like the Language of the Knee; </l>
              <l>'Tis between Brothers an ungrateful Tongue. </l>
              <pb n="38" xml:id="ep000511-024-a"/>
              <l>Then rise to me, or I will kneel to you; </l>
              <l>We will be equal. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e24060">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>That shall never be: </l>
              <l>I'le rise to your commmand; and so I still </l>
              <l>Bow in obedience low. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e24110">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Once more your arms, </l>
              <l>My dearest Brother. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e24150">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>My most excellent King. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e24180">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Now dear Philisthenes! thy arms, sweet Youth. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e24220">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, give me leave to fall and kiss your Feet. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e24250">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Indeed it shall not be. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e24280">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Pray suffer me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e24310">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>No, hang upon my Neck, thou art my Son: </l>
              <l>Wilt thou not own the Title of my Son? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e24350">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Not own it, Sir?— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e24380">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Now last let me embrace </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e24410">[Embraces Peneus. </stage>
              <l>The standing blessing of our Family. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e24440">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Had I been only born for this good hour, </l>
              <l>And all my fourscore years a desart Road, </l>
              <l>Without one joy to ease my Pilgrimage, </l>
              <l>This Journeys end had made amends for all. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e24500">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Good man! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e24530">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Now Father, do you credit us? </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e24560">
              <hi>[To </hi>Thy. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e24580">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Still there are Clouds that darken my delight, </l>
              <l>My Brothers Garments— Brother spare my Eyes, </l>
              <l>And with these Royal Ornaments conceal </l>
              <l>These Reliques of deceas'd unhappiness. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e24640">The Attendants give Thyestes rich Robes. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e24660">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, These foul Garments are the Livery </l>
              <l>Of a good Master, sorrow for my sins. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e24700">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>But you shall have no Master in my Court; </l>
              <l>For with these Ornaments receive my Crown. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e24740">Takes his Diadem from his head, and gives it to Thyestes. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e24760">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>A second Usurpation? Gods forbid! </l>
              <l>If my more fitting Garb offend your Eyes, </l>
              <l>Let me lye hid among th' attending Crowd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e24810">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>You shall be hid no more. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e24840">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>I'm great enough, </l>
              <pb n="39" xml:id="ep000511-024-b"/>
              <l>Whilst you are so; Friendship so makes me yours, </l>
              <l>In lessening your own self, you lessen me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e24890">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>It is more great to give, than wear a Crown. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e24920">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>And to refuse more glorious than to give; </l>
              <l>That is the share of greatness I will chuse; </l>
              <l>And you invited me to take my share. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e24970">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>I did, then both of us will be thus great, </l>
              <l>I in my Crown, you in excelling me. </l>
              <l>But see my Aerope, my dearest Queen. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e25030">Enter the Queen attended, and richly habited. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e25040">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>My shame, my horror, my Eternal Hell. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e25070">
              <speaker>Aero. </speaker>
              <l>Your spacious goodness, Sir, has farther reach'd </l>
              <l>Than guilt cou'd fly; and has invited home, </l>
              <l>To all the glories of your Court, a man, </l>
              <l>I'le boldly tell it him before his face, </l>
              <l>For whom Hell has not punishment enough. </l>
              <l>There is a Creature, for whom Heaven has scarce </l>
              <l>Rewards enow, opprest with heavy wrongs, </l>
              <l>And is not suffer'd to breath open Air. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e25170">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>What is this Creature? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e25200">
              <speaker>Aero. </speaker>
              <l>Injur'd Innocence: </l>
              <l>Which before man and Gods I claim for mine. </l>
              <l>And I intreat you, nay, conjure you, Sir, </l>
              <l>Not as you are my Husband, but my King, </l>
              <l>The Representative of the Just Gods, </l>
              <l>To bring my innocence into the light, </l>
              <l>And if the Sun himself has not more spots— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e25290">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>You'd have my Brother speak your innocence? </l>
              <l>What need? I have exactly weigh'd your cause? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e25330">
              <speaker>Aero. </speaker>
              <l>I'le have the Ballance hang'd upon Sun beams, </l>
              <l>That Heaven and Earth may see my innocence— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e25370">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>My Throne exalts it into all mens view. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e25400">
              <speaker>Aero. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, it exalts your goodness, and not mine: </l>
              <l>Unless you Crown my Fame as well as me, </l>
              <l>I only bear the luggage of your praise. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e25450">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>The world may be assur'd I've not a doubt. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e25480">
              <speaker>Aer. </speaker>
              <l>But nothing in the World shall have a doubt. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e25510">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>By the Eternal Gods, the Whore commits </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e25540">[Aside. </stage>
              <pb n="40" xml:id="ep000511-025-a"/>
              <l>Incest in fancy with the Villain here, </l>
              <l>Before my Face: The very sight of him </l>
              <l>Has got her Spirit big with Insolence. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e25580">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, you but lately offer'd me your Crown; </l>
              <l>I for a moment will assume the gift, </l>
              <l>And be a King; that is, be uncontroul'd, </l>
              <l>Whilst I declare the Queens wrong'd innocence. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e25640">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>What need all this? I know what you wou'd say. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e25670">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>I ravish'd her, and Hell did ravish me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e25700">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>And I, who have been wrong'd by both of you, </l>
              <l>Must, for my Recompence, be disobey'd. </l>
              <l>Nature (I find) has to the Birth and Death </l>
              <l>Of every thing annex'd tormenting pangs. </l>
              <l>Pangs wait upon the Birth of our new joys, </l>
              <l>And our past ills dye with Convulsion fits. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e25780">
              <speaker>Aer. </speaker>
              <l>My innocence is clear'd, and now dispose </l>
              <l>Of me, Sir, at your pleasure. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e25820">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>And of me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e25850">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Then thus I will dispose of all of you. </l>
              <l>My Broher to my Friendship and my Crown. </l>
              <l>To my delighted bosome, my dear Queen. </l>
              <l>To my Antigone, this noble Youth. </l>
              <l>This good old man to my rewards, and thanks.— </l>
              <l>Do you all weep for joy? Come dry your Eyes;— </l>
              <l>My Love shall be too hot for such light dew. </l>
              <l>Now let the Trumpets reparation make, </l>
              <l>For frightning Argos with the sounds of War, </l>
              <l>And set hearts dancing to the sounds of Peace. </l>
              <l>Let the pale Mothers trembling for their Babes, </l>
              <l>Now dandle 'em in their Arms with smiling Cheeks. </l>
              <l>Return the Husbands back to their young Wives, </l>
              <l>And let not Armour hinder their embrace. </l>
              <l>Let Swords wear Rust, the Livery of Peace, </l>
              <l>Let every Door be with a Garland Crown'd, </l>
              <l>And all the Conduits surfeited with Wine, </l>
              <l>Till they o're flow with infinite excess. </l>
              <l>And now prepare the Temple, Altars, Priests, </l>
              <l>For the great Ceremony of the Day. </l>
              <l>Call my Antigone to meet her Love. </l>
              <l>Brother, lead on— indeed you must— you shall— </l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="41" xml:id="ep000511-025-b"/>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e26120">Ex. <hi>Thy. Atreus, Aerope</hi>, and as they go off Antigone enters, runs to Philisthenes, and emberaces him. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e26160">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>My Love! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e26190">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>My Love! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e26220">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! my excessive joy. </l>
              <l>And is this possible? oh! God! gods Gods </l>
              <l>When I lost thee at the unfaithful Cave, </l>
              <l>Did I e're think to find thee with this joy? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e26280">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>When I was seiz'd and dragg'd before the King, </l>
              <l>Did Ie're think that this shou'd be my Death, </l>
              <l>To dye in thy embraces with delight? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e26330">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>This was the art of the Celestial Powers, </l>
              <l>To hold their Jewels up at a high price. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e26370">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>The Gods give nothing cheap, but misery. </l>
              <l>What have I suffer'd for this happiness? </l>
              <l>I have a large account to bring thee in. </l>
              <l>And thou shalt pay it all, I will extend </l>
              <l>All the Estate of Beauty which thou hast. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e26440">Enter a Gentleman. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e26450">
              <speaker>Gent. </speaker>
              <l>The Temple is prepar'd, the Priests attend; </l>
              <l>The Court expects you with impatience, Sir. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e26490">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Is't possible? And does Love stay for us? </l>
              <l>Pardon us Love, thou ne're didst so before: </l>
              <l>Since thou art so impatient for thy work; </l>
              <l>By all the Gods I'le find thee work enough. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e26550">[Ex. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e26560">The Scene a Temple. Priests at the Altar, Enter <hi>Atreus, Aerope, Thyestes, Philisthenes, Antigone, Peneus, </hi>Attendants. The Nuptial Ceremony perform'd; they come out of the Temple. The Scene continues. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e26580">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Now, Madam, you shall entertain the Bride. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e26610">
                <hi>[To </hi>Aero. </stage>
              <l>The Bridegroom I have chosen for my Guest. </l>
              <l>And Daughter, you shall spare him for an hour, </l>
              <l>To Gods that fill our lusty bowls with Wine, </l>
              <l>We usually pour some in gratitude. </l>
              <pb n="42" xml:id="ep000511-026-a"/>
              <l>Daughter, I've fill'd your Life brim-full of Joy, </l>
              <l>And you shall offer the first hour to me. </l>
              <l>So long the Bridegroom is my Sacrifice. </l>
              <l>Stay in the Temple, noble Youth, a while, </l>
              <l>I will return to thee immediately, </l>
              <l>I wou'd unfold to thee some mysteries. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e26730">Aerope and Ladies lead out Antigone at one Door: At another go <hi>Atreus, Thyestes, Peneus. Philisthenes </hi>follows as to wait upon the King— after a short pawse Priests bring in Phi. stript and bound. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e26780">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Ha! what means this? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e26810">
              <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis by the Kings command. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e26840">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>What does the King intend? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e26870">
              <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
              <l>We cannot tell. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e26900">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>You lye. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e26930">
              <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
              <l>Why shou'd we lye? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e26960">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>'Cause ye are Priests. </l>
              <l>It is your Trade to lye, you live by lies. </l>
              <l>Your Temples are your shops where you sell lyes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e27010">
              <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
              <l>What lyes sell we? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e27040">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Why, any lyes you please; </l>
              <l>Fools take 'em off your hands at any rate. </l>
              <l>You Cheats, you Murderers, you Quacks of Hell, </l>
              <l>You keep mankind diseas'd to vend your Drugs. </l>
              <l>The King was cur'd of his disease, Revenge, </l>
              <l>And you have sold him some Religious lye, </l>
              <l>Has poyson'd him with Cruelty again: </l>
              <l>And I among you shall be murder'd here— </l>
              <l>Barb'rously murder'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e27150">
              <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
              <l>Who shou'd murder you? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e27180">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Need I doubt that, when I am among Priests. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e27210">
              <speaker>Priests. </speaker>
              <l>Why do you wrong us thus? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e27240">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>How, I wrong you? </l>
              <l>Can any one wrong Priests? Kings wrong themselves </l>
              <l>And all the world, they do not hang you all. </l>
              <l>For Kings are never safe, nor Subjects good, </l>
              <l>Where Priests prevail; you keep the Power of Kings, </l>
              <l>And only let 'em have what share you please. </l>
              <l>You take the foolish peoples Consciences, </l>
              <pb n="43" xml:id="ep000511-026-b"/>
              <l>And give 'em back what honesty you please; </l>
              <l>You keep the Keys of Womens Chambers too, </l>
              <l>And let men have what share in 'em you please: </l>
              <l>When you deliver up a Marriage Lock, </l>
              <l>You still reserve a Key for your own use: </l>
              <l>But Men or Women may play any game, </l>
              <l>And cheat their fill, if they will pay your Box. </l>
              <l>Oh! my <hi>Antigone! Antigone</hi>! </l>
              <l>Thou little think'st thy beautious Eyes have had </l>
              <l>Their last, last view of poor Philisthenes, </l>
              <l>A bloudy Carcass, or a moaning Ghost </l>
              <l>Is all that ever thou wilt see of me; </l>
              <l>For I am in Priests hands, and the world knows </l>
              <l>How little they will leave of what they grasp. </l>
              <l>Why do you use me thus, you Murderers? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e27500">
              <speaker>Pr. </speaker>
              <l>You wrong us, we abhor the bloody name. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e27530">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Will you not murder me? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e27560">
              <speaker>Pr. </speaker>
              <l>We'l rather dye. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e27590">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Nor aid the King to do't? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e27620">
              <speaker>Pr. </speaker>
              <l>Nor aid the King: </l>
              <l>But we must sacrifice you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e27660">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! you Dogs; </l>
              <l>What differs that from murder but in name? </l>
              <l>Oh! how these Villains cheat the world with names? </l>
              <l>Were Wolves, or Lyons e're the tamer Beasts, </l>
              <l>For being call'd Lambs, give murders, Massacres, </l>
              <l>Good names, they are transform'd to ex'lent works. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e27740">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>The King has vowed you to th'infernal Gods. </l>
              <l>And 'tis our duty to assist his Vows. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e27780">
              <speaker>Pr. </speaker>
              <l>And shou'd the people enter into Leagues, </l>
              <l>And vow the King to the infernal Gods, </l>
              <l>For money you wou'd aid their hellish Vows, </l>
              <l>And curse all honest men that wou'd not aid. </l>
              <l>Religion's made by you a Lottery Book, </l>
              <l>Which cheats the world of every thing they have. </l>
              <l>Oh! Gods! deliver poor mankind from Priests: </l>
              <l>But oh! who can deliver wretched me? </l>
              <l>For I am in their dark Dominion here; </l>
              <l>One of Hells strongest frontier Garrisons. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="44" xml:id="ep000511-027-a"/>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e27900">Enter Atreus. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e27920">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Philisthenes? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e27950">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Yes, Sir— what is your will? </l>
              <l>Why have you order'd me to be thus bound? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e27990">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>To dye. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e28020">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>For what? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e28050">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Thou art Thyestes Son. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e28090">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>That's not my fault. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e28120">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>But a damn'd fault of his, </l>
              <l>To dare to multiply his cursed self, </l>
              <l>And send a filthy and incestuous Stream </l>
              <l>To poyson all the Ages of the World; </l>
              <l>But here it stops, I'le turn its course to Hell. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e28190">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>I thought y' had pardon'd all my Fathers faults. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e28220">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Thou art a Boy, thy Father is a Fool, </l>
              <l>Peneus a Dotard, all run up to Beard; </l>
              <l>I have ensnar'd you all, to feed my Fiends, </l>
              <l>As men hunt savage Beasts to give their Dogs. </l>
              <l>But Tyrants Furies are so highly fed, </l>
              <l>That mine will scorn the Souls of such damn'd Fools. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e28310">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Y' embrac'd us all with Vows and Oaths and Smiles, </l>
              <l>And promises of everlasting love; </l>
              <l>Can such disguises well become a King? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e28360">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>They are thy Fathers own cast Vizards all. </l>
              <l>He embrac'd me with Vows and Oaths and Smiles, </l>
              <l>Then made my Wife an everlasting Whore. </l>
              <l>Now more— the Caldron and the Fire.— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e28420">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>For what? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e28450">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>To serve thee, as thy Father has serv'd me; </l>
              <l>He has enkindled such a Fire in me, </l>
              <l>As boyls my Flesh in my own scalding bloud. </l>
              <l>I'le boyl thy Heart in thy own purest bloud, </l>
              <l>To treat thy Father at thy Bridal Feast. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e28520">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Hell! all Hell is in your words and looks! </l>
              <l>Why start you not at your own dreadful voice; </l>
              <l>For 'tis a Devils voice, and not a mans; </l>
              <l>And Hell pours all its rage into your Breast. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e28580">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Then Hells an Ass to throw away its rage, </l>
              <pb n="45" xml:id="ep000511-027-b"/>
              <l>On a heart, full as it cou'd hold before▪ </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e28620">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! horrour! </l>
              <l>Are these my Nuptial joys? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e28660">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Such as thy Fathers fins provided thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e28690">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! my <hi>Antigone! Antigone</hi>! </l>
              <l>Tyrant thank her for all the tears I shed. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e28740">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Canst thou be tortur'd with the loss of her? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e28770">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>More than with all thou canst inflict besides. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e28800">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>By all thy torment then, guess half of mine, </l>
              <l>Thou losest but the half of what thou lov'st, </l>
              <l>Only her sight a while, and with no shame. </l>
              <l>My Aerope was once as dear to me; </l>
              <l>Her Heart was stollen, and body whor'd for me, </l>
              <l>That I have lost all of her, and with all shame. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e28890">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>I must acknowledge, Sir, your wrongs are great </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e28920">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>And my revenge shall equal all my wrongs. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e28950">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>But why on me? unless you mean to spare </l>
              <l>My Father; and if so, pour all on me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e28990">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>I cannot wound they Father, but through thee </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e29020">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! spare me! spare me! for your own sake </l>
              <l>See the Gods threaten you in Prodigies. </l>
              <l>Your Palace nods to bid you have a care. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e29070">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>My Palace shakes for fear of its own Fate; </l>
              <l>It did assist thy Father in his Crimes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e29110">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>The Temple Columns bend, to beg my life. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e29140">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Did Gods come down to beg thy hated Life, </l>
              <l>Into their Faces I wou'd spurt thy blood. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e29180">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Then you'l not mind their weeping Images; </l>
              <l>Like frightned women in cold sweats they reel. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e29220">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Let frightned women mind 'em. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e29250">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Th' Angry Gods </l>
              <l>Dart fiery Javelins fiercely at your Head, </l>
              <l>But miss it, 'cause their hands with horrour shake. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e29300">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Then I am here the only thing unmov'd, </l>
              <l>And I dare do, what nothing dare behold. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e29340">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Yes Tyrant, I dare see, and suffer too, </l>
              <l>With greater courage, all thou canst inflict, </l>
              <l>Than thou darst look on thy own frightful Soul. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e29390">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>How now! what is this? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e29420">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>This is Philisthenes, </l>
              <l>Tyrant, thou never spok'st with me till now. </l>
              <pb n="46" xml:id="ep000511-028-a"/>
              <l>The wretched thing that tumbled at thy feet, </l>
              <l>Was but a Garment which thou kep'st in pawn▪ </l>
              <l>Whilst my Soul went to see <hi>Antigone▪ </hi>
              </l>
              <l>And take its leave; but now I am come home, </l>
              <l>My Breast will meet thy Dagger when it dares. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e29530">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>I thank you Gods I did not kill this Boy, </l>
              <l>For of the sudden he is grown a man. </l>
              <l>Come Priests. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e29580">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>I, ever while you live call Priests, </l>
              <l>If you wou'd have a solemn murder done. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e29620">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Bind with a purple band the Victims head: </l>
              <l>Perpare the Incense, Fire, Knife, wine and Meal. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e29660">
              <speaker>Phi. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! spare your pains, Priests are not to be taught </l>
              <l>The way to murder Princes decently, </l>
              <l>As to your sorrow you may quickly find </l>
              <l>If any Rebels shall e're need your blood. </l>
              <l>But I will give the remnant of my breath </l>
              <l>In one full sigh to dear Antigone! </l>
              <l>What have I suffer'd long for a short hope, </l>
              <l>Which in a moment perishes with me? </l>
              <l>A short sweet hope was all I had of thee; </l>
              <l>And a long mournful memory will be all </l>
              <l>Thou, dear Antigone, wilt have of me. </l>
              <l>But I will render it so glorious, </l>
              <l>Thou shalt not be quite void of Nuptial joys, </l>
              <l>As I am not in hopes thou all thy life </l>
              <l>Wilt love my name, as I dye sighing thine, </l>
              <l>Antigone! oh! my <hi>Antigone▪ </hi>
              </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e29880">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Then dye!— 'tis done— 'tis well— 'tis excellent. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e29910">
              <hi>[Atr. </hi>stabs Phi. he falls. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e29940">
              <l>So now Thyestes I shall bring thee in </l>
              <l>A dreadfull score for all thy pleasant sin; </l>
              <l>Much dost thou owe me, and much shalt thou pay; </l>
              <l>Gods ask of him the blood is shed to day. </l>
              <l>I lodg'd the Traytor, and he rob'd my throne, </l>
              <l>And whor'd my Wife, for which I seize his Son, </l>
              <l>If you have title to the blood that's lost, </l>
              <l>Pursue the Robber, not the plunder'd Host. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e30040">[Ex. </stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="ep000511-e30050">
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="ep000511-e30060">
            <pb n="47" xml:id="ep000511-028-b"/>
            <head>ACT V. SCENE V. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e30080">Enter Atreus and Thyestes. A Table and Banquet. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e30110">SCENE the Court. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e30130">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>COme Brother sit; </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e30160">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>May not Philistenes </l>
              <l>Sit with us, Sir? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e30210">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>He waits upon the Bride. </l>
              <l>The Queen, the Bride, and Ladies are all sat; </l>
              <l>They are before-hand with us, let us haste </l>
              <l>To overtake 'em. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e30270">[Atr. and Thy. sit. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e30300">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Let us bless the Feast </l>
              <l>With the Brides health— Sir, to the fair Brides health. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e30340">[Both drink. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e30350">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>My most dear Brother, I will do you right. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e30380">Musique. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e30390">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>A deeper bowl; this to the Bridegrooms health. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e30420">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>This to the Gods for this most joyful day, </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e30450">
                <hi>[Thy. </hi>pours some wine on the ground, both drink. </stage>
              <l>Now to the Bridegrooms health. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e30480">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>This day shall be </l>
              <l>To Argos an Eternal Festival. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e30530">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Fortune and I to day try both our strengths, </l>
              <l>I have quite tyr'd her left-hand misery, </l>
              <l>She now relieves it with her right-hand joy, </l>
              <l>Which she lays on me with her utmost force; </l>
              <l>But both shall be too weak for my strong Spirit. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e30600">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>So! now my Engines of delight have scru'd </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e30630">Aside. </stage>
              <l>The Monster to the top of Arrogance, </l>
              <l>And now he's ready for his deadly fall. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e30660">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! these extreams of misery and joy, </l>
              <l>Measure the vast extent of a mans Soul, </l>
              <l>My Spirit reaches Fortunes East and West. </l>
              <pb n="48" xml:id="ep000511-029-a"/>
              <l>She has ost set and risen here, yet cannot get </l>
              <l>Out of the vast Dominion of my mind. </l>
              <l>Ha! my proud vaunting has a sudden check; </l>
              <l>See! from my Head my Crown of Roses falls. </l>
              <l>My Hair, though almost drown'd beneath sweet Oyls, </l>
              <l>With strange and sudden horrours starts upright. </l>
              <l>Something, I know not what, bids me not eat; </l>
              <l>And what I have devour'd, within me groans, </l>
              <l>I fain wou'd tear my breast to set it free. </l>
              <l>And I have catch'd the eager thirst of tears, </l>
              <l>Which all weak Spirits have in misery; </l>
              <l>I who in banishment ne're wept, weep now. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e30830">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Brother regard it not, 'tis fancy all. </l>
              <l>Misery like night is haunted with ill Spirits, </l>
              <l>And Spirits leave not easily then haunts▪ </l>
              <l>'Tis said, sometimes they'l impudently stand </l>
              <l>A flight of beams from the forlorn of day, </l>
              <l>And scorn the Crowing of the Sprightly Cocks: </l>
              <l>Brother 'tis morning with our pleasure yet, </l>
              <l>Nor has the sprightly Wine Crow'd oft enough; </l>
              <l>See in great Flaggons at full length it sleeps, </l>
              <l>And lets these melancholly thoughts break in </l>
              <l>Upon our weaker pleasures, rouze the Wine, </l>
              <l>And bid him chase these fancies hence for shame, </l>
              <l>Fill up that reverend unvanqush'd bowl, </l>
              <l>Who many a Gyant in his time has fallen, </l>
              <l>And many a Monster, Hercules. 〈…〉. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31010">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>If he descends into my groaning breast, </l>
              <l>Like Hercules, he will descend to Hell. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31060">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>And he will vanquish all the Monsters there. </l>
              <l>Brother, your courage with this Hero try; </l>
              <l>He o're our house has reign'd two hundred years, </l>
              <l>And he's the only King shall rule you here. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31120">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>What ails me? I cannot heave it to my Lips. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31150">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>What▪ is the bowl too heavy? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31180">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>No, my heart. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31210">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>The Wine will lighten it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31240">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>The Wine will not </l>
              <l>Come near my Lips. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31280">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Why shou'd they be so strange? </l>
              <pb n="49" xml:id="ep000511-029-b"/>
              <l>They'r near a kinne. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31320">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>A kinne? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31350">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>As possible, Father and Son not nearer? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31380">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>What do you mean? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31410">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Does not good Wine beget good blood? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31440">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis true. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31470">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Your Lips then and the Wine may be a kin. </l>
              <l>Off with your kindred Wine, leave not a drop </l>
              <l>To dye alone, bewildred in that bowle. </l>
              <l>Help him to heave it to his Head, that's well. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e31530">Thyestes drinks; a clap of Thunder, the Table oversets, and falls in pieces; all the lights go out. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31550">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>What ponderous Crimes pull Heaven on our Heads? </l>
              <l>Nature is choak'd with some vast Villany, </l>
              <l>And all her Face is black. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31600">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Some lights, some lights. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31630">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>The Sky is stun'd, and reels 'tween Night and Day; </l>
              <l>Old Chaos is return'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31680">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>It is to see </l>
              <l>A young one born, more dreadful than her self, </l>
              <l>That promises great comfort to her age, </l>
              <l>And to restore her Empire. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31740">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>What do you mean? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31770">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Confusion I have in thy bowels made. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31800">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Dire thoughts, like Furies, break into my mind </l>
              <l>With flaming brands, and shew me what he means. </l>
              <l>Where is Philisthenes? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31860">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Ask thy own bowels: </l>
              <l>Thou heardst 'em groan, perhaps they now will speak. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31900">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Thou hast not Tyrant— what?— I dare not ask— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31930">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>I kill'd thy Son, and thou hast drunk his blood. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e31960">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Villany so vast it broke the Poles; </l>
              <l>And through the spacious flaw, Hell rush'd on Earth. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e32000">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Thy groaning bowels call'd up Hell to Earth; </l>
              <l>Wild beasts will follow one anothers howles. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e32040">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Hell came to have an interview with thee, </l>
              <l>The greater Monster; one whose Villany </l>
              <l>Has scar'd away the Sun; he wou'd depose </l>
              <pb n="50" xml:id="ep000511-030-a"/>
              <l>Himself, e're lend thy wickedness his light. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e32100">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>E're lend my Justice,— but he cou'd lend all </l>
              <l>His wealth to help thee to corrupt my Wife; </l>
              <l>That he and all the Gods may flye for shame; </l>
              <l>They all combin'd to that; Gods step'd the Mouth </l>
              <l>Of blabbing Thunder, left it spoyl'd the sport, </l>
              <l>Nature cou'd see that sight, and not be sick, </l>
              <l>Nor in disorder rowl; as she does now. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e32190">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>I must confess, thy impious self, or I </l>
              <l>Wou'd make Hell strain to out do us in sin; </l>
              <l>But of the three thou art the overmatch, </l>
              <l>For Hell has bounds, thy wickedness has none. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e32250">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>My just rewards of wickedness have none. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e32280">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Gods! If I deserve this punishment, </l>
              <l>Revenge the Heavens plunder'd of their light: </l>
              <l>Compose of lightning a false dreadful day, </l>
              <l>And take no aim, but dart it at us both; </l>
              <l>Hit one of us, and tis no matter which, </l>
              <l>You strike the wickedst man that lives on Earth. </l>
              <l>You will be merciful in burning me, </l>
              <l>Make me become my dear Son's Funeral pile. </l>
              <l>All Gods have left us but the Powers of Hell, </l>
              <l>Those only are fit to bear us Company; </l>
              <l>And with a Sword I fear to end my grief, </l>
              <l>Left I in my own bosom stab my Son. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e32420">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>I never had thee in my power till now; </l>
              <l>I had thy Fortune, Children, and thy Life; </l>
              <l>But now these tears confess I have thy Soul, </l>
              <l>And now I'm well rewarded for my pains. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e32480">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>If now I shou'd not grieve, I were no man; </l>
              <l>But a more horrid Monster than thy self. </l>
              <l>What was my poor Sons fault? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e32530">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>That he was thine. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e32560">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>And being mine, wou'dst thou give me, give me </l>
              <l>His blood to drink? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e32600">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Who injur'd me but thee? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e32630">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Bear witness Gods! he owns the innocence </l>
              <l>Of this poor Youth, whose bloud he made me drink? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e32670">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>What Gods? the Guardians of Nuptial Beds? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e32700">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Must sin with sin be punish'd? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e32730">
              <pb n="51" xml:id="ep000511-030-b"/>
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>No, that sin </l>
              <l>Becomes a Vertue, that chastises sin. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e32770">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! my poor Son! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e32800">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>All these are tears of rage, </l>
              <l>'Cause I' a aforehand with thee in this sin. </l>
              <l>Thou with my Children wou'dst have treated me, </l>
              <l>But that thou wert afraid they were thy own </l>
              <l>Incestuous Bastards all. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e32870">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>I' ve done with thee, </l>
              <l>And leave thee to the Gods for punishment. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e32910">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>But I've not done with thee; for though thy eyes </l>
              <l>Please me with weeping, so they shall not scape. </l>
              <l>The sight of the remainders of thy Son, </l>
              <l>And of her death thou lov'st above thy Son, </l>
              <l>Shall tear 'em out, and then the work's compleat. </l>
              <l>Open the Temple Gates, and call the Queen. </l>
              <l>You mingled Lusts, now you shall mingle pains, </l>
              <l>And through your Eyes, the passage of your Lusts. </l>
              <l>Here shew the Father the Sons torn remains. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e33020">[The Temple is open, Philisthenes lyes bloudy. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e33040">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! my Philisthenes! my mangled Son! </l>
              <l>Had ever Hell such cruelty as this? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e33090">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Nor man such Treason and such lust as thine, </l>
              <l>Nor injur'd Monarch such revenge as I. </l>
              <l>Thy former Villany, and present Tears, </l>
              <l>I'le cast in Brass, and in Effigie </l>
              <l>I'le drag thee round all ages of the world. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e33160">Enter Antigone in a raving posture, women offer to hold her. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e33180">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Stand off, I am not mad, but I shall be, </l>
              <l>If this be true; it never can be true, </l>
              <l>Oh! Sir, I've heard— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e33230">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>What have you heard? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e33260">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Gods! </l>
              <l>Oh! horrour!— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e33300">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>What's the matter with you?— speak! </l>
              <l>What have you heard? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e33340">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>You have Kill'd Philisthenes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e33380">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>There was no secret love between you? ha? </l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="54" xml:id="ep000511-031-a"/>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e33410">Enter Aerope, between her two Children Agamemon and Menelaus. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e33450">
              <speaker>Aero. </speaker>
              <l>What is the matter both with Heaven and Earth? </l>
              <l>For every Face below is white as Death, </l>
              <l>And Heavens Face above is black as Hell. </l>
              <l>Sir, you was pleas'd to send for me they say? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e33510">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>I did. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e33540">
              <speaker>Aero. </speaker>
              <l>But I had come if you had not. </l>
              <l>I was with my two little pretty Sons, </l>
              <l>My Agamemnon, and my Menelaus. </l>
              <l>When of the sudden, with a thousand groans, </l>
              <l>The Air brought forth a monstrous Shade, as black </l>
              <l>As Hell had vomited a Lake of Pitch. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e33640">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Thy sins were then in labour, and brought forth </l>
              <l>This bloody Vengeance. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e33680">
              <speaker>Aero. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! most dreadful sight! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e33710">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>The worst I ever saw, except thy self. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e33740">
              <speaker>Aero. </speaker>
              <l>My Child is murder'd! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e33770">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>By thy own lust. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e33800">
              <speaker>Aero. </speaker>
              <l>No, by thy Perjury, inhumane Prince. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e33830">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>How durst thou name, or think of Perjury. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e33860">
              <speaker>Aero. </speaker>
              <l>That Villain clear'd the innocence the wrong'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e33890">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>I never will believe either him or thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e33920">
              <speaker>Aero. </speaker>
              <l>This bloody spectacle says that too loud. </l>
              <l>I see a Dagger in my poor Childs hand. </l>
              <l>I thank thee Daughter for this Legacy. </l>
              <l>Now hear me Gods, for hear me well you may; </l>
              <l>Born high on Innocence, I reach your Throne, </l>
              <l>If e're in thought I yielded to that sin, </l>
              <l>For which I suffer so much misery; </l>
              <l>Kindle a Hell o' purpose for my Soul: </l>
              <l>But if I undeserv'd have born all this, </l>
              <l>Then build a Heaven fit for my reward, </l>
              <l>And I will lay the first Foundation Stone. </l>
              <l>Thus, thus, thus; </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e34060">[She stabs Thy. </stage>
              <l>Nay Villain I will lay you firm. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e34090">[Stabs Thy. several times. </stage>
              <l>This for the loss of my dear Husband's Love: </l>
              <l>This for the loss of my dear Daughters Life: </l>
              <pb n="55" xml:id="ep000511-031-b"/>
              <l>This for the ruin of my honest Name: </l>
              <l>This for my Life I am about to lose. </l>
              <l>Now I have done my self this little right, </l>
              <l>I can with comfort dye!— oh! Sir, farewell; </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e34170">
                <hi>[To </hi>Atr. </stage>
              <l>You loose a faithful Wife, what e're you think, </l>
              <l>Made by great wrongs unfit for your embrace </l>
              <l>But most deserving your kind memory. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e34220">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Sir! come here and see your workmanship. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e34250">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! my deluded miserable age! </l>
              <l>Have I toyl'd fourscore years for Innocence, </l>
              <l>And am I made a murderer at last? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e34300">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Hence Hypocrite! thou never hadst conceal'd </l>
              <l>My lewd and Trait'rous Brother in thy House, </l>
              <l>So nurtur'd all his horrid sins, when born, </l>
              <l>But that thou wert a bawd to 'em before. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e34360">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>An ex'lent thing it is to serve your house. </l>
              <l>For Charity to him I'm call'd a bawd; </l>
              <l>For serving you I'm made a Murderer. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e34410">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>For serving my revenge I give thee Life; </l>
              <l>But for concealing him, thy feeble Life </l>
              <l>I cumber with the load of all this blood. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e34460">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>The scarlet Livery of your Family; </l>
              <l>I wear your badge; Furies will know me now, </l>
              <l>They are the Stewards of your Family, </l>
              <l>They'l pay me all the wages I deserve. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e34520">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Go, for thy wages then— to Hell— begone— </l>
              <l>Begone I say, and see my Face no more. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e34560">
              <speaker>Pen. </speaker>
              <l>Wou'd I had never seen the face of you, </l>
              <l>Or any of your impious Family. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e34600">
              <hi>[Ex. </hi>Pen. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e34620">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Thrust the old Traytour out, away with him. </l>
              <l>I do no more by him, then Gods by me; </l>
              <l>For I am driven by them from plague to plague. </l>
              <l>Man is a vagabond both poor and proud, </l>
              <l>He treads on beasts who give him Cloaths and Food. </l>
              <l>But the Gods catch him wheresoe're he lurks, </l>
              <l>Whip him, and set him to all painful works. </l>
              <l>And yet he brags he shall be crown'd when dead, </l>
              <l>Were ever Princes in a Bridewell bred? </l>
              <l>Nothing is sinfully begot but he; </l>
              <l>Can baseborn Bastards lawful Soveraigns be? </l>
              <pb n="52" xml:id="ep000511-032-a"/>
              <l>Confess it, was there? have you been so false? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e34760">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Sir, you fill my heart with dreadful fears: </l>
              <l>The news is true— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e34800">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>What's true?— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e34830">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>That you have kill'd— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e34860">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>That you have lov'd my Enemy?— is that true?— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e34890">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>He is not, never was your Enemy. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e34920">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>But did you love him? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e34950">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Yes above my Soul. </l>
              <l>We both lov'd long, above expression lov'd, </l>
              <l>Unknown to any but our faithful selves. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e35000">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Hast thou abus'd me so? why then let that </l>
              <l>Which has thy Lover take thy Soul. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e35040">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>What's that? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e35070">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>What shou'd have damn'd Thyestes Son, but Hell? </l>
              <l>If thou wilt take Hells leavings there thou mayst. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e35120">Atr. points to <hi>Phi. Ant. </hi>runs to him and falls at his feet in a Swoun. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e35150">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! my Philisthenes! my murder'd Love? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e35190">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>And, oh! my murder'd hopes! I thought this Maid </l>
              <l>Had Vertues wou'd support our falling House; </l>
              <l>I thought o'her side I was thunder proof, </l>
              <l>And she's as false as any of our Race, </l>
              <l>A Traytress to her Father and her King. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e35260">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Now 'tis my turn, fell Tyrant▪ to insult, </l>
              <l>Thou hast devour'd thy own beloved Child </l>
              <l>As well as I, the Gods have given my heart </l>
              <l>This Cordial of Revenge before I dye. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e35320">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>She's none of mine. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e35350">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>May they be curst that wake thee from this Dream, </l>
              <l>Till thou hast shed thy Daughters innocent blood. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e35390">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! horrour! horrour! my Philisthenes </l>
              <l>All mangled, torn, and gory!— horrour— oh! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e35440">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>How durst thou, Traytress, love my Enemy. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e35470">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>He had more worth than all our Race besides, </l>
              <l>None of our Race did e're deserve to live, </l>
              <l>But this sweet Youth, and me for loving him. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e35520">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>How dar'st thou talk thus? Fond Idolatrous Fool! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e35550">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>After this murder, what have I to fear? </l>
              <l>Nothing but Life, and keeping of my Wits. </l>
              <pb n="53" xml:id="ep000511-032-b"/>
              <l>Oh! with these words you have more cut my heart, </l>
              <l>Than had you pierc'd it with a thousand Swords; </l>
              <l>For now I find 'twas I shed all this blood. </l>
              <l>Oh! Gods! oh Father! oh Philisthenes, </l>
              <l>What have I spyed? The Knife that kill'd my Love? </l>
              <l>Oh! you good Gods! </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e35660">[Aside. </stage>
              <l>I thought a Priest shou'd once have joyn'd our hands; </l>
              <l>But now this Knife shall mingle our hearts blood. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e35690">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>What art thou doing there? thy looks are wild, </l>
              <l>I like 'em not— to thy Apartment— go, </l>
              <l>I can repair thy loss, but the whole world </l>
              <l>Can never repair mine, shou'd I lose thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e35750">
              <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
              <l>I have so wounded my obedience, </l>
              <l>By loving that dear Youth without your leave, </l>
              <l>That 'tis too weak to hold my mighty grief, </l>
              <l>Which forces me to dye without your leave. </l>
              <l>Besides, Sir, all the Gods have call'd me hence, </l>
              <l>And sent their pleasure by this Instrument. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000511-e35830">[Stabs her self. </stage>
              <l>I come Philisthenes— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e35860">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! hold her hand— </l>
              <l>Too late, too late, </l>
              <l>The Fatal blow is given; </l>
              <l>Where had she that accursed Instrument? </l>
              <l>She's past recovery! oh! my dear Child. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e35930">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! you just Gods!— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e35960">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Incestuous Traytor peace, </l>
              <l>Thy Villany did help to murder her, </l>
              <l>Thy guilt is greater, and I'm more enrag'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e36010">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>I scorn thy rage, for what have I to fear? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e36040">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Look here, and think what thou hast not to fear. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e36070">[Pointing to Ant. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e36090">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>Ay, but look there, and what have I to fear? </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e36120">[Pointing to Phi. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e36140">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>An age of lingring torments. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e36170">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>That I bear </l>
              <l>In this one minutes sight of that poor Youth. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e36210">
              <speaker>Atr. </speaker>
              <l>Then I will add. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000511-e36240">
              <speaker>Thy. </speaker>
              <l>New will refresh with change. </l>
              <pb n="54" xml:id="ep000511-033-a"/>
              <gap extent="1" reason="duplicate" unit="pages"/>
              <pb n="55" xml:id="ep000511-033-b"/>
              <gap extent="1" reason="duplicate" unit="pages"/>
              <pb n="56" xml:id="ep000511-034-a"/>
              <l>That Tyrant then does best, who uses worst, </l>
              <l>A mutinous Impostour, so accurst: </l>
              <l>I'le breed with care these Boys for mischiefs born, </l>
              <l>That men may feel new Rods when th' old is worn. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000511-e36350">[E 〈…〉 </stage>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="epilogue" xml:id="ep000511-e36370">
        <head>Epilogue. </head>
        <sp xml:id="ep000511-e36390">
          <l>WE shewed you in the Priests to day, a true </l>
          <l>And perfect Picture of old Rome and new; </l>
          <l>One Face serves both; Pagan and Popish Priests </l>
          <l>Are but two names for the same bloody Beasts. </l>
          <l>Wonder not Poets ne're with Priests agree, </l>
          <l>For Priests invade the Poet's Property. </l>
          <l>Lying belongs to Poets; as appears </l>
          <l>By old Prescriptions of three thousand years; </l>
          <l>And Priests permit none but themselves to lye, </l>
          <l>Or those that do't by Church-Authority: </l>
          <l>Nay, they'l impose their lyes on you for true, </l>
          <l>Which honest Poets ne're presum'd to do. </l>
          <l>They talk of being inspired, but do most care, </l>
          <l>To have you be such Fools to think they are. </l>
          <l>But when Priests meet in Councels, Synods, Classes, </l>
          <l>They feign wou'd have you think Heaven Mounts the Asses. </l>
          <l>The Devil rides 'em very oft 'tis true▪ </l>
          <l>When he has any cursed work to do; </l>
          <l>But they have this damn'd fault in ways of sin, </l>
          <l>They run so fast the Devil can't hold 'em in. </l>
          <l>Then halter Priests, and tye 'em to the racks, </l>
          <l>If you will keep the Devil off their backs: </l>
          <l>But pray let Poets live, for they no ways </l>
          <l>Offend you with damn'd Plots, but in their Plays, </l>
          <l>And ask but half a Crown for holding forth, </l>
          <l>And that's as much as any lye is worth. </l>
        </sp>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
        <pb xml:id="ep000511-034-b"/>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
