<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000822" xml:lang="eng">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     Certaine small poems lately printed with the tragedie of Philotas. Written by Samuel Daniel.
    </title>
    <title>
     Selections
    </title>
    <author>
     <!--Daniel, Samuel-->
     <persName>
      <forename>
       Samuel
      </forename>
      <surname>
       Daniel
      </surname>
     </persName>
    </author>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher xml:id="dracor">
     DraCor
    </publisher>
    <idno type="URL">
     https://dracor.org/
    </idno>
    <availability>
     <licence>
      <ab>
       CC0 1.0
      </ab>
      <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
       Licence
      </ref>
     </licence>
    </availability>
    <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl type="digitalSource">
     <name>
      EarlyPrint Project
     </name>
     <idno type="URL">
      https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A19812_00.xml
     </idno>
     <availability>
      <p>
       This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is available for reuse, according to the terms of
       <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
        Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
       </ref>
       . The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
      </p>
     </availability>
     <bibl type="originalSource">
      <biblFull>
       <titleStmt>
        <title>
         Certaine small poems lately printed with the tragedie of Philotas. Written by Samuel Daniel.
        </title>
        <title>
         Selections
        </title>
        <author>
         Daniel, Samuel, 1562-1619.
        </author>
       </titleStmt>
       <extent>
        [224] p.
       </extent>
       <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>
         Printed by G. Eld for Simon Waterson [and Edward Blount],
        </publisher>
        <pubPlace>
         At London :
        </pubPlace>
        <date>
         1605.
        </date>
       </publicationStmt>
       <notesStmt>
        <note>
         Signatures: A-H; A-F.
        </note>
        <note>
         H8 and the last two leaves are blank; &#185;A1,2 are blank except for signature-marks.
        </note>
        <note>
         "The tragedie of Philotas" has separate register and title page with imprint: At London printed by G.E. for Simon Waterson and Edward Blount. 1605.
        </note>
        <note>
         Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
        </note>
       </notesStmt>
      </biblFull>
     </bibl>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
   <profileDesc>
    <textClass>
     <classCode scheme="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">
      Q80930
     </classCode>
    </textClass>
    <particDesc>
     <listPerson>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-pro">
       <persName>
        Pro
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-caes">
       <persName>
        Caes,
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-sy">
       <persName>
        Sy
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-cle">
       <persName>
        Cle
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-syr">
       <persName>
        Syr
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-seleu">
       <persName>
        Seleu
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-dol">
       <persName>
        Dol
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-cel">
       <persName>
        Cel
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-arius">
       <persName>
        Arius
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-syrvlisses">
       <persName>
        Syr. Vlisses,
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-nuntius">
       <persName>
        Nuntius
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-cho">
       <persName>
        Cho
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-ari">
       <persName>
        Ari
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-rod">
       <persName>
        Rod
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-tit">
       <persName>
        Tit
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-nun">
       <persName>
        Nun
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-caesar">
       <persName>
        Caesar
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-nu">
       <persName>
        Nu
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-cleopatra">
       <persName>
        Cleopatra
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-cleo">
       <persName>
        Cleo:
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-proc">
       <persName>
        Proc
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-syren">
       <persName>
        Syren
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-vlis">
       <persName>
        Vlis
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-phi">
       <persName>
        Phi
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-chorvs">
       <persName>
        CHORVS
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-sel">
       <persName>
        Sel
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000822-sl">
       <persName>
        S&#9679;l
       </persName>
      </person>
     </listPerson>
    </particDesc>
   </profileDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <standOff>
  <listEvent>
   <event type="written" when="1605">
    <desc/>
   </event>
  </listEvent>
 </standOff>
 <text>
  <front>
   <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000822-e10">
    <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000822-001-a"/>
    <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000822-001-b"/>
    <p>
     CERTAINE SMALL POEMS LATELY PRINTED: with the Tragedie of Philotas.
    </p>
    <p>
     Written by SAMVEL DANIEL.
    </p>
    <q>
     Carmen amat, quisquis carmine digna gerit.
    </q>
    <p>
     AT LONDON Printed by
     <hi>
      G. Eld
     </hi>
     for
     <hi>
      Simon Waterson
     </hi>
     . 1605.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000822-e90">
    <pb xml:id="ep000822-002-a"/>
    <pb xml:id="ep000822-002-b"/>
    <head>
     To the right Honourable and most vertuous Ladie, the Ladie Margaret Countesse of Cumberland.
    </head>
    <l>
     ALthough the meaner sort (whose thoughts are plac'd
    </l>
    <l>
     As in another region, farre below
    </l>
    <l>
     The Sphere of greatnesse) cannot rightly taste
    </l>
    <l>
     What touch it hath, nor right her passions know:
    </l>
    <l>
     Yet haue I here aduentur'd to bestow
    </l>
    <l>
     Words vpon griefe, as my griefes comprehend,
    </l>
    <l>
     And made this great afflicted Ladie show
    </l>
    <l>
     Out of my feelings, what she might haue pend.
    </l>
    <l>
     And here the same, I bring forth, to attend
    </l>
    <l>
     Vpon thy reuerent name, to liue with thee
    </l>
    <l>
     Most vertuous Ladie, that vouchsaf'st to lend
    </l>
    <l>
     Eare to my notes, and comfort vnto me,
    </l>
    <l>
     That one day may thine owne faire vertues spread
    </l>
    <l>
     Be'ing Secretarie now, but to the dead.
    </l>
   </div>
   <div type="argument" xml:id="ep000822-e250">
    <pb xml:id="ep000822-003-a"/>
    <pb xml:id="ep000822-003-b"/>
    <head>
     The Argument.
    </head>
    <p>
     VPon the second agreement (the first being broken through iealousie of a disproportion of eminencie) betweene the
     <hi>
      Triumuiri Octauius Caesar, Marcus Antonius,
     </hi>
     and
     <hi>
      Lepidus: Octauia
     </hi>
     the sister of
     <hi>
      Octauius Caesar
     </hi>
     , was maried to Antonius, as a linke to combine that which neuer yet, the greatest strength of nature, or anie power of nearest respect could long hold togither, who made but the instrument of others endes, and deliuered vp as an Ostage to serue the oportunity of aduantages, met not with that integritie she brought: but as highly preferred to affliction encountred with all the greeuances that beat vpon the misery of greatnesse, exposed to stand betwixt the diuers tending humours of vnquiet parties. For Antonie hauing yet vpon him the fetters of AEgipt, layde on by the power of a most incomparable beauty, could admit no new lawes into the state of his affection, or dispose of himselfe being not himselfe, but as hauing his heart turned Eastward whither the point of his desires were directed, toucht with the strongest allurements that ambition, and a licencious soueraintie could draw a man vnto: could not truly descend to the priuate loue
     <pb xml:id="ep000822-004-a"/>
     of a ciuill nurtred. Matrone, whose entertainment bounded with modesty and the nature of her education, knew not to cloth her affections in any other colours then the plain habit of truth: wherein she euer suted al her actions&#9679; and vsed all her best ornaments of honesty, to win the good liking of him that helde her but as a Curtaine drawne betweene him and Octauius to shadow his other purposes withall; which the sharpe sight of an equally iealous ambition could soone pierce into, &amp; as easily looke thorow and ouer bloud and nature as he to abuse it: And therefore to preuent his aspiring, he armes his forces either to reduce Antonie to the ranke of his estate, or else to disranke him out of state and al. When Octauia by the imployment of Antonie (as being not yet ready to put his fortune to her triall) throwes her selfe, great with childe, and a&#9679; big with sorrow, into the trauaile of a most laboursome recon&#9679;iliacion: taking her iourney from the farthest parte of Greece to find Octauius, with whom her care and teares were so good agents that they effected their Commission beyond all expectation, and for that time quite disarmed their wrath, which yet long could not hold so. For Antonius falling into the relaps of his former disease, watching his oportunity got ouer again into Egypt, where he so forgot himselfe, that he quite put off his owne nature, and wholy became a pray to his pleasures, as if hee had wound himselfe out of the respect of Country, bloud &amp; alliance, which gaue to Octauia the cause of much affliction, and to me the Argument of this letter.
    </p>
   </div>
  </front>
  <group>
   <text>
    <body>
     <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000822-e450">
      <pb xml:id="ep000822-004-b"/>
      <head>
       A Letter sent from Octauia to her husband Marcus Antonius into AEgypt.
      </head>
      <lg n="1">
       <head>
        1
       </head>
       <l>
        TO thee (yet deere) though most disloyall Lord,
       </l>
       <l>
        Whom impious loue keeps in a barbarous land,
       </l>
       <l>
        Thy wronged wife Octauia sendeth word
       </l>
       <l>
        Of th'vnkind wounds receiued by thy hand,
       </l>
       <l>
        Great Antony, &#244; let thine eyes afford
       </l>
       <l>
        But to permit thy heart to vnderstand
       </l>
       <l>
        The hurt thou dost, and do but read her teares
       </l>
       <l>
        That still is thine though thou wilt not be hers.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="2">
       <head>
        2
       </head>
       <l>
        Although perhaps, these my complaints may come
       </l>
       <l>
        Whilst thou in th'armes of that incestious Qeeene
       </l>
       <l>
        The staine of Aegypt, and the shame of Rome
       </l>
       <l>
        Shalt dallying sit, and blush to haue them seene:
       </l>
       <l>
        Whilst proud disdainfull she, gessing from whome
       </l>
       <l>
        The message came, and what the cause hath beene,
       </l>
       <l>
        Will scorning say, saith, this comes from your Deere,
       </l>
       <l>
        Now sir you must be shent for staying heere.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="3">
       <head>
        3
       </head>
       <l>
        From her indeed it comes, delitious dame,
       </l>
       <l>
        (Thou royall Concubine, and Queene of lust)
       </l>
       <l>
        Whose armes yet pure, whose brests are void of blame,
       </l>
       <l>
        And whose most lawfull flame proues thine vniust:
       </l>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-005-a"/>
       <l>
        Tis she that sends the message of thy shame,
       </l>
       <l>
        And his vntruth that hath betraid her trust:
       </l>
       <l>
        Pardon, deare lord, from her these sorrows are
       </l>
       <l>
        Whose bed brings neither infamie nor warre.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="4">
       <head>
        4
       </head>
       <l>
        And therefore heare her words, that too too much
       </l>
       <l>
        Hath heard the wronges committed by thy shame;
       </l>
       <l>
        Although at first my trust in thee was such
       </l>
       <l>
        As it held out against the strongest fame;
       </l>
       <l>
        My heart would neuer let in once a touch
       </l>
       <l>
        Of least beliefe, till all confirmd the same:
       </l>
       <l>
        That I was almost last that would belieue
       </l>
       <l>
        Because I know mee first that most must grieue.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="5">
       <head>
        5
       </head>
       <l>
        How oft haue poore abused I tooke parte
       </l>
       <l>
        With falshood onely for to make thee true?
       </l>
       <l>
        How oft haue I argued against my heart
       </l>
       <l>
        Not suffring it to know that which it knew?
       </l>
       <l>
        And for I would not haue thee what thou arte
       </l>
       <l>
        I made my selfe, vnto my selfe vntrue:
       </l>
       <l>
        So much my loue labourd against thy Sinne
       </l>
       <l>
        To shut our feare which yet kept feare within:
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="6">
       <head>
        6
       </head>
       <l>
        For I could neuer thinke th'aspiring mind
       </l>
       <l>
        Of worthy and victorious Antonie,
       </l>
       <l>
        Could be by such a Syren so declinde,
       </l>
       <l>
        As to be traind a pray to Luxury:
       </l>
       <l>
        I could not thinke my Lord would be s&#9679; vnkind
       </l>
       <l>
        As to despise his Children, Rome and me:
       </l>
       <l>
        But &#244; how soone are they deceiued that trust
       </l>
       <l>
        And more their shame, that wilbe so vniust.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="7">
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-005-b"/>
       <head>
        7
       </head>
       <l>
        But now that certaine same hath open laid
       </l>
       <l>
        Thy new relaps, and strange reuolt from mee,
       </l>
       <l>
        Truth hath quite beaten all my hopes away
       </l>
       <l>
        and made the passage of my sorrows free:
       </l>
       <l>
        For now poore hart, there's nothing in the way
       </l>
       <l>
        Remaines to stand betwixt despaire and thee;
       </l>
       <l>
        All is throwne downe, there comes no succors newe
       </l>
       <l>
        It is most true, my Lord is most vntrue.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="8">
       <head>
        8
       </head>
       <l>
        And now I may with shame inough pull in
       </l>
       <l>
        The colours I aduanced in his grace
       </l>
       <l>
        For that subduing powre, that him did win
       </l>
       <l>
        Hath lost me too, the honour of my face:
       </l>
       <l>
        Yet why should I bearing no part of sinne
       </l>
       <l>
        Beare such a mightie part of his disgrace?
       </l>
       <l>
        Yes though it be not mine, it is of mine;
       </l>
       <l>
        And his renowne being clips'd, mine cannot shine,
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="9">
       <head>
        9
       </head>
       <l>
        Which makes me as I do, hide from the eie
       </l>
       <l>
        Of the misiudging vulger that will deeme,
       </l>
       <l>
        That sure there was in me some reason why
       </l>
       <l>
        Which made thee thus, my bed to disesteeme:
       </l>
       <l>
        So that alas poore vndeseruing I
       </l>
       <l>
        A cause of thy vncleane deserts shall seeme,
       </l>
       <l>
        Though lust takes neuer ioy in what is t&#9679;ue,
       </l>
       <l>
        But still leaues known delights to seeke out new.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="10">
       <head>
        10
       </head>
       <l>
        And yet my brother Caesar laboured
       </l>
       <l>
        To haue me leaue thy house, and liue more free,
       </l>
       <l>
        But God forbid, Octauia should be led
       </l>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-006-a"/>
       <l>
        To leaue to liue in thine, though left by thee
       </l>
       <l>
        The pledges here of thy forsaken bed,
       </l>
       <l>
        Are still the obiects that remember me
       </l>
       <l>
        What Antony was once, although false now,
       </l>
       <l>
        And is my Lord, though he neglect his vow.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="11">
       <head>
        11
       </head>
       <l>
        These walles that here do keepe me out of sight
       </l>
       <l>
        Shall keepe me all vnspotted vnto thee,
       </l>
       <l>
        And testifie that I will do thee right,
       </l>
       <l>
        Ile neuer staine thy house, though thou shame me:
       </l>
       <l>
        The now sad Chamber of my once delight
       </l>
       <l>
        Shall be the temple of my pietie
       </l>
       <l>
        Sacred vnto the faith I reuerence,
       </l>
       <l>
        Where I will pay my teares for thy offence.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="12">
       <head>
        12
       </head>
       <l>
        Although my youth, thy absence, and this wrong
       </l>
       <l>
        Might draw my bloud to forfeit vnto shame,
       </l>
       <l>
        Nor need I frustrate my delights so long
       </l>
       <l>
        That haue such meanes to carry so the same,
       </l>
       <l>
        Since that the face of greatnesse is so strong
       </l>
       <l>
        As it dissolues suspect, and beares out blame,
       </l>
       <l>
        Hauing all secret helps that long thereto
       </l>
       <l>
        That seldome wants there ought but will to do:
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="13">
       <head>
        13
       </head>
       <l>
        Which yet to do, ere lust this heart shall frame
       </l>
       <l>
        Earth swallow me aliue, hell rap me hence:
       </l>
       <l>
        Shall I because despisd contemne my shame,
       </l>
       <l>
        And add disgrace to others impudence?
       </l>
       <l>
        What can my powre but giue more powre to fame?
       </l>
       <l>
        Greatnesse must make it great incontinence;
       </l>
       <l>
        Chambers are false, the bed and all will tell,
       </l>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-006-b"/>
       <l>
        No doore keepes in their shame that do not well.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="14">
       <head>
        14
       </head>
       <l>
        Hath greatnesse ought peculiar else alone
       </l>
       <l>
        But to stand faire and bright aboue the base?
       </l>
       <l>
        What doth deuide the cottage from the throne,
       </l>
       <l>
        If vice shall lay both leuell with disgrace?
       </l>
       <l>
        For if vncleannesse make them but all one
       </l>
       <l>
        What priuiledge ha&#9679;h honor by his place?
       </l>
       <l>
        What though our sinnes go braue and better clad,
       </l>
       <l>
        They are as those in rags as base as bad.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="15">
       <head>
        15
       </head>
       <l>
        I know not how, but wrongfully I know
       </l>
       <l>
        Hath vndiscerning custome plac'd our kind
       </l>
       <l>
        Vnder desert, and set vs farre below
       </l>
       <l>
        The reputation to our sexe assign'd;
       </l>
       <l>
        Charging our wrong reputed weakenes, how
       </l>
       <l>
        We are vnconstant, fickle, false, vnkinde:
       </l>
       <l>
        And though our life with thousand proofs shewes no
       </l>
       <l>
        Yet since strength saies it, weaknes must be so.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="16">
       <head>
        16
       </head>
       <l>
        Vnequall partage to b'allow'd no share
       </l>
       <l>
        Of power to do of lifes best benefite;
       </l>
       <l>
        But stand as if we interdicted were
       </l>
       <l>
        Of vertue, action, libertie and might:
       </l>
       <l>
        Must you haue all, and not vouchsafe to spare
       </l>
       <l>
        Our weaknes any intrest of delight?
       </l>
       <l>
        Is there no portion left for vs at all,
       </l>
       <l>
        But sufferance, sorrow, ignorance and thrall?
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="17">
       <head>
        17
       </head>
       <l>
        Thrice happy you in whom it is no fault,
       </l>
       <l>
        To know, to speake, to do, and to be wise:
       </l>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-007-a"/>
       <l>
        Whose words haue credit, and whose deeds though naught
       </l>
       <l>
        Must yet be made to seeme far otherwise:
       </l>
       <l>
        You can be onely heard whilst we are taught
       </l>
       <l>
        To hold our peace, and not to exercise
       </l>
       <l>
        The powers of our best parts, because your parts
       </l>
       <l>
        Haue with our freedome robb'd vs of our hearts,
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="18">
       <head>
        18
       </head>
       <l>
        We in this prison of our selues confin'd
       </l>
       <l>
        Must here shut vp with our own passions liue
       </l>
       <l>
        Turn'd in vpon vs, and denied to find
       </l>
       <l>
        The vent of outward means that might relieue:
       </l>
       <l>
        That they alone must take vp all our mind;
       </l>
       <l>
        And no roome left vs, but to thinke and grieue,
       </l>
       <l>
        Yet oft our narrowed thoughts looke more direct
       </l>
       <l>
        Then your loose wisdoms borne with wild neglect.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="19">
       <head>
        19
       </head>
       <l>
        For should we too (as God forbid we should)
       </l>
       <l>
        Carry no better hand on our desires
       </l>
       <l>
        Then your strength doth; what int'rest could
       </l>
       <l>
        Our wronged patience paie you for your hires?
       </l>
       <l>
        What mixture of strange generations would
       </l>
       <l>
        Succeed the fortunes of vncertaine Sires?
       </l>
       <l>
        What foule confusion in your blood and race
       </l>
       <l>
        To your immortall shame, and our disgrace?
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="20">
       <head>
        20
       </head>
       <l>
        What? are there bars for vs, no bounds for you?
       </l>
       <l>
        Must leuitie stand sure, though firmnes fall?
       </l>
       <l>
        And are you priuiledg'd to be vntrue,
       </l>
       <l>
        And we no grant to be dispens'd withall?
       </l>
       <l>
        Must we inuiolable keepe your due,
       </l>
       <l>
        Both to your loue, and to your falshood thrall?
       </l>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-007-b"/>
       <l>
        Whilst you haue stretch'd your lust vnto your will
       </l>
       <l>
        As if your strength were licenc'd to do ill.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="21">
       <head>
        21
       </head>
       <l>
        O if you be more strong then be more iust
       </l>
       <l>
        Cleere this suspition, make not the world to doubt,
       </l>
       <l>
        Whether in strong, or weake be better trust,
       </l>
       <l>
        If frailry, or else valour be more stout:
       </l>
       <l>
        And if we haue shut in our hearts from lust
       </l>
       <l>
        Let not your bad example let them out,
       </l>
       <l>
        Thinke that there is like &#9679;eeling in our bloud,
       </l>
       <l>
        If you will haue vs good, be you then good.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="22">
       <head>
        22
       </head>
       <l>
        Is it that loue doth take no true delight
       </l>
       <l>
        In what it hath, but still in what it would,
       </l>
       <l>
        Which drawes you on to do vs this vnright,
       </l>
       <l>
        Whilst feare in vs of loosing what we hold
       </l>
       <l>
        Keepes vs in still to you, that set vs light,
       </l>
       <l>
        So that what you vnties, doth vs infold?
       </l>
       <l>
        Then loue tis thou that dost confound vs so
       </l>
       <l>
        To make our truth the occasion of our wo.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="23">
       <head>
        23
       </head>
       <l>
        Distressed woman kind that either must
       </l>
       <l>
        For louing loose your loues, or get neglect;
       </l>
       <l>
        Whilst wantons are more car'd for then the iust
       </l>
       <l>
        And falshood cheerisht, faith without respect:
       </l>
       <l>
        Better she fares in whom is lesser trust,
       </l>
       <l>
        And more is lou'd that is in more suspect.
       </l>
       <l>
        Which (pardon me) shews no great strength of minde
       </l>
       <l>
        To be most theirs, that vse you most vnkinde.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="24">
       <head>
        24
       </head>
       <l>
        Yet well it fit&#9679; for that sinne euer must
       </l>
       <l>
        Be tortur'd with the racke of his owne frame,
       </l>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-008-a"/>
       <l>
        For he that holds no faith shall find no trust:
       </l>
       <l>
        But sowing wrong is sure to reape the same:
       </l>
       <l>
        How can he looke to haue his measure iust
       </l>
       <l>
        That fils deceipt, and reckons not of shame,
       </l>
       <l>
        And being not pleas'd with what he &#9679;ath in lo&#9679;
       </l>
       <l>
        Shall euer pine for that which he hath not?
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="25">
       <head>
        25
       </head>
       <l>
        Yet if thou couldst not loue, thou mightst haue seem'd
       </l>
       <l>
        Though to haue seem'd had likewise beene vniust:
       </l>
       <l>
        Yet so much are leane shewes of vs esteem'd
       </l>
       <l>
        That oft they feed, though not suffice our trust,
       </l>
       <l>
        Because our nature grieueth to be deem'd
       </l>
       <l>
        To be so wrong'd, although we be and must.
       </l>
       <l>
        And it's some ease yet to be kindly vs'd
       </l>
       <l>
        In outward shew, though secretly abus'd.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="26">
       <head>
        26
       </head>
       <l>
        But wo to her, that both in shew despis'd.
       </l>
       <l>
        And in effect disgrac'd and left forlorne,
       </l>
       <l>
        For whom no comforts are to be deuis'd,
       </l>
       <l>
        Nor no new hopes can euermore, be borne:
       </l>
       <l>
        O Antony, could it not haue suffiz'd
       </l>
       <l>
        That I was thine, but must be made her skorne
       </l>
       <l>
        That enuies all our bloud, and doth deuide
       </l>
       <l>
        Thee from thy selfe, onely to serue her pride?
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="27">
       <head>
        27
       </head>
       <l>
        What fault haue I committed that should make
       </l>
       <l>
        So great dislike of me and of my loue?
       </l>
       <l>
        Or doth thy fault but an occasion take
       </l>
       <l>
        For to dislike what most doth it reproue?
       </l>
       <l>
        Because the conscience gladly would mistake
       </l>
       <l>
        Her own misdeedes which she would faine remoue,
       </l>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-008-b"/>
       <l>
        And they that are vnwilling to amend
       </l>
       <l>
        Will take offence because they will offend.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="28">
       <head>
        28
       </head>
       <l>
        Or hauing run beyond all pardon quite
       </l>
       <l>
        They flie and ioyne with sin as wholy his,
       </l>
       <l>
        Making it now their side their part, their right,
       </l>
       <l>
        And to turne backe would shew t'haue done amisse:
       </l>
       <l>
        For now they thinke not to be opposite
       </l>
       <l>
        To what obraides their fault, were wickednesse:
       </l>
       <l>
        So much doth folly thrust them into blame
       </l>
       <l>
        That euen to leaue off shame, they count it shame.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="29">
       <head>
        29
       </head>
       <l>
        Which do not thou deere Lord, for I do not
       </l>
       <l>
        Pu&#9679;su&#9679; thy fault, but sue for thy retourne
       </l>
       <l>
        Backe to thy selfe, whom thou hast both forgot
       </l>
       <l>
        With me, poore me, that doth not spight but mourne.
       </l>
       <l>
        And if thou couldst as well amend thy blot
       </l>
       <l>
        As I forgiue, these plaints had beene forborne:
       </l>
       <l>
        And thou shouldst be the same vnto my hart
       </l>
       <l>
        Which once thou were, not that which now thou art.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="30">
       <head>
        30
       </head>
       <l>
        Though deepe doth sit the hard recouering smart
       </l>
       <l>
        Of that last wound (which God grant be the last)
       </l>
       <l>
        And more doth touch that tender feeling part
       </l>
       <l>
        Of my sad soule, then all th'vnkindnes past:
       </l>
       <l>
        And Antony I appeale to thine own hart,
       </l>
       <l>
        (If th'h&#9679;rt which once was thine thou yet still hast)
       </l>
       <l>
        To iudge if euer woman that did liue
       </l>
       <l>
        Had iuster cause, then wretched I, to grieue.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="31">
       <head>
        31
       </head>
       <l>
        For comming vnto Athens as I did,
       </l>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-009-a"/>
       <l>
        Wearie and weake with &#9679;oyle, and all distrest,
       </l>
       <l>
        After I had with sorrow compassed
       </l>
       <l>
        A hard consent, to graunt me that request:
       </l>
       <l>
        And how my trauaile was considered
       </l>
       <l>
        And all my care, and cost, thy selfe knowes best:
       </l>
       <l>
        That wouldst not moue one foot from lust for me
       </l>
       <l>
        That had left all was deere to come to thee:
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="32">
       <head>
        32
       </head>
       <l>
        For first what great ado had I to win.
       </l>
       <l>
        My offended brother Caesars backward will?
       </l>
       <l>
        And praid, and wept, and cride to stay the sinne
       </l>
       <l>
        Of ciuill rancor rising twixt you still:
       </l>
       <l>
        For in what &#9679;as&#9679; shall wretched I be in,
       </l>
       <l>
        Set betwixt both to share with both your ill?
       </l>
       <l>
        My blood said I with either of you goes,
       </l>
       <l>
        Who euer win, I shall be sure to lose.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="33">
       <head>
        33
       </head>
       <l>
        For what shame should such mighty persons get
       </l>
       <l>
        For two weake womens cause to disagree?
       </l>
       <l>
        Nay what shall I that shall be deem'd to set
       </l>
       <l>
        Th'inkindled fire, seeming inflam'd for me?
       </l>
       <l>
        O if I be the motiue of this heate
       </l>
       <l>
        Let these vnguilty hands the quenchers bee,
       </l>
       <l>
        And let me trudge to mediate an accord
       </l>
       <l>
        The Agent twixt my brother and my Lord.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="34">
       <head>
        34
       </head>
       <l>
        With praiers, vowes and teares, with vrging hard
       </l>
       <l>
        I wrung from him a slender grant at last,
       </l>
       <l>
        And with the rich prouisions I prepaid
       </l>
       <l>
        For thy (intended Parthian war) made hast
       </l>
       <l>
        Weighing not how my poore weake body far'd,
       </l>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-009-b"/>
       <l>
        But all the tedious difficulties past:
       </l>
       <l>
        And came to Athens; whence I Niger sent
       </l>
       <l>
        To shew thee of my comming and intent.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="35">
       <head>
        35
       </head>
       <l>
        Whereof when he had made relation:
       </l>
       <l>
        I was commanded to approch no neare?
       </l>
       <l>
        Then sent I backe to know what should be done
       </l>
       <l>
        With th'horse, and men, and monie I had there:
       </l>
       <l>
        Whereat perhaps when some remorse begun
       </l>
       <l>
        To touch thy soule, to thinke yet what we were.
       </l>
       <l>
        Th'Inchanters straight steps twixt thy hart &amp; the
       </l>
       <l>
        And intercepts all thoughts that came of mee.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="36">
       <head>
        36
       </head>
       <l>
        She armes her teares, the ingins of deceit
       </l>
       <l>
        And all her battery, to oppose my loue;
       </l>
       <l>
        And bring thy comming grace to a retrait
       </l>
       <l>
        The powre of all her subtilty to proue:
       </l>
       <l>
        Now pale and faint she languishes, and straight
       </l>
       <l>
        Seemes in a sound vnable more to moue:
       </l>
       <l>
        Whilst her instructed followers plie thine eares.
       </l>
       <l>
        with forged passions, mixt with fained teares.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="37">
       <head>
        37.
       </head>
       <l>
        Hard-harted lord: say they, how canst thou see
       </l>
       <l>
        This mighty Queene a creature so diuine,
       </l>
       <l>
        Lie thus distrest, and languishing for thee
       </l>
       <l>
        And onely wretched but for being thine?
       </l>
       <l>
        Whilst base Octauia must intitled bee
       </l>
       <l>
        Thy wife, and she esteem'd thy concubine:
       </l>
       <l>
        Aduance thy heart, raise it vnto his right
       </l>
       <l>
        And let a scepter baser passions quit:
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="38">
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-010-a"/>
       <head>
        38
       </head>
       <l>
        Thus they assaile thy natures weakest side
       </l>
       <l>
        And worke vpon th'aduantage of thy mind,
       </l>
       <l>
        Knowing where iudgment stood least fortified
       </l>
       <l>
        And how t'incounter folly in her kinde:
       </l>
       <l>
        But yet the while O what dost thou abide,
       </l>
       <l>
        Who in thy selfe such wrastling thoughts dost finde?
       </l>
       <l>
        In what confused case is thy soule in
       </l>
       <l>
        Rackt betwixt pitie, sorrow, shame and sin?
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="39">
       <head>
        39
       </head>
       <l>
        I cannot tell but sure I dare beleeue
       </l>
       <l>
        My trauailes needs must some co&#772;passion moue:
       </l>
       <l>
        For no such locke to bloud could nature giue
       </l>
       <l>
        To shut out pitie, though it shut out loue:
       </l>
       <l>
        Conscience must leaue a little way to grieue
       </l>
       <l>
        To let in horror comming to reproue,
       </l>
       <l>
        The guilt of thy offence that caus'd the same,
       </l>
       <l>
        For deepest wou&#772;ds the hand, of our owne shame.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="40">
       <head>
        40
       </head>
       <l>
        Neuer haue vniust pleasures beene compleet
       </l>
       <l>
        In ioyes intire, but still feare kept the dore
       </l>
       <l>
        And held back something from that ful of sweet
       </l>
       <l>
        To interfowre vnsure delights the more:
       </l>
       <l>
        For neuer did all circumstances meete
       </l>
       <l>
        With those desires which were co&#772;ceiu'd before
       </l>
       <l>
        Something must still be left to check our sinne,
       </l>
       <l>
        And giue a touch of what should not haue bin.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="41">
       <head>
        41
       </head>
       <l>
        Wretched mankind, wherefore hath nature made
       </l>
       <l>
        The lawfull vndelightfull, th'vniust shame?
       </l>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-010-b"/>
       <l>
        As if our pleasure onely were forbade,
       </l>
       <l>
        But to giue fire to lust, t'ad greater flame;
       </l>
       <l>
        Or else but as ordained more to lade
       </l>
       <l>
        Our heart with passions to confound the same,
       </l>
       <l>
        Which though it be, yet ad not worse to ill,
       </l>
       <l>
        Do, as the best men do, bound thine owne will.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="42">
       <head>
        42
       </head>
       <l>
        Redeeme thy selfe, a&#9679;d now at length make peace
       </l>
       <l>
        With thy deuided hart opprest with toyle:
       </l>
       <l>
        Breake vp this war, this brest dissention cease,
       </l>
       <l>
        Thy passions to thy passions reconcile:
       </l>
       <l>
        I do not only seeke my good t'increase,
       </l>
       <l>
        But thine owne ease, and liberty the while:
       </l>
       <l>
        Thee in the circuite of thy selfe confine.
       </l>
       <l>
        And be thine owne, and then thou wilt be mine.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="43">
       <head>
        43
       </head>
       <l>
        I know my pittied loue, doth aggrauate
       </l>
       <l>
        Enuy and wrath for these wrongs offered:
       </l>
       <l>
        And that my suffrings adde with my estate
       </l>
       <l>
        Coales in thy bosome, hatred on thy head:
       </l>
       <l>
        Yet is not that, my, fault, but my hard fate,
       </l>
       <l>
        Who rather wish to haue beene vnpitied
       </l>
       <l>
        Of all but thee, then that my loue should be
       </l>
       <l>
        Hurtfull to him that is so deere to me.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="44">
       <head>
        44
       </head>
       <l>
        Cannot the busie world let me alone
       </l>
       <l>
        To beare alone the burthen of my griefe,
       </l>
       <l>
        But they must intermeddle with my mone
       </l>
       <l>
        And seeke t'offend me with vnsought reliefe?
       </l>
       <l>
        Whilst my afflictions labour'd to moue none
       </l>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-011-a"/>
       <l>
        But only thee; must pitty play the thiefe,
       </l>
       <l>
        To steale so many harts to hurt my hart,
       </l>
       <l>
        And moue a part against my deerest part,?
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="45">
       <head>
        45
       </head>
       <l>
        Yet all this shall not preiudice my Lord
       </l>
       <l>
        If yet he will but make returne at last,
       </l>
       <l>
        His sight shall raze out of the sad record
       </l>
       <l>
        Of my inrowled griefe all that is past;
       </l>
       <l>
        And I will not so much as once affoord
       </l>
       <l>
        Place for a thought to thinke I was disgrac'st:
       </l>
       <l>
        And pity shall bring back againe with me
       </l>
       <l>
        Th'offended harts that haue forsaken thee,
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="46">
       <head>
        46
       </head>
       <l>
        And therefore come deere lord, least longer stay
       </l>
       <l>
        Do arme against thee all the powers of spight.
       </l>
       <l>
        And thou bee made at last the wofull pray
       </l>
       <l>
        Of full inkindled wrath, and ruin'd quite:
       </l>
       <l>
        But what presaging thought of bloud doth stay
       </l>
       <l>
        My trembling hand, and doth my soule affright?
       </l>
       <l>
        What horror do I see, prepar'd t'attend
       </l>
       <l>
        Th'euent of this? what end vnlesse thou end?
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="47">
       <head>
        47
       </head>
       <l>
        With what strange formes and shadowes ominous
       </l>
       <l>
        Did my last sleepe, my grieu'd soule intertaine?
       </l>
       <l>
        I dreampt, yet &#244;, dreames are but friuolous,
       </l>
       <l>
        And yet Ile tell it, and God graunt it vaine.
       </l>
       <l>
        Me thought a mighty Hippopotamus
        <ref corresp="A19812-e5330-b" target="A19812-e5330-b"/>
        <note corresp="A19812-e5330-a" place="margin">
         A Sea Horse.
        </note>
       </l>
       <l>
        From Nilus floting, thrusts into the maine,
       </l>
       <l>
        Vpon whose backe a wanton Mermaid sate,
       </l>
       <l>
        As if she ruld his course and steerd his &#9679;ite.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="48">
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-011-b"/>
       <head>
        48
       </head>
       <l>
        With whom t'incounter, forth another makes,
       </l>
       <l>
        Alike in kind, of strength and powre as good:
       </l>
       <l>
        At whose ingrappling Neptunes mantle takes
       </l>
       <l>
        A purple colour dyde with streames of bloud,
       </l>
       <l>
        Whereat, this looker on, amaz'd forsakes
       </l>
       <l>
        Her Champion there, who yet the better stood;
       </l>
       <l>
        But se'ing her gone straight after her he hies
       </l>
       <l>
        As if his hart and strength laye in her eies:
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="49">
       <head>
        49
       </head>
       <l>
        On followes wrath vpon disgrace and feare,
       </l>
       <l>
        Whereof th'euent forsooke me with the night,
       </l>
       <l>
        But my wak'd cares, gaue me, these shadowes were
       </l>
       <l>
        Drawne but from darknes to instruct the light,
       </l>
       <l>
        These secret figures, natures message beare
       </l>
       <l>
        Of comming woes, where they desciphered right;
       </l>
       <l>
        But if as cloudes of sleepe thou shalt them take,
       </l>
       <l>
        Yet credit wrath and spight that are awake.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="50">
       <head>
        50
       </head>
       <l>
        Preuent great spirit the tempest that begin,
       </l>
       <l>
        If lust and thy ambition haue left way
       </l>
       <l>
        But to looke out, and haue not shut all in,
       </l>
       <l>
        To stop thy iudgement from a true suruay
       </l>
       <l>
        Of thy estate; and let thy hart within
       </l>
       <l>
        Consider in what danger thou doost lay
       </l>
       <l>
        Thy life and mine&#9679; to leaue the good thou hast,
       </l>
       <l>
        To follow hopes with shadows ouercast,
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="51">
       <head>
        51
       </head>
       <l>
        Come, come away from wrong, from craft, fro&#772; toile,
       </l>
       <l>
        Possesse thine owne with right, with truth, with peace;
       </l>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-012-a"/>
       <l>
        Breake from these snares, thy iudgment vnbeguile.
       </l>
       <l>
        Free thine owne torment, and my griefe release.
       </l>
       <l>
        But whither am I carried all this while
       </l>
       <l>
        Beyond my scope, and know not when to cease?
       </l>
       <l>
        Words still with my increasing so&#9679;owes grow;
       </l>
       <l>
        I know t'haue said too much but not ynow.
       </l>
       <l>
        Wherefore no more but onely I commend
       </l>
       <l>
        To thee the hart that's thine, and so I end,
       </l>
      </lg>
      <trailer>
       FINIS.
      </trailer>
     </div>
     <div type="play" xml:id="ep000822-e5820">
      <pb xml:id="ep000822-012-b"/>
      <head>
       THE TRAGEDIE of Cleopatra. To the Lady Marie Countisse of Pembrooke.
      </head>
      <epigraph>
       <q>
        AEtas prima canat veneres postrema tumultus.
       </q>
      </epigraph>
      <div type="argument" xml:id="ep000822-e5890">
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-013-a"/>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-013-b"/>
       <head>
        The Argument.
       </head>
       <p>
        AFter the death of
        <hi>
         Antonius, Cleopatra
        </hi>
        , (liuing still in the Monument she had caused to be built,) could not, by any meanes be drawne foorth, although
        <hi>
         Octauius Caesar
        </hi>
        very earnestly laboured it: and sent Proculeius, to vse all dilligence to bring her vnto him: for that he thought it would bee a great Ornament to his Triumphes, to get her aliue to Rome. But neuer would she put her selfe into the hands of Proculeius, although on a time hee found the meanes, (by a window that was at the toppe of the Monument) to come downe vnto he&#9679;&#9679; where hee perswaded her (all hee might) to yeelde her selfe to Caesars mercy. Which shee, (to be ridde of him,) cunningly seemed to grant vnto. After that, Octauius in person went to visit her, to whom she excused her offence, laying all the fault vpon the greatnes, and feare she had of Antonius, and withall, seemed very tractable, and willing to be disposed of by him.
       </p>
       <p>
        Wherevpon Octauius, (thinking himselfe sure) resolued presently to send her away to Rome. Whereof, Dolabella, a fauourite of Caesars, (and one that was growne into some good liking of her) hauing certified her, shee makes her humble petition to Caesar, that he would suffer
        <pb xml:id="ep000822-014-a"/>
        her to sacrifice to the ghost of Antonius: which being gra&#772;ted her, she was brought vnto his sepulchre, where, after her rites performed, she returned to the monument, and there dined with great magnific&#9679;nce. And in dinner time, came there one in the habite of a countr&#9679;man, with a basket of Figs vnto her, who (vnsuspected) was suffered to carry them in. And in that Basket (among the Figges) were conueyed the Aspickes wherewith she did her selfe to death. Dinner being ended, she dispatched Letters to Caesar, containing great lamentations&#9679; with an earnest supplication, that she might be intombed with Antonius. Whereupon Caesar knowing what she intended, sent presently with all speede, Messengers to haue preuented her death, which notwithstanding, before they came, was dispatched.
       </p>
       <p>
        Caesario her sonne, which she had by
        <hi>
         Iulius Caesar
        </hi>
        (con&#9679;eyed before vnto India, out of the danger of the warres) was about the same time of her death, murthered at Rhodes: trained thither by the falshoode of his Tutor, corrupted by Caesar. And so, hereby came the race of the Prolomies to be wholy extinct, and the flourishing rich kingdome of Egypt vtterly ouerthrowne and subdued.
       </p>
      </div>
      <div type="play_proper" xml:id="ep000822-e6130">
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-014-b"/>
       <head>
        THE TRAGEDIE of Cleopatra.
       </head>
       <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="ep000822-e6150">
        <p>
         The Scaene supposed Alexandria.
        </p>
        <list>
         <head>
          THE ACTORS
         </head>
         <item>
          Cleopatra.
         </item>
         <item>
          Octauius Caesar.
         </item>
         <item>
          Proculeius.
         </item>
         <item>
          Dolobella.
         </item>
         <item>
          Titius, seruant to dolabella.
         </item>
         <item>
          two Philosophers.
          <list>
           <item>
            Arius
           </item>
           <item>
            Philostratus.
           </item>
          </list>
         </item>
         <item>
          Seleucus, secretary to Cleopatra.
         </item>
         <item>
          Rodon, tutor to Caesario.
         </item>
         <item>
          Nuntius.
         </item>
         <item>
          The Chorus, all Egyptians.
         </item>
        </list>
       </div>
       <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="ep000822-e6330">
        <head>
         ACTVS PRIMVS.
        </head>
        <sp who="ep000822-cleopatra" xml:id="ep000822-e6350">
         <speaker>
          Cleopatra.
         </speaker>
         <lg>
          <l>
           YET do I liue, and yet doth breath extend
          </l>
          <l>
           My life beyond my life? not can my graue
          </l>
          <l>
           Shut vp my griefes, to make my end my end?
          </l>
          <l>
           Will yet confusion haue more then I haue?
          </l>
          <l>
           Is th'honor, wonder, glory, pompe, and all
          </l>
          <l>
           Of Cleopatra dead, and she not dead?
          </l>
          <l>
           Haue I out-liu'd my selfe, and seene the fall
          </l>
          <l>
           Of all vpon me, and not ruined?
          </l>
          <l>
           Can yet these eyes endure the ghastly looke
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-015-a"/>
          <l>
           Of Desolations darke and ougly face,
          </l>
          <l>
           Wont but on Fortunes fairest side to l&#9679;oke,
          </l>
          <l>
           Where nought was but applause, but smiles, &amp; grace?
          </l>
          <l>
           Whiles on his shoulders all my rest relide
          </l>
          <l>
           On whom the Bu&#9679; then of &#9679;&#9679;' ambition lay,
          </l>
          <l>
           My Atlas, and supporter of my pride
          </l>
          <l>
           That did the world of all my glory sway,
          </l>
          <l>
           Who now throwne downe, disgrac'd, confounded lies
          </l>
          <l>
           Crusht with the weight of Shame and Infamy,
          </l>
          <l>
           Following th'vnlucky party of mine eies,
          </l>
          <l>
           The traines of lust and imbecilitie.
          </l>
          <l>
           Whereby my dissolution is become
          </l>
          <l>
           The graue of Egypt and the wracke of all;
          </l>
          <l>
           My vnforeseeing weakenesse must int&#9679;&#9679;ome
          </l>
          <l>
           My Countries fame, and glorie with my fall.
          </l>
          <l>
           Now who would thinke that I were she who late
          </l>
          <l>
           With all the ornaments on earth inrich'd,
          </l>
          <l>
           Enuiron'd with delights, compass'd with state,
          </l>
          <l>
           Glittring in pomp that h&#9679;&#9679;s and eyes bewitch'd;
          </l>
          <l>
           Should thus distrest, cast downe from off that height
          </l>
          <l>
           Leuell'd with low disgrac'd calamitie,
          </l>
          <l>
           Vnder the weight of such affliction sigh,
          </l>
          <l>
           Reduc'd vnto th'extr&#9679;&#9679;amest misery&#9679;
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           Am I the woman whose inu&#9679;n&#9679;ue pride,
          </l>
          <l>
           Adorn'd like Isis, sco&#9679;&#9679;d mortality?
          </l>
          <l>
           Is't I would haue my frailety so belide,
          </l>
          <l>
           That fla&#9679;terie could perswade I was no&#9679; I.
          </l>
          <l>
           Well, then I see, they but delude that praise vs,
          </l>
          <l>
           Greatnesse is mocke, prosperitie betraye vs:
          </l>
          <l>
           And we are but our selues, although this cloude
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-015-b"/>
          <l>
           Of interposed smoake makes vs seeme more:
          </l>
          <l>
           These spreading parts of pomp whereof w'are p&#9679;ov&#9679;d.
          </l>
          <l>
           Are not our parts, but parts of others store.
          </l>
          <l>
           Witnesse these gallant fortune following traines,
          </l>
          <l>
           These Summer Swallowes of felicitie
          </l>
          <l>
           Gone with the heate: of all, see what remaines,
          </l>
          <l>
           This monument, two maides, and wretched I.
          </l>
          <l>
           And I t'adorne their triumphs am reseru'd
          </l>
          <l>
           A captiue, kept to honour others spoyles,
          </l>
          <l>
           Whom Caesar labors so to haue preseru'd
          </l>
          <l>
           And seekes to entertaine my life with wiles.
          </l>
          <l>
           But Caesar, it is more then thou canst do,
          </l>
          <l>
           Promise, flatter, threaten extreamitie.
          </l>
          <l>
           Imploy thy wits and all thy force thereto,
          </l>
          <l>
           I haue both hands, and will, and I can die.
          </l>
          <l>
           Though thou, of both my country and my crowne,
          </l>
          <l>
           Of powre, of meanes and all dost quite bereaue me&#9679;
          </l>
          <l>
           Though thou hast wholy Egypt made thine owne&#9679;
          </l>
          <l>
           Yet hast thou left me that which will deceiue thee.
          </l>
          <l>
           That courage with my bloud and birth innated,
          </l>
          <l>
           Admir'd of all the earth as thou art now,
          </l>
          <l>
           Can neuer be so abiectly abated
          </l>
          <l>
           To be thy slaue that rul'd as good as thou.
          </l>
          <l>
           Thinke Caesar, I that liu'd and raign'd a Queene.
          </l>
          <l>
           Doe scorne to buy my life at such a rate,
          </l>
          <l>
           That I should vnderneath my selfe be seene,
          </l>
          <l>
           Basely induring to suruiue my state:
          </l>
          <l>
           That Rome should see my scepter-bearing hands
          </l>
          <l>
           Behind me bound, and glory in my teares,
          </l>
          <l>
           That I should passe whereas Octauia stands,
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-016-a"/>
          <l>
           To veiw my miserie that purchas'd he&#9679;s.
          </l>
          <l>
           No, I disdaine that head which wore a crowne,
          </l>
          <l>
           Should stoope to rake vp that which others giue;
          </l>
          <l>
           I must not be, vnlesse I be mine owne&#9679;
          </l>
          <l>
           Tis sweet to die when we are forc'd to liue.
          </l>
          <l>
           Nor had I staide behind my s&#9679;lfe this space,
          </l>
          <l>
           Nor paid such intr'est for this borrow'd breath,
          </l>
          <l>
           But that hereby I seeke to purchase grace&#9679;
          </l>
          <l>
           For my distressed scede after my death&#9679;
          </l>
          <l>
           It's that which doth my deerest bloud controule,
          </l>
          <l>
           That's it alas detaines me from my to&#9679;&#9679;be,
          </l>
          <l>
           Whiles Nature brings to contradict my soule
          </l>
          <l>
           The argument of mine vnhappy wombe.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           You lucklesse issue of an wofull mother,
          </l>
          <l>
           The wretched pledges of a wanton bed,
          </l>
          <l>
           You Kings design'd, must subiects liue &#9679;o other;
          </l>
          <l>
           Or else, I feare, scarce liue, when I am dead.
          </l>
          <l>
           It is for you I temporize with Caesar,
          </l>
          <l>
           And stay this while to mediate your safetie:
          </l>
          <l>
           For you I faine content and sooth his pleasure,
          </l>
          <l>
           Calamitie herein hath made me craftie.
          </l>
          <l>
           But this is but to trie what may be done,
          </l>
          <l>
           For come what will, this stands I must &#9679;ie free,
          </l>
          <l>
           And die my selfe vncaptiu'd and unwon.
          </l>
          <l>
           Bloud, Children, Nature, all must pardon me.
          </l>
          <l>
           My soule yeelds Honor vp the victorie&#9679;
          </l>
          <l>
           And I must be a Queene, forget a mother,
          </l>
          <l>
           Though mother would I be, were I no I:
          </l>
          <l>
           And Queene would not be now, could I be other.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           But what know I if th'heauens haue decreed,
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-016-b"/>
          <l>
           And that the sinnes of Egypt haue deseru'd
          </l>
          <l>
           The Ptolomies should faile and none succeed,
          </l>
          <l>
           And that my weaknesse was thereto reseru'd
          </l>
          <l>
           That I should bring confusion to my stare,
          </l>
          <l>
           And fill the measure of iniquity,
          </l>
          <l>
           Luxuriousnesse in me should raise the rate
          </l>
          <l>
           Of loose and ill-dispensed liberty.
          </l>
          <l>
           If it be so, then what neede these delaies?
          </l>
          <l>
           Since I was made the meanes of misery:
          </l>
          <l>
           Why should I striue but to make death my praise,
          </l>
          <l>
           That had my life but for my infamie?
          </l>
          <l>
           And let me write in letters of my bloud
          </l>
          <l>
           A fit memoriall for the times to come,
          </l>
          <l>
           To be example to such Princes good
          </l>
          <l>
           As please themselues, and care not what become.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           And Antony although the world takes note
          </l>
          <l>
           That my defects haue onely ruin'd thee:
          </l>
          <l>
           And my ambitious practises are thought
          </l>
          <l>
           The motiue and the cause of all to be:
          </l>
          <l>
           Yet God thou know'st this staine is wrongly laide
          </l>
          <l>
           Vpon my soule, whom ill successe makes ill:
          </l>
          <l>
           And my condemn'd misfortune hath no aide
          </l>
          <l>
           Against prowd lucke that argues what it will.
          </l>
          <l>
           I haue no meanes to vndeceiue their minds,
          </l>
          <l>
           But to bring in the witnesse of my bloud.
          </l>
          <l>
           To testifie the faith and loue that bindes
          </l>
          <l>
           My equall shame, to fall with whom I stood.
          </l>
          <l>
           Defects I grant I had, but this was worst,
          </l>
          <l>
           That being the first to fall I dy'd not first.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           Though I perhaps could lighten mine own side
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-017-a"/>
          <l>
           With some excuse of my constrained case
          </l>
          <l>
           Drawn downe with pow&#9679;e: but that were to deuide
          </l>
          <l>
           My shame: to stand alone in my disgrace.
          </l>
          <l>
           To cleere me so, would shew m&#9679;'affections naught
          </l>
          <l>
           And make th'excuse more hainous then the faule.
          </l>
          <l>
           Since if I should ou&#9679; errors disunite,
          </l>
          <l>
           I should confound afflictions onely rest,
          </l>
          <l>
           That from sterne death euen steales a sad delight
          </l>
          <l>
           To die with friends or with the like distrest.
          </l>
          <l>
           And since we tooke of either such firme hold
          </l>
          <l>
           In th'ouerwhelming seas of fortune cast.
          </l>
          <l>
           What powre should be of powre to revnfold
          </l>
          <l>
           The a&#9679;&#9679;mes of our affections lockt so fast.
          </l>
          <l>
           For grapling in the ocean of our pride,
          </l>
          <l>
           We sunke&#9679;adh others greatnesse both together:
          </l>
          <l>
           And both made shipwracke of our fame beside,
          </l>
          <l>
           Both wrought a like destruction vnto either:
          </l>
          <l>
           And therefore I am bound to sacrifice
          </l>
          <l>
           To death and thee, the life that doth reproue'me:
          </l>
          <l>
           Our like distresse I feele doth simpathi&#9679;e,
          </l>
          <l>
           And euen affliction makes me truly loue thee,
          </l>
          <l>
           Which Antonie, I must confesse my fault
          </l>
          <l>
           I neuer did sincerely vntill now,
          </l>
          <l>
           Now I protest I do, now am I taught
          </l>
          <l>
           In death to loue, in life that knew not how.
          </l>
          <l>
           For whilst my glory in her greatnesse stoode,
          </l>
          <l>
           And that I saw my state, and knew my beauty:
          </l>
          <l>
           Saw how the world admir'd me, how they woo'd,
          </l>
          <l>
           I then thought all men must loue me of duty:
          </l>
          <l>
           And I loue none; for my lasciuious Court,
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-017-b"/>
          <l>
           Fertile in euer fresh and new-choise pleasure,
          </l>
          <l>
           Affoorded me so bountifull disport,
          </l>
          <l>
           That I to stay on Loue had neuer leisure:
          </l>
          <l>
           My vagabond desires no limites sound.
          </l>
          <l>
           For lust is endlesse, pleasure hath no bound.
          </l>
          <l>
           Thou comming from the strictnesse of thy Citty.
          </l>
          <l>
           And this loose pomp of monarchs neuer learnest,
          </l>
          <l>
           Inur'd to warres, in womens wiles vnwitty,
          </l>
          <l>
           Whilst others faind, thou fell'st to loue in earnest;
          </l>
          <l>
           Not knowing how we like them best that houer,
          </l>
          <l>
           And make least reckning of a doting louer.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           And yet thou cam'st but in my beauties waine,
          </l>
          <l>
           When new appeering wrinckles of declining
          </l>
          <l>
           Wrought with the hand of yeeres, seem'd to detaine
          </l>
          <l>
           My graces light, as now but dimly shining
          </l>
          <l>
           Euen in the confines of mine age, when I
          </l>
          <l>
           Failing of what I was, and was but thus;
          </l>
          <l>
           When such as we do deeme in iealousie
          </l>
          <l>
           That men loue for themselues, and not for vs.
          </l>
          <l>
           Then, and but thus, thou didst loue most sincerely
          </l>
          <l>
           O Antony (who best deseru'st it better)
          </l>
          <l>
           This Autumne of my beauty bought so dearly,
          </l>
          <l>
           For which in more then death, I stand thy debter.
          </l>
          <l>
           Which I will pay thee with so true a minde,
          </l>
          <l>
           (Casting vp all these deepe accompts of mine)
          </l>
          <l>
           That both our soules, and all the world shall find
          </l>
          <l>
           All recknings cleer'd, betwixt my loue and thine.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           But to the end I may preuent prowd Caesar,
          </l>
          <l>
           Who doth so eagerly my life importune,
          </l>
          <l>
           I must preuaile me of this little leasure,
          </l>
          <l>
           Seeming to sute my minde vnto my fortune;
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-018-a"/>
          <l>
           Thereby with more conuenience to prouide
          </l>
          <l>
           For what my death and honour best shall fit:
          </l>
          <l>
           An yeelding base content must wary hide
          </l>
          <l>
           My last dissigne till I accomplish it,
          </l>
          <l>
           That hereby yet the world shall see that I,
          </l>
          <l>
           Although vnwise to live, had wit to die.
          </l>
         </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000822-e8550">
         Exit
        </stage>
        <sp who="ep000822-chorvs" xml:id="ep000822-e8560">
         <speaker>
          CHORVS.
         </speaker>
         <lg>
          <l>
           BEhold what furies still
          </l>
          <l>
           Torment their tortur'd brest,
          </l>
          <l>
           Who by their doing ill,
          </l>
          <l>
           Haue wrought the worldes vnrest.
          </l>
          <l>
           Which when being most distrest,
          </l>
          <l>
           Yet more to vexe their sprite,
          </l>
          <l>
           The hidious face of sinne.
          </l>
          <l>
           (In formes they must detest)
          </l>
          <l>
           Standes euer in their sight.
          </l>
          <l>
           Their conscience still within
          </l>
          <l>
           Th'eternall larum is
          </l>
          <l>
           That euer-barking dog that calles vpon their misse.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           No meanes at all to hide
          </l>
          <l>
           Man from himselfe can finde:
          </l>
          <l>
           No way to start aside
          </l>
          <l>
           Out from the hell of minde.
          </l>
          <l>
           But in himselfe confin'd,
          </l>
          <l>
           He still sees sinne before:
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-018-b"/>
          <l>
           And winged-footed paine,
          </l>
          <l>
           That swiftly comes behinde,
          </l>
          <l>
           The which is euer-more,
          </l>
          <l>
           The sure and certaine gaine
          </l>
          <l>
           Impiety doth get,
          </l>
          <l>
           And wanton loose respect, that doth it selfe forget.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           And Cleopatra now,
          </l>
          <l>
           Well sees the dangerous way
          </l>
          <l>
           She tooke, and car'd not&#9679; how,
          </l>
          <l>
           Which led her to decay.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           And likewise makes vs pay
          </l>
          <l>
           For her disordred lust,
          </l>
          <l>
           The int'rest of our blood:
          </l>
          <l>
           Or liue a seruile pray,
          </l>
          <l>
           Vnder a hand vniust,
          </l>
          <l>
           As others shall thinke good.
          </l>
          <l>
           This hath her riot woone
          </l>
          <l>
           And thus she hath her state her selfe and vs vndone.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           Now euery mouth can tell,
          </l>
          <l>
           What close was muttered:
          </l>
          <l>
           How that she did not well,
          </l>
          <l>
           To take the course she did.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           For now is nothing hid,
          </l>
          <l>
           Of what feare did restraine,
          </l>
          <l>
           No secret closely done,
          </l>
          <l>
           But now is vttered.
          </l>
          <l>
           The text is made most plaine
          </l>
          <l>
           That flatterie glos'd vpon,
          </l>
          <l>
           The bed of sinne reueal'd,
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-019-a"/>
          <l>
           And all the luxurie that shame would have conceal'd.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           The scene is broken downe,
          </l>
          <l>
           And all vncou'red lyes,
          </l>
          <l>
           The purple actors knowne
          </l>
          <l>
           Scarce men, whom men despise.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           The complots of the wise,
          </l>
          <l>
           Proue imperfections smoake:
          </l>
          <l>
           And all what wonder gaue
          </l>
          <l>
           To pleasure-gazing eyes,
          </l>
          <l>
           Lyes scattred, dasht, all broke.
          </l>
          <l>
           Thus much beguiled haue
          </l>
          <l>
           Poore vnconsiderate wights,
          </l>
          <l>
           These momentarie pleasures&#9679; fugitiue delights.
          </l>
         </lg>
        </sp>
       </div>
       <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="ep000822-e9270">
        <head>
         ACTVS SECVNDVS.
        </head>
        <sp xml:id="ep000822-e9290">
         <stage xml:id="ep000822-e9300">
          Caesar. Proculeius.
         </stage>
         <lg>
          <l>
           KIngdoms I see we winne, we conquere Climates,
          </l>
          <l>
           Yet cannot vanquish hearts, nor force obedience,
          </l>
          <l>
           Affections kept in close-concealed limits.
          </l>
          <l>
           Stand farre without the reach of sworde or violence,
          </l>
          <l>
           Who forc'd do pay vs dutie, pay not loue:
          </l>
          <l>
           Free is the heart, the temple of the minde,
          </l>
          <l>
           The Sanctuarie sacred from aboue,
          </l>
          <l>
           Where nature keeps the keyes that loose and bind.
          </l>
          <l>
           No mortall hand force open can that doore,
          </l>
          <l>
           So close shut vp, and lockt to all mankind:
          </l>
          <l>
           I see mens bodies onely ours, no more,
          </l>
          <l>
           The rest, anothers right, that rules the minde.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-019-b"/>
          <l>
           Behold, my forces vanquisht haue this Land,
          </l>
          <l>
           Subdu'd that strong Competitor of mine:
          </l>
          <l>
           All Egypt yeelds to my all-conqu'ring hand,
          </l>
          <l>
           And all their treasure and themselues resigne,
          </l>
          <l>
           Onely this Queene, that hath lost all this all.
          </l>
          <l>
           To whom is nothing left except a minde:
          </l>
          <l>
           Cannot into a thought of yeelding fall,
          </l>
          <l>
           To be dispos'd as Chance hath her assign'd.
          </l>
          <l>
           But Proculei, what hope doth she now giue,
          </l>
          <l>
           Will shee be brought to condiscend to liue?
          </l>
         </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000822-proc" xml:id="ep000822-e9560">
         <speaker>
          Proc.
         </speaker>
         <lg>
          <l>
           My Lord, what time being sent from you to try
          </l>
          <l>
           To win her forth al&#9679;&#9679;e (if that I might)
          </l>
          <l>
           From out the Monument, where wo&#9679;ully
          </l>
          <l>
           She liues inclos'd in most afflicted plight:
          </l>
          <l>
           No way I found, no meanes how to surprize her,
          </l>
          <l>
           But through a gra&#9679;e at th'entry of the place
          </l>
          <l>
           Standing to treat, I labour'd to aduise her,
          </l>
          <l>
           To come to Caesar, and to sue for grace.
          </l>
          <l>
           She said she crau'd not life, but leaue to die,
          </l>
          <l>
           Yet for her children, pray'd they might inherite,
          </l>
          <l>
           That Caesar would vouchsafe (in clemencie)
          </l>
          <l>
           To pittie them, though she deseru'd no merite.
          </l>
          <l>
           So leauing her for then; and since of late,
          </l>
          <l>
           With Gallus sent to trie an other time,
          </l>
          <l>
           The whilst he entertaines her at the grate,
          </l>
          <l>
           I found the meanes vp to the Tombe to clime.
          </l>
          <l>
           Where, in descending in the closest wise,
          </l>
          <l>
           And silent manner as I could contriue:
          </l>
          <l>
           Her woman me descri'd, and out she cries,
          </l>
          <l>
           Poore Cleopatra, thou art tane aliue.
          </l>
          <l>
           With that the Queene &#9679;aught from her side her knife,
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-020-a"/>
          <l>
           And euen in act to stab her martred brest,
          </l>
          <l>
           I stept with speed, and held, and sau'd her life,
          </l>
          <l>
           And forth her trembling hand the blade did wrest.
          </l>
          <l>
           Ah Cleopatra, why shouldst thou, (said I)
          </l>
          <l>
           Both iniurie thy selfe and Caesar so?
          </l>
          <l>
           Barre him the honour of his victorie,
          </l>
          <l>
           Who euer deales most mildly with his foe?
          </l>
          <l>
           Liue, and relie on him, whose mercy will
          </l>
          <l>
           To thy submission alwayes ready be.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           With that (as all amaz'd) she held her still,
          </l>
          <l>
           Twixt maiestie confuz'd and miserie.
          </l>
          <l>
           Her proud grieu'd eyes, held sorrow and disdaine,
          </l>
          <l>
           State and distresse warring within her soule:
          </l>
          <l>
           Dying ambition disposlest her raigne,
          </l>
          <l>
           So base affliction seemed to controule.
          </l>
          <l>
           Like as a burning Lampe, whose liquor spent
          </l>
          <l>
           With intermitted flames, when dead you deeme it,
          </l>
          <l>
           Sends forth a dying slash, as discontent,
          </l>
          <l>
           That so the matter failes that should redeeme it:
          </l>
          <l>
           So she (in spight) to see her low-brought state,
          </l>
          <l>
           When all her hopes were now consum'd to nought)
          </l>
          <l>
           Scornes yet to make an abiect league with Fate,
          </l>
          <l>
           Or once descend into a seruile thought.
          </l>
          <l>
           Th'imperious tongue vnused to beseech,
          </l>
          <l>
           Authoritie confounds with prayers so
          </l>
          <l>
           That words of powre conioyn'd with humble speech,
          </l>
          <l>
           Shew'd she would liue, yet scorn'd to pray her foe.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           Ah, what hath Caesar heere to do, said she,
          </l>
          <l>
           In confines of the dead in darknesse lying?
          </l>
          <l>
           Will he not grant our sepulchres be free,
          </l>
          <l>
           But violate the priuiledge of dying?
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-020-b"/>
          <l>
           What, must he stretch foorth his ambitious hand
          </l>
          <l>
           Into the right of Death, and force vs heere?
          </l>
          <l>
           Hath Miserie no couert where to stand
          </l>
          <l>
           Free from the storme of Pride, is't safe no where?
          </l>
          <l>
           Cannot my land, my golde, my crowne suffice,
          </l>
          <l>
           And all what I held deere, to him made common,
          </l>
          <l>
           But that he must in this sort tyrannize,
          </l>
          <l>
           Th'afflicted body of an wofull woman?
          </l>
          <l>
           Tell him, my frailetie, and the gods haue giuen
          </l>
          <l>
           Sufficient glory, could he be content:
          </l>
          <l>
           And let him now with his desires make euen,
          </l>
          <l>
           And leaue me to this horror, to lament.
          </l>
          <l>
           Now he hath taken all away from mee,
          </l>
          <l>
           What must he take me from my selfe by force?
          </l>
          <l>
           Ah, let him yet (in mercie) leaue me free
          </l>
          <l>
           The kingdome of this poore distressed corse.
          </l>
          <l>
           No other crownel seeke, no other good.
          </l>
          <l>
           Yet wish that Caesar would vouchsafe this grace,
          </l>
          <l>
           To fauour the poore of-spring of my bloud.
          </l>
          <l>
           Confused issue, yet of Romane race.
          </l>
          <l>
           If bloud and name be linckes of loue in Princes,
          </l>
          <l>
           Not spurres of hate; my poore Caesario may
          </l>
          <l>
           Finde fauour notwithstanding mine offences,
          </l>
          <l>
           And Caesars bloud, may Caesars raging stay.
          </l>
          <l>
           But if that with the torrent of my fall,
          </l>
          <l>
           All must be rapt with furious violence,
          </l>
          <l>
           And no respect, nor no regard at all,
          </l>
          <l>
           Can aught with nature or with bloud dispence:
          </l>
          <l>
           Then be it so, if needs it must be so.
          </l>
          <l>
           There staies and shrinckes in horror of her state:
          </l>
          <l>
           When I beganne to mittigate her woe,
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-021-a"/>
          <l>
           And thy great mercies vnto her relate;
          </l>
          <l>
           Wishing her not despaire, but rather come
          </l>
          <l>
           And sue for grace&#9679; and shake off idle feares:
          </l>
          <l>
           No doubt she should obtaine as gentle doome
          </l>
          <l>
           As she desir'd, both for her selfe and hers.
          </l>
          <l>
           And so with much adoe, (well pacifide
          </l>
          <l>
           Seeming to be) she shew'd content to liue,
          </l>
          <l>
           Saying she was resolu'd thy doome t'abide,
          </l>
          <l>
           And to accept what fauour thou would'st giue,
          </l>
          <l>
           And here withall crau'd also that shee might
          </l>
          <l>
           Performe her last&#9679;&#9679;tes to her lost belou'd.
          </l>
          <l>
           To sacrifice to him that wrought her plight:
          </l>
          <l>
           And that she might not be by force remou'd.
          </l>
          <l>
           I granting from thy part this her request,
          </l>
          <l>
           L&#9679;&#9679;&#9679; her for then, seeming in better rest.
          </l>
         </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000822-caes" xml:id="ep000822-e10700">
         <speaker>
          Caes.
         </speaker>
         <l>
          But dost thou thinke she will remaine so still?
         </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000822-pro" xml:id="ep000822-e10730">
         <speaker>
          Pro.
         </speaker>
         <l>
          I thinke, and do assure my selfe she will.
         </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000822-caes" xml:id="ep000822-e10760">
         <speaker>
          Caes.
         </speaker>
         <l>
          Ah, priuate men sound not the harts of Princes,
         </l>
         <l>
          Whose purposes beare contrarie pretences.
         </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000822-pro" xml:id="ep000822-e10800">
         <speaker>
          Pro.
         </speaker>
         <l>
          Why tis her safetie to come yeeld to thee.
         </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000822-caes" xml:id="ep000822-e10830">
         <speaker>
          Caes.
         </speaker>
         <l>
          But tis more honour for her to die free.
         </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000822-pro" xml:id="ep000822-e10860">
         <speaker>
          Pro.
         </speaker>
         <l>
          She may thereby procure her childrens good.
         </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000822-caes" xml:id="ep000822-e10890">
         <speaker>
          Caes.
         </speaker>
         <l>
          Princes are not ally'd vnto their blood.
         </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000822-pro" xml:id="ep000822-e10920">
         <speaker>
          Pro.
         </speaker>
         <l>
          Can Princes powre dispence with nature than?
         </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000822-caes" xml:id="ep000822-e10950">
         <speaker>
          Caes.
         </speaker>
         <l>
          To be a Prince, is more then be a man.
         </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000822-pro" xml:id="ep000822-e10980">
         <speaker>
          Pro.
         </speaker>
         <l>
          There's none but haue in time perswaded beene,
         </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000822-caes" xml:id="ep000822-e11010">
         <speaker>
          Caes,
         </speaker>
         <l>
          And so might she too, were she not a Queene.
         </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000822-pro" xml:id="ep000822-e11040">
         <speaker>
          Pro.
         </speaker>
         <l>
          Diuers respects will force her be reclaim'd.
         </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000822-caes" xml:id="ep000822-e11070">
         <speaker>
          Caes.
         </speaker>
         <l>
          Princes (like Lions) neuer will be &#9679;am'd
         </l>
         <l>
          A priuate man may yeeld and care not how,
         </l>
         <l>
          But greater hearts will breake before they bow.
         </l>
         <pb xml:id="ep000822-021-b"/>
         <l>
          And sure I thinke sh'will neuer condiscend,
         </l>
         <l>
          To liue to grace our spoiles with her disgrace:
         </l>
         <l>
          But yet let still a wary troupe attend,
         </l>
         <l>
          To guard her person, and to watch the place.
         </l>
         <l>
          And looke that none with her come to confer:
         </l>
         <l>
          Shortly my selfe will go to visite her.
         </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000822-chorvs" xml:id="ep000822-e11180">
         <speaker>
          CHORVS.
         </speaker>
         <lg>
          <l>
           OPINION, how doost thou molest
          </l>
          <l>
           Th'affected minde of restlesse man?
          </l>
          <l>
           Who following thee neuer can,
          </l>
          <l>
           Nor euer shall attaine to rest,
          </l>
          <l>
           For getting what thou saist is best,
          </l>
          <l>
           Yet loe, that best he findes farre wide
          </l>
          <l>
           Of what thou promisedst before:
          </l>
          <l>
           For in the same he lookt for more,
          </l>
          <l>
           Which proues but small when once tis tride
          </l>
          <l>
           Then something else thou find'st beside.
          </l>
          <l>
           To draw him still from thought to thought,
          </l>
          <l>
           When in the end all prooues but nought.
          </l>
          <l>
           Farther from rest he findes him than,
          </l>
          <l>
           Then at the first when he began.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           O malecontent seducing guest,
          </l>
          <l>
           Contriuer of our greatest woes:
          </l>
          <l>
           Which borne of winde, and fed with showes.
          </l>
          <l>
           Doost nurse thy selfe in thine vnrest.
          </l>
          <l>
           Iudging vngotten things the best,
          </l>
          <l>
           Or what thou in conceit desig'nst,
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-022-a"/>
          <l>
           And all things in the world dost deeme,
          </l>
          <l>
           Not as they are, but as they seeme:
          </l>
          <l>
           Which shews, their state thou ill design'st,
          </l>
          <l>
           And liu'st to come, in present pin'st.
          </l>
          <l>
           For what thou hast, thou still dost lacke:
          </l>
          <l>
           O mindes tormentor, bodies wracke,
          </l>
          <l>
           Vaine promiser of that sweete rest,
          </l>
          <l>
           Which neuer any yet possest.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           If we vnto ambition tend,
          </l>
          <l>
           Then doost thou drawe our weakenesse on,
          </l>
          <l>
           With vaine imagination
          </l>
          <l>
           Of that which neuer hath an end.
          </l>
          <l>
           Or if that lust we apprehend,
          </l>
          <l>
           How doth that pleasant plague infest?
          </l>
          <l>
           O what strange formes of luxurie,
          </l>
          <l>
           Thou strait dost cast t'intice vs by?
          </l>
          <l>
           And tell'st vs that is euer best,
          </l>
          <l>
           Which we haue neuer yet possest.
          </l>
          <l>
           And that more pleasure rests beside,
          </l>
          <l>
           In something that we haue not tride.
          </l>
          <l>
           And when the sanse likewise is had,
          </l>
          <l>
           Then all is one, and all is bad.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           This Antony can say is true,
          </l>
          <l>
           And Cleopatra knowes tis so,
          </l>
          <l>
           By th'experience of their woe.
          </l>
          <l>
           She can say, she neuer knew
          </l>
          <l>
           But that lust found pleasures new,
          </l>
          <l>
           And was neuer satisfide:
          </l>
          <l>
           He can say by proofe of toile,
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-022-b"/>
          <l>
           Ambition is a Vulture vile,
          </l>
          <l>
           That feeds vpon the hart of pride:
          </l>
          <l>
           And findes no rest when all is tride.
          </l>
          <l>
           For worlds cannot confine the one,
          </l>
          <l>
           Th'other, lists and bounds hath none.
          </l>
          <l>
           And both subuert the minde, the state,
          </l>
          <l>
           Procure destruction, enuie, hate.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           And now when all this is prou'd vaine,
          </l>
          <l>
           Yet Opinion leaues not heere,
          </l>
          <l>
           But sticks to Cleopatra neere,
          </l>
          <l>
           Perswading now, how she shall gaine
          </l>
          <l>
           Honour by death&#9679; and fame attaine.
          </l>
          <l>
           And what a shame it were to liue,
          </l>
          <l>
           Her kingdome lost, her Louer dead:
          </l>
          <l>
           And so with this perswasion led,
          </l>
          <l>
           Dispaire doth such a courage giue,
          </l>
          <l>
           That nought else can her minde relieue,
          </l>
          <l>
           Nor yet diuert her from that thought:
          </l>
          <l>
           To this conclusion all is brought:
          </l>
          <l>
           This is that rest this vaine world lends,
          </l>
          <l>
           To end in death that all things ends.
          </l>
         </lg>
        </sp>
       </div>
       <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="ep000822-e11990">
        <head>
         ACTVS TERTIVS.
        </head>
        <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000822-e12010">
         <sp xml:id="ep000822-e12020">
          <stage xml:id="ep000822-e12030">
           Philostratus. Arius.
          </stage>
          <lg>
           <l>
            HOw deepely Arius am I bound to thee,
           </l>
           <l>
            That sau'dst fro&#772; death this wretched life of mine:
           </l>
           <l>
            Obtaining Caesars gentle grace for mee,
           </l>
           <l>
            When I of all helpes else dispaird but thine?
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-023-a"/>
           <l>
            Although I see in such a woful state.
           </l>
           <l>
            Life is not that which should be much desir'd
           </l>
           <l>
            Sith all our glories come to end their date,
           </l>
           <l>
            Our Countries honour and our own expir'd
           </l>
           <l>
            Now that the hand of wrath hath ouer-gone vs.
           </l>
           <l>
            We liue but as i&#9679; th'armes of our dead mother,
           </l>
           <l>
            With bloud vnder our feet, ruine vpon vs,
           </l>
           <l>
            And in a Land most wretched of all other,
           </l>
           <l>
            When yet we reckon life our deerest good.
           </l>
           <l>
            And so we liue, we care not how we liue:
           </l>
           <l>
            So deepe we feele impressed in our blood,
           </l>
           <l>
            That touch which Nature with our breath did giue.
           </l>
           <l>
            And yet what blasts of words hath Learning found,
           </l>
           <l>
            To blow against the feare of death and dying?
           </l>
           <l>
            What comforts vnsicke eloquence can sound,
           </l>
           <l>
            And yet all failes vs in the point of trying.
           </l>
           <l>
            For whilst we reason with the breath of safety,
           </l>
           <l>
            Without the compasse of destruction liuing,
           </l>
           <l>
            What precepts shew we then what courage lofty
           </l>
           <l>
            In taxing others feares in councell giuing?
           </l>
           <l>
            When all this ayre of sweet-contriued wordes
           </l>
           <l>
            Proues but weake armour to defend the hart.
           </l>
           <l>
            For when this life, pale Feare and Terrour boords,
           </l>
           <l>
            Where are our precepts then, where is our arte?
           </l>
           <l>
            O who is he that from himselfe can tourne,
           </l>
           <l>
            That beares about the body of a man?
           </l>
           <l>
            Who doth not toile and labour to adiorne
           </l>
           <l>
            The day of death, by any meanes he can?
           </l>
           <l>
            All this I speake to th'end my selfe t'excuse,
           </l>
           <l>
            For my base begging of a seruile breath,
           </l>
           <l>
            Wherein I grant my selfe much to abuse,
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-023-b"/>
           <l>
            So shamefully to seeke t'auoide my death.
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-arius" xml:id="ep000822-e12430">
          <speaker>
           Arius.
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            Philostratus, that selfe s&#9679;me care to liue,
           </l>
           <l>
            Possesseth all alike, and grieue not then,
           </l>
           <l>
            Nature doth vs no more then others giue:
           </l>
           <l>
            Though we speake more then men, we are but men.
           </l>
           <l>
            And yet (in truth) these miseries to see,
           </l>
           <l>
            Wherein we stand in most extreame distresse:
           </l>
           <l>
            Might to our selues sufficient motiues be
           </l>
           <l>
            To loath this life, and weigh our death the lesse:
           </l>
           <l>
            For neuer any age hath better taught,
           </l>
           <l>
            What feeble footing pride and greatnesse hath.
           </l>
           <l>
            How 'improuident prosperity is caught.
           </l>
           <l>
            And cleane confounded in the day of wrath.
           </l>
           <l>
            See how dismaid Confusion keepes those streetes.
           </l>
           <l>
            That nought but mirth and musique late resounded,
           </l>
           <l>
            How nothing with our eic but horror meetes,
           </l>
           <l>
            Our state, our wealth, our pride and all confounded.
           </l>
           <l>
            Yet what weake sight did not discerne from far
           </l>
           <l>
            This black-arising tempest, all confounding?
           </l>
           <l>
            Who did not see we should be what we are,
           </l>
           <l>
            When pride and ryot grew to such abounding.
           </l>
           <l>
            When dissolute impietie possest
           </l>
           <l>
            Th'vnrespectiue mindes of prince and people:
           </l>
           <l>
            When insolent Securitie found rest
           </l>
           <l>
            In wanton thoughts, which lust and ease made feeble.
           </l>
           <l>
            Then when vnwary Peace with fat-fed pleasure:
           </l>
           <l>
            New-fresh muented ryots still detected.
           </l>
           <l>
            Purchac'd with all the Ptolomies rich treasure,
           </l>
           <l>
            Our lawes, our gods, our mysteryes neglected.
           </l>
           <l>
            Who saw not how this confluence of vice,
           </l>
           <l>
            This inundation of disorders, must
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-024-a"/>
           <l>
            At length of force pay backe the bloodie price
           </l>
           <l>
            Of sad destruction, (a reward for lust)
           </l>
           <l>
            O thou and I haue heard, and read, and knowne
           </l>
           <l>
            Of like proud states, as wofully incombred.
           </l>
           <l>
            And fram'd by them, examples for our owne:
           </l>
           <l>
            Which now among examples must be numbred.
           </l>
           <l>
            For this decre a law from high is giuen,
           </l>
           <l>
            An ancient Canon, of eternall date,
           </l>
           <l>
            In Consistory of the starres of heauen,
           </l>
           <l>
            Entred the Booke of vnauoyded Fate:
           </l>
           <l>
            That no state can in heigh of happinesse.
           </l>
           <l>
            In the'exaltation of their glory stand:
           </l>
           <l>
            But thither once arriu'd declining lesse,
           </l>
           <l>
            Ruine themselues, or fall by others hand.
           </l>
           <l>
            Thus doth the euer-changing course of things
           </l>
           <l>
            Runne a perpetuall cirkle, euer turning:
           </l>
           <l>
            And that same day that hiest glory brings,
           </l>
           <l>
            Brings vs vnto the poynt of back-returning:
           </l>
           <l>
            For sencelesse sensualty, doth euer
           </l>
           <l>
            Accompany felicity and greatnesse.
           </l>
           <l>
            A fatall witch, whose charmes do leaue vs neuer
           </l>
           <l>
            Till we leaue all in sorrow for our sweetnesse;
           </l>
           <l>
            When yet our selues must be the cause we fall,
           </l>
           <l>
            Although the same be first decreed on hie:
           </l>
           <l>
            Our errors still must beare the blame of all,
           </l>
           <l>
            This must it be: earth, aske not heauen why.
           </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
           <l>
            Yet mighty men with wary iealous hand,
           </l>
           <l>
            Striue to cut off all obstacles of feare:
           </l>
           <l>
            All whatsoeuer seems but to withstand
           </l>
           <l>
            Their least conceit of quiet held so &#9679;eere:
           </l>
           <l>
            And so intrench themselues with blood with crimes,
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-024-b"/>
           <l>
            With all iniustice as their feares dispose:
           </l>
           <l>
            Yet for all this we see, how oftentimes
           </l>
           <l>
            The meanes they worke to keepe are meanes to lose,
           </l>
           <l>
            And sure I cannot see, how this can stand
           </l>
           <l>
            With great Augustus glory and his honor,
           </l>
           <l>
            T'extinguish the succession of our land,
           </l>
           <l>
            For her offence that pulld the warres vpon her,
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-phi" xml:id="ep000822-e13180">
          <speaker>
           Phi.
          </speaker>
          <l>
           Must all her yssue be confounded now?
          </l>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-ari" xml:id="ep000822-e13210">
          <speaker>
           Ari.
          </speaker>
          <l>
           Yea all that from the roots of kings did grow,
          </l>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-phi" xml:id="ep000822-e13240">
          <speaker>
           Phi.
          </speaker>
          <l>
           And sweet Caesario sprong of Caesars blood?
          </l>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-ari" xml:id="ep000822-e13290">
          <speaker>
           Ari.
          </speaker>
          <l>
           Plurality of Caesars are not good.
          </l>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-phi" xml:id="ep000822-e13320">
          <speaker>
           Phi.
          </speaker>
          <l>
           Alas, what hurt procures his feeble arme?
          </l>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-ari" xml:id="ep000822-e13350">
          <speaker>
           Ari.
          </speaker>
          <l>
           Not for it doth, but that it may do harme.
          </l>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-phi" xml:id="ep000822-e13380">
          <speaker>
           Phi.
          </speaker>
          <l>
           Then when it offers hurt, represse the same.
          </l>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-ari" xml:id="ep000822-e13410">
          <speaker>
           Ari.
          </speaker>
          <l>
           Tis best to quench a sparke before it flame.
          </l>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-phi" xml:id="ep000822-e13440">
          <speaker>
           Phi.
          </speaker>
          <l>
           Tis inhumane, an innocent to kill.
          </l>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-ari" xml:id="ep000822-e13470">
          <speaker>
           Ari.
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            Such innocents seldome remaine so still.
           </l>
           <l>
            And sure his death may best procure our peace,
           </l>
           <l>
            Competitors the subiect deerely buies:
           </l>
           <l>
            And so that our affliction may surcease,
           </l>
           <l>
            Let great men be the peoples sacrifice.
           </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
           <l>
            But see where Caesar comes himselfe to try
           </l>
           <l>
            And worke the minde of our distressed Queene
           </l>
           <l>
            With some deluding hope: whereby
           </l>
           <l>
            She might be drawn to haue her fortune seene.
           </l>
           <l>
            But yet I trust, Rome will not see that face
           </l>
           <l>
            (That queld her champions) blush in base disgrace,
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="ep000822-e13620">
         <pb xml:id="ep000822-025-a"/>
         <head>
          SCENA SECVNDA.
         </head>
         <stage xml:id="ep000822-e13640">
          Caesar, Cleopatra, Selucus, Dolabella.
         </stage>
         <sp who="ep000822-caesar" xml:id="ep000822-e13650">
          <speaker>
           Caesar.
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            VVHat Cleopatra, doost thou doubt so much
           </l>
           <l>
            Of Caesars mercy, that thou hid'st thy face?
           </l>
           <l>
            Or dost thou thinke, thy offences can be such,
           </l>
           <l>
            That they surmount the measure of our grace?
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-cle" xml:id="ep000822-e13730">
          <speaker>
           Cle.
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            O Caesar, not for that I flie thy sight
           </l>
           <l>
            My soule this sad retire of sorrow chose:
           </l>
           <l>
            But that m'oppressed thoughts abhorring light
           </l>
           <l>
            Like best in darkenesse, my disgrace t'inclose.
           </l>
           <l>
            And heere to these close limites of despaire,
           </l>
           <l>
            This solitary horror where I bide:
           </l>
           <l>
            Caesar, I thought no Roman should repaire,
           </l>
           <l>
            More after him, who here oppressed dyde.
           </l>
           <l>
            Yet now, here at thy conquering feete I lie,
           </l>
           <l>
            Poore captiue soule, that neuer thought to bow:
           </l>
           <l>
            Whose happy foote of rule and Maiestie
           </l>
           <l>
            Stood late on that same ground thou standest now.
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-caes" xml:id="ep000822-e13890">
          <speaker>
           Caes.
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            Rise Queene, none but thy selfe is cause of all,
           </l>
           <l>
            And yet, would all were but thine owne alone:
           </l>
           <l>
            That others ruine had not with thy fall
           </l>
           <l>
            Brought Rome her sorrowes, to my triumphes mone.
           </l>
           <l>
            For breaking off the league of loue and blood,
           </l>
           <l>
            Thou mak'st my winning ioy againe vnpleasing:
           </l>
           <l>
            Sith th'eye of griefs looke not into our good,
           </l>
           <l>
            But thor'w the horror of our owne blood shedding.
           </l>
           <l>
            And all, we must attribute vnto thee.
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-cle" xml:id="ep000822-e14010">
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-025-b"/>
          <speaker>
           Cle.
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            To me? Caesar, what should a woman doe
           </l>
           <l>
            Opprest with greatnes? what was it for me
           </l>
           <l>
            To contradict my Lord, being bent thereto?
           </l>
           <l>
            I was by loue, by feare by weakenesse, made
           </l>
           <l>
            An instrument to such disseignes as these.
           </l>
           <l>
            For when the Lord of all the Orient bade,
           </l>
           <l>
            Who but obey'd? who was not glad to please?
           </l>
           <l>
            And how could I withdraw my succouring hand
           </l>
           <l>
            From him that had my heart, and what was mine?
           </l>
           <l>
            The int'rest of my faith in streightest band,
           </l>
           <l>
            My loue to his most firmely did combine.
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-caes" xml:id="ep000822-e14160">
          <speaker>
           Caes.
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            Loue? ah no no, it was th'innated hatred
           </l>
           <l>
            That thou and thine hast euer borne our people:
           </l>
           <l>
            That made thee seeke all meanes to haue vs scattred,
           </l>
           <l>
            To disunite our strength, and make vs feeble.
           </l>
           <l>
            And therefore did that breast nurse our dissention,
           </l>
           <l>
            With hope t'exalt thy selfe, t'augment thy state:
           </l>
           <l>
            To pray vpon the wracke of our contention,
           </l>
           <l>
            And (with the rest our foes,) to ioy thereat.
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-cleo" xml:id="ep000822-e14270">
          <speaker>
           Cleo:
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            O Caesar, see how easie tis t'accuse
           </l>
           <l>
            Whom Fortune hath made faulty by their fall,
           </l>
           <l>
            The wretched conquered may not resuse
           </l>
           <l>
            The titles of reproch hee's charg'd withall.
           </l>
           <l>
            The conquering cause hath right, wherein thou art,
           </l>
           <l>
            The vanquisht still is iudgde the worser part.
           </l>
           <l>
            Which part is mine, because I lost my part.
           </l>
           <l>
            No lesser then the portion of a Crowne.
           </l>
           <l>
            Enough for me, alas was needed art
           </l>
           <l>
            To gaine by others, but to keepe mine owne?
           </l>
           <l>
            But heere let weaker powers note what it is,
           </l>
           <l>
            To neighbour great Compe&#9679;itors too neere,
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-026-a"/>
           <l>
            If wee take part, we oft do perish thus,
           </l>
           <l>
            If neutrall bide, both parties we must feare.
           </l>
           <l>
            Alas, what shall the forst partakers doe,
           </l>
           <l>
            When following none, yet must they perish too?
           </l>
           <l>
            But Caesar, sith thy right and cause is such,
           </l>
           <l>
            Be not a heauy weight vpon calamitie:
           </l>
           <l>
            Depresse not the afflicted ouer-much,
           </l>
           <l>
            The chie&#9679;est glorie is the Victors lenitie.
           </l>
           <l>
            Th'inheritance of mercie from him take,
           </l>
           <l>
            Of whom thou hast thy fortune&#9679; and thy name:
           </l>
           <l>
            Great Caesar me a Queene at first did make,
           </l>
           <l>
            And let not Caesar now confound the same,
           </l>
           <l>
            Reade here these lines which still I keepe with me,
           </l>
           <l>
            The witnesse of his loue and fauours euer:
           </l>
           <l>
            And God forbid this should be said of thee,
           </l>
           <l>
            That Caesar wrong'd the fauoured of Caesar.
           </l>
           <l>
            For looke what I haue beene to Antony
           </l>
           <l>
            Thinke thou the same I might haue beene to thee.
           </l>
           <l>
            And here I do present thee with the note
           </l>
           <l>
            Of all the treasure, all the iewels rate
           </l>
           <l>
            That Egypt hath in many ages got;
           </l>
           <l>
            And looke what Cleopatra hath, is there.
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-seleu" xml:id="ep000822-e14720">
          <speaker>
           Seleu.
          </speaker>
          <l>
           Nay there's not all set down within that roule,
          </l>
          <l>
           I know some things she hath reseru'd apart.
          </l>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-cle" xml:id="ep000822-e14760">
          <speaker>
           Cle.
          </speaker>
          <l>
           What vile vngrateful wretch, dar'st tho&#9679; co&#772;troule
          </l>
          <l>
           Thy Queene and soueraigne, cai&#9679;i&#9679;e as thou art.
          </l>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-caes" xml:id="ep000822-e14800">
          <speaker>
           Caes.
          </speaker>
          <l>
           Holde, holde; a poore reuenge ca&#772; worke so feeble hands
          </l>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-cle" xml:id="ep000822-e14830">
          <speaker>
           Cle.
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            Ah Caesar, what a great indignitie
           </l>
           <l>
            Is this, that here my vassall subiect stands
           </l>
           <l>
            T' accuse me to my Lord of trecher&#9679;e?
           </l>
           <l>
            If I reseru'd some certaine womens toyes,
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-026-b"/>
           <l>
            Alas it was not for my selfe (God knowes,)
           </l>
           <l>
            Poore miserable soule, that little ioyes
           </l>
           <l>
            In trifling ornaments in outward showes.
           </l>
           <l>
            But what I kept, I kept to make my way
           </l>
           <l>
            Vnto thy Liuia and Octauius grace,
           </l>
           <l>
            That thereby in compassion mooued, they
           </l>
           <l>
            Might mediate thy fauour in my case.
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-caes" xml:id="ep000822-e15000">
          <speaker>
           Caes.
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            Well Cleopatra, feare not, thou shalt finde
           </l>
           <l>
            What fauour thou desir'st, or canst expect:
           </l>
           <l>
            For Caesar neuer yet was found but kinde
           </l>
           <l>
            To such as yeeld, and can themselues subiect.
           </l>
           <l>
            And therefore giue thou comfort to thy minde,
           </l>
           <l>
            Relieue thy soule thus ouer-charg'd with care,
           </l>
           <l>
            How well I will intreate thee thou shalt find,
           </l>
           <l>
            So soone as some affaires dispatched are.
           </l>
           <l>
            Till when farewel. Cl. Thanks thrise renowned Caesar,
           </l>
           <l>
            Poore Cleopatra rests thine owne for &#9679;uer.
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-dol" xml:id="ep000822-e15180">
          <speaker>
           Dol.
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            No maruell Caesar though our greatest spirits,
           </l>
           <l>
            Haue to the powre of such act arming beautie
           </l>
           <l>
            Been brought to yeeld the honor of their merits:
           </l>
           <l>
            Forgetting all respect of other dutie.
           </l>
           <l>
            Then whilst the glory of her youth remain'd
           </l>
           <l>
            The wondring object to each wanton eye':
           </l>
           <l>
            Before her full of sweet (with sorrow wain'd,)
           </l>
           <l>
            Came to the period of this miserie.
           </l>
           <l>
            If still, euen in the midst of death and horror
           </l>
           <l>
            Such beautie shines, thorow clouds of age &amp; sorrow,
           </l>
           <l>
            If euen those sweet decaies seeme to pleade for her,
           </l>
           <l>
            Which from affliction mouing graces borrow:
           </l>
           <l>
            If in calamitie she could thus moue,
           </l>
           <l>
            What could she do adorn'd with youth and loue?
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-027-a"/>
           <l>
            What could she do then, when as spreading wide
           </l>
           <l>
            The pomp of beauty, in her glory dight?
           </l>
           <l>
            When arm'd with wonder, she could vse beside,
           </l>
           <l>
            Th'ingines of her loue, Hope and Delight?
           </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
           <l>
            Daughter of Meruaile beauty O see how
           </l>
           <l>
            Thou canst disgracing sorrowes sweetly grace.
           </l>
           <l>
            What power thou show'st in a distressed brow,
           </l>
           <l>
            That mak'st affliction faire, giu'st teares their grace.
           </l>
           <l>
            What can vntressed locks, can torne rent haire,
           </l>
           <l>
            A weeping eye, a waiilng face be faire?
           </l>
           <l>
            I see then, artlesse feature can content,
           </l>
           <l>
            And that true beauty needs no ornament,
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-caes" xml:id="ep000822-e15490">
          <speaker>
           Caes.
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            What in passion a Dolabella? what take heed:
           </l>
           <l>
            Let others fresh examples be thy warning:
           </l>
           <l>
            What mischiefs these, so idle humors breed,
           </l>
           <l>
            Whilst error keepes vs from a true discerning.
           </l>
           <l>
            Indeed I saw she labour'd to impart
           </l>
           <l>
            Her sweetest graces in her saddest cheere:
           </l>
           <l>
            Presuming on the face that knew the art
           </l>
           <l>
            To moue with what aspect so eu'r it were.
           </l>
           <l>
            But all in vaine, she takes her ayme amisse.
           </l>
           <l>
            The ground and marke her leuel much deceiues:
           </l>
           <l>
            Time now hath altred all, for neither is
           </l>
           <l>
            She as she was, nor we as she conceiues.
           </l>
           <l>
            And therefore now leaue he&#9679; vnto her sadnesse
           </l>
           <l>
            Folly in youth is sinne, in age, tis madnesse.
           </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
           <l>
            And for my part, I seeke but t'entertaine
           </l>
           <l>
            In her some feeding hope to draw her forth,
           </l>
           <l>
            The greatest Trophey that my trauaile &#9679; gaine,
           </l>
           <l>
            &#9679;&#9679;to bring home a prizall of such worth.
           </l>
           <l>
            A&#9679;&#9679; now, sith that she seemes so well content.
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-027-b"/>
           <l>
            To be dispos'd by vs, without more stay
           </l>
           <l>
            She with her children shall to Rome be fent,
           </l>
           <l>
            Whilst I by Syria thither take my way.
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-chorvs" xml:id="ep000822-e15770">
          <speaker>
           CHORVS.
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            O Fearefull frowning Nemesis,
           </l>
           <l>
            Daughter of Iustice, most seuere,
           </l>
           <l>
            That art the worlds great arbitresse,
           </l>
           <l>
            And Queene of causes raigning heere:
           </l>
           <l>
            Whose swift-sure hand is euer neere
           </l>
           <l>
            Eternall iustice, righting wrong:
           </l>
           <l>
            Who neuer yet deferrest long
           </l>
           <l>
            The prowds decay, the weaks redresse:
           </l>
           <l>
            But through thy power euery where,
           </l>
           <l>
            Dost raze the great, and raise the lesse.
           </l>
           <l>
            The lesse made great dost ruine too,
           </l>
           <l>
            To shew the earth what heauen can do.
           </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
           <l>
            Thou from darke-clos'd eternitie,
           </l>
           <l>
            From thy blacke cloudy hidden seate,
           </l>
           <l>
            The worlds disorders dost desery:
           </l>
           <l>
            Which when they swell so prowdly great,
           </l>
           <l>
            Reuersing th'order nature set,
           </l>
           <l>
            Thou giu'st thy all confounding doome,
           </l>
           <l>
            Which none can know before it come.
           </l>
           <l>
            Th'ineuitable destinie,
           </l>
           <l>
            Which neither wit nor strength can let,
           </l>
           <l>
            Fast chain'd vnto necessitie,
           </l>
           <l>
            In mortall things doth order so,
           </l>
           <l>
            Th'alternate course of weale or wo.
           </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-028-a"/>
           <l>
            O how the powres of heauen doe play
           </l>
           <l>
            With trauailed mortalitie:
           </l>
           <l>
            And doth their weakenesse still betray,
           </l>
           <l>
            In their best prosperitie?
           </l>
           <l>
            When being lifted vp so hie,
           </l>
           <l>
            They looke beyond themselues so farre,
           </l>
           <l>
            That to themselues they take no care;
           </l>
           <l>
            Whilst swift confusion downe doth lay,
           </l>
           <l>
            Their late prowd mounting vanitie:
           </l>
           <l>
            Bringing their glory to decay,
           </l>
           <l>
            And with the ruine of their fall,
           </l>
           <l>
            Extinguish people, state and all.
           </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
           <l>
            But is it Iustice that all wee
           </l>
           <l>
            The innocent poore multitude,
           </l>
           <l>
            For great mens faults should punisht be,
           </l>
           <l>
            And to destruction thus pursude?
           </l>
           <l>
            O why should th'heauens vs include,
           </l>
           <l>
            Within the compasse of their fall,
           </l>
           <l>
            Who of themselues procured all?
           </l>
           <l>
            Or do the gods in close decree,
           </l>
           <l>
            Occasion take how to extrude
           </l>
           <l>
            Man from the earth with crueltie?
           </l>
           <l>
            Ah no, the gods are euer iust,
           </l>
           <l>
            Our faults excuse their rigor must.
           </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
           <l>
            This is the period Fate set downe,
           </l>
           <l>
            To Egypts fat prosperitie:
           </l>
           <l>
            Which now vnto her greatest growne,
           </l>
           <l>
            Must perish thus, by course must die,
           </l>
           <l>
            And some must be the causers why
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-028-b"/>
           <l>
            This reuolution must be wrought:
           </l>
           <l>
            As borne to bring their state to nought:
           </l>
           <l>
            To change the people and the crowne,
           </l>
           <l>
            And purge the worlds iniquitie:
           </l>
           <l>
            Which vice so farre hath ouer growne.
           </l>
           <l>
            As we, so they that treate vs thus,
           </l>
           <l>
            Must one day perish like to vs.
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
        </div>
       </div>
       <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="ep000822-e16450">
        <head>
         ACTVS QVARTVS.
        </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000822-e16470">
         Seleucus. Rodon.
        </stage>
        <sp who="ep000822-sel" xml:id="ep000822-e16480">
         <speaker>
          Sel.
         </speaker>
         <lg>
          <l>
           FRiend Rodon neuer in a better bowre,
          </l>
          <l>
           Could I haue met thee then eu'n now I do,
          </l>
          <l>
           Hauing affliction in the greatest powre
          </l>
          <l>
           Vpon my soule, and none to tell it too.
          </l>
          <l>
           For tis some ease our sorrowes to reueale,
          </l>
          <l>
           If they to whom we shall impart our woes
          </l>
          <l>
           Seeme but to feele a part of what we feele:
          </l>
          <l>
           And meete vs with a sigh but at a cloze.
          </l>
         </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000822-rod" xml:id="ep000822-e16600">
         <speaker>
          Rod.
         </speaker>
         <lg>
          <l>
           And neuer (friend Seleuchus) found'st thou one
          </l>
          <l>
           That better could beare such a part with thee:
          </l>
          <l>
           Who by his own, knows others cares to mone,
          </l>
          <l>
           And can, in like accord of griefe, agree.
          </l>
          <l>
           And therefore tell th'oppression of thy hart,
          </l>
          <l>
           Tell to an eare prepar'd and tun'd to care:
          </l>
          <l>
           And I will likewise vnto thee impart
          </l>
          <l>
           As sad a tale as what thou shalt declare.
          </l>
          <l>
           So shall we both our mournefull plaints combine,
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-029-a"/>
          <l>
           Ile waile thy state, and thou shalt pittie mine.
          </l>
         </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000822-cel" xml:id="ep000822-e16740">
         <speaker>
          Cel.
         </speaker>
         <lg>
          <l>
           Wel then, thou know'st how I haue liu'd in grace
          </l>
          <l>
           With Cleopatra, and esteem'd in Court
          </l>
          <l>
           As one of Councell, and of chiefest place,
          </l>
          <l>
           And euer held my credite in that sort.
          </l>
          <l>
           Till now in this confusion of our state,
          </l>
          <l>
           When thinking to haue vs'd a meane to climbe,
          </l>
          <l>
           And fled the wretched, flowne vnto the great,
          </l>
          <l>
           (Following the fortune of the present time,)
          </l>
          <l>
           Am come to be cast downe and ruin'd cleane;
          </l>
          <l>
           And in the course of mine own plot vndone.
          </l>
          <l>
           For hauing all the secrets of the Queene
          </l>
          <l>
           Reueald to Caesar, to haue fauor wonne.
          </l>
          <l>
           My trechery is quited with disgrace,
          </l>
          <l>
           My falshood loath'd, and not without great reason.
          </l>
          <l>
           Though good for him, yet Princes in this case
          </l>
          <l>
           Do hate the Traitor, though they loue the treason.
          </l>
          <l>
           For how could he imagine I would be
          </l>
          <l>
           Faithfull to him, being false vnto mine owne?
          </l>
          <l>
           And false to such a bounteous Queene as she.
          </l>
          <l>
           That had me rais'd and made mine honor knowne.
          </l>
          <l>
           He saw twas not for zeale to him I bare,
          </l>
          <l>
           But for base feare, or mine owne state to settle.
          </l>
          <l>
           Weakenesse is false, and faith in Cowards rare,
          </l>
          <l>
           Feare findes out shifts, timiditie is subtle.
          </l>
          <l>
           And therefore scorn'd of him, scorn'd of mine own.
          </l>
          <l>
           Hatefull to all that looke into my state:
          </l>
          <l>
           Despis'd Seleucus now is onely grown
          </l>
          <l>
           The marke of infamy, that is pointed at.
          </l>
         </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000822-rod" xml:id="ep000822-e17080">
         <speaker>
          Rod.
         </speaker>
         <lg>
          <l>
           Tis much thou saist, and O too much to feele,
          </l>
          <l>
           And I do grieue and do lament thy fall:
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-029-b"/>
          <l>
           But yet all this which thou doest heere reueale,
          </l>
          <l>
           Compar'd with mine, will make thine seeme but small.
          </l>
          <l>
           Although my fault be in the selfe-same kind,
          </l>
          <l>
           Yet in degree far greater, far more hatefull;
          </l>
          <l>
           Mine sprong of mischiefe, thine from feeble mind,
          </l>
          <l>
           I staind with blood, thou onely but vngratefull.
          </l>
          <l>
           For vnto me did Cleopatra giu&#9679;&#9679;
          </l>
          <l>
           The best and deerest treasure of her blood,
          </l>
          <l>
           Louely Caesario, whom she would haue liue
          </l>
          <l>
           Free from the dangers wherein Egypt stoode.
          </l>
          <l>
           And vnto me with him this charge she gaue,
          </l>
          <l>
           Here Rodon, take, conuey from out this coast,
          </l>
          <l>
           This precious Gem, the chiefest that I haue,
          </l>
          <l>
           The iewell of any soule I value most.
          </l>
          <l>
           Guide him to India, leade him farre from hence,
          </l>
          <l>
           Safeguard him where secure he may remaine,
          </l>
          <l>
           Till better fortune call him backe from thence,
          </l>
          <l>
           And Egypts peace be reconcil'd againe.
          </l>
          <l>
           For this is he that may our hopes bring backe;
          </l>
          <l>
           (The rising Sunne of our declining state:)
          </l>
          <l>
           These be the hands that may restore our wracke,
          </l>
          <l>
           And raise the broken ruines made of late.
          </l>
          <l>
           He may giue limits to the boundlesse pride
          </l>
          <l>
           Of fierce Octauius, and abate his might:
          </l>
          <l>
           Great Iulius of&#9679; spring, he may come to guide
          </l>
          <l>
           The Empire of the world, &#9679;s his by right.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           O how he seemes the modell of his Syre?
          </l>
          <l>
           O how I gaze my Caesar in his face?
          </l>
          <l>
           Such was his gate, so did his lookes aspire;
          </l>
          <l>
           Such was his threatning brow, such was his grace.
          </l>
          <l>
           High shouldred, and his forehead euen as hie.
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-030-a"/>
          <l>
           And O, (if he had not beene borne so late.)
          </l>
          <l>
           He might haue rul'd the worlds great Monarchy.
          </l>
          <l>
           And now haue beene the Champion of our state.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           Then vnto him, O my deere Sonne (she saies,)
          </l>
          <l>
           Sonne of my youth, flie hence, O flie, be gone,
          </l>
          <l>
           Reserue thy selfe, ordain'd for better dayes,
          </l>
          <l>
           For much thou hast to ground thy hopes vpon.
          </l>
          <l>
           Leaue me (thy wofull Mother) to endure
          </l>
          <l>
           The fury of this tempest heere alone,
          </l>
          <l>
           Who cares not for her selfe, so thou be sure,
          </l>
          <l>
           Thou mayst reuenge, when others can but mone:
          </l>
          <l>
           Rodon will see thee safe, Rodon will guide
          </l>
          <l>
           Thee and thy wayes, thou shalt not neede to feare.
          </l>
          <l>
           Rodon (My faithfull seruant) will prouide
          </l>
          <l>
           What shal be best for the, take thou no care.
          </l>
          <l>
           And O good Rodon, looke well to his youth,
          </l>
          <l>
           The wayes are long, and dangers eu'ry where.
          </l>
          <l>
           I vrge it not that I doe doubt thy truth,
          </l>
          <l>
           Mothers will cast the worst, and alwayes feare.
          </l>
          <l>
           The absent danger greater still appeares,
          </l>
          <l>
           Lesse feares he, who is neere the thing he feares.
          </l>
          <l>
           And O, I know nor what presaging thought
          </l>
          <l>
           My sprite suggests of lucklesse bad euent:
          </l>
          <l>
           But yet it may be tis but Loue doth doate,
          </l>
          <l>
           Or ydle shadowes with my feares present,
          </l>
          <l>
           But yet the memory of mine owne fate
          </l>
          <l>
           Makes me feare his. And yet why should I feare
          </l>
          <l>
           His fortune may recouer better state,
          </l>
          <l>
           And he may come in pomp to gouerne here.
          </l>
          <l>
           But yet I doubt the Genius of our race
          </l>
          <l>
           By some malignant spirit comes ouerthrowne:
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-030-b"/>
          <l>
           Our bloud must be extinct, in my disgrace,
          </l>
          <l>
           Egypt must haue no more Kings of their owne,
          </l>
          <l>
           Then let him stay, and let vs fall together,
          </l>
          <l>
           Sith it is fore-decreed that we must all?
          </l>
          <l>
           Yet who knowes what may come? let him go thither.
          </l>
          <l>
           What Merchaunt i&#9679; one vessell ventures all?
          </l>
          <l>
           Let vs d&#9679;uide our starres. Go, go my sonne,
          </l>
          <l>
           Let not the fate of Egypt finde thee here:
          </l>
          <l>
           Try if so be thy destinie can shunne
          </l>
          <l>
           The common wracke of vs by being there.
          </l>
          <l>
           But who is he found&#9679; euer yet defence
          </l>
          <l>
           Against the heauens, or hid him any where?
          </l>
          <l>
           Then what neede I to send thee so farre hence
          </l>
          <l>
           To seeke thy death that mayst as well die here?
          </l>
          <l>
           And here die with thy mother, die in rest,
          </l>
          <l>
           Not trauelling to what will come to thee.
          </l>
          <l>
           Why should we leaue our bloud vnto the East,
          </l>
          <l>
           When Egypt may a Tombe sufficient be?
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           O my diuided soule, what shall I do?
          </l>
          <l>
           Whereon shall now my resolution rest?
          </l>
          <l>
           What were I best resolue to yeeld vnto,
          </l>
          <l>
           When both are bad, how shall I know the best?
          </l>
          <l>
           Stay, I may hap so worke with Caesar now,
          </l>
          <l>
           That he may yeelde him to restore thy right.
          </l>
          <l>
           Goe: Caesar neuer will consent that thou
          </l>
          <l>
           So neere in bloud, shalt be so great in might.
          </l>
          <l>
           Then take him Rodon, go my sonne, farewell.
          </l>
          <l>
           But stay there's something else that I would say:
          </l>
          <l>
           Yet nothing now, but O god speede thee well,
          </l>
          <l>
           Lest saving more, that more may make thee stay.
          </l>
          <l>
           Yet let me speake: It may be tis the last,
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-031-a"/>
          <l>
           That euer I shall speake to thee my sonne,
          </l>
          <l>
           Do Mothers vse to part in such post hast?
          </l>
          <l>
           What, must I end when I haue scarce begunne?
          </l>
          <l>
           Ah no (deere heart) tis no such slender twine
          </l>
          <l>
           Where with the knot is tide twixt thee and me,
          </l>
          <l>
           That bloud within thy veins came out of mine,
          </l>
          <l>
           Parting from thee I part from part of me:
          </l>
          <l>
           And therefore I must speake. Yet what? O sonne.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           Here more she would, when more she could not say,
          </l>
          <l>
           Sorrow rebounding backe whence it begunne,
          </l>
          <l>
           Filld vp the passage, and quite stopt the way:
          </l>
          <l>
           When sweet Caesario with a princely spirit,
          </l>
          <l>
           (Though comfortlesse himselfe) did comfort giue,
          </l>
          <l>
           With mildest wordes perswading her to beare it.
          </l>
          <l>
           And as for him, she should not neede to grieue.
          </l>
          <l>
           And I (with protesta&#9679;ions of my part.)
          </l>
          <l>
           Swore by that faith, (which sworne I did deceiue)
          </l>
          <l>
           That I would vse all care, all wit and art
          </l>
          <l>
           To see him safe; And so we tooke our leaue.
          </l>
          <l>
           Scarce had we trauail'd to our iurnie&#9679; end,
          </l>
          <l>
           When Caesar hauing knowledge of our way,
          </l>
          <l>
           His Agents after vs with speede doth send
          </l>
          <l>
           To labour me Caesario to betray.
          </l>
          <l>
           Who with rewards and promises so large,
          </l>
          <l>
           Assail'd me then, that I grew soone content
          </l>
          <l>
           And backe to Rhodes did reconuay my charge,
          </l>
          <l>
           Pretending that Octauius for him sent,
          </l>
          <l>
           To make him King of Egypt presently.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           And thither come, seeing himselfe betray'd.
          </l>
          <l>
           And in the hands of death through trechery,
          </l>
          <l>
           Wayling his state, thus to himselfe he said.
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-031-b"/>
          <l>
           Lo here brought backe by subtile traine to death
          </l>
          <l>
           Betraide by Tutors faith, or traitors rather
          </l>
          <l>
           My fault my bloud, and mine offence my birth,
          </l>
          <l>
           For being sonne of such a mighty Father.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           From India, (whither sent by mothers care,
          </l>
          <l>
           To be reseru'd from Egipts common wracke,)
          </l>
          <l>
           To Rhodes, (so long the armes of tyrants are,)
          </l>
          <l>
           I am by Caesars subtile reach brought backe:
          </l>
          <l>
           Heere to be made th'oblation for his feares,
          </l>
          <l>
           Who doubts the poore reuenge these ha&#772;ds may do him
          </l>
          <l>
           Respecting neither bloud, nor youth, nor yeeres,
          </l>
          <l>
           Or how small safety can my death be to him.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           And is this all the good of being borne great?
          </l>
          <l>
           Then wretched greatnesse proud rich miserie,
          </l>
          <l>
           Pompous distresse, glittering calamity.
          </l>
          <l>
           Is it for this th'ambitious Fathers sweat,
          </l>
          <l>
           To purchase bloud and death for them and theirs?
          </l>
          <l>
           I&#9679; this the issue that their glories get,
          </l>
          <l>
           So leaue a sure dest&#9679;uction to their heires?
          </l>
          <l>
           O how much better had it beene for me,
          </l>
          <l>
           From low descent, deriu'd of humble birth,
          </l>
          <l>
           T'haue eat the sweete sowre bread of pouerty,
          </l>
          <l>
           And drunke of Nylus streams in Nilus earth.
          </l>
          <l>
           Vnder the cou'ring of some quiet Cottage,
          </l>
          <l>
           Free from the wrath of heauen, secure in minde,
          </l>
          <l>
           Vntoucht when sad euents of princes dottage
          </l>
          <l>
           Confounds what euer mighty it doth finde.
          </l>
          <l>
           Out of the way of greatnesse, whose condition
          </l>
          <l>
           Is to haue all made cleere, and all thing plaine
          </l>
          <l>
           Betweene them and the marke of their ambition,
          </l>
          <l>
           That nothing let, the full sight of their raigne
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-032-a"/>
          <l>
           Where nothing stands, that stands not in submission;
          </l>
          <l>
           Where greatnesse must all in it selfe containe.
          </l>
          <l>
           Kings will be alone, Competitors must downe,
          </l>
          <l>
           Neere death he stands, that stands to neare a Crowne.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           Such is my case, for Caesar will haue all.
          </l>
          <l>
           My bloud must feale th'assurance of his state:
          </l>
          <l>
           Yet ah weake state that bloud assure him shall,
          </l>
          <l>
           Whose wrong full shedding, gods and men do hate.
          </l>
          <l>
           Iniustice neuer scapes vnpunisht still,
          </l>
          <l>
           Though men reuenge not, yet the heauens will.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           And thou Augustus that with bloudy hand,
          </l>
          <l>
           Cut'st off succession from anothers race,
          </l>
          <l>
           Maist find the heauens thy vowes so to withstand,
          </l>
          <l>
           That others may depriue thine in like case
          </l>
          <l>
           When thou mayst see thy prowde contentious bed
          </l>
          <l>
           Yeelding thee none of thine that may inherite:
          </l>
          <l>
           Subuert thy bloud, place others in their sted,
          </l>
          <l>
           To pay this thy iniustice her due merite.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           If it be true (as who can that denie
          </l>
          <l>
           Which sacred Priests of Memphis doe fore-say)
          </l>
          <l>
           Some of the of-spring yet of Antony.
          </l>
          <l>
           Shall all the rule of this whole Empire sway;
          </l>
          <l>
           And then Augustus, what is it thou gainest
          </l>
          <l>
           By poore Antillus bloud, or this of mine?
          </l>
          <l>
           Nothing but this thy victory thou, stainest,
          </l>
          <l>
           And pull'st the wrath of heauen on thee and thine.
          </l>
          <l>
           In vaine doth man contend against the starr's,
          </l>
          <l>
           For that he seekes to make, his wisdome marr's.
          </l>
          <l>
           Yet in the mean-time we whom Fates reserue,
          </l>
          <l>
           The bloudy sacrifices of ambition
          </l>
          <l>
           We feele the smart what euer they deserue,
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-032-b"/>
          <l>
           And we indure the present times condition.
          </l>
          <l>
           The iustice of the heauens reuenging thus,
          </l>
          <l>
           Doth onely satisfie it selfe, not vs.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           Yet tis a pleasing comfort that doth ease
          </l>
          <l>
           Affliction in so great extremity.
          </l>
          <l>
           To thinke their dike destruction shall appease
          </l>
          <l>
           Our ghosts, who did procure our misery.
          </l>
          <l>
           But dead we are, vncertaine what shall bee,
          </l>
          <l>
           And liuing, we are sure to feele the wrong:
          </l>
          <l>
           Our certaine ruine we our selues do see.
          </l>
          <l>
           They ioy the while, and we know not how long.
          </l>
          <l>
           But yet Caesarie, thou must die content,
          </l>
          <l>
           For men will mone, and God reuenge th'innocent.
          </l>
          <l>
           Thus he complain'd, and thus thou hea'rst my shame,
          </l>
         </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000822-sl" xml:id="ep000822-e19550">
         <speaker>
          S&#9679;l.
         </speaker>
         <l>
          But how hath Caesar now rewarded thee?
         </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000822-rod" xml:id="ep000822-e19590">
         <speaker>
          Rod.
         </speaker>
         <lg>
          <l>
           As he hath thee. And I expect the same,
          </l>
          <l>
           As fell to Theodor to fall to me:
          </l>
          <l>
           For he (one of my coate) hauing betraid
          </l>
          <l>
           The yong Antillus sonne of Anthony,
          </l>
          <l>
           And at his death from off his necke conuaid
          </l>
          <l>
           A iewell: which being ask&#9679;, he did denie:
          </l>
          <l>
           Caesar occasion tooke to hang him strait.
          </l>
          <l>
           Such instruments with Princes liue not long.
          </l>
          <l>
           Although they need such actors of deceit,
          </l>
          <l>
           Yet still our sight seemes to vpbraid their wrong;
          </l>
          <l>
           And therefore we must needes this daunger runne,
          </l>
          <l>
           And in the net of our owne guile be caught:
          </l>
          <l>
           We must not liue to brag what we haue done.
          </l>
          <l>
           For what is done, must not appeare their fault.
          </l>
          <l>
           But here comes Cleopatrae, Wofull Queene,
          </l>
          <l>
           And our shame wil not that we should be seene.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <stage xml:id="ep000822-e19820">
          Exeunt.
         </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000822-cleopatra" xml:id="ep000822-e19830">
         <pb xml:id="ep000822-033-a"/>
         <speaker>
          Cleopatra.
         </speaker>
         <lg>
          <l>
           WHat hath my face yet power to win a Louer?
          </l>
          <l>
           Can this torne remnant serue to grace me so,
          </l>
          <l>
           That it can Caesars secret plots discouer
          </l>
          <l>
           What he intends with me and mine to do?
          </l>
          <l>
           Why then poore Beautie thou hast done thy last,
          </l>
          <l>
           And best good seruice thou could'st do vnto me.
          </l>
          <l>
           For now the time of death reueal'd thou hast,
          </l>
          <l>
           Which in my life didst serue but to vndoe me.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           Heere Dolabella far forsooth in loue,
          </l>
          <l>
           Writes, how that Caesar meanes forthwith, to send
          </l>
          <l>
           Both me and mine, th'ayre of Rome to proue:
          </l>
          <l>
           There his Triumphant Chariot to attend.
          </l>
          <l>
           I thanke the man, both for his loue and letter;
          </l>
          <l>
           The one comes fit to warne me thus before,
          </l>
          <l>
           But for th'other, I must die his debter,
          </l>
          <l>
           For Cleopatra now can loue no more.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           But hauing leaue, I must go take my leaue
          </l>
          <l>
           And last farewell of my dead Anthonie:
          </l>
          <l>
           Whose deerly honour'd tombe must here receiue
          </l>
          <l>
           This sacrifice, the last before I die
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           O sacred euer-memorable stone,
          </l>
          <l>
           That hast without my teares, within my flame,
          </l>
          <l>
           Receiue th'oblation of the wofull'st mone
          </l>
          <l>
           That euer yet from sad affliction came.
          </l>
          <l>
           And you deare reliques of my Lord and Loue,
          </l>
          <l>
           (The sweetest parcels of the faithfull'st liuer,)
          </l>
          <l>
           O let no impious hand dare to remoue
          </l>
          <l>
           You out from hence, but rest you here for euer.
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-033-b"/>
          <l>
           Let Egypt now giue peace vnto you dead,
          </l>
          <l>
           That liuing gaue you trouble and turmoile:
          </l>
          <l>
           Sleepe quiet in this euer-lasting bed,
          </l>
          <l>
           In forraine land preferr'd before your soile,
          </l>
          <l>
           And O, if that the sp'rits of men remaine
          </l>
          <l>
           After their bodies; and do neuer die,
          </l>
          <l>
           Then heare thy ghost, thy captiue spouse complaine,
          </l>
          <l>
           And be attentiue to her miserie.
          </l>
          <l>
           But if that laboursome mortallitie
          </l>
          <l>
           Found this sweete error, onely to confine
          </l>
          <l>
           The curious search of idle vanitie,
          </l>
          <l>
           That would the deapth of darknesse vndermine:
          </l>
          <l>
           Or rather to giue rest vnto the thought
          </l>
          <l>
           Of wretched man, with th'after-comming ioy
          </l>
          <l>
           Of those conceiued fields whereon we dote,
          </l>
          <l>
           To pacifie the present worlds annoy:
          </l>
          <l>
           Then do I speake but onely to the ayre:
          </l>
          <l>
           But tis not so, my Anthonie doth heare:
          </l>
          <l>
           His euer-liuing ghost attends my prayer,
          </l>
          <l>
           And I do know his houering sprite is neere.
          </l>
          <l>
           And I will speake, and pray, and mourne to thee,
          </l>
          <l>
           O pure immortall loue that daign'st to heare:
          </l>
          <l>
           I feele thou answer'st my credulitie
          </l>
          <l>
           With touch of comfort, finding none elsewhere.
          </l>
          <l>
           Thou know'st these hands intomb'd thee here of late,
          </l>
          <l>
           Free and vnforc'd, which now must seruile be,
          </l>
          <l>
           Reseru'd for bands to grace proud Caesars state,
          </l>
          <l>
           Who seekes in me to triumph ouer thee.
          </l>
          <l>
           O if in life we could not seuerd be,
          </l>
          <l>
           Shall death diuide our bodies now a sunder?
          </l>
          <l>
           Must thine in Egypt, mine in Italie,
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-034-a"/>
          <l>
           Be kept the Monuments of Fortunes wonder?
          </l>
          <l>
           If any powres be there whereas thou art,
          </l>
          <l>
           (Sith our owne cuntry gods betray our case,)
          </l>
          <l>
           O worke they may their gracious helpe impart,
          </l>
          <l>
           To saue thy wofull wife from such disgrace.
          </l>
          <l>
           Do not permit she shoutd in triumph shew
          </l>
          <l>
           The blush of her reproach, ioyn'd with thy shame
          </l>
          <l>
           But (rather) let that hate full tyrant know,
          </l>
          <l>
           That thou and I had powre t'auoyde the same.
          </l>
          <l>
           But what do I spend breath and ydle winde.
          </l>
          <l>
           In vaine inuoking a conceiued ayde?
          </l>
          <l>
           Why do I not my selfe occasion finde
          </l>
          <l>
           To breake the bounds wherein my selfe am staide?
          </l>
          <l>
           Words are for them that can complaine and liue,
          </l>
          <l>
           Whose melting hearts composd of baser frame,
          </l>
          <l>
           Can to their sorrows, time and leasure giue,
          </l>
          <l>
           But Cleopatra may not do the same.
          </l>
          <l>
           No Antony, thy loue requireth more:
          </l>
          <l>
           A lingring death, with thee deserues no merite,
          </l>
          <l>
           I must my selfe force open wide a dore
          </l>
          <l>
           To let out life, and so vnhouse my spirit.
          </l>
          <l>
           These hands must breake the prison of my soule
          </l>
          <l>
           To come to thee, there to enioy like state,
          </l>
          <l>
           As doth the long-pent solitary Foule.
          </l>
          <l>
           That hath escapt her cage, and found her mate,
          </l>
          <l>
           This sacrifice to sacrifize my life,
          </l>
          <l>
           Is that true incense that dooth best beseeme:
          </l>
          <l>
           These rites may serue a life-desiring wife,
          </l>
          <l>
           Who doing them, t'haue done enough doth deeme.
          </l>
          <l>
           My-hart-bloud should the purple flowers haue beene,
          </l>
          <l>
           Which heere vpon thy Tombe to thee are offred.
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-034-b"/>
          <l>
           No smoake but dying breath should here bin seene,
          </l>
          <l>
           And this it had bin too, had I bin suffred.
          </l>
          <l>
           But what haue I saue these bare silly hands?
          </l>
          <l>
           And these weake fingers are not iron-poynted:
          </l>
          <l>
           They cannot pierce with them which stands
          </l>
          <l>
           And I of all meanes else am disapointed.
          </l>
          <l>
           But yet I must some way endeuour how
          </l>
          <l>
           To come vnto thee, whatsoere I do.
          </l>
          <l>
           O Death, art thou sohard to come by now,
          </l>
          <l>
           That we must pray, intreate, and seeke thee too?
          </l>
          <l>
           But I will finde thee wheresoere thou lie.
          </l>
          <l>
           For who can stay a minde resolu'd to die?
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           And now I go to worke th'effect indeed,
          </l>
          <l>
           Ile neuer send more words or sights to thee:
          </l>
          <l>
           Ile bring my soule my selfe, and that with speede,
          </l>
          <l>
           My selfe will bring my soule to Antony.
          </l>
          <l>
           Come go my maides, my fortunes sole attenders,
          </l>
          <l>
           That minister to misery and sorrow:
          </l>
          <l>
           Your Mistris you vnto your freedome renders.
          </l>
          <l>
           And Will discharge your charge yet ere to morrow.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           And now by this, I thinke the man I sent,
          </l>
          <l>
           Is neere retourn'd that brings me my dispatch.
          </l>
          <l>
           God grant his cunning sort to good euent,
          </l>
          <l>
           And that his skill may well beguile my watch:
          </l>
          <l>
           So shall I shun disgrace, leaue to be sorry,
          </l>
          <l>
           Flie to my loue, scape my foe, free my soule;
          </l>
          <l>
           So shall I act the last of life with glory,
          </l>
          <l>
           Die like a Queene, and rest without controule.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <stage xml:id="ep000822-e21190">
          Exit.
         </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000822-chorvs" xml:id="ep000822-e21200">
         <pb xml:id="ep000822-035-a"/>
         <speaker>
          CHORVS.
         </speaker>
         <lg>
          <l>
           MIsterious Egypt, wonder breeder,
          </l>
          <l>
           Strict Religions strange obseruer,
          </l>
          <l>
           State-ordrer zeale, the best rule-keeper,
          </l>
          <l>
           Fostring still in temp'rate feruor:
          </l>
          <l>
           O how cam'st thou to lose so wholy
          </l>
          <l>
           all religion, law and order?
          </l>
          <l>
           And thus become the most vnholy
          </l>
          <l>
           of all Lands, that Nylus border?
          </l>
          <l>
           How could confus'd Disorder enter
          </l>
          <l>
           where sterne Law sate so seuerely?
          </l>
          <l>
           How durst weake lust and riot venter
          </l>
          <l>
           th'eye of Iustice looking neerely?
          </l>
          <l>
           Could not those meanes that made thee great
          </l>
          <l>
           Be still the meanes to keepe thy state?
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           Ah no, the course of things requireth
          </l>
          <l>
           change and alteration euer:
          </l>
          <l>
           That stayd continuance man desireth,
          </l>
          <l>
           th'vnconstant world yeeldeth neuer.
          </l>
          <l>
           We in our counsels must be blinded,
          </l>
          <l>
           And not see what doth import vs:
          </l>
          <l>
           And often times the thing least minded
          </l>
          <l>
           is the thing that most must hurt vs.
          </l>
          <l>
           Yet they that haue the sterne in guiding,
          </l>
          <l>
           tis their fault that should preuent it,
          </l>
          <l>
           Who when they see their Country sliding,
          </l>
          <l>
           for their priuate are contented.
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-035-b"/>
          <l>
           We imitate the greater powers,
          </l>
          <l>
           The Princes manners fashion ours.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           Th'example of their light regarding,
          </l>
          <l>
           vulgar loosenesse much incenses:
          </l>
          <l>
           Vice uncontrould, growes wide inlarging,
          </l>
          <l>
           Kings small faults be great offences.
          </l>
          <l>
           And this hath set the window open
          </l>
          <l>
           vnto licence, lust, and riot:
          </l>
          <l>
           This way confusion first found broken,
          </l>
          <l>
           whereby entred our disquiet,
          </l>
          <l>
           Those lawes that olde Sesostris founded,
          </l>
          <l>
           and the Ptolomies obserued,
          </l>
          <l>
           Hereby first came to be confounded,
          </l>
          <l>
           which our state so long preserued.
          </l>
          <l>
           The wanton luxurie of Court.
          </l>
          <l>
           Did forme the people of like sort.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           For all (respecting priuate pleasure,)
          </l>
          <l>
           vniuersally consenting
          </l>
          <l>
           To abuse their time their treasure,
          </l>
          <l>
           in their owne delights contenting:
          </l>
          <l>
           And future dangers nought respecting,
          </l>
          <l>
           whereby, (O how easie matter
          </l>
          <l>
           Made this so generall neglecting,
          </l>
          <l>
           confus'd weakenesse to discatter?)
          </l>
          <l>
           Caesar found th'effect true tried,
          </l>
          <l>
           in his easie entrance making:
          </l>
          <l>
           Who at the sight of armes, deseryed
          </l>
          <l>
           all our people, all forsaking.
          </l>
          <l>
           For ryot (worse then warre,) so sore
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000822-036-a"/>
          <l>
           Had wasted all our strength before.
          </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
          <l>
           And thus is Egypt seruile rendred
          </l>
          <l>
           to the insolent destroyer:
          </l>
          <l>
           And all their sumptuous treasure tendred,
          </l>
          <l>
           all her wealth that did betray her,
          </l>
          <l>
           Which poison (O if heauen be rightfull,)
          </l>
          <l>
           may so farre infect their sences,
          </l>
          <l>
           That Egypts pleasures so delightfull,
          </l>
          <l>
           may breed them the like offences.
          </l>
          <l>
           And Romans learne our way of weakenes,
          </l>
          <l>
           be instructed in our vices:
          </l>
          <l>
           That our spoiles may spoile your greatnes,
          </l>
          <l>
           ouercome with our deuises.
          </l>
          <l>
           Fill full your hands, and carry home
          </l>
          <l>
           Enough from vs to ruine Rome.
          </l>
         </lg>
        </sp>
       </div>
       <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="ep000822-e22010">
        <head>
         ACTVS QVINTVS.
        </head>
        <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000822-e22030">
         <stage xml:id="ep000822-e22040">
          Dolabella. Titius.
         </stage>
         <sp who="ep000822-dol" xml:id="ep000822-e22050">
          <speaker>
           Dol.
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            COme tell me Titius eu'ry circumstance
           </l>
           <l>
            How Cleopatra did receiue my newes:
           </l>
           <l>
            Tell eu'ry looke, each gesture, countenance,
           </l>
           <l>
            That she did in my Letters reading vse.
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-tit" xml:id="ep000822-e22140">
          <speaker>
           Tit.
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            I shall my Lord, so farre as I could note,
           </l>
           <l>
            Or my conceit obserue in any wise.
           </l>
           <l>
            It was the time when as she hauing got
           </l>
           <l>
            Leaue to her Deerest dead to sacrifice;
           </l>
           <l>
            And now was issuing out the monument
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-036-b"/>
           <l>
            With odors, incense, garlands in her hand,
           </l>
           <l>
            When I approacht (as one from Caesar sent,)
           </l>
           <l>
            And did her close, thy message t'vnderstand.
           </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
           <l>
            She turnes her backe, and with her takes me in,
           </l>
           <l>
            Reades in thy lines thy strange vnlookt for tale:
           </l>
           <l>
            And reades, and smiles, and staies, and doth begin
           </l>
           <l>
            Againe to read, then blusht, and then was pale.
           </l>
           <l>
            And hauing ended with a sigh, refoldes
           </l>
           <l>
            Thy Letter vp: and with a fixed eye,
           </l>
           <l>
            (Which stedfast her imagination holds)
           </l>
           <l>
            She mus'd a while, standing confusedly:
           </l>
           <l>
            At length. Ah friend, saith she) tell thy good Lord,
           </l>
           <l>
            How deere I hold his pittying of my case:
           </l>
           <l>
            That out of his sweete nature can affoord
           </l>
           <l>
            A miserable woman so much grace.
           </l>
           <l>
            Tell him how much my heauy soule doth grieue;
           </l>
           <l>
            Mercilesse Caesar should so deale with me:
           </l>
           <l>
            Pray him that he would all the counsell giue,
           </l>
           <l>
            That might diuert him from such crueltie.
           </l>
           <l>
            As for my loue, say Antony hath all,
           </l>
           <l>
            Say that my hart is gone into the graue
           </l>
           <l>
            With him, in whom it rests and euer shall:
           </l>
           <l>
            I haue it not my selfe, not cannot haue.
           </l>
           <l>
            Yet tell him, he shall more command of me
           </l>
           <l>
            Then any, whosoeuer liuing can.
           </l>
           <l>
            Hee that so friendly shewes himselfe to be
           </l>
           <l>
            A right kinde Roman, and a Gentleman.
           </l>
           <l>
            Although his Nation (fatall vnto me,)
           </l>
           <l>
            Haue had mine age a spoile, my youth a pray,
           </l>
           <l>
            Yet his affection must accepted be,
           </l>
           <l>
            That fauours one distrest in her decay.
           </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-037-a"/>
           <l>
            Ah. he was worthy then to haue been lou'd,
           </l>
           <l>
            Of Cleopatra whiles her glory lasted;
           </l>
           <l>
            Before she had declining fortune prou'd,
           </l>
           <l>
            Or seen her honour wrackt, her flowre thus blasted.
           </l>
           <l>
            Now there is nothing left her but disgrace,
           </l>
           <l>
            Nothing but her affliction that can moue,
           </l>
           <l>
            Tell Dolabella, one that's in her case.
           </l>
           <l>
            (Poore soule) needs rather pity now then loue.
           </l>
           <l>
            But shortly shall thy Lord heare more of me.
           </l>
           <l>
            And ending so her speech, no longer stai'd,
           </l>
           <l>
            But hasted to the tombe of Antonie,
           </l>
           <l>
            And this was all she did, and all she said.
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-dol" xml:id="ep000822-e22730">
          <speaker>
           Dol.
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            Ah sweete distressed Lady. What hard hart
           </l>
           <l>
            Could chuse but pity thee, and loue thee too?
           </l>
           <l>
            Thy worthines, the state where in thou art
           </l>
           <l>
            Requireth both, and both I vow to doo.
           </l>
           <l>
            Although ambition lets not Caesar see
           </l>
           <l>
            The wrong he doth thy maiesty and sweetnesse.
           </l>
           <l>
            Which makes him now exact so much of thee,
           </l>
           <l>
            To adde vnto himselfe to grace his greatnesse,
           </l>
           <l>
            He knowes thou canst no hurt procure vs now,
           </l>
           <l>
            Sith all thy strength is seizd into our hands:
           </l>
           <l>
            Nor seares he that, but rather labours how
           </l>
           <l>
            He might shew Rome so great a Queene in bands:
           </l>
           <l>
            That our great Ladies (enuying thee so much
           </l>
           <l>
            That stain'd them all, and held them in such wonder,)
           </l>
           <l>
            Might ioy to see thee, and thy fortune such,
           </l>
           <l>
            Thereby extolling him that brought thee vnder,
           </l>
           <l>
            But I will seeke to stay it what I may;
           </l>
           <l>
            I am but one, yet one that Caesar loues,
           </l>
           <l>
            And O if now I could do more then pray,
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-037-b"/>
           <l>
            Then should'st thou know how farre affection moues,
           </l>
           <l>
            But what my powre and prayer may preuaile,
           </l>
           <l>
            Ile ioyne them both, to hinder thy disgrace:
           </l>
           <l>
            And euen this present day I will not faile
           </l>
           <l>
            To doe my best with Caesar in this case.
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-tit" xml:id="ep000822-e23030">
          <speaker>
           Tit.
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            And sir, euen now herselfe hath letters sent.
           </l>
           <l>
            I met her messenger as I came hither,
           </l>
           <l>
            With a dispatch as he to Caesar went,
           </l>
           <l>
            But know not what imports her sending thither.
           </l>
           <l>
            Yet this he told, how Cleopatra late
           </l>
           <l>
            Was come from sacrifice. How richly clad
           </l>
           <l>
            Was seru'd to dinner in most sumptuous state,
           </l>
           <l>
            With all the brauest ornaments she had.
           </l>
           <l>
            How hauing din'd, she writes, and sends away
           </l>
           <l>
            Him strait to Caesar, and commanded than
           </l>
           <l>
            All should depart the Tombe, and none to stay
           </l>
           <l>
            But her two maides, and one Poore countriman.
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-dol" xml:id="ep000822-e23210">
          <speaker>
           Dol.
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            Why then I know she sends t'haue audience now,
           </l>
           <l>
            And meanes t'experience what her state can do:
           </l>
           <l>
            To see it maiestie will make him bow
           </l>
           <l>
            To what affliction could not moue him too.
           </l>
           <l>
            And O, if now she could but bring a view
           </l>
           <l>
            Of that fresh beauty she in youth possest
           </l>
           <l>
            (The argument wherewith she ouerthrew
           </l>
           <l>
            The wit of
            <hi>
             Iulius Caesar
            </hi>
            , and the rest,)
           </l>
           <l>
            Then happily Augustus might relent.
           </l>
           <l>
            Whilst powrefull Loue, (farre stronger then ambition)
           </l>
           <l>
            Might worke in him, a minde to be content
           </l>
           <l>
            To condescend vnto her small petition
           </l>
           <l>
            But being as she is, yet doth she merite
           </l>
           <l>
            To be respected for her hauing been,
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-038-a"/>
           <l>
            The wonder of her kinde, of so rare spirit,
           </l>
           <l>
            A glorious Lady, and a mighty Queene.
           </l>
           <l>
            And now, but by a little weakenesse &#9679;alling
           </l>
           <l>
            To do that which perhaps sh'was forst to do:
           </l>
           <l>
            Alas, an errour past, is past recalling,
           </l>
           <l>
            Take away weakenesse, and take women too.
           </l>
           <l>
            But now I go&#9679; to be thy aduocate,
           </l>
           <l>
            Sweete Cleopatra, now &#9679;le vse mine arte.
           </l>
           <l>
            Thy presence will me greatly animate,
           </l>
           <l>
            Thy face will teach my tongue, thy loue my hart.
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="ep000822-e23510">
         <head>
          SCENA SECVNDA.
         </head>
         <sp who="ep000822-nuntius" xml:id="ep000822-e23530">
          <speaker>
           Nuntius.
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            AM I ordain'd the carefull Messenger,
           </l>
           <l>
            And sad newes-bringer of the strangest death,
           </l>
           <l>
            Which selfe hand did vpon it selfe inferre,
           </l>
           <l>
            To free a captiue soule from seruile breath?
           </l>
           <l>
            Must I the lamentable wonder shew,
           </l>
           <l>
            Which all the world may grieue and maruell at?
           </l>
           <l>
            The rarest forme of death on earth below,
           </l>
           <l>
            That euer pitty, glory, wonder gat.
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-cho" xml:id="ep000822-e23640">
          <speaker>
           Cho.
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            What newes bringst thou, can Egipt yet yeeld more,
           </l>
           <l>
            Of sorrow than it hath? what can it adde
           </l>
           <l>
            Vnto th'already ouerflowing store
           </l>
           <l>
            Of sad affliction, matter yet more sad?
           </l>
           <l>
            Haue we not seene our worst calamity?
           </l>
           <l>
            Is there behind yet something of distresse
           </l>
           <l>
            Vnknowne? if there be greater misery
           </l>
           <l>
            Relate it, that we do not waile the lesse.
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-038-b"/>
           <l>
            Tell vs what so it be, and tell at first,
           </l>
           <l>
            For sorrow euer longs to heare her worst.
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-nu" xml:id="ep000822-e23770">
          <speaker>
           Nu.
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            Well then, the strangest thing relate I will,
           </l>
           <l>
            That euer eye of mortall man hath seene.
           </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
           <l>
            I (as you know) euen from my youth, haue still
           </l>
           <l>
            Attended on the person of the Queene:
           </l>
           <l>
            And euer in all fortunes good or ill,
           </l>
           <l>
            With her as one of chiefest trust haue beene.
           </l>
           <l>
            And now in these so great extremities,
           </l>
           <l>
            That euer could to maiesty be fall,
           </l>
           <l>
            I did my best in what I could deuise,
           </l>
           <l>
            And left her not, till now she left vs all.
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-cho" xml:id="ep000822-e23910">
          <speaker>
           Cho.
          </speaker>
          <l>
           What is she gone. Hath Caesar forst her so?
          </l>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-nun" xml:id="ep000822-e23950">
          <speaker>
           Nun.
          </speaker>
          <l>
           Yea, she is gone, and hath deceiu'd him too.
          </l>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-cho" xml:id="ep000822-e23980">
          <speaker>
           Cho.
          </speaker>
          <l>
           What, fled to India; to go find her sonne?
          </l>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-nun" xml:id="ep000822-e24020">
          <speaker>
           Nun.
          </speaker>
          <l>
           No, not to India, but to finde her sonne.
          </l>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-cho" xml:id="ep000822-e24060">
          <speaker>
           Cho.
          </speaker>
          <l>
           Why the&#772; there's hope she may her state recouer
          </l>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-nun" xml:id="ep000822-e24090">
          <speaker>
           Nun.
          </speaker>
          <l>
           Her state? nay rather honour, and her Louer.
          </l>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-cho" xml:id="ep000822-e24120">
          <speaker>
           Cho.
          </speaker>
          <l>
           Her Louer? him she cannot haue againe.
          </l>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-nun" xml:id="ep000822-e24150">
          <speaker>
           Nun.
          </speaker>
          <l>
           Wel, him she hath, with him she doth remaine
          </l>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-cho" xml:id="ep000822-e24180">
          <speaker>
           Cho.
          </speaker>
          <l>
           Why the&#772; she's dead Istso? why speakst not thou
          </l>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-nun" xml:id="ep000822-e24210">
          <speaker>
           Nun.
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            You gesse aright, and I will tell you how.
           </l>
           <l>
            When she perceiu'd all hope was cleane bereft,
           </l>
           <l>
            That Caesar meant to send her strait away,
           </l>
           <l>
            And saw no meanes of reconcilement left,
           </l>
           <l>
            Worke what she could, she could not worke to stay:
           </l>
           <l>
            She calls me to her, and she thus began.
           </l>
           <l>
            O thou, whose trust hath euer beene the same,
           </l>
           <l>
            And one in all my fortunes, faithfull man,
           </l>
           <l>
            Alone conten&#9679; t'attend disgrace and shame.
           </l>
           <l>
            Thou, whom the fea&#9679;efull ruine of my fall,
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-039-a"/>
           <l>
            Neuer deterr'd to leaue calamitie:
           </l>
           <l>
            As did those others smooth state-pleasers all,
           </l>
           <l>
            Who followed but my fortune, and not me.
           </l>
           <l>
            Tis thou must do a seruice for thy Queene,
           </l>
           <l>
            Wherein thy faith and skill must do their best:
           </l>
           <l>
            Thy honest care and d&#9679;uy shal be seene,
           </l>
           <l>
            Performing this, more then in all the rest.
           </l>
           <l>
            For all what thou hast done, may die with thee,
           </l>
           <l>
            Although tis pitty that such faith should die.
           </l>
           <l>
            But this shall euermore remembred be,
           </l>
           <l>
            A rare example to posterity.
           </l>
           <l>
            And looke how long as Cleopatra shall
           </l>
           <l>
            In after ages liue in memory.
           </l>
           <l>
            So long shall thy cleere same endure withall,
           </l>
           <l>
            And therefore thou must not my sute deny
           </l>
           <l>
            Nor contradict my will. For what I will
           </l>
           <l>
            I am resolu'd&#9679; and this now must it be:
           </l>
           <l>
            Go find me out with all thy art and skill
           </l>
           <l>
            Two Aspicks, and conuay them close to me.
           </l>
           <l>
            I haue a worke to do with them in hand,
           </l>
           <l>
            Enquire not what, for thou shalt soone see what,
           </l>
           <l>
            If th'heauens do not my disseigns withstand,
           </l>
           <l>
            But do thy charge, and let me shift with that.
           </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
           <l>
            Being thus coniur'd by her t'whom I had vow'd
           </l>
           <l>
            My true perpetuall seruice, forth I went,
           </l>
           <l>
            Deuising how my close attempt to shrowde,
           </l>
           <l>
            So that there might no art my art preuent.
           </l>
           <l>
            And so disguisd in habite as you see,
           </l>
           <l>
            Hauing found out the thing for which I went,
           </l>
           <l>
            I soone return'd againe, and brought with me
           </l>
           <l>
            The Aspicks, in a basket closely pent.
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-039-b"/>
           <l>
            Which I had filld with Figges, and leaues vpon.
           </l>
           <l>
            And comming to the guard that kept the dore,
           </l>
           <l>
            What hast thou there? said they, and lookt thereon.
           </l>
           <l>
            Seeing the figges, they deem'd of nothing more,
           </l>
           <l>
            But said, they were the fayrest they had seene.
           </l>
           <l>
            Taste some, said I, for they are good and pleasant.
           </l>
           <l>
            No, no, said they, go beare them to thy Queene,
           </l>
           <l>
            Thinking me some poore man that brought a present.
           </l>
           <l>
            Well, in I went, wherebrighter then the Sunne,
           </l>
           <l>
            Glittering in all her pompous rich aray,
           </l>
           <l>
            Great Cleopatra sate, as if sh'had wonne
           </l>
           <l>
            Caesar, and all the world beside this day:
           </l>
           <l>
            Euen as she was when on thy cristall streames.
           </l>
           <l>
            Cleere Cydnos she did shew what earth could shew.
           </l>
           <l>
            When Asia all ama'zd in wonder deemes
           </l>
           <l>
            Venus from heauen was come on earth below,
           </l>
           <l>
            Euen as she went at first to meet her Loue,
           </l>
           <l>
            So goes she now at last againe to find him.
           </l>
           <l>
            But that first, did her greatnesse onely proue,
           </l>
           <l>
            This last her loue, that could not liue behind him.
           </l>
           <l>
            Yet as she sate, the doubt of my good speed,
           </l>
           <l>
            Detracts much from the sweetnesse of her looke:
           </l>
           <l>
            Cheere-marrer Care, did then such passions breed,
           </l>
           <l>
            That made her eye bewray the griefe she tooke.
           </l>
           <l>
            But she no sooner sees me in the place,
           </l>
           <l>
            But strait her sorrow-clouded brow she cleeres,
           </l>
           <l>
            Lightning a smile from out a stormie face.
           </l>
           <l>
            Which all her tempest-beaten sences cheeres.
           </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
           <l>
            Looke how a strayed perplexed traueller,
           </l>
           <l>
            When chasd by theeues, and euen at point of &#9679;&#9679;king,
           </l>
           <l>
            Descrying sodainly some towne not far,
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-040-a"/>
           <l>
            Or some vnlookt for aide to him-warde making;
           </l>
           <l>
            Cheeres vp his tyred sprites, thrusts forth his strength
           </l>
           <l>
            To meete that good, that comes in so good houre:
           </l>
           <l>
            Such was her ioy perceiuing now at length,
           </l>
           <l>
            Her honour was t'escape so proud a power.
           </l>
           <l>
            Forth from her seate she hastes to meete the present,
           </l>
           <l>
            And as one ouer-ioy'd, she caught it strait.
           </l>
           <l>
            And with a smiling cheere in action pleasant,
           </l>
           <l>
            Looking among the figs, findes the deceit.
           </l>
           <l>
            And seeing there the vgly venemous beast,
           </l>
           <l>
            Nothing dismaid, she fayes and views it well,
           </l>
           <l>
            At length th'extreamest of her passion ceast,
           </l>
           <l>
            When she began with words her ioy to tell.
           </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
           <l>
            O rarest beast (saith she) that Affrick breeds,
           </l>
           <l>
            How deerely welcome art thou vnto me?
           </l>
           <l>
            The fearest creature that faire Nylus feedes
           </l>
           <l>
            Me thinks I see, in now beholding thee.
           </l>
           <l>
            What though the euer-erring world doth deeme
           </l>
           <l>
            That angred Nature fram'd thee bu&#9679; in spight?
           </l>
           <l>
            Little they know what they of light esteeme,
           </l>
           <l>
            That neuer learn'd the wonder of thy might.
           </l>
           <l>
            Better then Death, Deaths office thou dischargest.
           </l>
           <l>
            That with on&#9679; gentle touch canst free our breath:
           </l>
           <l>
            And in a pleasing sleepe our soule inlargest,
           </l>
           <l>
            Making our selues not priuy to our death,
           </l>
           <l>
            If Nature err'd, O then how happy e&#9679;&#9679;or,
           </l>
           <l>
            Thinking to make thee worst, she made the best:
           </l>
           <l>
            Sith thou best freest vs from our liues worst terror,
           </l>
           <l>
            In sweetly bringing; soules to quiet rest.
           </l>
           <l>
            When that inexorable Monster Death
           </l>
           <l>
            That follows Fortune, flies the poore distressed,
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-040-b"/>
           <l>
            Tortures our bodies ere he takes our breath,
           </l>
           <l>
            And loads with paines th'already weake oppressed.
           </l>
           <l>
            How oft haue I begg'd praid. intreated him
           </l>
           <l>
            To take my life, which he would neuer do,
           </l>
           <l>
            And when he comes, he coms so vgly grim,
           </l>
           <l>
            Attended on with hidious torments to.
           </l>
           <l>
            Therefore come thou, of wonders wonder chiefe
           </l>
           <l>
            That open canst with such a&#9679; easiekey
           </l>
           <l>
            The doore of life, come gentle cunning thiefe,
           </l>
           <l>
            That from our selues so steal'st our selues away.
           </l>
           <l>
            Well did our Priests discerne somthing diuine
           </l>
           <l>
            Shadow'd in thee, and therefore first they did
           </l>
           <l>
            Offrings and worships due to thee assigne,
           </l>
           <l>
            In whom they found such mysteries were hid.
           </l>
           <l>
            Comparing thy swift motion to the Sunne,
           </l>
           <l>
            That mou'st without the instruments that moue:
           </l>
           <l>
            And neuer waxing old, but alwayes one,
           </l>
           <l>
            Doost therein a diuinity approue.
           </l>
           <l>
            And therefore too, the rather vnto thee
           </l>
           <l>
            In zeale I make the offring of my bloud,
           </l>
           <l>
            Calamity confirming now in me
           </l>
           <l>
            A sure beliefe that piety makes good.
           </l>
           <l>
            Which happy men neglect, or hold ambiguous,
           </l>
           <l>
            And only the afflicted are religious.
           </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
           <l>
            And here I sacrifice these armes to Death,
           </l>
           <l>
            That Lust late dedicated to Delights:
           </l>
           <l>
            Offring vp for my last, this last of breath,
           </l>
           <l>
            The complement of my loues dearest rites,
           </l>
           <l>
            With that she bares her arme, and offer makes
           </l>
           <l>
            To touch her death, yet at the touch with drawes,
           </l>
           <l>
            And seeming more to speake, occasion takes,
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-041-a"/>
           <l>
            Willing to die, and willing too to pause.
           </l>
           <l>
            Looke how a mother at her sonnes departing
           </l>
           <l>
            For some farre voyage bent to get him fame,
           </l>
           <l>
            Doth entertaine him with an idle pa&#9679;ling
           </l>
           <l>
            And still doth speake, and still speakes but the same;
           </l>
           <l>
            Now bids farewell, and now recalles him backe,
           </l>
           <l>
            Tells what was told, and bids againe farewell,
           </l>
           <l>
            And yet againe recalles; for still doth lacke
           </l>
           <l>
            Something that Loue would faine and cannot tell.
           </l>
           <l>
            Pleas'd he should go, yet cannot let him go.
           </l>
           <l>
            So she, although she knew there was no way
           </l>
           <l>
            But this, yet this she could not handle so
           </l>
           <l>
            But she must shew that life desir'd delay.
           </l>
           <l>
            Faine would she entertaine the time as now.
           </l>
           <l>
            And now would faine that Death would seize vpo&#772; her,
           </l>
           <l>
            Whilst I might see presented in her brow,
           </l>
           <l>
            The doubtfull combate tride twixt Life and Honor.
           </l>
           <l>
            Life bringing Legions of fresh hopes with her,
           </l>
           <l>
            Arm'd with the proofe of time, which yeeldes we say
           </l>
           <l>
            Comfort and helpe, to such as doe referre
           </l>
           <l>
            All vnto him, and can admit delay.
           </l>
           <l>
            But Honour scorning Life, loe forth leades hee
           </l>
           <l>
            Cleere Immorralitie arm'd all in flames:
           </l>
           <l>
            Through whose bright shining rayes of glory, she
           </l>
           <l>
            Might see how base was life that her defames.
           </l>
           <l>
            Besides she saw whole armies of reproches,
           </l>
           <l>
            And base Disgraces, Furies fearfull, sad,
           </l>
           <l>
            Marching therewith, and Shame that still incroches
           </l>
           <l>
            Vpon her face, in blushing colours clad.
           </l>
           <l>
            Which representments seeing, farre worse then death
           </l>
           <l>
            Shee deem'd to yeeld to Life, and therefore chose
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-041-b"/>
           <l>
            To render all to Honour, heart and breath:
           </l>
           <l>
            And that with speede, least that her inward foes
           </l>
           <l>
            False flesh and bloud, ioyning with life and hope,
           </l>
           <l>
            Should mutinie against her resolution.
           </l>
           <l>
            And to the end she would not giue them scope,
           </l>
           <l>
            Shee presently proceeds to th'execution.
           </l>
           <l>
            And sharpely blaming of her rebell powres,
           </l>
           <l>
            False flesh (saith she) and what dost thou conspire
           </l>
           <l>
            With Caesar too, as thou wert none of ours,
           </l>
           <l>
            To worke my shame, and hinder my desire?
           </l>
           <l>
            Wilt thou retaine in closure of thy vaines,
           </l>
           <l>
            That enemy base life, to let my good?
           </l>
           <l>
            No, know there is a greater powre constraines
           </l>
           <l>
            Then can be counterchekt with fearefull blood.
           </l>
           <l>
            For to the minde that's great, nothing seemes great&#9679;
           </l>
           <l>
            And seeing death to be the last of woes,
           </l>
           <l>
            And life lasting disgrace, which I shall get,
           </l>
           <l>
            What doe I lose, that haue but life to lose?
           </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
           <l>
            This hauing said, strengthned in her owne hart.
           </l>
           <l>
            And vnion of her selfe, sences in one
           </l>
           <l>
            Charging together, she performes that part
           </l>
           <l>
            That hath so great a part of glory wonne,
           </l>
           <l>
            And so receiues the deadly poys'ning tuch;
           </l>
           <l>
            That touch that tride the gold of her loue, pure,
           </l>
           <l>
            And hath confirm'd her honour to be such,
           </l>
           <l>
            As must a wonder to all worlds endure.
           </l>
           <l>
            Now not an yeelding shrinke or touch of feare,
           </l>
           <l>
            Consented to bewray least sence of paine:
           </l>
           <l>
            But still in one same sweete vnalired cheere,
           </l>
           <l>
            Her honour did her dying thoughts retaine.
           </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
           <l>
            Well, now this worke is done (saith she) heere ends
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-042-a"/>
           <l>
            This act of Life, that part the Fares assign'd:
           </l>
           <l>
            What glory of disgraces this world lends,
           </l>
           <l>
            Both haue I had, and both I leaue behind.
           </l>
           <l>
            And now &#244; earth, the Theater where I
           </l>
           <l>
            Haue acted this, witnesse I die vnforst.
           </l>
           <l>
            Witnesse my soule partes free to Antony,
           </l>
           <l>
            And now prowde Tyrant Caesar do thy worst.
           </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
           <l>
            This said, she staies, and makes a sodaine pause,
           </l>
           <l>
            As if to feele w&#9679;&#9679;&#9679;her the poyson wrought:
           </l>
           <l>
            Or rather else the working might be cause
           </l>
           <l>
            That made her stay, and intertain'd her thought.
           </l>
           <l>
            For in that instant I might well perceiue
           </l>
           <l>
            The drowsie humour in her falling brow:
           </l>
           <l>
            And how each powre, each part opprest did leaue
           </l>
           <l>
            Their former office, and did sencelesse grow.
           </l>
           <l>
            Looke how a new pluckt branch against the Sunne,
           </l>
           <l>
            Declines his fading leaues in feeble sort;
           </l>
           <l>
            So her disioyned ioyntures as vndone,
           </l>
           <l>
            Let fall her weake dissolued limbes support.
           </l>
           <l>
            Yet loe that face the wonder of her life,
           </l>
           <l>
            Retaines in death, a grace that graceth death,
           </l>
           <l>
            Colour so liuely, cheere so louely rise,
           </l>
           <l>
            That none would think such beauty could wa&#772;t breath.
           </l>
           <l>
            And in that cheere th'impression of a smile,
           </l>
           <l>
            Did seeme to shew she scorned Death and Caesar,
           </l>
           <l>
            As glorying that she could them both beguile,
           </l>
           <l>
            And telling Death how much her death did please her
           </l>
           <l>
            Wonder it was to see how soone she went,
           </l>
           <l>
            She went with such a will, and did so haste it,
           </l>
           <l>
            That sure I thinke shee did her paine preuent,
           </l>
           <l>
            Fore-going paine, or staying not to taste it,
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-042-b"/>
           <l>
            And sencelesse, in her sincking downe she wries
           </l>
           <l>
            The Diademe which on her head she wore,
           </l>
           <l>
            Which Charmion (poore weake feeble maid) espies,
           </l>
           <l>
            And hastes to right it as it was before.
           </l>
           <l>
            For Eras now was dead, and Charmion too
           </l>
           <l>
            Euen at the point, for both would immitate
           </l>
           <l>
            Their Mistresse glory, striuing like to doo.
           </l>
           <l>
            But Charmion would in this exceed her mate,
           </l>
           <l>
            For she would haue this honour to be last,
           </l>
           <l>
            That should adorne that head that must be seene
           </l>
           <l>
            To weare that Crowne in death, which life held fast,
           </l>
           <l>
            That all the world might know she dide a Queene,
           </l>
           <l>
            And as she stood setting it fitly on,
           </l>
           <l>
            Loe, in rush Caesars messengers in haste,
           </l>
           <l>
            Thinking to haue preuented what was done.
           </l>
           <l>
            But yet they came too late, for all was past.
           </l>
           <l>
            For there they found stretcht on a bed of gold,
           </l>
           <l>
            Dead Cleopatra, and that prowdly dead,
           </l>
           <l>
            In all the rich attire procure she could,
           </l>
           <l>
            And dying Charmion trimming of her head,
           </l>
           <l>
            And Eras at her feete, dead in like case.
           </l>
           <l>
            Charmion, is this well done? said one of them.
           </l>
           <l>
            Yea, well said she, and her that from the race
           </l>
           <l>
            Of so great Kings descends, doth best become.
           </l>
           <l>
            And with that word, yeelds to, her faithfull breath,
           </l>
           <l>
            To passe th'assurance of her loue with death.
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-cho" xml:id="ep000822-e27050">
          <speaker>
           Cho.
          </speaker>
          <l>
           But how knew Caesar of her close intents
          </l>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-nun" xml:id="ep000822-e27090">
          <speaker>
           Nun.
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            By Letters which before to him she sent.
           </l>
           <l>
            For when she had procur'd this meanes to die,
           </l>
           <l>
            She writes, and earnestly intreates, she might
           </l>
           <l>
            Be buried in one Tombe with Antony,
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-043-a"/>
           <l>
            Whereby then Caesar gess'd all went not right.
           </l>
           <l>
            And forthwith sends, yet ere the message came
           </l>
           <l>
            She was dispatcht, he crost in his intent.
           </l>
           <l>
            Her prouidence had ordred so the same,
           </l>
           <l>
            That she was sure none should her plot preuent.
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
         <sp who="ep000822-chorvs" xml:id="ep000822-e27230">
          <speaker>
           CHORVS.
          </speaker>
          <lg>
           <l>
            THen thus we haue beheld
           </l>
           <l>
            Th'accomplishment of woes
           </l>
           <l>
            The full of ruine and
           </l>
           <l>
            The worst of worst of ills:
           </l>
           <l>
            And seene all hope expeld,
           </l>
           <l>
            That euer sweete repose
           </l>
           <l>
            Shall repossesse the Land,
           </l>
           <l>
            That Desolation fills,
           </l>
           <l>
            And where Ambition spills
           </l>
           <l>
            With vncontrouled hand,
           </l>
           <l>
            All th'issue of all those
           </l>
           <l>
            That so long rule haue held:
           </l>
           <l>
            To make vs no more vs,
           </l>
           <l>
            But cleane confound vs thus.
           </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
           <l>
            And canst O Nylus thou,
           </l>
           <l>
            Father of flouds indure,
           </l>
           <l>
            That yellow Tyber should
           </l>
           <l>
            With sandy streames rule thee?
           </l>
           <l>
            Wilt thou be pleas'd to bow
           </l>
           <l>
            To him those feete so pure,
           </l>
           <l>
            Whose vnknowne head we hold
           </l>
           <l>
            A powre diuine to be?
           </l>
           <l>
            Thou that didst euer see
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-043-b"/>
           <l>
            Thy free bankes vncontrould,
           </l>
           <l>
            Liue vnder thine owne care:
           </l>
           <l>
            Ah wilt thou beare it now?
           </l>
           <l>
            And now wilt yeeld thy streames
           </l>
           <l>
            A prey to other Reames?
           </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
           <l>
            Draw backe thy waters flo
           </l>
           <l>
            To thy concealed head:
           </l>
           <l>
            Rockes strangle vp thy waues,
           </l>
           <l>
            Stop Cataractes thy fall.
           </l>
           <l>
            And turne thy courses so,
           </l>
           <l>
            That sandy Desarts dead,
           </l>
           <l>
            (The world of dust that craues
           </l>
           <l>
            To swallow thee vp all,
           </l>
           <l>
            May drinke so much as shall
           </l>
           <l>
            Reuiue from vastie graues
           </l>
           <l>
            A liuing greene which spred
           </l>
           <l>
            Far florishing, may gro
           </l>
           <l>
            On that wide face of Death,
           </l>
           <l>
            Where nothing now drawes breath,
           </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
           <l>
            Fatten some people there,
           </l>
           <l>
            Euen as thou vs hast done,
           </l>
           <l>
            With plenties wanton store,
           </l>
           <l>
            And feeble luxurie:
           </l>
           <l>
            And them as vs prepare
           </l>
           <l>
            Fit for the day of mone
           </l>
           <l>
            Respected not before.
           </l>
           <l>
            Leaue leuell'd Egypt drie,
           </l>
           <l>
            A barren prey to lie,
           </l>
           <l>
            Wasted for euer-more,
           </l>
           <l>
            Of plenties yeelding none
           </l>
           <pb xml:id="ep000822-044-a"/>
           <l>
            To recompence the care
           </l>
           <l>
            Of Victors greedy lust,
           </l>
           <l>
            And bring forth nought but dust.
           </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
           <l>
            And so O leaue to be,
           </l>
           <l>
            Sith thou art what thou art:
           </l>
           <l>
            Let not our race possesse
           </l>
           <l>
            Th'inheritance of shame,
           </l>
           <l>
            The fee of sinne, that we
           </l>
           <l>
            Haue left them for their part:
           </l>
           <l>
            The yoake of whose distresse
           </l>
           <l>
            Must still vpbraid our blame,
           </l>
           <l>
            Telling from whom it came,
           </l>
           <l>
            Our weight of wantonnesse
           </l>
           <l>
            Lies heauie on their hart,
           </l>
           <l>
            Who neuer-more shall see
           </l>
           <l>
            The glory of that worth
           </l>
           <l>
            They left, who brought vs forth.
           </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
           <l>
            O thou all-seeing light,
           </l>
           <l>
            High President of heauen,
           </l>
           <l>
            You magistrates the starres
           </l>
           <l>
            Of that eternall Court
           </l>
           <l>
            Of Prouidence and Right
           </l>
           <l>
            Are these the bounds y'haue giuen
           </l>
           <l>
            Th'vntranspassable barres,
           </l>
           <l>
            That limit pride so short,
           </l>
           <l>
            Is greatnesse of this sort,
           </l>
           <l>
            That greatnesse greatnesse marres,
           </l>
           <l>
            And wracks it selfe, selfe driuen
           </l>
           <l>
            On Rocks of her owne might?
           </l>
           <l>
            Doth Order order so
           </l>
           <l>
            Disorders ouer-thro?
           </l>
          </lg>
         </sp>
        </div>
       </div>
       <trailer>
        FINIS.
       </trailer>
      </div>
     </div>
     <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000822-e28210">
      <pb xml:id="ep000822-044-b"/>
      <head>
       THE COMPLAINT of ROSAMOND.
      </head>
      <lg>
       <l>
        OVT from the horror of Infernall deepes,
       </l>
       <l>
        My poore afflicted ghost coms heere to plaine it,
       </l>
       <l>
        Attended with my shame that neuer sleepes,
       </l>
       <l>
        The spot where-with my kinde &amp; youth did staine it.
       </l>
       <l>
        My body found a graue where to containe it.
       </l>
       <l>
        A sheete could hide my face, but not my sin,
       </l>
       <l>
        For Fame findes neuer tombe t'inclose it in.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        And which is worse, my soule is now denied,
       </l>
       <l>
        Her transport to the sweet Elisian rest,
       </l>
       <l>
        The ioyfull blisse for ghosts repurified,
       </l>
       <l>
        The euer-springing Gardens of the blest:
       </l>
       <l>
        Caron denies me waftage with the rest.
       </l>
       <l>
        And saies, my soule can neuer passe the Riuer,
       </l>
       <l>
        Till Louers sighes on earth shall it deliuer.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        So shall I neuer passe; for how should I
       </l>
       <l>
        Procure this sacrifice amongst the liuing?
       </l>
       <l>
        Time hath long since worne out the memorie
       </l>
       <l>
        Both of my life, and liues vniust depriuing,
       </l>
       <l>
        Sorrow for me is dead for aye reuiuing:
       </l>
       <l>
        Rosamond hath little left her but her name,
       </l>
       <l>
        And that disgrac'd for time hath wrong'd the same.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-045-a"/>
       <l>
        No muse, suggests the pitty of my case,
       </l>
       <l>
        Each pen doth ouerpasse my iust complaint,
       </l>
       <l>
        Whilst others are preferd, though far more base:
       </l>
       <l>
        Shores wife is grac'd, and passes for a Saint;
       </l>
       <l>
        Her Legend iustifies her foule attaint,
       </l>
       <l>
        Her wel-told tale did such compassion find,
       </l>
       <l>
        That she is pass'd, and I am left behinde.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Which seene with griefe, my miserable ghost,
       </l>
       <l>
        (Whilome inuested in so faire a vaile,
       </l>
       <l>
        Which whilst it liu'd, was honored of the most,
       </l>
       <l>
        And being dead giues matter to bewaile,)
       </l>
       <l>
        Comes to solicite thee, (since others faile,)
       </l>
       <l>
        To take this taske, and in thy wofull song
       </l>
       <l>
        To forme my case, and regester my wrong.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Although I know thy iust lamenting Muse.
       </l>
       <l>
        Toyld in th'affliction of thine owne distresse,
       </l>
       <l>
        In others cares hath little time to vse,
       </l>
       <l>
        And therefore maist esteeme of mine the lesse:
       </l>
       <l>
        Yet as thy hopes attend happy redresse,
       </l>
       <l>
        Thy ioyes depending on a womans grace,
       </l>
       <l>
        So moue thy minde a wofull womans case.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        DHLIA may hap to deigne to reade our story,
       </l>
       <l>
        And offer vp her sigh among the rest.
       </l>
       <l>
        Who&#9679;e merit would suffice for both our glory,
       </l>
       <l>
        Whereby thou might'st be grac'd and I be blest;
       </l>
       <l>
        That indulgence would profit me the best.
       </l>
       <l>
        Such power she hath by whom thy youth is led,
       </l>
       <l>
        To ioy the liuing, and to blesse the dead.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-045-b"/>
       <l>
        So I (through beauty) made the wofull'st wight,
       </l>
       <l>
        By beauty might haue comfort after death:
       </l>
       <l>
        That dying fairest, by the fairest might
       </l>
       <l>
        Find life aboue on earth, and rest beneath.
       </l>
       <l>
        She that can blesse vs with one happy breath,
       </l>
       <l>
        Giue comfort to thy Muse to do her best,
       </l>
       <l>
        That thereby thou mayst ioy, and I might rest
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Thus said: forth with mou'd with a tender care,
       </l>
       <l>
        And pitty, (which my selfe could neuer find,)
       </l>
       <l>
        What she desir'd, my Muse deign'd to declare,
       </l>
       <l>
        And therefore, will'd her boldely tell her minde.
       </l>
       <l>
        And I (more willing) tooke this charge assign'd,
       </l>
       <l>
        Because her griefs were worthy to be knowne,
       </l>
       <l>
        And telling hers, might hap forget mine owne.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Then write (quoth she) the ruine of my youth,
       </l>
       <l>
        Report the downe-fall of my slip&#9679;y st&#9679;te,
       </l>
       <l>
        Of all my life reuaile the simple trueth,
       </l>
       <l>
        To teach to others what I learnt too late.
       </l>
       <l>
        Exemplifie my frailty, tell how Fate
       </l>
       <l>
        Keeps in eternall darke our fortunes hidden,
       </l>
       <l>
        And ere they come, to know them tis forbidden.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        For Whilst the Sun-shine of my fortune lasted,
       </l>
       <l>
        I ioy'd the happiest warmth, the sweetest hea&#9679;e:
       </l>
       <l>
        That euer yet imper&#9679;ous beauty tasted,
       </l>
       <l>
        I had what glory euer flesh could get:
       </l>
       <l>
        But this faire morning had a shamefull set.
       </l>
       <l>
        Disgrace darkt honor, sinne did cloud my brow,
       </l>
       <l>
        As note the sequel, and Ile tell thee how.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-046-a"/>
       <l>
        The bloud I staind, was good and of the best,
       </l>
       <l>
        My b&#9679;th had honour, and my beauty fame:
       </l>
       <l>
        Nature and Fortune ioin'd to make me blest,
       </l>
       <l>
        Had I had grace t'haue knowne to vse the same.
       </l>
       <l>
        My education shew'd from whence I came,
       </l>
       <l>
        And all concurd to make me happy furst,
       </l>
       <l>
        That so great hap might make me more accurst,
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Happy liu'd I whilst parents eye did guide
       </l>
       <l>
        The indiscretion of my feeble wayes,
       </l>
       <l>
        And country home kept me from being eide,
       </l>
       <l>
        Where best vnknowne I spent my sweetest dayes:
       </l>
       <l>
        Till that my friends mine honor sough to raise
       </l>
       <l>
        To higher place, which greater credite yeeldes.
       </l>
       <l>
        Deeming such beauty was vnfit for feeldes.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        From Country then to Court I was preferr'd,
       </l>
       <l>
        From calme to stormes, from shore into the deepes:
       </l>
       <l>
        There where I perish'd, where my youth first err'd,
       </l>
       <l>
        There where I lost the floure which honour keepes,
       </l>
       <l>
        There where the worser thriues, the better weepes;
       </l>
       <l>
        Ay me (poore wench) on that vnhappy shelfe,
       </l>
       <l>
        I grounded me, and cast away my selfe.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        There whereas fraile and tender Beauty stands,
       </l>
       <l>
        With all assaulting powres inuironed;
       </l>
       <l>
        Hauing but prayers and weake feeble hands
       </l>
       <l>
        To hold their honors Fort vnvanquished;
       </l>
       <l>
        There where to stand, and be vnconquered,
       </l>
       <l>
        Is to b'aboue the nature of our kinde,
       </l>
       <l>
        That cannot long for pitty be vnkinde.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-046-b"/>
       <l>
        For thither com'd, when yeeres had arm'd my youth,
       </l>
       <l>
        With rarest proofe of beauty euer seene:
       </l>
       <l>
        When my reuiuing eye had learnt the truth,
       </l>
       <l>
        That it had power to make the winter greene,
       </l>
       <l>
        And floure affections whereas none had beene;
       </l>
       <l>
        Soone could I teach my brow to tyrannize,
       </l>
       <l>
        And make the world do homage to mine eies.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        For age I saw, (though yeeres with cold conceit,
       </l>
       <l>
        Congeald their thoughts against a warme des&#9679;e,)
       </l>
       <l>
        Yet sigh their want, and looke at such a bait;
       </l>
       <l>
        I saw how youth was waxe before the fire;
       </l>
       <l>
        I saw by stealth, I fram'd my looke a lyre,
       </l>
       <l>
        Yet well perceiued, how Fortune made me then
       </l>
       <l>
        The enuy of my sexe, and wonder vnto men.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Looke how a Comet at the first appearing,
       </l>
       <l>
        Drawes all mens eyes with wonder to behold it:
       </l>
       <l>
        Or as the saddest tale at suddaine hearing,
       </l>
       <l>
        Makes silent listning vnto him that told it,
       </l>
       <l>
        So did my speech when Rubies did vnfold it:
       </l>
       <l>
        So did the blasing of my blush appeare,
       </l>
       <l>
        T'amaze the world, that holds such sights so deere.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Ah beauty Syren, faire enchaunting good,
       </l>
       <l>
        Sweete silent rhetorique of perswading eyes:
       </l>
       <l>
        Dombe eloquence, whose power doth moue the bloud
       </l>
       <l>
        More then the words, or wisdome of the wise:
       </l>
       <l>
        Still harmony, whose diapason lies
       </l>
       <l>
        Within a brow, the &#9679;oy which passions moue.
       </l>
       <l>
        To rauish sence, and play a world in loue.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-047-a"/>
       <l>
        What might I then not do whose powre was such?
       </l>
       <l>
        What cannot women do that knowe their powre?
       </l>
       <l>
        What women knowes it not (I feare too much)
       </l>
       <l>
        How blisse or bale lyes in their laugh or lowre?
       </l>
       <l>
        Whilst they enioy their happy blooming flowre,
       </l>
       <l>
        Whilst nature deckes them in their best attires
       </l>
       <l>
        Of youth and beauty which the world admires.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Such one was I, my beauty was mine owne,
       </l>
       <l>
        No borrowed blush which bank-rot beau&#9679;les seeke:
       </l>
       <l>
        That new-found shame, a finne to vs vnknowne,
       </l>
       <l>
        Th'adulterate beauty of a falsed cheeke:
       </l>
       <l>
        Vilde staine to honour, and to women eeke,
       </l>
       <l>
        Seeing that time our f&#9679;ding must detect.
       </l>
       <l>
        Thus with defect to couer our defect.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Implety of times, Chastities aba&#9679;or,
       </l>
       <l>
        Falshood, wherein thy selfe thy selfe deniest:
       </l>
       <l>
        Treason to counterfet the seale of Nature,
       </l>
       <l>
        The stampe of heauen, impressed by the hiest.
       </l>
       <l>
        Disgrace vnto the world, to whom thou liest.
       </l>
       <l>
        Idoll vnto thy selfe, shame to the wise,
       </l>
       <l>
        And all that honour thee idolatrise.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Farre was that sinne from vs whose age was pure,
       </l>
       <l>
        When simple beauty was accounted best,
       </l>
       <l>
        The time when women had no other lure
       </l>
       <l>
        But modestie, pure cheekes, a vertuous brest.
       </l>
       <l>
        This was the pompe wherewith my youth was blest.
       </l>
       <l>
        These were the weapons which mine honour won.
       </l>
       <l>
        In all the conflicts which mine eyes begunne.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-047-b"/>
       <l>
        Which were not smale, I wrought on no mean&#9679; oblect,
       </l>
       <l>
        A Crowne was at my feete, Scepters obeyd me,
       </l>
       <l>
        Whom Fortu&#772;e made my King, Loue made my subiect,
       </l>
       <l>
        Who did co&#772;maund the Land, most humbly praid me,
       </l>
       <l>
        Henry the second, that so highly weigh'd me.
       </l>
       <l>
        Found wel (by proofe) the priuiledge of beuty,
       </l>
       <l>
        That it had powre to counter-maund all duty.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        For after all his victories in France,
       </l>
       <l>
        And all the triumphs of his honor wonne:
       </l>
       <l>
        Vnmatcht; by sword, was vanquisht by a glance.
       </l>
       <l>
        And hotter warres within his breast begunne.
       </l>
       <l>
        Warres, whom whole legions of desires drew on:
       </l>
       <l>
        Against all which, my chastity contends
       </l>
       <l>
        With force of honour, which my shame defends.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        No armour might be found that could defend,
       </l>
       <l>
        Transpearcing raies of cristall poynted eyes:
       </l>
       <l>
        No stratagem, no reason could amend,
       </l>
       <l>
        No not his age; (yet olde men should be wise.)
       </l>
       <l>
        But shews deceiue, outward appearance lies.
       </l>
       <l>
        Let none for seeming so, thinke Saints of others,
       </l>
       <l>
        For all are men, and all haue suckt their mothers.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Who would haue thought a Mo&#772;arch would haue eues
       </l>
       <l>
        Obeyd his hand-maide of so meane estate:
       </l>
       <l>
        Vultu&#9679;e &#9679;mbition feeding on his liuer,
       </l>
       <l>
        Age haui&#9679;g worne his pleasures out of date,
       </l>
       <l>
        But hap comes neuer, or it comes too late.
       </l>
       <l>
        For such a dainty which his youth found not,
       </l>
       <l>
        Vnto his feeble age did chaunce a lot.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-048-a"/>
       <l>
        Ah Fortune, neuer absolutely good,
       </l>
       <l>
        For that some crosse still counter-checks our luck:
       </l>
       <l>
        As heere behold th'incomparible blood,
       </l>
       <l>
        Of age and youth was that whereon we stuck:
       </l>
       <l>
        Whose lothing, we from natures brests do suck,
       </l>
       <l>
        As opposite to what our bloud requires,
       </l>
       <l>
        For equall age, doth equall like desires.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        But mighty men, in highest honour sitting,
       </l>
       <l>
        Nought but applause and pleasure can behold:
       </l>
       <l>
        Sooth'd in their liking, carelesse what is fitting,
       </l>
       <l>
        May not be suffred once to thinke the'are old:
       </l>
       <l>
        Not trusting what they see, but what is told.
       </l>
       <l>
        Miserable fortune to forget so farre
       </l>
       <l>
        The state of flesh, and what our frailties are.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Yet must I needs excuse so great defect
       </l>
       <l>
        For drinking of the Lethe of mine eies,
       </l>
       <l>
        H'is forc'd forget himselfe, and all respect
       </l>
       <l>
        Of maiesty, whereon his state relies:
       </l>
       <l>
        And now of loues, and pleasures must deuise.
       </l>
       <l>
        For thus reuiu'd againe he serues and su'th,
       </l>
       <l>
        And seekes all meanes to vndermine my youth.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Which neuer by assault he could recouer,
       </l>
       <l>
        So well incamp'd in strength of chast desires:
       </l>
       <l>
        My cleane-arm'd thoughts repelld an vnchaste louer.
       </l>
       <l>
        The Crowne that could commaund what it requires,
       </l>
       <l>
        I lesser prizd then Chastities attires.
       </l>
       <l>
        Th'vnstayned vaile, which innocents adornes,
       </l>
       <l>
        Th'vngathred Rose, defended with the thrones.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-048-b"/>
       <l>
        And safe mine honour stoode, till that in truth,
       </l>
       <l>
        One of my sexe, of place, and nature bad,
       </l>
       <l>
        Was set in ambush to intrap my youth.
       </l>
       <l>
        One in the habite of our frailty clad,
       </l>
       <l>
        One who the liu'ry of like weaknesse had.
       </l>
       <l>
        A seeming Matron, yet a sinfull monster,
       </l>
       <l>
        As by her wordes the chaster sort may conster.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        She set vpon me with the smoothest speech
       </l>
       <l>
        That Court and Age could cunningly deuise,
       </l>
       <l>
        Th'one authentique, made her fit to teach,
       </l>
       <l>
        The other learnd her how to subtelise.
       </l>
       <l>
        Both were enough to circumuent the wise.
       </l>
       <l>
        A document that well might teach the sage,
       </l>
       <l>
        That there's no trust in youth, nor hope in age.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Daughter (said she) behold thy happy chance,
       </l>
       <l>
        That hast the lot cast downe into thy lap.
       </l>
       <l>
        Whereby thou maist thy honor great aduance,
       </l>
       <l>
        Whilst thou (vnhappy) wilt not see thy hap:
       </l>
       <l>
        Such fond respect thy youth doth so inwrap,
       </l>
       <l>
        T'oppose thy selfe against thine owne good fortune,
       </l>
       <l>
        That poynts thee out, and seemes thee to importune.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Doost thou not see&#9679; how that thy King (thy Ioue)
       </l>
       <l>
        Lightens forth glory on thy darke estate:
       </l>
       <l>
        And showres downe golde and treasure from aboue.
       </l>
       <l>
        Whilst thou doost shut thy lap against thy fate?
       </l>
       <l>
        Fie sondling fie, thou wilt repent too late
       </l>
       <l>
        The error of thy youth; that canst not see
       </l>
       <l>
        What is the fortune that doth follow thee.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-049-a"/>
       <l>
        Thou must not thinke thy flowre can alwaies florish,
       </l>
       <l>
        And that thy beautie will be still admired:
       </l>
       <l>
        But that those raies which all these flames do nourish,
       </l>
       <l>
        Cancel'd with Time, will haue their date expired,
       </l>
       <l>
        And men will scorne what now is so desired.
       </l>
       <l>
        Our frailties doome is written in the flowers,
       </l>
       <l>
        Which flourish now, and fade ere many howers.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Reade in my face the ruines of my youth,
       </l>
       <l>
        The wracke of yeeres vpon my aged brow;
       </l>
       <l>
        I haue beene faire (I must confesse the truth)
       </l>
       <l>
        And stood vpon as nice respects as thou;
       </l>
       <l>
        I lost my time, and I repent it now.
       </l>
       <l>
        But were I to begin my youth againe,
       </l>
       <l>
        I would redeeme the time I spent in vaine.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        But thou hast yeeres, and priuiledge to vse them,
       </l>
       <l>
        Thy priuiledge doth beare Beauties great seale:
       </l>
       <l>
        Besides, the lawe of Nature doth excuse them,
       </l>
       <l>
        To whom thy youth may haue a iust appeale.
       </l>
       <l>
        Esteeme not Fame more then thou doost thy weale.
       </l>
       <l>
        Fame (wherof the world seems to make such choice)
       </l>
       <l>
        Is but an Eccho, and an idle voice,
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Then why should this respect of honour bound vs,
       </l>
       <l>
        In th'imaginarie listes of reputation?
       </l>
       <l>
        Titles which cold seueritie hath found vs,
       </l>
       <l>
        Breath of the vulgar, foe to recreation:
       </l>
       <l>
        Ages opinion, Customes out-worne fashion,
       </l>
       <l>
        Pleasures plague, beauties scourge, hell to the faire,
       </l>
       <l>
        To leaue the sweete, for Castles in the aire.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-049-b"/>
       <l>
        Pleasure i&#9679; felt, opinion but conceau'd,
       </l>
       <l>
        Honor, a thing without vs, not our owne:
       </l>
       <l>
        Whereof we see how many are bereau'd,
       </l>
       <l>
        Which should haue reap'd the glory they had sowne
       </l>
       <l>
        And many haue it, yet vnworthy, knowne.
       </l>
       <l>
        So breaches his blast this many-headed beast,
       </l>
       <l>
        Whereof the wisest haue esteemed least.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        The subtile Citty-women, better learned,
       </l>
       <l>
        Esteeme them chast enough that best seeme so:
       </l>
       <l>
        Who though they sport, it shall not be discerned,
       </l>
       <l>
        Their face bewrayes not what their bodyes do;
       </l>
       <l>
        Tis warie walking that doth safeliest go.
       </l>
       <l>
        With shew of vertue, as the cunning knowes.
       </l>
       <l>
        Babes are beguild with sweets, &amp; m&#235; with sho,
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Then vse thy tallent youth shall be thy warrant,
       </l>
       <l>
        And let not honour from thy sports detract:
       </l>
       <l>
        Thou must not fondly thinke thy selfe transparent,
       </l>
       <l>
        That those who see thy face can iudge thy fact,
       </l>
       <l>
        Let her haue shame that cannot closely act.
       </l>
       <l>
        And seeme the chast, which is the chiefest arte,
       </l>
       <l>
        For what we seeme each see, none knows out hart.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        The mighty, who can with such sinnes dispence,
       </l>
       <l>
        In steed of shame do honors great bestow:
       </l>
       <l>
        A worthy Author doth redeeme th'offence,
       </l>
       <l>
        And makes the scarlet sinne as white as snow,
       </l>
       <l>
        The Maiestie that doth descend so low,
       </l>
       <l>
        Is not defilde but pure remaines therein,
       </l>
       <l>
        And being sacred, sanctifies the sinne,
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-050-a"/>
       <l>
        What, doost thou stand on this, that he is old?
       </l>
       <l>
        Thy beautie hath the more to worke vpon.
       </l>
       <l>
        Thy pleasures want shall be supplide with gold,
       </l>
       <l>
        Cold age dotes most when heate of youth is gone:
       </l>
       <l>
        Enticing words preuaile with such a one.
       </l>
       <l>
        Alluring shewes most deepe impression strikes
       </l>
       <l>
        For age is prone to credite what it likes.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Heere interrupt, she leaues me in a doubt,
       </l>
       <l>
        When loe began the combate in my blood,
       </l>
       <l>
        See'ing my weake youth inuiron'd round about,
       </l>
       <l>
        The ground vncertaine where my reasons stood;
       </l>
       <l>
        Small my defence to make my party good,
       </l>
       <l>
        Against such powers which were so surely laid,
       </l>
       <l>
        To ouerthrow a poore vnskilfull Maid.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Treason was in my bones, my selfe conspiring,
       </l>
       <l>
        To fell my selfe to lust, my soule to sin:
       </l>
       <l>
        Pure-blushing shame was euen vpon retiring,
       </l>
       <l>
        Leauing the sacred hold it glori'd in.
       </l>
       <l>
        Honor lay prost&#9679;ate for my flesh to win,
       </l>
       <l>
        When cleaner thoughts my weaknesse gan vpbray
       </l>
       <l>
        Against my selfe, and shame did force me say;
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Ah Rosamond, what doth thy flesh prepare?
       </l>
       <l>
        Destruction to thy dayes, death to thy fame,
       </l>
       <l>
        Wilt thou betray that honour held with care,
       </l>
       <l>
        T'entombe with black reproch a spotted name?
       </l>
       <l>
        Leauing thy blush the colours of thy shame?
       </l>
       <l>
        Opening thy feete to sinne, thy soule to lust,
       </l>
       <l>
        Gracelesse to lay thy glory in the dust?
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-050-b"/>
       <l>
        Nay, first let th'earth gape wide to swallow thee,
       </l>
       <l>
        And shut thee vp in bosome with her dead,
       </l>
       <l>
        Ere Serpent tempt thee taste forbidden Tree,
       </l>
       <l>
        Or feele the warmth of an vnlawfull bed;
       </l>
       <l>
        Suffring thy selfe by lust to be misled;
       </l>
       <l>
        So to disgrace thy selfe and g&#9679;ieue thine heires,
       </l>
       <l>
        That Cli&#9679;&#9679;ords race should scorne thee one of theirs.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Neuer wish longer to enioy the aire,
       </l>
       <l>
        Then that thou breath'st the breath of chastitie:
       </l>
       <l>
        Longer then thou preseru'st thy soule as faire
       </l>
       <l>
        As is thy face, free from impu&#9679;itie.
       </l>
       <l>
        Thy face, that makes th'admir'd in euery eye,
       </l>
       <l>
        Where Natures care such rarities inroule,
       </l>
       <l>
        Which vs'd amisse, may serue to damne thy soule.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        But what? he is my King and may constraine me,
       </l>
       <l>
        Whether I yeelde or not, I liue diffamed.
       </l>
       <l>
        The world will thinke authori&#9679;ie did gaine me,
       </l>
       <l>
        I shall be iudg'd his Loue, and so be shamed.
       </l>
       <l>
        We see the faire condem'nd, that neuer gamed.
       </l>
       <l>
        And if I yeeld, tis honourable shame,
       </l>
       <l>
        If no&#9679;, I liue disgrac'd, yet thought the same.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        What way is left thee then (vnhappy maide,)
       </l>
       <l>
        Whereby thy spotlesse foote, may wander out
       </l>
       <l>
        This dreadfull danger, which thou seest is laid,
       </l>
       <l>
        Wherein thy shame doth compasse thee about?
       </l>
       <l>
        Thy simple yeares cannot resolue this doubt.
       </l>
       <l>
        Thy youth can neuer guide thy foote so euen,
       </l>
       <l>
        But (in despite) some scandale will be giuen.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-051-a"/>
       <l>
        Thus stood I ballanc'd equally precize,
       </l>
       <l>
        Till my fraile flesh did weigh me downe to sin;
       </l>
       <l>
        Till world and pleasure made me partialize,
       </l>
       <l>
        And glittering pompe my vanitie did win,
       </l>
       <l>
        When to excuse my fault my lusts begin.
       </l>
       <l>
        And impious thoughts alledg'd this wanton clause,
       </l>
       <l>
        That though I sinn'd, my sinne had honest cause.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        So well the golden balles cast downe before me,
       </l>
       <l>
        Could entertaine my course, hinder my way:
       </l>
       <l>
        Whereat my retchlesse youth stooping to store me,
       </l>
       <l>
        Lost me the gole, the glory, and the day.
       </l>
       <l>
        Pleasure had set my well school'd thoughts to play,
       </l>
       <l>
        And bade me vse the vertue of mine eies,
       </l>
       <l>
        For sweetly it fits the faire to wantonise.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Thus wrought to sin, soone was I traind from Court,
       </l>
       <l>
        T'a solitarie G&#9679;ange, there to attend
       </l>
       <l>
        The time the King should thither make resort,
       </l>
       <l>
        Where he Loues long desired worke should end.
       </l>
       <l>
        Thither he daily messages doth send,
       </l>
       <l>
        With costly Iewels (Orators of Loue,)
       </l>
       <l>
        Which (ah too well men know) do women moue.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        The day before the night of my defeature,
       </l>
       <l>
        He greets me with a Casket richly wrought;
       </l>
       <l>
        So rare, that Arte did seeme to striue with Nature,
       </l>
       <l>
        T'expresse the cunning worke-mens curious thought&#9679;
       </l>
       <l>
        The mysterie whereof I prying sought,
       </l>
       <l>
        And found engrauen on the lidde aboue,
       </l>
       <l>
        Amymone, how she with Neptune stroue.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-051-b"/>
       <l>
        Amymone, old Danaus fairest Daughter,
       </l>
       <l>
        As she was fetching water all alone
       </l>
       <l>
        At Lerna: whereas Neptune came and caught her,
       </l>
       <l>
        From whom she striu'd and strugled to be gone,
       </l>
       <l>
        Beating the ay&#9679;e with cries and piteous mone:
       </l>
       <l>
        But all in vaine, with him she's forc'd to go,
       </l>
       <l>
        Tis shame that men should vse poore maidens so.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        There might I see described how she lay,
       </l>
       <l>
        At those proud feet, not satisfide with prayer:
       </l>
       <l>
        Wayling her heauy hap, cursing the day,
       </l>
       <l>
        In act so pitious to expresse despaire.
       </l>
       <l>
        And by how much more grieu'd, so much more faire.
       </l>
       <l>
        Her teares vpon her cheekes (poore carefull gerle,)
       </l>
       <l>
        Did seeme against the Sunne christall and pearle.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Whose pure cleere streams, (which lo so faire appears)
       </l>
       <l>
        Wrought hotter flames, (O miracle of loue.)
       </l>
       <l>
        That kindles fire in water, heate in teares,
       </l>
       <l>
        And makes neglected beauty mightier proue,
       </l>
       <l>
        Teaching afflicted eyes affects to moue;
       </l>
       <l>
        To shew that nothing ill becomes the faire,
       </l>
       <l>
        But crueltie, which yeelds vnto no prayer.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        This hauing viewd, and therewith something moued,
       </l>
       <l>
        Figured I find within the other squares,
       </l>
       <l>
        Transformed
        <hi>
         Io, Ioues
        </hi>
        deerely loued,
       </l>
       <l>
        In her affliction how she strangely fares.
       </l>
       <l>
        Strangely distress'd (O beautie, borne to cares,)
       </l>
       <l>
        Turn'd to a Heiffer, kept with iealous eyes,
       </l>
       <l>
        Alwayes in danger of her hatefull spies.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-052-a"/>
       <l>
        These presidents presented to my view,
       </l>
       <l>
        Wherein the presage of my fall was showne,
       </l>
       <l>
        Might haue fore-warn'd me well what would ensue,
       </l>
       <l>
        And others harmes haue made me shun mine owne.
       </l>
       <l>
        But fate is not preuented, though foreknowne.
       </l>
       <l>
        For that must hap, decreed by heauenly powres,
       </l>
       <l>
        Who worke our fall, yet make the fault still ours.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Witnesse the world, wherein is nothing riser,
       </l>
       <l>
        Then miseries vnkend before they come:
       </l>
       <l>
        Who can the characters of chaunce decipher,
       </l>
       <l>
        Written in cloudes of our concealed dome?
       </l>
       <l>
        Which though perhaps haue beene reueald to some,
       </l>
       <l>
        Yet that so doubtfull, (as successe did proue them,)
       </l>
       <l>
        That me&#772; must know they haue the heu'ns aboue &#9679;&#9679;
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        I saw the sinne wherein my foot was entring,
       </l>
       <l>
        I saw how that dishonour did attend it,
       </l>
       <l>
        I saw the shame whereon my flesh was ventring,
       </l>
       <l>
        Yet had I not the vertue to defend it.
       </l>
       <l>
        So weake is sence when error hath condemn'd it.
       </l>
       <l>
        We see what's good, and thereto we consent,
       </l>
       <l>
        But yet we choose the worst, and soone repent.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        And now I come to tell the worst of illnesse,
       </l>
       <l>
        Now drawes the date of mine affliction neere.
       </l>
       <l>
        Now when the darke had wrapt vp all in stilnesse,
       </l>
       <l>
        And dreadfull black had dispossess'd the cleere,
       </l>
       <l>
        Com'd was the night, (mother of sleepe and feare;)
       </l>
       <l>
        Who with her sable-mantle friendly couers,
       </l>
       <l>
        The sweet-stolne sports, of ioyfull meeting Louers.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-052-b"/>
       <l>
        When loe, I ioy'd my Louer, not my Loue,
       </l>
       <l>
        And felt the hand of lust most vndesired:
       </l>
       <l>
        Enforc'd th'vnprooued bitter sweet to proue,
       </l>
       <l>
        Which yeelds no mutuall pleasure when tis hired.
       </l>
       <l>
        Loue's not constrain'd, nor yet of due required.
       </l>
       <l>
        Iudge they who are vnfortunately wed,
       </l>
       <l>
        VVhat tis to come vnto a loathed bed.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        But soone his age receiu'd his short contenting,
       </l>
       <l>
        And sleepe seald vp his languishing desires:
       </l>
       <l>
        VVhen he turnes to his rest, I to repenting,
       </l>
       <l>
        Into my selfe my waking thought retires:
       </l>
       <l>
        My nakednes had prou'd my sences liers.
       </l>
       <l>
        Now op'ned were mine eyes to looke therein,
       </l>
       <l>
        For first we taste the fruit, then see our sin.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Now did I find my selfe vnparadis'd,
       </l>
       <l>
        From those pure fields of my so cleane beginning:
       </l>
       <l>
        Now I perceiu'd how ill I was aduis'd,
       </l>
       <l>
        My flesh gan loathe the new-felt touch of sinning,
       </l>
       <l>
        Shame leaues vs by degrees, not at first winning.
       </l>
       <l>
        For nature checks a new offence with loathing,
       </l>
       <l>
        But vse of sinne doth make it seeme as nothing.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        And vse of sinne did worke in me a boldnesse,
       </l>
       <l>
        And loue in him, incorporates such ze&#9679;le,
       </l>
       <l>
        That iealousie increas'd with ages coldnes,
       </l>
       <l>
        Fearing to loose the ioy of all his weale.
       </l>
       <l>
        Or doubting time his stealth might else reueale&#9679;
       </l>
       <l>
        H'is driuen to deuise some subtill way,
       </l>
       <l>
        How he might safeliest keepe so rich a pray.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-053-a"/>
       <l>
        A stately Pallace he forthwith did build,
       </l>
       <l>
        Whose, intricate innumerable wayes,
       </l>
       <l>
        With such confused errors so beguild
       </l>
       <l>
        Th'vnguided entrers with vncertaine strayes&#9679;
       </l>
       <l>
        And doubtfull turnings kept them in delayes,
       </l>
       <l>
        With bootlesse labour leading them about,
       </l>
       <l>
        Able to finde no way, nor in, nor out.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Within the closed bosome of which frame,
       </l>
       <l>
        That seru'd a Centre to that goodly Round:
       </l>
       <l>
        Were lodgings, with a Garden to the same,
       </l>
       <l>
        With sweetest flowers that eu'r adorn'd the ground.
       </l>
       <l>
        And all the pleasures that delight hath found,
       </l>
       <l>
        T'intertaine the sence of wanton eies,
       </l>
       <l>
        Fuel of loue, from whence lusts flame arise.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Heere I inclos'd from all the world asunder,
       </l>
       <l>
        The Mino aure of shame kept for disgrace,
       </l>
       <l>
        The Monster of misfortune th'ages wonder,
       </l>
       <l>
        Liu'd cloistred in so desolate a case:
       </l>
       <l>
        None but the King might come into the place,
       </l>
       <l>
        Wi&#9679;h certaine Maides that did attend my neede,
       </l>
       <l>
        And he himselfe came guided by a threed.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        O &#9679;ealousie, daughter of Hate and Loue,
       </l>
       <l>
        Most way ward issue of a gentle fire;
       </l>
       <l>
        Fostred with feares thy fathers ioyes t'improue,
       </l>
       <l>
        Mirth-marring Monster borne a subtile lier;
       </l>
       <l>
        Hatefull vnto thy selfe, flying thine owne desire:
       </l>
       <l>
        Feeding vpon suspect that doth renue thee,
       </l>
       <l>
        Happy were Louers if they neuer knew thee.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-053-b"/>
       <l>
        Thou hast a thousand gates thou enterest by,
       </l>
       <l>
        Condemning trembling passions to our hart:
       </l>
       <l>
        Hundred ey'd Argus, euer-waking Spie.
       </l>
       <l>
        Pale Hagge, infernall Fury, pleasures smart,
       </l>
       <l>
        Enuious Obseruer, prying in euery part:
       </l>
       <l>
        Suspicious, fearefull, gazing still about thee,
       </l>
       <l>
        O would to God that loue could be without thee.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Thou didst depriue (through false suggesting feare,)
       </l>
       <l>
        Him of content, and me of liberty:
       </l>
       <l>
        The onely good that women holde so deere,
       </l>
       <l>
        And turnst my freedome to captiuity,
       </l>
       <l>
        First made a prisoner ere an enemy.
       </l>
       <l>
        Enioynd the ransome of my bodyes shame,
       </l>
       <l>
        Which though I paide, could not redeeme the same,
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        What greater torment euer could haue beene,
       </l>
       <l>
        Then to inforce the faire to liue retir'd?
       </l>
       <l>
        For what is beautie if it be not seene?
       </l>
       <l>
        Or what is't to beseene, vnlesse admir'd?
       </l>
       <l>
        And though admir'd vnlesse in loue desir'd?
       </l>
       <l>
        Neuer were cheekes of Roses, lockes of Amber,
       </l>
       <l>
        Ordain'd to liue imprison'd in a Chamber.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Nature created Beauty for the view,
       </l>
       <l>
        (Like as the fire for heate, the Sunne for light:)
       </l>
       <l>
        The faire do hold this priuiledge as due
       </l>
       <l>
        By ancient Charter, to liue most in sight,
       </l>
       <l>
        And she that is debarr'd it, hath not right.
       </l>
       <l>
        In vaine our friends from this, do vs dehort,
       </l>
       <l>
        For Beauty will be where is most resort.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-054-a"/>
       <l>
        Witnes the fairest streetes that Thames doth visite,
       </l>
       <l>
        The wondrous concourse of the glitt'ring Faire:
       </l>
       <l>
        For what rare woman deckt with, beauty is it,
       </l>
       <l>
        That thither couets not to make repaire?
       </l>
       <l>
        The solitary Country may not stay her.
       </l>
       <l>
        Here is the centre of all Beautyes best,
       </l>
       <l>
        Excepting DELIA, left t'adorne the West.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Here doth the curious with iudiciall eies,
       </l>
       <l>
        Contemplate Beauty gloriously atri&#9679;ed.
       </l>
       <l>
        And heerein all our chiefest glory lies,
       </l>
       <l>
        To liue where we are prais'd and most desired.
       </l>
       <l>
        O how we ioy to see our selues admired,
       </l>
       <l>
        Whilst niggardly our fauours we discouer.
       </l>
       <l>
        We loue to be belou'd, yet scorne the Louer.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Yet would to God my foot had neuer mou'd
       </l>
       <l>
        From country safetie, from the fieldes of rest:
       </l>
       <l>
        To know the danger to be highly lou'd,
       </l>
       <l>
        And liue in pompe to braue among the best,
       </l>
       <l>
        Happy for me, better had I beene blest,
       </l>
       <l>
        If I vnluckily had neuer straide,
       </l>
       <l>
        But liu'd at home a happy country maide,
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Whose vnaffected innocencie thinks
       </l>
       <l>
        No guilefull fraude, as doth the Courtly liuer:
       </l>
       <l>
        She's deck&#9679; with truth, the Riuer where she drinks
       </l>
       <l>
        Doth serue her for her glasse, her councell giuer:
       </l>
       <l>
        She loues sincerely, and is loued euer.
       </l>
       <l>
        Her daies are peace, and so she ends her breath.
       </l>
       <l>
        (True life that knowes not what's to die till death.)
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-054-b"/>
       <l>
        So should I neuer haue beene registred,
       </l>
       <l>
        In the blacke booke of the vnfortunate:
       </l>
       <l>
        Nor had my name enrold with Maids misled,
       </l>
       <l>
        Which bought their pleasures at so hie a rate.
       </l>
       <l>
        Nor had I taught (through my vnhappy fate,)
       </l>
       <l>
        This lesson (which my selfe learnt with expence)
       </l>
       <l>
        How most it hurts that most delights the sence:
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Shame follows sinne, disgrace is duly giuen;
       </l>
       <l>
        Impiety will out, neuer so closely done;
       </l>
       <l>
        No walls can hide vs from the eye of heauen,
       </l>
       <l>
        For shame must end what wickednes begun;
       </l>
       <l>
        Forth breakes reproch when we least think thereon,
       </l>
       <l>
        And this is euer proper vnto Courts,
       </l>
       <l>
        That nothing can be done, but fame reports.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Fame doth explore what lies most secret hidden,
       </l>
       <l>
        Entring the closet of the Pallace dweller:
       </l>
       <l>
        Abroad reuealing what is most forbidden:
       </l>
       <l>
        Of t&#9679;uth and falshod both an equall teller.
       </l>
       <l>
        Tis not a guard can serue for to expell her.
       </l>
       <l>
        The sword of iustice cannot cut her wings,
       </l>
       <l>
        Nor stop her mouth from vtt'ring secret thinges.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        And this our stealth she could not long conceale,
       </l>
       <l>
        From her whom such a forfeit most concerned:
       </l>
       <l>
        The wronged Queene, who could so closely deale,
       </l>
       <l>
        That she the whole of all our practise learned,
       </l>
       <l>
        And watcht a time when least it was descerned,
       </l>
       <l>
        In absence of the King, to wreake her wrong,
       </l>
       <l>
        With such reuenge as she desired long.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-055-a"/>
       <l>
        The Laberinth she entred by that threed.
       </l>
       <l>
        That seru'd a conduct to my absent Lord,
       </l>
       <l>
        Lest there by chance, reseru'd for such a deed,
       </l>
       <l>
        Where she surp&#9679;iz'd me whom she so abhord.
       </l>
       <l>
        Enrag'd with madnes, scarce she speakes a word,
       </l>
       <l>
        But flies with eager fury to my face,
       </l>
       <l>
        Offring me most vnwomanly disgrace.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Looke how a Tygresse that hath lost her whelpe,
       </l>
       <l>
        Runnes fiercely raging through the woods astray:
       </l>
       <l>
        And seeing her selfe depriu'd of hope or helpe,
       </l>
       <l>
        Doth furiously assault what's in her way,
       </l>
       <l>
        To satisfie her wrath, (not for a pray;)
       </l>
       <l>
        So fell she on me in outragious wise,
       </l>
       <l>
        As could Disdaine and Iealousie deuise.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        And after all her vile reproches vsde,
       </l>
       <l>
        She forc'd me &#9679;ake the poison shee had brought,
       </l>
       <l>
        To end the life that had her so abusde,
       </l>
       <l>
        And free her feares, and ease her iealous thought.
       </l>
       <l>
        No cruelty her wrath would leaue vnwrought,
       </l>
       <l>
        No spitefull act that to Reuenge is common;
       </l>
       <l>
        No beast being fiercer then a iealous woman.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Here take (saith she) thou impudent vncleane,
       </l>
       <l>
        Base gracelesse strumpet, take this next your heart;
       </l>
       <l>
        Your loue-sicke heart, that ouer charg'd hath beene
       </l>
       <l>
        With Pleasures surfeit, must be purg'd with Arte.
       </l>
       <l>
        This potion hath a power that will conuart
       </l>
       <l>
        To naught, those humors that oppresse you so.
       </l>
       <l>
        And (Gerle) Ile see you take it ere I go.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-055-b"/>
       <l>
        What stand you now amaz'd retire you backe?
       </l>
       <l>
        Tremble you (minion?) come dispatch with speed:
       </l>
       <l>
        There is no helpe, your Champion now you lack.
       </l>
       <l>
        And all these teares you shed will nothing steed:
       </l>
       <l>
        Those daynty fingers needs must do the deed.
       </l>
       <l>
        Take it or I will drench you els by force,
       </l>
       <l>
        And trifle not, left that I vse you worse.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Hauing this bloody doome from hellish breath,
       </l>
       <l>
        My wofull eyes on euery side I cast:
       </l>
       <l>
        Rigor about me, in my hand my death,
       </l>
       <l>
        Presenting me the horror of my last:
       </l>
       <l>
        All hope of pitty and of comfort past.
       </l>
       <l>
        No meanes, no power, no forces to contend,
       </l>
       <l>
        My trembling handes must giue my selfe my end.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Those hands that beauties ministers had been,
       </l>
       <l>
        They must giue death that me adorn'd of late,
       </l>
       <l>
        That mouth that newly gaue consent to sin,
       </l>
       <l>
        Must now receiue destruction in thereat,
       </l>
       <l>
        That body which my lust did violate,
       </l>
       <l>
        Must sacrifice it selfe t'appease the wrong.
       </l>
       <l>
        (So short is pleasure glory lasts not long.)
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        And she no sooner saw I had it taken,
       </l>
       <l>
        But foorth she rushes, (proud with victory,)
       </l>
       <l>
        And leaues m'alone, of all the world forsaken,
       </l>
       <l>
        Except of Death, which she had left with me.
       </l>
       <l>
        (Death and my selfe alone togither be.)
       </l>
       <l>
        To whom she did her full reuenge refer.
       </l>
       <l>
        Oh poore weake conquest both for him and her.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-056-a"/>
       <l>
        Then straight my conscience summons vp my sinne,
       </l>
       <l>
        T'appeare before me, in a hidious &#9679;ace;
       </l>
       <l>
        Now doth the terrour of my soule beginne,
       </l>
       <l>
        When eu'ry corner of that hatefull place
       </l>
       <l>
        Dictates mine error, and reueals disgrace;
       </l>
       <l>
        Whilst I remaine opprest in euery part,
       </l>
       <l>
        Deoth in my body, horror at my hart.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Downe on my bed my loathsome selfe I cast,
       </l>
       <l>
        The bed that likewise giues in euidence
       </l>
       <l>
        Against my soule, and tels I was vnchast,
       </l>
       <l>
        Tels I was wanton, tels I followed sence,
       </l>
       <l>
        And therefore cast, by guilt of mine offence.
       </l>
       <l>
        Must heere the right of heauen needes satisfie,
       </l>
       <l>
        And where I wanton lay, must wretched die.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Heere I began to waile my hard mishap,
       </l>
       <l>
        My suddaine, strange vnlookt for misery.
       </l>
       <l>
        Accusing them that did my youth intrap,
       </l>
       <l>
        To giue me such a fall of infamy.
       </l>
       <l>
        And poore distressed Rosamond. (said I,)
       </l>
       <l>
        Is this thy glory got, to die forlorne
       </l>
       <l>
        In Dezarts, where no eare can heare thee mourn&#9679;
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Nor any eye of pitty to behold
       </l>
       <l>
        The wofull end of thy sad tragedy;
       </l>
       <l>
        But that thy wrongs vnseene, thy tale vntold,
       </l>
       <l>
        Must heere in secret silence buried lie.
       </l>
       <l>
        And with thee, thine excuse togither die.
       </l>
       <l>
        Thy sin eeueal'd, but thy repentance hid,
       </l>
       <l>
        Thy shame aliue, but dead what thy death did.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-056-b"/>
       <l>
        Yet breath out to these walls the breath of mone,
       </l>
       <l>
        Tell th'aire thy plaints, since men thou canst not tell.
       </l>
       <l>
        And though thou perish desolate alone,
       </l>
       <l>
        Tell yet thy selfe, what thy selfe knowes too well:
       </l>
       <l>
        V&#9679;ter thy griefe where with thy soule doth swell.
       </l>
       <l>
        And let thy heart pitty thy hearts remorse.
       </l>
       <l>
        And be thy selfe the mourner and the corse.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Condole thee here, clad all in blacke dispaire,
       </l>
       <l>
        With silence onely, and a dying bed;
       </l>
       <l>
        Thou that of late, so flourishing, so faire,
       </l>
       <l>
        Didst glorious liue, admir'd and honoured:
       </l>
       <l>
        And now from friends, from succor hither led,
       </l>
       <l>
        Art made a spoyle to lust, to wrath, to death,
       </l>
       <l>
        And in disgrace, forc'd heere to yeeld thy breath.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Did Nature (for this good) ingeniate,
       </l>
       <l>
        To shew in thee the glory of her best;
       </l>
       <l>
        Framing thine eie the starre of thy ill fate.
       </l>
       <l>
        Making thy face the foe to spoile the rest?
       </l>
       <l>
        O Beauty, thou an enemie profest
       </l>
       <l>
        To Chastity and vs that loue thee most,
       </l>
       <l>
        Without theo how w'are loath'd, and with thee lost?
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        You, you that prowde with liberty and beautie,
       </l>
       <l>
        (And well may you be proude that you be so,)
       </l>
       <l>
        Glitter in Court, lou'd and obseru'd of duetie:
       </l>
       <l>
        Would God I might to you but ere I goe
       </l>
       <l>
        Speake what I feele&#9679; to warne you by my woe,
       </l>
       <l>
        To keepe your feete in cleanly paths of shame,
       </l>
       <l>
        That no inticing may diuert the same.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-057-a"/>
       <l>
        See'ng how against your tender weaknes still,
       </l>
       <l>
        The strength of wit, of gold, and all is bent:
       </l>
       <l>
        And all th'assaults that euer might or skill,
       </l>
       <l>
        Can giue against a chaste and cleane intent:
       </l>
       <l>
        Ah let not greatnesse worke you to consent.
       </l>
       <l>
        The spot is foule, though by a Monarch made,
       </l>
       <l>
        Kings cannot priuiledge what God forbade.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Locke vp therefore the treasure of your loue,
       </l>
       <l>
        Vnder the surest keyes of feare and shame:
       </l>
       <l>
        And let no powers haue powre chaste thoughts to moue
       </l>
       <l>
        To make a lawlesse entry on your fame.
       </l>
       <l>
        Open to those the comfort of your flame,
       </l>
       <l>
        Whose equall loue shall march with equall pace,
       </l>
       <l>
        In those pure wayes that leade to no disgrace.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        For see how many discontented beds,
       </l>
       <l>
        Our owne aspiring, or our Parents pride
       </l>
       <l>
        Haue caus'd, whilst that ambition vainely weds
       </l>
       <l>
        Wealth and not loue, honour and nought beside:
       </l>
       <l>
        Whilst married but to titles, we abide
       </l>
       <l>
        As wedded widowes, wanting what we haue,
       </l>
       <l>
        When shadowes cannot giue vs what we craue.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Or whilst we spend the freshest of our time,
       </l>
       <l>
        The sweet of youth in plotting in the ayre;
       </l>
       <l>
        Alas how oft we fall, hoping to clime;
       </l>
       <l>
        Or wither as vnprofitably faire,
       </l>
       <l>
        Whilst those decayes which are without repaire,
       </l>
       <l>
        Make vs neglected, scorned and reprou'd.
       </l>
       <l>
        (And O what are we, if we be not lou'd?)
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-057-b"/>
       <l>
        Fasten therefore vpon occasions fit,
       </l>
       <l>
        Lest this, or that, or like disgrace as mine,
       </l>
       <l>
        Do ouer-take your youth to ruine it,
       </l>
       <l>
        And cloude with infamie your beauties shine:
       </l>
       <l>
        Seeing how many seeke to vndermine
       </l>
       <l>
        The treasurie that's vnpossest of any:
       </l>
       <l>
        And hard tis kept that is desir'd of many.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        And flie (O flie) these Bed-brokers vncleane,
       </l>
       <l>
        (The monsters of our sexe, that make a pray
       </l>
       <l>
        Of their owne kinde, by an vnkindely meane;
       </l>
       <l>
        And euen (like Vipers) eating out a way
       </l>
       <l>
        Through th'wombe of their own shame, accursed they
       </l>
       <l>
        Liue by the death of Fame, the gaine of sin,
       </l>
       <l>
        The filth of lust, vncleannesse wallowes in.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        As if t'were not enough that we, (poore we)
       </l>
       <l>
        Haue weakenesse, beautie, golde, and men our foes,
       </l>
       <l>
        But we must haue some of our selues to be
       </l>
       <l>
        Traitors vnto our selues, to ioyne with those?
       </l>
       <l>
        Such as our feeble forces doe disclose,
       </l>
       <l>
        And still betray our cause, our shame our youth,
       </l>
       <l>
        To lust, to folly, and to mens vntruth?
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Hatefull confounders both of blood and lawes,
       </l>
       <l>
        Vilde Oraters of shame, that pleade delight:
       </l>
       <l>
        Vngracious Agents in a wicked cause,
       </l>
       <l>
        Factors for darkenesse, messengers of night,
       </l>
       <l>
        Serpents of guile, diuels, that do inuire
       </l>
       <l>
        The wanton taste of that forbidden tree,
       </l>
       <l>
        Whose fruit once pluckt, will shew how foule we be.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-058-a"/>
       <l>
        You in the habite of a graue aspect,
       </l>
       <l>
        (In credit by the trust of yeares, (can shoe
       </l>
       <l>
        The cunning wayes of lust, and can direct
       </l>
       <l>
        The faire and wily wantons how they goe,
       </l>
       <l>
        Hauing (youth lothsome selues) your youth spent so.
       </l>
       <l>
        And in vncleannes euer haue beene fed,
       </l>
       <l>
        By the reuenue of a wanton bed.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        By you, haue beene the innocent betraid,
       </l>
       <l>
        The blushing fearefull, boldned vnto sin,
       </l>
       <l>
        The wife made subtile, subtile made the maide,
       </l>
       <l>
        The husband scorn'd, dishonoured the kin:
       </l>
       <l>
        Parents disgrac'd, children infamous been.
       </l>
       <l>
        Confus'd our race, and falsi-fied our blood,
       </l>
       <l>
        Whilst fathers sonnes possesse wrong Fathers good.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        This, and much more, I would haue vttred then,
       </l>
       <l>
        A testament to be recorded still,
       </l>
       <l>
        Sign'd with my blood, subscrib'd with Conscience pen,
       </l>
       <l>
        To warne the faire and beautifull from ill.
       </l>
       <l>
        Though I could wish (by th'example of my will,)
       </l>
       <l>
        I had not left this note vnto the faire,
       </l>
       <l>
        But dyde intestate to haue had no heire.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        But now, the poyson spread through all my vaines,
       </l>
       <l>
        Gan dispossesse my liuing sences quite:
       </l>
       <l>
        And nought respecting death, (the last of paines,)
       </l>
       <l>
        Plac'd his pale colours, (th'ensigne of his might,)
       </l>
       <l>
        Vpon his new-got spoile before his right;
       </l>
       <l>
        Thence chac'd my soule, setting my day ere noone,
       </l>
       <l>
        When I least thought my ioyes could end so soone.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-058-b"/>
       <l>
        And as conuaid t'vntimely funerals,
       </l>
       <l>
        My scarce cold corse not suffred longer stay,
       </l>
       <l>
        Behold, the King (by chance) returning, fals
       </l>
       <l>
        T'incounter with the same vpon the way,
       </l>
       <l>
        As he repair'd to see his deerest ioy.
       </l>
       <l>
        Not thinking such a meeting could haue beene,
       </l>
       <l>
        To see his Loue, and seeing beene vnseene,
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Iudge those whom cha&#772;ce depriues of sweetest treasure,
       </l>
       <l>
        What tis to lose a thing we hold so deere:
       </l>
       <l>
        The best delight, wherein our soule takes pleasure,
       </l>
       <l>
        The sweet of life, that penetrates so neere.
       </l>
       <l>
        What passions feeles that hart, inforc'd to beare
       </l>
       <l>
        The deepe impression of so strange a sight,
       </l>
       <l>
        That ouerwhelmes vs, or confounds vs quite?
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Amaz'd he stands, nor voice nor body steares,
       </l>
       <l>
        Words had no passage, teares no issue found,
       </l>
       <l>
        For sorrow shut vp words, wrath kept in teares,
       </l>
       <l>
        Confus'd affects each other do confound:
       </l>
       <l>
        Oppress'd with griefe, his passions had no bound.
       </l>
       <l>
        Striuing to tell his woes, words would not come;
       </l>
       <l>
        For light cares speak, when mighty griefs are dombe.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        At length extreamity breakes out a way,
       </l>
       <l>
        Through which th'imprisned voice with tears atte&#772;ded,
       </l>
       <l>
        Wailes out a sound that sorrows do bewray,
       </l>
       <l>
        With armes a-crosse, and eies to heauen bended,
       </l>
       <l>
        Vaporing our sighes that to the skies ascended.
       </l>
       <l>
        Sighes (the poore ease calamity affoords,)
       </l>
       <l>
        Which serue for speech when sorow wanteth words.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-059-a"/>
       <l>
        O heauens) quoth he,) why do mine eies behold
       </l>
       <l>
        The hatefull raies of this vnhappy sunne?
       </l>
       <l>
        Why haue I light to see my sinnes contrould,
       </l>
       <l>
        With blood of mine own shame thus vildly done?
       </l>
       <l>
        How can my sight endure to looke thereon?
       </l>
       <l>
        Why doth not blacke eternall darknesse hide,
       </l>
       <l>
        That from mine eyes, my hart cannot abide?
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        What saw my life, wherein my soule might ioy,
       </l>
       <l>
        What had my dayes, whom troubles still afflicted,
       </l>
       <l>
        But onely this, to counterpoize annoy?
       </l>
       <l>
        This ioy, this hope, which Death hath interdicted;
       </l>
       <l>
        This sweet, whose losse hath all distresse inflicted:
       </l>
       <l>
        This, that did season all my sowre of life,
       </l>
       <l>
        Vext still at home with broiles, abrode in strife:
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Vext still at home with broiles, abroade in strife,
       </l>
       <l>
        Dissention in my blood, iarres in my bed:
       </l>
       <l>
        Distrust at boord, suspecting still my life,
       </l>
       <l>
        Spending the night in horror, dayes in dread:
       </l>
       <l>
        (Such life hath Tyrants, and this life I led.)
       </l>
       <l>
        These miseries go mask'd in glittering showes,
       </l>
       <l>
        Which wise men see, the vulgar littles knows.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Thus as these passions doe him ouerwhelme,
       </l>
       <l>
        He drawes him neere my body to behold it.
       </l>
       <l>
        And as the Vine married vnto the Elme
       </l>
       <l>
        With strict imbraces, so doth he infold it.
       </l>
       <l>
        And as he in his carefull armes doth hold it,
       </l>
       <l>
        Viewing the face that now euen death commends,
       </l>
       <l>
        On sencelesse lippes, millions of kisses spends.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-059-b"/>
       <l>
        Pitt&#9679;full mouth (saith he) that liuing gauest
       </l>
       <l>
        The sweetest comfort that my soule could wish:
       </l>
       <l>
        O be it lawfull now, that dead thou hauest,
       </l>
       <l>
        This sorrowing farewell of a dying kisle.
       </l>
       <l>
        And you faire eyes, containers of my blisse,
       </l>
       <l>
        Motiues of loue, borne to be matched neuer,
       </l>
       <l>
        Entomb'd in your sweet circles sleepe for euer.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Ah how me thinkes I see Death dallying seekes,
       </l>
       <l>
        To entertaine it selfe in Loues sweet place:
       </l>
       <l>
        Decayed Roses of discoloured cheekes,
       </l>
       <l>
        Doe yet retaine deerenotes of former grace:
       </l>
       <l>
        And vgly Death sits faire within her face;
       </l>
       <l>
        Sweete remnants resting of vermillian red,
       </l>
       <l>
        That Death it selfe doubts whether she be dead.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Wonder of beauty, oh receiue these plaints,
       </l>
       <l>
        These obsequies, the last that I shall make thee:
       </l>
       <l>
        For loe, my soule that now already faints,
       </l>
       <l>
        (That lou'd thee liuing, dead will not forsake thee,)
       </l>
       <l>
        Hastens her speedy course to ouer-take thee.
       </l>
       <l>
        I&#9679;e meete my death, and free my selfe thereby,
       </l>
       <l>
        For (ah) what can he doe that cannot die?
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Yet ere I die, thus much my soule doth vow,
       </l>
       <l>
        Reuenge shall sweeten death with ease of minde:
       </l>
       <l>
        And I will cause posterity shall know,
       </l>
       <l>
        How fa&#9679;e thou wert aboue all woman kinde,
       </l>
       <l>
        And after-ages monuments shall finde
       </l>
       <l>
        Shewing thy beauties title, no&#9679; thy name,
       </l>
       <l>
        Rose of the world that sweetned so the same.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-060-a"/>
       <l>
        This said, though more desirous yet to say,
       </l>
       <l>
        (For sorrow is vnwilling to giue ouer.)
       </l>
       <l>
        He doth represse what griefe would else bewray,
       </l>
       <l>
        Least he too much his passions should discouer.
       </l>
       <l>
        And yet respect scarce bridles such a Louer.
       </l>
       <l>
        So farre transported that he knew not whither,
       </l>
       <l>
        For Loue and Maiesty dwell ill together,
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Then were my funerals not long deferred.
       </l>
       <l>
        But done with all the rites pompe could deuise,
       </l>
       <l>
        At Godstow, where my body was interred.
       </l>
       <l>
        And richly tomb'd in honourable wise,
       </l>
       <l>
        Where yet as now scarce any note descries
       </l>
       <l>
        Vnto these times, the memory of mee,
       </l>
       <l>
        Marble and Brasse so little lasting be.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        For those walls which the credulous &#9679;euout,
       </l>
       <l>
        And apt-beleeuing ignorant did found;
       </l>
       <l>
        With willing zeale, that neuer call'd in doubt,
       </l>
       <l>
        That Time their works should euer so confound,
       </l>
       <l>
        Lye like confused heapes as vnder ground.
       </l>
       <l>
        And what their ignorance esteem'd so holy&#9679;
       </l>
       <l>
        Our wiser ages do account as follie.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        And were it not thy fauourable lines
       </l>
       <l>
        Re-edified the wracke of my decaies,
       </l>
       <l>
        And that thy accents willingly assignes
       </l>
       <l>
        Some farther date, and giue meelonger dayes,
       </l>
       <l>
        Few in this age had knowne my Beautyes praise.
       </l>
       <l>
        But thus renew'd, my fame redeemes some time,
       </l>
       <l>
        Till other ages shall neglect thy rime.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-060-b"/>
       <l>
        Then when Confusion in her course shall bri&#9679;g
       </l>
       <l>
        Sad desolation on the times to come:
       </l>
       <l>
        When mirthlesse Thames shall haue no Swanne to sing,
       </l>
       <l>
        All musicke silent, &amp; the Muses dombe:
       </l>
       <l>
        And yet euen then it must be knowne to some,
       </l>
       <l>
        That once they flourisht, though not cherisht so,
       </l>
       <l>
        And Thames had Swannes aswell as euer Po,
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        But heere an end, I may no longer stay.
       </l>
       <l>
        I must returne t'attend at Stygian flood:
       </l>
       <l>
        Yet ere I goe, this one word more I pray.
       </l>
       <l>
        Tell Delia, now her sight may do me good,
       </l>
       <l>
        And will her note the frailty of our blood.
       </l>
       <l>
        And if I passe vnto th&#9679;se happy bankes.
       </l>
       <l>
        Then she must haue her praise, thy pen her thankes.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        So vanquisht she, and left me to returne
       </l>
       <l>
        To prosecute the tenor of my woes:
       </l>
       <l>
        Eternall matter for my Muse to mourne,
       </l>
       <l>
        But (yet) the world hath heard too much of those,
       </l>
       <l>
        My youth such errors must no more disclose.
       </l>
       <l>
        Ile hide the rest, and grieue for what hath beene,
       </l>
       <l>
        Who made me knowne must make me liue vnsee&#9679;
       </l>
      </lg>
      <trailer>
       FINIS.
      </trailer>
     </div>
     <div type="ode" xml:id="ep000822-e38830">
      <pb xml:id="ep000822-061-a"/>
      <head>
       An Ode.
      </head>
      <lg>
       <l>
        NOW each creature ioyes the other,
       </l>
       <l>
        passing happy dayes and howers,
       </l>
       <l>
        One Bird reports vnto another,
       </l>
       <l>
        in the fall of siluer showers,
       </l>
       <l>
        Whilst the earth (our common mother)
       </l>
       <l>
        hath her bosome deckt with flowers.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Whilst the greatest Torch of heauen,
       </l>
       <l>
        with bright rayes warmes Floras lap,
       </l>
       <l>
        Making nights and dayes both euen,
       </l>
       <l>
        chearing plants with fresher sap:
       </l>
       <l>
        My field of flowers quite bereuen,
       </l>
       <l>
        wants refresh of better hap.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Eccho, daughter of the Aire,
       </l>
       <l>
        (babling guest of Rocks and hils,)
       </l>
       <l>
        Knowes the name of my fierce Faire,
       </l>
       <l>
        and sounds the accents of my ils.
       </l>
       <l>
        Each thing pitties my dispaire,
       </l>
       <l>
        whilst that she her Louer kils.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Whilst that she (O cruell Maid)
       </l>
       <l>
        doth me and my loue despise,
       </l>
       <l>
        My liues florish is decayed,
       </l>
       <l>
        that depended on her eyes:
       </l>
       <l>
        But her will must be obeyed,
       </l>
       <l>
        and well he ends for loue who dyes.
       </l>
      </lg>
     </div>
     <div type="pastoral" xml:id="ep000822-e39150">
      <pb xml:id="ep000822-061-b"/>
      <head>
       A Pastorall.
      </head>
      <lg>
       <l>
        O Happie golden Age,
       </l>
       <l>
        Not for that Riuers ranne
       </l>
       <l>
        With streames of milke, and hunny dropt from treet,
       </l>
       <l>
        Not that the earth did gage
       </l>
       <l>
        Vnto the husband-man
       </l>
       <l>
        Her voluntary frutes, free without fees:
       </l>
       <l>
        Not for no cold did freeze,
       </l>
       <l>
        Nor any cloud beguile,
       </l>
       <l>
        Th'eternall flowring Spring
       </l>
       <l>
        Wherein liu'd euery thing,
       </l>
       <l>
        And whereon th'heauens perpetually did smile,
       </l>
       <l>
        Not for no sh&#9679;p had brought
       </l>
       <l>
        From forraine shores, or warres or wares ill sought.
       </l>
       <l>
        But onely for that name,
       </l>
       <l>
        That Idle name of winde:
       </l>
       <l>
        That Idoll of deceit, that emptie sound
       </l>
       <l>
        Call'd Honor, which became
       </l>
       <l>
        The tyran of the minde:
       </l>
       <l>
        And so torments our Nature without ground,
       </l>
       <l>
        Was not yet vainly found:
       </l>
       <l>
        Nor yet sad griefes imparts
       </l>
       <l>
        Amidst the sweet delights
       </l>
       <l>
        Of ioyfull amorous wights.
       </l>
       <l>
        Nor were his hard lawes knowne to free-borne harts.
       </l>
       <l>
        But golden lawes like these
       </l>
       <l>
        Which Nature wrote.
        <hi>
         That's lawfull which doth please
        </hi>
        .
       </l>
       <l>
        Then amongst flowres and springs
       </l>
       <l>
        Making delightfull sport,
       </l>
       <l>
        Sate Louers without conflict, without flame:
       </l>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-062-a"/>
       <l>
        And Nimphs and shepheards sing
       </l>
       <l>
        Mixing in wanton sort
       </l>
       <l>
        Whisp'rings with Songs, then kisses with the same
       </l>
       <l>
        Which from affection came:
       </l>
       <l>
        The naked virgin then
       </l>
       <l>
        Her Roses fresh reueales,
       </l>
       <l>
        Which now her vayle conceales.
       </l>
       <l>
        The tender Apples in her bosome seene,
       </l>
       <l>
        And oft in Riuers cleere
       </l>
       <l>
        The Louers with their Loues consorting were.
       </l>
       <l>
        HONOR, thou first didst close
       </l>
       <l>
        The spring of all delight:
       </l>
       <l>
        Denying water to the amorous thirst
       </l>
       <l>
        Thou taught'st faire eyes to lose
       </l>
       <l>
        The glory of their light.
       </l>
       <l>
        Restrain'd from men, and on themselues reuerst.
       </l>
       <l>
        Thou in a Lawne didst first
       </l>
       <l>
        These golden haires incase,
       </l>
       <l>
        Late spred vnto the winde:
       </l>
       <l>
        Thou mad'st loose grace vnkinde,
       </l>
       <l>
        Gau'st bridle to their words, art to their pace.
       </l>
       <l>
        O Honour it is thou
       </l>
       <l>
        That mak'st that stealth, which loue doth free allow.
       </l>
       <l>
        It is thy worke that brings
       </l>
       <l>
        Our griefes, and torments thus:
       </l>
       <l>
        But thou fierce Lord of Nature and of Loue,
       </l>
       <l>
        The quallifier of Kings,
       </l>
       <l>
        What doest thou here with vs
       </l>
       <l>
        That are below thy power, shut from aboue?
       </l>
       <l>
        Goe and from vs remoue,
       </l>
       <l>
        Trouble the mighties sleepe,
       </l>
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-062-b"/>
       <l>
        Let vs neglected, base,
       </l>
       <l>
        Liue still without thy grace,
       </l>
       <l>
        And th'vse of th'auncient happie ages keepe,
       </l>
       <l>
        Let's loue, this life of ours
       </l>
       <l>
        Can make no truce with time that all deuours.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Let's loue, the sun doth set, and rise againe,
       </l>
       <l>
        But when as our short light
       </l>
       <l>
        Comes once to set, it makes eternall night.
       </l>
      </lg>
      <trailer>
       FINIS.
      </trailer>
     </div>
     <div type="dialogue" xml:id="ep000822-e39910">
      <pb xml:id="ep000822-063-a"/>
      <head>
       Vlisses and the Syren.
      </head>
      <sp who="ep000822-syren" xml:id="ep000822-e39930">
       <speaker>
        Syren.
       </speaker>
       <lg>
        <l>
         COme worthy Greeke, Vlisses come
        </l>
        <l>
         Possesse these shores with me:
        </l>
        <l>
         The windes and Seas are troublesome,
        </l>
        <l>
         And heere we may be free.
        </l>
        <l>
         Here may we sit, and view their toile
        </l>
        <l>
         That trauaile in the deepe,
        </l>
        <l>
         And ioy the day in mirth the while,
        </l>
        <l>
         And spend the night in sleepe.
        </l>
       </lg>
      </sp>
      <sp who="ep000822-vlis" xml:id="ep000822-e40050">
       <speaker>
        Vlis.
       </speaker>
       <lg>
        <l>
         Faire Nimph, if fame, or honor were
        </l>
        <l>
         To be attaynd with case
        </l>
        <l>
         Then would I come, and rest with thee,
        </l>
        <l>
         And leaue such toyles as these.
        </l>
        <l>
         But here it dwels, and here must I
        </l>
        <l>
         With danger seeke it forth,
        </l>
        <l>
         To spend the time luxuriously
        </l>
        <l>
         Becomes not men of worth.
        </l>
       </lg>
      </sp>
      <sp who="ep000822-syrvlisses" xml:id="ep000822-e40160">
       <speaker>
        Syr. Vlisses,
       </speaker>
       <lg>
        <l>
         O be not deceiu'd
        </l>
        <l>
         With that vnreall name:
        </l>
        <l>
         This honour is a thing conceiu'd,
        </l>
        <l>
         And rests on others fame.
        </l>
        <l>
         Begotten onely to molest
        </l>
        <l>
         Our peace, and to beguile
        </l>
        <l>
         (The best thing of our life) our rest,
        </l>
        <l>
         And giue vs vp to toile.
        </l>
       </lg>
      </sp>
      <sp who="ep000822-vlis" xml:id="ep000822-e40270">
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-063-b"/>
       <speaker>
        Vlis.
       </speaker>
       <lg>
        <l>
         Delicious Nimph, suppose there were
        </l>
        <l>
         Nor honour, nor report,
        </l>
        <l>
         Yet manlines would scorne to weare
        </l>
        <l>
         The time in idle sport.
        </l>
        <l>
         For toyle doth giue a better touch,
        </l>
        <l>
         To make vs feele our ioy;
        </l>
        <l>
         And case findes tediousnesse as much
        </l>
        <l>
         As labour yeelds annoy.
        </l>
       </lg>
      </sp>
      <sp who="ep000822-syr" xml:id="ep000822-e40380">
       <speaker>
        Syr.
       </speaker>
       <lg>
        <l>
         Then pleasure likewise seemes the shore,
        </l>
        <l>
         Whereto tends all your toyle,
        </l>
        <l>
         Which you forgo to make it more,
        </l>
        <l>
         And perish oft the while.
        </l>
        <l>
         Who may disporte them diuersly,
        </l>
        <l>
         Finde neuer tedious day,
        </l>
        <l>
         And ease may haue varietie,
        </l>
        <l>
         As well as action may.
        </l>
       </lg>
      </sp>
      <sp who="ep000822-vlis" xml:id="ep000822-e40490">
       <speaker>
        Vlis.
       </speaker>
       <lg>
        <l>
         But natures of the noblest frame
        </l>
        <l>
         These toyles, and dangers please,
        </l>
        <l>
         And they take comfort in the same,
        </l>
        <l>
         As much as you in ease.
        </l>
        <l>
         And with the thought of actions past
        </l>
        <l>
         Are recreated still;
        </l>
        <l>
         When pleasure leaues a touch at las&#9679;,
        </l>
        <l>
         To shew that it was ill.
        </l>
       </lg>
      </sp>
      <sp who="ep000822-sy" xml:id="ep000822-e40600">
       <pb xml:id="ep000822-064-a"/>
       <speaker>
        Sy.
       </speaker>
       <lg>
        <l>
         That doth opinion onely cause,
        </l>
        <l>
         That's out of custome bred,
        </l>
        <l>
         Which makes vs many other lawes
        </l>
        <l>
         Then euer Nature did.
        </l>
       </lg>
       <lg>
        <l>
         No widdowes waile for our delights,
        </l>
        <l>
         Our sportes are without bloud,
        </l>
        <l>
         The world we see by warlike wights.
        </l>
        <l>
         Receiues more hurt then good.
        </l>
       </lg>
      </sp>
      <sp who="ep000822-vlis" xml:id="ep000822-e40720">
       <speaker>
        Vlis.
       </speaker>
       <lg>
        <l>
         But yet the state of things require
        </l>
        <l>
         These motions of vnrest,
        </l>
        <l>
         And these great Spirits of high desire,
        </l>
        <l>
         Seeme borne to turne them best.
        </l>
        <l>
         To purge the mischiefes that increase,
        </l>
        <l>
         And all good order mar:
        </l>
        <l>
         For oft we see a wicked peace
        </l>
        <l>
         To be well chang'd for war.
        </l>
       </lg>
      </sp>
      <sp who="ep000822-sy" xml:id="ep000822-e40830">
       <speaker>
        Sy.
       </speaker>
       <lg>
        <l>
         Well, well Vlisses then I see,
        </l>
        <l>
         I shall not haue thee heere,
        </l>
        <l>
         And therefore I will come to thee,
        </l>
        <l>
         And take my fortunes there.
        </l>
        <l>
         I must be wonne that cannot win,
        </l>
        <l>
         Yet lost were I not wonne:
        </l>
        <l>
         For beauty hath created bin,
        </l>
        <l>
         T'vndoo, or be vndonne.
        </l>
       </lg>
      </sp>
      <trailer>
       FINIS.
      </trailer>
      <pb xml:id="ep000822-064-b"/>
      <pb xml:id="ep000822-065-a"/>
      <pb xml:id="ep000822-065-b"/>
     </div>
    </body>
   </text>
   <text>
    <body>
     <div>
      <p>
       <label>
        Editor's note
       </label>
       Daniel's
       <hi>
        Philotas
       </hi>
       , published originally here, appears in the EarlyPrint Project as as separate document and under its own name
              with the filename A19812_02
      </p>
     </div>
    </body>
   </text>
  </group>
 </text>
</TEI>
