<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000823" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Delia and Rosamond augmented Cleopatra by Samuel Daniel.</title>
        <title>Delia</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Samuel</forename>
            <surname>Daniel</surname>
          </persName>
          <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q954735</idno>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A19816_00.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <p>
            This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is available for reuse, according to the terms of
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>
            . The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
          </p>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull>
              <titleStmt>
                <title>Delia and Rosamond augmented Cleopatra by Samuel Daniel.</title>
                <title>Delia</title>
                <author>Daniel, Samuel, 1562-1619.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[196] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>[By James Roberts and Edward Allde] for Simon Waterson, and are to be sold in Paules Church-yarde at the signe of the Crowne,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>1594. Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                <date>[1594]</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>An expanded edition of "Delia".</note>
                <note>In verse.</note>
                <note>Printers' names from colophon.</note>
                <note>Signatures: A² B-N.</note>
                <note>"The complaynt of Rosamond" and "The tragedie of Cleopatra" have separate divisional title pages, the second dated; register is continuous.</note>
                <note>Identified as STC 6254 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <classCode scheme="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q80930</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1594">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <group>
      <text>
        <front>
          <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000823-e30">
            <pb xml:id="ep000823-001-a"/>
            <pb xml:id="ep000823-001-b"/>
            <p>DELIA and ROSAMOND augmented. </p>
            <p>CLEOPATRA </p>
            <p>By <hi>Samuel Daniel</hi>. </p>
            <p>
              <foreign xml:lang="lat">AEtas prima canat veneres postrema tumultus. </foreign>
            </p>
            <p>1594. </p>
            <p>Printed at London for <hi>Simon Waterson</hi>; and are to be sold in Paules Church-yarde at the signe of the Crowne. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000823-e150">
            <pb xml:id="ep000823-002-a"/>
            <pb xml:id="ep000823-002-b"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, THE LADY MARY, Countesse of Pembrooke. </head>
            <lg>
              <l>WOnder of these, glory of other times, </l>
              <l>O thou whom Enuy eu'n is forst t'admyre: </l>
              <l>Great Patroness of these my humble Rymes, </l>
              <l>Which thou from out thy greatnes doost inspire: </l>
              <l>Sith onely thou hast deign'd to rayse them higher, </l>
              <l>Vouchsafe now to accept them as thine owne, </l>
              <l>Begotten by thy hand, and my desire, </l>
              <l>Wherein my Zeale, and thy great might is showne. </l>
              <l>And seeing this vnto the world is knowne, </l>
              <l>O leaue not, still to grace thy worke in mee: </l>
              <l>Let not the quickning seede be ouer-throwne, </l>
              <l>Of that which may be borne to honour thee. </l>
              <l>Whereof, the trauaile I may challenge mine, </l>
              <l>But yet the glory, (Madam) must be thine. </l>
            </lg>
          </div>
          <div type="errata" xml:id="ep000823-e340">
            <pb xml:id="ep000823-003-a"/>
            <head>Gentle Reader correct these faultes escaped in the printing. </head>
            <lg>
              <l>SOnnet 18. lyne 3. for error, reade terror. </l>
              <l>G. 1. page 2. for Condemning, read Conducting. </l>
              <l>In L. page 16. Marke the Speaker, and read thus, </l>
              <l>
                <hi>The iustice of the heauens reuenging thus, </hi>
              </l>
              <l>
                <hi>Doth onely satisfie it selfe, not vs. </hi>
              </l>
              <l>In the last Chorus, for care, reade cure. </l>
            </lg>
          </div>
        </front>
        <body>
          <div type="sonnet_sequence" xml:id="ep000823-e460">
            <pb xml:id="ep000823-003-b"/>
            <head>TO DELIA. </head>
            <lg n="1">
              <head>SONNET. I. </head>
              <l>VNto the boundles Ocean of thy beautie, </l>
              <l>Runs this poore riuer, charg'd with streams of zeale, </l>
              <l>Returning thee the trybute of my duty, </l>
              <l>Which here my loue, my youth, my plaints reueale. </l>
              <l>Heere I vnclaspe the booke of my charg'd soule, </l>
              <l>Where I haue cast th'accounts of all my care: </l>
              <l>Heere haue I summ'd my sighes; here I enrole </l>
              <l>How they were spent for thee; looke what they are. </l>
              <l>Looke on the deere expences of my youth, </l>
              <l>And see how iust I reckon with thine eyes: </l>
              <l>Examine well thy beauty with my truth, </l>
              <l>And crosse my cares ere greater summes arise. </l>
              <l>Read it (sweet maid,) though it be doone but slightly, </l>
              <l>Who can shew all his loue, doth loue but lightly. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-004-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. II. </head>
              <l>GOE wayling verse, the Infants of my loue, </l>
              <l>Minerua-lyke, brought foorth without a mother: </l>
              <l>Present the Image of the cares I proue, </l>
              <l>Witnes your Fathers griefe exceedes all other. </l>
              <l>Sigh out a story of her cruell deedes, </l>
              <l>With inter-rupted accents of dispaire: </l>
              <l>A monument that whosoeuer reedes, </l>
              <l>May iustly praise, and blame my louelesse Fayre. </l>
              <l>Say her disdaine hath dryed vp my blood, </l>
              <l>And starued you, in succours still denying: </l>
              <l>Presse to her eyes, importune me some good, </l>
              <l>Waken her sleeping pitty with your crying, </l>
              <l>Knock at her hard hart, beg till you haue mou'd her, </l>
              <l>And tell th'vnkind, how decrely I haue lou'd her. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-004-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. III. </head>
              <l>IF so it hap, this of-spring of my care, </l>
              <l>These fatall Antheames, sad and mournful songs: </l>
              <l>Come to their view, who like afflicted are; </l>
              <l>Ah let them sigh theyr owne, and mone my wrongs. </l>
              <l>But vntoucht hatts, with vnaffected eye, </l>
              <l>Approch not to behold so great distresse: </l>
              <l>Cleer-sighted you, soone note what is awry, </l>
              <l>Whilst blinded ones mine errours neuer gesse. </l>
              <l>You blinded soules whom youth and errors leade, </l>
              <l>You out-cast Eaglets, dazeled with your sunne: </l>
              <l>Ah you, and none but you my sorrowes reade, </l>
              <l>You best can iudge the wrongs that she hath done. </l>
              <l>That she hath done, the motiue of my paine, </l>
              <l>Who whilst I louē, doth kill me with disdaine. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-005-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. IIII. </head>
              <l>THese plaintiue verse, the Posts of my desire, </l>
              <l>Which haste for succour to her slow regard: </l>
              <l>Beare not report of any slender fire, </l>
              <l>Forging a griefe to winne a fames reward. </l>
              <l>Nor are my passions lymnd for outward hewe, </l>
              <l>For that no colours can depaint my sorrows: </l>
              <l>DELIA her selfe, and all the world may view </l>
              <l>Best in my face, where cares hath till'd deep furrows. </l>
              <l>No Bayes I seeke to deck my mourning brow, </l>
              <l>O cleer-eyde Rector of the holy Hill: </l>
              <l>My humble accents beare the Oliue bough, </l>
              <l>Of intercession to a Tyrants will. </l>
              <l>These lines I vse, t'vnburthen mine owne hart; </l>
              <l>My loue affects no fame, nor steemes of Art. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-005-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. V. </head>
              <l>WHilst youth and error led my wandring minde, </l>
              <l>And sette my thoughts in heedles waies to range: </l>
              <l>All vnawares, a Goddesse chaste I finde, </l>
              <l>
                <hi>(Diana-like</hi>) to worke my suddaine change. </l>
              <l>For her no sooner had mine eye bewraid, </l>
              <l>But with disdaine to see mee in that place: </l>
              <l>With fairest hand, the sweet vnkindest maid, </l>
              <l>Casts water-cold disdaine vpon my face. </l>
              <l>Which turn'd my sport into a Harts despaire, </l>
              <l>Which still is chac'd, while I haue any breath, </l>
              <l>By mine owne thoughts; sette on mee by my faire: </l>
              <l>My thoughts (like hounds) pursue me to my death. </l>
              <l>Those that I fostred of mine owne accord, </l>
              <l>Are made by her to murder thus theyr Lord. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-006-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. VI. </head>
              <l>FAyre is my loue, and cruell as sh'is fayre; </l>
              <l>Her brow shades frowns, althogh her eyes are sunny; </l>
              <l>Her smyles are lightning, though her pride dispaire; </l>
              <l>And her disdaines are gall, her fauours hunny. </l>
              <l>A modest mayde, deckt with a blush of honour, </l>
              <l>Whose feet do tread greene pathes of youth &amp; loue, </l>
              <l>The wonder of all eyes that looke vpon her: </l>
              <l>Sacred on earth, design'd a Saint aboue. </l>
              <l>Chastity and Beauty, which were deadly foes, </l>
              <l>Liue reconciled friends within her brow: </l>
              <l>And had she pitty to conioyne with those, </l>
              <l>Then who had heard the plaints I vtter now. </l>
              <l>O had shee not beene fayre, and thus vnkind, </l>
              <l>My Muse had slept, &amp; none had knowne my minde. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-006-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. UII. </head>
              <l>O Had shee not beene faire and thus vnkind, </l>
              <l>Then had no finger pointed at my lightnes: </l>
              <l>The world had neuer knowne what I doe finde, </l>
              <l>And clowdes obscure had shaded stil her brightnes. </l>
              <l>Then had no Censors eye these lynes suruaide, </l>
              <l>Nor grauer browes haue iudg'd my Muse so vaine; </l>
              <l>No sunne my blush and errour had bewraid, </l>
              <l>Nor yet the world had heard of such disdaine. </l>
              <l>Then had I walkt with bold erected face, </l>
              <l>No downe-cast looke had signified my misse: </l>
              <l>But my degraded hopes, with such disgrace </l>
              <l>Did force me grone out griefes, and vtter this. </l>
              <l>For being full, should I not then haue spoken, </l>
              <l>My sence oppress'd, had faild, and hart had broken. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-007-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. VIII. </head>
              <l>THou poore hart sacrifiz'd vnto the fairest, </l>
              <l>Hast sent the incens of thy sighes to heauen: </l>
              <l>And still against her frownes fresh vowes repayrest, </l>
              <l>And made thy passions with her beauty euen. </l>
              <l>And you mine eyes, the agents of my hart, </l>
              <l>Told the dumbe message of my hidden griefe: </l>
              <l>And oft with carefull turnes, with silent Arte, </l>
              <l>Did treat the cruell Fayre to yeeld reliefe. </l>
              <l>And you my verse, the Aduocates of loue, </l>
              <l>Haue followed hard the processe of my case: </l>
              <l>And vrg'd that tytle which doth plainly proue, </l>
              <l>My faith should win, if iustice might haue place. </l>
              <l>Yet though I see, that nought we doe can moue her, </l>
              <l>Tis not disdaine must make me cease to loue her. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-007-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. IX. </head>
              <l>IF thys be loue, to draw a weary breath, </l>
              <l>Paint on floods, till the shore cry to th'ayre: </l>
              <l>With downward lookes, still reading on the earth; </l>
              <l>The sad memorials of my loues despayre. </l>
              <l>If this be loue, to warre against my soule, </l>
              <l>Lye downe to waile, rise vp to sigh and grieue, </l>
              <l>The neuer-resting stone of care to roule, </l>
              <l>Still to cōplaine my griefes, whilst none relieue. </l>
              <l>If this be loue, to cloathe me with darke thoughts, </l>
              <l>Haunting vntroden pathes to waile apart; </l>
              <l>My pleasures horror, Musique tragick notes, </l>
              <l>Teares in mine eyes, and sorrow at my hart. </l>
              <l>If thys be loue, to liue a liuing death, </l>
              <l>O then loue I, and draw this weary breath. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="10">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-008-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. X. </head>
              <l>O Then loue I, and draw this weary breath, </l>
              <l>For her the cruell Fayre, within whose brow, </l>
              <l>I written finde the sentence of my death, </l>
              <l>In vnkind letters; wrought she cares not how. </l>
              <l>O thou that rul'st the confines of the night, </l>
              <l>Laughter-louing goddesse, worldly plesures Queen, </l>
              <l>Intencrat that hart that sets so light, </l>
              <l>The truest loue that euer yet was seene. </l>
              <l>And cause her leaue to tryumph in this wise, </l>
              <l>Vpon the prostrate spoyle of that poore hart: </l>
              <l>That serues a Trophey to her conquering eyes, </l>
              <l>And must theyr glory to the world impart. </l>
              <l>Once let her know, sh' hath done enough to proue me, </l>
              <l>And let her pitty if she cannot loue me. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="11">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-008-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. XI. </head>
              <l>TEares, vowes and prayers, winne the hardest hart; </l>
              <l>Teares, vowes and prayers, haue I spent in vaine; </l>
              <l>Teares cannot soften Flint, nor vowes conuart, </l>
              <l>Prayers preuaile not with a quaint disdaine. </l>
              <l>I lose my teares, where I haue lost my loue, </l>
              <l>I vowe my faith, where faith is not regarded, </l>
              <l>I pray in vaine, a merciles to moue: </l>
              <l>So rare a faith ought better be rewarded; </l>
              <l>Yet though I cannot win her will with teares, </l>
              <l>Though my soules I doll scorneth all my vowes; </l>
              <l>Though all my prayers be to so deafe eares, </l>
              <l>No sauour though the cruell faire allowes, </l>
              <l>Yet will I weepe, vowe, pray to cruell shee: </l>
              <l>Flint, frost, disdaine, weares, melts, and yeelds we see. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="12">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-009-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. XII. </head>
              <l>MY spotlesse loue hoouers with purest wings, </l>
              <l>About the temple of the proudest frame: </l>
              <l>Where blaze those lights fayrest of earthly things, which cleer our clowded world with brightest flame. </l>
              <l>M'ambitious thoughts confined in her face, </l>
              <l>Affect no honour but what she can giue, </l>
              <l>My hopes doe rest in limits of her grace, </l>
              <l>I weigh no comfort vnlesse she relieue. </l>
              <l>For she that can my hart imparadize, </l>
              <l>Holds in her fairest hand what deerest is, </l>
              <l>My fortunes wheele's the circle of her eyes, </l>
              <l>Whose rowling grace deigne once a turne of blis. </l>
              <l>All my liues sweet consists in her alone, </l>
              <l>So much I loue the most vnlouing one. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="13">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-009-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. XIII. </head>
              <l>BEhold what hap Pigmalion had to frame, </l>
              <l>And carue his propper griefe vpon a stone, </l>
              <l>My heauy fortune is much like the same, </l>
              <l>I worke on Flint, and that's the cause I mone. </l>
              <l>For haplesse loe euen with mine owne desires, </l>
              <l>I figured on the Table of mine hart, </l>
              <l>The fairest forme, that all the world admires, </l>
              <l>And so did perrish by my proper arte. </l>
              <l>And still I toyle, to change the Marble breast </l>
              <l>Of her, whose sweetest grace I doe adore, </l>
              <l>Yet cannot finde her breathe vnto my rest, </l>
              <l>Hard is her hart, and woe is me therefore. </l>
              <l>O happy he that ioy'd his stone and arte, </l>
              <l>Vnhappy I to loue a stony hart. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="14">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-010-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. XIIII. </head>
              <l>THose snary locks, are those same nets (my Deere,) </l>
              <l>Where-with my libertie thou didst surprize; </l>
              <l>Loue was the flame that fired me so neere, </l>
              <l>The Dart transpearsing, were those Christall eyes. </l>
              <l>Strong is the net, and feruent is the flame; </l>
              <l>Deepe is the wound my sighes doe well report: </l>
              <l>Yet doe I loue, adore, and praise the same, </l>
              <l>That holds, that burnes, that wounds me in this sort. </l>
              <l>And list not seeke to breake, to quench, to heale, </l>
              <l>The bond, the flame, the wound that festreth so, </l>
              <l>By knife, by liquor, or by salue to deale: </l>
              <l>So much I please to perrish in my woe. </l>
              <l>Yet least long trauailes be aboue my strength, </l>
              <l>Good DELIA lose, quench, heale me now at length. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="15">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-010-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. XV. </head>
              <l>IF that a loyall hart and fayth vnfained, </l>
              <l>If a sweet languish with a chast desire, </l>
              <l>If hunger-staruen thoughts so long retained, </l>
              <l>Fed but with smoake, and cherisht but with fire. </l>
              <l>And if a brow with cares characters painted, </l>
              <l>Bewraies my loue, with broken words halfe spoken, </l>
              <l>To her that sits in my thoughts Temple sainted, </l>
              <l>And layes to view my Vultur-gnawne hart open. </l>
              <l>If I haue done due homage to her eyes, </l>
              <l>And had my sighes still tending on her name; </l>
              <l>If on her loue my life and honour lyes, </l>
              <l>And shee (th'vnkindest mayd) still scornes the same, </l>
              <l>Let this suffise, that all the world may see, </l>
              <l>The fault is hers, though mine the hurt must bee. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="16">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-011-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. XUI. </head>
              <l>HAppy in sleepe, waking content to languish, </l>
              <l>Imbracing clowdes by night, in day time mourne, </l>
              <l>My ioyes but shadowes, touch of truth my anguish, </l>
              <l>Griefes euer springing, comforts neuer borne. </l>
              <l>And still expecting when she will relent, </l>
              <l>Growne hoarce with crying mercy, mercy gyue; </l>
              <l>So many vowes, and prayers hauing spent, </l>
              <l>That weary of my selfe, I loathe to lyue. </l>
              <l>And yet the Hydra of my cares renewes, </l>
              <l>Still new-borne sorrowes of her fresh disdaine: </l>
              <l>And still my hope the Sommer windes pursues, </l>
              <l>Finding no end nor period of my paine. </l>
              <l>This is my state, my griefes doe touch so neerely, </l>
              <l>And thus I liue because I loue her deerely. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="17">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-011-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. XVII. </head>
              <l>WHy should I sing in verse, why should I frame, </l>
              <l>These sad neglected notes for her deere sake? </l>
              <l>Why should I offer vp vnto her name, </l>
              <l>The sweetest sacrifice my youth can make? </l>
              <l>Why should I striue to make her liue for euer, </l>
              <l>That neuer deignes to giue me ioy to liue? </l>
              <l>Why should m'afflicted Muse so much endeuour, </l>
              <l>Such honour vnto crueltie to giue? </l>
              <l>If her defects haue purchast her this fame, </l>
              <l>What should her vertues doe, her smiles, her loue? </l>
              <l>If this her worst, how should her best inflame? </l>
              <l>What passions would her milder fauours moue? </l>
              <l>Fauours (I thinke) would sence quite ouer-come, </l>
              <l>And that makes happy Louers euer dombe. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="18">
              <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000823-012-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. XVIII. </head>
              <l>SInce the first looke that led me to this error, </l>
              <l>To this thoughts-maze, to my confusion tending: </l>
              <l>Still haue I liu'd in griefe, in hope, in error, </l>
              <l>The circle of my sorrowes neuer ending. </l>
              <l>Yet cannot leaue her loue that holds me hatefull, </l>
              <l>Her eyes exact it, though her hart disdaines me; </l>
              <l>See what reward he hath that serues th' vngrateful, </l>
              <l>So true and loyall loue no fauour gaines me. </l>
              <l>Still must I whet my young desires abated, </l>
              <l>Vpon the Flint of such a hart rebelling; </l>
              <l>And all in vaine, her pride is so innated, </l>
              <l>Shee yeeldes no place at all for pittyes dwelling. </l>
              <l>Oft haue I told her that my soule did loue her, </l>
              <l>(And that with teares,) yet all this will not moue her. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="19">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-012-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. XIX. </head>
              <l>REstore thy tresses to the golden Ore, </l>
              <l>Yeeld Cithereas sonne those Arkes of loue; </l>
              <l>Bequeath the heauens the starrs that I adore, </l>
              <l>And to th' Orient doe thy Pearles remoue. </l>
              <l>Yeeld thy hands pride vnto th' Iuory white, </l>
              <l>T' Arabian odors giue thy breathing sweet: </l>
              <l>Restore thy blush vnto Aurora bright, </l>
              <l>To Thetis giue the honour of thy feete. </l>
              <l>Let Venus haue thy graces, her resign'd, </l>
              <l>And thy sweet voyce giue backe vnto the Spheares: </l>
              <l>But yet restore thy fierce and cruell minde, </l>
              <l>To Hyrcan Tygers, and to ruthles Beares. </l>
              <l>Yeeld to the Marble thy hard hart againe; </l>
              <l>So shalt thou cease to plague, and I to paine. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="20">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-013-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. XX. </head>
              <l>IF Beauty thus be clowded with a frowne, </l>
              <l>That pitty shines no comfort to my blis, </l>
              <l>And vapours of disdaine so ouer-growne, </l>
              <l>That my liues light thus wholy darkned is. </l>
              <l>Why should I more molest the world with cryes? </l>
              <l>The ayre with sighes, the earth below with teares? </l>
              <l>Sith I liue hatefull to thōse ruthlesse eyes, </l>
              <l>Vexing with vntun'd moane her dainty eares. </l>
              <l>If I haue lou'd her deerer then my breath, </l>
              <l>My breath that calls the heauens to witnes it: </l>
              <l>And still must hold her deere till after death. </l>
              <l>And if that all this cannot moue a whit, </l>
              <l>Yet let her say, that she hath done me wrong, </l>
              <l>To vse me thus, and know I lou'd so long. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="21">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-013-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. XXI. </head>
              <l>COme Death the anchor-hold of all my thoughts, </l>
              <l>My last resort whereto my soule appeales, </l>
              <l>For all too-long on earth my fancy dotes, </l>
              <l>Whilst age vpon my wasted body steales. </l>
              <l>That hart being made the prospectiue of horror, </l>
              <l>That honored hath the cruelst faire that liues, </l>
              <l>The cruelst faire, that sees I languish for her, </l>
              <l>Yet neuer mercy to my merrite giues. </l>
              <l>Thys is her Lawrell and her triumphes prize, </l>
              <l>To tread me downe with foote of her disgrace: </l>
              <l>Whilst I did build my fortune in her eyes, </l>
              <l>And layd my liues rest on so faire a face; </l>
              <l>Which rest I lost, my loue, my life and all, </l>
              <l>So high attempts to low disgraces fall. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="22">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-014-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. XXII. </head>
              <l>THese sorrowing sighes, the smoakes of mine annoy, </l>
              <l>These teares, which heate of sacred flame distils, </l>
              <l>Are those due tributes that my faith doth pay </l>
              <l>Vnto the Tyrant, vvhose vnkindnes kils. </l>
              <l>I sacrifize my youth, and blooming yeeres, </l>
              <l>At her proude feete, and she respects not it: </l>
              <l>My flowre vntimely's withred with my teares, </l>
              <l>And Winter woes, for spring of youth vnfit. </l>
              <l>Shee thinks a looke may recompence my care, </l>
              <l>And so with lookes, prolongs my long-lookt ease, </l>
              <l>As short that blisse, so is the comfort rare, </l>
              <l>Yet must that blisse my hungry thoughts appease. </l>
              <l>Thus she returnes my hopes so fruitlesse euer, </l>
              <l>Once let her loue indeed, or eye me neuer. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="23">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-014-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. XXIII. </head>
              <l>FAlse Hope prolongs my euer certaine griefe, </l>
              <l>Traytour to me, and faithfull to my Loue: </l>
              <l>A thousand times it promis'd me reliefe, </l>
              <l>Yet neuer any true effect I proue. </l>
              <l>Oft when I find in her no truth at all, </l>
              <l>I bannish her, and blame her trecherie; </l>
              <l>Yet soone againe I must her backe recall, </l>
              <l>As one that dyes without her companie. </l>
              <l>Thus often as I chase my hope from mee, </l>
              <l>Straight-way shee hastes her vnto DELIAS eyes, </l>
              <l>Fed with some pleasing looke there shall shee bee, </l>
              <l>And so sent backe, and thus my fortune lyes. </l>
              <l>Lookes feede my Hope, Hope fosters me in vaine, </l>
              <l>Hopes are vnsure, when certaine is my paine. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="24">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-015-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. XXIIII. </head>
              <l>LOoke in my griefes, and blame me not to mourne, </l>
              <l>From care to care that leades a life so bad; </l>
              <l>Th' Orphan of Fortune, borne to be her scorne, </l>
              <l>Whose clowded brow doth make my dayes so sad. </l>
              <l>Long are their nights whose cares doe neuer sleepe, </l>
              <l>Lothsome their dayes, whom no sunne euer ioyd, </l>
              <l>Her fairest eyes doe penetrate so deepe, </l>
              <l>That thus I liue both day and night annoyd. </l>
              <l>But sith the sweetest roote doth yeeld thus much, </l>
              <l>Her praise from my complaint I may not part: </l>
              <l>I loue th' effect for that the cause is such, </l>
              <l>Ile praise her face, and blame her flinty hart. </l>
              <l>Whilst that we make the world admire at vs, </l>
              <l>Her for disdaine, and me for louing thus. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="25">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-015-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. XXU. </head>
              <l>RAigne in my thoughts faire hande, sweete eye, rare voyce, </l>
              <l>Posses me whole, my harts triumvirate: </l>
              <l>Yet heauy hart to make so hard a choyse, </l>
              <l>Of such as spoile thy poore afflicted state. </l>
              <l>For whilst they striue which shall be Lord of all, </l>
              <l>All my poore life by them is troden downe: </l>
              <l>They all erect their Trophies on my fall, </l>
              <l>And yeeld me nought that giues thē their renowne, </l>
              <l>When backe I looke, I sigh my freedome past, </l>
              <l>And waile the state wherein I present stand; </l>
              <l>And see my fortune euer like to last, </l>
              <l>Finding me rain'd with such a heauie hand; </l>
              <l>What can I do but yeeld? and yeeld I doo, </l>
              <l>And serue all three, and yet they spoyle me too. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="26">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-016-a"/>
              <head>
                <hi>SONNET. XXVI</hi>. Alluding to the Sparrow pursued by a Hauke, that flew into the bosome of Zenocrates. </head>
              <l>WHilst by her eyes pursu'd, my poore hart flew it, </l>
              <l>Into the sacred bosome of my deerest: </l>
              <l>Shee there in that sweet sanctuarie slew it, </l>
              <l>Where it presum'd his safetie to be neerest. </l>
              <l>My priuiledge of faith could not protect it, </l>
              <l>That was with blood &amp; three yeres witnes signed: </l>
              <l>In all which time shee neuer could suspect it, </l>
              <l>For well shee sawe my loue, and how I pined. </l>
              <l>And yet no comfort would her brow reueale me, </l>
              <l>No lightning looke, which falling hopes erecteth; </l>
              <l>What bootes to lawes of succour to appeale mee? </l>
              <l>Ladies and Tyrants, neuer lawes respecteth. </l>
              <l>Then there I die, where hop'd I to haue liuen; </l>
              <l>And by that hand, which better might haue giuen. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="27">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-016-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. XXVII. </head>
              <l>STill in the trace of my tormented thought, </l>
              <l>My ceaselesse cars must mattch on to my death: </l>
              <l>Thy least regard too deerelie haue I bought, </l>
              <l>Who to my comfort neuer deign'st a breath. </l>
              <l>Why should'st thou stop thine cares now to my cryes, </l>
              <l>Whose eyes were open, ready to oppresse me? </l>
              <l>Why shutt'st thou not the cause whence al did rise, </l>
              <l>Or heare me now, and seeke how to redresse me? </l>
              <l>Iniurious DELIA, yet He loue thee still, </l>
              <l>Whilst that I breathe in sorrow of my smart: </l>
              <l>Ile tell the world that I deseru'd but ill, </l>
              <l>And blame my selfe for to excuse thy hart. </l>
              <l>Then iudge who sinnes the greater of vs twaine, </l>
              <l>I in my loue, or thou in thy disdaine. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="28">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-017-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. XXVIII. </head>
              <l>OFt doe I meruaile, whether DELIAS eyes, </l>
              <l>Are eyes, or els two radiant starres that shine: </l>
              <l>For how could Nature euer thus deuise, </l>
              <l>Of earth on earth a substance so diuine. </l>
              <l>Starrs sure they are, whose motions rule desires, </l>
              <l>And calme and tempest follow their aspects: </l>
              <l>Their sweet appearing still such power inspires, </l>
              <l>That makes the world admire so strange effects. </l>
              <l>Yet whether fixt or wandring starrs are they, </l>
              <l>Whose influence rule the Orbe of my poore hart? </l>
              <l>Fixt sure they are, but wandring make me stray, </l>
              <l>In endles errors, whence I cannot part. </l>
              <l>Starrs then, not eyes, moue you with milder view, </l>
              <l>Your sweet aspect on him that honours you. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="29">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-017-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. XXIX. </head>
              <l>THE starre of my mishap imposd this paine, </l>
              <l>To spend the Aprill of my yeeres in wayling, </l>
              <l>That euer found my fortune in the wayne, </l>
              <l>With still fresh cares my present woes assayling. </l>
              <l>Yet her I blame not, though for her tis done, </l>
              <l>But my desires wings so high aspyring, </l>
              <l>Which now are melted by that glorious Sunne, </l>
              <l>That makes in fall from off my hie desiring. </l>
              <l>And in my fall, I cry for helpe with speed. </l>
              <l>No pittying eye lookes backe vpon my mourning, </l>
              <l>No succour finde I now when most I need, </l>
              <l>Th' Ocean of my teares must drowne me burning. </l>
              <l>Whilst my distress shall christen her a new, </l>
              <l>And giue the <hi>Cruell Fayre </hi>this title due. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="30">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-018-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. XXX. </head>
              <l>AND yet I cannot reprehend the flight, </l>
              <l>Or blame th'attempt presuming so to sore, </l>
              <l>The mounting venter for a high delight, </l>
              <l>Did make the honour of the fall the more. </l>
              <l>For who gets wealth that puts not from the shore? </l>
              <l>Daunger hath honour, great designes their fame, </l>
              <l>Glorie doth follow courage goes before. </l>
              <l>And though th'euent oft aunswers not the same, </l>
              <l>Suffise that high attempts haue neuer shame. </l>
              <l>The Meane-obseruer, (whom base Safety keepes,) </l>
              <l>Liues without honour, dies without a name, </l>
              <l>And in eternall darknes euer sleepes. </l>
              <l>And therefore DELIA, tis to me no blot, </l>
              <l>To haue attempted, though attain'd thee not. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="31">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-018-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. XXXI. </head>
              <l>RAysing my hopes on hills of high desire, </l>
              <l>Thinking to scale the heauen of her hart, </l>
              <l>My slender meanes presum'd too high a part; </l>
              <l>Her thunder of disdaine forst me retyre, </l>
              <l>And threw mee downe to paine in all this fire, </l>
              <l>Where loe I languish in so heauie smart, </l>
              <l>Because th'attempt was farre aboue my arte: </l>
              <l>Her pride brook'd not poore soules should come so nie her. </l>
              <l>Yet I protest my high aspyring will, </l>
              <l>Was not to dispossesse her of her right: </l>
              <l>Her soueraignty should haue remained still, </l>
              <l>I onely sought the blisse to haue her sight. </l>
              <l>Her sight contented thus to see mee spill, </l>
              <l>Fram'd my desires fit for her eyes to kill. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="32">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-019-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. XXXII. </head>
              <l>O Why doth DELIA credite so her glasse, </l>
              <l>Gazing her beautie deign'd her by the skyes; </l>
              <l>And doth not rather looke on him (alas) whose state best shewes the force of murthering eyes </l>
              <l>The broken tops of loftie trees declare, </l>
              <l>The furie of a mercy-wanting storme: </l>
              <l>And of what force your wounding glances are, </l>
              <l>Vpon my selfe you best may find the forme. </l>
              <l>Then leaue your glasse, and gaze your selfe on mee, </l>
              <l>That Mirror shewes what power is in your face: </l>
              <l>To view your forme too much, may daunger bee, </l>
              <l>Narcissus chang'd t'a flower in such a case. </l>
              <l>And you are chang'd, but not t'a Hiacint; </l>
              <l>I feare your eye hath turn'd your hart to flint. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="33">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-019-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. XXXIII. </head>
              <l>I Once may see when yeres shall wreck my wrong, </l>
              <l>When golden hayres shall change to siluer wier: </l>
              <l>And those bright rayes that kindle all this fire, </l>
              <l>Shall faile in force, their working not so strong. </l>
              <l>Then beautie, (now the burthen of my song,) </l>
              <l>Whose glorious blaze the world doth so admire, </l>
              <l>Must yeeld vp all to tyrant Times desire; </l>
              <l>Thē fade those flowers that deckt her pride so long. </l>
              <l>When, if shee grieue to gaze her in the glasse, </l>
              <l>Which then presents her winter-withered hew, </l>
              <l>Goe you my verse, goe tell her what she was; </l>
              <l>For what shee was shee best shall finde in you. </l>
              <l>Your fierie heate lets not her glorie passe, </l>
              <l>But (Phenix-like) shall make her liue anew. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="34">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-020-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. XXXIIII. </head>
              <l>LOoke Delia how we steeme the half blowne Rose, </l>
              <l>The image of thy blush, and Sommers honour: </l>
              <l>Whilst in her tender greene shee doth inclose, </l>
              <l>The pure sweet beauty Time bestowes vpon her. </l>
              <l>No sooner spreades her glory in the ayre, </l>
              <l>But straight her ful-blowne pride is in declining; </l>
              <l>Shee then is scorn'd that late adorn'd the fayre: </l>
              <l>So clowdes thy beauty after fairest shining. </l>
              <l>No Aprill can reuiue thy withred flowers, </l>
              <l>Whose blooming grace adornes thy glory now: </l>
              <l>Swift speedy Time, feathred with flying howers, </l>
              <l>Dissolues the beautie of the fairest brow. </l>
              <l>O let not then such riches waste in vaine, </l>
              <l>But loue whilst that thou maist be lou'd againe. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="35">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-020-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. XXXV. </head>
              <l>BVT loue whilst that thou maist be lou'd againe. </l>
              <l>Now whilst thy May hath fill'd thy lap with flowers, </l>
              <l>Now whilst thy beauty beares without a staine; </l>
              <l>Now vse thy Sommer smiles, ere Winter lowers. </l>
              <l>And whilst thou spread'st vnto the rysing sunne, </l>
              <l>The fairest flowre that euer saw the light, </l>
              <l>Now ioy thy time before thy sweet be done, </l>
              <l>And (Delia,) thinke thy morning must haue night. </l>
              <l>And that thy brightnes sets at length to West, </l>
              <l>When thou wilt close vp that which now thou showest, </l>
              <l>And thinke the same becomes thy fading best, </l>
              <l>Which then shall hide it most, and couer lowest. </l>
              <l>Men doe not wey the stalke for that it was, </l>
              <l>When once they find her flowre her glory passe. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="36">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-021-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. XXXVI. </head>
              <l>WHen men shall finde thy flower, thy glory passe, </l>
              <l>And thou with carefull brow sitting alone: </l>
              <l>Receiued hast this message from thy glasse, </l>
              <l>That tells the truth, and saies that all is gone; </l>
              <l>Fresh shalt thou see in mee the wounds thou madest, </l>
              <l>Though spent thy flame, in me the heat remaining, </l>
              <l>I that haue lou'd thee thus before thou fadest, </l>
              <l>My faith shall waxe, when thou art in thy waining. </l>
              <l>The world shall finde this myracle in mee, </l>
              <l>That fire can burne when all the matter's spent: </l>
              <l>Then what my faith hath beene thy selfe shalt see, </l>
              <l>And that thou wast vnkind, thou maist repent. </l>
              <l>Thou maist repent that thou hast scorn'd my teares, </l>
              <l>When winter snowes vpon thy golden haires. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="37">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-021-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. XXXVII. </head>
              <l>WHen VVinter snowes vpon thy golden haires, </l>
              <l>And frost of age hath nipt thy flowers neere, </l>
              <l>VVhen dark shal seeme thy day that neuer cleeres, </l>
              <l>And all lies withred that was held so deere. </l>
              <l>Then take this picture which I heere present thee, </l>
              <l>Limned with a Pensill not all vnworthy: </l>
              <l>Heere see the gifts that God and nature lent thee, </l>
              <l>Heare reade thy selfe, and what I suffred for thee. </l>
              <l>This may remaine thy lasting monument, </l>
              <l>Which happily posteritie may cherrish, </l>
              <l>These colours with thy fading are not spent, </l>
              <l>These may remaine when thou and I shall perrish. </l>
              <l>If they remaine, then thou shalt liue thereby. </l>
              <l>They will remaine, and so thou canst not die. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="38">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-022-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. XXXVIII. </head>
              <l>THou canst not die whilst any zeale abound </l>
              <l>In feeling harts, that can conceiue these lynes; </l>
              <l>Though thou a Laura hast no Petrarch found, </l>
              <l>In base attyre, yet cleerely Beauty shines. </l>
              <l>And I (though borne within a colder clime,) </l>
              <l>Doe feele mine inward heate as great, (I know it,) </l>
              <l>Hee neuer had more faith, although more rime, </l>
              <l>I loue as well, though he could better show it. </l>
              <l>But I may add one feather to thy fame, </l>
              <l>To helpe her flight throughout the fairest Ile. </l>
              <l>And if my pen could more enlarge thy name, </l>
              <l>Then shouldst thou liue in an immortall stile. </l>
              <l>For though that Laura better limned bee, </l>
              <l>Suffise, thou shalt be lou'd as well as shee. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="39">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-022-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. XXXIX. </head>
              <l>O Be not grieu'd that these my papers should </l>
              <l>Bewray vnto the world how faire thou art: </l>
              <l>Or that my wits haue shewed the best they could. </l>
              <l>(The chastest flame that euer warmed hart.) </l>
              <l>Thinke not (sweet DELIA,) this shall be thy shame, </l>
              <l>My Muse should sound thy praise with mournefull warble, </l>
              <l>How many liue, the glory of whose name, </l>
              <l>Shall rest in Ise, when thine is grau'd in Marble. </l>
              <l>Thou maist in after ages liue esteem'd, </l>
              <l>Vnburied in these lines reseru'd in purenes; </l>
              <l>These shall intombe those eyes, that haue redeem'd </l>
              <l>Mee from the vulgar, thee from all obscurenes. </l>
              <l>Although my carefull accents neuer moou'd thee, </l>
              <l>Yet count it no disgrace that I haue lou'd thee. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="40">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-023-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. XL. </head>
              <l>DELIA, these eyes that so admireth thine, </l>
              <l>Haue seene those walls the which ambition reared, </l>
              <l>To check the world, how they intombd haue lyen. </l>
              <l>Within thēselues; &amp; on them ploughes haue eared. </l>
              <l>Yet found I that no barbarous hand attaind. </l>
              <l>The spoyle of same deseru'd by vertuous men: </l>
              <l>VVhose glorious actions luckily had gaind, </l>
              <l>Th'eternall Annals of a happy pen. </l>
              <l>Why thē though DELIA fade, let that not moue her, </l>
              <l>Though time doe spoile her of the fairest vaile </l>
              <l>That euer yet mortalitie did couer; </l>
              <l>Which must instarre the needle and the Raile. </l>
              <l>That grace, that vertue, all that seru'd t'in-woman, </l>
              <l>Dooth thee vnto eternitie assommon. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="41">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-023-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. XLI. </head>
              <l>FAyre and louely mayde, looke from the shore, </l>
              <l>See thy Leander striuing in these waues: </l>
              <l>Poore soule quite spent, whose force can do no more, </l>
              <l>Now send forth hopes, for now calme pitty saues. </l>
              <l>And waft him to thee with those louely eyes, </l>
              <l>A happy conuoy to a holy Land: </l>
              <l>Now shewe thy power, and where thy vertue lyes, </l>
              <l>To saue thine owne, stretch out the fairest hand. </l>
              <l>Stretch out the fairest hand, a pledge of peace; </l>
              <l>That hand that darts so right and neuer misses: </l>
              <l>I shall forget old wrongs, my griefes shall cease; </l>
              <l>And that which gaue me wounds, Ile giue it kisses. </l>
              <l>O then let th'Ocean of my care find shore, </l>
              <l>That thou be pleas'd, and I may sigh no more. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="42">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-024-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. XLII. </head>
              <l>REade in my face a volume of dispayres, </l>
              <l>The wailing Iliads of my tragicke woe; </l>
              <l>Drawne with my blood, &amp; printed with my cares, </l>
              <l>VVrought by her hand that I haue honour'd so. </l>
              <l>VVho whilst I burne, shee sings at my soules wrack, </l>
              <l>Looking aloft from Turret of her pride: </l>
              <l>There my soules Tyrant ioyes her, in the sack </l>
              <l>Of her owne seate, whereof I made her guide. </l>
              <l>There doe these smoakes that from affliction rise, </l>
              <l>Serue as an incense to a cruell Dame; </l>
              <l>A sacrifice thrice-gratefull to her eyes, </l>
              <l>Because their powre serue to exact the same. </l>
              <l>Thus ruines shee (to satisfie her will,) </l>
              <l>The Temple, where her name was honour'd still. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="43">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-024-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. XLIII. </head>
              <l>MY DELIA hath the waters of mine eyes, </l>
              <l>The ready handmaids on her grace attending: </l>
              <l>That neuer fall to ebb, but euer rise, </l>
              <l>For to their flow shee neuer grants an ending. </l>
              <l>Th'Ocean neuer did attend more dulie </l>
              <l>Vpon his soueraignes course, the nights pale Queen, </l>
              <l>Nor paid the impost of his waues more truely, </l>
              <l>Then mine vnto her Deitie haue been. </l>
              <l>Yet nought the rock of that hard hart can moue, </l>
              <l>Where beate these teares with zeale, &amp; fury driueth, </l>
              <l>And yet I rather languish in her loue, </l>
              <l>Then I would ioy the fairest shee that liueth. </l>
              <l>I doubt to finde such pleasure in my gayning, </l>
              <l>As now I taste, in compasse of complayning. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="44">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-025-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. XLIIII. </head>
              <l>HOwe long shall I in mine affliction mourne? </l>
              <l>A burthen to my selfe, distrest in mind, </l>
              <l>VVhen shall my interdicted hopes returne, </l>
              <l>From out dispaire wherein they liue confin'd. </l>
              <l>VVhen shall her troubled brow, charg'd with disdaine, </l>
              <l>Reueale the treasure which her smyles impart: </l>
              <l>VVhen shall my faith the happines attaine, </l>
              <l>To breake the Ise that hath congeald her hart. </l>
              <l>Vnto herselfe, herselfe my loue doth sommon, </l>
              <l>(If loue in her hath any power to moue,) </l>
              <l>And let her tell me as shee is a woman, </l>
              <l>VVhether my faith hath not deseru'd her loue. </l>
              <l>I know shee cannot but must needs confesse it, </l>
              <l>Yet deignes not with one simple signe t'expresse it. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="45">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-025-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. XLV. </head>
              <l>BEautie (sweet Loue,) is like the morning dewe, </l>
              <l>VVhose short refresh vpon the tender greene: </l>
              <l>Cheeres for a time but till the Sunne doth shew, </l>
              <l>And straight tis gone as it had neuer beene. </l>
              <l>Soone doth it fade that makes the fairest florish, </l>
              <l>Short is the glory of the blushing Rose: </l>
              <l>The hewe which thou so carefully dost nourish, </l>
              <l>Yet which at length thou must be forc'd to lose. </l>
              <l>VVhen thou surcharg'd with burthen of thy yeeres, </l>
              <l>Shalt bend thy wrinkles homeward to the earth, </l>
              <l>VVhen time hath made a pasport for thy seares, </l>
              <l>Dated in age the Kalends of our death. </l>
              <l>But ah no more, this hath beene often tolde, </l>
              <l>And women grieue to thinke they must be olde. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="46">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-026-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. XLVI. </head>
              <l>I Must not grieue my Loue, whose eyes would reede </l>
              <l>Lynes of delight, whereon her youth might smyle; </l>
              <l>Flowers haue a tyme before they come to seed, </l>
              <l>And shee is young, and now must sport the while. </l>
              <l>Ah sport (sweet Maid) in season of these yeeres, </l>
              <l>And learne togather flowers before they wither: </l>
              <l>And where the sweetest blossoms first appeares, </l>
              <l>Let loue and youth conduct thy pleasures thither. </l>
              <l>Lighten forth smyles to cleere the clowded ayre, </l>
              <l>And calme the tempest which my sighes do rayse, </l>
              <l>Pittie and smiles doe best become the faire, </l>
              <l>Pittie and smiles shall yeeld thee lasting praise. </l>
              <l>I hope to say, when all my griefes are gone, </l>
              <l>Happie the hart that sigh'd for such a one. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="47">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-026-b"/>
              <head>
                <hi>SONNET. XLVII</hi>. At the Authors going into Italie. </head>
              <l>O Whether (poore forsaken) wilt thou goe, </l>
              <l>To goe from sorrow, and thine owne distresse, </l>
              <l>When euery place presents like face of woe, </l>
              <l>And no remoue can make thy sorrowes lesse? </l>
              <l>Yet goe (forsaken,) leaue these woods, these playnes, </l>
              <l>Leaue her and all, and all for her that leaues </l>
              <l>Thee and thy loue forlorne, and both disdaines; </l>
              <l>And of both, wrongfull deemes, and ill conceaues. </l>
              <l>Seeke out some place, and see if any place </l>
              <l>Can giue the least release vnto thy griefe: </l>
              <l>Conuay thee from the thought of thy disgrace, </l>
              <l>Steale from thy selfe, and be thy cares own thiefe. </l>
              <l>But yet what comfort shall I heereby gaine? </l>
              <l>Bearing the wonnd, I needs must feele the paine. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="48">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-027-a"/>
              <head>
                <hi>SONNET. XLVIII</hi>. This Sonnet was made at the Authors beeing in Italie. </head>
              <l>DRawne with th'th'attractiue vertue of her eyes, </l>
              <l>My toucht hart turnes it to that happie cost: </l>
              <l>My ioyfull North, where all my fortune lyes, </l>
              <l>The leuell of my hopes desired most. </l>
              <l>There where my DAELIA, fairer then the Sunne, </l>
              <l>Deckt with her youth wheron the world doth smile, </l>
              <l>Ioyes in that honour which her eyes haue wonne, </l>
              <l>Th'eternall wonder of our happy Ile. </l>
              <l>Florish faire ALBION, glorie of the North, </l>
              <l>Neptunes best darling, held betweene his armes: </l>
              <l>Deuided from the world as better worth, </l>
              <l>Kept for himselfe, defended from all harmes. </l>
              <l>Still let disarmed peace decke her and thee: </l>
              <l>And Muse-foe Mars, abroad farre fostred bee. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="49">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-027-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. XLIX. </head>
              <l>CAre-charmer Sleepe, sonne of the sable Night, </l>
              <l>Brother to death, in silent darknes borne: </l>
              <l>Relieue my languish, and restore the light, </l>
              <l>With darke forgetting of my cares returne. </l>
              <l>And let the day be time enough to mourne, </l>
              <l>The shipwrack of my ill aduentred youth: </l>
              <l>Let waking eyes suffise to waile their scorne, </l>
              <l>Without the torment of the nights vntruth. </l>
              <l>Cease dreames, th'imaginary of our day desires, </l>
              <l>To modell forth the passions of the morrow, </l>
              <l>Neuer let rysing Sunne approue you lyers, </l>
              <l>To adde more griefe to agrauate my sorrow. </l>
              <l>Still let mee sleepe, imbracing clowdes in vaine, </l>
              <l>And neuer wake to seele the dayes disdaine. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="50">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-028-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. L. </head>
              <l>LET others sing of Knights and Palladines, </l>
              <l>In aged accents, and vntimely words, </l>
              <l>Paint shadowes in imaginarie lines, </l>
              <l>Which wel the reach of their high wits records; </l>
              <l>But I must sing of thee, and those faire eyes. </l>
              <l>Autentique shall my verse in time to come, </l>
              <l>When yet th'vnborne shal say, Loe where she lyes, </l>
              <l>Whose beauty made him speak that els was dombe. </l>
              <l>These are the Arkes the Trophies I erect, </l>
              <l>That fortifie thy name against old age: </l>
              <l>And these thy sacred vertues must protect, </l>
              <l>Against the darke and Times consuming rage. </l>
              <l>Though th'error of my youth they shall discouer, </l>
              <l>Suffise, they shew I liu'd, and was thy louer. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="51">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-028-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. LI. </head>
              <l>AS to the Roman that would free his Land, </l>
              <l>His error was his honour and renowne: </l>
              <l>And more the fame of his mistaking hand, </l>
              <l>Then if he had the Tyrant ouer-throwne. </l>
              <l>So DELIA hath mine errour made me knowne. </l>
              <l>And my deceiu'd attempt, deseru'd more fame, </l>
              <l>Then if I had the victory mine owne: </l>
              <l>And thy hard hart had yeelded vp the same. </l>
              <l>And so likewise, renowmed is thy blame, </l>
              <l>Thy crueltie, thy glorie; ô strange case, </l>
              <l>That errours should be grac'd that merrite shame, </l>
              <l>And sinne of frownes bring honor to the face. </l>
              <l>Yet happy DELIA that thou wast vnkind, </l>
              <l>But happier yet, if thou wouldst change thy minde. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="52">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-029-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. LII. </head>
              <l>LIke as the Lute, that ioyes or els dislikes, </l>
              <l>As is his arte that playes vpon the same, </l>
              <l>So sounds my Muse, according as shee strikes </l>
              <l>On my hart strings, high tun'd vnto her fame. </l>
              <l>Her touch doth cause the warble of the sound, </l>
              <l>Which heere I yeeld in lamentable wise, </l>
              <l>A wailing deskant on the sweetest ground, </l>
              <l>VVhose due reports giue honour to her eyes. </l>
              <l>Els harshe my stile, vntunable my Muse, </l>
              <l>Hoarce sounds the voyce that praiseth not her name, </l>
              <l>If any pleasing relish heere I vse, </l>
              <l>Then iudge the world her beauty giues the same. </l>
              <l>Ō happy ground that makes the musique such, </l>
              <l>And blessed hand that giues so sweet a touch, </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="53">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-029-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. LIII. </head>
              <l>NOne other fame myne vnambitious Muse, </l>
              <l>Affected euer, but t'eternize thee: </l>
              <l>All other honours doe my hopes refuse, </l>
              <l>Which meaner priz'd and momentarie be. </l>
              <l>For God forbid I should my papers blot, </l>
              <l>VVith mercynarie lines, with seruile pen: </l>
              <l>Praysing vertues in them that haue them not, </l>
              <l>Basely attending on the hopes of men. </l>
              <l>No no, my verse respects nor Thames nor Theaters, </l>
              <l>Nor seekes it to be knowne vnto the great, </l>
              <l>But Auon poore in fame, and poore in waters, </l>
              <l>Shall haue my song where DELIA hath her seate. </l>
              <l>Auon shall be my Thames, and shee my song, </l>
              <l>Ile sound her name the Riuer all along. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="54">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-030-a"/>
              <head>SONNET. LIIII. </head>
              <l>VNhappy pen, and ill accepted papers, </l>
              <l>That intimate in vaine my chast desires: </l>
              <l>My chast desires, (the euer-burning Tapers,) </l>
              <l>Inkindled by her eyes celestiall fires. </l>
              <l>Celestiall fires, and vnrespecting powers, </l>
              <l>That deigne not viewe, the glory of your might: </l>
              <l>In humble lines the worke of carefull howres, </l>
              <l>The sacrifice I offer to her sight. </l>
              <l>But sith shee scornes her owne, this rests for mee, </l>
              <l>Ile mone my selfe, and hide the wrong I haue, </l>
              <l>And so content mee that her frownes should be </l>
              <l>To m'infant stile the cradle and the graue. </l>
              <l>What though my selfe no honour get thereby, </l>
              <l>Each byrd sings to her selfe, and so will I. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="55">
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-030-b"/>
              <head>SONNET. LU. </head>
              <l>LOE heere the impost of a faith vnfayning, </l>
              <l>That loue hath paid, and her disdaine extorted: </l>
              <l>Behold the message of my iust complaining, </l>
              <l>That shewes the world how much my griefe imported. </l>
              <l>These tributarie plaints fraught with desire, </l>
              <l>I send those eyes, the cabinets of loue; </l>
              <l>The Paradice whereto my hopes aspire, </l>
              <l>From out this hell, which mine afflictions proue. </l>
              <l>Wherein I thus doe liue, cast downe from myrth, </l>
              <l>Pensiue alone, none but dispaire about mee, </l>
              <l>My ioyes abortiue, perrisht at their birth, </l>
              <l>My cares long liu'd, and will not die without mee. </l>
              <l>This is my state, and DELIAS hart is such; </l>
              <l>I say no more, I feare I said too much. </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
          </div>
        </body>
        <back>
          <div type="ode" xml:id="ep000823-e9550">
            <pb xml:id="ep000823-031-a"/>
            <head>An Ode. </head>
            <lg>
              <l>NOW each creature ioyes the other, passing happy dayes and houres, </l>
              <l>One byrd reports vnto an other, in the fall of siluer showers, </l>
              <l>Whilst the earth (our common mother,) hath her bosome deckt with flowers. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Whilst the greatest Torche of heauen, with bright rayes warmes FLORAS lap, </l>
              <l>Making nights and dayes both euen, cheering plants with fresher sap: </l>
              <l>My field of flowers quite bereauen, wants refresh of better hap. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>ECCHO, daughter of the Ayre, (babbling guest of Rocks and Hills,) </l>
              <l>Knowes the name of my fierce Fatre, And sounds the accents of my ills. </l>
              <l>Each thing pitties my dispaire, whilst that shee her Louer kills. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Whilst that shee (O cruell Mayd,) doth mee and my loue dispise, </l>
              <l>My liues florish is decayd, that depended on her eyes: </l>
              <l>But her will must be obeyd, and well he ends for loue who dies. </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
          </div>
        </back>
      </text>
      <text>
        <front>
          <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000823-e9780">
            <pb xml:id="ep000823-031-b"/>
            <p>THE Complaynt of ROSAMOND. </p>
          </div>
        </front>
        <body>
          <div type="complaint" xml:id="ep000823-e9810">
            <pb xml:id="ep000823-032-a"/>
            <pb xml:id="ep000823-032-b"/>
            <head>THE COMPLAINT <hi>OF ROSAMOND</hi>. </head>
            <lg>
              <l>OVT from the horror of Infernall deepes, </l>
              <l>My poore afflicted ghost comes heere to plaine it, </l>
              <l>Attended with my shame that neuer sleepes, </l>
              <l>The spot wher-with my kinde and youth did staine it. </l>
              <l>My body found a graue where to containe it. </l>
              <l>A sheete could hide my face, but not my sin, </l>
              <l>For Fame findes neuer tombe t'inclose it in. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And which is worse, my soule is now denied, </l>
              <l>Her transport to the sweet Elisian rest, </l>
              <l>The ioyfull blisse for ghostes repurified, </l>
              <l>Th' euer-springing Gardens of the blest, </l>
              <l>Caron denies mee wastage with the rest. </l>
              <l>And sayes, my soule can neuer passe the Riuer, </l>
              <l>Till Louers sighes on earth shall it deliuer. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>So shall I neuer passe; for how should I </l>
              <l>Procure this sacrifice amongst the liuing? </l>
              <l>Time hath long since worne out the memorie, </l>
              <l>Both of my life, and liues vniust depriuing, </l>
              <l>Sorrow for mee is dead for aye reuiuing. </l>
              <l>ROSAMOND hath little left her but her name, </l>
              <l>And that disgrac'd, for time hath wrong'd the same. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-033-a"/>
              <l>No Muse suggests the pittie of my case, </l>
              <l>Each penne doth ouer-passe my iust complaint, </l>
              <l>VVhilst others are preferd, though farre more base; </l>
              <l>Shores wife is grac'd, and passes for a Saint; </l>
              <l>Her Legend iustifies her foule attaint. </l>
              <l>Her wel-told tale did such compassion finde, </l>
              <l>That shee is pass'd, and I am left behind. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>VVhich seene with griefe, my miserable ghost, </l>
              <l>(VVhilome inuested in so faire a vaile, </l>
              <l>VVhich whilst it liu'd, was honoured of the most, </l>
              <l>And being dead, giues matter to bewaile.) </l>
              <l>Comes to sollicite thee, (since others faile,) </l>
              <l>To take this taske, and in thy wofull song </l>
              <l>To forme my case, and register my wrong. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Although I know thy iust lamenting Muse, </l>
              <l>Toyld in th'affliction of thine owne distresse, </l>
              <l>In others cares hath little time to vse, </l>
              <l>And therefore maist esteeme of mine the lesse: </l>
              <l>Yet as thy hopes attend happy redresse, </l>
              <l>Thy ioyes depending on a womans grace, </l>
              <l>So mooue thy minde a wofull womans case. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-033-b"/>
              <l>DELIA may hap to deigne to reade our story, </l>
              <l>And offer vp her sigh among the rest, </l>
              <l>VVhose merrite would suffise for both our glory, </l>
              <l>VVhereby thou might'st be grac'd, and I be blest; </l>
              <l>That indulgence would profit me the best. </l>
              <l>Such power shee hath by whom thy youth is led, </l>
              <l>To ioy the liuing, and to blesse the dead. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>So I (through beauty) made the wofull'st wight, </l>
              <l>By beauty might haue comfort after death: </l>
              <l>That dying fayrest, by the fairest might </l>
              <l>Find life aboue on earth, and rest beneath. </l>
              <l>Shee that can blesse vs with one happy breath. </l>
              <l>Giue comfort to thy Muse to doe her best, </l>
              <l>That thereby thou maist ioy, and I might rest. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Thus said: forth-with mou'd with a tender care, </l>
              <l>And pittie, (which my selfe could neuer finde,) </l>
              <l>VVhat shee desir'd, my Muse deign'd to declare, </l>
              <l>And therefore, will'd her boldly tell her mind. </l>
              <l>And I (more willing,) tooke this charge assignd, </l>
              <l>Because her griefes were worthy to be knowne, </l>
              <l>And telling hers might hap forget mine owne. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-034-a"/>
              <l>Then write (quoth shee) the ruine of my youth, </l>
              <l>Report the downe-fall of my slippry state, </l>
              <l>Of all my life reueale the simple truth, </l>
              <l>To teach to others what I learnt too late. </l>
              <l>Exemplifie my frailtie, tell how Fate </l>
              <l>Keepes in eternall darke our fortunes hidden, </l>
              <l>And ere they come, to know them tis forbidden. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>For whilst the sun-shine of my fortune lasted, </l>
              <l>I ioy'd the happiest warmth, the sweetest heate </l>
              <l>That euer yet imperious beautie tasted, </l>
              <l>I had what glorie euer flesh could get: </l>
              <l>But this faire morning had a shamefull set. </l>
              <l>Disgrace darkt honour, sinne did clowd my brow, </l>
              <l>As note the sequel, and Ile tell thee how. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>The blood I staind, was good and of the best, </l>
              <l>My birth had honour, and my beautie fame: </l>
              <l>Nature and Fortune ioyn'd to make me blest, </l>
              <l>Had I had grace t'haue knowne to vse the same. </l>
              <l>My education shew'd from whence I came, </l>
              <l>And all concurd to make me happy furst, </l>
              <l>That so great hap might make me more accurst. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-034-b"/>
              <l>Happie liu'd I, whilst Parents eye did guide, </l>
              <l>The indiscretion of my feeble waies, </l>
              <l>And Country home kept mee from being eyde, </l>
              <l>Where best vnknowne I spent my sweetest dayes; </l>
              <l>Till that my friends mine honour sought to raise, </l>
              <l>To higher place, which greater credite yeelds, </l>
              <l>Deeming such beauty was vnfit for seeldes. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>From Country then to Court I was preferr'd, </l>
              <l>From calme to stormes, from shore into the deepes: </l>
              <l>There where I perrish'd, where my youth first err'd, </l>
              <l>There where I lost the flowre which honour keepes; </l>
              <l>There where the worser thriues, the better weepes; </l>
              <l>Ah mee (poore wench,) on this vnhappy shelfe, </l>
              <l>I grounded me, and cast away my selfe. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>For thither com'd, when yeeres had arm'd my youth, </l>
              <l>With rarest proofe of beautie euer seene: </l>
              <l>When my reuiuing eye had learnt the truth, </l>
              <l>That it had power to make the winter greene, </l>
              <l>And flowre affections whereas none had beene; </l>
              <l>Soone could I teach my brow to tyrannize, </l>
              <l>And make the world doe homage to mine eyes. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-035-a"/>
              <l>For age I saw, (though yeeres with cold conceit, </l>
              <l>Congeald their thoughts against a warme desire,) </l>
              <l>Yet sigh their want, and looke at such a baite. </l>
              <l>I saw how youth was waxe before the fire. </l>
              <l>I saw by stealth, I fram'd my looke a lyre. </l>
              <l>Yet well perceiu'd, how Fortune made me then </l>
              <l>The enuie of my sexe, and wonder vnto men. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Looke how a Comet at the first appearing. </l>
              <l>Drawes all mens eyes with wonder to behold it; </l>
              <l>Or as the faddest tale at suddaine hearing, </l>
              <l>Makes silent lishring vnto him that told it, </l>
              <l>So did my speech when Rubies did vnfold it. </l>
              <l>So did the blazing of my blush appeare, </l>
              <l>T'amaze the world, that holds such sights so deer. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Ah beauty Syred, faire enchaunting good, </l>
              <l>Sweet silent rethorique of perswading eyes: </l>
              <l>Dombe eloquēce, whose power doth moue the blood, </l>
              <l>More then the words, or wisedome of the wise; </l>
              <l>Still harmonie, whose diapason lies </l>
              <l>Within a brow, the key which passions moue, </l>
              <l>To rauish sence, and play a world in loue. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-035-b"/>
              <l>VVhat might I then not doe whose power was such? </l>
              <l>What cannot women doe that know their powre? </l>
              <l>VVhat women knowes it not (I feare too much) </l>
              <l>How blisse or bale lyes in their laugh or lowre? </l>
              <l>Whilst they enioy their happy blooming flowre, </l>
              <l>Whilst nature decks her her proper faire </l>
              <l>Which cheeres the world, ioyes each sight, sweetens th'ayre. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Such one was I, my beauty was mine owne, </l>
              <l>No borrowed blush which banck-rot beauties seeke: </l>
              <l>That new-found shame, a sinne to vs vnknowne, </l>
              <l>Th'adulterate beauty of a falsed cheeke: </l>
              <l>Vilde staine to honour, and to women eeke, </l>
              <l>Seeing that time our fading must detect, </l>
              <l>Thus with defect to couer our defect. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Impietie of times, chastitles abator, </l>
              <l>Falshood, wherein thy selfe thy selfe deniest: </l>
              <l>Treason, to counterfeit the seale of Nature, </l>
              <l>The stampe of heauen, impressed by the hiest. </l>
              <l>Disgrace vnto the world, to whom thou lyest. </l>
              <l>Idoll vnto thy selfe, shame to the wise, </l>
              <l>And all that honour thee idolatrise. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-036-a"/>
              <l>Farre was that sinne from vs whose age was pure, </l>
              <l>VVhen simple beauty was accounted best, </l>
              <l>The time when women had no other lure </l>
              <l>But modestie, pure cheekes, a vertuous brest. </l>
              <l>Thys was the pompe wher-with my youth was blest. </l>
              <l>These were the weapons which mine honor wun </l>
              <l>In all the conflicts which mine eyes begun. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>VVhich were not smal, I wrought on no meane obiect, </l>
              <l>A Crowne was at my feete, Scepters obeyde mee, </l>
              <l>Whō Fortune made my King, Loue made my subiect, </l>
              <l>Who did cōmaund the land, most humbly praid mee, </l>
              <l>HENRY the second, that so highly weigh'd mee, </l>
              <l>Found well (by proofe) the priuiledge of Beauty, </l>
              <l>That it had powre to counter-maund all duty. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>For after all his victories in FRAVNCE, </l>
              <l>Tryumphing in the honour of his deedes: </l>
              <l>Vnmatch'd by sword, was vanquisht by a glaunce, </l>
              <l>And hotter warrs within his bosome breedes. </l>
              <l>VVarrs, whom whole Legions of desires feedes. </l>
              <l>Against all which, my chastitie opposes </l>
              <l>The field of honour, vertue neuer loses. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-036-b"/>
              <l>No armour might be found that could defend, </l>
              <l>Transpearcing rayes of Christall poynted eyes: </l>
              <l>No stratagem, no reason could amend, </l>
              <l>No not his age; (yet old men should be wise.) </l>
              <l>But shewes deceiue, outward appearance lies. </l>
              <l>Let none for seeming so, thinke Saints of others, </l>
              <l>For all are men, and all haue suckt their mothers. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Who wold haue thought a Monarch would haue euer </l>
              <l>Obeyd his hand-mayde of so meane estate; </l>
              <l>Vultur ambition feeding on his lyuer, </l>
              <l>Age hauing worne his pleasures out of date, </l>
              <l>But hap comes neuer, or it comes too late. </l>
              <l>For such a dainty which his youth found not, </l>
              <l>Vnto his feeble age did chaunce a-lot. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Ah Fortune, neuer absolutely good, </l>
              <l>For that some crosse still counter-checks our luck; </l>
              <l>As heere behold th'incompatible blood, </l>
              <l>Of age and youth was that whereon we stuck: </l>
              <l>VVhose lothing, we from natures brests doe suck, </l>
              <l>As opposite to what our blood requires. </l>
              <l>For equall age, doth equall like desires. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-037-a"/>
              <l>But mighty men, in highest honour sitting, </l>
              <l>Nought but applause and pleasure can behold: </l>
              <l>Sooth'd in their liking, carelesse what is fitting, </l>
              <l>May not be suffred once to thinke the'are old: </l>
              <l>Not trusting what they see, but what is told. </l>
              <l>Miserable fortune to forget so farre, </l>
              <l>The state of flesh, and what our frailties are. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Yet must I needes excuse so great defect, </l>
              <l>For drinking of the Lethe of mine eyes, </l>
              <l>H'is forc'd forget himselfe, and all respect </l>
              <l>Of maiestie, whereon his state relies: </l>
              <l>And now of loues, and pleasures must deuise. </l>
              <l>For thus reuiu'd againe, he serues and su'th, </l>
              <l>And seekes all meanes to vndermine my youth. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Which neuer by assault he could recouer, </l>
              <l>So well incamp'd in strength of chaste desires: </l>
              <l>My cleane-arm'd thoughts repell'd an vnchast louer. </l>
              <l>The Crowne that could commaund what it requires, </l>
              <l>I lesser priz'd then chastities attires. </l>
              <l>Th'vnstained vaile, which innocents adorns, </l>
              <l>Th'vngathred Rose, defended with the thornes. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-037-b"/>
              <l>And safe mine honour stood, till that in truth, </l>
              <l>One of my sexe, of place, and nature bad, </l>
              <l>VVas set in ambush to intrap my youth. </l>
              <l>One in the habite of like frailty clad. </l>
              <l>One who the liu'ry of like weakenes had. </l>
              <l>A seeming Matron, yet a sinfull Monster, </l>
              <l>As by her words the chaster sort may conster. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Shee set vpon mee with the smoothest speech </l>
              <l>That Court and age could cunningly deuise: </l>
              <l>Th'one autentique, made her fit to teach, </l>
              <l>The other learnt her how to subtelise. </l>
              <l>Both were enough to circumuent the vvise. </l>
              <l>A document that well may teach the sage, </l>
              <l>That ther's no trust in youth, nor hope in age. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Daughter (said shee,) behold thy happy chaunce, </l>
              <l>That hast the lot cast downe into thy lap, </l>
              <l>VVhereby thou maist thy honor great aduaunce, </l>
              <l>Whilst thou (vnhappy) wilt not see thy hap: </l>
              <l>Such fond respect thy youth doth so inwrap, </l>
              <l>T'oppose thy selfe against thine own good fortune, </l>
              <l>That points thee out, &amp; seemes thee to importune. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-038-a"/>
              <l>Doost thou not see, how that thy King (thy Ioue,) </l>
              <l>Lightens forth glory on thy darke estate: </l>
              <l>And showres downe gold and treasure from aboue, </l>
              <l>VVhilst thou doost shut thy lap against thy fate? </l>
              <l>Fie fondling fie, thou wilt repent too late </l>
              <l>The error of thy youth; that canst not see </l>
              <l>VVhat is the fortune that doth follow thee. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Thou must not thinke thy flowre can alwaies florish, </l>
              <l>And that they beautie will be still admired: </l>
              <l>But that those rayes which all these flames do nourish, </l>
              <l>Canceld with Time, will haue theyr date expired, </l>
              <l>And men will scorne what nowe is so desired. </l>
              <l>Our frailties doome is written in the flowers, </l>
              <l>Which florish now, and fade ere many howers. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Reade in my face the ruines of my youth, </l>
              <l>The wrack of yeeres vpon my aged brow, </l>
              <l>I haue beene faire, (I must confesse the truth,) </l>
              <l>And stoode vpon as nyce respects as thou; </l>
              <l>I lost my time, and I repent it now. </l>
              <l>But were I to begin my youth againe, </l>
              <l>I would redeeme the time I spent in vaine. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-038-b"/>
              <l>But thou hast yeeres, and priuiledge to vse them, </l>
              <l>Thy priuiledge doth beare Beauties great seale; </l>
              <l>Besides, the law of nature doth excuse them, </l>
              <l>To whom thy youth may haue a iust appeale. </l>
              <l>Esteeme not Fame more then thou doost thy weale. </l>
              <l>Fame, (wherof the world seems to make such choice,) </l>
              <l>Is but an Eccho, and an idle voyce. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Then why should this respect of honor bound vs, </l>
              <l>In th' imaginary lifts of reputation? </l>
              <l>Titles which cold seueritie hath found vs, </l>
              <l>Breath of the vulgar, foe to recreation: </l>
              <l>Melancholies opinion, Customes relation; </l>
              <l>Pleasures plague, beauties scourge, hell to the faire, </l>
              <l>To leaue the sweet, for Castles in the ayre. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Pleasure is felt, opinion but conceau'd, </l>
              <l>Honour, a thing without vs, not our owne: </l>
              <l>VVhereof we see how many are bereau'd, </l>
              <l>VVhich should haue reap'd the glory they had sowne. </l>
              <l>And many haue it, yet vnworthy, knowne. </l>
              <l>So breathes his blast thys many-headed beast, </l>
              <l>VVhereof the wisest haue esteemed least. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-039-a"/>
              <l>The subtile Citty-women, better learned, </l>
              <l>Esteeme them chast enough that best seeme so: </l>
              <l>Who though they sport, it shall not be discerned, </l>
              <l>Their face bewraies not what their bodies doe; </l>
              <l>Tis warie walking that dooth safeliest goe. </l>
              <l>With shew of vertue, as the cunning knowes, </l>
              <l>Babes are beguild with sweets, &amp; men with showes. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Then vse thy tallent, youth shall be thy warrant, </l>
              <l>And let not honour from thy sports detract: </l>
              <l>Thou must not fondly thinke thy selfe transparent, </l>
              <l>That those who see thy face can iudge thy fact, </l>
              <l>Let her haue shame that cannot closely act. </l>
              <l>And seeme the chast, which is the chiefest arte, </l>
              <l>For what we seeme each see, none knowes our hart. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>The mighty, who can with such sinnes dispence, </l>
              <l>In steed of shame doe honors great bestow: </l>
              <l>A worthy author doth redeeme th'offence, </l>
              <l>And makes the scarelet sinne as white as snow. </l>
              <l>The Maiestie that doth descend so low, </l>
              <l>Is not defilde, but pure remaines therein, </l>
              <l>And being sacred, sanctifies the sin. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-039-b"/>
              <l>VVhat, doost thou stand on this, that hee is olde? </l>
              <l>Thy beauty hath the more to worke vpon. </l>
              <l>Thy pleasures want shall be supply d with gold, </l>
              <l>Cold age dotes most when heate of youth is gone: </l>
              <l>Enticing words preuaile with such a one. </l>
              <l>Alluring shewes most deepe impression strikes, </l>
              <l>For age is prone to credite what it likes. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Heere interupt, shee leaues mee in a doubt, </l>
              <l>VVhen loe began the combat in my blood, </l>
              <l>Seeing my youth inuirond round about, </l>
              <l>The ground vncertaine where my reasons stood; </l>
              <l>Small my defence to make my party good, </l>
              <l>Against such powers which were so surely layd, </l>
              <l>To ouer-throw a poore vnskilfull Mayd. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Treason was in my bones, my selfe conspiring, </l>
              <l>To sell my selfe to lust, my soule to sin: </l>
              <l>Pure-blushing shame was euen in retiring, </l>
              <l>Leauing the sacred hold it glori'd in. </l>
              <l>Honor lay prostrate for my flesh to win, </l>
              <l>When cleaner thoughts my weakenes gan vp bray, </l>
              <l>Against my selfe, and shame did force mee say; </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-040-a"/>
              <l>Ah ROSAMOND, what dooth thy flesh prepare? </l>
              <l>Destruction to thy dayes, death to thy fame; </l>
              <l>Wilt thou betray that honor held with care, </l>
              <l>T'entombe with blacke reproch a spotted name, </l>
              <l>Leauing thy blush, the colours of thy shame. </l>
              <l>Opening thy feete to sinne, thy soule to lust, </l>
              <l>Gracelesse to lay thy glory in the dust. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Nay, first let th'earth gape wide to swallow thee, </l>
              <l>And shut thee vp in bosome with her dead, </l>
              <l>Ere Serpent tempt thee taste for bidden Tree, </l>
              <l>Or feele the warmth of an vnlawfull bed; </l>
              <l>Suffring thy selfe by lust to be misled; </l>
              <l>So to disgrace thy selfe and grieue thine heyres, </l>
              <l>That Cliffords race should scorne thee one of theirs. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Neuer wish longer to inioy the ayre, </l>
              <l>Then that thou breath'st the breath of chastitie: </l>
              <l>Longer then thou preseru'st thy soule as faire </l>
              <l>As is thy face, free from impuritie. </l>
              <l>Thy face, that makes th'admir'd in euery eye, </l>
              <l>Where Natures care such rarities inroule, </l>
              <l>Which vs'd amisse, may serue to damne thy soule. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-040-b"/>
              <l>But what? hee is my King, &amp; may constraine mee, </l>
              <l>Whether I yeeld or not, I liue defamed. </l>
              <l>The world will thinke authority did gaine mee, </l>
              <l>I shall be iudg'd his Loue, and so be shamed. </l>
              <l>We see the faire condemn'd, that neuer gamed. </l>
              <l>And if I yeeld, tis honourable shame, </l>
              <l>If not, I liue disgrac'd, yet thought the same. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>What way is left thee then (vnhappy maide,) </l>
              <l>Whereby thy spotlesse foote, may wander out </l>
              <l>This dreadfull daunger, which thou seest is layd, </l>
              <l>Wherein thy shame dooth compasse thee about? </l>
              <l>Thy simple yeeres cannot resolue this doubt. </l>
              <l>Thy youth can neuer guide thy foote so euen, </l>
              <l>But (in despight) some scandale will be giuen. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Thus stood I ballanc'd equally precize, </l>
              <l>Till my fraile flesh did weigh me downe to sin; </l>
              <l>Till world and pleasure made me partialize, </l>
              <l>And glittering pompe my vanity did win. </l>
              <l>When to excuse my fault my lusts begin. </l>
              <l>And impious thoughts alledg'd this wanton clause, </l>
              <l>That though I sinn'd, my sinne had honest cause. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-041-a"/>
              <l>So well the golden balls cast downe before me, </l>
              <l>Could entertaine my course, hinder my way: </l>
              <l>Whereat my retchlesse youth stooping to store me, </l>
              <l>Lost me the gole, the glory, and the day. </l>
              <l>Pleasure had set my wel-schoold thoughts to play, </l>
              <l>And bade me vse the vertue of mine eyes, </l>
              <l>For sweetly it fits the fayre to wantonise. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Thus wrought to sin, soone was I traind from Court, </l>
              <l>T'a solitarie Grange, there to attend </l>
              <l>The time the King should thither make resort, </l>
              <l>Where he loues long-desired worke should end. </l>
              <l>Thither he daily messages doth send, </l>
              <l>VVith costly Iewels (Orators of loue,) </l>
              <l>Which (ah too wel men know) doe women moue. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>The day before the night of my defeature, </l>
              <l>Hee greets mee with a Casket ritchly wrought; </l>
              <l>So rare, that arte did seeme to striue with nature, </l>
              <l>T' expresse the cunning work-mans curious thought; </l>
              <l>The mistery whereof I prying sought. </l>
              <l>And found engrauen on the lidde aboue, </l>
              <l>Amymone, how shee with Neptune stroue. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-041-b"/>
              <l>Amymone, old Danans fairest Daughter, </l>
              <l>As shee was fetching water all alone </l>
              <l>At Lerna: whereas Neptune came and caught her, </l>
              <l>From whom shee striu'd and strugled to be gone, </l>
              <l>Beating the ayre with cryes and pittious mone. </l>
              <l>But all in vaine, with him sh' is forc'd to goe, </l>
              <l>Tis shame that men should vse poore maidens so. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>There might I see described how shee lay, </l>
              <l>At those proude feete, not satis-fied with prayer: </l>
              <l>VVayling her heauie hap, cursing the day, </l>
              <l>In act so pittious to expresse dispatre. </l>
              <l>And by how much more grieu'd, so much more faire. </l>
              <l>Her teares vpon her cheekes (poore careful gerle,) </l>
              <l>Did seeme against the sunne christall and pearle. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Whose pure cleer streams, (which loe so faire appeares,) </l>
              <l>VVrought hotter flames, (ô miracle of loue,) </l>
              <l>That kindles fire in water, heate in teares, </l>
              <l>And makes neglected beautie mightier proue, </l>
              <l>Teaching afflicted eyes affects to moue; </l>
              <l>To shew that nothing ill becomes the faire, </l>
              <l>But cruelty, which yeelds vnto no prayer. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-042-a"/>
              <l>This hauing viewd, &amp; therewith somthing moued, </l>
              <l>Figured I finde within the other squares, </l>
              <l>Trans-formed IO, IOVES deerely loued, </l>
              <l>In her affliction how shee strangely fares. </l>
              <l>Strangely distress'd, (ô beauty, borne to cares.) </l>
              <l>Turn'd to a Heiffer, kept with iealous eyes, </l>
              <l>Alwaies in danger of her hatefull spyes. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>These presidents presented to my view, </l>
              <l>Wherein the presage of my fall was showne, </l>
              <l>Might haue fore-warn'd me well what would ensue, </l>
              <l>And others harmes haue made me shun mine owne. </l>
              <l>But fate is not preuented, though fore-knowne. </l>
              <l>For that must hap, decreed by heauenly powers, </l>
              <l>Who worke our fall, yet make the fault still ours. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Witnes the world, wherein is nothing rifer, </l>
              <l>Then miseries vnkend before they come: </l>
              <l>Who can the characters of chaunce discipher, </l>
              <l>Written in clowdes of our concealed dome? </l>
              <l>Which though perhaps haue been reueald to some, </l>
              <l>Yet that so doubtful, (as successe did proue them,) </l>
              <l>That men must know they haue the heauens aboue thē. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-042-b"/>
              <l>I saw the sinne wherein my foote was entring, </l>
              <l>I saw how that dishonour did attend it, </l>
              <l>I saw the shame whereon my flesh was ventring, </l>
              <l>Yet had I not the powre for to defend it. </l>
              <l>So weake is sence when error hath condemn'd it. </l>
              <l>We see what's good, and thereto we consent, </l>
              <l>But yet we choose the worst, and soone repent. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And now I come to tell the worst of ilnes, </l>
              <l>Now drawes the date of myne affliction neere. </l>
              <l>Now when the darke had wrapt vp all in stilnes, </l>
              <l>And dreadfull black had dispossess'd the cleere, </l>
              <l>Com'd was the Night, (mother of sleepe and feare;) </l>
              <l>Who with her Sable-mantle friendly couers, </l>
              <l>The sweet-stolne sports, of ioyfull meeting Louers. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>When loe, I ioyd my Louer, not my Loue, </l>
              <l>And felt the hand of lust most vndesired: </l>
              <l>Enforc'd th'vnprooued bitter sweet to proue, </l>
              <l>Which yeelds no mutuall pleasure when tis hired. </l>
              <l>Loue's not constrain'd, nor yet of due required. </l>
              <l>Iudge they who are vnfortunately wed, </l>
              <l>What tis to come vnto a loathed bed. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-043-a"/>
              <l>But soone his age receiu'd his short contenting, </l>
              <l>And sleepe seald vp his languishing desires: </l>
              <l>VVhen he turnes to his rest, I to repenting, </l>
              <l>Into my selfe my waking thought retires: </l>
              <l>My nakednes had prou'd my sences lyers. </l>
              <l>Now opned were mine eyes to looke therein, </l>
              <l>For first we taste the fruite then see our sin. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Now did I finde my selfe vnparadis'd, </l>
              <l>From those pure fieldes of my so cleane beginning: </l>
              <l>Now I perceiu'd how ill I was aduis'd, </l>
              <l>My fleshe gan loathe the new-felt touch of sinning. </l>
              <l>Shame leaues vs by degrees, not at first winning. </l>
              <l>For nature checks a new offence with lothing. </l>
              <l>But vse of sinne doth make it seeme as nothing. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And vse of sinne did worke in me a boldnes, </l>
              <l>And loue in him, incorporates such zeale, </l>
              <l>That iealosie increas'd with ages coldnes, </l>
              <l>Fearing to loose the ioy of all his weale. </l>
              <l>Or doubting time his stealth might els reueale, </l>
              <l>H' is driuen to deuise somesubtile way, </l>
              <l>How he might safeliest keepe so ritch a pray. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-043-b"/>
              <l>A stately Pallace hee forth-with did builde, </l>
              <l>VVhose intricate in numerable waies, </l>
              <l>VVith such confused errors so beguild </l>
              <l>Th'vnguided entrers with vncertaine straies, </l>
              <l>And doubtfull turnings kept them in delayes, </l>
              <l>With bootlesse labour leading them about, </l>
              <l>Able to find no way, nor in, nor out. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>VVithin the closed bosome of which frame, </l>
              <l>That seru'd a Center to that goodly round: </l>
              <l>VVere lodgings, with a Garden to the same, </l>
              <l>With sweetest flowers that eu'r adorn'd the ground. </l>
              <l>And all the pleasures that delight hath found, </l>
              <l>T'entertaine the sence of wanton eyes, </l>
              <l>Fuell of loue, from whence lusts flames arise. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Heere I enclos'd from all the world a sunder, </l>
              <l>The Minotaure of shame kept for disgrace, </l>
              <l>The Monster of Fortune, and the worlds wonder, </l>
              <l>Liu'd cloystred in so desolate a case: </l>
              <l>None but the King might come into the place. </l>
              <l>VVith certaine Maydes that did attend my need, </l>
              <l>And he himselfe came guided by a threed. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-044-a"/>
              <l>O Iealousie, daughter of Enuy'and Loue, </l>
              <l>Most way-ward issue of a gentle Syer; </l>
              <l>Fostred with feares, thy Fathers ioyes t'improue, </l>
              <l>Myrth-marring Monster, borne a subtile lyer; </l>
              <l>Hatefull vnto thy selfe, flying thine owne desire: </l>
              <l>Feeding vpon suspect that doth renue thee, </l>
              <l>Happy were Louers if they neuer knew thee. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Thou hast a thousand gates thou enterest by, </l>
              <l>Condemning trembling passions to our hart; </l>
              <l>Hundred eyed Argus, euer-waking Spie, </l>
              <l>Pale Hagge, infernall Furie, pleasures smart, </l>
              <l>Enuious Obseruer, prying in euery part; </l>
              <l>Suspicious, fearefull, gazing still about thee, </l>
              <l>O would to God that loue could be without thee. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Thou didst depriue (through false suggesting feare,) </l>
              <l>Him of content, and mee of libertie: </l>
              <l>The onely good that women hold so deere, </l>
              <l>And turnst my freedome to captiuitie, </l>
              <l>First made a Frisoner, ere an enemy. </l>
              <l>Enioynd the raunsome of my bodies shame, </l>
              <l>Which though I paid, could not redeeme the same. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-044-b"/>
              <l>What greater torment euer could haue beene, </l>
              <l>Then to inforce the faire to liue retir'd? </l>
              <l>For what is beauty if it be not seene? </l>
              <l>Or what is't to be seene, vnlesse admir'd? </l>
              <l>And though admir'd, vnlesse in loue desir'd? </l>
              <l>Neuer were cheekes of Roses, locks of Amber, </l>
              <l>Ordain'd to lyue imprison'd in a Chamber. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Nature created beauty for the view, </l>
              <l>(Like as the fire for heate, the Sunne for light:) </l>
              <l>The faire doe hold this priuiledge as due </l>
              <l>By auncient Charter, to lyue most in sight, </l>
              <l>And shee that is debarr'd it, hath not right. </l>
              <l>In vaine our friends (in this) vse their dehorting, </l>
              <l>For beauty will be where is most resorting. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Witnes the fairest streets that Thames doth visite, </l>
              <l>The wondrous concourse of the glittering Faire: </l>
              <l>For what rare women deckt with beauty is it, </l>
              <l>That thether couets not to make repayre? </l>
              <l>The solitary Country may not stay her. </l>
              <l>Heere is the center of all beauties best, </l>
              <l>Excepting DELIA, left t'adorne the West. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-045-a"/>
              <l>Heere doth the curious with iudiciall eyes, </l>
              <l>Contemplate beauty gloriously attired: </l>
              <l>And heerein all our chiefest glory lyes, </l>
              <l>To liue where we are prais'd and most desired. </l>
              <l>O how we ioy to see our selues admired, </l>
              <l>Whilst niggardly our fauours we discouer, </l>
              <l>We loue to be belou'd, yet scorne the Louer. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Yet would to God my foote had neuer mou'd </l>
              <l>From Countrey safetie, from the fields of rest: </l>
              <l>To know the danger to be highly lou'd, </l>
              <l>And lyue in pompe to braue among the best, </l>
              <l>Happy for mee, better had I been blest; </l>
              <l>If I vnluckily had neuer straide, </l>
              <l>But liu'd at home a happy Country Maide. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>VVhose vnaffected innocencie thinks </l>
              <l>No guilefull fraude, as doth the Courtly liuer: </l>
              <l>She's deckt with trueth, the Riuer where shee drinks </l>
              <l>Doth serue her for her glasse, her counsell giuer: </l>
              <l>She loues sincerely, and is loued euer. </l>
              <l>Her daies are peace, and so she ends her breath, </l>
              <l>(True life that knowes not what's to diecil death.) </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-045-b"/>
              <l>So should I neuer haue beene registred, </l>
              <l>In the blacke booke of the vnfortunate: </l>
              <l>Nor had my name enrold with Maydes misled, </l>
              <l>VVhich bought theyr pleasures at so hie a rate. </l>
              <l>Nor had I taught (through my vnhappy sate,) </l>
              <l>This lesson, (which my selfe learnt with expence,) </l>
              <l>How most it hurts that most delights the sence. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Shame followes sinne, disgrace is duly giuen, </l>
              <l>Impietie will out, neuer so closely done: </l>
              <l>No walls can hide vs from the eye of heauen, </l>
              <l>For shame must end what wickednes begun; </l>
              <l>Foorth breakes reproch when we least thinke thereon. </l>
              <l>And this is euer propper vnto Courts, </l>
              <l>That nothing can be done, but Fame reports. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Fame doth explore what lyes most secrete hidden, </l>
              <l>Entring the closet of the Pallace dweller: </l>
              <l>Abroade reuealing what is most forbidden, </l>
              <l>Of truth and falshood both an equall teller. </l>
              <l>Tis not a guard can serue for to expell her. </l>
              <l>The sword of iustice cannot cut her wings, </l>
              <l>Nor stop her mouth from vtt'ring secrete things. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-046-a"/>
              <l>And this our stealth shee could not long conceale, </l>
              <l>From her whom such a forfeit most concerned: </l>
              <l>The wronged Queene, who could so closely deale, </l>
              <l>That shee the whole of all our practise learned, </l>
              <l>And watcht a time when least it was discerned, </l>
              <l>In absence of the King, to wreake her wrong, </l>
              <l>With such reuenge as shee desired long. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>The Laberinth shee entred by that threed, </l>
              <l>That seru'd a conduct to my absent Lord, </l>
              <l>Left there by chaunce, reseru'd for such a deed, </l>
              <l>VVhere shee surpriz'd mee whom shee so abhord. </l>
              <l>Enrag'd with madnes, scarce shee speakes a word, </l>
              <l>But flyes with eager furie to my face, </l>
              <l>Offring mee most vnwomanly disgrace. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Looke how a Tygresse that hath lost her whelpe, </l>
              <l>Runns fiercely raging through the woods astray: </l>
              <l>And seeing her selfe depriu'd of hope or helpe, </l>
              <l>Furiously assaults what's in her way, </l>
              <l>To satis-fie her wrath, (not for a pray;) </l>
              <l>So fell shee on mee in outragious wise, </l>
              <l>As could disdaine and iealousie deuise. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-046-b"/>
              <l>And after all her vile reproches vs'd, </l>
              <l>Shee forst mee take the poyson shee had brought, </l>
              <l>To end the lyfe that had her so abus'd, </l>
              <l>And free her feares, and case her iealous thought. </l>
              <l>No cruelty her wrath would leaue vnwrought, </l>
              <l>No spightfull act that to reuenge is common; </l>
              <l>(For no beast fiercer then a iealous woman.) </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Heere take (saith shee) thou impudent vncleane, </l>
              <l>Base graceles strumpet, take this next your hart; </l>
              <l>Your loue-sick hart, that ouer-charg'd hath beene </l>
              <l>With pleasures surfeite, must be purg'd with arte. </l>
              <l>This potion hath a power, that will conuart </l>
              <l>To nought those humors that oppresse you so. </l>
              <l>And (Gerle,) Ile see you take it ere I goe. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>What stand you now amaz'd, retire you back? </l>
              <l>Tremble you (minion?) come dispatch with speed. </l>
              <l>There is no helpe, your Champion now you lack, </l>
              <l>And all these teares you shed will nothing steed; </l>
              <l>Those dainty fingers needes must doe the deed. </l>
              <l>Take it, or I will drench you els by force, </l>
              <l>And trifle not, least that I vse you worse. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-047-a"/>
              <l>Hauing this bloody doome from hellish breath, </l>
              <l>My wofull eyes on euery side I cast: </l>
              <l>Rigor about me, in my hand my death, </l>
              <l>Presenting mee the horror of my last; </l>
              <l>All hope of pitty and of comfort past. </l>
              <l>No meanes, no powre, no forces to contend, </l>
              <l>My trembling hands must giue my selfe my end. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Those hands that beauties Ministers had been, </l>
              <l>They must giue death that me adorn'd of late, </l>
              <l>That mouth that newly gaue consent to sin, </l>
              <l>Must nowe receiue destruction in thereat. </l>
              <l>That body which my lust did violate, </l>
              <l>Must sacrifize it selfe t'appease the wrong. </l>
              <l>(So short is pleasure, glory lasts not long.) </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And shee no sooner saw I had it taken, </l>
              <l>But foorth shee rushes, (proude with victory,) </l>
              <l>And leaues m'alone, of all the world forsaken, </l>
              <l>Except of Death, which shee had left with me. </l>
              <l>(Death and my selfe alone together be.) </l>
              <l>To whom shee did her full reuenge refer. </l>
              <l>Ah poore weake conquest both for him and her. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-047-b"/>
              <l>Then straight my Conscience summons vp my sin, </l>
              <l>T'appeare before me, in a hideous face; </l>
              <l>Now doth the terror of my soule begin, </l>
              <l>When eu'ry corner of that hatefull place </l>
              <l>Dectates mine error, and reueales disgrace; </l>
              <l>Whilst I remaine opprest in euery part, </l>
              <l>Death in my bodie, horror at my hart. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Downe on my bed my lothsome selfe I cast, </l>
              <l>The bed that likewise giues in euidence </l>
              <l>Against my soule, and tells I was vnchast, </l>
              <l>Tells I was wanton, tells I followed sence. </l>
              <l>And therefore cast, by guilt of mine offence, </l>
              <l>Must heere the right of heauen needes satis-fie. </l>
              <l>And where I wanton lay, must wretched die. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Heere I began to waile my hard mishap, </l>
              <l>My suddaine, strange vnlookt for misery. </l>
              <l>Accusing them that did my youth intrap, </l>
              <l>To gyue me such a fall of infamie. </l>
              <l>And poore distressed ROSAMOND, (said I,) </l>
              <l>Is this thy glory got, to die forlorne </l>
              <l>In Dezarts, where no eare can heare thee morne? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-048-a"/>
              <l>Nor any eye of pitty to behold </l>
              <l>The wofull end of thy sad tragedie; </l>
              <l>But that thy wrongs vnseene, thy tale vntold, </l>
              <l>Must heere in secrete silence buried lie. </l>
              <l>And with thee, thine excuse together die. </l>
              <l>Thy sin reueal'd, but thy repentance hid, </l>
              <l>Thy shame aliue, but dead what thy death did. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Yet breathe out to these walls the breath of mone, </l>
              <l>Tell th'ayre thy plaints, sith men thou canst not tell. </l>
              <l>And though thou perrish desolate alone, </l>
              <l>Tell yet thy selfe, what thy selfe knowes too well: </l>
              <l>Vtter thy griefe where with thy soule doth swell. </l>
              <l>And let thy hart, pitty thy harts remorse, </l>
              <l>And be thy selfe the mourner and the Corse. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Condole thee heere, clad all in black dispaire, </l>
              <l>With silence onely, and a dying bed; </l>
              <l>Thou that of late, so florishing, so fayre, </l>
              <l>Did glorious liue, admir'd and honored: </l>
              <l>And now from friends, from succour hether led, </l>
              <l>Art made a spoyle to lust, to wrath, to death, </l>
              <l>And in disgrace, forst heere to yeeld thy breath. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-048-b"/>
              <l>Did Nature (ô for thys) deliberate, </l>
              <l>To shew in thee the glory of her best; </l>
              <l>Framing thine eye the star of thy ill fate, </l>
              <l>And made thy face the foe to spoyle the rest? </l>
              <l>O Beautie, thou an enemy profest, </l>
              <l>To chastitie and vs that loue thee most, </l>
              <l>Without thee how w'are loath'd, &amp; with thee lost? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>O you that proude with liberty and beautie, </l>
              <l>(And ô may well be proude that you be so,) </l>
              <l>Glitter in Court, lou'd and obseru'd of dutie; </l>
              <l>O that I might to you but ere I goe </l>
              <l>Speake what I feele, to warne you by my woe, </l>
              <l>To keepe your feet in pure cleane pathes of shame, </l>
              <l>That no inticing may diuert the same. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>See'ng how against your tender weaknes still, </l>
              <l>The strength of wit, of gold, and all is bent; </l>
              <l>And all th'assaults that euer might or skill, </l>
              <l>Can giue against a chaste and cleane intent: </l>
              <l>Ah let not greatnes worke you to consent. </l>
              <l>The spot is foule, though by a Monarch made, </l>
              <l>Kings cannot priuiledge a sinne forbade. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-049-a"/>
              <l>Lock vp therefore the treasure of your loue, </l>
              <l>Vnder the surest keyes of feare and shame: </l>
              <l>And let no powres haue powre chast thoughts to moue </l>
              <l>To make a lawlesse entry on your fame. </l>
              <l>Open to those the comfort of your flame, </l>
              <l>VVhose equall loue shal martch with equal pace, </l>
              <l>In those pure waies that leade to no disgrace. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>For see how many discontented beds, </l>
              <l>Our owne aspyring, or our Parents pride </l>
              <l>Haue caus'd, whilst that ambition vainely weds </l>
              <l>Wealth and not loue, honor and nought beside: </l>
              <l>VVhilst married but to titles, we abide </l>
              <l>As wedded widdowes, wanting what we haue, </l>
              <l>When shadowes cannot giue vs what we craue. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Or whilst we spend the freshest of our time, </l>
              <l>The sweet of youth in plotting in the ayre; </l>
              <l>Alas how oft wee fall, hoping to clime. </l>
              <l>Or wither as vnprofitably faire, </l>
              <l>Whilst those decayes which are without repayre, </l>
              <l>Make vs neglected, scorned and reprou'd. </l>
              <l>(And ô what are we, if we be not lou'd?) </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-049-b"/>
              <l>Fasten therefore vpon occasions fit, </l>
              <l>Least this, or that, or like disgrace as mine, </l>
              <l>Doe ouer-take your youth to ruine it, </l>
              <l>And clowde with infamie your beauties shine: </l>
              <l>Seeing how many seeke to vndermine </l>
              <l>The treasury that's vnpossest of any: </l>
              <l>And hard tis kept that is desir'd of many. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And flye, (ô flye,) these Bed-brokers vncleane, </l>
              <l>(The Monsters of our sexe,) that make a pray </l>
              <l>Of theyr owne kind, by an vnkindly meane; </l>
              <l>And euen (like Vipers,) eating out a way </l>
              <l>Thorow th wombe of their own shame, accursed they </l>
              <l>Lyue by the death of Fame, the gaine of sin, </l>
              <l>The filth of lust, vncleanes wallowes in. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>O is it not enough that wee, (poore wee,) </l>
              <l>Haue weaknes, beauty gold, and men our foes, </l>
              <l>But we must haue some of our selues to bee </l>
              <l>Traytors vnto our selues, to ioyne with those? </l>
              <l>Such as our feeble forces doe disclose, </l>
              <l>And still betray our cause, our shame, our youth, </l>
              <l>To lust, to follie, and to mens vntruth? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-050-a"/>
              <l>Hatefull confounders both of blood and lawes, </l>
              <l>Vilde Orators of shame, that pleade delight: </l>
              <l>Vngracious Agents in a wicked cause, </l>
              <l>Factors for darknes, messengers of night, </l>
              <l>Serpents of guile, diuels, that doe inuite </l>
              <l>The wanton taste of that forbidden tree, vvhose fruit once pluckt, will shew how foule we be. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>You in the habite of a graue aspect, </l>
              <l>(In credite by the trust of yeeres,) can shoe </l>
              <l>The cunning wayes of lust, and can direct </l>
              <l>The fayre and wilie wantons how to goe: </l>
              <l>Hauing (your lothsome selues) your youth spent so. </l>
              <l>And in vncleanes, euer haue beene fed, </l>
              <l>By the reuenue of a wanton bed. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>By you, haue beene the innocent betrayd, </l>
              <l>The blushing fearefull boldned vnto sin, </l>
              <l>The wife made subtile, subtile made the mayd, </l>
              <l>The husband scorn'd, dishonored the kin: </l>
              <l>Parents disgrac'd, children infamous been. </l>
              <l>Confus'd our race, and falsi-fied our blood, </l>
              <l>Whilst fathers sonnes, possess wrong Fathers good. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-050-b"/>
              <l>This, and much more, I would haue vttred then, </l>
              <l>A testament to be recorded still, </l>
              <l>Signd with my blood, subscrib'd with Conscience pen, </l>
              <l>To warne the faire and beautifull from ill. </l>
              <l>And ô I wish (by th'example of my will,) </l>
              <l>I had not left this sin vnto the fayre, </l>
              <l>But dyde intestat to haue had no heire. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>But now, the poyson spred through all my vaines, </l>
              <l>Gan dispossesse my liuing sences quite: </l>
              <l>And naught respecting Death, (the last of paines,) </l>
              <l>Plac'd his pale colours, (th'ensigne of his might,) </l>
              <l>Vpon his new-got spoyle before his right; </l>
              <l>Thence chac'd my soule, setting my day erenoone, </l>
              <l>When I least thought my ioyes could end so soone. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And as conuaid t'vntimely suneralles, </l>
              <l>My scarce cold corse not suffred longer stay, </l>
              <l>Behold, the King (by chaunce) returning, falles </l>
              <l>T'incounter with the same vpon the way, </l>
              <l>As he repaird to see his deerest ioy. </l>
              <l>Not thinking such a meeting could haue beene, </l>
              <l>To see his Loue, and seeing beene vnscene. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-051-a"/>
              <l>Iudge those whō chance depriues of sweetest treasure, </l>
              <l>VVhat tis to lose a thing we hold so deere: </l>
              <l>The best delight, wherein our soule takes pleasure, </l>
              <l>The sweet of life, that penetrates so neere. </l>
              <l>VVhat passions feeles that hart, inforc'd to beare </l>
              <l>The deepe impression of so strange a sight? </l>
              <l>Tongue, pen, nor arte can neuer shew aright. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Amaz'd hee stands, nor voyce nor body steares, </l>
              <l>Words had no passage, teares no issue found, </l>
              <l>For sorrow shut vp words, wrath kept in teares, </l>
              <l>Confus'd affects each other doe confound: </l>
              <l>Oppress'd with griefe, his passions had no bound. </l>
              <l>Striuing to tell his woes, words would not come; </l>
              <l>For light cares speak, whē mighty griefs are dombe. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>At length, extreamitie breakes out a way. </l>
              <l>Through Which th'imprisoned voice with teares attended, </l>
              <l>VVailes out a sound that sorrowes doe bewray, </l>
              <l>VVith armes a-crosse, and eyes to heauen bended, </l>
              <l>Vaporing out sighes that to the skyes ascended. </l>
              <l>Sighes, (the poore ease calamitie affoords,) </l>
              <l>Which serue for speech whē sorrow wanteth words. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-051-b"/>
              <l>O heauens (quoth hee,) why doe mine eyes behold </l>
              <l>The hatefull rayes of this vnhappy sunne? </l>
              <l>Why haue I light to see my sinnes controld, </l>
              <l>With blood of mine own shame thus vildly done? </l>
              <l>How can my sight endure to looke thereon? </l>
              <l>VVhy doth not blacke eternall darknes hide, </l>
              <l>That from mine eyes, my hart cannot abide? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>VVhat saw my life, wherein my soule might ioy, </l>
              <l>VVhat had my dayes, whom troubles stil afflicted, </l>
              <l>But onely this, to counterpoize annoy? </l>
              <l>This ioy, this hope, which Death hath interdicted; </l>
              <l>This sweet, whose losse hath all distresse inflicted. </l>
              <l>This, that did season all my sowre of life, </l>
              <l>Vext still at home with broyles, abroad in strise. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Vext still at home with broyles, abroad in strife, </l>
              <l>Dissention in my blood, iarres in my bed: </l>
              <l>Distrust at boord, suspecting still my life, </l>
              <l>Spending the night in horror, dayes in dread; </l>
              <l>(Such life hath Tyrants, and this life I led.) </l>
              <l>These miseries goe mask'd in glittering showes, </l>
              <l>Which wise men see, the vulgar little knowes. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-052-a"/>
              <l>Thus as these passions doe him ouer-whelme, </l>
              <l>Hee drawes him neere my body to behold it. </l>
              <l>And as the Vine married vnto the Elme </l>
              <l>With strict imbraces, so doth hee infold it. </l>
              <l>And as he in his carefull armes doth hold it, </l>
              <l>Viewing the face that euen death commends, </l>
              <l>On sencelesse lips, millions of kisses spends. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Pittifull mouth (saith hee) that lyuing gauest </l>
              <l>The sweetest comfort that my soule could wish: </l>
              <l>O be it lawfull now, that dead thou hauest, </l>
              <l>This sorrowing fare-well of a dying kisse. </l>
              <l>And you faire eyes, containers of my blisse, </l>
              <l>Motiues of loue, borne to be matched neuer, </l>
              <l>Entomb'd in your sweet circles sleepe for euer. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Ah how me thinks I see Death dallying seekes, </l>
              <l>To entertaine it selfe in Loues sweet place; </l>
              <l>Decayed Roses of discolloured checkes, </l>
              <l>Doe yet retaine deere notes of former grace: </l>
              <l>And vglie Death sits faire within her face; </l>
              <l>Sweet remnants resting of vermillion Red, </l>
              <l>That Death it selfe doubts whether shee be dead. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-052-b"/>
              <l>VVonder of beauty, oh receiue these plaints, </l>
              <l>These Obsequies, the last that I shall make thee: </l>
              <l>For loe, my soule that now already faints, </l>
              <l>(That lou'd thee liuing, dead will not forsake thee,) </l>
              <l>Hastens her speedy course to ouer-take thee. </l>
              <l>Ile meet my death, and free my selfe thereby, </l>
              <l>For (ah) what can hee doe that cannot die? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Yet ere I die, thus much my soule doth vow, </l>
              <l>Reuenge shall sweeten death with ease of minde: </l>
              <l>And I will cause posteritie shall know, </l>
              <l>How faire thou wert aboue all women kind. </l>
              <l>And after-ages Monuments shall find, </l>
              <l>Shewing thy beauties title, not thy name, </l>
              <l>Rose of the world that sweetned so the same. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>This said, though more desirous yet to say, </l>
              <l>(For sorrow is vnwilling to giue ouer,) </l>
              <l>Hee doth represse what griefe would els bewray, </l>
              <l>Least hee too much his passions should discouer. </l>
              <l>And yet respect scarce bridles such a Louer. </l>
              <l>So farre transported that he knew not whither, </l>
              <l>For Loue and Maiestie dwell ill together. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-053-a"/>
              <l>Then were my funeralls not long deferred, </l>
              <l>But done with all the rites pompe could deuise, </l>
              <l>At Godstow, where my body was interred, </l>
              <l>And ritchly tomb'd in honourable wise, </l>
              <l>Where yet as now scarce any note descries </l>
              <l>Vnto these times, the memory of mee, </l>
              <l>Marble and Brasse so 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 bee. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>For those walls which the credulous deuout, </l>
              <l>And apt-belieuing ignorant did found: </l>
              <l>With willing zeale, that neuer call'd in doubt, </l>
              <l>That time theyr works should euer so confound, </l>
              <l>Lye like confused heapes as vnder-ground. </l>
              <l>And what theyr ignoraunce esteem'd so holy, </l>
              <l>The wiser ages doe account as follie. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And were it not thy fauourable lynes, </l>
              <l>Re-edified the wrack of my decayes, </l>
              <l>And that thy accents willingly assignes, </l>
              <l>Some farthar date, and giue me longer dayes, </l>
              <l>Few in this age had knowne my beauties prayse. </l>
              <l>But thus renewd, my fame redeemes some time, </l>
              <l>Till other ages shall neglect thy time. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000823-053-b"/>
              <l>Then when confusion in her course shall bring, </l>
              <l>Sad desolation on the times to come: </l>
              <l>When mirth-lesse Thames shal haue no Swan to sing, </l>
              <l>All Musique silent, and the Muses dombe. </l>
              <l>And yet euen then it must be knowne to some, </l>
              <l>That once they florisht, though not cherisht so, </l>
              <l>And Thames had Swannes as well as euer Po. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>But heere an end, I may no longer stay thee, </l>
              <l>I must returne t'attend at Stigian flood: </l>
              <l>Yet ere I goe, this one word more I pray thee, </l>
              <l>Tell DELIA, nowe her sigh may doe mee good, </l>
              <l>And will her note the frailtie of our blood. </l>
              <l>And if I passe vnto those happy banks, </l>
              <l>Thē she must haue her prayse, thy pen her thanks. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>So vanquisht shee, and left mee to returne, </l>
              <l>To prosecute the tenor of my woes: </l>
              <l>Eternall matter for my Muse to Mourne, </l>
              <l>But (ah) the world hath heard too much of those, </l>
              <l>My youth such errors must no more disclose. </l>
              <l>Ile hide the rest, and grieue for what hath beene, </l>
              <l>Who made me known, must make me liue vnseene. </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text>
        <body>
          <p>
            <label>Editor's note</label>The text of Daniel's <hi>Cleopatra</hi>, originally published here, appears in
          the EarlyPrint corpus as a separate document under its own name and with the filename A19816_03.</p>
        </body>
      </text>
    </group>
  </text>
</TEI>
