<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Temple of Love</title>
        <author>
<!--Davenant, William-->
          <persName>
            <forename>William</forename>
            <surname>Davenant</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <idno type="dracor" xml:base="https://dracor.org/id/">ep000088</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A04600.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull n="TCP source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">The temple of love. A masque. Presented by the Queenes Majesty, and her ladies, at White-hall on Shrove-Tuesday, 1634. By Inigo Iones, surveyor of his Maties. workes, and William Davenant, her Maties. servant.</title>
                <author>Jones, Inigo, 1573-1652.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>10 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
                <date>2003 January (TCP phase 1)</date>
                <idno type="marc">99843551</idno>
                <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 14719.</idno>
                <idno type="stc">Greg, II, 497.</idno>
                <idno type="vid">8293</idno>
                <idno type="DLPS">A04600</idno>
                <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2240915539</idno>
                <availability>
                  <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
                </availability>
              </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
            <biblFull n="printed source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">The temple of love. A masque. Presented by the Queenes Majesty, and her ladies, at White-hall on Shrove-Tuesday, 1634. By Inigo Iones, surveyor of his Maties. workes, and William Davenant, her Maties. servant.</title>
                <author>Jones, Inigo, 1573-1652.</author>
                <author>D'Avenant, William, 1606-1668.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[26] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Printed for Thomas Walkley, and are to be sold at his shop neare White-hall,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication_date">1634.</date>
                <date type="creation_date">1634</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>
                  <p>Signatures: A-B4 (-B4) C4 D2.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>B4 was intended to be cancelled, but persists in most copies.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Variant: title page in an earlier version, with "surveyour of his Majesties workes" and other differences.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</p>
                </note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1634">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000088-e100030">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000088-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000088-001-b"/>
        <p>THE TEMPLE OF LOVE. A Masque. Presented by the QVEENES Majesty, and her Ladies, at White-hall on Shrove-Tuesday, 1634. By Inigo Iones, Surveyor of his Ma .Workes, and William Davenant, her Maties. Servant. </p>
        <p>LONDON: Printed for Thomas Walkley, and are to be sold at his Shop neare White-hall. 1634. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="argument" xml:id="ep000088-e100060">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000088-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000088-002-b"/>
        <head>The Argument. </head>
        <p>DIvine Poesie (the Secretary of Nature) is sent by Fate to Indamora, Queene of Narsinga, to signifie the time prefix'd was come, when by the influence of her beauty (attended with those lesser lights, her Contributary Ladies) the Temple of Chast Love should be re-established in this Island; which Temple being long sought for by certaine Magicians (enemies to chast Love) intending to use it to their intemperate ends, was by Divine Poesie hidden in mists and clouds; so as the Magicians being frustrate of their hopes, sought by enchantments to hinder all others from finding it; and by this imposture many Noble Knights and Ladies had been tempted and mis-led. The fame of this Temple of Loue being quickly spread over all the Easterne world, enflamed a company of noble Persian youths, borderers on India to travell in quest of it; who arriving, were by the illusions of the Magicians, and their spirits of severall Regions, almost seduced, as others had beene: But Divine Poesie appearing, discover'd unto them some part of the Temple unshadow'd, and prophecied <pb xml:id="ep000088-003-a"/>of the time when Indamora and her traine should arrive to effect this miracle; which though it seemes somewhat hard Doctrine to most young men, yet these being spirits of the highest ranke, forsaking the false Magicians and their allurements, were resolved to entertaine themselves to contemplate on this Apparision untill the comming of the glorious Indian Queen. At whose sight they being inspir'd with chast flames might be permitted by their faithfull observance and legitimate affections to enter and enjoy the privileges of that sacred Temple. Then Divine Poesie sends Orpheus her chiefe Priest in a Barque (assisted by the Brachmant and Priests of the Temple, who meet him on the shores) to calme the Seas with his Harpe, that a maritime Chariot prepared by the Indian Sea-gods, might safer, and more swiftly convay them to atchieve this Noble adventure; after whose landing having paid their Ceremonies by moving in harmonicall and numerous figures, Sunesis and Thelema (which intimate the understanding and the will) joyning together, the true Temple appeares, and Chast Love descends to invoke the last and living Heroe (Indamora's royall Lover) that hee may helpe and witnesse the Consecration of it. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="text" xml:id="ep000088-e100090">
        <pb xml:id="ep000088-003-b"/>
        <head>THE TEMPLE OF LOVE. </head>
        <p>AT the lower end of the Banquetting-house, opposite to the State, was a Stage of six foot high, and on that was raised an Ornament of a new Invention agreeable to the Subject; consisting of Indian Trophees: on the one side upon a basement sate a naked Indian on a whitish Elephant, his legges shortning towards the necke of the beast, his tire and bases of severall coloured feathers, representing the Indian Monarchy: On the other side an Asiatique in the habit of an Indian borderer, riding on a Camell; his Turbant and Coat differing from that of the Turkes, figured for the Asian Monarchy: over these hung sheild like Compartiments: In that over the Indian was painted a Sunne rising, and in the other an halfe Moone; these had for finishing the Capitall of a great pillaster, which served as a ground to sticke them of, and bore up a large freeze or border with a Coronice. In this over the Indian lay the figure of an old man, with a long white haire and beard, representing the flood Tigris; on his head a wreath of Canes and Seage, and leaning upon a great Vrne, out of which runne water, by him in an extravagant posture stood a Tyger. </p>
        <p>At the other end of this freeze lay another naked man, representing Meander, the famous River of Asia, who likewise had a great silver urne, and by him lay an Vnicorne. </p>
        <p>In the midst of this border was fixed a rich Compartiment, <pb xml:id="ep000088-004-a"/>behind which was a crimson Drapery part of it borne up by naked Children tack'd up in severall pleats, and the rest was at each end of the Freeze tyed with a great knot, and from thence hung downe in foulds to the bottome of the pedestalls: In the midst of this Compartiment in an Ovall was written TEMPLVM AMORIS: all these figures were in their naturall colours bigger than the life, and the Compartiments of Gold. </p>
        <p>A Curtaine flying up the first Sceane was discover'd, in which appeared a spacious grove of shady trees; and a farre off on a mount with a winding way to the top was seated a pleasant bower environed with young trees, and in the lower part walkes planted with Cypresse, representing the place where the Soules of the Ancient Poets are fained to reside: the delight of this prospect was quickly diverted to the fight of a more strange apparision; for, out of the heaven by little and little broke foorth a great Cloud of a Rosie Colour, which being come downe some little way beganne to open, and in it was seene sitting a beautifull woman; her garment was Sky-colour set all with Starres of gold, her head was crowned with Laurell, with a spangled vaile hanging downe behind, and her haire in artificiall curles graciously dress'd, representing Divine Poesie, and by her a milke white Swanne, as she descends singing out of those venerable shades came forth a company of ancient Greeke Poets, as Demodicus, Foemius, Homer, Hesiod, Terpander, and Sapho a Poetesse in habits varied and of severall colours, with laurell wreaths on their heads. Divine Poesie sung this: </p>
        <pb xml:id="ep000088-004-b"/>
        <sp who="A04600-divine_poesy" xml:id="ep000088-e100140">
          <speaker>Divine Poesie. </speaker>
          <lg n="1">
            <head>(1.) </head>
            <l>AS chearefull as the Mornings light, </l>
            <l>Comes Indamora from above, </l>
            <l>To guide those Lovers that want sight, </l>
            <l>To see and know what they should love. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg n="2">
            <head>(2.) </head>
            <l>Her beames into each breast will steale, </l>
            <l>And search what ev'ry Heart doth meane, </l>
            <l>The sadly wounded shee will heale, </l>
            <l>And make the fouly tainted cleane. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg n="3">
            <head>(3.) </head>
            <l>Rise you, from your darke shades below, </l>
            <l>That first gave words an harmony, </l>
            <l>And made false Love in Numbers flow, </l>
            <l>'Till vice became a mysterie. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg n="4">
            <head>(4.) </head>
            <l>And when I've purifi'd that Ayre </l>
            <l>To which Death turn'd you long agoe, </l>
            <l>Helpe with your voyces to declare </l>
            <l>What Indamora comes to show. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-poets" xml:id="ep000088-e100350">
          <speaker>The Poets. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Soule of our Science! how inspir'd we come? </l>
            <l>By thee restor'd to voyces that lay dumbe, </l>
            <l>Awd lost in many a forgotten Tombe. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-divine_poesy" xml:id="ep000088-e100400">
          <speaker>D. Poesie. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <pb xml:id="ep000088-005-a"/>
            <l>Y'are spirits all; and have so long </l>
            <l>From flesh, and frailty absent bin, </l>
            <l>That sure though Love should fill your song, </l>
            <l>It could not rellish now of sinne. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-poets" xml:id="ep000088-e100460">
          <speaker>The Poets. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Vex not our sad remembrance with our shame! </l>
            <l>We have bin punish'd for ill-gotten fame, </l>
            <l>For each loose verse, tormented with a flame. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-divine_poesy" xml:id="ep000088-e100510">
          <speaker>D. Poesie. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Descend then, and become with me, </l>
            <l>The happy Organs to make knowne </l>
            <l>In an harmonious Embassie, </l>
            <l>Our great affaire to yonder Throne. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <p>Shee being descended to the ground in a Majesticke pace, goes up to the State, attended by the fore-named Poets; and the Cloud that brought her downe, closeth as it ascends. </p>
        <sp who="A04600-divine_poesy" xml:id="ep000088-e100580">
          <speaker>D. Poesie. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Thou Monarch of mens hearts rejoyce! </l>
            <l>So much thou art belov'd in heaven, </l>
            <l>That Fate hath made thy reigne her choyce, </l>
            <l>In which Love's blessings shall be given. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-poets" xml:id="ep000088-e100640">
          <speaker>The Poets. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Truth shall appeare, and rule 'till she resists </l>
            <l>Those subtle charmes, and melts those darker mists, </l>
            <l>In which Love's Temple's hid from Exorcists. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <pb xml:id="ep000088-005-b"/>
            <l>(Whom forsooth Divine Poesie they stile) </l>
            <l>This morne proclaim'd it from a falling Cloud. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-speaker_2" xml:id="ep000088-e100720">
          <speaker>(2.) </speaker>
          <l>Who? Divine Poesie? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-speaker_2" xml:id="ep000088-e100740">
          <speaker>(3.) </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>I know her well. </l>
            <l>Shee's one that makes the holy Jigges, </l>
            <l>And sacred Catches for the gods, when they </l>
            <l>Are merry with mis-takes of men, and laugh </l>
            <l>To see us carelesse of their punishment. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-speaker_1" xml:id="ep000088-e100810">
          <speaker>(1.) </speaker>
          <l>But who shall bring this mischiefe to our Art? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-speaker_3" xml:id="ep000088-e100830">
          <speaker>(3.) </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Indamora, the delight of Destiny! </l>
            <l>Shee, and the beauties of her Traine: who sure </l>
            <l>Though they discover Summer in their lookes, </l>
            <l>Still carry frozen Winter in their blood. </l>
            <l>They raise strange doctrines, and new sects of Love: </l>
            <l>Which must not wooe or court the Person, but </l>
            <l>The Mind; and practise generation not </l>
            <l>Of Bodies but of Soules. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-speaker_2" xml:id="ep000088-e100930">
          <speaker>(2.) </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Beleeve me, my Magicall friends, </l>
            <l>They must bring bodies with 'em that worship </l>
            <l>In our pleasant Temple: I have an odde </l>
            <l>Fantasticke faith perswades me there will be </l>
            <l>Little pastime upon earth without Bodies. </l>
            <l>Your Spirit's a cold Companion at midnight. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-speaker_1" xml:id="ep000088-e101010">
          <speaker>(1.) </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Have we so long misse-led and entertain'd </l>
            <l>The youthfull of the world, (I meane their bodies) </l>
            <l>And now doe they betake themselves unto </l>
            <l>The dull imaginary pleasures of </l>
            <l>Their soules? This humor cannot last. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-speaker_2" xml:id="ep000088-e101080">
          <speaker>(2.) </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>If it should, we may rid our Temple </l>
            <l>Of all our Persian Quilts, imbroyder'd Couches, </l>
            <l>And our standing Beds; these (I take it) are </l>
            <l>Bodily implements; our soules need 'em not. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000088-006-a"/>
            <l>But where shall this new Sect be planted first? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-speaker_3" xml:id="ep000088-e101150">
          <speaker>(3.) </speaker>
          <l>In a dull Northerne Ile, they call Britaine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-speaker_2" xml:id="ep000088-e101170">
          <speaker>(2.) </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Indeed 'tis a cold Northerly opinion; </l>
            <l>And I'le lay my life begot since their late </l>
            <l>Great Frosts. It will be long enough e're it </l>
            <l>Shall spread, and prosper in the South! Or if </l>
            <l>The Spaniard or Italian ever be </l>
            <l>Perswaded out of the use of their bodies, </l>
            <l>I'le give mine to a Raven for his Supper. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-speaker_3" xml:id="ep000088-e101260">
          <speaker>(3.) </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>The Miracle is more increas'd, in that </l>
            <l>It first takes birth and nourishment in Court. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-speaker_2" xml:id="ep000088-e101300">
          <speaker>(2.) </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>But my good damn'd friend tell me? Is there not </l>
            <l>One Courtier will resent the cause, and give </l>
            <l>Some countenance to the affaires of the body? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-speaker_3" xml:id="ep000088-e101350">
          <speaker>(3) </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Certain yong Lords at first disliked the Phylosophy </l>
            <l>As most uncomfortable, sad, and new; </l>
            <l>But soone inclin'd to a superior vote, </l>
            <l>And are growne as good Platonicall Lovers </l>
            <l>As are to be found in an Hermitage, where he </l>
            <l>That was borne last, reckons above fourescore. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <p>To these come foorth in hast another Magician, in shape and habit differing from the other, and spake as followeth. </p>
        <sp who="A04600-speaker_1" xml:id="ep000088-e101440">
          <speaker>(1.) </speaker>
          <l>Here comes a brother of our misticke Tribe! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-speaker_3" xml:id="ep000088-e101460">
          <speaker>(3.) </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>He knowes th'occasion of our griefe, and by </l>
            <l>His hast imports discoveries more strange! </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-speaker_4" xml:id="ep000088-e101500">
          <speaker>(4.) </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Newes! newes! my sad companions of the shade! </l>
            <l>There's lately landed on our fatall shore </l>
            <l>Nine Persian youths, their habit and their lookes </l>
            <l>So smooth, that from the pleasures i'th Elisian fields </l>
            <l>Each female ghost will come, and enter in </l>
            <l>Their flesh againe, to make embraces warme. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000088-006-b"/>
        <sp who="A04600-speaker_2" xml:id="ep000088-e101580">
          <speaker>(2.) </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>I hope these are no Platonicall Lovers, </l>
            <l>No such Carthusian Poets as doe write </l>
            <l>Madrigals to the mind? more of thy newes! </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-speaker_4" xml:id="ep000088-e101630">
          <speaker>(4.) </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>The rest inferres small joy, and little hope: </l>
            <l>For though at first their youth and eager thoughts </l>
            <l>Directed them where our gay Altar stood, </l>
            <l>And they were ready too for sacrifice, </l>
            <l>I cannot tell what lucklesse light inform'd </l>
            <l>Their eyes, but Loves true Temple straight they spy'd </l>
            <l>Through the ascending mists, and would have enterd it </l>
            <l>To read grave frosty Homilies, </l>
            <l>And Anticke sawes of Chastitie, but that </l>
            <l>(As my swift Spirit brought me word) a voyce </l>
            <l>Sent from within bad them with reverence </l>
            <l>Desist till Indamora did appeare, for then </l>
            <l>The gates would open, and the mists dry up </l>
            <l>That thus conceal'd it from the generall view, </l>
            <l>Which now their expectation doth attend. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-speaker_3" xml:id="ep000088-e101800">
          <speaker>(3.) </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>'Tis time to wake our drowsie Art, and try </l>
            <l>If we have power to hinder Destinie. </l>
            <l>Mount! mount! our charmes! fetch me, whilst you aspire, </l>
            <l>A Spirit of the Element of fire! </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-speaker_2" xml:id="ep000088-e101860">
          <speaker>(2.) </speaker>
          <l>Me one of Ayre! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-speaker_1" xml:id="ep000088-e101880">
          <speaker>(1.) </speaker>
          <l>The water me supplies! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-speaker_4" xml:id="ep000088-e101900">
          <speaker>(4.) </speaker>
          <l>Mine from the center of the earth shall rise! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-speaker_3" xml:id="ep000088-e101920">
          <speaker>(3.) </speaker>
          <l>These shall infuse their sev'rall qualities </l>
          <l>In men; if not t'uphold the faction of </l>
          <l>The flesh, yet to infect the queasie age </l>
          <l>With blacker sinnes: If we (now we have joyn'd </l>
          <l>The force of all the Elements t'assist </l>
          <l>The horror of our will) shall not prevaile </l>
          <l>Against this hum'rous vertue of the Time, </l>
          <l>Nature, our weaknesse must be thought thy crime. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="A04600-missing" xml:id="ep000088-e102010">
          <gap extent="2" n="6-b-3040" unit="pages"/>
          <pb xml:id="ep000088-007-a"/>
          <l>From Persian Princes too, and each as fierce </l>
          <l>A Lover, as did ever sigh in verse! </l>
          <l>Give audience then, you Ladies of this Ile! </l>
          <l>Lord how you lift your fannes up now, and smile! </l>
          <l>To thinke (forsooth) they are so fond to take </l>
          <l>So long a journey for your beauties sake! </l>
          <l>For know, th'are come! but sure, e're they returne, </l>
          <l>Will give your femallships some cause to mourne! </l>
          <l>For I must tell you, that about them all </l>
          <l>There's not one graine, but what's Platonicall! </l>
          <l>So bashfull that I thinke they might be drawne </l>
          <l>(Like you) to weare close Hoods, or vailes of Lawne. </l>
          <l>My Master is the chiefe that doth protect, </l>
          <l>Or (as some say) misse-lead this precise sect: </l>
          <l>One heretofore that wisely could confute </l>
          <l>A Lady at her window with his Lute. </l>
          <l>There devoutly in a cold morning stand </l>
          <l>Two howres, praysing the snow of her white hand, </l>
          <l>So long, till's words were frozen 'tweene his lips, </l>
          <l>And's Lute-strings learnt their quav'ring from his hips. </l>
          <l>And when he could not rule her to's intent, </l>
          <l>Like Tarquin he would proffer ravishment. </l>
          <l>But now, no feare of Rapes, untill he find </l>
          <l>A maydenhead belonging to the mind. </l>
          <l>The rest are all so modest too, and pure, </l>
          <l>So virginly, so coy, and so demure, </l>
          <l>That they retreat at kissing, and but name </l>
          <l>Hymen, or Love, they blush for very shame! </l>
          <l>Ladies! I must needs laugh! you'le give me leave </l>
          <l>I hope; and 'tis to thinke how you deceive </l>
          <l>Your selves with all this precious art, and care </l>
          <l>Tane in your glasse to dresse your lookes, and haire! </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000088-007-b"/>
          <l>When (in good faith!) they heed no outward merit, </l>
          <l>But fervently resolve to wooe the Spirit! </l>
          <l>Hah! doe you all looke melancholy uow? </l>
          <l>And cast a Cloud of anger o're the brow? </l>
          <l>'Tis time to flye, and my best swiftnesse use, </l>
          <l>Lest kill'd with pinnes, and Bodkins for my newes. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>The Page retires, and the Noble Persian youths make their entry, apparelled in Asian Coats of Sea-greene embroidered that reached downe above their knees, with buttons and loops before and cut up square to their hips, and returned downe with two short skirts; the sleeves of this Coat were large without seame, and cut short to the bending of the Arme, and hanging downe long behinde, trimm'd with buttons as those of the breast; out of this came a sleeve of white Sattin embroidered, and the Basis answerable to the sleeve, hung downe in gathering underneath the shortest part of their Coat; on their heads they wore Persian Turbants silver'd underneath, and wound about with white Cypresse, and one fall of a white feather before. </p>
        <p>Their Dance ended, the mist and Clouds at an instant disappeare, and the Sceane is all changed into a Sea somewhat calme, where the billowes moving sometimes whole, and sometimes breaking, beat gently on the land, which represented a new and strange prospect; the nearest part was broken grounds and Rockes, with a mountainous Countrey, but of a pleasant Aspect, in which were trees of strange forme and Colour, and here and there were placed in the bottome severall Arbors like Cottages, and strange beasts and birds, farre unlike the Countrey of these parts, expressing an Indian Landschape: In the Sea were severall I- </p>
        <p>
          <gap extent="2" n="7-b-3230" unit="pages"/>
          <pb xml:id="ep000088-008-a"/>Indamora Queene of Narsinga sate enthron'd in the highest part of this Chariot, in a rich seat, the backe of which was a great Skallop Shell. The habit of the Masquers was of Isabella Colour, and Watchet, with Bases in large paines cut through, all over richly embroyder'd with silver, and the dressing of their heads was of silver, with small falls of white feathers tipp'd with Watchet. This sight thus moving on the water, was accompanied with the musicke and voyces of the Chorus. </p>
        <lg type="song">
          <lg n="1">
            <head>(1.) </head>
            <l>SHe comes! each Princesse in her traine hath all </l>
            <l>That wise enamor'd Poets, beauty call! </l>
            <l>So fit and ready to subdue: </l>
            <l>That had they not kind hearts which take a care </l>
            <l>To free, and counsell, whom their eyes ensnare, </l>
            <l>Poore Lovers would have cause to rue. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg n="2">
            <head>(2.) </head>
            <l>More welcome than the wandring Sea-mans starre, </l>
            <l>When in the Night the Winds make causelesse warre, </l>
            <l>Vntill his Barque so long is tost, </l>
            <l>That's sayles to ragges are blowne, the Maine-yard beares </l>
            <l>Not sheet enough to wipe, and dry those teares </l>
            <l>He shed to see his Rudder lost. </l>
          </lg>
        </lg>
        <p>The Song ended, all the forepart of the Sea was in an instant turn'd to dry land, and Indamora with her Contributary Ladies descended into the roome, and made their entry. Then for enter medium the Musicke began againe, and sung this Song. </p>
        <lg type="song">
          <pb xml:id="ep000088-008-b"/>
          <head>The Song. </head>
          <lg n="1">
            <head>(1.) </head>
            <l>THe Planets though they move so fast, </l>
            <l>Have power to make their swiftnesse last, </l>
            <l>But see, your strength is quickly gone! </l>
            <l>Yet move by sense and rules of Art, </l>
            <l>And each hath an immortall part, </l>
            <l>Which cannot tire, but they have none: </l>
          </lg>
          <lg n="2">
            <head>(2.) </head>
            <l>Let then your soft, and nimble feet </l>
            <l>Lead and in various figures meet </l>
            <l>Those stranger Knights, who though they came </l>
            <l>Seduc'd at first by false desire, </l>
            <l>You'le kindle in their breasts a fire </l>
            <l>Shall keepe Love warme, yet not enflame. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg n="3">
            <head>(3.) </head>
            <l>At first they were your beauties prize, </l>
            <l>Now offer willing sacrifice </l>
            <l>Vnto the Vertues of the minde, </l>
            <l>And each shall weare when they depart, </l>
            <l>A lawfull though a loving heart, </l>
            <l>And wish you still both strict and kinde. </l>
          </lg>
        </lg>
        <p>The Masquers having a while reposed, danced their second Dance, which ended, and the Queene being seated under the State by the King, the Sceane was changed into the true Temple of Chast Love; this Temple instead of Columnes had termes of young Satyrs bearing <pb xml:id="ep000088-009-a"/>up the returnes of Architrane Freeze and Coronice, all enrich'd of Gold-smiths worke, the further part of the Temple running farre from the eye was design'd of another kind of Architecture, with Pillasters, Neeches, and Statues; and in the midst a stately gate adorn'd with Colomns and their Ornaments, and a Frontispice on the top, all which seemed to bee of burnish'd gold. Into this Temple enters Sunesis and Thelema; Sunesis a man of a noble Aspect, and richly attir'd; his garment of Cloth of gold reaching downe below his knees, and girt with a tucke at the wast, with wide sleeves turn'd up; his mantle of Watchet fastned on both shoulders, and hanging downe long behind, a garland of Sinope on his head, with a flame of fire issuing out of it, his Buskins were yellow, wrought with gold. Thelema a young woman in a Robe of changeable silke girt with severall tuckes, under her breast, and beneath her wast, and great leaves of silver about her shoulders hanging downe to the midst of her Arme; upon her head a garland of great Marigolds, and puffs of silver'd Lawne betweene. And at her shoulders were Angels wings, these sung this Dialogue, assisted by the Chori. </p>
        <floatingText>
          <body>
            <div type="song" xml:id="ep000088-e102860">
              <head>The Song. </head>
              <stage xml:id="ep000088-e102870">Sunesis and Thelema. </stage>
              <sp who="A04600-sunesis" xml:id="ep000088-e102880">
                <speaker>Sunesis. </speaker>
                <l>COme melt thy soule in mine, that when unite, </l>
                <l>We may become one virtuous appetite. </l>
              </sp>
              <pb xml:id="ep000088-009-b"/>
              <sp who="A04600-thelema" xml:id="ep000088-e102910">
                <speaker>Thelema. </speaker>
                <l>First breath thine into me, thine is the part </l>
                <l>More heavenly, and doth more adorne the heart. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp who="A04600-both" xml:id="ep000088-e102940">
                <speaker>Both. </speaker>
                <l>Thus mix'd, our love will ever be discreet, </l>
                <l>And all our thoughts and actions pure, </l>
                <l>When perfect Will, and strengthned Reason meet, </l>
                <l>Then Love's created to endure. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp who="A04600-chorus" xml:id="ep000088-e102990">
                <speaker>Chorus. </speaker>
                <l>Were Heaven more distant from us, we would strive </l>
                <l>To reach't with Pray'rs to make this Vnion thrive. </l>
              </sp>
            </div>
          </body>
        </floatingText>
        <p>Whilst this Song continued, there came softly downe from the highest part of the heaven a bright and transparent Cloud, which being come to the middle part of the Ayre it opened, and out of it came Amianteros, or Chast Love flying downe, clad all in Carnation and White, and two garlands of Laurell in one hand, and crown'd with another of the same; whilst he descended the Cloud closeth againe and returnes upwards, and is hidden in the heavens; Chast Love being come downe to the earth, was accompanied by Sunesis and Thelema, Divine Poesie, Orpheus, and the rest of the Poets up to the State, the great Chorus following at a distance, where they sung this Song. </p>
        <floatingText>
          <body>
            <div type="song" xml:id="ep000088-e103050">
              <head>The Song. </head>
              <stage xml:id="ep000088-e103060">Amianteros, or Chast Love. </stage>
              <lg n="1">
                <head>(1.) </head>
                <l>WHilst by a mixture thus made one, </l>
                <l>Y'are th' Embleme of my Deitie, </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000088-010-a"/>
                <l>And now you may in yonder Throne, </l>
                <l>The patterne of your Vnion see. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg n="2">
                <head>(2.) </head>
                <l>Softly as fruitfull showeres I fall, </l>
                <l>And th'undiscern'd increase I bring, </l>
                <l>Is of more precious worth than all </l>
                <l>A plenteous Summer payes a Spring. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg n="3">
                <head>(3.) </head>
                <l>The benefit it doth impart, </l>
                <l>Will not the barren earth improve, </l>
                <l>But fructifie each barren heart, </l>
                <l>And give eternall growth to Love. </l>
              </lg>
              <sp who="A04600-sunesis" xml:id="ep000088-e103220">
                <speaker>Sunesis. </speaker>
                <l>To CHARLES the mightiest and the best, </l>
                <l>And to the Darling of his breast, </l>
                <l>(Who rule b' example as by power) </l>
                <l>May youthfull blessings still increase, </l>
                <l>And in their Off-spring never cease, </l>
                <l>Till Time's too old to last an hower. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp who="A04600-chorus" xml:id="ep000088-e103290">
                <speaker>Chorus. </speaker>
                <l>These wishes are so well deserv'd by thee, </l>
                <l>And thought so modest too by Destinie, </l>
                <l>That heaven hath seal'd the grant as a Decree. </l>
              </sp>
            </div>
          </body>
        </floatingText>
        <p>After which they all retire to the Sceane, and Indamora and her Ladies beginne the Revels with the King and the Lords, which continue the most part of the night. Thus ended this Masque which for the newnesse <pb xml:id="ep000088-010-b"/>of the invention, variety of Sceanes, Apparitions, and richnesse of habits was generally approved to be one of the most magnificent that hath beene done in England. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="ep000088-e103350">
        <head>The Masquers Names. </head>
        <list>
          <head>The Queenes Majesty. </head>
          <item>Lady Marquesse Hamilton. </item>
          <item>Lady Mary Herbert. </item>
          <item>Countesse of Oxford. </item>
          <item>Countesse of Berkshire. </item>
          <item>Countesse of Carnarvan. </item>
          <item>Countesse of Newport. </item>
          <item>Lady Herbert. </item>
          <item>Lady Katherine Howard </item>
          <item>Lady Anne Carre. </item>
          <item>Lady Elizabeth Fielding </item>
          <item>Lady Thimbleby. </item>
          <item>Mistris Dorothy Savage. </item>
          <item>Mistris Victorie Cary. </item>
          <item>Mistris Nevill. </item>
        </list>
        <list>
          <head>The Lords and others that presented the Noble Persian Youths. </head>
          <item>The Duke of Lenox. </item>
          <item>Earle of Newport. </item>
          <item>Earle of Desmond. </item>
          <item>Viscount Grandeson. </item>
          <item>Lord Russell. </item>
          <item>Lord Doncaster. </item>
          <item>Master Thomas Weston. </item>
          <item>Master George Goring. </item>
          <item>Master Henry Murrey. </item>
        </list>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist">
        <head>Machine-generated castlist</head>
        <list n="163-A04600">
          <item n="8">
            <seg type="character_name">A04600-speaker_2</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="7">
            <seg type="character_name">A04600-speaker_3</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="4">
            <seg type="character_name">A04600-divine_poesy</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="4">
            <seg type="character_name">A04600-speaker_1</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="3">
            <seg type="character_name">A04600-poets</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="3">
            <seg type="character_name">A04600-speaker_4</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="2">
            <seg type="character_name">A04600-sunesis</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="2">
            <seg type="character_name">A04600-chorus</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="1">
            <seg type="character_name">A04600-both</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="1">
            <seg type="character_name">A04600-missing</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="1">
            <seg type="character_name">A04600-thelema</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
          </item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-digit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber. A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a keyword in context.</p>
        <note target="A04600-003-a-1090">
          <label>c3bwd-003-a-1090</label>
          <sic>Brachman●</sic>
          <seg>chiefe Priest in a Barque ( assisted by the</seg>
          <corr>Brachmant</corr>
          <seg>and Priests of the Temple , who meet him</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A04600-003-a-1530">
          <label>c3bwd-003-a-1530</label>
          <sic>●dventure</sic>
          <seg>swiftly convay them to atchieve this Noble</seg>
          <corr>adventure</corr>
          <seg>; after whose landing having paid their</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A04600-004-a-0620">
          <label>c3bwd-004-a-0620</label>
          <sic>TEMPLVMAMORIS</sic>
          <seg>this Compartiment in an Ovall was written</seg>
          <corr>TEMPLVM AMORIS</corr>
          <seg>: all these figures were in their</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A04600-006-b-1020">
          <label>c3bwd-006-b-1020</label>
          <sic>●awes</sic>
          <seg>read grave frosty Homilies , And Anticke</seg>
          <corr>sawes</corr>
          <seg>of Chastitie , but that ( As my swift Spirit</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A04600-007-b-2910">
          <label>c3bwd-007-b-2910</label>
          <sic>bot●ome</sic>
          <seg>Colour , and here and there were placed in the</seg>
          <corr>bottome</corr>
          <seg>severall Arbors like Cottages , and strange</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A04600-007-b-3150">
          <label>c3bwd-007-b-3150</label>
          <sic>▪</sic>
          <seg>these parts , expressing an Indian Landschape</seg>
          <corr>:</corr>
          <seg>In the Sea were severall I -</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A04600-008-a-1440">
          <label>c3bwd-008-a-1440</label>
          <sic>ensuare</sic>
          <seg>To free , and counsell , whom their eyes</seg>
          <corr>ensnare</corr>
          <seg>, Poore Lovers would have cause to rue .</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A04600-008-a-1850">
          <label>c3bwd-008-a-1850</label>
          <sic>toragges</sic>
          <seg>his Barque so long is tost , That's sayles</seg>
          <corr>to ragges</corr>
          <seg>are blowne , the Maine-yard beares</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A04600-008-b-0560">
          <label>c3bwd-008-b-0560</label>
          <sic>▪</sic>
          <seg>, Which cannot tire , but they have none</seg>
          <corr>:</corr>
          <seg/>
        </note>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
