<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Albovine, King of the Lombards</title>
        <author>
<!--Davenant, Sir William-->
          <persName>
            <forename>Sir William</forename>
            <surname>Davenant</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <idno type="dracor" xml:base="https://dracor.org/id/">ep000367</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A19881.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull n="TCP source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">The tragedy of Albouine, King of the Lombards: by Wm. D'auenant.</title>
                <author>D'Avenant, William, Sir, 1606-1668.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>47 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
                <date>2006 February (TCP phase 1)</date>
                <idno type="marc">99844959</idno>
                <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 6307.</idno>
                <idno type="stc">Greg, II, 422(a).</idno>
                <idno type="vid">9818</idno>
                <idno type="DLPS">A19881</idno>
                <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2240879911</idno>
                <availability>
                  <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
                </availability>
              </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
            <biblFull n="printed source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">The tragedy of Albouine, King of the Lombards: by Wm. D'auenant.</title>
                <title type="alt">Albovine</title>
                <title type="alt">Albovine.</title>
                <title type="alt">Tragedy of Albovine, King of the Lombards.</title>
                <title type="alt">Tragedy of Albouine, King of Lombardy.</title>
                <title type="alt">Tragedy of Albovine, King of Lombardy.</title>
                <author>D'Avenant, William, Sir, 1606-1668.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[96] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Printed [by Felix Kingston] for R. M[oore] and are to bee sold in Saint Dunstanes Church-yard,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication_date">1629.</date>
                <date type="creation_date">1629</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>
                  <p>Printer's and publisher's names from STC.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Signatures: A-M4.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Running title reads: The tragedy of Albouine, King of Lombardy.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
                </note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
      <profileDesc>
        <particDesc>
          <listPerson>
            <person xml:id="ep000367-paradine">
              <persName>Paradine</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000367-grimold">
              <persName>Grimold</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000367-unassigned">
              <persName>Unassigned</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000367-gondibert">
              <persName>Gondibert</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000367-hermegild">
              <persName>Hermegild</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000367-frollo">
              <persName>Frollo</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000367-albovine">
              <persName>Albovine</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000367-vollterri">
              <persName>Vollterri</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000367-governor">
              <persName>Governor</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000367-rhodolinda">
              <persName>Rhodolinda</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000367-valdaura">
              <persName>Valdaura</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000367-cunymond">
              <persName>Cunymond</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000367-conrade">
              <persName>Conrade</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000367-thesina">
              <persName>Thesina</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000367-gentleman">
              <persName>Gentleman</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000367-page">
              <persName>Page</persName>
            </person>
          </listPerson>
        </particDesc>
        <textClass>
          <classCode scheme="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q80930</classCode>
        </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1626">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000367-e100030">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000367-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-001-b"/>
        <p>THE TRAGEDY OF ALBOVINE, KING OF THE LOMBARDS: By Wm. D'auenant. </p>
        <p>LONDON, Printed for R. M. and are to bee sold in Saint Dunstanes Church-yard. 1629. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000367-e100060">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000367-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-002-b"/>
        <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE THE EARLE OF SOMMERSET, &amp;c. </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My Lord, </salute>
        </opener>
        <p>YOu read this Tragedie, and smil'd vpon't, that it might liue: and therein, your mercy was diuine; for it exceeded Iustice. My Numbers I not shew vnto the publike Eye, with an ambition to bee quickly knowne; (for so I couet noyse, not fame) but that the world may learne, with what an early haste, I striue to manifest my seruice to your Lordship. I haue imaginations of a greater height then these, which I doe also dedicate to your Lordship. And I shall liue in vaine, vnlesse you still continue to acknowledge </p>
        <closer>
          <signed>Your humblest Creature, D'auenant. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000367-e100120">
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-003-a"/>
        <head>VPON THE TRAGICK MVSE OF MY HONOVR'D FRIEND, Mr. Wm. D'AVENANT. </head>
        <l>OVr stately Tragick Scene (whose high disdaines </l>
        <l>Slight humble Muses) courts thy lofty straines: </l>
        <l>And with ambitious loue doth clime thy Bayes, </l>
        <l>Whose ample branches her bright glory rayes: </l>
        <l>Whence (as from Heauen) her spacious Eye doth view </l>
        <l>Of storyed teares, and blood, the heauy crue, </l>
        <l>How low they crawle, while she (farre more Diuine!) </l>
        <l>Sides great Seianus, and fierce Cateline: </l>
        <l>Where, in calme vertue, she more sweet doth shew </l>
        <l>Then Ioue, when he in Golden drops did flow: </l>
        <l>But if in Stygian Lake her veines she steepe, </l>
        <l>Her act infernall runnes so horrid deepe, </l>
        <l>As saints Medea: makes th' Herculian rage </l>
        <l>Seeme a tame patience to thy rauisht Stage. </l>
        <l>Had sterne Achilles brest such fury knowne; </l>
        <l>His Story had turn'd Miracle, and growne </l>
        <l>Too much for his great Poet, vnlesse Fate </l>
        <l>Had rackt his spirit vp to thy high rate. </l>
        <l>Rash Imitation at thy heauenly Ayre, </l>
        <l>Intombes faint Enuy in a iust despaire. </l>
        <closer>
          <signed>Hen: Blount. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000367-e100350">
        <head>To his friend, Mr. Wm. D'auenant. </head>
        <l>WHy should the fond ambition of a friend, </l>
        <l>With such Industrious accents striue to lend </l>
        <l>A Prologue to thy worth? Can ought of mine </l>
        <l>Inrich thy Volume? Th' hast rear'd thy selfe a Shrine </l>
        <l>Will out-liue Piramids; Marble Pillars shall, </l>
        <l>Ere thy great Muse, receiue a funerall: </l>
        <l>Thy wit hath purchas'd such a Patrons name </l>
        <l>To deck thy front, as must deriue to Fame </l>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-003-b"/>
        <l>These Tragick raptures, and indent with Eyes </l>
        <l>To spend hot teares, t'inrich the Sacrifice. </l>
        <closer>
          <signed>Ed: Hyde. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000367-e100480">
        <head>To my honor'd Friend, th'Author, on his Tragedy of the warlike Albouine. </head>
        <l>GReat Albouine, whose Fate in warre had cut </l>
        <l>His passage through the neighb'ring Earth, and shut </l>
        <l>Large Prouinces within his grasping palme, </l>
        <l>Had sunke from honour in the patient calme </l>
        <l>Of a long silenc't Fame, had not thy pen </l>
        <l>(With soaring language) rays'd him vp agen. </l>
        <l>He vowes, by coole Elizeum (from whence </l>
        <l>He breath'd the valiant oath) he would dispense </l>
        <l>With all those ioyes that court his soule, to fling </l>
        <l>His open'd brest vpon the poys'nous sting </l>
        <l>Of rougher warres, if the triumphant Bayes </l>
        <l>Sprung from thy inke, might crowne his second prayse. </l>
        <l>This is a Poets height; conquest by thee </l>
        <l>Describ'd, becomes a double victory. </l>
        <closer>
          <signed>Rich: Clerk. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000367-e100650">
        <head>To my deseruing Friend, the Author. </head>
        <lg>
          <l>WEre those Tragedians, whom the world so fame, </l>
          <l>For their ingenious and admired straine, </l>
          <l>Aliue, to see this Poem, and thy Name; </l>
          <l>Asham'd they'd dye, finding their Lines too vaine. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Were that pure Spring the winged hoofe brought forth, </l>
          <l>Wanting supply, dry'd vp, thy abler Pen </l>
          <l>Would worke a second wonder by it's worth, </l>
          <l>In making it a running streame agen. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Be then assur'd, this Tragick straine shall liue </l>
          <l>A patterne for th' next age to imitate, </l>
          <l>And to the best wits of our times shall giue </l>
          <l>Iust cause of enuy, for thy learned Fate. </l>
        </lg>
        <closer>
          <signed>Rob: Ellice. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000367-e100830">
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-004-a"/>
        <head>To his noble Friend, th'Author on his Tragedy of Albouine. </head>
        <l>THe gelid North growes warme, and by thy fire </l>
        <l>Cold ignorance exil'd. The Virgin Quire </l>
        <l>O' th' soft-hayr'd Muses leaue the Thespian Spring, </l>
        <l>To tread a fun'rall Measure, whilst you sing </l>
        <l>This Tragick Storie. With sad plaints of loue </l>
        <l>Fam'd Orpheus charm'd rude heapes, did Cedars mooue, </l>
        <l>Forc'd Mountaines from their station: but thy Pen </l>
        <l>Hath now amaz'd the firie soules of men. </l>
        <closer>
          <signed>Will: Habington. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000367-e100940">
        <head>To my Friend, Mr. D'auenant. </head>
        <l>SCarce home return'd, but straight I finde great Fame </l>
        <l>Ayring her wings to spread abroad thy Name. </l>
        <l>One of the Nine (before of me ne'r seene, </l>
        <l>Sure sent by thee) assaults my merry spleene </l>
        <l>With mighty Verse; and makes me laugh at those </l>
        <l>That are so dull, to melt their thoughts in Prose. </l>
        <l>I wish her prosp'rous flight, may she returne </l>
        <l>With happier wings, if happier may be worne. </l>
        <l>My flame is spent. I dare not vndertake </l>
        <l>Thy praise, who am but newly for thy sake </l>
        <l>A fierce Poet, and doubtlesse had been one </l>
        <l>Ne'r but for thee, or else had been vnknowne. </l>
        <closer>
          <signed>Rog: Lorte. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000367-e101090">
        <head>To his much-honour'd friend, the Author. </head>
        <l>LEt not loud Enuy's sulph'rous blasts cast forth </l>
        <l>Venom'd aspersions, on thy noble worth: </l>
        <l>'Gainst saucy Criticks thou need'st no defence, </l>
        <l>Whose sacred lines, arm'd with sweet eloquence, </l>
        <l>Are proofe against their censures, whoo'd prophane. </l>
        <l>With their bold breath, the glory of thy straine: </l>
        <l>Wise came shall sing the prayse of thy deserts, </l>
        <l>And voyce thee glorious both in Armes and Arts. </l>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-004-b"/>
        <l>Whilst thou, releast from the Warres sad mishaps, </l>
        <l>Rests in soft dalliance on the Muses laps; </l>
        <l>Those beautious Ladies loue shall high aduance </l>
        <l>Thy fame, whose worth exceeds my vtterance. </l>
        <l>Their Tragicke falles, who in thy Scenes appeare, </l>
        <l>Shall on these Monuments faire Trophees reare </l>
        <l>Vnto their Fame. Thus are thy workes become </l>
        <l>To be to them, as their Elizium. </l>
        <closer>
          <signed>Tho: Ellice. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000367-e101280">
        <head>To his worthy friend, Mr. Wm. D'auenant. </head>
        <l>HAst thou vnmaskt thy Muse? And shall the Aire </l>
        <l>Breathe on her matchlesse Fabrick? then repaire. </l>
        <l>To some soft censure, lest the churlish sence </l>
        <l>Of Ignorance accrues thy recompence; </l>
        <l>And hudwinkt Error doe surprize the Fame </l>
        <l>Due to thy Story, and Verona's name, </l>
        <l>Whose limits Plinies and Catullus bred, </l>
        <l>But in thy Muse her ioyes are centupled: </l>
        <l>For her inuention, truth, rare wit, and state; </l>
        <l>Copper-lac'd Christians cannot personate. </l>
        <l>Her Tragick Scenes, like well-tun'd Chimes ith' Skie, </l>
        <l>Leaue Time loud Ecchoes of thy memorie. </l>
        <closer>
          <signed>H: Howard. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="ep000367-e101430">
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-005-a"/>
        <head>The Actors in this Tragedy. </head>
        <list>
          <item>Albouine, King of the Lombards. </item>
          <item>Paradine, A captiue Souldier, his Fauourite. </item>
          <item>Hermegild, A captiue Statesman, the Queenes Fauourite. </item>
          <item>Grimold, A rough old Captaine. </item>
          <item>Gondibert, A Captaine, his friend. </item>
          <item>Vollterri, A Souldier, friend to both. </item>
          <item>Cunymond, A Courtier. </item>
          <item>Conrade, His Companion. </item>
          <item>Frollo, His Companion. </item>
          <item>The Gouernour Of Verona. </item>
          <item>Rhodolinda, Captine, and Queene to Albouine. </item>
          <item>Valdaura, Wife to Paradine. </item>
          <item>Thesina, A Court-Lady. </item>
          <item>A Page To Paradine. </item>
          <item>A Gentleman, A Messenger. </item>
          <item>The Guard, Seruants, and Attendants, &amp;c. </item>
        </list>
        <p>The Scene, Verona. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <head>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-005-b"/>THE TRAGEDY OF ALBOVINE, KING OF THE LOMBARDS. </head>
      <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="ep000367-e101630">
        <head>Act the first. Scene first. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e101640">Enter Paradine, Grimoald, Gondibert; the Drummes ceasing. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e101650">
          <speaker>Paradine. </speaker>
          <p>Giue the word aloud? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e101670">
          <speaker>Grimo. </speaker>
          <p>Stand? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-unassigned" xml:id="ep000367-e101690">
          <speaker>Within. </speaker>
          <p n="1">1. Stand! 2. Stand! 3. Stand! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e101710">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Our motion has been swift: wee </l>
          <l>out-march Time. </l>
          <l>Verona, (which with the mornings dim eye </l>
          <l>We seem'd to view like Landschaip, afarre off) </l>
          <l>Is our full obiect now. She must repent; </l>
          <l>Our King is Steward vnto Fate; the world </l>
          <l>Receiue from him their destinies. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e101790">
          <speaker>Grimo. </speaker>
          <l>Sure, the Gouernour sleepes. My Lord, is't fit </l>
          <l>We waite vpon such Silkewormes, crepp'd in wooll? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e101820">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Since we attaind the Towne not by assault, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-006-a"/>
          <l>But composition free, he shall expresse </l>
          <l>Humilitie enough to meet vs at the Gate. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e101860">Enter Hermegild. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e101870">
          <speaker>Gondib. </speaker>
          <p>Here comes Hermegild. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e101890">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Haile, young souldier! My noble Paradine! </l>
          <l>The King must hold my nature much excus'd, </l>
          <l>If I do greet his safe approach with loue, </l>
          <l>Lesse violent then I expresse to thy </l>
          <l>Rich soule. I am resolu'd thou art in health, </l>
          <l>And fauour with thy starres. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e101960">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Ere I returne your kinde salute, I would </l>
          <l>After your faire charge inquire. Say the Queene </l>
          <l>Smiles in captiuitie, my Valdaura </l>
          <l>Hurts not her health with griefe; then I haue heard </l>
          <l>Enough to make me cherish life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e102020">
          <speaker>Hermig. </speaker>
          <l>Rhodolinda doth become her title </l>
          <l>And her birth. Since depriu'd of popular </l>
          <l>Homage, she hath been Queene ore her great selfe. </l>
          <l>In this captiuity nere passionate </l>
          <l>But when she heares me name the King, and then </l>
          <l>Her passions not of anger taste, but loue: </l>
          <l>Loue of her Conquerour: he that in fierce </l>
          <l>Battaile (when the Cannons sulpherous breath </l>
          <l>Clouded the day) her noble Father slew: </l>
          <l>Our Royall Master once; now sunke into </l>
          <l>His soyle; where like the Lilly wither'd, </l>
          <l>He neuer shall renew his growth agen. </l>
          <l>My memory disturbes my Tongue! Your faire </l>
          <l>Valdaura makes the Queene her rare and iust </l>
          <l>Example, and is in patience skilfull. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e102180">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Know, Hermegild, no hasty minute pass'd </l>
          <l>(Since their captiuitie) wherein I fail'd </l>
          <l>To be a sutor to the King for both. </l>
          <l>But he's in kindnesse prompt, and still doth speake </l>
          <l>Like Musicke, when he Rhodolinda names: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-006-b"/>
          <l>You heare tis his edict we call her Queene? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e102250">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Thy vanquish'd Country owes vnto thy fame </l>
          <l>A tall Pyramid! The captiu'd virgins </l>
          <l>Of our Nation shall in their last Dirges </l>
          <l>Sing thy prayse with mirth. O, I could grow old </l>
          <l>Within thy sight. Something we now must talke </l>
          <l>Together, and heauen will listen to't, </l>
          <l>As to the breath of Saints— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e102330">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>I knew we should haue vse of conference: </l>
          <l>Which made me begge the leading of the Vanne, </l>
          <l>The more t'assist our opportune meeting. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e102370">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>Afford your eares in priuat. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e102390">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Though Paradine looke flourishing, and like </l>
          <l>A thing new brush'd; a flame of triumph, </l>
          <l>(As if his father surfetted in some </l>
          <l>O're-growne City when he got him) yet he </l>
          <l>Hath in him seeds of warre, bold thoughts, and we </l>
          <l>I'th Campe, esteeme him honest too. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e102460">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <p>He is our Kings Minion, sleepes in his bosome. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e102480">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>True, &amp; the Royall foole greets him with such </l>
          <l>Rauenous kisses, that you would thinke, he meant </l>
          <l>To eate his lips. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e102520">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <l>The Captiue captiuates the Conquerour. </l>
          <l>Three Moones haue not expir'd their vsuall change, </l>
          <l>Since he was prisoner to the King; though now </l>
          <l>His Fauorite. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e102570">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Th'art too loud! If thou'lt talke safely, go get </l>
          <l>A sore throat; hoarce men speake low. </l>
          <l>The captiu'd Rhodolinda, (whose father </l>
          <l>Albouine depriu'd of life and kingdome) </l>
          <l>Hath with such amorous subtiltie behau'd </l>
          <l>Her gesture, that Albouine is now her </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-007-a"/>
          <l>Prisoner. This martiall progresse was but made </l>
          <l>To visit her. She makes him guilty of </l>
          <l>Idolatry, and knowes the thrifty vse </l>
          <l>Of time: as she ascends, her Countrimen </l>
          <l>Must rise. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e102690">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <p>You haue call'd that Hermegild her Creature? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e102710">
          <speaker>Grimo. </speaker>
          <l>He was her fathers Councellor; a man </l>
          <l>Created in the darke: he walkes inuisibly; </l>
          <l>He dwels in Labyrinths; he loues silence: </l>
          <l>But when he talkes, his language carries more </l>
          <l>Promiscuous sense, then ancient Oracles. </l>
          <l>So various in his shapes, that oft he is </l>
          <l>Disguiz'd from his owne knowledge. An error </l>
          <l>Much incident to humane Politicks, </l>
          <l>Who striue to know others more then themselues. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e102810">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <p>Obserue their complement. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e102830">
          <speaker>Grimo. </speaker>
          <l>Pox o' these French ligges? Courtiers alwaies dance. </l>
          <l>This is to Hermegild meere lechery: </l>
          <l>This wanton gesture doth obscure </l>
          <l>Thoughts of such consequence and weight, as hang </l>
          <l>Like Plummets on his heart. Paradine is </l>
          <l>A soft, easie foole, and must be guld. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e102900">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>O my sweet Lord— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e102920">
          <speaker>Grimo. </speaker>
          <p>Now the Motion speakes. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e102940">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Such indeerements would too much impouerish </l>
          <l>My gratitude: yet, tis meet our actions </l>
          <l>Carry smooth equalitie: your consent </l>
          <l>Must further all my Sutes You are the Kings </l>
          <l>Iewell, and hang richly in his eare. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e103000">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>You are precious vnto her, whom loud noise </l>
          <l>Already calls our Queene: faire Rhodolinda! </l>
          <l>We may (if they prooue naturall and kinde) </l>
          <l>Gouerne the Nation that hath conquered vs; </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-007-b"/>
          <l>Gaine our Countrey liberty, and yet </l>
          <l>Not stray from noble Arts: such hopes our free </l>
          <l>Imbraces prophecy. The King. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e103080">Loud musick. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e103090">Enter Albouine, Frollo, Conrade, Vollterri, &amp;c. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-frollo" xml:id="ep000367-e103100">
          <speaker>Frollo. </speaker>
          <l>Your Troopes (Sir) are so diuided into </l>
          <l>Mix'd files, that to the City you doe march </l>
          <l>Betweene thick walles of men. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e103140">
          <speaker>Albou. </speaker>
          <l>Let my Horse-guard bring vp the Rere. We'le sport </l>
          <l>With warre. We haue no vse of safety now, </l>
          <l>But of magnificence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-vollterri" xml:id="ep000367-e103180">
          <speaker>Vollterri. </speaker>
          <l>The order is already giuen. It was </l>
          <l>Your Royall will, we hasten in our March, </l>
          <l>Therefore each Squadron double their paces. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e103220">
          <speaker>Albou. </speaker>
          <l>My Boy, I bring thee home my chiefe Trophy: </l>
          <l>Thou dost delight me more then victory. </l>
          <l>Retire. I am in loue too violent. </l>
          <l>My embraces crush thee, thou art but yet </l>
          <l>Of tender growth— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e103280">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>My Countriman would kisse your Royal hands, </l>
          <l>And then expect no greater happinesse </l>
          <l>Till he arriue in heauen. He hath done your </l>
          <l>Rhodolinda seruice— <stage xml:id="ep000367-e103330">Presents Hermeg. on his knee to the King. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e103340">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Rhodolinda is your humblest captiue. </l>
          <l>She inserts you often in her prayers, </l>
          <l>And call'd it my chiefe duty to present </l>
          <l>Her true seruice to your Maiesty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e103390">
          <speaker>Albou. </speaker>
          <l>Her name doth inrich our Language. My boy </l>
          <l>Can witnesse that I loue her: she makes me </l>
          <l>Prattle in my sleepe: I'ue drunke Mandragora, </l>
          <l>To become drowzie, in hope that I might </l>
          <l>Dreame of her. Rise, and expect Honour. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e103450">
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-008-a"/>Enter Gouernour of Verona. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-governor" xml:id="ep000367-e103460">
          <speaker>Gouernour. </speaker>
          <l>High and sacred Maiesty! Verona </l>
          <l>Hath vnhindg'd her wide Gates: proud to admit </l>
          <l>The fate of Kingdomes. Our crooked Matrones </l>
          <l>Forget their age: and (as the ragged Earth </l>
          <l>At the Springs warme approach) look fresh, &amp; young, </l>
          <l>To intertaine you. Our timorous Virgins </l>
          <l>(With the bold Youth) ioyne in one wanton Quire </l>
          <l>To sing your welcome. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e103550">
          <speaker>Grimo. </speaker>
          <p>How the Spaniell fawnes, 'cause he dares not barke? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-governor" xml:id="ep000367-e103570">
          <speaker>Gouer. </speaker>
          <l>Th'amorous Vine clips not the shady Poplar </l>
          <l>With such regard (about whose mossie waste </l>
          <l>She hangs a smiling Louer.) Our City is </l>
          <l>By the reflection of your blest approach </l>
          <l>Like Pelion deck'd, whom Tython's Mistresse </l>
          <l>(Leauing the weeping East) with brightnesse guilds. </l>
          <l>There's not a wrinkle left in all Verona, </l>
          <l>Wherein pale sorrow, or rebellious enuy </l>
          <l>Can finde their loathed Mansion. Flattering ioy </l>
          <l>Swells big each loyall bosome. All implore </l>
          <l>You as their safety; who hath hush'd the noise </l>
          <l>Of discord, and loud warre. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e103700">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>The Rascall flatters, as if he had seru'd </l>
          <l>His prentiship in Court. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e103730">
          <speaker>Albou. </speaker>
          <l>Th'ast done me iustice, Gouernor, &amp; know'st </l>
          <l>The way to make me thankefull, but not proud. </l>
          <l>I vnderstand thou hast with honor'd safety </l>
          <l>Preseru'd those Iewels to thy charge committed, </l>
          <l>(My Rhodolinda, and my Boys Valdaura.) </l>
          <l>And so increas'd new motiues of our thanks. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-governor" xml:id="ep000367-e103800">
          <speaker>Gouer. </speaker>
          <l>Heauen has made your memory too humble, </l>
          <l>Thus to record your creatures seruice. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-008-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e103830">
          <speaker>Albou. </speaker>
          <l>Let now the knotty Laborer rust with ease, </l>
          <l>And aloud proclaime, that the vpland Boore </l>
          <l>Release his Teeme, and his industrious Plough. </l>
          <l>Let him sing glad Iös to the rustick </l>
          <l>Powers that guard his fields, and vnto me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-governor" xml:id="ep000367-e103890">
          <speaker>Gouern. </speaker>
          <l>It is by you we are: no warlike Ram, </l>
          <l>Nor battering engine forc'd a bloody entrance </l>
          <l>Through our thicke walls. It was the powerfull breath </l>
          <l>Of your victorious fame, that conquer'd vs. </l>
          <l>To that we yeelded: which as a rough blast </l>
          <l>That poasts from the cold Artick Pole, hath borne </l>
          <l>Before it captiu'd Nations. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e103970">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>By heauen a good old man! if he be learn'd, </l>
          <l>Ile haue him write my Annales. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e104000">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <p>Indeed he lookes like a Chronicler. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e104020">
          <speaker>Albou. </speaker>
          <l>Paradine? Informe him of my deeds. </l>
          <l>Thou hast beheld my discipline full of </l>
          <l>Shape and order, when confusion did oppresse </l>
          <l>The foe, and stifled them in throngs. Hah! Looke! </l>
          <l>Rhodolinda's come to guild our Triumph! </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e104080">Enter Rhodolinda, Valdaura, Thesina, and Attendants in mourning. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e104090">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>And my Valdaura too! let Nature shew </l>
          <l>A third obiect so delightfull, we'le sweare </l>
          <l>She is not old, nor her first materials </l>
          <l>Wasted, but in creation still retaines </l>
          <l>Her former strength and skill. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e104150">
          <speaker>Albou </speaker>
          <l>But why (my beautious Captiue) art thou still </l>
          <l>In Sables wrapp'd? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e104180">
          <speaker>Rhodo. </speaker>
          <l>Your starres bid you be happy. My crosse fate </l>
          <l>Like the Rauen, croaks a funerall note: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-009-a"/>
          <l>This swarthy habit, but paints forth the griefe </l>
          <l>That chaines my soule in darknesse. And filiall loue </l>
          <l>Commands me mourne for him, whom you too soone </l>
          <l>Depriu'd of life, my conquer'd father. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e104250">
          <speaker>Albou. </speaker>
          <l>Let his ashes rest </l>
          <l>At quiet in their Vrne. His ghost long since </l>
          <l>Hath wash'd away the memory of his fate </l>
          <l>In slow-pac'd Laethe. Take me, modest faire, </l>
          <l>Into thy bosome. O hide me there! </l>
          <l>My glad soule, how full is thy content? </l>
          <l>Now thou fear'd thing, that guid'st the heauenly Empire, </l>
          <l>Rend all the murmuring clouds, and dart </l>
          <l>Thy Thunder at me: I am safe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e104350">
          <speaker>Rhodo. </speaker>
          <l>My captiuity must needs seeme easie, </l>
          <l>Whilst the Conquerour proues so kinde. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e104380">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>I could gaze thus on thee, till my wonder </l>
          <l>Did conuert me into marble; and yet </l>
          <l>My soule would in her selfe retaine a fire, </l>
          <l>Liuely as that which bold Prometheus stole. </l>
          <l>Were the Sea coagulate, and the world </l>
          <l>Returnd to th' antick Chaos, a blinde Lumpe; </l>
          <l>Thy looke would force the warring elements </l>
          <l>Into a sacred order; and beget </l>
          <l>A harmony like this they now inioy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e104480">
          <speaker>Rhodo. </speaker>
          <p>You are too powerfull in you speech. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e104500">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Yet when I valew thus thy excellence, </l>
          <l>Let me not forget my owne high being. </l>
          <l>I'ue humbled all the Nations of the earth; </l>
          <l>Brought home as spoyles the whole wealth of Nature: </l>
          <l>Yet, Rhodolinda, nought like thee. Let me </l>
          <l>Whisper my content, for soft musicke most </l>
          <l>Delights the female eare. <stage xml:id="ep000367-e104580">They walke aside. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e104590">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Why, my deare Valdaura, dost thou suspect </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-009-b"/>
          <l>My warme embraces? Let hungry death ceaze </l>
          <l>On my honour, before it ceaze on me, </l>
          <l>If in my brest I intertaine a thought </l>
          <l>Vnlawfull. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e104650">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>I esteeme you (Sir) a friend to vertue, </l>
          <l>And in that hope would cherish all your loue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e104680">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>In thy faire brow, there's such a Legend writ </l>
          <l>Of timorous chastitie, that it doth blinde </l>
          <l>Th'adulterous Eye. Not the Mountaine Ice, </l>
          <l>(Congeal'd to Christall) is so frosty chaste </l>
          <l>As thy victorious soule, which conquers Man, </l>
          <l>And Mans proud Tyrant-passion. But I am </l>
          <l>Too rough for Courtship, the soft harmony </l>
          <l>Which wanton Peace instructs the Tongue to make, </l>
          <l>I haue forgot. Trust me (bright Maid!) </l>
          <l>I loue thee dearely. Though I'ue found thy heart </l>
          <l>Like Pibble, smooth, but stony. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e104800">
          <speaker>Valda. </speaker>
          <l>I'ue heard my mother say: the curled Youth </l>
          <l>Of Italy, were prompt in wanton stealths, </l>
          <l>And sinfull Arts. Till Time had giuen me </l>
          <l>Assurance of your noble thoughts; 'twas safe </l>
          <l>To doubt your loue. But now I wish I were </l>
          <l>More worthy, and then would prooue more liberall </l>
          <l>Of my selfe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e104880">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Let me enioy thy hand! that moyst Adamant </l>
          <l>That so attracts my soule! We will (ere night </l>
          <l>Her black Curtaine drawes) make compleat this loue, </l>
          <l>With marriage Rites. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e104930">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>How now, Boy! Is my interest so decay'd </l>
          <l>In your young person, that you giue away your selfe </l>
          <l>Without my leaue! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e104970">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Humbly on my knee, I beg the vulgar </l>
          <l>Priuiledge due to all hearts. To loue, and not enioy, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-010-a"/>
          <l>Is a torture, I cannot suffer long, </l>
          <l>And still remaine possess'd with breath. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e105020">
          <speaker>Albou. </speaker>
          <l>Thou hast shew'd me physick for my passion. </l>
          <l>Take him, Valdaura, and be proud! Tis I </l>
          <l>That loue him: nor shall your ioyes be single. </l>
          <l>Ile make the number yet more full. This day </l>
          <l>We'le consecrate to Hymens vse. Behold </l>
          <l>Your Queene (who though my Captiue) for her birth </l>
          <l>And beauty, is the first of Queenes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-governor" xml:id="ep000367-e105100">
          <speaker>Gouer. </speaker>
          <p>High Heauen increase your ioyes! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e105120">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>And may you liue together vntill Time </l>
          <l>Shall sicken with his age. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-frollo" xml:id="ep000367-e105150">
          <speaker>Frollo. </speaker>
          <p>Conrad. Long liue Albouine, King of the Lombards! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e105170">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>Cry vp Rhodolinda too! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-frollo" xml:id="ep000367-e105190">
          <speaker>Frollo. </speaker>
          <p>Conrad. Liue Rhodolinda, Queene of the Lombards! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e105210">
          <speaker>Alb. </speaker>
          <l>Gouernor! Tis our will that you expect </l>
          <l>Honour, and true safety. Your Cities loue </l>
          <l>I shall perceiue by popular noise, and your </l>
          <l>Behauiour in this great solemnitie. </l>
          <l>Let the Sunne smile; the Winde sport with our Plumes! </l>
          <l>This day let sick-men too forget to groane. </l>
          <l>Let all glad Hymnes in one mix'd concord sound, </l>
          <l>And make the ecchoing heauen your mirth rebound. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e105300">Exeunt all, but Grimold, Vollterri, Gondibert. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e105310">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <p>The King's head must now conuert to rotten wood. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e105330">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <p>Why, Grimold? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e105350">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>That Court Earewiggs may liue there, and deuoure </l>
          <l>His brains. Dost not perceiue how they begin </l>
          <l>To creepe into his eares? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e105390">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <l>Generous soules are still most subiect to </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-010-b"/>
          <l>Credulitie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e105420">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>He is a Germane in his drinke: busied </l>
          <l>With a wanton pride, which his Flatterers </l>
          <l>Admire for mirth, but his friends doe pitie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-vollterri" xml:id="ep000367-e105460">
          <speaker>Vollt. </speaker>
          <p>He should be told his sinnes. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e105480">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>By whom? Vollterri, now the King forsakes </l>
          <l>The Campe, he must maintaine luxurious mouthes, </l>
          <l>Such as can vtter perfum'd breath, and these </l>
          <l>Straite compose a faction, engrosse his eares. </l>
          <l>They limit still his conuersation. </l>
          <l>Euen as the slow finger of the Diall </l>
          <l>Doth in its motion circular remoue </l>
          <l>To distant figures: so by a subtill </l>
          <l>Leasure, they doe prefix the houres, </l>
          <l>When he must change his rotten Parasite, </l>
          <l>For one more skilfull, how t'admire, and praise. </l>
          <l>No honest Tongue can euer interpose </l>
          <l>To tell him he is mortall. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e105620">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <l>It is the chiefe misery of Princes, </l>
          <l>Nere to vnderstand their owne crimes, to sinne </l>
          <l>In ignorance. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e105660">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>True, his Confessor, that in sight externe </l>
          <l>A Patriarke seemes, will gaine by flattery, </l>
          <l>And superscribe vnto the King, as to the Pope </l>
          <l>(His holinesse.) But Gondibert, </l>
          <l>Whom Conclaues here in Court doe canonize </l>
          <l>For Saints, will scarce be admitted in heauen </l>
          <l>For Angels. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-vollterri" xml:id="ep000367-e105740">
          <speaker>Vollter. </speaker>
          <l>Now Rhodolinda is become his Riuall </l>
          <l>In high Soueraigntie, she will permit </l>
          <l>No errors but her owne: The King must mend </l>
          <l>What she mislikes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e105790">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>She giues vs leasure to expect </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-011-a"/>
          <l>Her character. Women make themselues more known </l>
          <l>When they doe rule, then when th'obey. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e105830">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <l>Valdaura is inrich'd with a sweetnesse </l>
          <l>So religious, that Paradine must sinne </l>
          <l>In priuate, or need no mercy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e105870">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Th'ast nam'd her! Though my obdurate sufferance </l>
          <l>In actiue warre hath quite depriu'd me of </l>
          <l>All amorous gesture. Though not these forty </l>
          <l>Winters, I haue seene any of her sex </l>
          <l>But Suttlers wiues, who, in stead of Fillets, </l>
          <l>Wrap their sooty haire in Horses girts. Though </l>
          <l>My marrow is frozen in my bones, </l>
          <l>Yet I melt before her eyes. When I see her, </l>
          <l>I grow proud below the Nauell. For she </l>
          <l>Is none o' th' French Noursery, that practice </l>
          <l>The sublime friske. None o' your jigging Girles, </l>
          <l>That pearch Paraqueeto's on their fists, </l>
          <l>And ride toth' Court like Venus Falconers. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e106010">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <l>Grimold, hoarce men speake low, thou hast not caught </l>
          <l>A cold yet. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e106040">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>She's none of those that on their heads aduance </l>
          <l>High, swagg'ring Plumes, like a gay Forehorse </l>
          <l>In a Country Teeme. O, she's worth the tempting! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-vollterri" xml:id="ep000367-e106080">
          <speaker>Vollter. </speaker>
          <l>Dost thou so commend her vertues, and yet </l>
          <l>Wouldst thou tempt her vnto vice? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e106110">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>That's a trick I learnt of the deuill. Those </l>
          <l>That are vertuous, need his temptation, </l>
          <l>The wicked haue power enough to damne themselues. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e106150">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <l>Hark how they showte! Away Grimold, or we </l>
          <l>Shall lose the Triumph! </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e106180">Showting within. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e106190">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Roome for Cuckolds, whose hornes are so high, </l>
          <l>They bore the Moone, as she friskes in the skie! </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e106220">Exeunt omnes. </stage>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="ep000367-e106230">
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-011-b"/>
        <head>Act the second. Scene first. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e106240">Enter Grimold, Gondibert, Vollterri. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e106250">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>This Peace makes me rotten, dusty </l>
          <l>As a Cobweb. I liue like a Cricket </l>
          <l>ith' corner of an Ouen. Pox o' these oregrowne </l>
          <l>Cities. To be valiant here, is to forfeit </l>
          <l>The Statute: and these furr'd gownes hold, </l>
          <l>There is no sinne so great as pouerty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e106320">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <p>Thou art as melancholy as a leane Iudge! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e106340">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>I, or a corrupted Officer, at the noise </l>
          <l>Of a Parliament. In this diuision </l>
          <l>Of vnualewed Tropheys, Territories </l>
          <l>Vast and ample, (gain'd partly by my sweat) </l>
          <l>Not a single Acre falls to my share. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e106400">Enter Cunymond, Frollo, Conrade, Seruants with a Banquet. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e106410">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <l>Beare back there! They thrust as if they meant </l>
          <l>To get me with child— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-frollo" xml:id="ep000367-e106440">
          <speaker>Frollo. </speaker>
          <l>You sirrah! d'ye get the Kings officer </l>
          <l>With child? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-conrade" xml:id="ep000367-e106470">
          <speaker>Conr. </speaker>
          <l>Beare back there! or we'le put ye to the charge </l>
          <l>Of Surgery— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e106500">
          <speaker>Cuni. </speaker>
          <p>Dispatch, fellowes! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e106520">
          <speaker>Gondib. </speaker>
          <p>Is not that Cunymond? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e106540">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>The same. He is a great Astrologer. </l>
          <l>The meere Anotamy i'th front o'th Kalender. </l>
          <l>You may know where the Signe is, by some toy </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-012-a"/>
          <l>In's habit, which he remoues, as the Signe </l>
          <l>Remoues. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e106600">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <p>Frollo, did they enter here by your permission? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-frollo" xml:id="ep000367-e106620">
          <speaker>Frollo. </speaker>
          <p>Not by mine, Sir. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e106640">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <p>Nor yours, Conrade? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-conrade" xml:id="ep000367-e106660">
          <speaker>Conrad. </speaker>
          <p>They are men of China for ought I know. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e106680">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <l>Then they must out. Gentlemen, pray auoide </l>
          <l>The Presence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e106710">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <p>'S death Sir! d'ye make vs your Voyders? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-vollterri" xml:id="ep000367-e106730">
          <speaker>Vollter. </speaker>
          <l>Must we carry away your Cheese-parings? </l>
          <l>Thrust your Bodkins forth! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e106760">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <p>Draw i'th Presence? Art thou mad? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e106780">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>How he stands? he is created of Starch, </l>
          <l>And dares not vse a boysterous motion, </l>
          <l>Lest he should fall in Rumples. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e106820">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <l>Sir, you may speake like a Cannon! but you </l>
          <l>Shall either goe, or— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e106850">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <p>Or what, Sir? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e106870">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <p>Or stay, Sir. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-conrade" xml:id="ep000367-e106890">
          <speaker>Conrad. </speaker>
          <l>By heauen he shall doe one, Sir— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-frollo" xml:id="ep000367-e106910">
          <speaker>Frollo. </speaker>
          <l>Nay, Captaine, doe not look, as if y'had drunk </l>
          <l>Vineger. You must, or go, or— stay Sir— </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e106940">Loud knocking. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e106950">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <l>Hey! we are tumbling in a Drum. </l>
          <l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000367-e106980">Within .</stage>Fellowes o' the Guard, make way there! Officers! </l>
          <l>Open the doore— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e107000">
          <speaker>Cun. </speaker>
          <l>Beare back there! Gentlemen! what d'ye meane? </l>
          <l>Pray' beare back— </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e107030">Loud Musicke. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e107040">Enter Albouine, Rhodolinda, Paradine, Valdaura, Hermegild, Thesina, &amp;c. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e107050">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Phoebus will be thought more rash then Phaeton, </l>
          <l>If now he hasten to the West. Sir, this </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-012-b"/>
          <l>Glorious day, merits well a longer age, </l>
          <l>Then what is limitted to all within </l>
          <l>Our Kalender. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e107110">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>Hermegild, thy free heart adds to our triumph! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e107130">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Sir, I'ue some few words, I needs must vtter: </l>
          <l>Since my last seruices in Hungary, </l>
          <l>You remaine on my Tally six thousand </l>
          <l>Duckats: I'm loth to skore vp still, and pay </l>
          <l>My selfe with my owne Chalke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e107190">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>Wouldst haue thy Soule dismissed a naturall way? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e107210">
          <speaker>Gri. </speaker>
          <l>I would not starue, looke, like a parch'd Anotamy </l>
          <l>Sow'd in a Kid-skin. Pay your debts, Sir! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e107240">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>I neuer met with boldnesse, vntill now! </l>
          <l>My courage is quite puzled! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e107270">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Do your eares blister to heare this? My breath is </l>
          <l>Wholsome. I cannot tipple like a Duck </l>
          <l>In a greene Poole. Nor feed on Berries in </l>
          <l>A Hedge, like some lost remnant o' my fathers </l>
          <l>Scatterd lust. Sir, pay your debts! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e107330">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>Sure, thou art some spirit! I cannot kill thee! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e107350">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>In this diuision of the Lands, I help'd </l>
          <l>To conquer; I am not furnish'd with </l>
          <l>A Mole-hill for a pillow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e107390">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Hermegild sat chiefe in the Committee </l>
          <l>For diuision of those Lands: bid him reward </l>
          <l>Your seruice: besides, I mistake the custome, </l>
          <l>Or tis my Treasurers office to pay </l>
          <l>My debts, not mine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e107450">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>No Sir, (thanks to your Royall thrift) it is </l>
          <l>Your office to pay all; your Treasurers </l>
          <l>Custome to pay nothing. <stage xml:id="ep000367-e107490">Thrusts him away. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e107500">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>Do not interrupt my marriage Rites! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e107520">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <p>I cannot take your reference for paiment. </p>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-013-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e107540">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>Would thou wert dead! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e107560">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Sir, Ile make my Ghost, my Executor, </l>
          <l>And walke after death, ere Ile lose my mony. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e107590">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Sit, my Rhodolinda: This is thy Spheare! </l>
          <l>In th'absence of the Sunne, we must receiue </l>
          <l>Our light from thee. Paradine, thy Bride expects </l>
          <l>Thy seruice. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e107640">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Sh'as an ill bargaine on't, to rule one night, </l>
          <l>And euer after to obey. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e107670">
          <speaker>Her. </speaker>
          <l>Captaine, though the King be prompt in mercy, </l>
          <l>Yet hath he so much anger in him, </l>
          <l>As will expresse him mortall. Tis for your </l>
          <l>Safety, to auoid the Presence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e107720">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <p>Ile bribe your Lordship with a Ginny Tooth-pick! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e107740">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>You must repent this language. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e107760">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>He must not, Hermegild! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e107780">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>How, my Lord! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e107800">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>These whom you number in your faction, </l>
          <l>Enioy, by your assistance, proud structures; </l>
          <l>And fertill Granges, to maintaine their gaudy </l>
          <l>Riot. Sir, you had a fraile memory, </l>
          <l>Or a degenerate heart, when you forgot </l>
          <l>His merit; might you incorporate those in one, </l>
          <l>The sordid bulke could nere make vp his shadow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e107880">
          <speaker>Hermeg. </speaker>
          <p>I am prescrib'd my discipline in Court! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e107900">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Grimold, away! Tis my desire you leaue </l>
          <l>The Presence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e107930">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <p>I am obedient (Sir) to your desire. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e107950">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <p>'Slight, thou hast made a braue retreat. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-vollterri" xml:id="ep000367-e107970">
          <speaker>Vollt. </speaker>
          <l>I look'd when both of vs should taste </l>
          <l>Of immortalitie. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e108000">Exeunt Grimo. Gond. Vollt. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e108010">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>He that inflam'd this fire, will scorch his busie </l>
          <l>Fingers. My Lord, it was vnkindly done </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-013-b"/>
          <l>T'affront my anger thus: but I haue hope </l>
          <l>It is your last fault. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e108060">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>I cannot reckon it among my faults. </l>
          <l>Sir, you inuolue your meaning in your speech. </l>
          <l>The world shall finde me honest. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e108100">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>You are a Bridegroome now. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e108120">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Hermegild, make your anger knowne, </l>
          <l>For else your frownes will cause your loyaltie </l>
          <l>To be suspected. This night should be as smooth </l>
          <l>And pleasant, as that to which we owe our bless'd </l>
          <l>Natiuitie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e108180">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Sir, you are great on Earth! I am meerely </l>
          <l>Your creation. My passions doe afford </l>
          <l>Your high delight all sympathy. </l>
          <l>Old Time hath throwne his feathers from his heeles, </l>
          <l>And slowly limps in's motion to prolong </l>
          <l>This Triumph: but if Paradine affront </l>
          <l>Hymen, and me with sullen rage, it shall </l>
          <l>Be call'd my piety to suffer. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e108270">Rhodo. stands vp. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e108280">
          <speaker>Rho. </speaker>
          <l>How! your Excellence ought t'excuse my speech! </l>
          <l>When your victorious sword depriu'd me of </l>
          <l>My Father; I enter'd to captiuity, </l>
          <l>As to th'oblique shade, where death inhabits. </l>
          <l>Till you allowd me Hermegild; who with </l>
          <l>His high Philosophy did make </l>
          <l>My bondage sweete. My Father lou'd him well: </l>
          <l>He was his noblest Seruant, and must not </l>
          <l>For his vertues suffer, vntill your sacred tongue </l>
          <l>Forbid me share with you in Soueraignty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e108390">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Boy, this was a bold crime. You must not giue </l>
          <l>Me cause to chide my fond heart. Valdaura, </l>
          <l>Vrge him to proffer friendship </l>
          <l>Vnto Hermegild; you are powerfull </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-014-a"/>
          <l>Ore his nature. I haue deseru'd to lose </l>
          <l>My chiefe prerogatiue— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e108460">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>I am too timorous to deale with anger: </l>
          <l>If he prooue sterne of nature, my Marriage </l>
          <l>Is my funerall. My Lord! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e108500">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Paradine, I'ue an humble loue. I will </l>
          <l>Present it first to your refusall— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e108530">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>I want your phrase, to make my manners seeme </l>
          <l>Lesse rugged. All that is loue, I cherish </l>
          <l>With such religious heate, as my Valdaura </l>
          <l>Claimes, since our young Nuptiall— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e108580">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>This embracement is a sacrifice </l>
          <l>To thee my Queene: whose deity </l>
          <l>Consists of loue. Sit, and with your </l>
          <l>Persons, straight intrench the Table. Some wine! </l>
          <l>Fill in my Germane Plate; Ile drinke as when </l>
          <l>I'm hot with victory. This to my Bride— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e108650">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <p>Sound high! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e108670">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>More wine, and noise! Now Boy, I celebrate </l>
          <l>Valdaura's health— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e108700">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <l>Bid their Instruments speake lowder. </l>
          <l>They're afraid to wake the Neighbours. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e108730">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>This is legitimate blood of the rich </l>
          <l>Corsick Grape: precious as thy teares </l>
          <l>(My Royall Girle) when thou art penitent </l>
          <l>To heauen. <stage xml:id="ep000367-e108780">Whilest the King talkes, they drinke. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e108790">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Spare me in the next, and Ile esteeme you </l>
          <l>Courteous; so much wine will put me to the charge </l>
          <l>Of Physicke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e108830">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <p>Your Lordship ownes it as a prime vertue— </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e108850">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Shall the world bleed? but frowne, and thou renew'st </l>
          <l>A Chaos. Maligne the pride of some farre </l>
          <l>Easterne Queene, whom Trauellers bely, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-014-b"/>
          <l>And I will forage there, like loud thunder! </l>
          <l>Or like the Northerne winde vpon the Maine, </l>
          <l>Where lazie Hulkes are toss'd like chips. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e108920">
          <speaker>Rhodo. </speaker>
          <p>I merit no such complement. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e108940">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Ile do't. Tis thought, I am immortall. </l>
          <l>The chiefe of my great Ancestors, that made </l>
          <l>A wilde incursion ore this fertill soile, </l>
          <l>Was but a tipe of me. More wine!— Thy breath </l>
          <l>Is as the smoke of spices. I taste thy </l>
          <l>Melting lippes, and straight ingender kisses. </l>
          <l>Heart! Boy, you are too rauenous! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e109020">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>I euer held your Maiesty my best </l>
          <l>Example. Kisses nimbly gather'd, </l>
          <l>The faster grow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e109060">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>The Lombards vse to share this sport! <stage xml:id="ep000367-e109080">He kisses Thesina. </stage>
          </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e109090">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>Is not your name Pigwiggin? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e109110">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <l>Pigwiggin! your Grace was wont to call me </l>
          <l>Cunymond: I am no Faery. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e109140">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Nor I the King of Faeries. 'Slight, sir, d'ye </l>
          <l>Present me with a Cup, made, o'th bottome </l>
          <l>Of an Akehorne, or Queene Mabbs Thimble? </l>
          <l>Fill me a bowle, where I may swimme, </l>
          <l>And bathe my head, then rise like Phoebus from </l>
          <l>The Ocean, shaking my dewy Locks. </l>
          <l>A health to Cesars memory. Boy, doe me </l>
          <l>Iustice, or thou afrontst my Triumph! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e109230">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>Conrade, the King will drowne vs all! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-conrade" xml:id="ep000367-e109250">
          <speaker>Conr. </speaker>
          <p>Y'haue now, Sir, but the moiety of his draught. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e109270">
          <speaker>Rhodo. </speaker>
          <l>Though Fame lends you her Trumpet, giues you leaue </l>
          <l>To speake your owne praise, you cannot vtter more </l>
          <l>Then my beliefe shall warrant. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e109310">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Now thou whisper'st like the amorous Lute! </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-015-a"/>
          <l>I am the Broome of Heauen, when th'world grows foule, </l>
          <l>Ile sweepe the Nations into'th Sea, like dust. </l>
          <l>Thy father was magnanimous, and great </l>
          <l>King of the Girpides. Yet his title </l>
          <l>Sat not so nobly on him, as my conquest. </l>
          <l>Know, his vnkind fate, was his chiefe glory: </l>
          <l>For it was I that slew him; and thou his </l>
          <l>Captiu'd Daughter art my Queene. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e109410">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Sir, if you continue this narration, </l>
          <l>I shall weepe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e109440">
          <speaker>Albou. </speaker>
          <l>Doe, weepe! then on my heart-strings I will thread </l>
          <l>Thy teares in stead of Pearle: such a wealthy </l>
          <l>Bracelet, loue would present vnto his Queene: </l>
          <l>And she tuck vp her sleeues, to shew her gawdy wrists. </l>
          <l>More wine! Bring vs the Bowle of Victory. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e109500">Exit Cunymond. Paradine kneeles. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e109510">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Sir, you ingag'd your Royall word, neuer </l>
          <l>To present that fatall obiect. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e109540">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Paradine, doe not resist my pleasure. </l>
          <l>Ile crush thee into Ayre. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e109570">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>I am in my ambition vertuous, </l>
          <l>If I desire t'expire a sacrifice </l>
          <l>To loyaltie. Sir, ruine what you made, </l>
          <l>But doe not violate your Vow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e109620">
          <speaker>Albou. </speaker>
          <l>Hence! I shall delight in fury! </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000367-e109640">Enter Cunymond with a Skull, made into a drinking-Bowle. </stage>
          <l>Welcome, the horrid Trophey of my chiefe warre! </l>
          <l>Rhodolinda, Ile try thy fortitude. </l>
          <l>This was thy Fathers Skull: thou shalt pledge a health </l>
          <l>Vnto his Ghost. <stage xml:id="ep000367-e109690">He drinks: all rise vp. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-015-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e109700">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>O fatall! my eies shrinke within my brow! </l>
          <l>I gather Agues like the Spring, and tremble </l>
          <l>Like the vnlick'd Lambe, newly yeand vpon </l>
          <l>A sheete of Snow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e109750">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>Hide me, Paradine! the obiect doth so </l>
          <l>Penetrate, that when I winke, I spie it </l>
          <l>Through my Lids. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e109790">
          <speaker>Albou. </speaker>
          <l>Tame, feeble Soule! Will she not pledge </l>
          <l>What we doe celebrate? Returne her person— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e109820">
          <speaker>Cunym. </speaker>
          <l>Madam, the King— <stage xml:id="ep000367-e109840">Strikes him, and exit. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e109850">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>The King's a Tyrant, and thou his slaue. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-frollo" xml:id="ep000367-e109870">
          <speaker>Frollo. </speaker>
          <p>That's a fauour, Signior. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e109890">
          <speaker>Cunym. </speaker>
          <p>I weare it as a Iewell in my eare. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e109910">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Fly, deare Valdaura; sweeten her censure </l>
          <l>Of this act, and mediate for the King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e109940">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>Thesina, prethee helpe me in discourse; </l>
          <l>My wonder (Wench) doth so disturbe my speech, </l>
          <l>I feare I shall grow dumbe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e109980">
          <speaker>Thesi. </speaker>
          <p>The work is pious we attempt. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e110000">Exeunt Vald. Thes. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e110010">
          <speaker>Her. </speaker>
          <l>The harmony of your sweet tongue is his </l>
          <l>Best physicke: diuorce him from those black thoughts, </l>
          <l>Whil'st I imploy my vtmost skill, to win </l>
          <l>The Queene to his imbraces. She's great of Soule, </l>
          <l>And may determine what my fond heart laments </l>
          <l>To prophecy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e110080">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>Y'are my best Countriman, kind and loyall. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e110100">Exit Herm. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e110110">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>So pale and timorous! Ile sooner couple </l>
          <l>With a Mandrake, and beget groanes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e110140">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>My Royall Lord! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e110160">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Hah! Am I alone? Haue they all left me? </l>
          <l>Where is my Empire? Doe I gouerne in </l>
          <l>The vacant Ayre? </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-016-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e110200">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Sir, am I lost vnto your memory? </l>
          <l>You were wont to trust my seruice: the way </l>
          <l>Vnto your Couch lyes here— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e110240">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>None shall be proud but I. My smiles reuiue </l>
          <l>The dead: but when I frowne, the liuing straight </l>
          <l>Melt into Ghosts. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e110280">
          <speaker>Cunym. </speaker>
          <p>Lights for the King there! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e110300">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Cunymond, you are too officious! The Kings </l>
          <l>Departure must be priuat. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e110330">Exeunt Albo. Parad. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-frollo" xml:id="ep000367-e110340">
          <speaker>Frollo. </speaker>
          <l>The King is light enough himselfe: he needs </l>
          <l>No Torches. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e110370">
          <speaker>Cunym. </speaker>
          <l>And heauy enough! for he seemes to reele </l>
          <l>With his owne weight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-conrade" xml:id="ep000367-e110400">
          <speaker>Conrad. </speaker>
          <l>No Maskes! No Epithelamion now! </l>
          <l>Call for a Bonesetter, for Time hath sprain'd </l>
          <l>His feete, and goes awry. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e110440">Exeunt omnes. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e110450">Enter Rhodolinda, Hermegild. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e110460">
          <speaker>Rhodo. </speaker>
          <l>O Hermegild! a generall eclips </l>
          <l>In Nature, would not seeme so horrid! </l>
          <l>To cut those cordiall strings which Hymen had </l>
          <l>But newly ty'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e110510">
          <speaker>Her. </speaker>
          <l>I, there's the horror! whil'st his Vowes sat warm </l>
          <l>Vpon his Lips; his breath not mingled yet </l>
          <l>With cooler Ayre; thus to perturbe by sterne </l>
          <l>Practice your sweet rest, was worse then periury. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e110560">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>To present my Royall Fathers Skull, </l>
          <l>In drunken Triumph. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e110590">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Take heede! you will distract your memory. </l>
          <l>There's a Record, Time striues to lose; and Fame </l>
          <l>To hide beneath some oblique fold in her </l>
          <l>Thicke Volume, as loth to discredit all </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-016-b"/>
          <l>Mankind. Your father valewed you next to </l>
          <l>His interest in heauen. I'ue seene the good </l>
          <l>Old King search for his picture in your eyes; then— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e110670">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>No more: Patience is sinfull now. Thou art </l>
          <l>Deepely read and wise: instruct me to be bold, </l>
          <l>For Albouine hath taught me to be cruell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e110710">
          <speaker>Hermeg. </speaker>
          <l>Y'are now by holy Church incorporate; </l>
          <l>Therefore Diuinitie forbids me vse </l>
          <l>My naturall motions. How e're I thinke </l>
          <l>It fit, you giue him direfull cause, soone to </l>
          <l>Repent: Repentance sure is physick for his soule. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000367-e110770">Enter Paradine, Valdaura. </stage>
          <l>Paradine and 's young Bride! Your excellence </l>
          <l>Shall please that we retire: whil'st I disguize </l>
          <l>My kind gesture, and seeme to flatter in </l>
          <l>The Kings behalfe— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e110820">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>To bed soft modesty! I will my selfe </l>
          <l>Deliuer to the Queene the King's intent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e110850">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>Sir, the King is cruell. Should you proue so </l>
          <l>To me, I'ld soone distill my soule to teares, </l>
          <l>And weepe an Ocean deepe enough to drowne </l>
          <l>My sorrowes, and my selfe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e110900">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>'Twere sterne guilt to doubt my nature. Faire Saint, </l>
          <l>To bed, I long to lose my Youth in warme </l>
          <l>Embraces, and ere the pearly Morne appeare, </l>
          <l>Make thee a teeming Mother. To bed! with winged hast </l>
          <l>Expect my presence. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e110960">Exit Valdaura. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e110970">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>How smooth appeares the Brow of Youth! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e110990">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Haile Rhodolinda! the Royall Mistresse </l>
          <l>Of this night. Thus Albouine (our great King) bade </l>
          <l>Me say, Y'are dearer to his eyes then light. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-017-a"/>
          <l>Though euery Bride may claime from Hymen </l>
          <l>Priuiledge to rule her Lord, till Hesperus </l>
          <l>Appeare, and cancell her briefe Charter. </l>
          <l>Yet he doth humbly beg, you'le not infringe </l>
          <l>The Lombards custome, whose Virgins neuer vow </l>
          <l>A continence the Nuptiall night. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e111090">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>I yet want your meaning. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e111110">
          <speaker>Par. </speaker>
          <l>Tis his chiefe hope that you will straight expect </l>
          <l>His person in your bed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e111140">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>How! lye with him? Ile sooner choose a Mansion </l>
          <l>In a sepulcher: There commit incest </l>
          <l>With the raw remnant of my fathers bones: </l>
          <l>Sooner imbrace an ayrie Incubus: </l>
          <l>Mingle Limmes with some vlcerous Cripple, </l>
          <l>Able to infect an Hospitall. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e111210">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>O take heed! Take heed, faire Maiesty! let not </l>
          <l>His rash sinne prouoke you to intend so dire </l>
          <l>An abstinence: ere yet the wine hath lost </l>
          <l>Th'vnruly operation. The King disclaimes </l>
          <l>His wanton pride, and mortifies himselfe </l>
          <l>With sullen griefe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e111280">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Canst thou suspect, I will prooue inconstant, </l>
          <l>To what in cold temperance I determine? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e111310">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>Heauen auert you should approue your error. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e111330">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Ile kneele, and vow with all solemnitie— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e111350">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>O hold! 'twere blacke impietie in vs </l>
          <l>To suffer such a horrid crime. You may </l>
          <l>Informe the King of my religious loyalty, </l>
          <l>Already I haue vs'd perswasiue speech </l>
          <l>To reconcile this ods: but she growes wilde, </l>
          <l>Repugnant to all mercy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e111420">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>As you esteeme your Royall selfe, or vs, </l>
          <l>Who (when kinder Planets rul'd) were seruants </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-017-b"/>
          <l>To th'vnhappy King your father; cherish </l>
          <l>No more this anger in your brest, lest Time </l>
          <l>Afford it growth and violence, till it </l>
          <l>Disturbe the world. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e111490">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>He councels like a sacred Oracle. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e111510">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>I will informe the King, your continence </l>
          <l>You onely celebrate to this blacke night, </l>
          <l>And giue him hope, that you'le hereafter smile, </l>
          <l>His kinde inticements meet with equall heate, </l>
          <l>And fertill loue. Though I'm vnhewne, and shap'd </l>
          <l>In warre, this softens all my faculties— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e111580">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>Stay, Paradine; didst thou not name my Father? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e111600">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>I did with a deuout remembrance! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e111620">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>And thou know'st how thy good Country suffers? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e111640">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>I think on it, and my heart hangs heauy </l>
          <l>On its strings; galles them with its sullen weight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e111670">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Hermegild oft receiues certificate </l>
          <l>From some in bondage there, which writ in Prose, doe, </l>
          <l>I'th reading into Verse dissolue: so sad </l>
          <l>The businesse is, so fit for elegie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e111720">
          <speaker>Hermeg. </speaker>
          <l>So sad a Requiem yet was neuer sung, </l>
          <l>Though the hoarce Rauen, and the Whistler shrill, </l>
          <l>The Howlet, and the euening Dorr made vp </l>
          <l>The fatall Quire. The young men there are yoak'd </l>
          <l>In payres, and stretch their sinnews in a Teeme, </l>
          <l>To draw the wealthy haruest to the Grange, </l>
          <l>Where th'insulting foe resides. The aged </l>
          <l>(Heretofore in purple cloth'd) that dispos'd </l>
          <l>Of Law and Iustice; are now sow'd vp </l>
          <l>In dunghill clouts; and dwell on parched hills, </l>
          <l>To tend the flocks; whose fleece the Victor weares </l>
          <l>In gawdy triumph. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e111850">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>O harsh captiuitie! Our Country groanes! </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-018-a"/>
          <l>Till now I thought the Conqueror gan to ease </l>
          <l>Their bondage, not adde to the weight of their </l>
          <l>Compell'd burdens. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e111900">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>The King's a sterne Tyrant. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e111920">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Yet he hath vs'd me still with gentle power, </l>
          <l>Ta'ne me from the cold Earth, and warm'd me in </l>
          <l>His bosome: and Hermegild has full cause </l>
          <l>To blesse his bounty. But you (now our Queene) </l>
          <l>He valewes next to heauen; howe're this rash </l>
          <l>Error striues to disgrace his loue. We are </l>
          <l>His captiues too; heretofore not heeded </l>
          <l>By our Starres; though we now grow tall with titles </l>
          <l>And his fauour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e112020">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord, the King is kinde! Our memories </l>
          <l>Were fraile, should we forget what hath so much </l>
          <l>Pertain'd vnto our knowledge. I'm so fond </l>
          <l>O're my Religion, I dare not taste </l>
          <l>Ingratitude: yet giue me leaue to say, </l>
          <l>You may mistake his loue vnto the Queene. </l>
          <l>The dry Tartar, who yoakes his females neck </l>
          <l>With rusty Yron, not with Carckanets </l>
          <l>Of threaded Pearle; whom he preserues for physick </l>
          <l>More then increase; will the first night of their </l>
          <l>Coniunction, feast her in's imbroader'd tent; </l>
          <l>Call her Soueraigne; and like some amorous winde, </l>
          <l>Sport with her haire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e112160">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>But my Nuptiall the King did celebrate </l>
          <l>In Golgotha, where Skulls, and dusty bones </l>
          <l>Inhabit. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e112200">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Y'are skilfull in the deeds that appertaine </l>
          <l>To strength and fury; but they that aime </l>
          <l>At victory in Court, must practise smooth </l>
          <l>And subtill Arts. Wise Fauourites doe walke </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-018-b"/>
          <l>I'th darke, and vse false lights. Nay, oft disguize </l>
          <l>Their breadth and stature; seeme lesser then they are: </l>
          <l>For know, the slender Worme, or nimble Grig, </l>
          <l>May wriggle downe into th' oblique, and low </l>
          <l>Descent o'th narrow hole; whilst th'oregrowne Snake </l>
          <l>Peepes at the brimme, but ne're can view the bottome. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e112310">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Thinke on thy Country, Paradine! Is there </l>
          <l>In Story no mention of some great Soule, </l>
          <l>That did his Country prize aboue his owne </l>
          <l>Mortalitie, and dy'd to gaine his Nation Freedome? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e112360">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>The Noble Brutus for his Countreys health, </l>
          <l>Made Cesar bleed; Cassius was heroique too, </l>
          <l>And had in warre loud Fame, which he increas'd </l>
          <l>By mingling in this Act.— Tis wrought with skill, </l>
          <l>And apt leasure. His thoughts grow numerous, </l>
          <l>And ingender horrid shapes; such as fright </l>
          <l>His fancy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e112440">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>Paradine, good night! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e112460">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Hymen and your Bride, will blame your tardy </l>
          <l>Seruice. Sweet Lord, a thousand times good night. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e112490">Exeunt Herm. and Rhodolinda. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e112500">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>False vnto me! when Thunder wakes the dead: </l>
          <l>When the Skie looks swarthy: the clouds like inke </l>
          <l>In water powr'd: when the Earth seemes to stand </l>
          <l>As in a gloomy shade. When the winde blowes </l>
          <l>Till it growes hoarce: till it conuert </l>
          <l>And sprinkle Seas euen to a Dew; then I </l>
          <l>Shall try the King, and fathome his wide Soule. </l>
          <l>If he start, complaine of his mortalitie, </l>
          <l>Kneele oft; and pray aloud, as Heauen </l>
          <l>Were deafe: if thus, I will conclude him false. </l>
          <l>For horrid stormes that Tyrants waking keepe, </l>
          <l>Doe rock the noble Conscience safe asleepe. <stage xml:id="ep000367-e112630">Exit. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="ep000367-e112640">
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-019-a"/>
        <head>Act the third. Scene first. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e112650">Enter Rhodolinda, Valdaura, Thesina. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e112660">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>I knew your Excellence did visit me </l>
          <l>For mirth and laughter. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e112690">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>So early vp? Your Lord is temperate. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e112710">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>I should like their tempers better, if she </l>
          <l>Were downe, and her Lord vp. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e112740">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <p>Fye, Thesina, your tongue's vnruly. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e112760">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>The morning might haue shewne me too for mirth, </l>
          <l>Had not the false King made the night so sad. </l>
          <l>Black fancy flye! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e112800">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>She moues as she were sicke, this skirmish has </l>
          <l>Much weakened her. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e112830">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>Dost thou call't a skirmish? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e112850">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>I, Madam, a French skirmish; where th' onset </l>
          <l>Is hot and fiery, but the retreat cold and tame. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e112880">Enter Hermegild. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e112890">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>Madam, the King? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e112910">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>Hah! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e112930">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>He greets your Excellence in a smooth phrase, </l>
          <l>And begs, you will permit his early visit. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e112960">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>I'ld rather lose my eyes then see him. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e112980">Valdaura kneeles. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e112990">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>When you did triumph in your fathers Court, </l>
          <l>My entreaty then had power to alter </l>
          <l>Your commands; reward my young seruice </l>
          <l>With kindnesse to your selfe. When the tall </l>
          <l>Cedar falls, with burly weight it strikes </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-019-b"/>
          <l>The neighbouring shrubs, low, into the ground: </l>
          <l>So we that spring like Rushes neere your roote, </l>
          <l>Must in your death receiue a funerall. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e113080">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>What's this? D'ye moralize? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e113100">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>The King may haue his anger warranted. </l>
          <l>For heauen forbids such wilde diuision </l>
          <l>'Tweene those whom holy Church vnites. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e113140">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Harke, Thesina! She has been gossiping </l>
          <l>With the holy Sisters: she preaches to me </l>
          <l>Of Matrimoniall zeale. Troth Valdaura, </l>
          <l>If thy husband doe infuse such schisme, </l>
          <l>Ile practise a diuorce. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e113200">
          <speaker>Thesina. </speaker>
          <l>We Court Ladies grow so squeamish after </l>
          <l>We haue tasted Man. Your Maiesty may </l>
          <l>Much profit her behauiour, if you </l>
          <l>A while deuide her from her Lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e113250">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>So soone? Ere Time permits them second </l>
          <l>Their imbraces? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e113280">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>I Hermegild. If those imbraces doe </l>
          <l>Include such high delight, such rapsody; </l>
          <l>She makes me enuious then; since all my hopes </l>
          <l>Are widdowed by the King. To night, Valdaura, </l>
          <l>You are to sleepe beneath my Roofe. This I </l>
          <l>Impose as a command. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e113350">Exeunt Rhodo. Thesin. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e113360">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>Is not this a harsh compulsion? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e113380">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>Sir, I willingly obey it. But as </l>
          <l>Y'are Noble, vse your ablest skill, t'instruct </l>
          <l>The Queene how of her anger to dispose </l>
          <l>A safer way, then 'gainst the King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e113430">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Alas! I'ld rather cut my Eye-lids off </l>
          <l>To preuent sleepe then lose one minute that </l>
          <l>Could aduantage a designe so pious. </l>
          <l>And be it part of your kinde charity, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-020-a"/>
          <l>T' indeere me to your Lord. Tis all the pride </l>
          <l>In my ambition to doe him seruice. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e113500">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>Sir, he already knowes your worth, and thinks </l>
          <l>Your friendship precious. <stage xml:id="ep000367-e113530">Exit. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e113540">
          <speaker>Her. </speaker>
          <l>I kisse your faire hands. The King already come? </l>
          <l>I must seeme pensiue as the night. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e113570">Enter Albouine, Paradine, Cunymond, Frollo, Conrade. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e113580">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>She's lost, my Boy: blowne from my fist: her wings </l>
          <l>Haue gather'd wind: they flye (like those of Time) </l>
          <l>Swiftly forward, but neuer backe returne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e113620">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Sir, I haue hope, she will repent this breach </l>
          <l>Of duty, and court your Royall smiles agen. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e113650">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Is it a sinne to drinke? Nature has giuen </l>
          <l>To fishes a prerogatiue, greater </l>
          <l>Then we inioy. They can euer tipple </l>
          <l>And not be drunke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e113700">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <l>Fishes are dumb (Sir) they neuer fox themselues </l>
          <l>With talke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e113730">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Slaue! thy mirth is treacherous! Paradine! </l>
          <l>Thou hast consum'd to night the wealth of loue, </l>
          <l>Wasted thy lips in moyst kisses, imbrac'd </l>
          <l>A warmth, that would giue life to marble. </l>
          <l>Whilst I, (like the solitary Phoenix) </l>
          <l>Expect no heate but in my funerall flame: </l>
          <l>And striue t'ingender of my selfe. Yet Boy, </l>
          <l>Thou canst not make me enuious; thou art more </l>
          <l>Delightfull; then my Rodolinda's sinnes. </l>
          <l>Let me suruay those blue circles: his lids </l>
          <l>Fall downe, as if weighty Plummets hung on </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-020-b"/>
          <l>Their sinnes. Thou art not temperate. Preserue </l>
          <l>Thy deare eyes. Loue was pictur'd blind, because </l>
          <l>It makes men blinde. I hugge thee as my health— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e113880">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>He bruis'd me in his armes. Can loue expresse </l>
          <l>Such violence, and yet be false? Hermegild </l>
          <l>Still whispers in my eare, the King doth hate </l>
          <l>Thee, Paradine. But Hermegild is read in all </l>
          <l>The Arts of Court, and striues perhaps </l>
          <l>My sence to poyson with leane iealousie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e113950">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Sweet Lord! Y' appeare blushing like the Morne! </l>
          <l>Something your Bride and you haue done t' increase </l>
          <l>The number of the Worthies. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e113990">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>He courts me too! I want a Perspectiue, </l>
          <l>To draw these distant figures neere my sight. </l>
          <l>I ne're shall sleepe agen. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e114030">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Hermegild, thy aspect shewes ominous! </l>
          <l>How thriues our embasie? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e114060">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>I haue consum'd my breath, till I grew faint, </l>
          <l>And wept to inuite her mercy; but teares </l>
          <l>Were spilt like water in the Forge, onely </l>
          <l>T' inrage the fire. She doth abiure your visit. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e114110">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>Harsh, Iron, nature! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e114130">
          <speaker>Her. </speaker>
          <l>The King seemes fetter'd in his lims: he wreathes </l>
          <l>His armes, as if he meant to bruise his heart. </l>
          <l>And Paradine doth find my charmes predominant. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e114170">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>He that drinks, forfeits his mortalitie! </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e114190">Enter Grimold. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e114200">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <p>How Sir, must we not drink? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e114220">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Souldier, to keepe thy bladder moyst, I will </l>
          <l>Permit thee gape i'th mornings face, and catch </l>
          <l>Her mizzling teares. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e114260">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>If you'll extirpate this vice of drinking, </l>
          <l>Giue order for a priuy search i'th the Ocean; </l>
          <l>There dwell the greatest drinkers. The Whale (Sir) </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-021-a"/>
          <l>Drinks deeper let's hale her on shore, and impownd her </l>
          <l>In a Cesterne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e114320">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Good! we will imbarke for Sea. I presse thee vp </l>
          <l>For this imployment. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e114350">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Stay (Sir) ere I ingage my selfe in new </l>
          <l>Seruices, pay me for my old. You rest </l>
          <l>Vpon my Ticket, six thousand Duckats; </l>
          <l>And I haue not seene your Maiesties face </l>
          <l>In any other metall, but your owne </l>
          <l>Flesh and blood these three moneths. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e114420">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>Thou grumblest like a gray Wolfe. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e114440">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <p>Tis then for hunger, Sir. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e114460">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Captaine, you mistake the King. He's Royall </l>
          <l>As his blood, and liberall as the Sunne </l>
          <l>That shines on all. This vnruly breath, where </l>
          <l>The Citie meete in councell, might perhaps </l>
          <l>Blow their Purse-strings loose, so fill the Exchequer. </l>
          <l>And then you shall number your pay with your owne </l>
          <l>Fingers. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e114540">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>I will out-rore thunder, or the Cannon! </l>
          <l>Must they still walke in wealthy Furres; whilst men </l>
          <l>Of merit here are cloth'd in Cabidge leaues? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e114580">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>Grimold, you indanger your friends. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e114600">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord, giue losers leaue to speake. I'ue lost </l>
          <l>My youth and blood ith' warres, and I want food, </l>
          <l>A reuerend Asse beares my wife and her young egges </l>
          <l>In Paniers vp and downe the streets. I trauaile </l>
          <l>Like a Tartar, with all my family </l>
          <l>About me. Nay, nay, nay! you would be gon! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e114670">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>Art thou not yet dead? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e114690">
          <speaker>Gri. </speaker>
          <l>You must not moue, till y'haue paid me. I know, </l>
          <l>You may be angry with more safety then I. </l>
          <l>Bid some Colossus of your Guard cleaue me </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-021-b"/>
          <l>With his Falchon; yet I shall steale a passage </l>
          <l>Ore the blacke Riuer, when Charon slumbers, </l>
          <l>And fright your Grace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e114760">
          <speaker>Alb. </speaker>
          <l>I dare not strike thee (old man) lest thou shouldst fall </l>
          <l>To dust, and choke me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e114790">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Good King, pay me. I loue thy Grace: </l>
          <l>And will fight for thee, whilst I'ue motion left </l>
          <l>To stirre a feather. My want constraines me to't. </l>
          <l>By this hand, I'm faine to eate Branne and Parsley </l>
          <l>Like a tame Rabbit. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e114850">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>Lend me your eare, Captaine! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e114870">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <p>You'll intice me now t'enter into bond? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e114890">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>You look indeed like a young heire. Well, Sir, </l>
          <l>Valew me according to my true rate. </l>
          <l>I am your friend. You make ill choice of howers </l>
          <l>For helpe of your designe. The King hath now </l>
          <l>Sad and tumultuous thoughts about his heart. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e114950">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Great men are alwayes sad, when they should pay </l>
          <l>Their debts. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e114980">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Sir, you interpret ill. Grow more sober, </l>
          <l>Then challenge all my power in your behalfe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e115010">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>He that receiues a kindnes from the Diuell, </l>
          <l>Shall bee sure to lose by his gaines. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e115040">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <l>Captaine, you should chuse a luckier minute: </l>
          <l>The King is now in loue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e115070">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <p>With whom? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-frollo" xml:id="ep000367-e115090">
          <speaker>Frollo. </speaker>
          <p>With the Queene. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e115110">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>In loue with his owne wife! that's held incest </l>
          <l>In Court: varietie is more luscious. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e115140">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Be powerfull in thy speech, my Paradine, </l>
          <l>Yet gentle too. She is the Starre that rules </l>
          <l>My faculties. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e115180">
          <speaker>Par. </speaker>
          <l>The Queen will blesse your temperance, &amp; repent. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-022-a"/>
          <l>Hermegild is too busie: he must be more </l>
          <l>At leasure, and I more actiue. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e115220">Exit Parad. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e115230">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>Hermegild, weare thy sences neere vs— </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e115250">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Your Maiesty has a fraile memory </l>
          <l>To forget me so soone— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e115280">
          <speaker>Her. </speaker>
          <p>You'll forfeit me, and the Kings mercy! away! </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e115300">Exeunt Albouine, Hermegild. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e115310">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Tis no piece of vnkindnesse to wish thee </l>
          <l>In hell, for all thy friends dwell there. Th'ast none </l>
          <l>Vpon the earth. Gentlemen will you be open to me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e115350">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <p>In all parts, Sir, but our purses. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e115370">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Draw neere! let vs communicate our hearts! </l>
          <l>Does not that wealth, which you disburse for powders, </l>
          <l>Perfumes, clothes, and physicke for the face, </l>
          <l>Returne with gaine? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-frollo" xml:id="ep000367-e115420">
          <speaker>Frollo. </speaker>
          <p>Expound your Riddle, Sir. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e115440">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Haue you not each a Mistresse that maintaines </l>
          <l>You in expence and riot? Hah? Fame giues </l>
          <l>It out, you smooth Gallants are much oblig'd </l>
          <l>Vnto the sinnes of Ladies. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e115490">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <l>Conrade can prattle somewhat, Sir, to that </l>
          <l>Purpose. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-conrade" xml:id="ep000367-e115520">
          <speaker>Conr. </speaker>
          <l>Good faith you do me wrong. I'ue worne, Sir, </l>
          <l>A Ladies slipper in my hat, or so. </l>
          <l>Frollo is the man that gets their Pendants, </l>
          <l>Armelets, Rings, and all the Toyes of valew. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-frollo" xml:id="ep000367-e115570">
          <speaker>Frollo. </speaker>
          <l>Excuse me, sir, not I. Signior Cunymond </l>
          <l>Has all the voyce at Court. We know, Sir, when, </l>
          <l>And where, a certaine Dutchesse, Sir; </l>
          <l>You copulate with Titles, you. </l>
          <l>The Heralds are your Bawds. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e115630">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <p>Hold! grow particular in such a Theame as this! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e115650">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <p>Well, Gentlemen, I must be furnish'd too. </p>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-022-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e115670">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <p>With a Mistresse? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e115690">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Yes, inquire me out some old Land-Carack. </l>
          <l>I am content to stretch my loynes for a </l>
          <l>Pension. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e115730">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <p>At what rate doe you valew your selfe? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e115750">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <p>I was neuer pawn'd, Sir. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e115770">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <p>How, Captaine! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e115790">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>In this leane age, we valew all things </l>
          <l>According to the rate, they pawne for. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-frollo" xml:id="ep000367-e115820">
          <speaker>Frollo. </speaker>
          <l>But we must know, how much you would receiue </l>
          <l>In price of your actiuitie? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-conrade" xml:id="ep000367-e115850">
          <speaker>Conrad. </speaker>
          <p>You must neuer stray after fresh pasture. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e115870">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Some eight; I, I, eight hundred Crownes a yeere will doe't. </l>
          <l>I am desirous of no more then will </l>
          <l>Maintaine my Genet, and my Dwarfe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e115910">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <l>Your excuse procur'd, tis fit you now tell, </l>
          <l>How farre in your defence I may ingage </l>
          <l>My honour: is not your flesh a little tainted! </l>
          <l>Are you not vnwholsome? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e115960">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>O death, no; no, no, no! Do not thinke I haue </l>
          <l>A conscience so ill bred, to put my selfe </l>
          <l>Vpon a Lady, when vnfit for the affaire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e116000">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <l>Well, Captaine, now with your own eies suruay </l>
          <l>Your limmes; what vse can a Lady haue </l>
          <l>Of you? To propagate the Cough o'th lungs? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-frollo" xml:id="ep000367-e116040">
          <speaker>Frollo. </speaker>
          <p>Or beget Cripples, to people an Hospitall? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-conrade" xml:id="ep000367-e116060">
          <speaker>Conrad. </speaker>
          <l>Or produce another Nation that may </l>
          <l>Wage fierce battaile 'gainst the Cranes? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e116090">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Yet I can follow your bodies with rough </l>
          <l>Motion, and not shed my limmes by the way— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e116120">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <p>I told ye, he'ld make a ieast on't. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e116140">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>But I will kick ye in earnest,— kick ye </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-023-a"/>
          <l>For my exercise and warmth— till my toes </l>
          <l>Grow crooked— </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e116180">Exeunt omnes. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e116190">Enter Valdaura, reading to her selfe, then Albouine, Hermegild. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e116200">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>Pursue Valdaura, Sir. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e116220">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>I hate these Iiggeries. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e116240">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>You know, I am materiall in my speech, </l>
          <l>Full of duty; you want the silken garbe, </l>
          <l>That must indeere you to the Ladies eyes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e116280">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>Yet I am louing in my drinke. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e116300">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Greet her kindly, Sir: tis Paradines Bride. </l>
          <l>You haue not seene her since she indeuour'd </l>
          <l>To increase the number of your subiects, </l>
          <l>With losse of her virginitie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e116350">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Rhodolinda doth so ingrosse my loue, </l>
          <l>That on other Ladies I'ue but little </l>
          <l>To bestow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e116390">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Sir, practise but your Courtship here. In troth </l>
          <l>You must affect the amorous Cringe, gestures </l>
          <l>Smooth and pliant; it will neuer doe else. </l>
          <l>I'ue heard the Queene complaine, you are too rough: </l>
          <l>And what these Ladies doe obserue, will take </l>
          <l>A sudden flight vnto her eare. Strike but </l>
          <l>Their sences gently with your tongue. Often </l>
          <l>Flatter'em, and with a vigorous breath; </l>
          <l>They'll then implore the Queene in your behalfe: </l>
          <l>And, Sir, th' indeuour of their praise will soone </l>
          <l>Procure your peace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e116510">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>If they would soften Rhodolinda's heart, </l>
          <l>And reconcile me to her smiles, I would </l>
          <l>Grow fond, and dally then with all the Sex. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-023-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e116550">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Begin your triall. If you salute this, </l>
          <l>(And other Ladies too) with some impression on </l>
          <l>Their lipps; with managing their fingers thus,— </l>
          <l>With seysure on her wrist; as if you had </l>
          <l>Some businesse with her Pulse: then you inchant. </l>
          <l>Be flexiue in your smiles, and wanton like, </l>
          <l>Seeke pictures in their eyes: and when they moue, </l>
          <l>Then with personall conduct, guide their feet. </l>
          <l>'Mongst them you cannot seeme too cheape. They will </l>
          <l>Admire you for't, and sing your prayses to </l>
          <l>The Queene. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e116670">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>I shall be taught to spin, and starch! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e116690">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>The engin's now compact; each wheele doth moue </l>
          <l>With silent screwes. The Mole's the subtle Pioner: </l>
          <l>For when she vndermines the earth, her slow </l>
          <l>Motion makes no noise. <stage xml:id="ep000367-e116740">Exit. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e116750">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Y'are deuout, Vauldaura. Teach me to pray: </l>
          <l>We haue no leasure for't in warre; and 't has </l>
          <l>Been long time out of fashion here in Court. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e116790">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>I feare I make some breach of duty with </l>
          <l>Your Excellence, to hinder thus </l>
          <l>The passage of your Royall thoughts. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e116830">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>You teach me now, t'excuse my owne abrupt </l>
          <l>Demeanour; but I can doe't. My harsh Queene </l>
          <l>(Whom the perspicuous Eye of heauen forgiue) </l>
          <l>Doth much mistake the posture of my limmes, </l>
          <l>And gesture of my tongue among your Sex. </l>
          <l>I neuer vse, like rugged Polypheame, </l>
          <l>To dandle Cubs. Thus, I can gently touch </l>
          <l>A Ladies lips— yet make no battery on </l>
          <l>Her teeth. Was it not an ayrie pressure? </l>
          <l>Tell my proud Queene, I'ue lost my Iron garbe, </l>
          <l>And now am growne thus fond and smooth. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-024-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e116950">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>O Royall Sir, her cruelty hath put </l>
          <l>My eyes vnto th'expence of many teares. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e116980">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>I, but in vaine! Those clouds must weep apace, </l>
          <l>That meane to penetrate the Marble, or </l>
          <l>The Flint. I weare no Gauntlet on my hand, </l>
          <l>Why should you thinke that I would bruise </l>
          <l>Your fingers with my touch— <stage xml:id="ep000367-e117040">Sports with her hand. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e117050">Enter Hermegild, Rhodolinda. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e117060">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>Is this Paradines Garden? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e117080">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>I Madam, and your Excellence may finde </l>
          <l>A sudden growth, in all that shadowes vs. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e117110">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>Hah I looke there! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e117130">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>What is 't your eyes so eagerly discerne? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e117150">
          <speaker>Rho. </speaker>
          <l>The King! How sportfull he is growne? how full </l>
          <l>Of amarous game and dalliance? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e117180">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>I spie Valdaura there: but is that the King? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e117200">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>Thou dost inquire, t'affront my sight. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e117220">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>You must informe the Queene of this: Say, I </l>
          <l>Am smooth, and musicall, and trim, and that </l>
          <l>I talke no more of warre, nor drinke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e117260">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>Tis my duty to vrge all circumstance, </l>
          <l>That may credit you in her esteeme. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e117290">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>It is a piece of courtship to salute </l>
          <l>At parting— <stage xml:id="ep000367-e117320">Kisses her. exit Valdaura. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e117330">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>Is that a safe coniunction in so hot a climate! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e117350">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Hell and death! What raw discipline is this? </l>
          <l>I should conduct her in her way— <stage xml:id="ep000367-e117380">Exit. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e117390">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>So violent in pursuit of your game? </l>
          <l>Let's follow, Hermegild? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e117420">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Not for all the Sunne beholds in's iourney </l>
          <l>Through the world— </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-024-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e117450">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>Why? be nimble in thy speech! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e117470">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>It shewes but silly art in industry, </l>
          <l>To seeke what you would not finde. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e117500">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>I pre thee grow particular! Dost thinke </l>
          <l>They purpose ought ith' darke? or, was this same </l>
          <l>But ceremonious forme! such a greeting </l>
          <l>As courtship will admit in publike interuiew? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e117550">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>The King was neuer giuen to complement, </l>
          <l>You know. As for Valdaura— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e117580">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>What of her? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e117600">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>I thinke that she is chaste, but— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e117620">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Doe not inuolue thy language thus </l>
          <l>In periods of suspence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e117650">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>I wish the King had not deseru'd to be </l>
          <l>Depriu'd of your soft imbraces, then </l>
          <l>He might haue kept his constitution tame. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e117690">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>O, is it so? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e117710">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>It ill becomes the garbe of Maiesty, </l>
          <l>To run thus neighing (like a riotous Horse) </l>
          <l>After each female that he spies. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e117750">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>Why, does he vse it? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e117770">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Madam, you question me, as if what I </l>
          <l>Declare, were to your knowledge new and strange. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e117800">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>By heauen and so it is. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e117820">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>O my officious Soule! must it be my crime </l>
          <l>To giue the information vp? would I </l>
          <l>Had knowne the King was here, you should haue made </l>
          <l>Another path, your walke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e117870">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>Hermegild, you did mis-spend that breath. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e117890">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Alas, you had enough of griefe before. </l>
          <l>This addition will but shew a tyranny </l>
          <l>In fate and me. It works with hight, like new </l>
          <l>Mighty wine! as if 't would split the Caske. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-025-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e117940">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>O periur'd, black, adulterous King! affront </l>
          <l>My Fathers Ghost? Disturbe his Ashes in </l>
          <l>His tombe? When drunk with pride, he mock'd me with </l>
          <l>The gawdy title of a Queene, and now </l>
          <l>I am become a stale for all his lust. </l>
          <l>Valdaura too! so pure of heart (forsooth) </l>
          <l>That she would blush to see her own hand, if nak'd: </l>
          <l>They are proscrib'd. Know, Hermegild, </l>
          <l>Our Country shall be free. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e118040">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>This is a noble rage! Heauen knowes how I </l>
          <l>Haue grieu'd at your decay of soule. 'T was my </l>
          <l>Sad feare, that all the angry sparkes, which were </l>
          <l>By Iustice kindled in your brest, had been </l>
          <l>Extinguish'd quite, now they grow vp in flames. </l>
          <l>You now like Phoebus shew, when he hath wash'd </l>
          <l>His face with Dew. Your influence doth infuse </l>
          <l>A noble heate, such as would motion giue </l>
          <l>Vnto aged Statues; make them pluck vp </l>
          <l>Their Mossie feet, and walke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e118150">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Thou giu'st my sences pride! What in this great </l>
          <l>Businesse wilt thou doe, t' incourage hope? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e118180">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>I will mingle poyson in my Inke, write </l>
          <l>With a Rauens Quill! 't will be a fatall </l>
          <l>Scripture: and shall charme like to those wise Iigs </l>
          <l>The Syrens sing. Some must direction beare </l>
          <l>T' our Pensioners, that in our Country rule </l>
          <l>The sterne Edicts of Law: some to Martiall </l>
          <l>Spirits, who with their able skill doe leade </l>
          <l>Those Regiments, the King hath garison'd </l>
          <l>I'th bordering Townes. They shall reuolt, my Queene, </l>
          <l>And seate thee in thy Fathers Chaire: they must </l>
          <l>Be drunke with the Elixir of my Gold. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e118300">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>When first I chose thee out for this great work, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-025-b"/>
          <l>I saw thee thorow a Perspectiue reuerss'd; </l>
          <l>For thou didst seeme much lesser then thou art. </l>
          <l>Kneele, and be happy!— Before </l>
          <l>The Genius of this place, and what is here </l>
          <l>Immortall, I vow to assist with my </l>
          <l>Most actiue skill, all thy designements 'gainst </l>
          <l>The King; and when my iust hopes are finish'd, </l>
          <l>To be thy Wife. Such as doe periur'd prooue, </l>
          <l>Lightning will surely clothe with subtle flames, </l>
          <l>And they shall burne like glimmering Tapers </l>
          <l>In darke hell: pale, and sickly as that fire </l>
          <l>The Ghost of Nero makes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e118440">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>This new ambition hath so exalted </l>
          <l>All my faculties, that I seeme taller </l>
          <l>Kneeling, then when I stood. But here with strict </l>
          <l>Solemnitie I vow to teach my Soule </l>
          <l>New wayes of merit: to reuenge with sterne, </l>
          <l>And horrid wrath, the Kings proud tyranny. </l>
          <l>To make your Greatnesse absolute, and high, </l>
          <l>Or sinke my selfe lower then a Plummet, </l>
          <l>In the Baltick Sea. Should I not this performe, </l>
          <l>The Starres would fall like Cinders on my head: </l>
          <l>And winds imprison'd in the Earth; breake forth, </l>
          <l>In a wilde ruine, and shake me into sand: </l>
          <l>Then blow me in your Eyes; where if in teares </l>
          <l>You drowne me, I am intomb'd in Pearle: and then </l>
          <l>My obsequies requite my death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e118600">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Enough. I proffet to thy lip, the first </l>
          <l>Taste of my affection— <stage xml:id="ep000367-e118630">They kisse, then rise. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e118640">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>'T was moyst and luscious! I will cherish this </l>
          <l>Indeerement. Trees that tallest grow, doe take </l>
          <l>The deepest roote; so I must first sinke low </l>
          <l>Ith' Earth; and after climbe to fathome clouds. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-026-a"/>
          <l>First, praise her mimick laughter: when she weepes, </l>
          <l>Then gather vp with couetous regard </l>
          <l>Her teares for scatter'd Pearle. Licke her spittle </l>
          <l>From the ground: this disguiz'd humilitie </l>
          <l>Is both the swift, and safest way to pride— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e118740">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Sure, Hermegild, I haue amaz'd thy sence, </l>
          <l>Thou look'st like some ore-growne Fiend, chain'd vp </l>
          <l>Within a silent caue. Let vs retire, and Ile </l>
          <l>Discouer how I'ue practis'd my reuenge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e118790">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>I proiect to make you mighty! You shall </l>
          <l>Ascend my beautious Soueraigne, till you </l>
          <l>Can reach the Moone, and pick those seeds of light </l>
          <l>(The lesser Stars) from forth their wandring Spheares; </l>
          <l>To weare as new imbroadery on your sleeue. </l>
          <l>I long to heare your fatall Arts. Let's mix </l>
          <l>Our sences, and contriue. A womans will, </l>
          <l>Is not so strong in anger, as her skill. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e118880">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e118890">Enter Paradine, a Gentleman and Page. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e118900">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>You bring no letters from Cracouia, Sir? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gentleman" xml:id="ep000367-e118920">
          <speaker>Gent. </speaker>
          <p>None, my Lord. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e118940">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>Nor from Sienna? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gentleman" xml:id="ep000367-e118960">
          <speaker>Gentlem. </speaker>
          <l>Your Lordship in those few, receiues th'intire </l>
          <l>Purpose of my iourney. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e118990">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Alas, my Countrymen! Captiuitie </l>
          <l>Is hoarce, they haue more griefs then tongue: they speak </l>
          <l>Not loud enough to wake the eare of heauen. </l>
          <l>Henceforth to Hermegild bid them direct </l>
          <l>Their sighs; for I'm so dull, so weary, and </l>
          <l>Neglectfull of ambitious ends, that I </l>
          <l>Shall lose my strength, and fauour with the King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gentleman" xml:id="ep000367-e119070">
          <speaker>Gent. </speaker>
          <p>My noble Lord, our prayers will ouer-rule that prophecy. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e119090">
          <speaker>Par. </speaker>
          <l>You may expect, whilst I am able to </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-026-b"/>
          <l>Performe. Boy, bespeake the Gentleman a free </l>
          <l>And bounteous welcome. Sir, I will hasten </l>
          <l>Your dispatch. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e119140">Exeunt Gent. Page. Enter Thesina. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e119150">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <p>My Lord; I haue tyr'd my selfe in your search. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e119170">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>The faire Thesina? You are rarely here </l>
          <l>A visitant! Where haue you left my Bride? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e119200">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>With the Queene, my Lord, who is so fond </l>
          <l>Of her attendance, she'le scarce allow her space </l>
          <l>To winke in her owne seruice, and to night </l>
          <l>She lyes within her chamber. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e119250">
          <speaker>Par. </speaker>
          <l>Hah! so soone deuided! Th'approching night </l>
          <l>Should helpe to second our imbraces. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e119280">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>Y'are now to trust my Art. For Valdaura </l>
          <l>Sent me t'expresse her ioy, i'th deliuery </l>
          <l>Of this message. You shall lye with her to night. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e119320">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>How can my faith admit of this, since she </l>
          <l>Is billited where the Queene sleepes? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e119350">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>Ile perfect my assurance; so you'll please </l>
          <l>T'obey what I inioyne. When you approach </l>
          <l>The Spheare, where your bright Phoebe rules, doe not </l>
          <l>Occasion so much noyse, as shall expresse </l>
          <l>You liuing. You must not speake to her, nor </l>
          <l>By your gestures, inuite her speech. All this </l>
          <l>Performe, lest you should wake the Queene. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e119430">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>To be dumbe in copulation! This is </l>
          <l>A fine receipt to get a silent Girle. </l>
          <l>But I shall prooue obedient. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e119470">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>And (Sir) as y'are mercifull to Ladies </l>
          <l>(Ripe in growth) doe not breathe too loud, lest we </l>
          <l>Ith' neighbouring roome, ore-heare the harmony, </l>
          <l>And sinne in wishes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e119520">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>Feare not, Thesina: I shall be temperate. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e119540">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>But you young souldiers are so boysterous, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-027-a"/>
          <l>You'll thinke anon, y'are battering some Towne-wall. </l>
          <l>Follow, Sir, Ile direct ye to the place, </l>
          <l>Where, when the darke howre arriues, you must </l>
          <l>Addresse your visit. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e119600">Exeunt omnes. </stage>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="ep000367-e119610">
        <head>Act the fourth. Scene first. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e119620">Enter Paradine dressing himselfe. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e119630">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>The early Lark climbes higher then his voice; </l>
          <l>And whispers into Phoebus eare, a glad </l>
          <l>Welcome; who smiles, and seemes to prophecy </l>
          <l>A gawdy day. Valdaura? Madame? speake, </l>
          <l>Sweet Lady! or, if for concealement of </l>
          <l>Our stolne rapture you silence still assume; </l>
          <l>Yet rise, and blesse my eye-sight with thy faire </l>
          <l>Presence. Come, and eclipse the enuious day! </l>
          <l>Not talke ith' businesse, nor yet behold </l>
          <l>The ground we till, as if we both were blinde </l>
          <l>And dumbe. Ile no more by stealth ingender; </l>
          <l>Cripples are got thus. Kind Valdaura, speake! </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000367-e119760">A hand is thrust out betweene the Arras. </stage>
          <l>See, a new day breakes in her hand! These are </l>
          <l>The rosie fingers of the Morne! </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000367-e119790">Pulls in Rhodolinda. </stage>
          <l>Hah! the Queene! Valdaura! Bride, where art thou? </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000367-e119810">Lookes in. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e119820">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>In vaine thou call'st. The Cannons Iron throat, </l>
          <l>Although high mounted on you 'Pinacle, </l>
          <l>Scarce could reach her eare. She's in Pauia now, </l>
          <l>Two Leagues situate from hence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e119870">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>Thou art mysterious as an Oracle! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e119890">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>I sent her thither, with pretence she should </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-027-b"/>
          <l>Suruay the modell of a Garden-worke. </l>
          <l>But 'twas done, that Thesina might intice </l>
          <l>With apter leasure, thy person to my bed. </l>
          <l>At noone thy wife returnes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e119950">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>I'ue mistaken then my warme embraces, </l>
          <l>And sinn'd with thee th' adulterous Queene! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e119980">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Thou hast inioy'd what Albouine with all </l>
          <l>His Royall sighs, his teares swolne bigger then </l>
          <l>His eyes, despair'd to merit. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e120020">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>O horror! gape, rugged Earth! Suck me in </l>
          <l>Like some old Pyramid, whose ponderous limmes </l>
          <l>Haue been thy burden since the Flood, and now </l>
          <l>Their owne foundation sinke. Could you make </l>
          <l>No choice to quench your rauenous lust, but me? </l>
          <l>Where were the broad-chin'd Zwitzers of your Guard? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e120090">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>This (Paradine) denotes a melting braine: </l>
          <l>Which out of vulgar pity I forgiue. </l>
          <l>'Twas not the wanton taste of thy smooth limmes, </l>
          <l>That could prouoke me vse this stratagem. </l>
          <l>But loue of my reuenge. I'ue strongly now </l>
          <l>Ingag'd thy power, to kill the King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e120160">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>Hah! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e120180">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Which do: and ere the Sun arriue ith' West; </l>
          <l>Or with disheuell'd haire, my vestments torne </l>
          <l>(As if I'd wandred thorow some Hathorne hedge) </l>
          <l>I will approach the Tyrant, acquaint him </l>
          <l>With this deed, and call my owne adultery </l>
          <l>Thy fowle rape. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e120250">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Who 's within there, hoa! My Hogs-head's empty. </l>
          <l>I was not borne with so much braines, as would </l>
          <l>Bedew a clout, that my cold Nosthrill stopt. </l>
          <l>These Court smocks containe the very Deuill. </l>
          <l>Good heauen! how leane should I haue made my heart </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-028-a"/>
          <l>With studious thoughts, ere I the skill had reach'd </l>
          <l>Of such a damn'd proiection. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e120330">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Collect thy scatter'd thoughts. What thy respect </l>
          <l>To thy captiu'd Country, could ne're charme thee </l>
          <l>To reuenge; be prompted to, by a kinde </l>
          <l>Affection of thy owne deare life: reuenge </l>
          <l>Vpon a Tyrant; One, that loues not me, </l>
          <l>Nor thee; vnlesse in speech: he hath a smooth </l>
          <l>Tongue, but a rugged heart. My Hermegild </l>
          <l>Perceiues this truth, and can deliuer it </l>
          <l>With all the pride of knowledge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e120430">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Sure Time growes humerous with age: for things </l>
          <l>Doe differ much from the sincerenesse of </l>
          <l>Their first creation. I will goe weepe </l>
          <l>Till I am blind— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e120480">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Stay, Paradine. If thou dost mocke my hopes </l>
          <l>With a slow motion in this iust designe, </l>
          <l>Expect to finde my anger fatall. Ile to </l>
          <l>The King, and make a forfeiture of both </l>
          <l>Our liues: but if with hardy sinnewes thou dost march </l>
          <l>To 's Throat, and slit the swarthy Pipe, I'le call </l>
          <l>Thee then my Souldier. Besides thy Countries thanks, </l>
          <l>Thou shalt enioy me for thy Queene, thy Wife, </l>
          <l>Paradine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e120580">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>New Arts, t'inuolue imagination! </l>
          <l>How can this be, and my owne wife strongly </l>
          <l>Possess'd of health and nature! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e120620">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Would'st thou imbrace so eminent a blisse, </l>
          <l>Without some danger to thy soule? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e120650">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>My memory betrayes my skill! I know </l>
          <l>There are a thousand wayes to discard her, </l>
          <l>From this foule, durty Orbe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e120690">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Alas, good easie Soule! She'le ne're be miss'd </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-028-b"/>
          <l>Among the liuing. Know, Valdaura's false. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e120720">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>How! False! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e120740">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>She is a open whore, and hath taught me </l>
          <l>This Art of lust. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e120770">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>More horrible then Hell! </l>
          <l>Now furnish but my hands with an Hower-glasse, </l>
          <l>And a long Dart, then seat me on some rotten </l>
          <l>Monument for the picture of leane Death. </l>
          <l>Make me the common Executioner </l>
          <l>Of Nature. For ere long I shall become </l>
          <l>The Sextons Pensioner to fill his Graues. </l>
          <l>Valdaura false! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e120860">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Wilt thou thus leaue me in a wilde suspence, </l>
          <l>Whether I shall finde thy courage actiue? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e120890">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>For credit of your owne humanitie, </l>
          <l>Doe not infringe the vulgar priuiledge </l>
          <l>Due to all hearts. Giue me but leaue to thinke; </l>
          <l>And ne're doubt your businesse! Though I'm a young </l>
          <l>Sinner; yet I shall soone inquire the way </l>
          <l>To hell. Tis a continu'd thorow-fare </l>
          <l>From this Climate thither. Or let me but </l>
          <l>Delay my iourney, till the triuiall rage </l>
          <l>Of Christian Princes, meete in horri'd battaile; </l>
          <l>And then I shall haue company enough: </l>
          <l>Whole throngs to choke the throat of hell. </l>
          <l>Good night, Madame. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e121020">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Ere yet the Morne 's faire cheek hath lost her teares, </l>
          <l>Dost call it night? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e121050">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>To me it seemes the Eye of heauen doth winke. </l>
          <l>All things are cloath'd in darkenesse, blacke as your </l>
          <l>Designe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e121090">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Stay, for else my rage will not permit </l>
          <l>That we suruiue another meeting. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-029-a"/>
          <l>If thou suspectst we are too loud, I will </l>
          <l>Distill my thoughts into thy eare. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e121140">She hangs about his necke whispering. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e121150">Enter Hermegild, Valdaura. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e121160">
          <speaker>Her. </speaker>
          <l>Though t'assist my great hopes with opportune </l>
          <l>Induction, I consented to this act: </l>
          <l>Yet now I chide my fond spirits. For who </l>
          <l>Dares trust th' vnruly appetite of youth? </l>
          <l>What I decreed she should but taste, she may </l>
          <l>Delight to surfeit on. It shewes fulsome! </l>
          <l>Here's the precious medicine that must restore </l>
          <l>Health to my hopes. Follow, gentle Lady. </l>
          <l>You see 'em now? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e121260">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>Fall, fall, you thicke and spungy clouds, vntill </l>
          <l>You choke my sight. Doe not my eyes begin </l>
          <l>To bleed at this obiect? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e121300">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Marke how close they meete: what variety </l>
          <l>They vse in lust: now she hath melted quite his lips </l>
          <l>With her hot breath, she hangs vpon his eare. </l>
          <l>Suruay their gestures still. Now they depart. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e121350">Exeunt Parad. Rhod. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e121360">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>Ile summon all the hierarchy of heauen </l>
          <l>To censure'em! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e121390">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Who knowes but they are gone to wallow in </l>
          <l>Their actiue sweats agen? Alas, pure soule! </l>
          <l>You perceiue these figures no Idea, </l>
          <l>No obiect of the minde, or ayre incorporate </l>
          <l>To cheate imaginary view. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e121450">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>Was this the cause, that made th'adulterous Queene </l>
          <l>So strictly vrge my swift iourney vnto </l>
          <l>Pauia? </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-029-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e121490">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>I, and the motiue that prouok'd my soft </l>
          <l>Conscience to hasten your returne, that you </l>
          <l>Might tell sad tales to heauen. For I </l>
          <l>(That still was nourc'd vpon a Sybils Lap) </l>
          <l>Who with prophetick Milke did nourish me, </l>
          <l>Can deepely guesse at th'ominous portent </l>
          <l>Of sinne. I hate such loose-rein'd Stallions; </l>
          <l>Such lasciuious harmony in guilt. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e121580">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>So soone proue false? ere the celebration </l>
          <l>Of our marriage Rites were fully ended? </l>
          <l>Ere the Sunne in's iourney o're this Region </l>
          <l>Had twice beheld thus incorporate </l>
          <l>By holy Church, and smil'd vpon the hopes </l>
          <l>Of our increase? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e121650">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>I, there's a contemplation that would crack </l>
          <l>Euen heart-strings made of wyer. Hymens Taper </l>
          <l>But newly lighted, and he with rude breath </l>
          <l>Blowes from the quickning weeke the gawdy flame. </l>
          <l>Then in the darke, thus wilfully misse-takes </l>
          <l>Your bed, and riots 'tweene vnlawfull sheets. </l>
          <l>Horror! horror! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e121730">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>O my sinister Starres! Thus I shall weepe </l>
          <l>Till I haue emptied all my veines. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e121760">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>What should such white and harmelesse soules as we </l>
          <l>Do crawling o're this mountainous Earth? Alas, </l>
          <l>We cannot drinke, till we intoxicate </l>
          <l>A Whale, nor surfeit, till our greazie cheekes </l>
          <l>Doe swell like Th'vdders of a Cow. Nor can </l>
          <l>We kneele like warme Idolaters, vnto </l>
          <l>The rusty metall in a bag. We want </l>
          <l>These helpes to gaine vs honour and esteeme. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e121850">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>I haue a resolute intent to die, </l>
          <l>And seeke my Mansion in a purer Orbe. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-030-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e121880">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>But ere you doe begin your last walke, ith' path </l>
          <l>Inuisible, some meritorious act </l>
          <l>(Ioynd to the Charter of your Creed) should helpe </l>
          <l>T'assure your future blisse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e121930">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>O name it, ere my sorrow shall decay </l>
          <l>Me strength: for I would mix abilitie </l>
          <l>With will. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e121970">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Your Lord (foule, and sinfull as mortalitie </l>
          <l>Can make him) Salamander-like, shall bathe </l>
          <l>In blue fires, vnlesse by sufferance here </l>
          <l>On earth, he penetrate the hearth of heauen, </l>
          <l>And soften their decree. It will be call'd </l>
          <l>Your merit to reuenge his crime, euen with his death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e122040">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>Would you haue me kill him? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e122060">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Since I am strict to vertue, I must needs </l>
          <l>Be cruell vnto vice. Let him not liue </l>
          <l>To increase his owne guilt, and betray more </l>
          <l>Ladies. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e122110">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>But shall I iustice take from powerfull Heauen, </l>
          <l>And vse it with such cruelty? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e122140">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Beleeue me skill in sacred Oracles, </l>
          <l>My piety to warrant the designe </l>
          <l>Nor will I fright the frailty of your Sex, </l>
          <l>With horrid circumstance; he shall not bleed, </l>
          <l>This Violl doth containe a draught; which if </l>
          <l>In's vsuall Beueridge powr'd, will coozen him </l>
          <l>Of's leprous soule in his most quiet sleepe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e122220">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>I doe suspect my courage! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e122240">
          <speaker>Her. </speaker>
          <l>Tak't, faire Pupill! think on't in your prayers. </l>
          <l>If you but enioy one single motion </l>
          <l>That informes you it is good: do't with pride </l>
          <l>And boldnesse masculine. Distinguish thus </l>
          <l>Its operation. Foure dayes must fully take </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-030-b"/>
          <l>Their room ith' Kalendar, ere it effect </l>
          <l>Our hopes. Before that houre ariue, he must </l>
          <l>Be wrought to kill the King. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e122330">Aside. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e122340">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>The Violl liquid Lead containes, or else </l>
          <l>Some farre more ponderous Metall: for whilst </l>
          <l>I beare it thus, the wieght seemes to infuse </l>
          <l>A Palsey in my hand. I tremble like </l>
          <l>A string touch'd on my Lute. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e122400">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>It is the Fiend, that would dehort you from </l>
          <l>A pious act: trust not his whispring charmes </l>
          <l>But with a hardy courage, (more then is </l>
          <l>Naturall in thy modest Sex) proceed </l>
          <l>To merit heauen. And now requite my forward zeale </l>
          <l>To vertue, with concealement of my name, </l>
          <l>And interest in this act. Let not the Queene </l>
          <l>Nor your false Lord, know me the Perspectiue, </l>
          <l>Through which you saw their rauenous lusts, but say, </l>
          <l>The King reueal'd it to your eare. 'Twill make </l>
          <l>Them wilde, and doubt their owne confedrate Bawds. </l>
          <l>Thinke not I forbid it as a danger </l>
          <l>To my person; for I affect not life. </l>
          <l>So soft and easie-metald is my heart, </l>
          <l>So well I loue your sinfull Lord, that when </l>
          <l>I heare the surly Bell proclaime his death, </l>
          <l>Like some new weand Babe, I shall dye crying. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e122580">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>Would you haue him kill'd, yet loue him thus? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e122600">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>I, but I loue heauen better. Where, when </l>
          <l>I come, troth I shall prooue too fond a Saint. </l>
          <l>Those Votaries that pray to me, shall finde </l>
          <l>Their businesse soone dispatch'd: here, let this key </l>
          <l>Obscure ye in my Clozet vntill noone: </l>
          <l>For then the Queene expects you will return </l>
          <l>From Pauia. Farewell, the most abus'd, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-031-a"/>
          <l>But noblest Lady in the world. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000367-e122690">Exeunt. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e122700">Enter Grimold (in an old rug gowne, muffled with cloutes) Gondibert, Vollterri. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e122710">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <l>This is the priuy Gallery: place the Chaire, </l>
          <l>Vollterri, where it needs must interrupt </l>
          <l>The Kings passage. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-vollterri" xml:id="ep000367-e122750">
          <speaker>Vollt. </speaker>
          <l>If thy disguize should faile vs, Gondibert </l>
          <l>And I must be attach'd for Impostors. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e122780">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>And then be crop-card too, like Irish Nags. </l>
          <l>You'le both prooue fleete in a Race, prouided </l>
          <l>The foe charge ye in the Rere. Seate me with </l>
          <l>Tender motion— This luxurious Citie </l>
          <l>Hath made me so rotten, I dare not walke </l>
          <l>ith' winde, lest I should be blowne in pieces. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e122850">Enter Hermegild. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e122860">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <l>Quick now counterfeit! Here comes Hermegild. Grimold groanes. </l>
          <l>Groane out like a Bore. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e122890">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>Who ownes that sicke clamor? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e122910">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <l>One (Sir) presented here to tempt compassion </l>
          <l>From all charitable eyes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-vollterri" xml:id="ep000367-e122940">
          <speaker>Vollt. </speaker>
          <l>Want hath betray'd him to hunger, hunger </l>
          <l>To this disease. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e122970">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <p>O, O, O, the Crampe! the Crampe! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e122990">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>Where, Sir? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e123010">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <p>In my stomacke. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e123030">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>That's indeed a cleere symptome of famine. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e123050">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>I'ue eaten nothing this moneth but raw ayre, </l>
          <l>And that giues but weake nourishment to age. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e123080">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>It is my wonder, in a State so rich </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-031-b"/>
          <l>As ours, a climate still befriended thus </l>
          <l>By nature (flourishing with hopefull Springs, </l>
          <l>And Summers chok'd with wealth) a Souldier should </l>
          <l>Be forc'd to make his hunger a disease. </l>
          <l>A prodigie vnparaleld, that want </l>
          <l>Should e're occasion such a dangerous fast. </l>
          <l>Wast not deuotion made him thus abstaine </l>
          <l>From meate? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e123180">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Pure want, Sir, I know small deuotion, I. </l>
          <l>For though I fast much, I pray as little </l>
          <l>As most Christians of my Calling. <stage xml:id="ep000367-e123220">Groanes agen. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e123230">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>He must be sent vnto some Hospitall, </l>
          <l>There eate warmth broths, till he recouer health: </l>
          <l>And then I will procure him from the State </l>
          <l>Some thrifty pension, to maintaine the short </l>
          <l>Remainder of his life in sober works. </l>
          <l>He shall sing Hymnes, and pray to the kind Saints </l>
          <l>In a blue gowne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e123310">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Alas, Sir, I am growne so hoarce, the Saints </l>
          <l>Can hardly heare my Orizons. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e123340">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <l>He will prooue (my Lord) a chargeable Cure: </l>
          <l>For the Physicions do prescribe him nought </l>
          <l>For med'cine, but Aurum-Palpabile. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e123380">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>The Elixir of Gold would surely much </l>
          <l>Asswage the griefe in my stomacke— <stage xml:id="ep000367-e123410">Groanes. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e123420">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>He must needs be hungry, that like th'Ostridge </l>
          <l>Can digest Metall. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-vollterri" xml:id="ep000367-e123450">
          <speaker>Vollt. </speaker>
          <l>The King for his last seruices remaines </l>
          <l>His debtor sixe thousand Duckats. My Lord, </l>
          <l>You shall expresse much charity, if you </l>
          <l>Procure it in a sudden payment. The same will </l>
          <l>Defray his sicknesse charge, and maintaine him </l>
          <l>Well in's health. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-032-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e123520">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <l>Your Lordship shall ingage vs then to drowne </l>
          <l>Your chiefe Title in the best Grape. Wee'le drinke </l>
          <l>Your health, vntill we raise the price of wine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e123560">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Let him continue there his seate. Perhaps </l>
          <l>They (whom I shall straight conduct this way) </l>
          <l>Will so commiserate his want, that he </l>
          <l>Will soone relieue't, though he increase his owne. </l>
          <l>There is some Arte in this, which I must needs </l>
          <l>Discouer, or forfeit my paines. <stage xml:id="ep000367-e123630">Exit. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e123640">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <p>The Fiend is gone! </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e123660">Grimold rises. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e123670">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Will all the vast accruements I proiect </l>
          <l>From this disguize, conuert into </l>
          <l>The slender purchase of an Hospitall? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-vollterri" xml:id="ep000367-e123710">
          <speaker>Vollt. </speaker>
          <p>Thou turne Votary? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e123730">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <l>He'le pray in no language but the High-Dutch, </l>
          <l>The angry Tongue, which seemes to threaten more, </l>
          <l>Then implore. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e123770">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Six thousand Duckats for a Mansion in </l>
          <l>An hospitall, no bigger then a coffin: </l>
          <l>Where like Carthusians, we must feed, not to </l>
          <l>Preuent hunger, but to hinder lust. Princes </l>
          <l>May easily pay their debts, when they inforce </l>
          <l>Their Creditors to buy Titles and Place </l>
          <l>At their owne rates. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-vollterri" xml:id="ep000367-e123850">
          <speaker>Vollt. </speaker>
          <l>Harke! there's somebody approaching hither. </l>
          <l>Tis no safe game to sport with Kings. I'le be gon. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e123880">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <l>Grimold, now trust to your owne performance, </l>
          <l>I may haue vse for my eares, I would not </l>
          <l>Yet leaue them in the Pillory. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e123920">Exeunt Gond. Vollt. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e123930">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Gondibert, Vollterri! forsake the storme </l>
          <l>Ere ye are wet? Weezels! Monkeys! Dogs! </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e123960">Drops downe in 's Chaire. </stage>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-032-b"/>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e123970">Enter Albouine, Hermegild, Thesina. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e123980">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Madame, you are now fully satisfied </l>
          <l>ith' intention of this visit. I wish </l>
          <l>You'ld be as free, and sportiue with him, as </l>
          <l>Your modesty will giue you leaue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e124030">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <p>Trust my obedience, and my skill, Sir. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e124050">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>He lookes like a watchman in that Rugge. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e124070">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Your Maiesty receiues new cause to doubt </l>
          <l>The truth of his disease, from my Seruants </l>
          <l>Information. Who sweares, this very Morne </l>
          <l>Hee hath been seene in all the violence </l>
          <l>Of drinke, and ith' Burdelli too. For, Sir, </l>
          <l>Though he be old, he's giuen much to propagation. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e124140">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Let vs retire 'tweene th'Arras, and we </l>
          <l>Shall share, ith' whole discouery. <stage xml:id="ep000367-e124170">He groanes. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e124180">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>Alas, who is't, that so prouokes the tongue </l>
          <l>Of pitty! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e124210">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>An old souldier o' the Kings— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e124230">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>Hah! Captaine Grimold! how come you thus </l>
          <l>Imprison'd in a Chaire? haue you the Gowte? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e124260">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <p>I am not rich enough t'inioy the Gowte. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e124280">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <p>What name then doe you giue to your disease! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e124300">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <p>The Physicions call it famine. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e124320">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>How? Heauen secure the State! I hope we are </l>
          <l>Not guilty of a sinne so horrible, </l>
          <l>To deny a Souldier fit materials </l>
          <l>For conseruation of his life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e124370">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Tis fourteene dayes since I haue had a iust </l>
          <l>Occasion but to picke my teeth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e124400">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <p>Alas the day! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e124420">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Each of my thighes are dry'd, and hardned like </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-033-a"/>
          <l>An old West-Falia Flitch. All m'interals </l>
          <l>Are shrunke vp. My bladder is no bigger then </l>
          <l>A Pigs: and were my leane iawes vnmuffled, </l>
          <l>You should see me mumpe, like a Matrone that </l>
          <l>Had lost her teeth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e124490">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <p>O cruell starres!— </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e124510">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <p>Hah! Does she weepe? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e124530">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>Could you on this wide Earth, finde no obiect </l>
          <l>For your fury, but braue Grimold? Or is't </l>
          <l>Because you saw, it was my chiefe vertue </l>
          <l>To affect a Souldier? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e124580">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <p>If she should be in earnest now? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e124600">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <p>I hope you doe not vtterly despaire of life? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e124620">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>I may linger out a score of yeeres, or so; </l>
          <l>But I cannot liue long. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e124650">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>Since you are mark'd for sudden death, cold death </l>
          <l>That silenceth all tongues: and since this place </l>
          <l>Is so secure from neighbouring eares, I will </l>
          <l>Disclose, what vntill now my modesty </l>
          <l>Inforc'd me to conceale. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e124710">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <p>I shall forget to counterfeit! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e124730">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>Know, Sir, that I haue lou'd you long; lou'd you </l>
          <l>With soft and tender passion. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e124760">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>O Rogue! What doe I like the picture </l>
          <l>Of Winter, in this wither'd habit? I must </l>
          <l>Recouer my health. But alas, Madame, </l>
          <l>Doe not deride his destiny, that now </l>
          <l>Is taking flight to reach that place, where your </l>
          <l>Best Starre inhabits, and shall haue power </l>
          <l>To tell loud tales: if you prooue thus cruell. </l>
          <l>How could you e're loue me? I haue been old, </l>
          <l>Euen since your first originall growth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e124860">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>But if you will permit, I may expresse </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-033-b"/>
          <l>A little vanity in loue, I can </l>
          <l>Informe you, Sir, how much we Ladies prize </l>
          <l>Age before Youth in Louers. Old men are </l>
          <l>Discreet sinners, and offend with silence. </l>
          <l>But young men, when the game is done, doe crow </l>
          <l>Like pregnant Cocks: boast to the world their strength </l>
          <l>In folly. Besides (Sir) an authentick </l>
          <l>Lady sayes in her Problemes thus: </l>
          <l>The Young and slender Graft is easly broke, </l>
          <l>But who can shake, or bruise the aged Oke? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e124980">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>A rare Adage. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e125000">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>The Lady Author sure, is o'th' Moddernes. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e125020">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>My ioy is turn'd to a disease; it makes </l>
          <l>Me speechlesse! I euer thought these Court-Tits </l>
          <l>Were much taken with my smooth lookes; but that </l>
          <l>Their modesty still kept them from my reach. </l>
          <l>Foolish modesty! It has hindred my </l>
          <l>Preferment much for since I left the Campe, </l>
          <l>I haue been in loue with some three hundred </l>
          <l>Of'em, yet neuer durst lay claime to one. </l>
          <l>Vh! vh! If Heauen should so affect </l>
          <l>Our mutuall appetites, as to restore </l>
          <l>My health, would you continue still to doate </l>
          <l>Vpon an old sinner? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e125150">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>O, I should grow more fond; preserue you long </l>
          <l>Aliue with zealous Orizons! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e125180">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Las! poore Maulkin! She's caught! I shall grow rich. </l>
          <l>For I haue heard, these Court-Ladies allow </l>
          <l>Large pensions to their Paramors. Helpe! helpe! </l>
          <l>To mooue me higher in my seate— </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e125230">She takes him by the hand, he rises. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e125240">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>Blesse vs! me thinks, Sir, you begin to vse </l>
          <l>Your legges with actiue strength. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-034-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e125270">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>A precious Ape! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e125290">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>He will shew fine tricks anon! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e125310">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Some strange influence from your touch, hath giuen </l>
          <l>A second Youth vnto my faculties: </l>
          <l>Before, I seem'd to crawle like to a Crab: </l>
          <l>Now my ioynts grow supple, as if I were </l>
          <l>Prouided for a Race. This hand inspires my strength— </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e125370">Enter Cunymond, Frollo, Conrade. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e125380">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <p>I haue a Key, will giue vs passage here to th'Park! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e125400">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>Vnhand me, Sir, for I shall forfeit all </l>
          <l>My fame else. They'll thinke, I am immodest— </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e125430">He spies them, then drops downe in's Chaire. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-conrade" xml:id="ep000367-e125440">
          <speaker>Conrad. </speaker>
          <p>Captaine Grimold! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-frollo" xml:id="ep000367-e125460">
          <speaker>Frollo. </speaker>
          <p>He sits like a Witch, sayling in a siue. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e125480">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <l>Hah! sicke! Gentlemen, auoid the windy side, </l>
          <l>Lest he infect ye with his breath. I know </l>
          <l>His disease, and whence it came, shortly </l>
          <l>You'le see him weare a Curtaine sore his Nose; </l>
          <l>That's now the newest fashion that came from Paris. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-frollo" xml:id="ep000367-e125540">
          <speaker>Frollo. </speaker>
          <l>I, tis it: he has them growing on his </l>
          <l>Temples here— They'll shortly be as bigge </l>
          <l>As Turnips. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-conrade" xml:id="ep000367-e125580">
          <speaker>Conrad. </speaker>
          <l>He must to Roterdam, to the fat Doctor there, </l>
          <l>And be stew'd in a Stoue, vntill he spit </l>
          <l>His venome out. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e125620">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <l>And whilst you are in physick (Captaine) </l>
          <l>You fare like Oberon. Tis a very </l>
          <l>Slender diet. The leane thigh of a Waspe </l>
          <l>To dinner; and some two or three of your </l>
          <l>Owne penitent teares for your beueridge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e125680">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>I'ue but so much breath left, as would make vp </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-034-b"/>
          <l>A short prayer to secure my last iaunt: </l>
          <l>Yet I will spend it in a hearty curse </l>
          <l>For your deare sakes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e125730">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <l>March on! If he doe finde himselfe agrieu'd, </l>
          <l>Let him send me a challenge after his death; </l>
          <l>And I will meete him, Ith' Elizian Fields. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e125770">Exeunt Cunimond, Conrade, Frollo. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e125780">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <p>I will eate that Cunymond! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e125800">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>How prompt the Slaue is, in 's metamorphosis? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e125820">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>To him agen, Madame? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e125840">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>Alas, deare Captaine, what bodily hope </l>
          <l>Can a young Lady haue of your performance, </l>
          <l>That fall so soone in a relapse? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e125880">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>When you depriu'd me of your hand, you took </l>
          <l>Away my strength and heate: touch me agen, </l>
          <l>And I shall walke stiffe as Cacus. <stage xml:id="ep000367-e125920">She lifts him vp. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e125930">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <p>Take leasure in your motion, Sir. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e125950">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Looke, Madame. I creepe as other mortall do, </l>
          <l>On the surface of the Earth— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e125980">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <p>Me thinks you stand vpright too. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e126000">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>I, a Ladies warme hand will make it stand. </l>
          <l>A little physicke from your Lip, and then </l>
          <l>My cure is quite finish'd— Hem! Sure this was </l>
          <l>Nestors receipt to recouer his Youth. Hem!— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e126050">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <p>I shall be fainted for this miracle. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e126070">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>I am as wholesome as a Nut, and haue </l>
          <l>As proud flesh about me, as the youngest </l>
          <l>Gamester of 'em all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e126110">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <p>Fye, Sir! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e126130">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>If this heate continue, I must e'en call </l>
          <l>For a Iulip, or sow my wilde Oates </l>
          <l>In the next soyle I meete. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e126170">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <p>Your tongue is blister'd. </p>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-035-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e126190">
          <speaker>Grimo. </speaker>
          <p>When shall we solace our bodies? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e126210">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <p>Your meaning, Sir? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e126230">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>I meane ith' darke. Speak, prety Finch with the </l>
          <l>Greene taile? Hah! Must we kisse close, and often? </l>
          <l>Wriggle vp and downe like young Eeles— </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e126270">Hermegild comes behind him, and puls him by the arme. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e126280">
          <speaker>Her. </speaker>
          <l>Captaine, I haue brought the King here to view, </l>
          <l>And to commiserate your leane sicknesse, </l>
          <l>And your feeble wants. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e126320">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>Thou old rauenous Goate! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e126340">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>He lookes now like an Alchymist, that is </l>
          <l>Broyling o'red Herrings. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e126370">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>Or like the brazen head, when 'twas about </l>
          <l>To speake— <stage xml:id="ep000367-e126400">He takes the King aside. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e126410">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <p>You meane to hang me now! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e126430">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>Hast thou deseru'd an easier sentence? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e126450">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>When I am dead, then all my debts are pay'd. </l>
          <l>For I leaue small Lands and Chattels behind me. </l>
          <l>But hearke ye (my Liege) you may pay your debts </l>
          <l>In your life time, so depriue your Executor </l>
          <l>Of a trouble. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e126510">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>O what a triuiall exit shall I make </l>
          <l>From my owne world? for when I die, I die </l>
          <l>For loue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e126550">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>And I for lechery. Sir, I would faine </l>
          <l>Depart in quiet like other young Chrysomes: </l>
          <l>Faine make all euen betweene the world and me. </l>
          <l>I beseech your Highnesse discharge my areres </l>
          <l>For my last seruice in Hungary, </l>
          <l>Then hang me when you please. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-035-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e126620">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Captaine, I will be a Sutor for your reprieue. </l>
          <l>You shall onely forfeit what his Grace owes you; </l>
          <l>And then your life's secur'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e126660">Grimold kneeles. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e126670">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>I will rather die twice. O Sir, pay me </l>
          <l>Six thousand Duckats, and then proclaime </l>
          <l>Your sentence here aloud. I would faine dye </l>
          <l>Merrily. I haue not been drunke at my owne charge </l>
          <l>This foure moneths. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e126730">Enter Rhodolinda. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e126740">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Hermegild, iterate now thy sweete raptures. </l>
          <l>Speake to her; for, by th' gentle carriage of </l>
          <l>Her eyes, I doe perceiue she 'gins to penetrate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e126780">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>Away Captaine! be gone whilst you are yet </l>
          <l>Mortall. I haue much power with Hermegild, </l>
          <l>And will vpon your patient sufferance </l>
          <l>Redeeme my credit with your thoughts. Quick then, </l>
          <l>Mooue with silence. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e126840">Exeunt Grim. Thes. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e126850">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Madame, the feather'd Arrow sings ith' Ayre, </l>
          <l>Ere it ariue where it must wound; so this </l>
          <l>Sweet harmony, I'ld haue you counterfeit, </l>
          <l>But tempts him to security in sleepe, </l>
          <l>Before his death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e126910">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>I'm much oblig'd to that good soule. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e126930">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>True, my Royall Lady! yet now peruse </l>
          <l>The greatnesse of his being, his fate in battailes, </l>
          <l>And by your owne remembrance be inform'd </l>
          <l>Of our captiuitie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e126980">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>Honest Hermegild? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e127000">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>He was too cruell to a nature so </l>
          <l>Remisse, and timorous as mine? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e127030">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Alas, this crime he expiats with sighs </l>
          <l>So hot, that they would sindge his Royall Beard, </l>
          <l>Did not his numerous teares opportunely drop, </l>
          <l>To quench the flame. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-036-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e127080">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>That's complement! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e127100">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>These angry frownes vpon your browes make you </l>
          <l>Appeare aged. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e127130">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Could I assure my heart; he would no more </l>
          <l>Triumph o're my deare Fathers memory; </l>
          <l>I then should meet his loue with too much passion. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e127170">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>When I am more my Chronicle, or speake </l>
          <l>My deeds with pride, may my tongue blister, till't </l>
          <l>Infect my breath with Epidemick-heate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e127210">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>You heare his vowes?— Seeme fond. If you can shead </l>
          <l>A teare, or two, the more to credit this </l>
          <l>Atonement, 'twill much aduantage our pretence. </l>
          <l>Sir, now enioy what your indulgent griefe </l>
          <l>Merits to keepe, e'en from the hands of death. </l>
          <l>Good heart, see how shee weepes? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e127280">King kisses her. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e127290">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>I'm soone o'recome in this soft warre. S'death all </l>
          <l>Can thaw but I. I neuer wept, but when </l>
          <l>Th'vnruly winde blew in my eyes; and tis </l>
          <l>No argument for sterne battaile: else I </l>
          <l>Would fight. To testifie the ioy my soule </l>
          <l>Conceiues, Ile drinke— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e127360">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Sir, you neglect to vse her like a Louer; </l>
          <l>With amorous gestures. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e127390">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Fill me a Bowle with Negro's blood, congeal'd </l>
          <l>Euen into Liuers! Tell her, Hermegild, </l>
          <l>Ile swallow Tarre, to celebrate her health! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e127430">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Sir, this dull Germane phrase, makes her suspect </l>
          <l>Your temperance. Marke how she trembles. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e127460">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>I must go learne to complement. Dost heare? </l>
          <l>Is't fit I proffer her to mingle limmes— Thou know'st— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e127490">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Sir, not to night. That was a serious sute </l>
          <l>She bade me make, when first she purpos'd this </l>
          <l>Atonement. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-036-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e127530">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>I do obey. Though I haue thoughts would faine </l>
          <l>Perswade me to rebellion. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e127560">Exeunt Albo. Rhod. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e127570">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>This was a subtill caution! else my hopes </l>
          <l>Had twice been Cuckolded. Let'em reuell </l>
          <l>With their salt Lippes. Th' other sport is fulsome. </l>
          <l>But Paradine disturbes my sleepe: he's young, </l>
          <l>Enrich'd with all the fertill strength of nature: </l>
          <l>And needs must prooue more riotous in sinne, </l>
          <l>Then I. My darke practice, and vse </l>
          <l>Of silent contemplation; has made </l>
          <l>My marrow thinne and black; like Inke within </l>
          <l>My bones. I want the prompt alacrity. The Queene </l>
          <l>Hath tasted him, and may (perhaps) still to </l>
          <l>Possesse his lust; remooue Valdaura from </l>
          <l>This foggy Soyle; then make him Lord of all </l>
          <l>My hopes. This to preuent, I haue decreed, </l>
          <l>Valdaura first shall minister his death. </l>
          <l>Iu'e taught her too; t' insinnuate to his Creede, </l>
          <l>That the King told her of 's adulterous lust; </l>
          <l>Good, for when he thinks the King doth know that guilt, </l>
          <l>His owne safety then, will soone prouoke him </l>
          <l>Hasten our prodigious murther. This may </l>
          <l>Be done, before the Poyson operate </l>
          <l>In dire effect; for that delays its power; </l>
          <l>Till fourescore houres expire their course: which then </l>
          <l>No Antidote, nor humane skill resists. </l>
          <l>Mount, mount my thoughts, that I may tread on Kings, </l>
          <l>Or if I chance to fall, thus soaring high; </l>
          <l>I melt like Icarus, in the Sunnes Eye. <stage xml:id="ep000367-e127850">Exit. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e127860">Enter Paradine, and his Page. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e127870">
          <speaker>Par. </speaker>
          <l>The Sun doth melt vs with his scorching beames. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-037-a"/>
          <l>Goe fill my vsuall Beuiridge: Ile drinke </l>
          <l>Till I am cold. <stage xml:id="ep000367-e127910">Exit Page. </stage>
          </l>
          <l>The constitution of my Soule, agrees </l>
          <l>Not with this Climate. I grow weary </l>
          <l>Of mortalitie. Euen in my first growth </l>
          <l>(Since my Corselet was my loade) I haue tooke </l>
          <l>My breeding in the Campe; where had I still </l>
          <l>Remain'd a dull practike souldier, and nere seene </l>
          <l>A Woman, nor the Court, I might haue had </l>
          <l>Some hope, to gaine by faith, but now I reach </l>
          <l>At wilde despaire. <stage xml:id="ep000367-e128010">Enter Page with a Bowle. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-page" xml:id="ep000367-e128020">
          <speaker>Page. </speaker>
          <l>My Lady, Sir, commends her loue, and this </l>
          <l>To your acceptance; she made the mixture </l>
          <l>With her owne hands. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e128060">
          <speaker>Par. </speaker>
          <l>The Queene prescrib'd this houre for her returne. </l>
          <l>That she growes black with sinne, peruerts my sense, </l>
          <l>I must seem not to know't. Say, I greet her health-drinks. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e128100">Exit Page. Enter Valdaura in close mourning. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e128110">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Hah! why, Valdaura, dost thou appeare like </l>
          <l>A funerall night, in darke, and swarthy weedes! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e128140">
          <speaker>Valdau. </speaker>
          <l>I mourne for you, since you must hasten your </l>
          <l>Eternall absence now from me, and all </l>
          <l>That else are mortall. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e128180">
          <speaker>Par. </speaker>
          <l>Speak things, that are lesse dangerous to my sense. </l>
          <l>This wonder will distract me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e128210">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>Ere winged Time, shall with swift motion adde </l>
          <l>Another houre, to th' life of this sicke day; </l>
          <l>Thou shalt begin thy last sleepe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e128250">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>A pale Swanne hath sung my Dirge! O fatall </l>
          <l>Musick! but how comes this intelligence </l>
          <l>To Eares of flesh and blood? haue you of late </l>
          <l>Been gossiping with the grim Stygian Dames, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-037-b"/>
          <l>And seene their Cisers gall my vitall Thread? </l>
          <l>For to my owne sense I need no Physicke. </l>
          <l>My faculties enioy that pleasant strength </l>
          <l>Which appertaines to youth and temperance; </l>
          <l>Why should I yet die? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e128350">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>How, Paradine? Art thou so full of guilt, </l>
          <l>(Most vlcerous and deform'd) yet thinkst to keepe </l>
          <l>Thy life at Natures charge, t' exist till age </l>
          <l>Makes thee a Cripple: then in thy bed, </l>
          <l>(Like some good old Patriarke) thy soule dismisse </l>
          <l>With a diuine rapture? No, no; iust Heauen </l>
          <l>Prouides more rash and horrid deaths for such, </l>
          <l>As in adultery bathe their silken limmes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e128440">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>Hah! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e128460">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>I know thy guilt; the King hath told me all. </l>
          <l>'Twas wondrous strange! Our vowes but new arriu'd </l>
          <l>In heauen, that did obliege our mutuall Faiths </l>
          <l>In loue: and thou with sauage lust to breake them? </l>
          <l>Though griefe hath much consum'd my teares, yet I </l>
          <l>Haue some still left t' expresse my pitty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e128530">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>My adultery already knowne, both to </l>
          <l>The King and her? why, these are prodigies </l>
          <l>Indeed. How sinne imboldens the aspect! </l>
          <l>She doth accuse me for a guilt, which yet </l>
          <l>Remaines vnpardon'd in her selfe. Mine was </l>
          <l>A dire mistake: but hers— that must be knowne, </l>
          <l>And then her veines shall weepe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e128610">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <p>You are poyson'd, Paradine. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e128630">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>With that cold draught you sent me now ith' Bowle? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e128650">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>The Vipers vomit, nor the blue steame, </l>
          <l>Which fat Toades doe breathe in tired motion, </l>
          <l>Beares not such a dangerous enmitie </l>
          <l>'Gainst humane Nature, as that you drunke. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-038-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e128700">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Stay! Me thinks I feele no insurrection </l>
          <l>In my blood, nor need an Iron Corselet </l>
          <l>To containe my flesh; sure it swels not yet. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e128740">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>It takes a subtill leasure to disperse </l>
          <l>Thorow all your Organs, and your Arteries, </l>
          <l>That it may straite with abler violence </l>
          <l>Consume your strength. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e128790">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>And then I shall look goggle-ey'd! and stretch </l>
          <l>Ith' cheekes, till my face shew like a Pompeon, </l>
          <l>Round and yellow? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e128830">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <p>Farre, farre more deform'd. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e128850">
          <speaker>Par. </speaker>
          <l>Will't make my eies start from my skull, or drop </l>
          <l>Like bullets at my feete? Speake, shall I fome </l>
          <l>At mouth like some young Courser, that is hot </l>
          <l>And angry with his bit? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e128900">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>Not the first Chaos was so vgly and </l>
          <l>Confus'd, as you'll appeare, when this distilment works. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e128930">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Yet I forgiue you all, e'en from my heart: </l>
          <l>Whilst my cogitations now are sober, </l>
          <l>And can distinguish things with pregnant sense. </l>
          <l>I doe applaude this cruell benefit. </l>
          <l>These subtill vanities of Court haue tyr'd </l>
          <l>My obseruation. I was nourc'd within </l>
          <l>Some Armory, and tooke a proud delight </l>
          <l>In actiue Warre; but since our Drummes haue ceas'd </l>
          <l>Their noble clamour, I finde no businesse </l>
          <l>Vpon Earth for me; tis fit I grow immortall. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e129040">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>I did not thinke, his fancy, at this newes, </l>
          <l>Could proue so temperate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e129070">
          <speaker>Par. </speaker>
          <l>To sleepe in cold earth, whilst my dead neighbour </l>
          <l>Neuer at my Coffin knocks, to inquire my health, </l>
          <l>By way of visit: for all are silent </l>
          <l>In the graue. Harsh destiny! Such as I </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-038-b"/>
          <l>Could ne'r expect from thee, Valdaura. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e129130">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>My nature you shall finde much different, </l>
          <l>From what your knowledge heretofore discern'd. </l>
          <l>I haue contriu'd another way to punish </l>
          <l>Thy adulterous heate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e129180">
          <speaker>Par. </speaker>
          <p>You find my sufferance tame enough. Publish all! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e129200">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>To meet your sin with apt reuenge, I'm growne </l>
          <l>A foule loose whore. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e129230">
          <speaker>Par. </speaker>
          <l>Hah! containe thy speech. Expresse but so much </l>
          <l>Modesty, as may secure thy life: for </l>
          <l>My death doth not concerne my rage so much, </l>
          <l>As this foule murder of thy fame. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e129280">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <p>Tis truth: and I confirm't with pride. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e129300">
          <speaker>Par. </speaker>
          <l>Oh, oh! these are the Mandrakes groanes (fatall!) </l>
          <l>For whoso heares them, straight incounters death. </l>
          <l>Now smile (sweet Heauen) since thus I but returne </l>
          <l>Her owne iustice. For my adulterous act, </l>
          <l>She takes my life, and shall I let that bold </l>
          <l>Adulteresse liue?— <stage xml:id="ep000367-e129370">Stabs her with 's Ponyard. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e129380">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>Oh, oh! Hold, hold! Leaue me a little breath </l>
          <l>To vse in prayer. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e129410">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>I am not fraught with diuels spleene; I would </l>
          <l>Not hurt thy soule: here solitary sit, </l>
          <l>Whilst I send vp an humble sacrifice, </l>
          <l>That shall bespeake a pardon for thy crime, </l>
          <l>Ere thou ariue neere heauen. <stage xml:id="ep000367-e129470">Puts her in a Chaire. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e129480">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <p>Dare you trust my last vtterance? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e129500">
          <speaker>Par. </speaker>
          <l>O speak, ere thou dost catch an euerlasting cold, </l>
          <l>And shalt be heard no more. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e129530">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>I am not false vnto your bed: I ne'r </l>
          <l>In act, nor guilty thought, did violate </l>
          <l>My Marriage vowes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e129570">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>Art thou not a Whore? </p>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-039-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e129590">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>No Vestall that preseru'd with quickning oyle, </l>
          <l>The sacred flame, was in her chastity </l>
          <l>More cold, more timorous then I: nor are </l>
          <l>You poyson'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e129640">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Hah! was not that a mixture of distill'd </l>
          <l>Venome, which I drunke? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e129670">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>'Twas healthfull, as the blood of Grapes to age, </l>
          <l>And all your faculties doe still preserue </l>
          <l>Their wonted harmony. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e129710">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Sweet spirit, doe not riddle thus with Heauen, </l>
          <l>Nor sport thy soule away. Why didst accuse </l>
          <l>Thy selfe of sterne murder, and pernicious lust; </l>
          <l>Yet art thus cleere from both? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e129760">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>'Twas to inrage your violence, with hope </l>
          <l>To make you soone my executioner. </l>
          <l>For hearing you were false, I found no ioy </l>
          <l>In life: your hand hath seal'd my wishes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e129810">
          <speaker>Par. </speaker>
          <l>New Arts t'increase my wonder: I'm orereach'd, </l>
          <l>Where I thought my nature was most skilfull! </l>
          <l>E'en in loue! O stay: had not distraction </l>
          <l>Ceaz'd my memory; I should at first haue told you </l>
          <l>The mistake, by which the sinfull Queene </l>
          <l>And Hermegild betray'd my chaste Honour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e129880">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <l>Nam'd you Hermegild, guilty of that sinne? </l>
          <l>He's then a horrid hypocrite: he did </l>
          <l>Entice me by a poysonous practice to </l>
          <l>Contriue your death, but found my nature loyall. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e129930">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>New wonders still! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e129950">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <p>I feele the frozen hand of death. Oh! oh! oh! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e129970">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>Valdaura! Bride! O noble Girle! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-valdaura" xml:id="ep000367-e129990">
          <speaker>Vald. </speaker>
          <p>Mercy! mercy! </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e130010">She dyes. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e130020">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Already turn'd a Ghost! There's rare musicke </l>
          <l>Now in heauen, since thou art gone t'increase </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-039-b"/>
          <l>The sacred Quire. I may behold thee in </l>
          <l>The purple skie, mix'd there with other Starres, </l>
          <l>But neuer on this soile agen. Be this </l>
          <l>Thy Tombe awhile. The Curtaines softly drawne— </l>
          <l>Hermegild treacherous! with poyson too? </l>
          <l>That was her word. Tis fit I seeme t' haue drunke </l>
          <l>The med'cine vp. Good! The rough young Souldier </l>
          <l>May spie at last these spirits of the Court, </l>
          <l>That walke in artificiall clouds: or if </l>
          <l>Their high conceptions soare aboue my reach, </l>
          <l>Yet they haue mortall hearts; such as our owne </l>
          <l>Country steele, may with feeble motion prick, </l>
          <l>Pricke till they groane: for I haue now decreed, </l>
          <l>Whom my dull sense cannot subdue, shall bleed. <stage xml:id="ep000367-e130190">Exit. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
      </div>
      <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="ep000367-e130200">
        <head>Act the fifth. Scene first. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e130210">Enter Hermegild, Thesina, Paradine, Rhodolinda. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e130220">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <p>Shall I belye my owne silence? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e130240">
          <speaker>Her. </speaker>
          <l>Be sudden in your speech! confirme my words: </l>
          <l>Then dispose e'en of my wealth and person. </l>
          <l>I will consent to matrimony; make </l>
          <l>Any vse of this new interest. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e130290">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <p>Sir, you'll forget my merit in this danger? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e130310">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Neuer.— My Lord, I haue discouer'd all. </l>
          <l>See, how aguish her guilt hath made her. </l>
          <l>How she trembles like a frosty Russian </l>
          <l>On a hill. Nay, Lady, nere scatter thus </l>
          <l>Your wilde lookes. Confesse the truth, and you'll gaine </l>
          <l>Mercy. Valdaura (whose Soule Heauen keepe </l>
          <l>From purging fires) hath told her Lord; the King </l>
          <l>Knowes of his wanton stealth with our good Queene. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-040-a"/>
          <l>You were the Instrument that betray'd him </l>
          <l>To th'mistake, and whose secrecy to doubt </l>
          <l>But yours, our reason cannot yet informe vs. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e130430">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>Thus kneeling, I confesse with penitence, </l>
          <l>'T was I reueal'd it to the King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e130460">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Teare forth her eies, and let her then grope out </l>
          <l>Her way to hell— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e130490">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>Stay, deare Madame! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e130510">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Paradine is poyson'd, who knowes, but she </l>
          <l>Doth amply share in that guilt too? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e130540">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>At my humble sute, containe your fury! </l>
          <l>We shall discouer all. My noble Lord, </l>
          <l>It is a griefe that will depriue my life </l>
          <l>Of many yeeres, to thinke, I'm held by your </l>
          <l>Suspect, an Agent in that practice. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e130600">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>I haue reueal'd the euidence, that doth </l>
          <l>Perswade my Creede. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e130630">
          <speaker>Her. </speaker>
          <l>What, Lady, doe you know of this?— Speak with </l>
          <l>Courage, I am your safety. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e130660">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>I saw the King reach to Valdaura's hand </l>
          <l>A poysonous violl; and with religious hints, </l>
          <l>Taught her to mixe it in her husbands draught. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e130700">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>Hah! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e130720">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>Persist in my instructions! <stage xml:id="ep000367-e130740">Aside. </stage>
          </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e130750">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>'T was that night when he enioy'd her person— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e130770">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>Inioy'd her! how? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e130790">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <p>As you inioy'd the Queene. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e130810">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>Heauen! will these miracles ne'r cease? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e130830">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>I shall conuert to stone! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e130850">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Now retire, Thesina, till I haue begg'd </l>
          <l>Your free restorement to the Queene's mercy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e130880">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord, you'll not forget your kind promise </l>
          <l>Of matrimony. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-040-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e130910">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>I'ue nought else, to trouble my remembrance. </l>
          <l>Away, Away! </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e130940">Exit Thesina. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e130950">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>What did remaine suspence, is heere confirm'd: </l>
          <l>My forehead feeles as rugged now as his. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e130980">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Now Sir, y'haue heard such reall circumstance, </l>
          <l>As needs must settle your beliefe, and free </l>
          <l>My heart, from your vnkind dislike. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e131020">
          <speaker>Par. </speaker>
          <l>Valdaura's damn'd! she howles so loude, that she </l>
          <l>Disturbes all hell! O periur'd Whore! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e131050">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Now Paradine! Instruct thy selfe with thoughts. </l>
          <l>Is't euident he euer could affect </l>
          <l>Thy person with sincere dotage, yet thus </l>
          <l>Betray thy strength in thy Fort? Where thy </l>
          <l>Honor still stood sentinell? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e131110">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>I haue other motiues to teach you doubt </l>
          <l>His loyaltie in loue. Which my fond heart </l>
          <l>Cannot conceale, though't would aduantage much </l>
          <l>My owne profit. He hath of late, hung thus— </l>
          <l>Vpon my neck; vntill his amorous weight </l>
          <l>Became my burden: and then lay slabbering o're </l>
          <l>My lips; like some rhumatick Babe. This sport </l>
          <l>My serious braine abhor'd. 'Twas my wonder </l>
          <l>(Since you are cal'd his Minion) he could ere </l>
          <l>Affect my looke. I that am like coffing </l>
          <l>Winter, old, and froward; you the darling </l>
          <l>Of the lusty Spring. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e131240">
          <speaker>Rho. </speaker>
          <l>Speak, is that Bag, that should containe thy Gall, </l>
          <l>Shrunke vp; hast thou nothing bitter in thee? </l>
          <l>Thou art farre, farre more opportunely stor'd </l>
          <l>With time and place for thy reuenge, then wee. </l>
          <l>Ith' middle age of day; when the bright Sunne </l>
          <l>Most powerfully doth warme the world; in thy </l>
          <l>Secret Clozet he takes his vsuall sleepe. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-041-a"/>
          <l>Goe, drill his heart! and make the Couch whereon </l>
          <l>He lyes, his easie monument. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e131340">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>And then enioy a Queene, with all that doth </l>
          <l>Belong to her atchieuement, or her birth. </l>
          <l>As for my seruices, they merit no </l>
          <l>Reward. I know my owne creation much </l>
          <l>Vnfit for Court affaires. If you but wrap </l>
          <l>Me in a shirt of haire, then seate me in </l>
          <l>A darke and gloomy Cell, where I may tumble o're </l>
          <l>Some deepe voluminous Rabbin, you make </l>
          <l>Me safe, and happy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e131440">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Doe't, Paradine! and Fame no Trumpet then </l>
          <l>Shall neede to speake thy praise. Thy Country will </l>
          <l>Afford thee power to sanctifie the chiefe </l>
          <l>O'th' dayes within our Kalender. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e131490">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>And to thy memory high Statues build, </l>
          <l>'Bout which our Noblest virgins once a yeere </l>
          <l>Shall dance in Circles, and sing, vntill they make </l>
          <l>The Marble mooue, like to those loose Quarries; </l>
          <l>Which ore-heard Orpheus and his Harp. Or if </l>
          <l>These cannot inspire heroique fury, </l>
          <l>Yet argue thus; you knew his Bed, but by </l>
          <l>Mistake; which was our guilt, not yours; and for </l>
          <l>Our Countries benefit contriu'd. But he </l>
          <l>Defil'd your sheets in the salt pride of lust. </l>
          <l>Horror! this would incense the temperate Doue; </l>
          <l>Turne all his moysture into gall; teach him </l>
          <l>To weare spurres on his heeles, and make him fierce </l>
          <l>In Duell, as a British Cocke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e131640">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Fier! fier! and warme blood! <stage xml:id="ep000367-e131660">Exit. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e131670">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Follow, follow him, my deare Soueraigne! </l>
          <l>Adde new heate vnto his rage. And d'ye heare! </l>
          <l>Since he is poyson'd, 'twere most fit, some learn'd </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-041-b"/>
          <l>Physicion, did indeuour to secure </l>
          <l>His health. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e131730">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>I heard him say, he is already furnish'd </l>
          <l>With a powerfull med'cine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e131760">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Should you now forget your Royall promise, </l>
          <l>I lose all my industrious merit, </l>
          <l>And remaine a sacrifice to loue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e131800">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>Dost thou grow iealous? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e131820">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Valdaura now is seuer'd from her Soule: </l>
          <l>And Paradine is abler in delights </l>
          <l>Of Youth, more moyst and amorous then I. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e131860">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>Away foole! I seale thy safety with my lip. <stage xml:id="ep000367-e131880">exit. </stage>
          </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e131890">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Thus Nurces hush their froward babes asleep. </l>
          <l>Shortly she'le present me with a Corall-club, </l>
          <l>A Whistle strung with Bells. These femall Arts </l>
          <l>Can ne'r my darke authenticke practice cheate. </l>
          <l>Paradine must die! So I still secure </l>
          <l>My hopes. When that sad houre arriues, </l>
          <l>Wherein the poysonous draught must worke, </l>
          <l>No charmed med'cine can resist its strength. </l>
          <l>I hugge my Genius! 'T was a subtill reach, </l>
          <l>To tell him, that the King hath horn'd his brow: </l>
          <l>For that will more incense his wrath, and aggrauate </l>
          <l>The Queenes reuenge. The weight I beare, doth make </l>
          <l>My motion slow: slow as the Snaile I tread, </l>
          <l>Who trauailes with his tenement on 's head. <stage xml:id="ep000367-e132040">Exit. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e132050">Enter Grimold in new Clothes, Gondibert, Vollterri. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e132060">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <p>The King has pay'd him all 's arreres. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-vollterri" xml:id="ep000367-e132080">
          <speaker>Vollt. </speaker>
          <l>'T was by Thesina's sute to Hermegild: </l>
          <l>The Snake has cast his skin too now. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e132110">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>I, Sir, 'tis a poore Snake that cannot cast, </l>
          <l>His skin once in a Summer. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e132140">
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-042-a"/>Enter Cunymond, Conrade, Frollo. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e132150">
          <speaker>Cun. </speaker>
          <p>'Slight, here's Grimold! Didst not thou say he was dead? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-conrade" xml:id="ep000367-e132170">
          <speaker>Conr. </speaker>
          <p>But I haue heard since, his ghost walks. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-frollo" xml:id="ep000367-e132190">
          <speaker>Frol. </speaker>
          <l>Look! 't has found the hidden treasure then, which </l>
          <l>Made it walke; for the Ghost hath bought it selfe </l>
          <l>New clothes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e132230">
          <speaker>Grimo. </speaker>
          <l>Nay, nay, stay, Gentlemen! Let vs forget </l>
          <l>Old quarrels, then end our new acquaintance. </l>
          <l>We are for the Countrey now. Ile but tell ye </l>
          <l>A few of your faults, and leaue th' amendment </l>
          <l>To your owne leasures: but you all thinke </l>
          <l>Y'are wiser then I. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-cunymond" xml:id="ep000367-e132300">
          <speaker>Cuny. </speaker>
          <p>We should abuse our iudgements else. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e132320">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Mark! This is a new Court-thrift: when you are </l>
          <l>Loth to maintaine flatterers, you publish </l>
          <l>Your selues with your owne prayse. Lay your fingers </l>
          <l>Here— Not a word, lest I returne ye a blow. </l>
          <l>I know ye cannot speake without a complement. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-vollterri" xml:id="ep000367-e132380">
          <speaker>Vollt. </speaker>
          <p>They vse it in their prayers, they. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e132400">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <l>Cunymond, in one single complement </l>
          <l>So much wasted his Lungs, that I was faine </l>
          <l>To call for Aqua vita to recouer </l>
          <l>His breath. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e132450">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>I'ue heard you haue transported from Paris </l>
          <l>The Geometricall cringe, and the Art </l>
          <l>Of numbring the haires vpon your chins. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-vollterri" xml:id="ep000367-e132490">
          <speaker>Vollt. </speaker>
          <p>And of starching your Beards. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e132510">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <p>Yes, and of perfuming your very shadowes. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e132530">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>And they say, it is your custome to sleepe </l>
          <l>In Pomatum Masques. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-vollterri" xml:id="ep000367-e132560">
          <speaker>Vollt. </speaker>
          <p>And that you paint your prety Vis'gnomies. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e132580">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Yes, and colour them so red, that you seeme </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-042-b"/>
          <l>To blush more, then the Signe of the Kings head </l>
          <l>Before a Country Inne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e132620">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <l>Y'abuse Astrology too; for you clip </l>
          <l>Black-Taffeta into Starres; and for a foile </l>
          <l>To your beauty; fix 'em in seuerall Regions </l>
          <l>Of your face. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e132670">
          <speaker>Gri. </speaker>
          <l>Which makes it look, like the picture of Doomes-day; </l>
          <l>When all the Planets are darkened. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-vollterri" xml:id="ep000367-e132700">
          <speaker>Vollt. </speaker>
          <p>Nay, nay, stay awhile! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e132720">
          <speaker>Grim. </speaker>
          <l>Leaue off your jigging motion, when you mix </l>
          <l>Your selues in a salute; your bodyes seeme </l>
          <l>To dance vpon your knees. You pinion vp </l>
          <l>Your Elbowes thus:— like Pullets trust vpon </l>
          <l>A spit. Then wreath your Hammes in thus; and mooue </l>
          <l>With a discreet leasure, as if you meant </l>
          <l>To number all the Pibbles in the street. </l>
          <l>And then you fleere, as if y' had wash'd your gummes </l>
          <l>In vineger. This you admire for gesture </l>
          <l>Of the newest fashion. I say, 'tis skiruy! </l>
          <l>For he that greets a Lady so, does looke </l>
          <l>Like a Sope-boyler, vpon a Close-stoole. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-vollterri" xml:id="ep000367-e132850">
          <speaker>Vollt. </speaker>
          <l>If you will take Physicke for your soules-health, </l>
          <l>Retire into that part of the Kingdome </l>
          <l>Which lies farthest from France. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-gondibert" xml:id="ep000367-e132890">
          <speaker>Gond. </speaker>
          <l>He counsels well: for the French ayre hath made </l>
          <l>Many of our Gentry drunke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-grimold" xml:id="ep000367-e132920">
          <speaker>Gri. </speaker>
          <l>And now moue hence; but with your lips sow'd vp, </l>
          <l>For feare of a complement. You two shall straite </l>
          <l>Take horse with me, and be billited in </l>
          <l>My Quarter. Stay, Gentlemen! One word more! </l>
          <l>This is a hot Climate: when you must needs </l>
          <l>Marry to increase your Tribe, your best way </l>
          <l>Is to goe a wooing in the Citie: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-043-a"/>
          <l>For certaine rich widdowes there, loue Court-fooles; </l>
          <l>And vse to play with their bables. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e133020">Exeunt omnes. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e133030">A Canopy is drawne, the King is discouer'd sleeping ouer papers: enter Paradine with his sword drawne. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e133040">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>To make him bleed, and leaue his arteries </l>
          <l>(Where the delighted spirits walke) shrunke vp, </l>
          <l>Vntill they curle with heate. The wither'd frame </l>
          <l>Straite to conuert to dust. Then th' vmerous winde, </l>
          <l>To fan it o're the world. Speake, iust Heauen! </l>
          <l>Is this fit vsage for a King? Cassius </l>
          <l>Was rash: perhaps to gaine noise at's funerall; </l>
          <l>Or in 's Elizian fields; beneath a pleasant Hedge </l>
          <l>To tell some prattling ghost what he had done— </l>
          <l>Hah! but Brutus, noble Brutus! the pride </l>
          <l>Of Arts and Warre: so temperate, his soule </l>
          <l>Was more harmonious then the Spheares. Instruct </l>
          <l>(Heroique Lord) thy young Pupill! Why did </l>
          <l>The mighty Cesar fall, by thy cold wrath? </l>
          <l>All silent as the night! He sleepes: before </l>
          <l>Him too, those papers that concerne my house </l>
          <l>Affaires; and my Officiall rule in State. </l>
          <l>Here he comments on my Letters! here with </l>
          <l>Thrifty documents limits my expence. </l>
          <l>Can this indulgent care be counterfeit? </l>
          <l>And meerely carry a pretence of loue? he made </l>
          <l>My wife a blacke adulteresse. O horror! </l>
          <l>Yet who knowes, but 'twas rather his reuenge, </l>
          <l>Then lust; a furious riot, after that </l>
          <l>He knew I whor'd his Queene— </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000367-e133300">He blinds his owne face with a scarfe, sheathes his sword, and then kneeles. </stage>
          <l>Sir! My Lord the King! Sir! </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-043-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e133320">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Hah! Paradine! What witty emblem's this? </l>
          <l>The more to certifie thy loue, dost thou </l>
          <l>Appeare blind. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e133360">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>O Sir, do not mocke my penitence, nor seeme </l>
          <l>Thus to disguize the knowledge of that crime, </l>
          <l>Which hath defil'd my modest bloud, and makes </l>
          <l>Me now asham'd t' incounter with your eyes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e133410">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>He is drunke! Maudlin drunke! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e133430">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Sir, I could creepe aliue into my Tombe, </l>
          <l>And mixe society with Ghosts, whilst I </l>
          <l>Haue yet warme motion left, could I but hide </l>
          <l>My guilt from your perspicuous sight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e133480">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>By heauen drunke with Cider, or with thinne Beere; </l>
          <l>That lookes like th' vrine of a Babe: I'm sure </l>
          <l>The Corsicke Grape infuseth no </l>
          <l>Such whining passion. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e133530">
          <speaker>Par. </speaker>
          <l>Those immateriall powers, that see the thoughts of men, </l>
          <l>When growing in their hearts, can witnesse I </l>
          <l>Abus'd your Royall bed, but by a dire </l>
          <l>Mistake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e133580">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>Hah! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e133600">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Your blacke adulterous Queene betray'd </l>
          <l>Me to her lust by wicked Arts. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e133630">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>This is a sober passion, but implies </l>
          <l>Something that is horrid. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e133660">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Had not heroique warre taught me t' affect </l>
          <l>No rage, but noble; she and Hermegild </l>
          <l>Had intic'd me now to lengthen this your sleepe, </l>
          <l>Vntill the day of generall accounts. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e133710">
          <speaker>Alb. </speaker>
          <l>Suspect must now be rash. Make your face known! </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000367-e133730">Snatches off his Scarfe. </stage>
          <l>He blushes like a Bride; whom through her thin </l>
          <l>Curtaines, the peeping Sunne beholds in soft </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-044-a"/>
          <l>Skirmish with her Lord. I must counterfeit, </l>
          <l>And seeme to know all. Paradine, 'twas farre </l>
          <l>From my coniecture, that a heart so much </l>
          <l>Oblig'd vnto my loue as thine, should wrong </l>
          <l>My Honour in a sense, which but to mould </l>
          <l>In words would teach my tongue to stammer, and </l>
          <l>Deafen all that heare it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e133830">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Thunder and sulpherous fire snatch my cold limmes </l>
          <l>From this dull earth. Sir, whilst my soule affords </l>
          <l>Me reason, and can direct me vnto whom </l>
          <l>My true alleageance is a debt, kill me! </l>
          <l>When I am mad, I shall forget all duty, </l>
          <l>And refuse t' obey your Royall Charter. </l>
          <l>Thrust your good Sword home, till my heart shall kisse </l>
          <l>Your Hilts. Are you so slow in iustice? Thinke, </l>
          <l>How by a darke mistake, I whor'd your Queene: </l>
          <l>Whor'd your Queene! O prodigious phrase! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e133940">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Houle, meager Wolues! empty Tygers! let the hoarce </l>
          <l>Thracian Bull bellow, till he rent his throat; </l>
          <l>And the hot mountaine-Lion rore, vntill </l>
          <l>Their clamour wake the dead. The resurrection </l>
          <l>Is too long delayd, since we want horror </l>
          <l>To celebrate this newes. Good! I haue now </l>
          <l>Decreed it. Draw thy bright weapon!— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e134020">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>For what dire vse? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e134040">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>That we may meet in single battaile here, </l>
          <l>And struggle till we want our Soules. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e134070">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Though this high inticement charmes my blood, like </l>
          <l>The musicke of the Drumme. Yet my remembrance </l>
          <l>Calls you King; My Royall Master. I would </l>
          <l>Not ioyne rebellion and ingratitude </l>
          <l>To the prolixe number of my sinnes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e134130">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>O fond, indulgent Boy! I mourne at this </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-044-b"/>
          <l>Decay of thy humanity and sense. </l>
          <l>Does it become my great being, and my </l>
          <l>Glorious name in story, to offend </l>
          <l>Without resistance? Draw: and be nimble </l>
          <l>In thy motion— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e134200">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>I dare not so disgrace my Religion, </l>
          <l>And my loue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e134230">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Tis time that I were dead, for I shall else </l>
          <l>Outliue my chiefe prerogatiue. I haue </l>
          <l>Forgot how to command. Vnsheath thy Sword! </l>
          <l>Or this breach of Duty shall teach me think, </l>
          <l>I ne'r inioy'd thy reall loue, and 'twas </l>
          <l>Not a mistake, that vsher'd thee to sinne betweene </l>
          <l>My sheetes, but a considerate lust— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e134310">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>No prouocation like to this, could tempt </l>
          <l>A danger from my Arme— <stage xml:id="ep000367-e134340">He drawes. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e134350">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Why dost thou dally thus with feeble motion? </l>
          <l>Beare vp! and vse more violence! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e134380">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Some surgery from heauen! Are you hurt, Sir? </l>
          <l>You willingly oppos'd your brest against </l>
          <l>My steele, and neuer sought t' indanger me </l>
          <l>With yours. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e134430">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>'Thast perform'd, what my wish did prophecy: </l>
          <l>I'm prickd heere, about the heart; and my veines </l>
          <l>Grow empty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e134470">
          <speaker>Par. </speaker>
          <l>Then glorious war, and all proud circumstance, </l>
          <l>That giues a souldier noyse, for euermore farewell— </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e134500">Falling on his sword. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e134510">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Hold, Paradine. Tis my last sute, that thou suruiue </l>
          <l>To minister a iust reuenge on those </l>
          <l>Whom I proscribe, helpe my quiuering Limmes, </l>
          <l>And seate me in the Chaire— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e134560">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Shall posteritie read it in story </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-045-a"/>
          <l>And beleeue; a Prince that doth deserue to be </l>
          <l>The first ith' List of those, that gatherd noyse </l>
          <l>In warre, can be thus couetous t' expire </l>
          <l>In silence darke. Fall on my fatall point, </l>
          <l>And yet command that I suruiue the Tragedy! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e134630">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>'Twere in me an affectation triuiall </l>
          <l>To cherish life, now Rhodolinda's false. </l>
          <l>For should I still preserue my soule in flesh, </l>
          <l>I know my mercy is so fond to her; </l>
          <l>I should forgiue her all: and wert thou dead, </l>
          <l>My hope were then depriu'd of future iustice. </l>
          <l>Liue to reuenge her falshood. I know thy heart </l>
          <l>So sincere and noble, that I suspect not thee </l>
          <l>A sharer in her guilt. When thou </l>
          <l>Didst first confesse th'adulterous crime, ioyn'd with </l>
          <l>Thy owne mistake, through Hermegilds deepe Art, </l>
          <l>My faith conceiu'd the truth: for thy Nature </l>
          <l>Is much too blunt, and credulous for Court. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e134770">
          <speaker>Par. </speaker>
          <l>Should I but speak each cunning circumstance— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e134790">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Containe thy breath! To heare that told, would make </l>
          <l>My soule wander in my last iourney. </l>
          <l>'Till thy relation brought it to my Eare, </l>
          <l>I neuer knew her false. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e134840">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Still my amazement doth increase! Were you </l>
          <l>Not told of this before! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e134870">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>My knowledge only learnt it of thy Tongue. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e134890">
          <speaker>Par. </speaker>
          <l>Stay! Nor with Valdaura, you did ne'r proiect </l>
          <l>My death by poyson? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e134920">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>Neuer. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e134940">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Yet one reply, then make my ioy exceed </l>
          <l>My wonder. Did you neuer in my bed, </l>
          <l>Commit a lustfull stealth? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e134980">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <p>Angels in that, are not more free from guilt. </p>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000367-045-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e135000">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>What Potter made this earthy Skull! pardon </l>
          <l>(Deare Valdaura) my dull suspect! Sing out </l>
          <l>Thy Hymnes in heauen, and neuer listen more </l>
          <l>To my fond speech; for they haue made mee mad! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e135050">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>I cannot gripe the Ayre. Marke how it steales </l>
          <l>Through all my knotty Fingers— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e135080">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>Extasie! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e135100">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Now my last, and short minute is ariu'd; </l>
          <l>I doe, resigne my Crowne— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e135130">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>To whom sir? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e135150">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>To him I hate. But be thou sure, he weare </l>
          <l>It not 'till neere his death: for it's a happinesse </l>
          <l>To liue enthron'd, but tis not safe to dye </l>
          <l>A King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e135200">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>He doth peruert my sense. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e135220">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>Let the Drum cease! Ile haue no more battailes. </l>
          <l>He that to waste his triuiall rage, doth fight </l>
          <l>A battaile, rides a Hawking with the diuell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e135260">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>Mad as the Northerne winde! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-albovine" xml:id="ep000367-e135280">
          <speaker>Albo. </speaker>
          <l>He sends a thousand drinking Animals </l>
          <l>To take their flight ith' ayre, whilst little blacke </l>
          <l>Diuels (d'ye not see 'em?) They looke like Rauens. </l>
          <l>Marke how they prey on those immortall Fowle, </l>
          <l>And plume 'em in their Talents! I doe not like </l>
          <l>This Falconry: it is too sad a game </l>
          <l>For sinners— Oh, oh, oh!— <stage xml:id="ep000367-e135360">Dies. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e135370">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>There dy'd the noblest Trophey of our war! </l>
          <l>The Lombards now haue lost their victory. </l>
          <l>So hardy of creation, his heart-strings </l>
          <l>Were as Cordage, tough; crack'd like a Cable, </l>
          <l>When the frighted Barke starts from the Anchor. </l>
          <l>All that are nours'd in warre, shall mourne for thee. </l>
          <l>Our Ensignes now we will of Cypresse make. <stage xml:id="ep000367-e135450">knocking. </stage>
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-046-a"/>
          <l>Hah! It is the winde that whispers! he must </l>
          <l>Be hid. I'm sure this noyse can neuer wake him— </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000367-e135480">He puts him behind the Arras, opens the doore, enter Rhodolinda. </stage>
          <l>O, are ye come? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e135500">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>Thou hast a wilde aspect! Is it done? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e135520">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>He has paid for his wharfage already, </l>
          <l>And is now entring Charons Boate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e135550">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>Th'art precious as my Soule! <stage xml:id="ep000367-e135570">He opes the Arras. </stage>
          </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e135580">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>There's the old Face. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e135600">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>He lookes like a pale Country Virgin </l>
          <l>That long'd to eate Morter. Our chiefe designe </l>
          <l>Is finish'd: but thou must adde one knot more </l>
          <l>T' obliege my gratitude, and then we shall </l>
          <l>Triumph with safety. Hermegild must die; </l>
          <l>He knowes too much. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e135670">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>It is as if the Parca spoke. If there </l>
          <l>Be any other whom your enuy, or </l>
          <l>Your hate would haue dismist the world, make him </l>
          <l>But knowne, and he is numbred with the dead. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e135720">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <l>Deare Paradine, I sure shall rauish thee, </l>
          <l>My appetite is growne so fierce. Let me </l>
          <l>Begin with thy moyst lip— <stage xml:id="ep000367-e135760">Pulls her to kisse him in the Chaire. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e135770">
          <speaker>Par. </speaker>
          <p>Let's to't like Monkeys, or the reeking Goat. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e135790">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>Oh! oh! oh! Helpe! helpe! </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e135810">Both are bloody about their mouthes. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e135820">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>Cease your loud clamor, Royall Whore. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e135840">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>Thou didst eate my lips. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e135860">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Thy flesh is sowre, musty; more tainted then </l>
          <l>A Carion in a phlegmatick ditch for else </l>
          <l>Like th' Anthropophagus, I had deuour'd thee vp. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-046-b"/>
          <l>This made Valdaura bleed, and must let forth </l>
          <l>Thy swarthy soule— <stage xml:id="ep000367-e135920">Stabs her with his Poniard. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e135930">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>Oh! oh! oh!— </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e135950">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>For Albouine my Royall Master, this— </l>
          <l>And this to pacifie Valdaura's Ghost— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e135980">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>Oh, oh, oh! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e136000">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>So hard and stony is thy heart, that it </l>
          <l>Reuerts the point of my bright steele. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-rhodolinda" xml:id="ep000367-e136030">
          <speaker>Rhod. </speaker>
          <p>Mercy Heauen! <stage xml:id="ep000367-e136050">She dies. </stage>
          </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e136060">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Since thou hast receiu'd my iustice, I wish </l>
          <l>Thee mercy too— <stage xml:id="ep000367-e136090">Knocking. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e136100">
          <speaker>Hermegild </speaker>
          <stage xml:id="ep000367-e136110">within. </stage>
          <l>My Lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e136130">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Tis Hermegild, now I shall end my chiefe </l>
          <l>Discouery. What a full Sepulcher is this— <stage xml:id="ep000367-e136160">Carries her in. Knocking agen. </stage>
          </l>
          <l>Now I must practise my disguize. Reuert </l>
          <l>The Springe twice, and you may enter. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e136190">Counterfeits a sicke voice, sitting. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e136200">Enter Hermegild, Thesina. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e136210">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord, I haue lost my honor in your seruice, </l>
          <l>You may chuse one that shall affect you worse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e136240">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Lady, this is no time to woo: but </l>
          <l>D'ye thinke I'm so prophane to violate </l>
          <l>My vow? Nimbly depart, I doe coniure </l>
          <l>Your absence with this kisse— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-thesina" xml:id="ep000367-e136290">
          <speaker>Thes. </speaker>
          <l>If you should proue false— </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e136310">Exit Thesina. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e136320">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>'Slight, these Wenches at </l>
          <l>Fifteene, are as riotous as Elephants. </l>
          <l>Marry a Court Kitten! There he sits! Hah, sick! </l>
          <l>My sweet Lord, how thriues your health? D'your pulses </l>
          <l>Still preserue their temp'rate musicke? haue you </l>
          <l>Effected yet our great businesse? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e136390">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>The King is dead, that sanguine instrument </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-047-a"/>
          <l>Did set his Soule at liberty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e136420">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>The Lawrell, Mertle, and the Bay shall still </l>
          <l>Cold and naked stand before the Winters </l>
          <l>Frosty breath; still strip their Boughes, to make </l>
          <l>Your head triumphant wreathes. Where is the Queene? </l>
          <l>Me thinks (my Lord) your body and your minde </l>
          <l>Seeme much disturb'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e136490">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Oh, oh! the poyson works— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e136510">
          <speaker>Her. </speaker>
          <l>Alas, my sweet deare Lord! (precious med'cine!) </l>
          <l>He cannot possibly suruiue the next </l>
          <l>Minute. Does it destroy your strength? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e136550">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Oh, oh! It skorches all my entrailes vp: </l>
          <l>As if like Porcia I had swallowed coales. </l>
          <l>I spit scumme, such as o're th' hot Caldron boyles— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e136590">
          <speaker>Her. </speaker>
          <p>And are you fastned in the chaire with weaknes? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e136610">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>I cannot rise. A stiffe conuulsion in </l>
          <l>My Sinnewes fetters all my limmes— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e136640">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>Hah! hah! ha! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e136660">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>O heauen, will you permit him laugh? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e136680">
          <speaker>Her. </speaker>
          <l>I know th'Ingredients of thy poysnous draught. </l>
          <l>'Twas I that gaue it to thy wife. 'Twas I </l>
          <l>Did counsell her to mingle it in thy wine, </l>
          <l>When thou wert hot, and all thy Pores open </l>
          <l>As thy mouth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e136740">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>Oh, oh, oh! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e136760">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Doe, groane, till thou raise an eccho in this </l>
          <l>Square roofe. Ere long thy Ribs will start from thy </l>
          <l>Loose Chine, thy lanke Belly swell into a hill. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e136800">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>O horror! horror! Is Heauen asleepe? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e136820">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>The King ne'r knew of thy adultrous crime. </l>
          <l>'Twas I told it to Valdaura, and made </l>
          <l>Her thinke, thy guilt proceeded not from a </l>
          <l>Mistake, but from thy wilfull lust. I'ue strung </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-047-b"/>
          <l>Thy Nosthrill with a spinners thread, so led </l>
          <l>Thee through subtill Labyrinths, t'inuolue </l>
          <l>Thy senses; and now I triumph o're thy fate. </l>
          <l>This is Italian Spleene. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e136910">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>Had I but strength to actuate my reuenge? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e136930">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Good, dull Souldier! why didst thou leaue the Camp, </l>
          <l>Thy rusty Morion there; thy batter'd Corselet; </l>
          <l>And thy shiuer'd Lance, t' amble here at Court </l>
          <l>In slippery silkes; to walke in cloudy mists </l>
          <l>Of perfum'd ayre? Tis I haue shak'd thy braines </l>
          <l>That heretofore were thicke as Curds, into </l>
          <l>A pale, thin whay. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e137010">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Draw neere, and let me then but kill thee— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e137030">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Troth, thou art so feeble now, that were I kill'd </l>
          <l>By thee, I scarce should thinke that I were dead. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e137060">Paradine rises, and snatches Hermegilds sword from his side. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e137070">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>No! that shall arriue vnto the test. Dog! grim </l>
          <l>As th'angry Fiend, that must deuoure thy soule! </l>
          <l>I am not poyson'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e137110">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>Hah! does he counterfeit? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e137130">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>See heere, what abiect ruines thou hast made </l>
          <l>O'the noblest structures in the world— </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e137160">He drawes the Arras, and discouers Albouine, Rhodolinda, Valdaura, dead in Chaires. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e137170">
          <speaker>Her. </speaker>
          <l>The Queene there too! O triuiall Arts with my </l>
          <l>Owne Myne I'ue blowne my selfe e'en into dust! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e137200">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>I will now see, if thou canst bleed like things mortall— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e137220">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Depriu'd of my defence! If th'ast a soule </l>
          <l>(Great as thy fame) restore my Sword. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e137250">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Thou bark'st against the Moone! I will requite </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-048-a"/>
          <l>Thy owne tyrannous scorne. That destinie </l>
          <l>Was iust, that thus betray'd thee to my mirth. </l>
          <l>There, Stygian Dogge— <stage xml:id="ep000367-e137300">Wounds him. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e137310">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Oh, oh! whilst I haue warmth, Ile moue with violence— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e137330">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Where now are all the subtill Tropheys of </l>
          <l>Thy braine? Plots, darke as hell! proiections grimme! </l>
          <l>Such, as threatned Nature, and seem'd to fright </l>
          <l>The Genius of the world. Now, now preuent </l>
          <l>These dire salutes— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e137390">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>Returne my Sword, then manage Steeples like </l>
          <l>To Pikes; yet, Ile affront thy fury— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e137420">
          <speaker>Par. </speaker>
          <l>Hardy as the Scythians race, I greet thy heart— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e137440">
          <speaker>Her. </speaker>
          <p>I stagger, and am drunk with my owne blood!— </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e137460">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <p>Take my last anger, and good night! <stage xml:id="ep000367-e137480">Falles. </stage>
          </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e137490">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <p>Oh, oh! thou hast stuck Needles in my heart! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e137510">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Now I doe swell with horror and sterne rage: </l>
          <l>I will distract the whole world. Fire! fire! fire! </l>
          <l>Murder, Treason, &amp; incestuous rapes! Fire! fire! <stage xml:id="ep000367-e137550">Exit. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-hermegild" xml:id="ep000367-e137560">
          <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
          <l>I spie </l>
          <l>A white Soule houering in the ayre! one when </l>
          <l>Corporeall, was sure some humble Hermit </l>
          <l>Here on earth. He's acquainted with the way </l>
          <l>To Heauen: should mine take flight alone, I feare </l>
          <l>'T would stray! Hoa! you, you that ascend the Spheares! </l>
          <l>We sinners still seeme hoarce to Angels eares. </l>
          <l>What, hoa! he turnes not yet: who knowes but he </l>
          <l>Still liu'd in low Valleyes, built his Mansion </l>
          <l>In some ag'd wall? but my path euer lay </l>
          <l>On hills, where the good Patriarkes neuer trod. </l>
          <l>Vaine Arts! Ambition in all sacred Schooles, </l>
          <l>Is held the sinne of Heathens, and of Fooles. <stage xml:id="ep000367-e137700">He dies. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000367-e137710">
          <pb xml:id="ep000367-048-b"/>Enter Paradine, Gouernor, Cunymond, Conrade, Frollo, the Guard, &amp;c. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000367-governor" xml:id="ep000367-e137720">
          <speaker>Gouer. </speaker>
          <l>O dire and tragick sight! The King, the Queene </l>
          <l>And faire Valdaura slaine! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e137750">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Heere's another obiect fit for wonder, </l>
          <l>Though not for pitty. <stage xml:id="ep000367-e137780">Spurnes Hermegild. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-governor" xml:id="ep000367-e137790">
          <speaker>Gou. </speaker>
          <l>Hah! he dead too? Whence should these sorrowes flow? </l>
          <l>Lay hold on Paradine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e137820">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>All stay. Ile bore his haggard soule that striues </l>
          <l>With sawcy strength, to captiuate my Limmes: </l>
          <l>Harke, the bigge drumme recouers breath, and speakes! </l>
          <l>March on! The scatter'd foe retires, and all </l>
          <l>The glorious Horse are slaine. I am magnanimous, </l>
          <l>And high! O ye vnkind false starres! ye mocke </l>
          <l>Poore Paradine! A few cleane Teares to wash </l>
          <l>My sinnes away, and I am seene no more. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-governor" xml:id="ep000367-e137910">
          <speaker>Gouern. </speaker>
          <p>Ceaze on him; on forfeit of your liues! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-paradine" xml:id="ep000367-e137930">
          <speaker>Parad. </speaker>
          <l>Their liues are forfeited to me— </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000367-e137950">He fights with the Guard, they wound and disarme him. </stage>
          <l>Heere, heere, it gauld my very heart!— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000367-governor" xml:id="ep000367-e137970">
          <speaker>Gouernor. </speaker>
          <l>Conuay him gently in, and vse all helpe </l>
          <l>Of surgery to stop his wounds: for from </l>
          <l>His mouth, wee must receiue the knowledge of </l>
          <l>These fatall deeds. Some giue th'Allarum to </l>
          <l>The Ports! You Siginors, leade to th'Cittadell; </l>
          <l>Where, we'le proclaime Albouines young Issue </l>
          <l>By's former wife, to bee his lawfull heire. </l>
          <l>Wilde Fancy may proiect things strange and new: </l>
          <l>But Time records no Tale so sad, and true. </l>
        </sp>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back></back>
  </text>
</TEI>
