<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000371" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Humor Out of Breath</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>John</forename>
            <surname>Day</surname>
          </persName>
          <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q2693017</idno>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A19975.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
        </bibl>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Humour out of breath. A comedie diuers times latelie acted, by the Children of the Kings Reuells. Written by Iohn Day.</title>
            <author>Day, John, 1574-1640?</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>30 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2009 March (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99845070</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 6411.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 268.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">9946</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19975</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2240866544</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Humour out of breath. A comedie diuers times latelie acted, by the Children of the Kings Reuells. Written by Iohn Day.</title>
            <author>Day, John, 1574-1640?</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[56] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>[By Richard Bradock] for Iohn Helmes, and are to be sold at his shop in Saint Dunstons Church-yard in Fleet-street,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
            <date type="publication_date">1608.</date>
            <date type="creation_date">1608</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Printer's name from STC.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: [A]2 B-G4 H2.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <person xml:id="ep000371-octavio">
            <persName>Octavio</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000371-francisco">
            <persName>Francisco</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000371-hippolito">
            <persName>Hippolito</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000371-florimell">
            <persName>Florimell</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000371-antonio">
            <persName>Antonio</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000371-hermia">
            <persName>Hermia</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000371-lucida">
            <persName>Lucida</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000371-aspero">
            <persName>Aspero</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000371-page">
            <persName>Page</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000371-hortensio">
            <persName>Hortensio</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000371-flamineo">
            <persName>Flamineo</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000371-boy">
            <persName>Boy</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000371-unassigned">
            <persName>Unassigned</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000371-florimel">
            <persName>Florimel</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000371-ambo">
            <persName>Ambo</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000371-assistance">
            <persName>Assistance</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000371-brothers">
            <persName>Brothers</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000371-jul">
            <persName>Jul</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000371-lord">
            <persName>Lord</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000371-messenger">
            <persName>Messenger</persName>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
      <textClass>
        <classCode scheme="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q40831</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1607">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000371-e100030">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000371-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000371-001-b"/>
        <p>Humour out of breath. </p>
        <p>A Comedie Diuers times latelie acted, By the Children Of The Kings Reuells WRITTEN BY Iohn Day. </p>
        <p>Printed at London for Iohn Helmes, and are to be sold at his shop in Saint Dunstons Church-yard in Fleet-street, 1608. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000371-e100070">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000371-002-a"/>
        <head>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-002-b"/>To Signior No-body. </head>
        <p>WOrthlesse sir, I present you with these my vnperfect labours, knowing that what defect in me or neglect in the Printer hath left vnperfect, iudgement in you will winke at, if not thinke absolute. Being to turne a poore friendlesse childe into the world, yet sufficiently featur'd too, had it been all of one mans getting, (woe to the iniquitie of Time the whilest) my desire is to preferre him to your seruice: in which, as he shall be sure to get nothing, so likewise my hope is, he shall not loose much: For your bountie neither makes strangers loue you, nor your followers enuie you: you are a Patrone worthie the Sister-hood, I meane, the poore halfe dozen, for the Three Elders, they climbe aboue my element: the Sunne, the Moone, and the seuen Stars being scarce worthy the suruey of their workings: I protest I had rather bestow my paynes on your good worship for a brace of Angells certaine, then stand to the bountie of a Better-mans Purse-bearer, or a very good womane Gentlemā-vsher: my reason is I cannot attend: your Bis dat, qui citò stands so like a Load-stone ouer your greate gate, that I feare, twill drawe all the Iron-pated Muse-mongers about the towne in a short time to your patronage. For mine owne part I had rather bee yours volens, then be driuen Nolens: So till I meete you next at your great Castle in Fish-street, ile neither taste of your bountie, nor be drunke to your health. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute>One of your first followers, </salute>
          <signed>Iohn Daye. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="play" xml:id="ep000371-e100130">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000371-003-a"/>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="ep000371-e100140">
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-003-b"/>
          <head>ACTVS 1. Scena. 1. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e100150">Enter Octauio Duke of Venice, Hippolito and Francisco his sonnes, Florimell his daughter: Hortensio and others attendants. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e100160">
            <speaker>Octa. </speaker>
            <l>SOnnes, hopefull buddes of fruitfull Italy, </l>
            <l>Hauing banisht war which like a prodigall </l>
            <l>Kept wastfull reuells with our subiects bloud: </l>
            <l>Since proude Anthonio our arch-enemy </l>
            <l>Is in his iourney towards th'vnderworld, </l>
            <l>Or houers in the shade of banishment; </l>
            <l>Let vs in peace smile at our victory, </l>
            <l>And euery brest passe his opinion </l>
            <l>What pastime best becomes a conqueror. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e100260">
            <speaker>Fran. </speaker>
            <l>What sport but conquest for a conqueror, </l>
            <l>Then with our wounds vndrest, our steeds still reind, </l>
            <l>Branded with steele ere we wipe off the bloud </l>
            <l>Of conquerd foes, lets with our shriller bugles </l>
            <l>Summon the surly Landlord of the forrest, </l>
            <l>The Kingly Lyon to a bloudy parle, </l>
            <l>Combat the Hart, the Leopard or the Bore, </l>
            <l>In single and aduenturous hardyment: </l>
            <l>The spirit of mirth in manly action rests, </l>
            <l>Hauing queld men lets now go conquer beasts. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e100370">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Manly resolu'd; Hippolitoes aduise. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e100390">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Rather like souldiers, and Octauioes sonnes, </l>
            <l>Lets throw a generall challenge through the world, </l>
            <l>For a proud turney, at the which our selues </l>
            <pb subtype="duplicate" type="blank" xml:id="ep000371-004-a"/>
            <pb subtype="duplicate" type="blank" xml:id="ep000371-004-b"/>
            <pb xml:id="ep000371-005-a"/>
            <l>Consorted with a hundred of our knights, </l>
            <l>Accoutred like so many Gods of warre, </l>
            <l>Will keepe the lists gainst all aduenturers, </l>
            <l>Which like the suns light figurd in a star, </l>
            <l>Should be a briefe Epitome of war. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e100480">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Noble and royall, your opinion daughter. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e100500">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Faith I shall anger souldiers, I woulde poure </l>
            <l>Spirit of life, Aurum Potabile </l>
            <l>Into the iawes of chap-falne schollership, </l>
            <l>That haue since amorous Quid was exild, </l>
            <l>Lyen in a swowne, y aue many holds for war, </l>
            <l>I would once view a garrison for witte: </l>
            <l>Twere heauenly sport to see a traine of schollers </l>
            <l>Like old traind soldiers skirmish in the schooles, </l>
            <l>Trauerse their Ergoes and discharge their iests </l>
            <l>Like peales of small-shot, were this motion granted </l>
            <l>My selfe would be free woman of their hall, </l>
            <l>And sit as sister at their festiuall. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e100630">
            <speaker>Oct </speaker>
            <l>Haue we not Padua </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e100650">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Yes, but the commaunders </l>
            <l>Deale with our graduates, as the generall </l>
            <l>Doth with his souldier, giues him place for fauoure, </l>
            <l>Not for deseruing, looke intoo't your selfe, </l>
            <l>You haue Courts for tennis, and me thinkes t'were meet, </l>
            <l>Learning should not stand balling in the street </l>
            <l>For want of houseroome: oh tis much vnfit </l>
            <l>Courtiers should be all pleasure and small wit. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e100740">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>All that you speake is but what we command </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e100760">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>But Officers fother cannot vnderstand </l>
            <l>Their Lords at first: wert not a gallant sight, </l>
            <l>To see wits army royall come from fight? </l>
            <l>Some crownd with gold, others with wreath of bayes, </l>
            <l>And whilst they hold their solemn holydaies, </l>
            <l>Musick should like a louer court the skies, </l>
            <l>And from the world wrest ringing plaudities. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e100840">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>My sister would make a rare beggar. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-005-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e100860">
            <speaker>Fra. </speaker>
            <p>True, shee's parcell Poet, parcell fidler already, and they commonly sing three parts in one. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e100880">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Wrong neither art nor musicke, they are twins </l>
            <l>Borne and begot in heate, your thought of both. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e100910">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>I thinke my Lord that musick is diuine, </l>
            <l>Whose sacred straines haue power to combine </l>
            <l>The soule and body; and it reason beares, </l>
            <l>For it is said that the Celestiall spheres, </l>
            <l>Dance to Apolloes lyre whose sprightly fires </l>
            <l>Haue tamd rude beasts and charmd mens wild desires: </l>
            <l>The author was immortall, the first strings, </l>
            <l>Made by a King, therefore an art for Kings: </l>
            <l>The world's a body, euery liberall art </l>
            <l>A needfull member, musick the soule and hart. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e101020">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Well for hir sex hath Florimell discourse </l>
            <l>Of heauenly musicke, and since all conclude </l>
            <l>It is an art diuine, we were too rude </l>
            <l>Should we reiect it, musick, I take great pride, </l>
            <l>To heare soft musick and thy shrill voice chide. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e101080">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>To please your grace, though J want voice and skill, </l>
            <l>Ile shew my selfe obedient to your will. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e101110">sing. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e101120">
            <speaker>Fra. </speaker>
            <l>This would haue done rare at a schollers window, </l>
            <l>How do you like it father? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e101150">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Highly my boies, I rellish all delight, </l>
            <l>For when the fiery spirit of hot youth </l>
            <l>Kept house within me, I was all delight: </l>
            <l>Then could I take my loue, no loue more fayre </l>
            <l>By the smooth hand, and gazing in loues ayre </l>
            <l>Tell her her beauty beautifide the skie, </l>
            <l>And that the sunne stole lustre from her eye. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e101230">
            <speaker>Fra. </speaker>
            <p>I do admire to heare my princely father thus merrilie discourse of trifling loue. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e101250">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Nay more my boyes, when J was at your yeares, </l>
            <l>I went a pilgrimage through Italie, </l>
            <l>to find the shrine of some loue-hallowed saynt. </l>
            <l>Deuote to beauty, I would pray for loue, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000371-006-a"/>
            <l>Desiring beauty I would sue for loue, </l>
            <l>Admiring beauty I would serue for loue: </l>
            <l>Pray, sue, and serue, till beauty graunted loue. </l>
            <l>If she denyd me, I would sweare she graunted, </l>
            <l>Jf she did sweare that she could neuer loue me, </l>
            <l>Then would I sweare she could not chuse but loue me: </l>
            <l>Let her sweare nere so much, still haue I sworne, </l>
            <l>Till she had said, I should not be forsworne. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e101380">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>I marry brothers, here was cunning loue, </l>
            <l>Learne like good schollers, heele make you wise in loue: </l>
            <l>He was a man in loue, were you such men, </l>
            <l>Then were you men indeed, but boyes till then. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e101430">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>To please my Father, ile inquest of beauty, </l>
            <l>And neuer make returne till I haue found, </l>
            <l>A loue so faire, so rich, so honorable, </l>
            <l>As fits the honor of Octauioes sonnes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e101480">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>The like (you pleasd) vowes young Hippolito. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e101500">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Doe boyes, and I will teach you how to chuse them. </l>
            <l>Elect not mongst whole troupes of Courtly dames, </l>
            <l>For amongst many, some must needs be ill: </l>
            <l>The seld seene Phoenix euer sits alone, </l>
            <l>Ioue courted Danae when she was alone: </l>
            <l>Alone my boyes, that is the onely way, </l>
            <l>Ladies yeeld that alone, they els say nay. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e101580">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>An expert souldier; how shall they choose them Father? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e101600">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>If her bright eye dim not the Diamond, </l>
            <l>Say it is bright, but brighter iems delight you, </l>
            <l>Jf that her breath do not perfume the ayre; </l>
            <l>Say it is sweet, but sweeter sweets content you. </l>
            <l>Jf that her cheeke compared to the Lilly, </l>
            <l>Make not the Lilly black with whiter whitenesse; </l>
            <l>Say it is Lilly white, but black to white, </l>
            <l>When your choise white must haue such high exceeds. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e101690">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Father you do exceed things possible, </l>
            <l>Faith say how many Ladyes haue you seene, </l>
            <l>Much fayrer then my selfe, in all your trauayle? </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-006-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e101730">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Should the Crow teach me, then no Lady fayrer, </l>
            <l>If iudgement tell me, then a many fayrer: </l>
            <l>Thou art myne owne, J must thinke well of thee, </l>
            <l>Yet Florimella many doe excell thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e101780">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Should the Crow teache, I am not all Crowblacke. </l>
            <l>Though iudgement; J not all perfection black, </l>
            <l>Though you haue seene Ladyes that dim the day, </l>
            <l>Yet will J thinke my selfe as fayre as they. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e101830">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Doe Florimella, and ile one day get, </l>
            <l>A husband for thee that shall thinke thee fayre. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e101860">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>And tyme ifaith, that prety sport would be, </l>
            <l>Wiue it for them, you shall not husband me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e101890">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Yet you will take my counsell in your choise. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e101910">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Yes, if I had not yeares ynough to choose, </l>
            <l>Would you direct me as you doe your sonnes? </l>
            <l>With daughter take a man with such a nose, </l>
            <l>With such an eye, with such a colour beard, </l>
            <l>Thus big, thus tall, with all his teeth afore; </l>
            <l>Thus lipt, thus legd, thus handsome, thus apparrelld, </l>
            <l>Were not this pittifull! o pittifull: </l>
            <l>Now by the soule of soule-commanding loue, </l>
            <l>I will not stoope to such obedience, </l>
            <l>I must be bid to blush when I am kist, </l>
            <l>Bid my loue welcome, and I thanke you sir, </l>
            <l>With no indeed, I know not what loue is, </l>
            <l>I neuer heard so much of loue before, </l>
            <l>I pray take heede, nay fie you goe too far, </l>
            <l>With such a rabble of prescriptions, </l>
            <l>As neuer mayd of a Conceiuing spirit, </l>
            <l>Will follow them, yet brothers goe you on, </l>
            <l>Take you good counsell, Florimell will none. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e102100">Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e102110">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>I daughter? are you so experienced? </l>
            <l>An elder woman might haue spoken lesse, </l>
            <l>Yet by your leaue mynion, ile watch you so, </l>
            <l>Your I shall still be gouernd by my no. </l>
            <l>But come my sonnes take patterne of great Ioue, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000371-007-a"/>
            <l>Early ith' morning suit your selues for loue. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e102180">Exeunt. </stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e102190">Enter Anthonio Duke of Mantua, Hermia and Lucida his daughters, they with angels and he with a net. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e102200">
            <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
            <l>Go daughters with your Angels to the brooke, </l>
            <l>And see if any siluer-coated fish, </l>
            <l>Will nibble at your worme-emboweld hooks: </l>
            <l>Deceiue the watry subiects, yet the name </l>
            <l>Of foule deceit me thinks should fray them from you, </l>
            <l>Alack, alack, I cannot blame the world, </l>
            <l>That in the world there is so much deceipt; </l>
            <l>When this poore simple trade must vse deceipt. </l>
            <l>But with what conscience can J make this net, </l>
            <l>Within whose meshes all are caught that come: </l>
            <l>They cousen one at once, this cousens many, </l>
            <l>I will vndoo't it shall not cousen any. </l>
            <l>But daughters go practise that little sinne, </l>
            <l>Ile mend this great fault ere the fault begin. </l>
            <l>O cousening fortune how hast thou deceiu'd me, </l>
            <l>Turning me out a doores to banishment, </l>
            <l>And made another Lord of Mantua. </l>
            <l>I that was Lord now slaue to misery. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e102390">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Take comfort yet deare father. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e102410">
            <speaker>Ant </speaker>
            <l>Comfort? no: </l>
            <l>My brest's turnd prison, my proude iaylor woe, </l>
            <l>Locks out all comfort: whers your valiant brother? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e102450">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>All discontent like to a wounded lyon </l>
            <l>He forrages the woods, daring proude fortune </l>
            <l>At her best weapon, he accounts this smart, </l>
            <l>As a slight hurt, but far off from the hart. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e102500">
            <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
            <l>How holds his humour? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-lucida" xml:id="ep000371-e102520">
            <speaker>Luc. </speaker>
            <l>The same fashion still: </l>
            <l>But somwhat sadder-colourd death may end </l>
            <l>But neuer change him, see our words haue raisd him. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e102560">Enter Aspero. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e102570">
            <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
            <p>Fitly applide for a walks like a ghost. Why how now sonne? </p>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-007-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e102590">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Peace. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e102610">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Brother. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e102630">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Good now peace, </l>
            <l>Wake me not as you loue me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-lucida" xml:id="ep000371-e102660">
            <speaker>Luc. </speaker>
            <l>What a sleepe? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e102680">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>I, in a most sweet sleepe, blisters o'your tongues for waking me. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e102700">
            <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
            <l>Thou forgettest thy selfe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e102720">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>J should not be a Courtier els, mee thought J was at a strange wedding? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e102740">
            <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
            <l>Prithee what wedding? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e102760">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Of a young Lawyer and old Madam Conscience. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e102780">
            <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
            <l>I scarce beleeue that. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e102800">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Nor J neither, because it was a dreame, but mee thought the yong man doted on the old woman exceedingly. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e102820">
            <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
            <l>That was miraculous! did they liue together? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e102840">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>In the country they did, and agreed passing well, all the long vacation, and but for two things he would haue carried her vp to the terme with him. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e102860">
            <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
            <l>What things were those? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e102880">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>One was, because her gowne was of the old fashion, the other was cause he would not haue her by when he tooke fees. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e102900">
            <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
            <l>His reason for that? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e102920">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>For feare if a bribe had bin offered, she being by he shold haue had the bad conscience to take it. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e102940">
            <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
            <l>His wife and he liued together. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e102960">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Conscience and the Lawyer, as louingly as men and their wiues do, one flesh but neither medle nor make one with another </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e102980">
            <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
            <l>Man and wife part, thats strange! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e103000">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>O lord sit, profit can part the soule and the body, and why not man and wife, now you haue had my dreame father, let me vnderstand yours. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e103020">
            <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
            <l>How can he dreame, that neuer sleeps my sonne? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e103040">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>O best of all: why, your whole world doth nothing but dreame, your machiauell he dreames of state, deposing kings, grounding new monarchies: the louer hee dreames of kisses, amorous embraces: the newe-married wife dreames, <pb xml:id="ep000371-008-a"/>that rid of her young husband she hugs her old loue, and likes her dreame well ynough too: the Country gentle woman dreams that when her first husband's dead, she marries a knight, and the name of Lady sticks so in her mind, that shees neuer at hearts-ease till she get her husband dub'd; the Captaine, he dreames of oppressing the souldiers, deuising stratagens, to keep his dreame, and that dreame wakes in the pate of Octauio your Arch-enemy, who is not content to hurle vs into the whirlepoole of banishment, but binds waights at our heeles leaden pouerty, to sinke vs to the very depth that we should neuer rise againe. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e103060">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Then since all dreame, let vs dreame of reuenge. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e103080">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>I marry sister, that were a dreame worth dreaming, and ile sleepe out my braines but ile compasse it. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e103100">
            <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
            <l>Pretty content; we kill our foes in dreames. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e103120">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Vds foot, ile doe it waking then. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e103140">
            <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
            <l>Aspero. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e103160">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>At Counsell table. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e103180">
            <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
            <l>Heare me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e103200">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>In his Dutches armes, twere base to go disguisd, </l>
            <l>No, my reuenge shall weare an open brow; </l>
            <l>J will not play the coward, kill him first </l>
            <l>And send my challenge after; ile make knowne </l>
            <l>My name, and cause of comming, if I thought </l>
            <l>Griefe like a painter had so spoyl'd my visage </l>
            <l>He could not know me, on my breast ide write </l>
            <l>How ere I am disfigured through woe, </l>
            <l>J am the thing was made for Aspero. </l>
            <l>Speake not, I am as constant as the Center, </l>
            <l>Some fortune good or bad doth beckon me, </l>
            <l>And I will run, bitter reuenge tasts sweete, </l>
            <l>Jf here on earth farewell, in heauen weele meete. </l>
            <l>Attendance sirra, your low Commedie, </l>
            <l>Craues but few Actors, weele breake company. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e103360">
            <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
            <l>As many blessings as the sea hath sands </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e103380">Exit cum Puero </stage>
            <l>Attend thee in thine honorable iourney: </l>
            <l>Come pretty maides we haue not wrought to day, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000371-008-b"/>
            <l>Or fish, or fast, our neede must needs obey. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e103420">Exeunt. </stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e103430">Enter Hippolito, Francisco, Florimell, and Page meeting them. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e103440">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Now sirra what haue you been about? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e103460">
            <speaker>Page. </speaker>
            <l>About my liuing sit. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e103480">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Whats that? feeding? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e103500">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <l>No sir, looking into the vnderofficers about the Court. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e103520">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Canst get any liuing out of them? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e103540">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>I sir, my betters get good liuings out of officers, and why not I? but to be plaine, I haue bin seeking your good Lordship. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e103560">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <p>But your boyship hath so sought vs, that wee haue found you. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e103580">
            <speaker>Page. </speaker>
            <l>Will you sell your findings my Lord? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e103600">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>They are scarce worth giuing. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e103620">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Yes, a boxe to keepe them in, for feare you loose them againe. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e103640">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>And I were a man as I am no woman, id'e pepper your box for that ieast. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e103660">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>You ieast. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e103680">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <l>In earnest law I would Madam. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e103700">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Well sir, no more, here comes our royall Father. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e103720">Enter Octauio, Hortensio, Flamineo, &amp;c. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e103730">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>How now my boyes? prouided for your iourney? </l>
            <l>Beauty conduct you: what, attyrd like shepheards? </l>
            <l>I thought t'haue seene you mounted on your steeds, </l>
            <l>Whose fiery stomackes from their nostrills breath </l>
            <l>The smoke of courage, and whose wanton mouthes </l>
            <l>Do proudely play vpon their yron bits: </l>
            <l>And you in stead of these poore weeds in robes, </l>
            <l>Richer then that which Ariadne wroughte, </l>
            <l>Or Cytharaes aery-mouing vestment. </l>
            <l>Thus should you seeme like louers suited thus, </l>
            <l>y'oude draw faire Ladies harts into their eies, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000371-009-a"/>
            <l>And strike the world dead with astonishment. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e103860">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Father such cost doth passe your sons reuenues </l>
            <l>We take example from immortall Ioue, </l>
            <l>Who like a shepheard would repaire to loue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e103900">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>And gentle loue conduct you both my sonnes, </l>
            <l>Daughter go bring them onward in their way, </l>
            <l>Were not we cald back by important busines, </l>
            <l>We would not leaue you thus: Hortensio </l>
            <l>Is my disguise prepard, for J vnknowne </l>
            <l>Will see how they behaue themselues in loue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e103970">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <l>Tis done my Lord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e103990">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Once more my boyes adieu: </l>
            <l>He sends you forth that meanes to follow you. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e104020">Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e104030">
            <speaker>Flo, </speaker>
            <l>Now brothers you must amongst these wenches, </l>
            <l>Faith for a wager which shall get the fairest? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e104060">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Ile gage a 100. crownes mine proues the fairest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e104080">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>A match, ile venter twice so much of mine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e104100">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>And ile lay gainst you both, that both your loues Get them when you can where you can, or how you can, shall not be able to compare with me in beauty. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e104120">
            <speaker>Fran. </speaker>
            <l>That wager ile take for tis surely won. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e104140">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Las thou art but a star to beauties sun. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e104160">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Star me no stars, go you and stare for loue, </l>
            <l>Ile stay at home, and with my homely beauty </l>
            <l>Purchase a loue, shall thinke my looks as faire, </l>
            <l>As those faire loues that you shall fetch so far; </l>
            <l>But take your course, fate send you both faire lucke. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e104220">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>How if't be fowle? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e104240">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Nay ift be forked, you must beare it off with head and shoulders. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e104260">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Oh stale, that ieast runs oth' lees. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e104280">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>You must consider tis drawne out of the bottome of my witte. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e104300">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>O shallow wit, at the bottome so soone. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e104320">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Deepe ynough to lay you in the mire. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-009-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e104340">
            <speaker>Page. </speaker>
            <l>Or els tis shallow indeede, for they are foundred already, </l>
            <l>but I must play dun, and draw them all out o'th mire, </l>
            <l>Whats a clock my Lord? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e104380">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Which of them dost aske? thou seest they are two. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e104400">
            <speaker>Pag. </speaker>
            <l>What two are they Madam? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e104420">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Why two fooles. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e104440">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <p>Is it not past two, doth it not come somewhat neere three sister: </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e104460">
            <speaker>Page. </speaker>
            <p>Shew perryall and tak't, but come my Lord you haue stood fooling long ynough, will you about your busines in good earnest? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e104480">
            <speaker>Fra. </speaker>
            <l>Indeed we will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e104500">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>And they are deeds you must trust too, for women will respect your words but slitely without deeds. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e104520">
            <speaker>Page. </speaker>
            <p>Why, are women called Angells but because they delight in good deeds, and loue heauen, but that it will not be won without them. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e104540">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>They shall haue deeds. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e104560">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Brother, and good deeds too: </l>
            <l>They are tongues that men must speake with when they woo. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e104590">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>That tongue weel practise, sister to loue we leaue you. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e104610">Exeunt brothers. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e104620">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Louers take heed least cunning loue deceiue you. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e104640">Exit with Page. </stage>
          </sp>
          <trailer>Finis actus primi. </trailer>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="ep000371-e104660">
          <head>ACTVS SECVNDVS. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e104670">Enter Octauio disguised, Hortensio Flamineo. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e104680">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>NO more; thus suted ile attend my sonnes, </l>
            <l>Impute it not to any ruffian vaine, </l>
            <l>But to a fathers wakefull prouidence, </l>
            <l>Louers like bees are priuiledgd to tast, </l>
            <l>All buds of beauty: should they chance to light </l>
            <l>Vpon some worthles weed ile hinder it: </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000371-010-a"/>
            <l>The eies of youth will now and then dwell there, </l>
            <l>Whereas they should not glance, this doubt I feare. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-flamineo" xml:id="ep000371-e104770">
            <speaker>Fla. </speaker>
            <l>And well aduisd my liege should they incline </l>
            <l>To loue not fitting their estates and births, </l>
            <l>You with your present counsell may preuent them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e104810">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Thats my intent, and further in my absence </l>
            <l>I leaue my land and daughter to thy charge, </l>
            <l>The girle is wanton, if she gad abroad </l>
            <l>Restraine her, bound her in hir chamber dore; </l>
            <l>My word's thy warrant, let her know so much: </l>
            <l>Farewell, at home I leaue my feare with thee </l>
            <l>And follow doubt abroad. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e104890">
            <speaker>Hor. </speaker>
            <l>Ile carefull be. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e104910">Exeunt. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e104920">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>Now to my busines, I haue a strange habit, and I must cut out an humour sutable to it, and humours are pickt so neere the bone, a man can scarce get humour ynough to giue a flea his breakfast, but I am a stale ruffian, my habit is braue, and so shall my humor be, and here comes one to giue me earnest of it. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e104940">Enter Aspero and his boy. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e104950">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Send him a letter that I come to kill him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e104970">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <l>Twere great valor but little pollicy my Lord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e104990">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>How long haue you bin a matchiauilian boy? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e105010">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <l>Euer since I practisd to play the knaue my Lord, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e105030">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Then policy and knauery are somewhat a kin. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e105050">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>As neere, as penury and gentry, a degree and half remou'de no more. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e105070">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>How came in the kindred twixt gentry and penury? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e105090">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Shall I tell you sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e105110">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>First tell me what thou art? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e105130">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>Lyme and haire: playster of Paris, kneaded together with rye dowe and goats milke, I am of a hot constitution, wonnot freeze. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e105150">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Thy profession. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e105170">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>A foole or a knaue choose you which. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e105190">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <l>Then thou art fit for any gentlemans company. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-010-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e105210">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>True boye, for your sweete foole and your fine knaue are like a paire of vpright shooes, that gentlemen weare so long now of one foote, then of another, till they leaue them neuer a good soale. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e105230">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>That makes your foole &amp; your knaue haue such bad soales; but what dost thou seeke? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e105250">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Mine owne vndoing sir, seruice. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e105270">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Indeed seruice is like the common law, it vndoes any one that followes it long, canst describe seruice? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e105290">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>Yes, tis a vacant place, fild vp with a compleate knaue, a miserable pandar, or an absolute beggar. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e105310">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>your opinion boy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e105330">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <l>I say a seruingman is an Antecedent. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e105350">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Because he sits before a Cloakebag. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e105370">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>He is likewise a nominatiue Case, and goes before his mistrisse. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e105390">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>Thats when the verbe he goes before his mistrisse and he can agree togither. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e105410">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <l>If not, he turnes Accusative and followes his master. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e105430">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Woot follow me fellow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e105450">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>To a tauerne, and thou woot pay for my ordenary. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e105470">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>My businesse is more serious, thou dost not know me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e105490">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Nor my selfe neither so long as I haue maintenance. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e105510">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Didst neuer heare of the wars betwixt Venice and Mantua. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e105530">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>I cut some few of the Mantuans throates. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e105550">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>And wert not a knaue for't. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e105570">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>No, J was a Venetian commander, a great man: the reason of this question. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e105590">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Dost know the Duke of Venice? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e105610">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>I am his right hand. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e105630">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Woot do me a message to him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e105650">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>What is't? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e105670">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Tell him J hate him, my name's Aspero, has banisht my father, vsurps his Dukedome, and I come to be reuengd. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e105690">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Anthonioes sonne? vesfoot hast any gold. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-011-a"/>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e105710">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Thy reason. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e105730">
            <speaker>Oct </speaker>
            <p>Shalt be reuengd, giue me money, ile be thy snaile &amp; score out a siluer path to his confusion. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e105750">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>No, my reuenge shall be like my fathers wrongs in Aperto lend me any honest aide. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e105770">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>Pax of honesty, it goes a begging vpon crutches, and can get reliefe out of few but schollers, I shall not kill him? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e105790">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Ide be thy death first. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e105810">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Yet you say you hate him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e105830">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Equall with my shame. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e105850">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Make him chew a bullet then. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e105870">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>No, though my state with pouerty be tainted, </l>
            <l>Mine acts and honor shall liue still acquainted. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e105900">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>True moulded honor I admire the temper </l>
            <l>Of thy mild patience, that not all the wrongs </l>
            <l>J layd vpon thee can enforce thy spleene </l>
            <l>To fowle requitall, had thy comming tane </l>
            <l>Any base leuell, it had cost thy life, </l>
            <l>But beeing free and full of honour liue, </l>
            <l>Thy vertues teach me honor freely goe, </l>
            <l>A secret friends worse then an open for: </l>
            <l>You are too honest for my attendance, farewell sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e106000">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>And thou too knauish for my employment. </l>
            <l>But here comes more company. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e106030">Enter Florimell and Page. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e106040">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Boy, let your attendance waite further of, </l>
            <l>Vnder this shade J meane to take a sleepe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e106070">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <l>And may you madam like a souldier sleepe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e106090">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>How boy in alarums. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e106110">
            <speaker>Pag. </speaker>
            <p>No Ladye but in armes, and you had neede of them too, for see the enemy comes downe, shall I sound a parlee? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e106130">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Peace wag. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e106150">
            <speaker>Pa </speaker>
            <l>Peace, O coward, offer peace and but two to two of them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e106170">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Boy dost know what gentleman it is? </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-011-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e106190">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <l>Gentle madam no, but he is a man. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e106210">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Beleeue me boy he is a proper man. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e106230">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>Man is a proper name to a man, and so he may be a proper man. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e106250">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>I loue him hees a very proper man. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e106270">
            <speaker>Pa, </speaker>
            <p>She loues him for his properties, and indeede many women loue men only to make properties of them. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e106290">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Pray gentleman if no more, tell mee where you were born. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e106310">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Faire virgine if so much, no where some where any where, where you would haue me. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e106330">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Faith I would haue it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e106350">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Marry and you shall haue it Ladie. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e106370">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>What shall J haue sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e106390">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Why a kisse. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e106410">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Nothing els: we Courtiers count them trifles, not woorth taking. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e106430">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Why then bestow one of mee ile take it most thankfully. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e106450">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>I wil not stand with you for a trifle, sir pray where were you borne? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e106470">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>In Italy, but neuer yet in Venice. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e106490">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>You may in Venice, gentle sir adieu. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e106510">Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e106520">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Gentle Lady thrice as much to you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e106540">
            <speaker>Pa </speaker>
            <l>Farewell sweet heart. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e106560">Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e106570">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <l>God a mercy bagpudding. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e106590">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>You may in Venice gentle sir adieu? this begets wonder. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e106610">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <l>Yare not wise then, what do you take her for? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e106630">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Some great woman. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e106650">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>Some woman great with child, be ruld, shees a pynk board her. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e106670">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>But how? the meanes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e106690">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>Make but a shotte of flattery at hir broad side, and sheele strike saile presently. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e106710">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Flattery? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e106730">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>I flattery, women are like fidlers, speake them faire theile play of any instrument. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e106750">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>I, that they can play of, </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-012-a"/>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e106770">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <l>Shees a botcher cannot play a little of all. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e106790">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>And to common that wil play too much of any, but come ile vse meanes to get her. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e106810">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <l>Nay you must first haue meanes to giue her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e106830">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Why in the course of schollership, the genitiue Case goes before the Datiue. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e106850">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>The Grammarians are fooles that plac'de them so; for in Rerum Natura, the Datiue goes before the genetiue, you must alwayes giue before you can get, louers are fooles, and fooles must be liberall. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e106870">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Will not women respect a man for his good parts? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e106890">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>yes, some few; but all for his good guiftes, a gentleman with his good guifts sit at the vpper end of the table on a chayre and a cushion, when a scholler with his good partes will be gladde of a ioynd stoole in the Lobby with the Chambermaids. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e106910">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>I will haue good guifts &amp; shew my selfe liberall to, though I beg for't. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e106930">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>I thinke that will be the end, for penury has tane a leafe of your pocket to keep Court in this Christmasse. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e106950">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Well, how so ere, shee's faire and courteous, </l>
            <l>And courteous faire, is a faire guift in Ladies: </l>
            <l>She may bee well discended, if shee be, </l>
            <l>Shee's fit for loue, and why not then for me. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e107000">Exeunt. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e107010">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>And you be not fitted in Venice tis straunge, for tis counted the best flesh shambles in Italie: but heer's no notable coward, that hauing suffered wrong by a man, seeks to right himselfe of a woman. </p>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e107030">Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e107040">Enter Hippolito Francisco like shepheards, Octauio in disguise. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e107050">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>Looke you sir, I am like an irish beggar, and an English bur, will sticke close where I finde a good nap, I must and will dwell with you. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e107070">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>What canst do: </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e107090">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>Still Aquauitæ, stampe Crabs, and make mustard, I can do as much as all the men you keepe. </p>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-012-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e107110">
            <speaker>Fra. </speaker>
            <l>Prithee what? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e107130">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>Why vndo you, and twenty could do no more, but busines, come my wits grow rusty for imployment. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e107150">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Canst keepe counsell? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e107170">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>My mother was a midwife. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e107190">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Hast any skill in Loue? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e107210">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>I am one of Cupids agents, haue Ouids ars amandi ad vngues, know causam and can apply remedium, and minister effectum to a haire, but why do you aske? haue you trauerst an action in loues spirituall court? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e107230">
            <speaker>Fra. </speaker>
            <l>Not to dissemble, we haue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e107250">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>And without dissembling youle neuer come out of it, but tell me true, are you in loue already? or have you the desire to bee in loue </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e107270">
            <speaker>Fra. </speaker>
            <l>Indeed I am in loue to be in loue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e107290">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>And I desire to liue in fond desire, </l>
            <l>And yet I doubt to touch blind fancies fier. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e107320">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Tis good to doubt, but tis not good to feare, </l>
            <l>Yet still to doubt, will at the lest proue feare; </l>
            <l>Doubt loue, tis good, but tis not good to feare it, </l>
            <l>Loue hurts them most, that least of all come neere it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e107370">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Then to doubt loue is the next way to loue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e107390">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Doubtles it is if you misdoubt not loue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e107410">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Doubt and misdoubt? what difference is there here? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e107430">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Yes, much: when men misdoubt, tis sayd they feare. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e107450">
            <speaker>Fra. </speaker>
            <l>But is it good in loue to be in doubt? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e107470">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>No not in loue, doubt then is iealousie: </l>
            <l>Tis good to doubt before you be in loue, </l>
            <l>Doubt counsells, how to shun loues misery. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e107510">
            <speaker>Fra. </speaker>
            <l>Your doubtfull counsell counsells vs to loue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e107530">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>To equall loue, I like experience speake. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e107550">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Experiencd louer, you haue spoken well. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e107570">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Experience wanting louers, truth I tell, </l>
            <l>Yong wits be wife, in loue liue constant still, </l>
            <l>You need nor doubt good hap not misdoubt ill. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e107610">Enter Lucida and Hermonia with Angles. </stage>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-013-a"/>
          <p>And see your discourse has coniurd vp beauty in the likenesse of two countrimaides, but you shall not come in the circles of their armes if J can keepe you out. </p>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e107630">
            <speaker>Fra. </speaker>
            <l>These are too meane for loue, brother lets leaue them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e107650">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>What? speechles? will you make dumbe virgins of them? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e107670">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Oh we are sonnes of a great father. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e107690">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>So is the sun of heauen, yet hee smiles on the bramble aswell as the Lilly, kisses the checke of a beggar as louingly as a gentlewoman, and tis good to imitate, him tis good. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e107710">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Say sister, had we not fine sport to day? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-lucida" xml:id="ep000371-e107730">
            <speaker>Luc. </speaker>
            <l>We had, if death may be accounted play. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e107750">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Why tis accounted pleasure to kill fish. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-lucida" xml:id="ep000371-e107770">
            <speaker>Luc. </speaker>
            <l>A pleasure nothing pleasant to the fish. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e107790">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Yet fishes were created to be kild. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-lucida" xml:id="ep000371-e107810">
            <speaker>Luc. </speaker>
            <l>Cruell creation then to haue liues spild. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e107830">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Their bodies being food, maintaine our breath. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-lucida" xml:id="ep000371-e107850">
            <speaker>Luc. </speaker>
            <l>What bodies then haue we to liue by death? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e107870">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Come, come, you vainely argue, it is good. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-lucida" xml:id="ep000371-e107890">
            <speaker>Luc. </speaker>
            <l>What is it good to kill? oh god oh god? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e107910">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>If it be sin, then you your self's a sinner. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-lucida" xml:id="ep000371-e107930">
            <speaker>Luc. </speaker>
            <l>I thank proud fortune fort, my woes beginner. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e107950">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>Foot are yee not ashamd to stand by like idle ciphers, &amp; such places of account voyde? and they had bin rich offices and you poore Courtiers, you would haue bin in them in halfe the time. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e107970">
            <speaker>Fra. </speaker>
            <l>Though against stomack.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e107990">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Nothing against stomack and you loue me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e108010">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Faire maids if so you be you are well met. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e108030">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Shepheards or be what els you are well met. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e108050">
            <speaker>Fra. </speaker>
            <l>Tis well, if that well met we be to you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-lucida" xml:id="ep000371-e108070">
            <speaker>Luc. </speaker>
            <l>If not to vs you are vnto your selues. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e108090">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>We did not meet, you saw vs come togither. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e108110">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>What ere we saw, you yet ere you came hither. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e108130">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>We did, we met in kindred, we are brothers. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-lucida" xml:id="ep000371-e108150">
            <speaker>Luc. </speaker>
            <l>So shepheards we did meet for we are sisters. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e108170">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Then sisters, let vs brothers husbands be. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-013-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e108190">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>So brothers without our leaues you well may be. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e108210">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Say we desire to husband it with you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-lucida" xml:id="ep000371-e108230">
            <speaker>Luc. </speaker>
            <l>Know we desire no husbands such as you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e108250">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>A shepheard is an honest trade of life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e108270">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Yet honest shepheard has with honest trade some strife. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e108290">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>He seldome sweares but by his honesty. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e108310">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>So honest men do too aswell as he. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e108330">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>But will you trust a shepheard when he vowes, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-lucida" xml:id="ep000371-e108350">
            <speaker>Luc. </speaker>
            <l>No neuer, if his oath be that he loues. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e108370">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Yet if I sweare, that needs must be mine oath, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e108390">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Sweare not, for we are misbeleeuers both. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e108410">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Let vs perswade you to beleeue we loue you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-lucida" xml:id="ep000371-e108430">
            <speaker>Luc. </speaker>
            <l>First we intreat you giue vs time to proue you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e108450">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Take time, meane time weele praise yee to our powers. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e108470">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Oh time, sometime shepheards haue idle howers. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e108490">
            <speaker>Fra. </speaker>
            <l>Ile say thy cheek no naturall beauty lacks, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-lucida" xml:id="ep000371-e108510">
            <speaker>Luc. </speaker>
            <l>Good, if it had bin spoke behind our backs. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e108530">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Ile say this is the heauen of heauenly graces. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e108550">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>O heauen, how they can flatters to our faces. Exeunt. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e108570">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Brother the last is fayrest in my eie. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e108590">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>I but the first brother is first in beauty. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e108610">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>First in your choice, but not in beauty sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e108630">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>Come yee so neere as choice: then tis time for mee to stop for feare the musick run too far out of tune, how now gallants? in dumps. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e108650">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>No, but in loue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e108670">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Thats a dumpe, loues nothing but an Jtalian dumpe or a </l>
            <l>French brawle. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e108700">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Me thinkes tis sweeter musicke. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e108720">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>And twere in tune I confesse it, but you take your parts too low, you are trebble Courtiers, and will neuer agree with these Country Mynnikins, the musickes too base, neuer meddle in't. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e108740">
            <speaker>Fra. </speaker>
            <l>Peace doatard, peace, thy sight of loue is done, </l>
            <l>Thou canst not see the glory of loues sunne. </l>
            <l>Spent age with frosty clowds thy sight doth dim, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000371-014-a"/>
            <l>That thou art blind to see and apt to sin. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e108790">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Is it accounted sin to speake the truth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e108810">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>And worse, when age spits poyson against youth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e108830">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>They do not fit your callings, let them go. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e108850">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Yet they are faire: we loue, thou art loues foe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e108870">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>J am your friend, and wish you from this loue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e108890">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <p>Canst thou heaue hills? then thou my thoughts maist moue. but neuer els. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e108910">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Neuer! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e108930">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>No neuer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e108950">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Stay. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e108970">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>We are bound for loue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e108990">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Hate. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e109010">
            <speaker>Fra. </speaker>
            <l>Hinder not our way. <stage xml:id="ep000371-e109030">Exeunt brothers. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e109040">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>J boyes? will Eagles Eglets turne to bastards. </l>
            <l>Then must J change my vaine, and once more proue, </l>
            <l>To teach you how to hate as well as loue. <stage xml:id="ep000371-e109080">Exit. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <trailer>Finis actus Secundi. </trailer>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="ep000371-e109100">
          <head>ACTVS TERTIVS. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e109110">Enter Page and Florimell. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e109120">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>SWeet hony candy madam, if it be no forfeit to tell tales out of Cupids free schoole, tell what proficient your louer Aspero proues. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-unassigned" xml:id="ep000371-e109140">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Now so loue helpe me lot, a passing weake one and verye vnready. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e109160">
            <speaker>Pag. </speaker>
            <p>The better, for women would haue their louers vnreadye to choose. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e109180">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Now ready you are to play the knaue? but to Aspero </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e109200">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>I do not thinke but thers good musick in him, your tongue harps so much vpon his name. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e109220">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>J shall neuer forget him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e109240">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <l>I faith Lady then I know what J know. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e109260">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>What do you know I prey? </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-014-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e109280">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>Marry that if you neuer forget him, you shall euer remember him, was he neuer in your chamber. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimel" xml:id="ep000371-e109300">
            <speaker>Fio. </speaker>
            <p>Yes, but he shewed himselfe the strangest foole: And by my troth loe. J am sorry for't to, J had as good an appetite to maintaine discourse; but here a comes, if euer I choose a man by the fulnesse of his Calfe, or a cock by the crowing, looke and the bashfull foole do not blush already. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e109320">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <l>You may do well to kisse him, and make him bold Madam. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e109340">
            <speaker>Pa </speaker>
            <l>Boy, go know what strange gentleman that is. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e109360">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Slid what a strange Lady's this madam though I seeme a stranger to you, J lay with one last night that's well acquainted with you. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e109380">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Acquainted with me? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e109400">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>And knowes you, and loues you, and you loue him, &amp; haue bestowed kind fauours of him to. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e109420">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>I bestow fauors? what fauours? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e109440">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Though twere but a triffle he tooke it as kindly as some would haue done a kisse. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e109460">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Lord what a while this iest has bin a brooding? and it proues but addle too now it is hatched. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e109480">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Tis a pig of your owne sow madam, and I hope your wit will bestow the nursing of it. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e109500">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>So it had need, I thinke tis like to haue but a drie nurse of yours. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e109520">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>O drie ieast, all the wit in your head will scarce make sippits in't, what a ground? and such a faire landing place? get a shore, or be ranke amongst fooles for euer. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e109540">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>And faith ist not pitty such a proper man should keep company with a foole. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e109560">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>I keepe company with none but you Lady. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e109580">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>You keepe mine against my will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e109600">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>So do I the fooles I protest; but take away yours, ile soone shift away the fooles. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e109620">
            <speaker>Pag. </speaker>
            <p>I haue not seene a foole so handsomely shifted in Venice. </p>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-015-a"/>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e109640">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>But come, shall the foole and you bee friends? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e109660">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>The foole and J? y'are too familiar. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e109680">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Why, J hope a foole may be a Ladies familiar at all times. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e109700">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Come y'are too saucy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e109720">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Indeed tis a fooles part of Ioue to be in the sauce afore my </l>
            <l>Lady; otherwise I am neither foole nor saucy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e109750">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Not, proude sir? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e109770">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Not, coy Lady; come why should your tongue make so many false fiers that neuer come from your heart: you loue me, I know you loue me, your spirit, your looke, your countenance bewrayes it. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e109790">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>You ieast. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e109810">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Jn earnest you do, and you shall know't in earnest too, lend me this iewell. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e109830">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Iewell? away you sharking companion. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e109850">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>How? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e109870">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Wandring strauagant, that like a droane flies humming from one land to another. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e109890">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <l>Slight and thou hast any wit, now shew her thy sting. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e109910">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>And lightst vpon euery dayry maid and kitchen-wench. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e109930">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>And now and then on a Ladies lip as— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e109950">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>You did of mine you would say, and J am hart sory you can say it, and when by your buzzing flattery, you haue suckt the smallest fauour from them, you presently make wing for another. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e109970">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Marry buz. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e109990">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Double the zard and take the whole meaning for your labour. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e110010">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <l>The buzzards wit's not so bald yet I tro. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e110030">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>A word in your eare, madam the buzzard will anger you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e110050">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>With staying you do. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e110070">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>With going I shall. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e110090">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Away. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e110110">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>I away, neuer intreat, tis too late, if you send after me, I wil not come back, if you write to me, I will not answer, drowne your eyes in teares, I will not wipe them, breake your heart with <pb xml:id="ep000371-015-b"/>sighes, J will not pitty you: neuer looke, signes cannot moue me, if you speake, tis too late, if you intreate, tis bootles, if you hang vpon me, tis needlesse, I offred loue &amp; you scornd it, my absence will be your death, and I am proud ont' </p>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e110130">Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e110140">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Js he gon boy? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e110160">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <l>Yes faith Madam. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e110180">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Cleane out of sight? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e110200">
            <speaker>Pag. </speaker>
            <p>And out of mind to, or els you haue not the mind of a true woman. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e110220">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Thou readst a false comment boy, call him againe; yet doe not, my heart shall breake ere it bend. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e110240">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>Or els it holdes not the true temper of woman-hood, but faith tell me Madam, do you loue him? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e110260">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>As a Welchman doth toasted cheese, I cannot dine without him, hee's my pillow I cannot sleep quietly without him; my rest, I cannot liue without him. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e110280">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <l>O that he knew it Lady. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e110300">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>He does, he would neuer haue left me els, he does </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e110320">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>You calld him foole, but me thinks he prooues a physitian, has found the disease of your liuer, by the complexion of your lookes, but see he returnes. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e110340">Enter Aspero meditating. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e110350">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>And now me thinks J loath him more then I lou'd him; goe run for Hortensio my guardian, bid him come armd, thet's intent of treason tell him. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e110370">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>My Lady cannot choose but dance well, shees so full of prety changes. </p>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e110390">Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e110400">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>I wonder you dare come in my sight, considering the wrong you did me. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e110420">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>I came I confesse, but with no intent to see you J protest, and that shall be manifested by the shortnes of my stay. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e110440">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Tis too long and twere shorter then tis, will he not court me? not? nor speak to me neither? nay neuer ask pardon, tis to late, we shal ha'you come to my window one of these mornings with <pb xml:id="ep000371-016-a"/>musicke, but doe not, my patience is to much out of tune, out of my sight I hate thee, worse then I loath painting, I hate thee, out of my sight. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e110460">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Inough, will you be a quiet woman yet? will you, speake afore my resolue take strength? will you, do but say you are sorry I aske no mends but a kisse, kindly, come: shall I hat'e? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e110480">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Ile kisse a toad first. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e110500">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>You will, remember this another time, a toade you will: J know thou lou'st me, and J see the pride of thy humour; I doe, and thou shalt know I doe; halfe an hower hence wee shall haue you weeping on your knees, with O my Aspero would I had died when I reiected thee, but doe, weepe till J pitty thee; a tooad! ile make thee creepe on thy knees for a kisse. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e110520">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>you will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e110540">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Thy bare knees, J will, and goe without it to. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e110560">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Out humourd? O I would sell my part of immortality. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e110580">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>But to touch my hand, thou wouldst, I know thou woldst, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e110600">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>O how spleene swells mee? helpe Hortensio, creepe a my knees? Hortensio. </p>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e110620">Enter Hortensio with his man Assistance. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e110630">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>How fares my beautious charge? weeping Lady? the law shall fetch red water from his veynes that hath drawne bloud of your eies, is this the traytor? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e110650">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Traytor? in thy disloyall throte thou liest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e110670">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <l>O monstrous, a wishes you choakt my Lord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e110690">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <l>How! choakt? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e110710">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>I choakt? for a wishes the traytor in your throate, and hee's a very small traytor that is not able to choake a wiser man then your Lordship. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e110730">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <l>Downe with him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e110750">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <l>I, downe with him, if he stick in your throat, and spare not. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e110770">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Do not kill him, though hee deserues death yet doe not kill him, onely disweapon him; so. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e110790">
            <speaker>Hor. </speaker>
            <l>But madam. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e110810">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>I will not heare him, keepe him; but keepe him safe on your <pb xml:id="ep000371-016-b"/>liues, if he get away or miscarry in prison: as I am heire of Venice ile haue your heads for't. <stage xml:id="ep000371-e110830">they bind </stage>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e110840">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <l>I warne you madam, if yrons will hold him. <stage xml:id="ep000371-e110860">him. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e110870">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Fie, fie, with a cord? here, bind him with my scarfe, that wil hold, and yet stand away, Ile doo't my selfe, I cannot trust him with you, least you should let him sometime scape free: besides, you cannot vse him according to the quality of his offence, and because ile glory in his bondage my chamber shall bee his prison, let him haue neither light meat nor drinke, but what J prouide him my selfe. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e110890">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <l>Your will's a law, we obey it madam. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e110910">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>She knowes me sure; well, though my ioyes be thrall, </l>
            <l>My comforts this, a speedy death ends all. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e110940">Exit with Hort. and Ass. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e110950">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Oh you are not gone then. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e110970">
            <speaker>Page. </speaker>
            <p>Heer's a newe kinde of courting, neuer seene before J thinke. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e110990">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>He would anger me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e111010">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <l>Nay you take a course, to anger him first J thinke. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e111030">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Should J haue let him go, (as I could no other way detaine him in modesty) and he had set his loue on some other, t'would haue fretted my hart strings a sunder. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e111050">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <l>Why did you set him so light then? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e111070">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Not for any hate, but in pride of my humour. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e111090">
            <speaker>Page. </speaker>
            <p>Why did you commaund him close prisoner to your chamber. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e111110">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>That I may feede mine eie with the sight of him, and be sure no other beauty can rob me of his company: I will ha't all, I will not loose an ynch of him: And in this, I but imitate our Italian dames, who cause their friends to clap their iealous husbands in prison, that if they haue occasion to vse them within fortie weekes and a day, they may surely know where to find them. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e111130">Exit. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e111140">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>If I had any knauēry in mee, as J am all honesty, I could make a notable sceane of mirth betwixt these two Amorists. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e111160">Enter </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e111170">
            <pb xml:id="ep000371-017-a"/>Enter Antonio with a net. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e111180">
            <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
            <l>Early sorrow, art got vp so soone? </l>
            <l>What? ere the Sun ascendeth in the East? </l>
            <l>O what an early waker art thou growne? </l>
            <l>But cease discourse, and close vnto thy worke; </l>
            <l>Vnder this drooping mirtle will I sit, </l>
            <l>And worke a while vpon my corded net; </l>
            <l>And as I worke, record my sorrowes past, </l>
            <l>Asking old Time, how long my woes shall last: </l>
            <l>And first, but stay alas what do J see? </l>
            <l>Moist gum like teares, drop from this mournfull tree </l>
            <l>And see, it sticks like birdlyme; twill not part; </l>
            <l>Sorrow is euen such birdlyme at my hart. </l>
            <l>Alas poore tree, dost thou want company? </l>
            <l>Thou dost, I see't, and J will weepe with thee, </l>
            <l>Thy sorrowes make thee dumb, and so shall mine. </l>
            <l>It shall be tongueles, and so seeme like thine; </l>
            <l>Thus will I rest my head vnto thy barke, </l>
            <l>Whilst my sighes tell my sorrowes; harke tree, harke. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e111370">Enter Hippolito and Francisco. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e111380">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <p>Fie, fie, how heauy is light loue in me? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e111400">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <p>How slow runs swift desire? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e111420">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>This leaden ayre, </l>
            <l>This pondrous feather, merry Melancholy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e111450">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>This passion, which, but in passion </l>
            <l>Hath not his perfect shape. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e111480">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>And shapelesse loue </l>
            <l>Hath in his watch of loue oreslept himselfe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e111510">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Then sleepy wakers, let these graue lets wander </l>
            <l>And waite th'ascension of beauties wonder: </l>
            <l>But stay, a man striuing twixt life and death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e111550">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Nay then tis so, my heauenly loue's gone by, </l>
            <l>And struck him dead with her loue-darting eye. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e111580">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>If speech-bereauing loue will let thee speake, </l>
            <l>Then speechles man, speake with the tongue of loue, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000371-017-b"/>
            <l>And tell me, if thou saw'st not Cynthia </l>
            <l>Seeking Endimion in these flowry dales. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e111630">
            <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
            <l>Dales for Endimion and faire Cynthia fit, </l>
            <l>But neuer heauenly goddesse blest this groue, </l>
            <l>These woods are consecrate to griefe, not loue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e111670">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Out Atheist, thou prophan'st loues deity, </l>
            <l>For, false-reporter, I in them haue seene </l>
            <l>A loue that makes a Negro of Loues Queene: </l>
            <l>One that when as the sunne keeps holliday, </l>
            <l>Hir beauty clads him in his best array, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e111730">
            <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
            <l>Now truly shepheard none such soiourn here </l>
            <l>Please you suruey the Cell, go in and see, </l>
            <l>I'me hearst, and none but sorrowe lies with me. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e111770">Enter Lucida. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e111780">
            <speaker>Fra. </speaker>
            <p>Call you this sorrowes caue? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e111800">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Rather a Cell, <stage xml:id="ep000371-e111820">Enter Octauio &amp; whisper with Antonio. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Where pleasure growes, and none but Angels dwell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e111840">
            <speaker>Fra. </speaker>
            <l>To what compare shall I compare thee to? </l>
            <l>Vncomparable beauties Paragon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e111870">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>I will compare her beauty to the sunne, </l>
            <l>For her bright lustre giues the morning light. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e111900">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Ile say she is like Cynthia when day's done, </l>
            <l>Or Lady to the mistrisse of the night. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e111930">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <p>O speake but to me, and J shall be blest. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e111950">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <p>One smile would lay my iarring thoughts at rest. </p>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e111970">Enter Hermia. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e111980">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <p>How now faire sister? you are hard beset. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e112000">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <p>Nymph. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e112020">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <p>Goddesse. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e112040">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <p>Saynt, once more, y'are both well met. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e112060">
            <speaker>Fra. </speaker>
            <p>O she is faire. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e112080">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <p>She fairer. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e112100">
            <speaker>Fra. </speaker>
            <l>Both more faire </l>
            <l>Then rocks of pearle, or the chast euening ayre. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e112130">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <p>Say sweet, intend you not to fish to day? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e112150">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <p>No, shepheards, now fish do not bite but play. </p>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-018-a"/>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e112170">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <p>What time, sweet loue, keepe fishes when they bite? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-lucida" xml:id="ep000371-e112190">
            <speaker>Luc. </speaker>
            <p>Early ith' morning, or els late at night. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e112210">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <p>Come, will you talke with me till time of fishing? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e112230">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <p>My father, sir, will chide if I be missing. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e112250">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>The match is made, th'are euen vpon going. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e112270">
            <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
            <p>What should we do? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e112290">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>Why as poore parents and dutifull seruants should doe, run amongst the bushes and catch flies. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e112310">
            <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
            <p>Stay forward daughters whether are yee going. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e112330">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <p>Father, I thinke these shepheards come a wooing. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e112350">
            <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
            <l>A wooing daughters? nere imagine so: </l>
            <l>What man's so mad to marry griefe and woe? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e112380">
            <speaker>Fra. </speaker>
            <p>Why where liues sad griefe? heer's all speaking ioy. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e112400">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <p>O I would liue and die with such annoy. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e112420">
            <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
            <p>But they are poore, and pouerty is despisde: </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e112440">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <p>No, they are faire, beauty is highly prizde. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e112460">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>Twill be a match, they are beating the price already. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e112480">
            <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
            <l>They once were faire, sorrow from that hath changd them </l>
            <l>They once knew wealth, but chance hath much estrangd them, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e112510">
            <speaker>Fra. </speaker>
            <l>Haue they bin faire? what fayrer then they are? </l>
            <l>Why tis not possible, this heauenly faire </l>
            <l>Hath only in it selfe beauties exceed, </l>
            <l>O then rich, fayre, and onely selues exceed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e112560">
            <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
            <l>Come daughters, and come shepheards, if you please, </l>
            <l>Ile leade you to the lodge of little ease, </l>
            <l>Where I will feast you with what cheere I may, </l>
            <l>Griefe shall turne mirth, and keepe high holliday. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e112610">Exit cumfiliabw. </stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e112620">The brothers going out Octauio staies them. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e112630">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>A word with you, you meane to marry these wenches, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-ambo" xml:id="ep000371-e112650">
            <speaker>Ambo. </speaker>
            <p>We doe. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e112670">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>And are going to contract your selues. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-ambo" xml:id="ep000371-e112690">
            <speaker>Ambo. </speaker>
            <p>We are. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e112710">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <p>And what say you to this? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e112730">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>God speede you: I would haue you marry on saint Lukes day. </p>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-018-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e112750">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <p>Why? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e112770">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>Because J would offer at your wedding. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e112790">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Come, th'art all enuy, feed vpon thy hate, </l>
            <l>This day our quest of loue shall terminate. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e112820">Exeunt manet Octauio, </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e112830">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Not if I liue, this maladie of loue, </l>
            <l>Js grown so strong, it will not be driuen out. </l>
            <l>To see the folly of a doating father; </l>
            <l>What toyle I had to fashion them to loue, </l>
            <l>And how tis doubled to misfashion them. </l>
            <l>They shall not wed, yet how shall J preuent it? </l>
            <l>Fearing th'euent I haue forethought a meanes, </l>
            <l>And here it lies, swaggering becomes not age, </l>
            <l>Now like the Fox, ile goe a pilgrimage. </l>
            <l>Frollick my boyes, I come to mar your sport, </l>
            <l>Your Country musicke must not play at Court. </l>
            <l>But first, ile write back to Hortensio </l>
            <l>For apprehension of yong Aspero: </l>
            <l>They haue not yet dynde, ile bid my selfe their guest </l>
            <l>Religion beg? a fashion in request. <stage xml:id="ep000371-e112990">Exit. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e113000">Enter Aspero and his boy. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e113010">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Art sure she hates me boy. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e113030">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>More then hir death, J haue bin in hir bosome sir, and this day she intends your execution. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e113050">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>My execution! the reason of hir hate? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e113070">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>Hir humour, nothing but a kind of strange crosse humor in that you reiected hir loue. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e113090">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Thats not capitall. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e113110">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>Not to crosse a great ones humour? no treason more: great personages humours are puritanes, thei'l as liue indure the diuel as soone as a crosse, and can away with him better. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e113130">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>I will submit, aske pardon on my knee. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e113150">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>Is your proud humour come down ifaith, your high humor that would not stoop an ynch of the knees; Ile help't vp againe, and't be but to vphold the ieast; I must bring her as low ere I haue done; O base, J woulde rather lay my necke vnder the Axe of her hate, then my sporte vnder the feete of <pb xml:id="ep000371-019-a"/>hir humor; but be counselld, ile teach you to preuent both, &amp; perchance make her vpstart humor stoope gallant too. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e113170">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Ile hold thee my best iewell and thou dost. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e113190">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>And pawne me as poore Lords do their iewells too, will you not? receiue me; you shall counterfet your selfe dead. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e113210">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>The life of that ieast. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e113230">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>It may be she dissembles all this while, loues you, and puts on this shew of hate of purpose to humble you: she may, and I beleeue— </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e113250">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>What? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e113270">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>That most intelligencers are knaues, and some women dissemblers; being thought dead (as let me alone to buz that into the credulous eare of the Court) if she haue any sparkes of loue, theil kindle and flame bright through the cinders of her hart. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e113290">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>If not, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e113310">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>If not, twill be a meanes for your escape: ile say you requested at your death to be buried at your natiue Citty: and what Courtier, if a Christian can deny that? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e113330">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>I am all thine, my humor's thy patient. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e113350">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>And if I do not kill it, I am not worthy to be your physitian. </p>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e113370">Exeunt. </stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e113380">Enter Florimell and hir Page. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e113390">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>I mary Lady; why now you credit your sex: a womans honor or humour should be like a ship vnder sayle, split her keele ere she vaile. <stage xml:id="ep000371-e113410">Enter Boy. </stage>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e113420">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Ile split my heart ere my humor strike saile: here comes his Page, how now boy? how doth your master. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e113440">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>Well madam he. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e113460">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Well? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e113480">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>Very well. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e113500">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Where is he? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e113520">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>Where none of your proude sex will euer come, I thinke: in heauen. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e113540">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Is he dead? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e113560">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>See madam, and seeing blush, and blushing shame, that your vngentle humor should be the death of so good and generous <pb xml:id="ep000371-019-b"/>a spirit. </p>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e113580">Discouer Aspero lying on a Table seeming dead. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e113590">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>My Aspero dead! </l>
            <l>Boy See madam, what a mutation </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e113620">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>I see too much, and curse my proud humour that was the cause of it: Aspero, kind soule, proud sullen Florimell, disdainefull humor, that in one minute hast eternally vndone me: I would not kisse the liuing substance, that being dead doate on thy picture: oh I lou'd thee euer with my soule: O let me kisse this shrowd of beauty: I would not accept thee liuing, that being dead on my knees adore thee: could kisses recouer thee, I would dwell on thy lips: kneele till my knees grew to the ground, deere gentle Aspero she that procurde thy death will die with thee, </p>
            <p>And craue no heauen, but still to lie with thee. </p>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e113650">Aspero starts vp. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e113660">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>I take you at your word Lady: </p>
            <p>Nay neuer recant, I haue witnes on't now: is your proud humor come downe? could you not haue said so at first? and sau'd me a labour of dying? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e113690">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Liues Aspero? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e113710">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Liue quotha? sfoot what man would bee so mad to lye in his colde graue alone, and may lie in a warme bed with such a beautifull wife as this will be? haue I tane your humour napping yfaith? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e113730">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Am I ore reacht? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e113750">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>In your humour Madam, nothing els, and I am as proude on't. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e113770">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Do not flowt me; and you doe, I shall grow into my humour againe. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e113790">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>In ieast. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e113810">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>In earnest I shall, and then I know what I know. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e113830">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>You may: but and you do, I shall die againe. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e113850">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>In ieast. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e113870">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Nay in earnest madam, and then— </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e113890">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>No more, thou hast driuen mee cleane out of conceite with my humor, I loue thee, I confesse it, shalt be my husband, ile liue <pb xml:id="ep000371-020-a"/>with thee, thou art my life, and ile die with thee. </p>
            <l>What more I meane is coated in my looke, </l>
            <l>If thou acceptst it, sweare, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e113930">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>I kisse the booke. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e113950">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Boy, run to the master of my Gundelo, and will him attend me after supper at the garden staires, I meane to take the euening ayre, tell him. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e113970">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>It shall be done madam. <stage xml:id="ep000371-e113990">Exit. </stage>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e114000">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Nay if I say the word, it shall be done Aspero. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e114020">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>Look to your selfe my Lord, I lay my life, my Lady means to steale you away to night. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e114040">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Away? ile call Hortensio, ile not be accessary to your fellony madam. </p>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e114060">Enter Hortensio and his man Assistance with a letter. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e114070">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>The foole comes without calling. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-assistance" xml:id="ep000371-e114090">
            <speaker>Ass. </speaker>
            <p>You shall know him by these signes. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e114110">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>Good figure, very good figure, for as the house is found out by the signe, so must this traytor be sented out by the token, vp with the first signe good Assistance. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-assistance" xml:id="ep000371-e114130">
            <speaker>Ass. </speaker>
            <p>A proper man without a beard. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e114150">
            <speaker>Hor. </speaker>
            <p>How? a proper man without a beard? we shall scarce finde that signe in all Venice: for the propernesse of a man liues altogether in the fashion of his beard, good Assistance the next. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-assistance" xml:id="ep000371-e114170">
            <speaker>Ass. </speaker>
            <p>Faire spoken and well conditioned. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e114190">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>More straunge: you shall haue many proper men fayrespoken, but not one amongst twenty well condicioned, but soft, this should be the house by the signe, I must pick it out of him by wit. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e114210">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>As good say steale my Lord, what mary-bone of witte is your iudgement going to pick now? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e114230">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>I must, like a wise Iustice of peace, picke treason out of this fellow. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e114250">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Treason? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e114270">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>I, treason madam; know you this hand? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e114290">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>My roiall fathers: </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e114310">
            <speaker>Hor. </speaker>
            <p>Then whilst you and your fathers letters talke togither, let <pb xml:id="ep000371-020-b"/>me examine this fellow: are you a proper man without a beard? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e114330">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>My propernes sir contents me: for my beard, indeed that was bitten the last great frost, and so were a number of Justices of peace besides. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e114350">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>Tis rumourd about the Court that your name is Aspero. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e114370">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>I am call'd Aspero. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e114390">
            <speaker>Hor. </speaker>
            <p>Sonne to the Duke of Mantua that was. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e114410">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>The duke of Mantuaes sonne that is. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e114430">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>Then the Duke of Mantua has a traytor to his sonne, lay hands of him and to close prison with him. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e114450">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Can he be closer then in my custody? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e114470">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>I do not thinke so madam, but your father has imposde the trust vpon me. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e114490">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>And dare not you trust mee? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e114510">
            <speaker>Hor. </speaker>
            <p>With my head if you were my wife, but not with my profit, if you were my mother: will you along sir? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e114530">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>With all my heart sir, see what your humour's come to now go my Lord? as willingly as a slaue from the gallies: for as I shall haue a stronger prison, so J shall bee sure of a kinder and a wiser iaylor. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e114550">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Do you obserue how he flowts you my Lord? that I had bin his keeper but one night longer: but keepe him close, if he escape (though against thy will) as I am a mayd, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e114570">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>A maide against your will. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e114590">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Shalt pay as deere for't as thou didst for thy office. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e114610">
            <speaker>Hort </speaker>
            <p>If he scape, hang me. <stage xml:id="ep000371-e114630">Exit &amp; As. with Aspero. </stage>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e114640">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>I shall wish thee hangd, if he do not: treason! I may thanke my peeuish humor fort. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e114660">Enter Page. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e114670">
            <speaker>Page. </speaker>
            <p>Madam the Gundelo is ready. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e114690">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Thou bringst physicke when the patient's dead boy: our ieast's turnd earnest. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e114710">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>Is a dead in earnest? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e114730">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>As good, or rather worse, hee's buried quick. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e114750">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>O madam, many a good thing has bin buried quick and suruiu'd againe, I would bee buried quicke my selfe, and I might <pb xml:id="ep000371-021-a"/>choose my graue. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e114770">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Hee's buried in close prison boy, hee's knowne for the duke of Mantuaes sonne, and by my fathers letter attached for a traytor. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e114790">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>Good gentleman, and I be not sorrie for him: who is his keeper? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e114810">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>The testie asse Hortensio. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e114830">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>Vds foot lets enlarge him, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-unassigned" xml:id="ep000371-e114850">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Not possible boy. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e114870">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>Not possible? tis: weele cousen his keeper. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e114890">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>We cannot. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e114910">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>Cannot! we can: your father made a Lord of him, but be rul'd by me, his daughter shall make a foole of him: you are not the first woman has made a foole of a wiser Lord then he is. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e114930">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Shall he be cousend? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e114950">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>As palpably as at the Lotterie, my brains are in labour of the stratagem alreadie. </p>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e114970">Exeunt. </stage>
          </sp>
          <trailer>Finis actus Tertiis. </trailer>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="ep000371-e114990">
          <head>ACTVS QVARTVS. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e115000">Enter Anthonio, Francisco, Hippolito, Hermia, Lucida and Octauio disguisd, </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e115010">
            <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
            <l>Sons of Octauio if your princely thoughts </l>
            <l>Can stoope to such meane beauty, from this hand </l>
            <l>Receiue your wiues, but should the Duke your father— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e115050">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <p>Feare not old man, he was the meanes that breath'd this spirit into vs. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-unassigned" xml:id="ep000371-e115070">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Wood vs to this course. </l>
            <l>But should he proue Apostata, denie </l>
            <l>Loue which he first enforcd vs to profes, </l>
            <l>So firme are our inseparate affections, </l>
            <l>To winne our loues weed loose the names of sonnes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e115130">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Your father thanks you, but hot-sprighted you that, </l>
            <l>Take counsell from experience, ere yee tie </l>
            <l>The gordian knot which none but heauen can loose, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000371-021-b"/>
            <l>Craue his consent: when an imperiall hand </l>
            <l>Shakes a weake shed, the building cannot stand. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e115190">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <p>Not stand? it shall: not Ioue himselfe can ruine the ground-worke for our loue. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e115210">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Not Ioue! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e115230">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Not Ioue, </l>
            <l>Should a speak thunder; then go boldly on, </l>
            <l>Our loue admits no separation. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e115270">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>Then to 〈…〉 your loue is chast. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e115290">
            <speaker>Fra. </speaker>
            <p>As innocence white soule. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e115310">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <p>As innocence white soule. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e115330">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>And yours. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e115350">
            <speaker>Herm. </speaker>
            <p>And ours, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-lucida" xml:id="ep000371-e115370">
            <speaker>Lucid. </speaker>
            <p>And ours, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e115390">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Then lend me all your hands, </l>
            <l>Whilst thus a fathers tongue forbids the bands, <stage xml:id="ep000371-e115420">discouers himselfe </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Forgetfull boyes, but most audacious traytor, </l>
            <l>That durst in thought consent to wrong thy Prince, </l>
            <l>Out of my fight; no Land that calls me Lord, </l>
            <l>Shall beare a waight so hatefull as they selfe: </l>
            <l>Liue euer banishd, if (three daies expirde) </l>
            <l>Thou or these lustfull strumpets. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e115490">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <p>Father. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e115510">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Boyes; </l>
            <l>If you be mine show't in obedience: </l>
            <l>If (three daies past) you liue within my dukedome, </l>
            <l>Thee as a slaue ile doome vnto the gallies, </l>
            <l>And these thy brats as common prostitutes▪ </l>
            <l>Shall drie their lustfull veynes in the Burdello. </l>
            <l>Come boyes, to Court; he that first gaue you liues, </l>
            <l>Will to your births prouide you equall wiues. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e115600">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <p>They haue our loues. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e115620">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <p>Our oathes. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e115640">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <p>Our hearts and hands. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e115660">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Tut, louers othes, like toyes writ down in sands </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000371-022-a"/>
            <l>Are soone blowne ore, contracts are common wiles, </l>
            <l>Tintangle fooles, Ioue himselfe sits and smiles </l>
            <l>At louers periuries, bawd, strumpets hence, </l>
            <l>My bosome's chargde, giue way to violence: </l>
            <l>Come doe not mind them. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e115730">Exeunt Anth, and his daughters. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e115740">
            <speaker>Fran. </speaker>
            <l>How? not minde them father? </l>
            <l>When in your Court you courted vs to loue, </l>
            <l>You red another lecture, women then </l>
            <l>Were angells. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e115790">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>True, but that was before Angells </l>
            <l>Had power to make them diuells; they were then </l>
            <l>Fiends to themselues, and Angells vnto men. </l>
            <l>When vpon Po thou find'st a cole-black swan, </l>
            <l>Th'ast found a woman constant to a man. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e115850">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <p>And not afore? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e115870">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>Neuer afore. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e115890">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Your tongue </l>
            <l>Vnspeaks your former speech. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e115920">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>It doth; new theames </l>
            <l>Must haue new change of Rhetorique; all streames </l>
            <l>Flow not alike one way; when I spake like a louer, </l>
            <l>Jt was to breake you from your souldiers humour; </l>
            <l>Hauing made you louers, I, like Enuy, speak </l>
            <l>To make you hate loue; Art still striues to breake </l>
            <l>Bad to make better: </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-brothers" xml:id="ep000371-e116000">
            <speaker>Brothers. </speaker>
            <p>You haue your wish. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e116020">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Then onward to the Court, </l>
            <l>Make vs of loue, as schoole-boyes do of sport. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e116050">Exeunt. </stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e116060">Enter Florimell and her Page. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e116070">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Call out the iaylor boy, yet doe not; hast got a beard like Hortensio? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e116090">
            <speaker>Page. </speaker>
            <p>Yes, madam, J haue got his hayre, if I coulde come as easily by his wit. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e116110">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Wouldst rob him of his wit? </p>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-022-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e116130">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>If I shold, he could not hang me for't: tis not worth thirteen pence halfe penny, but what shall I do with it? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e116150">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Put it on boy. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e116170">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>That shall J madam, O forward age, I am a man already: how do you like me Lady? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e116190">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Very ill, and my plot worse. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e116210">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <l>Then leaue't of, if you be grounded in the plot, </l>
            <l>You will but marre the Comedy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e116240">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>I purposde, thou in the habit of Hortensio, shouldst vnder pretence of remouing Aspero to a new prison, haue freed him out of the old one. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e116260">
            <speaker>Pa </speaker>
            <p>Tut, J can tell you a trick, worth two of that: madam, your eare, take some care in the managing, and let me alone to prepare it. </p>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e116280">Exeunt. </stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e116290">Enter Aspero and his Boy. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e116300">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>Vdsfoot breake prison my Lorde, tis but swimming the Riuer. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e116320">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Breake prison? twere both dishonour to my name, and treason to my loue, what benefit wer't for me to free my body, &amp; leaue my heart in bondage? ile die, ere ile harbour a disloyall thought. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e116340">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>Jt beares no rellish of disloyaltie: being in prison you liue as far from loue as liberty: being abroad, you may by letters, or a thousand meanes purchase hir company, and compasse your content. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e116360">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Shalt be my Lawyer boy and counsell me. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e116380">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>Ile looke for my Fee then. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e116400">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>If thy Counsell prospers. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e116420">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>Thats an exception Lawyers neuer respect, but come my lord, leape, as we haue risen togither, weele fall togither, </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e116440">Enter Hort. Florimell and Page. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e116450">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Blame me not loue, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-unassigned" xml:id="ep000371-e116470">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>Vdsfoot your iaylor my lord. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e116490">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Am I preuented? </p>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-023-a"/>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e116510">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>Yes faith, there had bin a Counsellors fee cast away now. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e116530">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>You haue heard his vsage Lady, seene his lodging, and if it please you, you both may and shall confer with him. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e116550">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Prithee call him. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e116570">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>My Lord, your keeper hath brought a Lady or two to see you. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e116590">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>To see me? why am I turnd monster? doth he take money to shew me? what doth a take a peece troe? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e116610">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Why how now gallant, not gone yet? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e116630">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Not, I thanke you Lady, and yet I was neer't. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e116650">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>How do you man? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e116670">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Musty for want of ayring. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e116690">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Weele haue you hangd out i'the fresh ayre, one of these mornings. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e116710">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Youl be glad to take me in then. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e116730">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Yes, when you had hangd abroad a little: but my Lorde Hortensio (for I think I must be your Lady when all's done) what sport? I would be merry a purpose to make him mad; the room's priuate and fit for any exercise. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e116750">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>Vdsfoot to her, can a woman offer fairer for't? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e116770">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>Why shall we go to span-counter madam? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e116790">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>To span-counter, best ask her and sheele go to Coits. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e116810">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>No, I loue some stirring exercise, my body's condiciond like the sun; it would neuer be out of motion. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e116830">
            <speaker>Hor. </speaker>
            <l>I hau't yfaith, when I was student in Padua, </l>
            <l>We vsde a most ingenious pastime. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e116860">
            <speaker>Flo </speaker>
            <p>The name my Lord. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e116880">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <l>I cannot giue it a name equall to the merit. </l>
            <l>Tis vulgarly calld Blindmans buffe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e116910">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>Blind mans buffe? ha, ha, ha, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e116930">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>Do you laugh at it? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e116950">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>At the happines of your wit my Lord, that you shoulde hit vpon that sport, which of all other I delight in. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e116970">
            <speaker>Hor. </speaker>
            <p>Will you heare an Apology I made in the commendation of it? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e116990">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Weele haue the thing it selfe first; and as we like that, weel <pb xml:id="ep000371-023-b"/>heare your Apologie after: who shall be hud-winckt first? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e117010">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>Who but the Author? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e117030">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>I, I, none shall be blind but I; helpe of with my gown boy. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e117050">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>What shall we haue to blind him? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e117070">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>My scarfe, take my scarfe my Lord. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e117090">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>There's a simple fauour for you. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e117110">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>And most fit, for indeed nothing blinds louers sooner then Ladies fauors, but who shall blind me. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e117130">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Mary that will I my Lord, let me alone to blind you. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e117150">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>Good againe; for who should blind men, but beautious women? come sweet madam. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e117170">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>But how if you take me? as I know that will be your ayme, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e117190">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>Jf J take you prisoner madam, you must either bee hudwinckt your selfe, or giue your conqueror a kisse for your ransome. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e117210">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>An easie ransome: ile not be prisoner long, if a kisse will enlarge me. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e117230">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>Lord what scambling shift has he made for a kisse and cannot get in neither; a little higher, so, so, so, are you blind my Lord? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e117250">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>As a purblind Poet: haue amongst you blind Harpers. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e117270">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Me thinks he looks for all the world like God Cupid. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e117290">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>Take heed of his dart madam, he comes vpon you, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e117310">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>He cannot come to fast, O I am taken prisoner. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e117330">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>Your ransome's but a kisse. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e117350">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Is that your law of armes? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e117370">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>Yes madam, but ile take it on your lips. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e117390">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>My lips like faithfull Treasurers shall see it dischargde. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e117410">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>And here are my honest receiuers to take it. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e117430">The Page puts his Pantoflle to his lips, he kisses it. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e117440">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Am I freed now? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e117460">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>As if you had seru'd seauen yeare for't: sweete kisse, rare lippe. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e117480">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>Has she not a sweet breath my Lord? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e117500">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>As perfume. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e117520">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>And a soft lip? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e117540">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>And smooth as veluet: I could scarce discerne it from <pb xml:id="ep000371-024-a"/>veluet: ide pawne my office for the fellow on't, madam. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e117560">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>Here. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e117580">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Here Aspero, on with this beard and gowne: I thinke hee followes me by the sent, his hat, so: a narrowe misse yfaith my Lord? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e117600">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>Gone madam? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e117620">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Euen vpon going, one of you counterfet my voice, there I deceiud you my Lord. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e117640">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>Haue you deceiu'd me madam? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e117660">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Not yet, but I will, and you look not the better too't, busie him till you thinke we are out of the Court, and then followe vs: you shall find vs at the south port, now or neuer my Lord. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e117680">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>Why then twill neuer be Lady. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e117700">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>Here. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e117720">
            <speaker>Hor. </speaker>
            <p>Where? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e117740">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>Here. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e117760">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>Scapt againe? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e117780">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>Shee's scapt indeed my Lord, you may cast your cap after her, for I see you can do no other good vpon hir. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e117800">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>What haue I catchd you? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e117820">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>Kisse her and let her goe. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e117840">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>Kings truce till I breath a little. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e117860">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>And you had neede so, for I thinke you are almost out of breath, if you be not, you shall be, and thats as good, but breathe and spare not. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e117880">Enter Aspero like Hortensio, Florimell, and Assistance on the vpper stage. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e117890">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Did you euer conuerse with a more straunger dissolute, madam? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e117910">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Peremptory iacke, iaylor, as you respect your office, lay speciall watch that none of what degree soeuer haue accesse to him. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e117930">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Without me. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-assistance" xml:id="ep000371-e117950">
            <speaker>Ass. </speaker>
            <p>Or your signet. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e117970">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Signet mee no signets, your goldsmiths shop is like your Swans neast, has a whole brood of signets, and all of a feather, &amp; amongst many, one may be like another, let none enter vpon the <pb xml:id="ep000371-024-b"/>stage where Aspero playes the madam, without Hortensio. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-assistance" xml:id="ep000371-e117990">
            <speaker>Ass. </speaker>
            <p>Is he mad my Lord? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e118010">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>As the Lord that gaue all to his followers, and beg'd more for himselfe. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e118030">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>If he call for me, tell him I scorne him. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e118050">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>If he counterfet my voice (as mad fellowes will counterfet great mens hands, and their tongues too) rate him for't, threaten him with the whip. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e118070">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>But come not at him. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e118090">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Jf he call for meat promise him faire; </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e118110">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>But giue him none. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-assistance" xml:id="ep000371-e118130">
            <speaker>Ass. </speaker>
            <p>If for light. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e118150">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>He may fire the house, let him haue none. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e118170">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Jf he chafe, laugh. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e118190">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>If he rayle, sing. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e118210">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Jf he speake fayre, flowt him. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e118230">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Do any thing to vexe him. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e118250">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>But nothing to content him, you heare my charge, as you respect your office regard it. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-assistance" xml:id="ep000371-e118270">
            <speaker>Ass. </speaker>
            <p>I warne you my Lord, let mee alone, and we knew not how to abuse a prisoner, we were not worthy to be a Iaylor. </p>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e118290">Exeunt. </stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e118300">They renew Blindmans Buffe on the Lower stage, </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e118310">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>Are you in breath my Lord? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e118330">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>As a bruers horse, and as long-winded; look to your selfe madam, I come vpon you. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e118350">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>J am ready for you sir; O for a bul-rush to run a tilt at's nose. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e118370">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>A fayre misse yfaith. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e118390">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>Ile mend it next course you shall see. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e118410">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>In the corner of the left hand; vdsfoot ware shins my Lord, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e118430">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>Madam. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e118450">
            <speaker>Boy </speaker>
            <p>Here. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e118470">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>Where? </p>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e118490">The boy throwes him downe, </stage>
            <p>Helpe me vp Madam, </p>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-025-a"/>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e118510">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>O strange, cannot you get vp without helpe? there's my gloue, but come no neerer, as you loue me. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e118530">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <l>I do loue you madam. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e118550">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <l>Oh blind loue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e118570">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <l>True madam; your beauty has made me blind. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e118590">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <l>Indeed loues sonnes like spaniells are all borne blind, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e118610">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <l>But they will see. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e118630">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <l>Not till they be nyne daies old my Lord, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e118650">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>But will you giue mee the fingers that hold this gloue madam? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e118670">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <p>And the whole body to pleasure you my Lord, but let me go a little. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e118690">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <l>I will not loose you yet Lady. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-boy" xml:id="ep000371-e118710">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <l>But you shall my Lord; hist, then keepe me still. </l>
            <l>He fastens the gloue to a post. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e118740">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>Faith let go my Lord, for she growes sullen, and you had as good talke to a post, and as good answer twould make you. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e118760">Exeunt. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e118770">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>Nay but deere madam, doe but answer me, may I presume, vppon my knees I beg it; but to take a fauour from your sweet lips? shall I? las I am not the first man, that loue has blinded, may I presume't I would be loth to offend your milde patience so much, as with an vnreuerend touch: speake; if I shall reape the haruest of my honest defires, make me blest in proposing the time when; what? not a word? are you displeased? or shall I take your silence for a consent? shall I? speake; or if modesty locke in your syllables, seale my assurance with a kisse: not? neither? shall I haue neither your word nor your bond? nay then I must make bold with modesty; by this kisse madam, O my hard fortune? haue I made suit to a poast all this while? what block but I, would haue bin so sencelesse? my excuse is, 'twas but to make my Lady sport: and: Madam? how? Lady? madam? boy; madam, Aspero: but whist, I haue the conceit, 'twas excellent in my Lady, and J applaud it, suppose my Lady and hir prisoner had an intent of priuate busines in the next roome; was it not better in her to blinde me, then I should as gentlemen vshers (cases so standing) haue <pb xml:id="ep000371-025-b"/>blinded my selfe? againe, J applaud her, and adore my starres that made me rather a blind then a seeing dore-keeper: shall I interrupt them? no: madam? they haue not done yet, sure they haue not: what haue we here? a base violl! though J cannot tickle the mynnikyn within, ile (though it be some what base) giue them a song without, and the name of the Ditty shall be; </p>
            <p>The Gentleman Vshers Voluntarie. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e118800">He sings. </stage>
          <lg>
            <l>Peace, peace, peace, make no noyse, </l>
            <l>Pleasure and feare lie sleeping? </l>
            <l>End, end, end your idle toyes, </l>
            <l>Iealous eies will be peeping. </l>
            <l>Kisse, kisse and part, though not for hate for pittie, </l>
            <l>Ha done, ha done, ha done, for I ha done my dittie. </l>
          </lg>
          <p>And if you haue not done now too, let me be as base as my fiddle, if I rowze you not: madam for shame, what doe you meane to make of me, how? sfoote what haue you made of me already? all gone? Iaylor? </p>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e118890">Enter Assistance aboue. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-assistance" xml:id="ep000371-e118900">
            <speaker>Ass. </speaker>
            <l>How now? who calls? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e118920">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <l>Why saucie knaue tis J. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-assistance" xml:id="ep000371-e118940">
            <speaker>Ass. </speaker>
            <l>You, what you? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e118960">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>A single V, I came in double, but I thanke them, they are gone out, and left me here a single.— </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-assistance" xml:id="ep000371-e118980">
            <speaker>Ass. </speaker>
            <l>Foole, and so I leaue you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e119000">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <l>Knaue, I am Hortensio, I charge thee let me out. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-assistance" xml:id="ep000371-e119020">
            <speaker>Ass. </speaker>
            <p>Foole, you lye, you are Aspero, and I haue charge to keepe you in. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e119040">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <l>From whom? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-assistance" xml:id="ep000371-e119060">
            <speaker>Ass. </speaker>
            <l>From my Lord Hortensio. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e119080">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>Sfoot knaue J tell thee I am hee, and thou wilt not beleeue me, trust thine eies, come in and see. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-assistance" xml:id="ep000371-e119100">
            <speaker>Ass. </speaker>
            <p>'Twill not serue your turne, J like a whole skinne better then a pinkt one: content your selfe to night, and in the morning ile tell you more. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e119120">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <l>Where's my Lady, send hir hither, </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-026-a"/>
          <sp who="#ep000371-assistance" xml:id="ep000371-e119140">
            <speaker>Ass. </speaker>
            <p>Shee's busie with my Lord Hortensio, but if you haue any vse for a woman, ile send you one of the Laundresses: fare you well sir, bee content, you shall want nothing of any thing you haue. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e119160">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>Hortensio gone outland my Ladie busie with Hortensio? I am gulld, palpably guld: whilst I like a blocke stood courting the post, Aspero is in my apparrell escapde: villains, traytors, open the doore, the Duke's abusd, his daughter's fled: I proclaime yee all traytors that hinder me in the pursuit. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-assistance" xml:id="ep000371-e119180">
            <speaker>Ass. </speaker>
            <p>O for a reasonable audience to applaud this sceane of merryment: ile goe call my Lady and my Lord Hortensio. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e119200">Exit </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e119210">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>Blindmans buffe? I haue bufft it fairely, and mine owne gullery grieues me not halfe so much as the Dukes displeasure, iaylor, not a word? iaylor, there's no way to please a knaue but fayre words, and gold: honest kinde iaylor, here's gold for thee: doe but take pittie vpon me, a miserable cony-catchd Courtier: not? neither fayre nor foule? thou art a degree worse then a woman; what shall I doe? I can compare my fortune and my vnfortunate selfe to nothing so fitlie as my Base here, wee suffer euerie foole to play vpon vs for their pleasure: and indeede 'twas the intent of our Creator that made fiddles and seruitors to nothing but to be playd vpon, and playd vpon wee shall be, till our heart strings crack, and then they either cast vs aside or hang vs vp, as worthy no other imployment; well, if I can worke my meanes, of escape, so: if not, I must lie by it. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e119230">Exit. </stage>
          <trailer>Finis actus Quarti. </trailer>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="ep000371-e119250">
          <head>ACTVS QVINTVS. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e119260">Enter Octauio, Francisco, Hippolito Flamineo. &amp;c. </stage>
          <lg>
            <l>MY daughter fled? and with Hortensio, </l>
            <l>It beares no formall shape of likelyhood, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000371-026-b"/>
            <l>Hir Eagle spirit soard to proud a pitch, </l>
            <l>To seize so base a prey; let priuy searche </l>
            <l>Look through the citties bosome till they find her: </l>
            <l>For gone she is not. </l>
          </lg>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e119340">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Has not Anthonies sonne </l>
            <l>Sent them by some base practise to their death? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e119370">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>His breasts too full of honor; trusty Iulio? </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e119390">Enter Iulio. </stage>
            <l>What waighty businesse drawes thee from thy charge? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-jul" xml:id="ep000371-e119410">
            <speaker>Iul. </speaker>
            <l>Came not the cause afore me? the proud Mantuans </l>
            <l>Basely reuolt, deposde me from the seate </l>
            <l>And chayre of Regentship, sending in quest </l>
            <l>Of proude Anthonio their late-banishd Duke, </l>
            <l>Him if they find or Aspero his sonne <stage xml:id="ep000371-e119470">Enter Assist. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Theile reinstall him in the regiment. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e119490">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>Him let them seeke in the vast shades of death, as for his sonne. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-assistance" xml:id="ep000371-e119510">
            <speaker>Ass. </speaker>
            <p>Hee's sure ynough my Lord, he was a mad knaue when he came in, but J thinke, I haue made a tame foole of him by this time: for a has neither had bread nor water these foure and forty houres. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e119530">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>More villain thou. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-assistance" xml:id="ep000371-e119550">
            <speaker>Ass. </speaker>
            <p>My Lord, Hortensio was the villain, he left such command with mee, hee's the wheele that turnes about, and I a Country Iack must strike when I am commanded. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e119570">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Although my foe, hee's honorably tempred, </l>
            <l>Yet armd against my life goe call him forth, </l>
            <l>Guard in my safety with a ring of steele, </l>
            <l>And marke how proudly heele demeane reuenge. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e119620">Enter Assistance and Hortensio bareheaded with his Crowd, </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-assistance" xml:id="ep000371-e119630">
            <speaker>Ass. </speaker>
            <l>Goblins, spirits, furies, faeryes, the prison is haunted. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e119650">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>With a knaue is't not? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-assistance" xml:id="ep000371-e119670">
            <speaker>Ass. </speaker>
            <p>Yes, and an olde foole my Lord, in the likenesse of Hortensio. </p>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-027-a"/>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e119690">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Villain where's Aspero. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-assistance" xml:id="ep000371-e119710">
            <speaker>Ass. </speaker>
            <p>I know not my Lord: I let him in and my Lady to laugh at him, and it seemes, he consented to treason, and let him out in his apparrell. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e119730">
            <speaker>Hor. </speaker>
            <p>They consented togither to cousen me, for taking delight (as my betters may doe) in a foolish pastime called Blindmans buffe, they stole away my gowne, escapt the prison, and left mee in fooles paradice, where, what song I haue playd, my Violl can witnesse, they made me a little better then a bawd my Lord. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e119750">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>In act: </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e119770">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>Not meerly in act: sed cogitatione, &amp; id satis est vt inquit Suetonius. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e119790">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Js hee escapt: and Florimell with him? </l>
            <l>Hortensio thy head shall answer it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hortensio" xml:id="ep000371-e119820">
            <speaker>Hort. </speaker>
            <p>I pray let my tongue be my heads Atturney, and pleade my excuse. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e119840">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Vrge no excuse, away with him to prison. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-assistance" xml:id="ep000371-e119860">
            <speaker>Ass. </speaker>
            <l>It shall be done my Lord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e119880">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>Nay you sir too, shall taste of the same sauce, away with both, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-flamineo" xml:id="ep000371-e119900">
            <speaker>Flamineo. </speaker>
            <l>Come my sonnes, </l>
            <l>Lets leauy present armes gaynst Mantua. </l>
            <l>Being scarce come home we must abroad againe, </l>
            <l>The Common good's a carefull Princes payne. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000371-e119950">Exeunt. </stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e119960">Enter Anthonio, Lucida, Hermia and Lords. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e119970">
            <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
            <l>You that in all my banisht pilgrimage, </l>
            <l>Would neuer alienate your naturall loues, </l>
            <l>But in desire to see me reinstalld, </l>
            <l>Haue thrust out proude Octauioes substitute, </l>
            <l>And seated me in antient dignity, </l>
            <l>I am yours, and ready at your best dispose. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-lord" xml:id="ep000371-e120040">
            <speaker>Lord </speaker>
            <l>Your owne, my liege, we like inferiour lights </l>
            <l>Take life from your reflection, for like stars </l>
            <l>Vnto the sunne, are Counsellours to Kings: </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000371-027-b"/>
            <l>He feeds their orbes with fier, and their shine </l>
            <l>Contend to make his glory more diuine. </l>
            <l>And such are we to great Anthonio. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e120110">
            <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
            <l>The veynes and arteries of Anthonio </l>
            <l>Through which the bloud of greatnesse flows in vs. </l>
            <l>Our life, and cause efficient of our state, </l>
            <l>And these our prety partners in exile. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-lord" xml:id="ep000371-e120160">
            <speaker>Lord. </speaker>
            <l>We ha yet performd but the least part of duetie, </l>
            <l>Your reinstalment: it rests, that with our bloud, </l>
            <l>We keepe out innouative violence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e120200">
            <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
            <l>You new-create me, and breath second life </l>
            <l>Into my dying bosome, knew my soone </l>
            <l>Of this vnlookt-for Fortune, but ill Fate </l>
            <l>Has playd the Traytor, and giuen vp his life </l>
            <l>To coward treason. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e120260">A shout within. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e120270">Enter Aspero and Florimell with their Pages. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e120280">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Vdsfoot what offence haue I committed against the state, that these yron-handed Plebeians so applaud me for? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e120300">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Tis a signe they loue you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e120320">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>I had rather thy should hate me, it makes mee suspect my bosome, for they loue none, but the masters of factions, treasons, and innouasions. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e120340">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Then you doe not loue the Commons. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e120360">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Yes, as wise men doe their flattering wiues, only for show: the popular voyce is like a crie of bauling hounds, and they get the foote of a fantasticke and popular-affecting statesman, they neuer leaue him, till they haue chac'd him into disgrace, &amp; then, like hounds, are at a losse, and with their losse, see, I haue found my father, safety attend you. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e120380">
            <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
            <l>Welcome thou hope of Mantua and of vs, </l>
            <l>We now are honors new beginners boy, </l>
            <l>And may we better thriue then heretofore. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e120420">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Neuer doubt it father, I haue attractiue stuffe that will draw customers. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e120440">
            <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
            <l>What Lady's that. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-028-a"/>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e120460">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>One that has playd the part of a Constable, brought you home a Runaway. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e120480">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>A friend of mine Father, but daughter to your Arch-enemy. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e120500">
            <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
            <l>Octauioes daughter? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e120520">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Yes faith, you are out with the Father, and ile see if I can fall in with the daughter. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e120540">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>And am I not a good child to leaue my fathers loue at sixe and seauen, and hazard my honor vpon your sonnes naked promise, and your hopefull acceptance. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e120560">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>She has followed me through much danger. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e120580">
            <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
            <l>The better welcome, I loue her for't. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e120600">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>Like her and you please, id'e haue no body loue her but my selfe. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-antonio" xml:id="ep000371-e120620">
            <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
            <l>And Lady, though your Father be our foe, </l>
            <l>The vertuous loue betwixt our sonne and you, </l>
            <l>May nerethelesse retaine his simpathie. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e120660">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Shall nerethelesse retaine his simpathy, </l>
            <l>Anthonio know I am loues resolute, </l>
            <l>Confirmd and grounded in affection: </l>
            <l>I lou'd your sonne, not for he was a Prince, </l>
            <l>But one no better then his present fortunes, </l>
            <l>Ile loue him still, since first I lou'd him so, </l>
            <l>Let Father, friends, and all the world say no. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e120740">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <p>There's mettle Father, how can wee choose but get cocking children, when father and mother too are both of the game. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e120760">Enter Messenger. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-messenger" xml:id="ep000371-e120770">
            <speaker>Mess. </speaker>
            <l>To armes my Lord, Octauio comes in armes </l>
            <l>To giue a proud assault vnto the Citty. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e120800">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Proud his assault, as proud be our resist, </l>
            <l>Vye shot for shot, and stake downe life for life, </l>
            <l>Our brest's as bold as theirs, our bloud as deepe, </l>
            <l>All that wee'l loose, or this our gettings keepe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e120850">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Come brother, talke not of deuouring war, </l>
            <l>Say messenger, comes not Octauioes sonnes? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-messenger" xml:id="ep000371-e120880">
            <speaker>Mess. </speaker>
            <l>They do, as proudly as the morning Sunne </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000371-028-b"/>
            <l>Beating the azurd pauement of the heauen. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e120910">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Then feare not father, my sister and my selfe, </l>
            <l>Will be your champions and defend the Citty. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e120940">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Why Ladies, haue you such large interest in our brothers. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e120960">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Princesse, we haue, within there: reach our shields, </l>
            <l>When beauty fights, the God of battaile yeelds. <stage xml:id="ep000371-e120990">Exeunt. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e121000">Enter Francisco, Hippolito, Flamineo, Iulio. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e121010">Enter Anthonio, Aspero, Florimell, two Pages Lords and Messenger aboue. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e121020">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>They offer parlee, let mee answer them. </l>
            <l>Brothers, how now? who made you souldiers? </l>
            <l>Faith een my father as he made you louers: </l>
            <l>What? hath he chang'd your shepheards hooks to swords? </l>
            <l>Of Amoradoes made you armed knights? </l>
            <l>O seld-seene metamorphosis! J haue knowne </l>
            <l>Souldiers turne louers, but for amorous louers </l>
            <l>To re-assume their valour, tis a change, </l>
            <l>Like winter-thunder, and a thing as strange. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e121120">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Our sister prisoner? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e121140">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Tell me Florimell, </l>
            <l>Dost thou liue there enforc'd, or of free-will? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e121170">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Free will, brothers, mine owne free will, all free in Mantua, here's free will yfaith, speake am I not a free-woman? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e121190">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>As if you had seru'd for't, any man may set vp vnder hir copy without a protection. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e121210">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>J wag? are you there too? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e121230">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>Yes faith my Lord, my Lady has had my attendaunce to a hayre. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e121250">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>You lie boy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e121270">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <l>If not mine, some bodies els: there's one has done— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e121290">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>What haue I done sirra? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e121310">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <p>Nay nothing, but what my Lady was very well content with. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e121330">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Why sister, shame you not to set your loue </l>
            <l>On one, that is our Fathers enemie. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-029-a"/>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e121360">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Shame? not a whit: but come, your wenches brothers, </l>
            <l>I make no question, I haue won my wager: </l>
            <l>Are they as faire as I? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e121400">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Leaue that to triall. </l>
            <l>Aspero make surrender of our sister. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e121430">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>And haue her in quiet possession? what do you thinke me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e121450">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>We thinke thee a proud villain and our foe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e121470">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>By heauen, th'are villains all that thinke him so, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e121490">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Why doe you loue him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e121510">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>I should curse my selfe </l>
            <l>if I should hate him: </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e121540">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Bring the ladders forth, </l>
            <l>Brauely assault to separate their liues, </l>
            <l>As they are sealing the walls, the Ladies come forth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e121580">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Stand proud Francisco. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e121600">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <l>Sand! O excellent word in a woman! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-lucida" xml:id="ep000371-e121620">
            <speaker>Luc. </speaker>
            <l>Hold Hippolito. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e121640">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <l>Hold! vp with that word, and tis as good as the other. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e121660">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>What nymphe or goddesse in my Hermiaes shape, </l>
            <l>Stands to debar my entrance to the towne: </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e121690">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <l>Madam, I wonder they enter not. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e121710">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Why boy it seemes they dare not, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-page" xml:id="ep000371-e121730">
            <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
            <l>O cowards and haue two such fayre breaches already, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e121750">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Immortall Pallas that art more diuine, </l>
            <l>In my loues beautie that thou cloth'st thee in, </l>
            <l>With drawe thy selfe, and giue our fury limits. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e121790">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>I will, but first Francisco take my shielde. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-lucida" xml:id="ep000371-e121810">
            <speaker>Luc. </speaker>
            <l>And mine as challenge to a single combat, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hermia" xml:id="ep000371-e121830">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Read the conditions and returne your answers. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e121850">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Well done yfaith wenches, O that the olde gray-beard my Father were here, ide haue about with him as I am honourable. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e121870">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Whats here! </l>
            <l>A shepheard wooing of a Country maide, </l>
            <l>As she sits angling by a Riuers side, </l>
            <l>By them an aged man making a net! </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000371-029-b"/>
            <l>The Motto: Sic! this Emblems morrall is, </l>
            <l>The former loue I had with Lucida, </l>
            <l>And this hope tells me that's faire Lucida. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e121950">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Brother, my shield the like presents to me, </l>
            <l>But holds far more familiar reference, </l>
            <l>Here doth the amorous shepheard kisse the Nymph; </l>
            <l>Which she with a chast blush consents vnto: </l>
            <l>And see, a gloomy man, clad like a pilgrim </l>
            <l>Comes in, and seperates their sweete delights: </l>
            <l>The Motto, Sic! I so my Father came, </l>
            <l>and banisht me from beautious Hermia, </l>
            <l>and this hope tells me is faire Hermia. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e122050">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>The more I looke, the more me thinkes tis she. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e122070">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>The more I think the more I find tis she. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e122090">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>What should I thinke to proue it is not she? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e122110">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Looke, thinke, find, proue, doe what you can, </l>
            <l>These are the wenches that you courted than: </l>
            <l>Then hony bees lay by your smarting stings, </l>
            <l>and buz sweet loue into your Ladies eares, </l>
            <l>Tell them of kisses, and such prety things, </l>
            <l>These drumming dub adubs loues pleasure feares. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e122180">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>O heauen, oh fortune, and most happie stars, </l>
            <l>Do I find loue, where I expected wars? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e122210">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>I that but now was all for war and death, </l>
            <l>am made all loue, wars humour's out of breath. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e122240">Enter Octauio, Iulio, and others. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e122250">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>How, my sonnes loue the daughters of my foe! it cannot be, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-jul" xml:id="ep000371-e122270">
            <speaker>Iul. </speaker>
            <l>Then question them your selfe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e122290">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Why how now sonnes, is this your worth in armes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e122310">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>Why are we not in armes father. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e122330">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>Yes, and in such armes as no Coward, but woulde venture life to march in. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e122350">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Then boies, you loue the daughters of Anthonio. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-francisco" xml:id="ep000371-e122370">
            <speaker>Fr. </speaker>
            <l>We lik'd them first. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-030-a"/>
          <sp who="#ep000371-hippolito" xml:id="ep000371-e122390">
            <speaker>Hip. </speaker>
            <l>WE keepe that liking still. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e122410">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>And you will loue them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e122430">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <l>Father infaith they will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e122450">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <p>I, run away are you there? whome has your Ladyship got to your husband? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-florimell" xml:id="ep000371-e122470">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>One that I stumbled on at Blindman buffe, a proper man, a man euery ynch of him: and you would say so, and you knewe but as much as I— meane to know ere I haue done with him. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e122490">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>Is he not sonne vnto Anthonio? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e122510">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Great Duke I am, and prostrate on my knee, </l>
            <l>I beg a peace, which if your spleene deny, </l>
            <l>I proudlie stand where erst I mildly kneel'd, </l>
            <l>and east downe bold defiance from theis walls. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-octavio" xml:id="ep000371-e122560">
            <speaker>Oct. </speaker>
            <l>No more your loues make my proud hart asham'd, </l>
            <l>Your consort's sweet, and ile not be a meane </l>
            <l>To make it iar: what my sonnes like shall stand, </l>
            <l>By my consent, allowed and perfected; </l>
            <l>all hate is banisht, and reuenge lies dead. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000371-aspero" xml:id="ep000371-e122620">
            <speaker>Asp. </speaker>
            <l>Then stead of speares, let Hymens torches flame </l>
            <l>With hallowed incence, and the God of spright, </l>
            <l>Swell vp your vaines with amorous delight: </l>
            <l>and so that vp our single Comedy, </l>
            <l>With Plautus phrase: Si placet, plaudite. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000371-e122680">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
          <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
          <pb xml:id="ep000371-030-b"/>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back></back>
  </text>
</TEI>
