<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000353" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>2 The Cid</title>
        <author>
<!--Desfontaines, Nicolas-Marc-->
          <persName>
            <forename>Nicolas-Marc</forename>
            <surname>Desfontaines</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A19347.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull n="TCP source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">The second part of the Cid.</title>
                <author>Desfontaines, Nicolas-Marc, d. 1652.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>35 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
                <date>2007 October (TCP phase 1)</date>
                <idno type="marc">99844351</idno>
                <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 5771.</idno>
                <idno type="stc">Greg, II, 596.</idno>
                <idno type="vid">9155</idno>
                <idno type="DLPS">A19347</idno>
                <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2240924469</idno>
                <availability>
                  <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
                </availability>
              </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
            <biblFull n="printed source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">The second part of the Cid.</title>
                <title type="alt">Vraye suitte du Cid. English</title>
                <title type="alt">La vraye suitte du Cid.</title>
                <title type="add">Le Cid.</title>
                <author>Desfontaines, Nicolas-Marc, d. 1652.</author>
                <author>J.R. fl. 1635-1640,</author>
                <author>Corneille, Pierre, 1606-1684.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[72] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Printed by I. Okes, for Samuell Browne, and are to be sold at his shop in St. Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the white Lion,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication_date">M.D.C.XL. [1640]</date>
                <date type="creation_date">1640</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>
                  <p>Translator's dedication signed: J. Rutter.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>A translation of: Desfontaines, Nicolas-Marc. La vraye suitte du Cid.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>A sequel to: Corneille, Pierre. Le Cid.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Signatures: A-C12.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>With an initial imprimatur leaf.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>The last leaf is blank.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
                </note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <person xml:id="ep000353-infanta">
            <persName>Infanta</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000353-cimena">
            <persName>Cimena</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000353-sancho">
            <persName>Sancho</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000353-unassigned">
            <persName>Unassigned</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000353-king">
            <persName>King</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000353-diego">
            <persName>Diego</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000353-arias">
            <persName>Arias</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000353-roderigo">
            <persName>Roderigo</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000353-spheranti">
            <persName>Spheranti</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000353-celimant">
            <persName>Celimant</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000353-serifa">
            <persName>Serifa</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000353-page">
            <persName>Page</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000353-boy">
            <persName>Boy</persName>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
      <textClass>
        <classCode scheme="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q192881</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1637">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div type="imprimatur" xml:id="ep000353-e100030">
        <pb xml:id="ep000353-001-a"/>
        <p>Imprimatur MATTH. </p>
        <p>CLAY. </p>
        <p>Aprilis 6. </p>
        <p>1639. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000353-e100080">
        <pb xml:id="ep000353-001-b"/>
        <p>THE Second Part of THE CID. </p>
        <p>LONDON, Printed by I. Okes, for Samuell Browne, and are to be sold at his shop in St. Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the white Lion. </p>
        <p>M. D. C. XL. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000353-e100120">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000353-002-a"/>
        <head>
          <pb xml:id="ep000353-002-b"/>TO THE TRUELY Noble the Ladie, Theophila Cooke. </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>MADAM, </salute>
        </opener>
        <p>IF I had no obligation to your Ladiship, which might challenge my endevours of honouring you, a fitter or a happier name could not protect this piece, (whose subject is the preferring of Dutie, and respects before Love, as the former did Honour and courage:) which I therefore offer to <pb xml:id="ep000353-003-a"/>your Ladiship; because in them there is none better studied than your selfe, in whom I have observ'd from the strength of Vertue, such a serenity as conducts your mind to the performance of whatsoever is fit and decent in humane life. And I remember I had the Honour to heare your Ladiship discourse of this subject, when you concluded that a perfect Lover should submit his desires to his Mistresses advancement: which made mee wish that our French Author had spoken with those Graces here in this, with which your Ladiship then did. But since it pleased his Majesty to thinke it worth the translating, and commanded it to be put into my hands, I will not censure it, though I believe, if that may carry the place which is free from deformities, without excellence before that which is here and there exceeding faire, and as much blemished, I think this may deserve it, which is rather not to be excepted to then much extold. Whatsoever it be, I beseech your Ladiship to let it <pb xml:id="ep000353-003-b"/>passe under your name, lest I be thought indiscreet in placing it else-where, or unmindfull of what I owe you, though this be the least part of that returne which is meant to you from </p>
        <closer>
          <signed>Your most humble and obedient Servant, ERUTTER. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="ep000353-e100180">
        <pb xml:id="ep000353-004-a"/>
        <head>The Persons of the Play. </head>
        <list>
          <item>The young King of Castile. </item>
          <item>Da. URRACA the INFANTA his Sister. </item>
          <item>CELIMANT King of Corduba. </item>
          <item>SPHERANTI Prince of Toledo. </item>
          <item>SERIFFA Sister to CELIMANT. </item>
          <item>D. DIEGO Father to the CID. </item>
          <item>RODERIGO the CID. </item>
          <item>CIMENA. </item>
          <item>D. SANCHO Favourite to the King. </item>
          <item>D. ARIAS. </item>
          <item>Guard. Attendants. Page to CIMENA. </item>
        </list>
        <p>The Scene. </p>
        <p>The Court of SEVILLE. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="play" xml:id="ep000353-e100340">
        <pb xml:id="ep000353-004-b"/>
        <head>The Second Part of The CID. </head>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="ep000353-e100350">
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e100360">
            <head>ACT I. SCENE I. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e100370">INFANTA. CIMENA. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e100380">
              <speaker>INFANTA. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Tell me Cimena and deal truly with me, </l>
                <l>What makes you thus disdain to be a Queen, </l>
                <l>Are the allurements of a Kingdome such </l>
                <l>As they can hardly touch, lesse charm your heart? </l>
                <l>No, I shall nere believe it, but must wonder </l>
                <l>At your refusall: do you think your Cid </l>
                <l>With all his fortune, and the best effects </l>
                <l>Of his great valour, can at any time </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-005-a"/>
                <l>Impale this faire head with a Diadem? </l>
                <l>That from the King alone you must expect </l>
                <l>Cid is as much a subject as thy selfe, </l>
                <l>And though he lift thy fortune to a height </l>
                <l>As great as any subjects, yet a thousand </l>
                <l>Will side with thee, when this my brother offers </l>
                <l>Will set thy beauties in a point to strike </l>
                <l>The gazers eyes with envy, or amazement. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e100560">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Madam, tis true so great a Princes love </l>
                <l>Might take another, though it cannot me, </l>
                <l>And the false lustre of a Soveraigne greatnesse </l>
                <l>May dazell any fond young Virgins eyes, </l>
                <l>But for my own direction ile take lesse </l>
                <l>Of their ambition, more of modesty, </l>
                <l>And truly Madam, I shall never envy </l>
                <l>Her who enjoyes the happinesse you offer, </l>
                <l>The pomp of Thrones seems troublesome to me, </l>
                <l>My desires draw themselves within their compasse, </l>
                <l>And look no higher then their proper reach: </l>
                <l>Equality does make the perfect match, </l>
                <l>Unequall persons render the link so weak </l>
                <l>That love can hardly make it hold together. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e100720">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I know Cimena thy great modesty, </l>
                <l>But let it not divert thee from a good </l>
                <l>Sent from the hand of Heaven, and a King. </l>
                <l>That power, which gave thee such rare parts, would never </l>
                <l>They should be streightned in a narrow fortune </l>
                <l>It knows this fore head's destin'd for a Crown </l>
                <l>Which to confirme, it makes a Monarch know </l>
                <l>That nought lesse then himselfe can suite thy merit </l>
                <l>Though Cid have heretofore made thee his Idoll. </l>
                <l>Dost think his love's not subject unto change </l>
                <l>And that he must continue in his absence </l>
                <l>As a great souldier, so a faithfull lover, </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-005-b"/>
                <l>Perhaps thy love may trouble him at present, </l>
                <l>Whilst his ambition grows up with his fortune: </l>
                <l>If ere he gain'd his glorious name of Cid, </l>
                <l>He thought himself already worthy thee, </l>
                <l>Dost think his heart will stay in the same bounds, </l>
                <l>Now that all Spain, and other Nations </l>
                <l>Admire and feare his valour? ah Cimena </l>
                <l>Some thing perswades me that his hopes fly higher, </l>
                <l>A throne will be the certain rock whereon </l>
                <l>Thy so much boasted faith must finde its Tombe. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e100960">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Oh heavens, how handsomely she would surprize me </l>
                <l>And ravish that from me her self would have! <stage xml:id="ep000353-e101000">Aside </stage>
                </l>
                <l>I without doubt she loves him; and I know </l>
                <l>She speaks more for herself then for the King: </l>
                <l>Madam, if Roder go leave Cimena </l>
                <l>To give his heart unto a nobler love, </l>
                <l>You shall perceive that she is one can suffer </l>
                <l>With as much ease his lightnesse, as his absence. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e101070">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>But since thou hast the very same advantage </l>
                <l>Serve thy selfe of it, and as his great honours </l>
                <l>Alter his passions, so let thine Cimena </l>
                <l>Take the same flight, and do not thinke thou shalt </l>
                <l>For that, be calld inconstant or lesse faithfull, </l>
                <l>Or that thy change should stick a crime upon thee, </l>
                <l>The wils of Kings can render all things lawfull. </l>
                <l>Besides thy fathers death may well excuse thee, </l>
                <l>And I remember with how much constraint </l>
                <l>Thou mad'st a promise of thy love to him </l>
                <l>Which was no more then hope; the King has power </l>
                <l>To cancell that, nor must thy vertue suffer </l>
                <l>So great a stain as to preferre the man </l>
                <l>Who kild thy father to the King. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e101230">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>But Madam. </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-006-a"/>
                <l>You know how strong a conflict I had in me </l>
                <l>Before I gave consent, whilst his great love </l>
                <l>Did lesse then my obedience, I resisted </l>
                <l>Till in the end I saw I must obey </l>
                <l>What the King will'd, he said, I must forget </l>
                <l>His Crime and my revenge: your father Madam </l>
                <l>Gave me into his hands, and since I am </l>
                <l>His prisoner, the same bonds shall end my life </l>
                <l>And fortune both at once. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e101350">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <l>But heare my reasons. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e101370">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <l>To what purpose. </l>
              <l>Should we dispute of what's resolv'd already? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e101400">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <l>Well you may think of it at better leasure. <stage xml:id="ep000353-e101420">Exit. </stage>
              </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e101430">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Yes: and I know the object of my Choice: </l>
                <l>If the Cids glory do put out his flame; </l>
                <l>And that's great lustre quench the heat of this </l>
                <l>I shall not stay the progresse of his fortune, </l>
                <l>Let him be on a Throne, me in my grave, </l>
                <l>Yet if this head must ever weare a Crown </l>
                <l>From none but Cid himselfe shall I accept it. </l>
                <l>But what's the reason that he writes not to me? </l>
                <l>I had some letters from him at the first, </l>
                <l>When the same hand which was bedewd in bloud </l>
                <l>Dry'd up my teares, but yet (alas) I feare </l>
                <l>Least distance of our eyes estrange our hearts: </l>
                <l>For of late (save the conquest of the Rebels) </l>
                <l>I can heare nothing from him, he destroyes </l>
                <l>His enemies and my hopes both at one time, </l>
                <l>His glory makes him to forget his dutie; </l>
                <l>But yet deare heart excuse my sad complaint </l>
                <l>True love was never yet without some feare </l>
                <l>Thou canst not be so generous and inconstant, </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-006-b"/>
                <l>And I should feare lesse, lov'd I not so much. </l>
                <l>Come then my foule and make no longer triall </l>
                <l>Both of my passion and my patience: </l>
                <l>Come to deliver me from those my doubts </l>
                <l>Or know that here I cannot live without thee. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e101690">
            <head>SCENE II. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e101700">DON SANCHO. </stage>
            <l>WHo's this Don Sancho? what may his businesse be? </l>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e101720">
              <speaker>SAN. </speaker>
              <l>The best of news unto the best of women. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-unassigned" xml:id="ep000353-e101740">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <l>What news? Is Cid return'd? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e101760">
              <speaker>SAN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Not yet sweet Madam, </l>
                <l>He's still expected, but a greater joy </l>
                <l>Attends you, which will soon dispell these clouds, </l>
                <l>How glorious is your fortune like to be? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e101820">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <l>What? has he overcome his enemies? </l>
              <l>Is he come home laden with Palmes and Lawrels? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e101850">
              <speaker>SAN. </speaker>
              <l>I heare his valor has assur'd our state, </l>
              <l>But that is not the cause of this my visit. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e101880">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <l>What's then my happinesse, pray let me know it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e101900">
              <speaker>SAN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Madam advise but with your own perfections </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-007-a"/>
                <l>And you will know the good provided for you, </l>
                <l>Aske counsell of your eyes; and they will tell you </l>
                <l>Gainst whom their quick &amp; burning darts are thrown </l>
                <l>They'l tell you that a King sprightly and young </l>
                <l>Chooses to be a slave before himself: </l>
                <l>And that he findes his chains so sweet and pleasant </l>
                <l>He seems to have no will to reigne without you, </l>
                <l>And I am sent to aske what he implores, </l>
                <l>Be not then rigorous to your self and him, </l>
                <l>But think what baits a Scepter carries in it, </l>
                <l>And that 'twill ill become you to be cruell </l>
                <l>When a Crown, and title of a Queen is offerd. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e102050">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I me sure it lesse becomes thee to afflict me </l>
                <l>With a discourse so hatefull, perjur'd man </l>
                <l>Hast thou so little shame, and courage in thee </l>
                <l>To speake this and not blush; hast thou forgot </l>
                <l>The glory of thy bonds; and that my self </l>
                <l>Permitted thee to weare em, whilst my pitty </l>
                <l>Made my looks gracious to thee, couldst thou then </l>
                <l>Having been once a Lover, proud to be so, </l>
                <l>Speak for another now, and that I should </l>
                <l>For thy sake take his love into my heart. </l>
                <l>Thou shewst by this thy basenesse, how unworthy </l>
                <l>Was Roderigoes rivall, since thou canst not </l>
                <l>Preserve the honour which thou hadst, for once </l>
                <l>To have been his Competitor. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e102210">
              <speaker>SAN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Did I think </l>
                <l>That you bore any thoughts of love to me, </l>
                <l>Or that th' impression of my former flame </l>
                <l>Were not quite worn out of your heart, I should not </l>
                <l>Speak for the King a word, but for my self, </l>
                <l>And you should see by my great constancie, </l>
                <l>How much Ide cherish such a hope. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000353-007-b"/>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e102300">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What traitour </l>
                <l>Should I love thee? canst thou imagine it? </l>
                <l>Or tempt thy self with such a vanity; </l>
                <l>I never yet receiv'd a flame so hatefull </l>
                <l>And if I thought my heart could entertain it, </l>
                <l>Ide pull it out my self: but canst thou have </l>
                <l>The confidence, Don Sancho to pretend </l>
                <l>To what thou wert not able to defend; </l>
                <l>Hast thou forgot the Duell where thou wert </l>
                <l>Forc'd to bring me the sword thou vainly hadst </l>
                <l>Imploy'd against the Cid, is it for that </l>
                <l>Thou lay'st thy clayme to my affection? </l>
                <l>For that must I preferre thee to the man </l>
                <l>Whom the Moores feare, and Spaine does reverence? </l>
                <l>Come let me heare thy actions; were our enemies </l>
                <l>Defeated by thy valour? Did the Moores </l>
                <l>Yield themselves at the hearing of thy name? </l>
                <l>Does thy arme hold our tottering Kingdome up? </l>
                <l>Art thou the glory of it? prove it true </l>
                <l>And I will run into thy deare embraces. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e102520">
              <speaker>SAN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Madam, I have not so much arrogance </l>
                <l>To challenge to my self such mighty deeds. </l>
                <l>My actions bound themselves more narrowly: </l>
                <l>I never did defeat the Moores, my arme </l>
                <l>Could nere do any thing worth your acceptance, </l>
                <l>And yet it reak, not with your fathers bloud. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e102600">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Knows thy fierce rage no bounds, tak'st thou delight </l>
                <l>To persecute me still, art thou not weary </l>
                <l>To see my teares run? thou mightst easier draw </l>
                <l>My bloud, and kill me with lesse cruelty. </l>
                <l>Come make it perfect, and revenge thy shame </l>
                <l>Upon my lives losse; yet let thy rage forbeare </l>
                <l>To wrong that goodnesse, which has spar'd thy life. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000353-008-a"/>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e102690">
              <speaker>SAN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>In telling truth I offer no man wrong, </l>
                <l>Nor did my rage suggest my words unto me </l>
                <l>Your Designe's fair indeed, but your hope vain; </l>
                <l>You care not how y'affront a Monarchs will; </l>
                <l>Nor can you think that your Cid will be faithlesse, </l>
                <l>You are the only she in all the Court </l>
                <l>To whom his love's unknown, you have not heard </l>
                <l>That Cordubas Infanta is his Mistris; </l>
                <l>But he himself avows it in his letters, </l>
                <l>Which he has done so to the life, that all </l>
                <l>Believe he's lesse their enemy, then her lover. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e102820">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Well let th' Infanta come, let her instead </l>
                <l>Of being captive be a conqueresse, </l>
                <l>Let Cid that should be victor, be her slave, </l>
                <l>It matters not, so I may have thy absence: </l>
                <l>Ile wait th'effects of his inconstancie </l>
                <l>With more assurance, and farre lesse disquiet, </l>
                <l>Pray leave me, I demand it as a favour </l>
                <l>And finde some better office when you next </l>
                <l>Addresse your selfe to any; 'tis no shame </l>
                <l>Not to have well discharg'd such an employment </l>
                <l>As being done must needs betray thy honour. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e102950">
              <speaker>SAN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Long as I serve my King, I feare no blame </l>
                <l>But here's an end of this; I leave you Madam, </l>
                <l>Till time shall make you to digest my counsaile. </l>
                <l>In the mean while I' me silent, and obay. <stage xml:id="ep000353-e103010">Exit. </stage>
                </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e103020">
            <pb xml:id="ep000353-008-b"/>
            <head>SCENE III. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e103030">KING, DON DIEGO, Guard, and Attendants. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e103040">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>DO not believe Don Diego, though I share </l>
                <l>My heart and Crown with the belov'd Cimena, </l>
                <l>That ile usurpe by my authority </l>
                <l>A treasure which thy sonne deserv'd so well. </l>
                <l>No, his great services do live too fresh </l>
                <l>In my remembrance to be so requited: </l>
                <l>Rather I mean t'augment his happinesse, </l>
                <l>And his reward shall paralell his valour, </l>
                <l>A nobler Mistris I designe for him </l>
                <l>To whom Cimena without blushing may </l>
                <l>Give place unto; nor should thy sonne complain </l>
                <l>Of this my affection, or of that his change. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-diego" xml:id="ep000353-e103180">
              <speaker>DIE. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>But we have never sir deserv'd this honour, </l>
                <l>Nor dare my sonne pretend to such a fortune, </l>
                <l>A higher happinesse attends the Princesse, </l>
                <l>Who is too generous to descend so low. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e103240">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>His actions tell me that he merits more </l>
                <l>Which to reward according to his value </l>
                <l>A Scepter is too little; I will share </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-009-a"/>
                <l>With him in his desires, he in my power. </l>
                <l>Love may content us both, if as my sister </l>
                <l>Is willing to receive him for her servant, </l>
                <l>So will the fair Cimena me for hers. </l>
                <l>Don Sancho from me is gone to see her, </l>
                <l>He knows her spirit, and should, how to tame it: </l>
                <l>I hope well of his fair tongues good successe. </l>
                <l>But why is he so slow in his return? </l>
                <l>Since he is conscious of my neerest secrets </l>
                <l>He must needs know that I burn all this while </l>
                <l>And that his slownesse causes me to languish. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e103400">
            <head>SCENE IV. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e103410">DON SANCHO. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000353-diego" xml:id="ep000353-e103420">
              <speaker>DIE. </speaker>
              <l>YOur Majesty has no cause of further trouble, </l>
              <l>See where he is. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e103450">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>Oh Don Sancho welcome, </l>
              <l>What says Cimena? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e103480">
              <speaker>SAN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>All that rigour can </l>
                <l>All that disdain and scorn does usually </l>
                <l>Inspire proud spirits with, that cruell faire </l>
                <l>Permitted to her tongue, my gentle words </l>
                <l>Were spent in vain; the Northern wind would sooner </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-009-b"/>
                <l>Have given them hearing, Roderigoes love </l>
                <l>Has made her to all else inexorable </l>
                <l>Nor can we hope to treat with her again. </l>
                <l>As for a Crown, Scepter, or any greatnesse </l>
                <l>They seem but to stirre up her anger more. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e103600">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What? will she be so cruell to her King? </l>
                <l>I must abate the pride of that fierce humour, </l>
                <l>And my resentment of t shall make her see </l>
                <l>That Princes must be treated otherwise: </l>
                <l>But these scorns her, Ile turn into her shame: </l>
                <l>And Cid whom she believes her own already, </l>
                <l>Shall as well fail her hopes, as she has mine </l>
                <l>When a more worthy object shall invite him </l>
                <l>To change his love, and his disdains of her </l>
                <l>Shall revenge hers of me. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e103720">
            <head>SCENE V. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e103730">DON ARIAS. </stage>
            <l>Don Arias, </l>
            <l>What news is it you bring? </l>
            <sp who="#ep000353-arias" xml:id="ep000353-e103760">
              <speaker>ARI. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Of Cids good fortune, </l>
                <l>And of the Rebels fate, he is hard by </l>
                <l>Victorious and in health. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e103810">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>I long to see him </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000353-010-a"/>
            <sp who="#ep000353-arias" xml:id="ep000353-e103830">
              <speaker>ARI. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>He is not farre sir from the City walls, </l>
                <l>Mean-while this Letter will confirme your Majesty, </l>
                <l>Ith' truth of what I said. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e103880">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>How am I ravish'd </l>
                <l>And my soule burns with hot impatience </l>
                <l>After this object which she so desires, </l>
                <l>Go tell him that my thoughts are swift to see him, </l>
                <l>Don Diego see that he be well received. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="ep000353-e103950">
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e103960">
            <head>Act II. Scene I. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e103970">KING, INFANTA; and CIMENA. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e103980">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>IT seems Cimena, you have no room left </l>
                <l>In this hard heart of yours for him that loves you, </l>
                <l>Must a King live and die in the same fetters? </l>
                <l>Were I a private man you'd be ingratefull </l>
                <l>To hate me, 'cause I love you, howsoever </l>
                <l>You were too blame to use Don Sancho so. </l>
                <l>Comming from me, and offering my service </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-010-b"/>
                <l>He might deserve a kinder entertainment </l>
                <l>Civility would require so much; and though </l>
                <l>He had displeas'd you, courting you for me </l>
                <l>Duty should have made good your want of love. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e104110">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I cannot tell, sir, what has raisd your anger, </l>
                <l>Nor how Don Sancho has describ'd me to you: </l>
                <l>But certainly, no vanity of mine </l>
                <l>Did make me to forget my duty to you: </l>
                <l>And my refusall of the soveraigne title </l>
                <l>Shew'd my respect, and not my cruelty, </l>
                <l>Don Sancho perhaps might be displeas'd, </l>
                <l>But his discourse mov'd me to what I said, </l>
                <l>Since he durst call to minde my fathers murder </l>
                <l>(A wound still bleeding in my memory.) </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e104230">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>If thou hast yet a feeling of this grief </l>
                <l>Both for thy honour, and content Cimena </l>
                <l>Tis fit thou banish from thy kinder thoughts </l>
                <l>The Author of it, nor does he now beare </l>
                <l>The same affection to thee which he did; </l>
                <l>When he left thee hee left his first intentions </l>
                <l>And having chang'd his climate, chang'd his love, </l>
                <l>Seriffas beauty is the mark he aymes at, </l>
                <l>Who once thy enemy, is now thy rivall. </l>
                <l>I'me sure he's much engag'd to this Jnfanta, </l>
                <l>But if he were not, yet the services </l>
                <l>My father had from all his Family </l>
                <l>Designe for him the Infanta of Castile. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e104380">
            <pb xml:id="ep000353-011-a"/>
            <head>SCENE II. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e104390">DON ARIAS. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000353-arias" xml:id="ep000353-e104400">
              <speaker>AR. </speaker>
              <l>SIr. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e104420">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>What wouldst thou? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-arias" xml:id="ep000353-e104440">
              <speaker>AR. </speaker>
              <l>Roderigo is without. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e104460">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Admit him then: now you shall see Cimena </l>
                <l>This glorious Conquerour, I know hele come </l>
                <l>Triumphantly, leading his Mistris with him, </l>
                <l>You'l easily perceive in this encounter </l>
                <l>Either his love or his ingratitude. </l>
                <l>Make your best use then of this time, compare </l>
                <l>Your Graces with your Rivals, and by them </l>
                <l>Guesse what your fortune's like to be. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e104560">
              <speaker>CI. </speaker>
              <l>Oh Heavens! </l>
              <l>With what eyes can I see this his approach? </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e104590">
            <pb xml:id="ep000353-011-b"/>
            <head>SCENE III. to them. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e104600">RODERIGO, SERIFFA; SPHERANTI, and CELIMANT. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e104610">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>GReat King, then whom the Sun sees nothing happier, </l>
                <l>(Joy of your subjects terror of your foes) </l>
                <l>At length the warre respiring, gives me leave </l>
                <l>To have the honour to kneele here before you, </l>
                <l>But as unto the Deity, of which </l>
                <l>You are the Image, none should dare to come </l>
                <l>Without an offering, so nor could I </l>
                <l>Hope to deserve the happinesse to see you </l>
                <l>Without a present: Then be pleas'd, great sir, </l>
                <l>T'accept from my hand what Heavens bounty gives you </l>
                <l>This Crown, and these two Princes, so far happy </l>
                <l>That they are falne your prisoners, under whom </l>
                <l>To be commanded is to live with freedom: </l>
                <l>This was the King of Corduba, and this </l>
                <l>The heire apparent of Toledos Kingdome. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e104780">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>He heare thy full relation, but before it </l>
                <l>Let me embrace thee, and behold this forehead </l>
                <l>Where Love and Mars do sit enthron'd, and make thee </l>
                <l>Victorious in either of their wars. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e104840">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Oh sir, how can I answer this discourse </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-012-a"/>
                <l>To spare my modesty, sir, spare your favours </l>
                <l>And share the honours, as y'have done the labours </l>
                <l>Your souldiers as much as I procur'd </l>
                <l>This victory, tis just they should receive </l>
                <l>Part of the honour from your Majesty </l>
                <l>Both for their valour and fidelity. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e104930">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Their merit can be easily satisfied </l>
                <l>But for thy deeds there can be no rewards: </l>
                <l>Sure thou wert born to make all men ungratefull, </l>
                <l>Thy tongue's no lesse a conquerour then thine arme, </l>
                <l>But for my sake spare thy sweet eloquence, </l>
                <l>Else I shall be thy captive as are these </l>
                <l>But now recite the fortune of thy armes; </l>
                <l>No entertainment can be halfe so pleasant. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e105030">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Sir( what soere it be) since you command it, </l>
                <l>Tis fit that I obey: Your rebels slain </l>
                <l>Or taken, and those Darers that oppos'd </l>
                <l>The current of your fortune quite defeated </l>
                <l>To make your name more glorious, I advanc'd </l>
                <l>My Army towards Corduba, which even then </l>
                <l>I had made sure of, if some timely succours </l>
                <l>Had not prevented me. This noble Prince </l>
                <l>Seeing it beleaguerd straitly; by his forces </l>
                <l>Thought to relieve it, but that hope being vain </l>
                <l>He like a wise Commander chang'd his purpose, </l>
                <l>And meant to try no valour but his owne: </l>
                <l>Then by a Herald sent he me a challenge </l>
                <l>Which easily my spirit gave consent to </l>
                <l>I named the place, where when we both were met, </l>
                <l>Many fierce blows were dealt, and sure the heavens </l>
                <l>Look'd pale to see the storms our anger made, </l>
                <l>Shine more in our wilde looks than in their lightning </l>
                <l>Whilst men durst do, that which they durst not see </l>
                <l>Twas equally between us fought, untill </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-012-b"/>
                <l>At length your fortune gave me th'advantage, </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-spheranti" xml:id="ep000353-e105260">
              <speaker>SPHR. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Here, sir, your modesty betrayes your valour, </l>
                <l>I suffered by your strength not my mishap, </l>
                <l>You may vaunt freely what I cann't deny. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e105310">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>This was the blow made Corduba to fall, </l>
                <l>After this Princes yielding their great thoughts </l>
                <l>A bated of their pride, and this fair Princesse </l>
                <l>To whom I owe for her intelligence, </l>
                <l>Made the Town yours almost without resistance, </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-celimant" xml:id="ep000353-e105380">
              <speaker>CEL. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Tis true great King, this woman, Natures monster, </l>
                <l>By her base treachery betray'd my state, </l>
                <l>You have my goods, my scepter and my person; </l>
                <l>But look, sir, who it is that gives them you, </l>
                <l>See from what hand you do receive these presents, </l>
                <l>The same put her brother in these fetters, </l>
                <l>It is my sister, or some Devill rather, </l>
                <l>That took that name upon her to betray me. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-serifa" xml:id="ep000353-e105480">
              <speaker>SER. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Leave to upbraid me thus, that name of sister </l>
                <l>Has bin the greatest stain upon my life: </l>
                <l>But you that stand so on the point of honour </l>
                <l>Was I us'd as a sister by you, rather </l>
                <l>Was I not treated as a slave? the name </l>
                <l>Away, I felt the thing: pray sir, believe not </l>
                <l>That out of any womanish impudence </l>
                <l>I gave th' intelligence I am accused of; </l>
                <l>But when I captiv'd him, I freed my self </l>
                <l>From those more cruell chains, where in his rage </l>
                <l>Shut up my will and free election, </l>
                <l>Designing me the object of my hate: </l>
                <l>Which when I saw, and that this haughty Prince </l>
                <l>Came from his country to my ravishment, </l>
                <l>Arm'd not with fair deserts, but souldiers </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-013-a"/>
                <l>I thought I justly might to his violence </l>
                <l>Oppose my artifice, which was to render </l>
                <l>Unto his enemies his place of refuge, </l>
                <l>Which my designe I kept long in suspence, </l>
                <l>Till this more noble object took my heart, </l>
                <l>And made me perfect my intentions. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e105710">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <l>I without doubt, his false heart does adore her. <stage xml:id="ep000353-e105730">Aside. </stage>
              </l>
              <l>Can I then see my rivall, and yet I live? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e105750">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>When the wit's nimble, and the courage ready, </l>
                <l>A good successe still follows the designe, </l>
                <l>The businesse that halts forward is half lost. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-serifa" xml:id="ep000353-e105800">
              <speaker>SER. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Sir, to neglect the execution, </l>
                <l>My courage, and my love were too important, </l>
                <l>I quickly was resolv'd, when love came in </l>
                <l>To finish up the plot my hate begun, </l>
                <l>This valiant Cid whose fame prevented him </l>
                <l>In my good thoughts, was of my enemy </l>
                <l>Become the object of my best desires; </l>
                <l>His vertue conquered me, and had I not </l>
                <l>Been overcome I had not been so happy: </l>
                <l>For giving up my arms to such a conquest, </l>
                <l>'Steed of my own losse I have got a prize, </l>
                <l>The honour of all souldiers: Roderigo. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e105940">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <l>Alas, what canst thou hope poor Lady now. <stage xml:id="ep000353-e105960">Aside. </stage>
              </l>
              <l>Canst thou doubt yet whether he be engag'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e105980">
              <speaker>RO </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Madam, you put a double tye upon me, </l>
                <l>That having done me a courtesie so happy, </l>
                <l>You adde to it, so much of kinde respect, </l>
                <l>And believe, Madam, that occasion </l>
                <l>Will make me blest, which points out my obedience, </l>
                <l>What may I do to serve you, pray command me. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000353-013-b"/>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e106060">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <l>What has she to desire, she has thy heart? <stage xml:id="ep000353-e106080">Aside. </stage>
              </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-serifa" xml:id="ep000353-e106090">
              <speaker>SER. </speaker>
              <l>Ah sir, you can do all, and Ide have all. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e106110">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>Madam, the King is here sole soveraigne, </l>
              <l>He only can give all. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e106140">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Which thou mayst promise, </l>
                <l>Such is thy merit as does challenge all, </l>
                <l>Freely dispose of my authority, </l>
                <l>And think I have done lesse then thou deserv'st. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-serifa" xml:id="ep000353-e106200">
              <speaker>SER. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>So great a favour, sir, I not desire </l>
                <l>The good I wish (great Cid) is in thy self, </l>
                <l>Which is the object my desires ayme at, </l>
                <l>And that sweet hope, which only makes me live. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e106260">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I know not, Madam, upon what apparence </l>
                <l>You have conceiv'd this hope, I'me sure Roderigo </l>
                <l>Nere spoke to you about it. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e106310">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <l>Oh, how finely! <stage xml:id="ep000353-e106330">Aside. </stage>
              </l>
              <l>He carries it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e106350">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <l>Tis prettily dissembled. <stage xml:id="ep000353-e106370">Aside. </stage>
              </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-serifa" xml:id="ep000353-e106380">
              <speaker>SER. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Have you then, sir, forgot your promises, </l>
                <l>Is this the love, and are these the indearments </l>
                <l>You promis'd to the action I perform'd. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e106430">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>Who gave you that false hope. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-serifa" xml:id="ep000353-e106450">
              <speaker>SER. </speaker>
              <l>Your self. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e106470">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>Who I, </l>
              <l>I doubt it much. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000353-014-a"/>
            <sp who="#ep000353-serifa" xml:id="ep000353-e106500">
              <speaker>SER. </speaker>
              <l>Oh Heavens, do you know </l>
              <l>This Letter? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e106530">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>Yes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-serifa" xml:id="ep000353-e106550">
              <speaker>SER. </speaker>
              <l>Pray read it sir, and there </l>
              <l>You shall perceive the reasons of my hope. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e106580">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>I know well what I owe, and what I promis'd, </l>
              <l>You shall see Madam, I am not ungratefull. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-serifa" xml:id="ep000353-e106610">
              <speaker>SER. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Oh then excuse my anger, my disdain </l>
                <l>Caus'd it, and not my will, I can be calme, </l>
                <l>Having my fear abated by those comforts </l>
                <l>You promis'd to my passion. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e106670">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Your desires, </l>
                <l>Madam, exceed my power, but from me </l>
                <l>Expect all duty, and all courtesie </l>
                <l>That you could hope for, from a Gentleman, </l>
                <l>Or I know how to give. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-serifa" xml:id="ep000353-e106740">
              <speaker>SER. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>How faithlesse man? </l>
                <l>Do you fall back unto your first discourse? </l>
                <l>Thou paper which betraydst my heart at first </l>
                <l>Discover to his infamy thy secrets, </l>
                <l>And shew his breach of faith. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e106810">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Let it be read </l>
                <l>Ile nere oppose it, and I sweare t'observe </l>
                <l>What ever that enjoyns. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e106860">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>The thing you offer </l>
                <l>Seems reasonable, thou art just Roderigo </l>
                <l>By it we shall perceive your interest. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000353-014-b"/>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e106910">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, if you please, I will be judg'd by it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-serifa" xml:id="ep000353-e106930">
              <speaker>SER. </speaker>
              <l>And so will I. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e106950">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>Then I shall do you justice. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e106970">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <l>Here must I stand with patience to heare <stage xml:id="ep000353-e106990">Aside. </stage>
              </l>
              <l>The sentence of my punishment. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e107010">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <l>From this, <stage xml:id="ep000353-e107030">Aside. </stage>
              </l>
              <l>I must expect either to live or die. </l>
            </sp>
            <floatingText type="letter">
              <body>
                <head>Seriffa reads the Letter. </head>
                <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM, </salute>
                </opener>
                <p>IF your brother have so little sence both of his own bloud and your beautie, that he had rather please himselfe in your afflictions, then his own duty, let mee entreat you to make good that bravery of Spirit which you mentioned to mee in your Letters; which is to leave him to his crueltie, letting him first know that you were sensible of it, by the revenge you take. And then enter into the Victors Campe, where you shall make your owne conditions, and <pb xml:id="ep000353-015-a"/>finde an entertainment to your content by </p>
                <closer>
                  <signed>Your most humble servant, RODERIGO. </signed>
                </closer>
              </body>
            </floatingText>
            <lg>
              <l>You understand the sence, sir, of these words, </l>
              <l>These are not terms that should make void a promise </l>
              <l>Am not I that Seriffa; you the victor, </l>
              <l>Did not I give you entrance into Corduba, </l>
              <l>And my own heart at once, and will you now </l>
              <l>Bereave me of the hope your self has rais'd </l>
              <l>Is this the great content you promis'd me: </l>
            </lg>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e107200">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What ist you can complain of Madam? who </l>
                <l>Durst be so insolent to do you hurt? </l>
                <l>Are you not heer in covert of that storm </l>
                <l>Which your fierce brother mean should overtake you? </l>
                <l>What could you hope more then this noble usage </l>
                <l>Did you suppose your eyes could conquer me, </l>
                <l>Alas, I am anothers; and when ere </l>
                <l>I change that object, I must think my self </l>
                <l>Led into blindnesse, and mistake of beauty. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-serifa" xml:id="ep000353-e107310">
              <speaker>SER. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Oh do not change, but end my misery, </l>
                <l>Let my bloud quite deface this character, </l>
                <l>As it looks black already with thy crime, </l>
                <l>So let it blush to punish me for mine, </l>
                <l>Why stay'st thou? satisfie thy hate in me, </l>
                <l>Teare from my brest my love and heart together. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-celimant" xml:id="ep000353-e107390">
              <speaker>CEL. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>How am I ravish'd with this sweet revenge, </l>
                <l>What pleasure tis to see thee in this case </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-015-b"/>
                <l>Where thy best hope is to sit down with nothing, </l>
                <l>Now Lady you may triumph, though you weare not </l>
                <l>These fetters, you're no lesse a slave then I. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-serifa" xml:id="ep000353-e107460">
              <speaker>SER. </speaker>
              <l>What villain? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e107480">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Fie, Madam, calme your anger. </l>
                <l>In the word of a King to both of you </l>
                <l>I promise a fair treatment, I am one </l>
                <l>That know to use a victory. Take you care </l>
                <l>That in their severall lodgings they want nothing </l>
                <l>That their state may requires how ere they be </l>
                <l>My prisoners, I'le not bate their due respect </l>
                <l>Go Roderigo home unto thy father, </l>
                <l>I know he longs to see thee. </l>
                <l>
                  <stage xml:id="ep000353-e107600">Exeunt omnes praeter Cimena, Infanta, Roderigo. </stage>
                </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e107610">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I obay, </l>
                <l>Pray, Madam, give me leave to do the duty </l>
                <l>I owe unto Cimena. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e107660">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>To me sir? </l>
                <l>Pray spare the labour, for you owe me none. </l>
                <l>Besides Seriffa, being vext already </l>
                <l>Has too much reason to complain of you, </l>
                <l>Though you commited not this last offence. </l>
                <l>
                  <stage xml:id="ep000353-e107740">She makes a courtsie, and goes out. </stage>
                </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e107750">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>What may the reason be she quits me so? </l>
              <l>What crime have I committed? whats my fault? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e107780">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I know not, but you see her cruelty, </l>
                <l>And what a little makes her to fly off; </l>
                <l>Perhaps y'are pleas'd well with your punishment, </l>
                <l>Thou shouldst shew more of courage Roderigo </l>
                <l>And let her see that he who comes home victor </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-016-a"/>
                <l>Should receive better welcome; she is( me thinks) </l>
                <l>Some what too full of vanity. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e107870">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ah, Madam, </l>
                <l>I must not murmur though she be ungratefull, </l>
                <l>She is Cimena, and I cannot hate her. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e107920">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <l>But this thy too much goodnesse will betray thee, </l>
              <l>Thou mak'st thy constancie unhappy to thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e107950">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>Madam, you know where tis my duty calls me, </l>
              <l>Pray give me leave to wait upon my father. <stage xml:id="ep000353-e107980">Exit. </stage>
              </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e107990">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Go; this was a pretext I know to leave mee, </l>
                <l>But I shall be reveng'd of this neglect </l>
                <l>When against all thy hopes of future joy </l>
                <l>The rigor of Cimena I employ. <stage xml:id="ep000353-e108050">Exit. </stage>
                </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="ep000353-e108060">
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e108070">
            <head>Act III. Scene I. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e108080">RODERIGO from CIMENA'S Lodging. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e108090">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Hence-forth Cimena live for euer quiet, </l>
                <l>Roderigo shall no more be so unhappy </l>
                <l>As to disturbe your peace, since you deny him </l>
                <l>The sight of you he is content to suffer, </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-016-b"/>
                <l>Not only want of that but all things else </l>
                <l>You being all to him, that he desir'd: </l>
                <l>Good heaven was there ever so much rigour </l>
                <l>Practiz'd on any as on wretched me? </l>
                <l>Did I hope any other recompence </l>
                <l>Of all my services, my labours, watchings, </l>
                <l>To bring home victory? but that she should </l>
                <l>Crown um with her acceptance; and must I </l>
                <l>(Courted by all else) be by her despis'd </l>
                <l>Into whose arms I look'd to have bin receiv'd? </l>
                <l>Nor is her anger more apparant then </l>
                <l>The cause of it conceal'd, I am not worthy </l>
                <l>To know the reason of my banishment. </l>
                <l>Therefore farewell for ever cruell Mistris, </l>
                <l>Ile seek some place unhabited by women, </l>
                <l>Where I may never see such shining eyes, </l>
                <l>As only light us to our miseries. <stage xml:id="ep000353-e108320">Exit. </stage>
                </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e108330">
            <head>SCENE II. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e108340">KING, th'INFANTA, SERIFFA, DON SANCHO, DON DIEGO. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e108350">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>BUt, Madam, spare Roderigos innocence, </l>
                <l>His vertues, and your worth are both too great </l>
                <l>To suffer such a stain. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000353-017-a"/>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e108400">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Think of it Madam, </l>
                <l>And call not him a traitour, but your heart </l>
                <l>Which entertain'd a love that was not sent </l>
                <l>You were too credulous, not he perfidious, </l>
                <l>What you desir'd you were willing to believe, </l>
                <l>And knowing the command of your own beauty </l>
                <l>With the advantage of your birth and fortune, </l>
                <l>I cannot blame you if you thought that love </l>
                <l>Which was but civill application: </l>
                <l>But now you have found your errour, let your courage </l>
                <l>Finde scorn for him that has not love for you. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-serifa" xml:id="ep000353-e108530">
              <speaker>SER. </speaker>
              <l>How easily the whole Counsail the sick, <stage xml:id="ep000353-e108550">Aside. </stage>
              </l>
              <l>And yet they have not hit my true disease. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e108570">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>My sister Madam, tels you right, desires </l>
                <l>That are not honorable ought to be short, </l>
                <l>Your quality which your beauty only equals, </l>
                <l>Invites a higher match then Roderigo. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-serifa" xml:id="ep000353-e108630">
              <speaker>SER. </speaker>
              <l>A conquerour is next unto a King, </l>
              <l>Since hees deny'd me, how can my hopes look higher? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e108660">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Don Sancho wait the Princesse to her lodgings, </l>
                <l>And see that she command my Court as freely </l>
                <l>As I my self. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e108710">
              <speaker>SAN. </speaker>
              <l>Your Graces humble creature. <stage xml:id="ep000353-e108730">Exit. </stage>
              </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e108740">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>Don Diego, is the Cid contented with </l>
              <l>The offer which I make him of my sister? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-diego" xml:id="ep000353-e108770">
              <speaker>D. DIE. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You are the King sir; he your humble vassall, </l>
                <l>He could not be my sonne if disobedient </l>
                <l>To you that are his master, and I finde </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-017-b"/>
                <l>His inclination ready only feare </l>
                <l>And modesty keeps in his strong desires. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e108840">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>Tis not his feare but Mistris which restrains him. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-diego" xml:id="ep000353-e108860">
              <speaker>D. DIE. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>He will forget her sooner then his duty </l>
                <l>Of which the Count can give you the best proof, </l>
                <l>For though at that time he ador'd Cimena, </l>
                <l>Yet ventur'd he to lose her for my sake </l>
                <l>(His honour and his duty so commanding) </l>
                <l>He can love well tis true, but obay better. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e108940">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I never doubled his obedience </l>
                <l>Of which his excellent vertue does assure me: </l>
                <l>Ide have (you sister) to accept the Courtship </l>
                <l>Which he shall make to you, and if you aske </l>
                <l>A reason why, know I will have it so; </l>
                <l>Though fortune have not blest him with a Crown, </l>
                <l>And though his greatnesse be within himself, </l>
                <l>Yet there propitious heaven has shew'd its power, </l>
                <l>Heaping its richest treasures on his person, </l>
                <l>Hi heart is valours proper spheare, his soule </l>
                <l>The throne of vertue where she sits and governs </l>
                <l>Directing all his actions to honour; </l>
                <l>These rare perfections must be the objects </l>
                <l>Sister, of your desires. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e109100">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Such a command </l>
                <l>Makes my obedience ready to love vertue, </l>
                <l>When you that are my King requires it of me </l>
                <l>I not to give consent to hard conditions, </l>
                <l>Tis your part to command, mine to obay. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e109170">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Tis well, it only rest now that Cimena </l>
                <l>Comply with my desires I will no longer </l>
                <l>Burn to so little purpose, my affection </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-018-a"/>
                <l>Hastes to its end, there can be no content </l>
                <l>T' approach a fire that will consume, not cherish, </l>
                <l>I am resolv'd to have her, as for love </l>
                <l>Which to the Cid she promis'd, I have power </l>
                <l>T' absolve her of it; Princes render lawfull </l>
                <l>What ever pleases them: respects become </l>
                <l>The people, not a King: send for her sister </l>
                <l>And tell her I would see her in your lodgings, </l>
                <l>To treat of somthing that concerns her neerly, </l>
                <l>Tis wearisome to live thus in desire, </l>
                <l>This day enjoying her, Ile quench my fire. <stage xml:id="ep000353-e109330">Exit. </stage>
                </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e109340">
            <head>SCENE III. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e109350">SERIFFA, DON SANCHO. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e109360">
              <speaker>D. SAN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>BEauty is loves object, Madam and twere hard </l>
                <l>T'approach such flames and keep a frozen heart, </l>
                <l>Dull fouls have eyes lent 'em to see their way, </l>
                <l>But men of courage to behold what's faire. </l>
                <l>Pardon divinest Lady if my spirit </l>
                <l>Made me to love where I should have ador'd </l>
                <l>And though you do estrange me from your heart </l>
                <l>Envy me not the glory of my sufferings. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-serifa" xml:id="ep000353-e109460">
              <speaker>SER. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Don Sancho cannot be so young a Courtier </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-018-b"/>
                <l>To think that any Lady can despise </l>
                <l>A noble love bounded with due respects, </l>
                <l>We have no other witnesse of our beauty </l>
                <l>And heaven defend that we should hate our lovers. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e109530">
              <speaker>D. SAN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Accept my vowes then, Madam, with the temper </l>
                <l>Of one that seem'd to love; and let my service </l>
                <l>Be entertain'd at least with faire acceptance. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-serifa" xml:id="ep000353-e109580">
              <speaker>SER. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>How can I do that without injury </l>
                <l>Either to you or my own modesty? </l>
                <l>To cherish you in what you cannot have </l>
                <l>Were to augment your punishment: to give </l>
                <l>A heart which is not mine, in me were falshood, </l>
                <l>And no lesse wrong to you should you receive it </l>
                <l>Then to its proper owner. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e109670">
              <speaker>D. SAN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>But he seems </l>
                <l>(As one that does not know his happinesse) </l>
                <l>To be insensible of what your goodnesse </l>
                <l>Has offerd him: why should you cast away </l>
                <l>That whereof Kings would be ambitious? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-serifa" xml:id="ep000353-e109740">
              <speaker>SER. </speaker>
              <l>Ay me! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e109760">
              <speaker>D. SAN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>That sigh the greatest Monarch scarce deserves </l>
                <l>Much lesse, a subject, thrust him from your thoughts </l>
                <l>And let some nobler love take up his room. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-serifa" xml:id="ep000353-e109810">
              <speaker>SER. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Take heed Don Sancho, you begin to forfeit </l>
                <l>Your first pretentions, I must not think, </l>
                <l>You can love one whom you believe to have </l>
                <l>The easie power to dislodge a love </l>
                <l>Which she had once receiv'd, but hence-forth know </l>
                <l>My flame runs up into a point so small </l>
                <l>As cannot be divided into parts. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000353-019-a"/>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e109900">
              <speaker>D. SAN. </speaker>
              <l>Not though there be division of your hearts </l>
              <l>The Cid I shame to say't, neglects you Madam: </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-serifa" xml:id="ep000353-e109930">
              <speaker>SER. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>If he did not I were more miserable </l>
                <l>This now seems strange to you, but when I shall </l>
                <l>Relate that to you which in part concerns you, </l>
                <l>As you are Favourite to the King your Master, </l>
                <l>And one that should advise him to be just, </l>
                <l>You will perceive, that what I utterd of </l>
                <l>Love to the Cid was to secure my self. </l>
                <l>But heres my brother, lets withdraw a little. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e110030">
            <head>SCENE IV. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e110040">SPHERANTI, CELIMANT. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000353-spheranti" xml:id="ep000353-e110050">
              <speaker>SPHE. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>IS not this fight enough deare Celimant, </l>
                <l>To choak that fire up within my brest </l>
                <l>Which I too long have nourish'd to my ruine </l>
                <l>For an ungratefull, and perfidious woman, </l>
                <l>Was it too little to disdain a Prince, </l>
                <l>And run into the hands of one she knew not </l>
                <l>Unlesse having quitted him, for whom his worth </l>
                <l>And valour pleaded she become the prey </l>
                <l>Of a y that will-seize her, see Don Sancho </l>
                <l>Has made her his already, and shall I </l>
                <l>Love where I am so rivall'd, no my heart </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-019-b"/>
                <l>If thou must be a captive, let thy fetters </l>
                <l>Be such as need not shame the wearer. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-celimant" xml:id="ep000353-e110200">
              <speaker>CEL. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Friend, </l>
                <l>Which name I rather chuse to call you by </l>
                <l>Then brother, (since you cannot be her husband </l>
                <l>With safety of your honour) could you think </l>
                <l>That she can spare her modesty, whose falshood </l>
                <l>Spar'd not her brother, and her Country too, </l>
                <l>No sir, believe, she that is base her self </l>
                <l>Cannot love vertue in an other person: </l>
                <l>For how should she love that she never knew; </l>
                <l>Heer then put out your flame, and think Spheranti </l>
                <l>That this conformity of our lives and fortune </l>
                <l>Which makes me share in all your passions </l>
                <l>May link our hearts so fast we shall not need </l>
                <l>Such an alliance to confirme the knot. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-spheranti" xml:id="ep000353-e110360">
              <speaker>SP. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>J know not friend whether I be more happy </l>
                <l>In losing of my love, then in the finding </l>
                <l>Th'assurance of thy friendship; now let fortune </l>
                <l>Look well or ill upon me in thy love </l>
                <l>Ile summe up all my blisse, nor can I think </l>
                <l>Brave Celimant, will professe lesse to me. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-celimant" xml:id="ep000353-e110440">
              <speaker>CEL. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Which to confirme, no ceremonious oath </l>
                <l>The band of doubtfull, and inconstant souls </l>
                <l>Shall I now take; thee friendship, I invoke, </l>
                <l>When I do leave this Prince, let me be left </l>
                <l>Without a friend, I and without a name. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-spheranti" xml:id="ep000353-e110510">
              <speaker>SP. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>J know my father at this time endevours </l>
                <l>My liberty, (if at least I can call </l>
                <l>This thraldom, where I am so well receiv'd) </l>
                <l>But I'me resolv'd to run your course of fortune, </l>
                <l>My freedom joyn'd with yours is welcome to me </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-020-a"/>
                <l>Else a worse torment then that bondage was </l>
                <l>Your sisters rigour did impose. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-celimant" xml:id="ep000353-e110600">
              <speaker>CEL. </speaker>
              <l>No more </l>
              <l>Deare friend of her; come, come forget her name. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-spheranti" xml:id="ep000353-e110630">
              <speaker>SP. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Since she could be so thanklesse to disdain, </l>
                <l>The man that quit his liberty for her, </l>
                <l>Which when the Cid did offer, I refus'd </l>
                <l>To follow her, who follow all men else </l>
                <l>And that her crime has merited my hate </l>
                <l>I have shook off that chain; but finde my self </l>
                <l>Caught in another which thou dost not know </l>
                <l>Tis such as makes me feare my liberty </l>
                <l>I cannot go from hence, and think I'me free. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-celimant" xml:id="ep000353-e110740">
              <speaker>CEL. </speaker>
              <l>You are in love it seems. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-spheranti" xml:id="ep000353-e110760">
              <speaker>SP. </speaker>
              <l>Yes Celimant. </l>
              <l>I am in love, and as much in despaire. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-celimant" xml:id="ep000353-e110790">
              <speaker>CEL. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Is there a beauty can oppose your Courtship, </l>
                <l>What quality is higher then your own? </l>
                <l>Why should you then despaire? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-unassigned" xml:id="ep000353-e110840">
              <speaker>S. P. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I but the horrour </l>
                <l>Of being vanquish'd makes me think my self </l>
                <l>Unworthy to look up to such a height. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-celimant" xml:id="ep000353-e110890">
              <speaker>CEL. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Consider that your fortune was to yield </l>
                <l>His to orecome, yet did you long dispute it </l>
                <l>And bravely too; what can you feare Spheranti? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-spheranti" xml:id="ep000353-e110940">
              <speaker>SP. </speaker>
              <l>To be too rash. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-celimant" xml:id="ep000353-e110960">
              <speaker>CEL. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>To be too rash, let hope </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-020-b"/>
                <l>Remove those thoughts, and you will not displease her, </l>
                <l>A vertuous love was never odious. </l>
                <l>But tell me sir, what name has this your Mistris, </l>
                <l>Honour my freedome with this trust. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-spheranti" xml:id="ep000353-e111030">
              <speaker>SP. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Th' Infanta, </l>
                <l>Deere Celimant has snatcht my heart, and though </l>
                <l>My eyes were caught in their first motion to her, </l>
                <l>Yet durst I not discover it till now; </l>
                <l>But such force has my flame, it will not be </l>
                <l>Contain'd within the limits of my heart </l>
                <l>But must break out to thee and suddainly </l>
                <l>To her, which if displeasing is my death. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-celimant" xml:id="ep000353-e111130">
              <speaker>CEL. </speaker>
              <l>Hope better sir, I am your caution </l>
              <l>She shall receive the offer of your vowes. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e111160">
            <head>SCENE V. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e111170">Enter DON ARIAS. </stage>
            <l>BUt here's Don Arias. </l>
            <sp who="#ep000353-arias" xml:id="ep000353-e111190">
              <speaker>D. ARI. </speaker>
              <l>The King sir askes for you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-celimant" xml:id="ep000353-e111210">
              <speaker>CEL. </speaker>
              <l>Ile wait him sir. <stage xml:id="ep000353-e111230">Exeunt. </stage>
              </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-spheranti" xml:id="ep000353-e111240">
              <speaker>SP. </speaker>
              <l>Tis strange he should be sent for and not I. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="6" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e111260">
            <pb xml:id="ep000353-021-a"/>
            <head>SCENE VI. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e111270">Enter INFANTA. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e111280">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <l>WHat, all alone? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-spheranti" xml:id="ep000353-e111300">
              <speaker>SP. </speaker>
              <l>I Madam, Celimant, </l>
              <l>Is sent for to the King. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e111330">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Oh, I know why </l>
                <l>His liberty is now in proposition, </l>
                <l>And yours too shortly, if you desire it. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-spheranti" xml:id="ep000353-e111380">
              <speaker>SP. </speaker>
              <l>That Madam, is the least part of my care </l>
              <l>J am so farre from wishing it, I feare it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e111410">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <l>This is a Courtship sir, I understand not </l>
              <l>Were not Toledo better than Sivill to you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-spheranti" xml:id="ep000353-e111440">
              <speaker>SP. </speaker>
              <l>Madam, th' effect will make you see it is not. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e111460">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <l>Well, we shall hope to see it then; adiew. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-spheranti" xml:id="ep000353-e111480">
              <speaker>SP. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>My duty, Madam, will not give me leave </l>
                <l>To let you go alone, do not deny me </l>
                <l>The honour to wait on you. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="7" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e111530">
            <pb xml:id="ep000353-021-b"/>
            <head>SCENE VII. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e111540">CIMENA. Page. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e111550">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <l>WHat said Roderigo, boy? when he departed. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-page" xml:id="ep000353-e111570">
              <speaker>PAGE. </speaker>
              <l>Nothing, but in his looks one might discover, </l>
              <l>Amazement joyn'd with grief to be excluded. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e111600">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Excluded, whence? not from my heart I'me sure </l>
                <l>There he makes good the place he ever had, </l>
                <l>Were it a easie to remove him thence </l>
                <l>As from my presence, I should feare no rivall, </l>
                <l>Take your Lute boy, and sing the song I gave you, </l>
                <l>It sutes my present state. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-boy" xml:id="ep000353-e111680">
              <speaker>The Boy sings. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'TWas not his person nor his parts, </l>
                <l>Though nere so fam'd that wonne me, </l>
                <l>He lov'd, he said, which I believ'd; </l>
                <l>And that faith has undone me. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-022-a"/>
                <l>His vertues were alike to all, </l>
                <l>Nor were they more to me, </l>
                <l>I honor'd them, but lov'd the man, </l>
                <l>Because that he was he. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Who since he has his love forgon, </l>
                <l>And is himself no more: </l>
                <l>I love him not as he is now, </l>
                <l>But as he was before. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e111840">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Tis true I must still love him, the remembrance </l>
                <l>That I was once Roderigo's only object, </l>
                <l>Is that I cherish now. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="7" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e111890">
            <head>SCENE VIII. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e111900">DON. ARIAS. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000353-arias" xml:id="ep000353-e111910">
              <speaker>D. ARI. </speaker>
              <l>MAdam, the King </l>
              <l>Stayes for you to come to him. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e111940">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <l>The King! where? </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000353-022-b"/>
              <l>Why would he speake with me? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-arias" xml:id="ep000353-e111970">
              <speaker>D. ARI. </speaker>
              <l>J cannot tell, </l>
              <l>But he expects you on the Infantas side. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e112000">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Tell him I come, I know what he would have </l>
                <l>But all his power shall not shake my firmenesse, </l>
                <l>In vain he tryes to winne me by his greatnesse. </l>
                <l>What is a throne to me that seek a grave? </l>
                <l>Ime sure he has no power ore my will, </l>
                <l>He that first took my heart shall keep it still. Exeunt. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="ep000353-e112080">
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e112090">
            <head>Act IV. Scene I. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e112100">SPHERANTI, INFANTA. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000353-spheranti" xml:id="ep000353-e112110">
              <speaker>SP. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>MAdam, tis true, I may have bin too rash </l>
                <l>To offer you a heart unworthy of you </l>
                <l>But yet my fault is such as cannot give </l>
                <l>Consent to any low thoughts of repentance; </l>
                <l>And if my service find no other grace, </l>
                <l>Let me have leave to cherish my attempt, </l>
                <l>And let me love my self for loving you, </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-023-a"/>
                <l>Then if you shall deny your presence to me, </l>
                <l>My soule may do the office of mine eyes </l>
                <l>Which may contemplate what these cannot see, </l>
                <l>And if my love cannot appeare from thence, </l>
                <l>From this you shall perceive my obedience. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e112250">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Though I am better read in my own faults, </l>
                <l>Then to believe I could charm any man; </l>
                <l>Yet for your sake, because you'le have it so. </l>
                <l>J am content to think you love me sir, </l>
                <l>And I am sensible of what I owe you, </l>
                <l>But you must know that I depend upon </l>
                <l>A brother to whose will I am confin'de, </l>
                <l>So that I am not Mistris of my heart, </l>
                <l>Nor dare I hazard it without his leave, </l>
                <l>Therefore to warrant your pretensions </l>
                <l>Make your addresse to him, till then I dare not </l>
                <l>Be known to entertain you for a suitor. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-spheranti" xml:id="ep000353-e112390">
              <speaker>SPH. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Tis fit I be obedient to this law </l>
                <l>Which is most reasonable, but may I be </l>
                <l>As sure of your favour, as his leave. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e112440">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Your vertue, sir, will be your best assurance, </l>
                <l>My love proceeds not freely, but deserts </l>
                <l>Must challenge it. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-spheranti" xml:id="ep000353-e112490">
              <speaker>SP. </speaker>
              <l>Kissing your faire hands, Madam, </l>
              <l>J go to make my way to blisse or ruine. <stage xml:id="ep000353-e112520">Exit. </stage>
              </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e112530">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What shall I do, my heart, this Prince is lovely, </l>
                <l>So is the Cid, but he lesse tractable, </l>
                <l>Spheranti is more soft and courteous, </l>
                <l>And yet not of lesse spirit then the other, </l>
                <l>Let Roderigo then endeare his Mistris, </l>
                <l>And since that love is th' only price of love, </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-023-b"/>
                <l>Let him that offers his, have his reward. </l>
                <l>Alas, what did I say? how can I leave </l>
                <l>That object, which rules all within my heart? </l>
                <l>Roderigo's free possessor there, and yet </l>
                <l>Me thinks, there is a room left for Spheranti. </l>
                <l>What shall I do then in this labyrinth? </l>
                <l>Shall I to oblige Cimena, quit the Cid. </l>
                <l>No Ile not leave him, but with patience wait </l>
                <l>The pleasure of my brother and my fate. <stage xml:id="ep000353-e112700">Exit. </stage>
                </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e112710">
            <head>SCENE II. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e112720">KING, CELIMANT, DON ARIAS. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e112730">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>DOn Sancho, sir, and Arias do wait you </l>
                <l>With the conditions of your liberty, </l>
                <l>They are but gentle ones, that you forgive </l>
                <l>Your sister, in the recompence of which </l>
                <l>Your ransome is remitted. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-celimant" xml:id="ep000353-e112800">
              <speaker>CEL. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Greatest Monarch, </l>
                <l>Who may dispose my life, you know that here, </l>
                <l>I am no lesse without a will then power </l>
                <l>I must obay, what ever you impose, </l>
                <l>But yet her crime joyn'd with the insolence </l>
                <l>In facing it is such, that giving me </l>
                <l>My Kingdome back with her, is worse to me </l>
                <l>Then to live here your captive, with what pleasure </l>
                <l>Can I behold that power re-deliver'd </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-024-a"/>
                <l>Which with my enemies I must receive. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e112920">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ile quit you of that feare, in taking care </l>
                <l>To keep Seriffa in the terms of duty </l>
                <l>You shall command her wholy, but at present </l>
                <l>Till you be better satisfied, her fight </l>
                <l>Shall not offend you, since her love has caus'd </l>
                <l>The treason which you blame her for, I mean </l>
                <l>To keep her fast in fetters, untill love </l>
                <l>And Hymen be the executioners </l>
                <l>Of the sweet sentence which I will pronounce. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-celimant" xml:id="ep000353-e113030">
              <speaker>CEL. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Such is her want of worth, the Prince you meant </l>
                <l>To Joyne her to, despises her, and truly </l>
                <l>I should believe him to be worth my pity, </l>
                <l>Of whom so base an object were consider'd. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e113090">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Sir, your too quick resentment makes you speak so, </l>
                <l>But leave that care to me, there is a Lord </l>
                <l>Within my Court, of birth as great as any, </l>
                <l>But vertue much beyond his quality, </l>
                <l>Which does a done your sister, though it be true </l>
                <l>That he has mingled with his love some boldnesse, </l>
                <l>Since he can't plead any descent from Kings, </l>
                <l>Yet if our spirit bids us despaire nothing, </l>
                <l>This noble Lover must obtain his wishes, </l>
                <l>In a word tis Don Sancho that I mean. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-celimant" xml:id="ep000353-e113210">
              <speaker>CEL. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Sir, I beseech you think how great the distance </l>
                <l>Is between their conditions; Don Sancho </l>
                <l>Has much worth in him, but he is no Prince, </l>
                <l>And though Seriffa has disgrac'd her birth, </l>
                <l>She's nere the lesse discended from a King. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e113280">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Don Sancho, sir, is all you can desire </l>
                <l>Being my Favourite, I will advance </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-024-b"/>
                <l>His fortune to that height as shall deserve, </l>
                <l>Seriffa's and your love: but did you know </l>
                <l>How much he has employ'd his favour with me </l>
                <l>For your advantage, you would recompence </l>
                <l>His care with this alliance, but if all </l>
                <l>That he has done, cann't make you flexible, </l>
                <l>Yet heare me that am King, and do conjure you </l>
                <l>To love your sister, and confirme this match, </l>
                <l>A Kings entreaties must have no deniall. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-celimant" xml:id="ep000353-e113410">
              <speaker>CEL. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Sir, I am yours, and since this marriage </l>
                <l>Is welcome to your thoughts: Don Sancho may </l>
                <l>In Celimant meet a brother, and Seriffa </l>
                <l>Being look'd on by me, through you and him, </l>
                <l>Shall see I can forget what she has done. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e113480">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Now you oblige me, and this clemencie </l>
                <l>Shews whence you are descended: how I love </l>
                <l>This sweetnesse in you, trust me your sister </l>
                <l>(Now I may tell you so) will well deserve </l>
                <l>This favour of you; such a beautie, sir, </l>
                <l>Ought not to dwell clouded in your dislikes: </l>
                <l>But you are for your businesse: Arias, </l>
                <l>See he finde no delay, and call Roderigo </l>
                <l>My sister too; I know they are without, </l>
                <l>So good successe when I speak for another </l>
                <l>Makes me hope all things in my own behalf: </l>
                <l>But I must change my countenance: Roderigo. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e113620">
            <pb xml:id="ep000353-025-a"/>
            <head>SCENE III. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e113630">The KING, RODERIGO, INFANTA. </stage>
            <lg>
              <l>ALL Spain from thy brave hand has felt that peace </l>
              <l>And quiet, which thy Prince cannot obtain, </l>
              <l>This work is wanting to fill up thy glory, </l>
              <l>Therefore to make thy victory more perfect, </l>
              <l>For my sake undertake this enemy, </l>
              <l>That would cut from thy valor half thy conquest. </l>
            </lg>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e113710">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>How sir? dares any, who may be so blest </l>
                <l>As to live under your just laws, shake off </l>
                <l>Their due obedience? what vain insolence </l>
                <l>Dares lift it self against so sweet a power: </l>
                <l>Name him sir, to me, that I may destroy him. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e113780">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>There's none can do't Roderigo. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e113800">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>None sir, Why? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e113820">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Tis love that little tyrant which rules all, </l>
                <l>The enemy which makes this warre upon me, </l>
                <l>Regards not majesty, but as a victor </l>
                <l>Triumphs already in my captiv'd heart, </l>
                <l>Which has consented to its own defeat </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-025-b"/>
                <l>So much that I am on the brink of ruine, </l>
                <l>If Roderigo's hand sustain me not. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e113910">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>If your ease sir, depend upon my service, </l>
                <l>You may be sure of my readinesse, </l>
                <l>Only sir, let me know what you desire? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e113960">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>Oh, Roderigo! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e113980">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Why do you sigh, sir? </l>
                <l>Ist that you doubt of my obedience? </l>
                <l>Or that my power is lesse then your desires. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e114030">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>By no means Roderigo, but I feare </l>
                <l>Lest some ill fortune, stead of putting me </l>
                <l>Into the haven, cast me further from't, </l>
                <l>And lest the difficulty should change thy courage, </l>
                <l>And leave me to my self in this fierce storm. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e114100">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>My courage is exempted from such feare. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e114120">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I'me well assur'd of thy faith and valour, </l>
                <l>And yet in this I feare, because thou must </l>
                <l>Combat thy self, subdue thy own desires, </l>
                <l>Conquer thy own deare passions to make </l>
                <l>Thy self a sacrifice to my affections. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e114190">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>Your Majesty may dispose then of my life. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e114210">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Tis not my purpose, nor for all Castile </l>
                <l>Shall it be said that I wish'd any good </l>
                <l>Which must be purchast at so deare a rate. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e114260">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>What can I do then for you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e114280">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Thou mayst put </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-026-a"/>
                <l>An end to all my pain in quitting of </l>
                <l>Cimena: do not start, they are her charms </l>
                <l>By which I'me caught and suffer, nor can I </l>
                <l>Believe though now she slight my offerd love </l>
                <l>Any thing else withholds her, but the thought </l>
                <l>Of being thine. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e114370">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Oh sir, assure your selfe, </l>
                <l>If that be all, and that your Majestie </l>
                <l>Vouchsafe to cast your eyes upon this beautie, </l>
                <l>I shall not be so rash to hope that good, </l>
                <l>Which has the honour to please you my Prince. </l>
                <l>In this sir, you may free me from suspect, </l>
                <l>My love is (much indeed) more my respect, </l>
                <l>And howsoere my heart be link'd to hers, </l>
                <l>J owe more to my Master then my Mistris. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e114480">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Oh royall soule, and truly generous, </l>
                <l>Great Cid, this instant thou hast made me happie: </l>
                <l>Now I am King indeed, for what thou giv'st me, </l>
                <l>I prize above the value of a Crown, </l>
                <l>In liew of which I mean to give thee one, </l>
                <l>Behold th' Infanta, whom I freely offer: </l>
                <l>Tis fit, the state, which owes all to thy valour, </l>
                <l>Should make thee a great sharer in her fortune. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e114580">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Every thing smiles upon me, blest effects <stage xml:id="ep000353-e114610">Aside </stage>
                </l>
                <l>O're take my wishes, what could I hope more? </l>
                <l>Love is made for me to my hand, Cimena </l>
                <l>Ingag'd, to which Roderigo gives consent. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e114650">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>Thou dost not answer me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e114670">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Excuse me sir, </l>
                <l>I am your subject, and you are my King, </l>
                <l>Tis not a Kingdome, which I wish or hope for </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-026-b"/>
                <l>To serve you is the honour I aspire to, </l>
                <l>Obaying you, I learn how to command, </l>
                <l>And since But see Cimena. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e114750">
            <head>SCENE IV. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e114760">CIMENA. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e114770">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>OH, Madam, </l>
                <l>The date now of your crueltie is out, </l>
                <l>Your coldnesse, and your hate no more in season </l>
                <l>Roderigo for my sake has quitted you, </l>
                <l>And if he had an interest in your person, </l>
                <l>He has now put me in full possession of it. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e114850">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Sir, Roderigo's free and may renounce me, </l>
                <l>I have no scepters to bestow upon him, </l>
                <l>But yet I think my birth is not so mean, </l>
                <l>As to live under his command; A slave </l>
                <l>I am not yet, and my affections </l>
                <l>Are not to be inclin'd and rule by his, </l>
                <l>Since greatnesse is the thing, not love he aymes at, </l>
                <l>Let him have his desires, I shan't be jealous </l>
                <l>Though love do wound him with more pleasing darts </l>
                <l>So that the tyrant which shall end his sufferings, </l>
                <l>Do not put me on new, nor that his great </l>
                <l>Felicitie be purchast at the rate </l>
                <l>Of my lost honour, or my libertie. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000353-027-a"/>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e115000">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Madam, think better of the man which loves you, </l>
                <l>To get you happinesse I quit mine own: </l>
                <l>And to obtain the sovereigne power for you, </l>
                <l>I make my affection stoop unto my duty, </l>
                <l>If when I see a Crown is offered you, </l>
                <l>I should come in, to crosse your better fortune, </l>
                <l>I must believe my love did then betray you, </l>
                <l>And had relation to my self not you. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e115100">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>This Roderigo were a faire pretext, </l>
                <l>If both our thoughts were levell'd at one height, </l>
                <l>But let not any right that I can plead </l>
                <l>Divert your deare ambition, mount upon </l>
                <l>A throne, and taste its sweetnesse, as for me </l>
                <l>I am so farre from blaming this your change, </l>
                <l>You cannot finde more pleasure then I praise, </l>
                <l>T'applaud your act; you see sir, I submit </l>
                <l>To the same laws your self has made. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e115210">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Oh, heavens! <stage xml:id="ep000353-e115240">Aside. </stage>
                </l>
                <l>How am I faln from all my hopes at once, </l>
                <l>He is Roderigo still, and she Cimena. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e115270">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You are resolv'd then Madam, to continue </l>
                <l>In the same cruelty? my love I see </l>
                <l>Is uselesse, and my vowes superfluous: </l>
                <l>Yet think I am a King, and can command. </l>
                <l>What you deny my love, you'l give my power, </l>
                <l>And since I can't perswade, I must constrain. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e115350">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <l>Sir since my presence does but move your anger </l>
              <l>Suffer me to retire I beseech you. <stage xml:id="ep000353-e115380">Exit. </stage>
              </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e115390">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>See Roderigo, how my love is answered, </l>
                <l>She flies my present; leaving not so much </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-027-b"/>
                <l>As a kinde look behinde her; if by this </l>
                <l>She thinks to coole the fire which burns my heart, </l>
                <l>She is deceiv'd; for this her suddainnesse </l>
                <l>Does not restrain but quicken more my flame, </l>
                <l>Tell me was ever King so rudely treated? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e115480">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>This her judicious and wise retreat, </l>
                <l>Being no effect of spight or arrogance, </l>
                <l>Should not excite your anger: sir you know </l>
                <l>A modest feare keeps subjects in restraint, </l>
                <l>When they are neer their King, and in that sex </l>
                <l>The dazling lustre of a Princes person, </l>
                <l>Strikes more respect into their hearts then love. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e115570">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Why, was I made a King then? if my quality </l>
                <l>Must crosse my dearest wishes, let me be </l>
                <l>A subject, any thing, so I have her: </l>
                <l>Some kinde fare rob me of my crown and scepter, </l>
                <l>And you shall see that I will blesse your rigour, </l>
                <l>If in exchange you'le give me but one heart: </l>
                <l>Cimena limits my ambition, </l>
                <l>On her depends either my life or death, </l>
                <l>Then if thou ever hadst a thought to please me, </l>
                <l>Roderigo winne Cimena to my love, </l>
                <l>Accomplish what thou hast begun, and try </l>
                <l>To melt the ice which circles in her heart, </l>
                <l>Or if it be a fire, oh turn it this way, </l>
                <l>From thee I must expect all my content: <stage xml:id="ep000353-e115730">Exit. </stage>
                </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e115740">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And I from you sir, all my punishment: </l>
                <l>Did ever any mischief equall this, </l>
                <l>I'me made the confident of my own rivall, </l>
                <l>To my self faithlesse, true to him that wrongs me, </l>
                <l>My duty and my love run contraries, </l>
                <l>One bindes me to obay a wilfull Prince, </l>
                <l>Th'other my Mistris, whom my heart adores, </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-028-a"/>
                <l>If I obay my love, I get his hate, </l>
                <l>And if my dutie, I must lose her love, </l>
                <l>But that I may however, since the King </l>
                <l>Has power to take her from me when he will: </l>
                <l>Then let me serve my King which I have promis'd, </l>
                <l>But that Cimena claims as well as he; </l>
                <l>On both sides thus engag'd, and thus distracted. </l>
                <l>Roderigo, what canst thou resolve to do, </l>
                <l>Since with thy love or dutie thou must part </l>
                <l>Give him thy life, and let her have thy heart. <stage xml:id="ep000353-e115930">Exit. </stage>
                </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="ep000353-e115940">
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e115950">
            <head>Act V. Scene I. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e115960">RODERIGO, CIMENA. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e115970">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <l>TH' Infanta's lodgings are that way. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e115990">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>Madam. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e116010">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You are mistaken, sir, I am Cimena, </l>
                <l>He that courts titles must forget a name </l>
                <l>That sounds not Princesse, nor would I divert </l>
                <l>The full stream of your hopes: here lies my way. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e116070">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>Madam, Cimena, stay and heare. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000353-028-b"/>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e116090">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <l>My ruine. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e116110">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>One word. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e116130">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <l>Pray let me go. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e116150">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>The last I mean </l>
                <l>To speak to any of your sex: what rigor </l>
                <l>Is this you use, did ever any yet </l>
                <l>Refuse to be a witnesse to a Will? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e116210">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Was ever any cruelty like this? </l>
                <l>Ah Roderigo, is it not enough, </l>
                <l>First to betray me to your love, and then </l>
                <l>Leave me, unlesse to shake my resolution: </l>
                <l>You set upon me with new batterie, </l>
                <l>I cannot heare and live. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e116290">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I do not come </l>
                <l>To urge ought in my own behalf, my dutie </l>
                <l>And promise made to him, who may command me, </l>
                <l>Forces this from me, can you love the King? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e116350">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <l>Can you be Roderigo, and demand it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e116370">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I have no more to say then, but to take </l>
                <l>My last farewell, perhaps when I'me remov'd </l>
                <l>Your dutie or ambition will perswade </l>
                <l>What from your servant is not credited, </l>
                <l>And when by this your obstinacie (as sure </l>
                <l>It must fall out so) my poore life grows forfeit, </l>
                <l>You will too late repent the losse of both. </l>
                <l>A lover and a Crown. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e116470">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Tis vainly urg'd. </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-029-a"/>
                <l>How can I lose a Lover, when he first </l>
                <l>Renounces me? a Crown I never had, </l>
                <l>And if I never seek it, as I shall not, </l>
                <l>Where is my losse? but rather where's thy courage </l>
                <l>Ah Roderigo must the feare of death </l>
                <l>Only come in to make some small pretence </l>
                <l>For leaving me, you did not use to be </l>
                <l>Frighted at such a name. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e116580">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Nor must you think </l>
                <l>That I am now, yet would I live to see </l>
                <l>Cimena in that lustre with her vertues </l>
                <l>Ever design'd her to, for me I think </l>
                <l>Nothing can adde unto my present state </l>
                <l>More happinesse then to have been the ground </l>
                <l>Where on my Mistris would erect her glory. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e116670">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And can you think Cimena will go lesse, </l>
                <l>While you discourse thus, you but teach my duty, </l>
                <l>The honour of our love must not be yours </l>
                <l>More then mine own, I have as great a share </l>
                <l>In it as you, and should it come to suffering </l>
                <l>I can as well expect to see you great </l>
                <l>As my self miserable; which must be so </l>
                <l>If fortune once divide us. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e116770">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Can our faith </l>
                <l>Be so rewarded? heavens, where is your justice? </l>
                <l>If we must needs be sever'd; why to both </l>
                <l>Gave you an equall minde, and thoughts alike? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e116830">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>That being parted, we might be more neere, </l>
                <l>For they that love alike are always one, </l>
                <l>Since but the sight nought can distinguish them. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e116880">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>These mysteries Cimena, are not strange </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-029-b"/>
                <l>Unto our loves, in which there has not been </l>
                <l>Any thing known, or easie, yet me thinks, </l>
                <l>We might finde out a way for intercourse. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e116940">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <l>Thy love is too materiall Roderigo, </l>
              <l>I could be satisfied with thy Idea. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e116970">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>And I with thine, but is it not some pleasure </l>
              <l>To stand thus, and to gaze on one another? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e117000">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Go Roderigo, for I feel within me </l>
                <l>Since this thy stay, some thing, that prompts me to </l>
                <l>Desire thy company, which must be fatall </l>
                <l>To both of us; adiew, and think we may </l>
                <l>Be sever'd yet continue still our selves. <stage xml:id="ep000353-e117070">Exit. </stage>
                </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e117080">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Our selves! am I Roderigo, or has she </l>
                <l>Bereft me of my spirit, can she brave </l>
                <l>The majesty of Kings secur'd within </l>
                <l>Her own firme constancy, and must I tremble, </l>
                <l>If the Kings will have not the wish'd successe? </l>
                <l>I ought him duty, and I have perform'd it, </l>
                <l>I've offerd with my life all my desires, </l>
                <l>Yet though I give, I may refuse to take, </l>
                <l>He cannot force me to a new affection, </l>
                <l>Or make me love her lesse, then she does mee, </l>
                <l>In other things he rules, in this I'me free. <stage xml:id="ep000353-e117210">Exit. </stage>
                </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e117220">
            <pb xml:id="ep000353-030-a"/>
            <head>SCENE II. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e117230">DON SANCHO, SERIFFA. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e117240">
              <speaker>D. SAN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>MAdam believe, I could not justifie </l>
                <l>The love I did pretend, if in this businesse </l>
                <l>I should preferre my passion before </l>
                <l>Your honour and content, I heare your brother </l>
                <l>The King has reconcil'd to you, it rests </l>
                <l>I let him know how much he owes to justice. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-serifa" xml:id="ep000353-e117320">
              <speaker>SER. </speaker>
              <l>But as you do it, spare my modesty, </l>
              <l>I would not be an offer, but his choice. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e117350">
              <speaker>D. SAN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>As you have given credit to my faith, </l>
                <l>In this distrust not my discretion, </l>
                <l>It is your honour which I seek, to which </l>
                <l>I made my love submit, and can you think </l>
                <l>I will not now preserve it, I am here </l>
                <l>T'attend the King as sent for, and shall use </l>
                <l>All opportunities to do you service, </l>
                <l>Please but your Highnesse to retire. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-serifa" xml:id="ep000353-e117450">
              <speaker>SER. </speaker>
              <l>Bequeathing to thy care, the hopes of all </l>
              <l>My future happinesse. <stage xml:id="ep000353-e117480">Exit. </stage>
              </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e117490">
              <speaker>D. SAN. </speaker>
              <l>Your Highnesse servant. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e117510">
            <pb xml:id="ep000353-030-b"/>
            <head>SCENE III. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e117520">KING, CELIMANT, DON SANCHO. </stage>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e117530">
              <speaker>KING. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>IN this sir, I confesse, Spheranti has </l>
                <l>Oblig'd our Family, the Prince is noble, </l>
                <l>And I could wish my sister would embrace </l>
                <l>The love he offers, what I can conferre, </l>
                <l>He may be sure of: but you know th' Jnfanta </l>
                <l>Is promis'd Roderigo, to whose valour </l>
                <l>She has been long a debt, and yet this businesse </l>
                <l>Is not arrived so farre as to cut off </l>
                <l>This noble Rivals hopes, sometimes a moment </l>
                <l>Alters the state of things; a Ladies minde </l>
                <l>Is not lesse changable: tell him from me </l>
                <l>He shall have all assistance. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-celimant" xml:id="ep000353-e117670">
              <speaker>CEL. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Tis the summe </l>
                <l>Of his desires, your Majestie will pardon </l>
                <l>Th' abruptnesse of my parting, he's my friend </l>
                <l>And such a happinesse he longs to heare </l>
                <l>As much as I to tell him. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e117740">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Your own time </l>
                <l>You may command brave Celimant: Don Sancho </l>
                <l>This Prince has royall thoughts &amp; more your friend, </l>
                <l>Then you could hope. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000353-031-a"/>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e117800">
              <speaker>D. SAN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Your Majesty still puts </l>
                <l>Fresh obligations on your humble vassall, </l>
                <l>I am your creature, and the Prince through you, </l>
                <l>Looking on me, may happily bestow </l>
                <l>His grace upon me as I am your servant, </l>
                <l>Though otherwise I be not worth his thought. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e117880">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>This modesty becomes thee, and sets off </l>
                <l>Thy vertues which I cherish; in reward </l>
                <l>Of which, and for thou hast been still an aid </l>
                <l>To my desires, I have assisted thine, </l>
                <l>The love thou mad'st to Corduba's Infanta, </l>
                <l>I have tane notice of, and though another </l>
                <l>Might suffer in the like attempt, in thee </l>
                <l>I've not dislik'd it, but commend thy choice, </l>
                <l>She is as great, in beauty as in birth. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e117990">
              <speaker>D. SAN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>She is an object for which mighty Kings </l>
                <l>Being rivals should take arms, such excellence </l>
                <l>Was never meant to be attain'd with ease. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e118040">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You speak sir, like a lover, but Don Sancho </l>
                <l>What would he say, that should be made the owner </l>
                <l>Of this rare beauty by consent of all? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e118090">
              <speaker>D. SAN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>That fortune had left nothing to confer, </l>
                <l>Being undone in this, hope cannot look </l>
                <l>So high. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e118140">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>She shall be thine, nay more, she is. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e118160">
              <speaker>D. SAN. </speaker>
              <l>Leave me not now my faith and honesty. <stage xml:id="ep000353-e118180">Aside. </stage>
              </l>
              <l>For I had nere more need of your assistance. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e118200">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>Thou dost not answer, has thy suddain joy </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000353-031-b"/>
              <l>Surpriz'd thy sences, and shut up thy speech? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e118230">
              <speaker>D. SAN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I must confesse, I'me ravish'd with this offer; </l>
                <l>And on my knees in signe of gratitude </l>
                <l>I here restore her to you. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e118280">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Dost thou mock, </l>
                <l>My courtesie, or is it madnesse in thee? </l>
                <l>Return unto thy self. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e118330">
              <speaker>D. SAN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Your favours, sir, </l>
                <l>Have come so thick upon me, that my thanks </l>
                <l>Are still ore taken, only now my fortune, </l>
                <l>Has given me leave to shew my gratitude, </l>
                <l>This Princesse whom you offer I adore, </l>
                <l>But dare not love, nor any but your self. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e118410">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>Thou mak'st me wonder, how can she concern me? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e118430">
              <speaker>D. SAN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>In justice, sir, she is your wife, if contracts </l>
                <l>Can stand in force with Princes, by your father, </l>
                <l>In your minority, with her a match </l>
                <l>Was made and ratifide, of which Don Diego </l>
                <l>Cannot be ignorant, nor Don Arias, </l>
                <l>Who did transact the businesse. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-unassigned" xml:id="ep000353-e118510">
              <speaker>L. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Some such thing </l>
                <l>I heard, but have forgotten, my Cimena </l>
                <l>Cals back my thoughts and fixes them on her; </l>
                <l>Beside she lov'd the Cid, and for his sake </l>
                <l>Betray'd her Country and her brother. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-sancho" xml:id="ep000353-e118580">
              <speaker>D. SAN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>True, </l>
                <l>She did, but not for him: had you great sir, </l>
                <l>But heard the story of her love, and how </l>
                <l>It grew up in her fancy, since the time </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-032-a"/>
                <l>The King her father mention'd first your name </l>
                <l>To her yet infant apprehension, </l>
                <l>And gave your picture to her, you would say </l>
                <l>Love entring by degrees, gathers his strength </l>
                <l>From small beginnings, but makes sure his hold. </l>
                <l>In fine, your Majestie has been the object, </l>
                <l>For whom she has despis'd the Prince Spheranti. </l>
                <l>Endur'd her brothers fury, and at length </l>
                <l>To colour her desires, made the occasion </l>
                <l>Of Roderigo's being there, the means </l>
                <l>To bring her to your Court, and acted that </l>
                <l>Unto the Cid, she truly meant to you: </l>
                <l>Feigned love is often better shew'd then true. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e118770">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I must confesse my self a debtor to her, </l>
                <l>But yet Cimena is my choice, the Princesse </l>
                <l>Consulted well for her own modestie, </l>
                <l>And no lesse for her good, when she made you </l>
                <l>Her speaker, I shall think on't: call Don Diego, </l>
                <l>My sister and Seriffa, to them all </l>
                <l>I have to say, Intreat the faire but cruell. </l>
                <l>Cimena come, and Roderigo too. </l>
                <l>I shall dispose of them: how unhappy <stage xml:id="ep000353-e118880">Exit San. </stage>
                </l>
                <l>Are Princes that must love by others reason, </l>
                <l>And not their own affections, this Princesse </l>
                <l>Is faire and loves me, so is my Cimena, </l>
                <l>But she abhors me; should I sacrifice </l>
                <l>To fame, Seriffa must be mine, but if </l>
                <l>To love, Cimena; one of these I'me led to </l>
                <l>By reason, to the other forc'd by love: </l>
                <l>Must a Prince suffer violence? he must </l>
                <l>Or else imprison them that offer it, </l>
                <l>(His wilde desires) there being no other course, </l>
                <l>But to submit to reason or to force. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="ep000353-e119000">
            <pb xml:id="ep000353-032-b"/>
            <head>SCENE IV. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000353-e119010">All the Actors, the INFANTA and CIMENA on one side; RODERIGO, CELIMANT, and SPHERANTI on the other. </stage>
            <lg>
              <l>BUt here they are: sister, I am resolv'd </l>
              <l>This day to see you married, and to make </l>
              <l>Your joy more perfect, I shall give you leave </l>
              <l>To choose your husband: the Prince of Toledo </l>
              <l>Courts you with such a love as nought can equall </l>
              <l>But his perfections, which you must honour, </l>
              <l>As well as he your beauty: yet Roderigo </l>
              <l>Is for himself so much to be considered, </l>
              <l>That we can hardly finde a Mistris for him, </l>
              <l>Which may deserve his vertues; both of them </l>
              <l>Out-weigh your merits, yet since equally </l>
              <l>They make an offer of their service to you, </l>
              <l>Declare which is the object of your choice. </l>
            </lg>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e119160">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I cannot, sir, believe my self so happy, </l>
                <l>As to have either of em for my husband: </l>
                <l>But if they do submit to my desires, </l>
                <l>Being both equall, I have no election. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e119220">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>They both adore you, and on this assurance </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000353-033-a"/>
              <l>You may distingish of their love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e119250">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <l>How, both. </l>
              <l>I doubt it much. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e119280">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>If you do not believe me, </l>
              <l>From their own voice I shall confirme it to you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-spheranti" xml:id="ep000353-e119310">
              <speaker>SP. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Yes divine beauty from my heart I speak, </l>
                <l>That heart which your fair eyes have set on fire, </l>
                <l>The light of which may shew you how I love. </l>
                <l>And if I lose my hope, I lose my life. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e119370">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>Can you doubt yet of his affection? </l>
              <l>And Roderigo sure will say as much. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e119400">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Tis true great King, all men adore the Princesse, </l>
                <l>She has such universall power ore harts, </l>
                <l>She cann't be seen by any, and not lov'd, </l>
                <l>But here's the difference between my love </l>
                <l>And theirs, they live with hope, I with despaire. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e119470">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>What robs thee of thy hope? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e119490">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>Love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e119510">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Speak more cleerly, </l>
                <l>Tis without reason that thou sayst: can love </l>
                <l>Take thy hope from thee, when it gives it thee? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e119560">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>Then when I love, my hope forsakes me quite. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e119580">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>But now it does restore what then it took. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e119600">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>In doing so it keeps me further from't. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000353-033-b"/>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e119620">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>These terms are too obscure, I cann't conceive em. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e119640">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>Time and my constancie will make it plain. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e119660">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>But I would know their meaning at this present. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e119680">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>Th' effect will quickly tell you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e119700">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>What effect. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e119720">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>My death. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e119740">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>Thy death, who can cause it? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e119760">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>Cimena, sir. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e119780">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>Cimena, thou hast yielded her to me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e119800">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>It was your will prescrib'd that Law unto me, </l>
              <l>I am your subject sir, and you my King. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e119830">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Though you be so, I never had intent </l>
                <l>To do you wrong, to do my self a pleasure: </l>
                <l>Thou knowst how deare thy person is to me, </l>
                <l>And that my sister is thy valours prize, </l>
                <l>Will you refuse her your affection. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e119900">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I have not, sir, ambition enough </l>
                <l>To look so high: pray sir, regard not me, </l>
                <l>But leave me to my self, possesse Cimena; </l>
                <l>In your love let her drown the memory </l>
                <l>Of mine, I am your subject, you my King. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e119970">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Well then since you refuse my profferd honours, </l>
                <l>And that my sister cannot touch your heart, </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-034-a"/>
                <l>My promises are disingag'd for me, </l>
                <l>I shall accept Cimena, and this Princesse </l>
                <l>You are content to part with, are you not? </l>
                <l>What do you fix upon? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e120050">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>On what I ought, </l>
              <l>I am your subject sir, and you my King. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e120080">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Spheranti, if my sister be your choice, </l>
                <l>So that your father will give his consent, </l>
                <l>I freely shall give mine. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-spheranti" xml:id="ep000353-e120130">
              <speaker>SP. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Your Majestie </l>
                <l>Shall quickly see that cleerd, I know my father </l>
                <l>Will be well satisfied, when he shall heare </l>
                <l>That I have joyn'd the Kingdoms of Toledo </l>
                <l>And Sevill by a match: but may I Madam </l>
                <l>Receive this happinesse from your consent? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-infanta" xml:id="ep000353-e120210">
              <speaker>IN. </speaker>
              <l>The King has made you, sir, disposer of me, </l>
              <l>And what he chooses answers my desires. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e120240">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>Th'art silent Roderigo, what dost think? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e120260">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <l>That she could hardly have a braver Prince, </l>
              <l>Nor he hope more then her. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e120290">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And you Cimena, </l>
                <l>Will you not put an end unto my sufferings, </l>
                <l>Will you be still obdurate to your King? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e120340">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Sir, I have no other faith then what I have given, </l>
                <l>You know your father made me weare these bonds, </l>
                <l>Which only death can break. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e120390">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>My constancie </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-034-b"/>
                <l>Shall overcome thy stubbornesse, I know </l>
                <l>The ground and cause of thy aversion, </l>
                <l>Thou hast some feeble hope t'enjoy the Cid, </l>
                <l>But that's without apparance; his own mouth </l>
                <l>Has ruin'd it, speak it again Roderigo, </l>
                <l>Assure her that her hopes but flatter her, </l>
                <l>Or if thou doft repent thy courtesie, </l>
                <l>Deal freely with me, say thy minde is chang'd, </l>
                <l>And that thou lov'st her spight of all her rigors. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e120510">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Great sir, my duty here restrains my tongue, </l>
                <l>It is enough for me that I have told you, </l>
                <l>You are my King, and I your humble vassall. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e120560">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <l>Though I am so, I will not force my subject </l>
              <l>To suffer for concealing his desires. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e120590">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ah sir, cast off all thoughts that may retard </l>
                <l>The course of your contentments, when a businesse </l>
                <l>Concerns the good of such a gracious King, </l>
                <l>What is the death of one unhappy man? </l>
                <l>Twill be a faire employment for my arme, </l>
                <l>To punish him thats troublesome to his Prince. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e120670">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Well thou hast overcome, thy extream vertue </l>
                <l>Shall serve for an example to thy King. <stage xml:id="ep000353-e120710">To Seriffa. </stage>
                </l>
                <l>See where I am oblig'd, Madam, Don Sancho, </l>
                <l>I hope has tane these blushes off, I know </l>
                <l>What right you have to me, and I to you. </l>
                <l>This should have been your work Don Diego rather </l>
                <l>Then his that did it, you were privy to </l>
                <l>All passages between our fathers; but </l>
                <l>You I say, as all else do, 'tis dangerous </l>
                <l>To turn the stream of Kings affections. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-diego" xml:id="ep000353-e120800">
              <speaker>D. DIE. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Your majestie is gracious, and prevents </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000353-035-a"/>
                <l>Excuses from your subjects, I could say </l>
                <l>No more in my own defence. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e120850">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Here I restore to thee thine own Cimena, </l>
                <l>(Most perfect lover) Madam, I hope your rigour </l>
                <l>Is not habituall, he's Roderigo, </l>
                <l>Who spight of my desires, has always lov'd </l>
                <l>And honour'd you, do not defer then longer, </l>
                <l>His and your own contentment, let his love </l>
                <l>Wrack'd with so many storms, finde here its harbour, </l>
                <l>He has conquer'd still abroad, let him not lose </l>
                <l>At home, but adde thy Mirtles to his Lawrels, </l>
                <l>And so confirming to him the same faith, </l>
                <l>Thou gav'st him once, receive him for thy husband. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e120980">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <l>On what shall I resolve? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-roderigo" xml:id="ep000353-e121000">
              <speaker>RO. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>To take my life, </l>
                <l>If you denie the price of my deare love, </l>
                <l>For since the hope of that has yet preserv'd it, </l>
                <l>They both must fall together, and twill be </l>
                <l>Some satisfaction to have dy'd your lover. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-cimena" xml:id="ep000353-e121070">
              <speaker>CIM. </speaker>
              <l>Rise, tis enough, I am Cimena ever, </l>
              <l>Thou Roderigo, and I wholy thine. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000353-king" xml:id="ep000353-e121100">
              <speaker>K. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Live happy Lovers then, and taste the pleasures, </l>
                <l>Which with so many crosses you have purchast: </l>
                <l>Quit all your cares, and celebrate this day, </l>
                <l>My Court shall be Loves Palace, come faire Princesse: </l>
                <l>Yare mine by a double tie of love and dutie, </l>
                <l>Which I shall still preserve, since I am taught </l>
                <l>To do not what I would; but what I ought. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
            <pb xml:id="ep000353-035-b"/>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back></back>
  </text>
</TEI>
