<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000537" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Beauties triumph a masque / written by T. Duffett.</title>
        <author>
<!--Duffett, Thomas-->
          <persName>
            <forename>Thomas</forename>
            <surname>Duffett</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A36756.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <p>
            This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is available for reuse, according to the terms of
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>
            . The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
          </p>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull>
              <titleStmt>
                <title>Beauties triumph a masque / written by T. Duffett.</title>
                <author>Duffett, Thomas.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[5], 22, [1] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                <date>1676.</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>"Presented by the scholars of Mr. Jeffery Banister and Mr. James Hart at their new boarding-school for young ladies and gentlewomen, kept in that house which was formerly Sir Arthur Gorges at Chelsey"</note>
                <note>Reproduction of originalsl in: Henry E. Huntington Library and Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc/>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000537-e10">
        <pb xml:id="ep000537-001-a"/>
        <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000537-001-b"/>
        <p>Beauties Triumph; A MASQUE. </p>
        <p>Presented by the Scholars of Mr. Jeffery Banister, AND Mr. James Hart, At their New BOARDING-SCHOOL for Young Ladies and Gentlewomen, kept in that House which was formerly Sir <hi>Arthur Gorges</hi>, AT CHELSEY. </p>
        <p>Written by <hi>T. Duffett</hi>. </p>
        <q>
          <l>— tutus, &amp; intra </l>
          <l>Spem veniae cautus— </l>
        </q>
        <p>LONDON, Printed in the year MDCLXXVI. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="prologue" xml:id="ep000537-e120">
        <pb xml:id="ep000537-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000537-002-b"/>
        <head>Prologue, spoken by a young Lady. </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Ladies, </salute>
        </opener>
        <l>Y'Are welcome,— and we hope y'are all sharp set, </l>
        <l>Good Appetites excuse a homely Treat; </l>
        <l>This was intended for our selves alone, </l>
        <l>From whom our Masters fear'd no cens'ring frown: </l>
        <l>But aw'd, and dazl'd by your piercing eyes, </l>
        <l>(For, though expected, you like Death surprize) </l>
        <l>They humbly bow,— and beg a kind excuse, </l>
        <l>For straiten'd time, and a disorder'd House; </l>
        <l>Hoping, the want of practice, fitting dress, </l>
        <l>And glorious Scenes, may make our failings less: </l>
        <l>As if defects could purchase good success. </l>
        <l>This might appease an accidental Guest; </l>
        <l>But you'r invited, and expect a Feast: </l>
        <l>Enlarged hopes, and longing looks y'have brought, </l>
        <l>Fine Dances, Songs, and Shew, swell ev'ry thought: </l>
        <l>Such things our Masters meant; but strove so fast </l>
        <l>To win the prize, we fall with too much hast. </l>
        <l>Like eager Gard'ners, that make Nature post </l>
        <l>The Flow'rs to early births, which being forc'd, </l>
        <l>Their sweet perfume and native beautie's lost. </l>
        <l>If we miscarry, let them feel the smart, </l>
        <l>They hardly gave us time to read a Part: </l>
        <l>Yet— if w'are out,— I fear 'twill break my heart.— </l>
        <l>Courage! be gone dull fear, and sullen doubt: </l>
        <l>The Cause! the Cause we fight shall bear us out. </l>
        <l>
          <hi>Beauties Triumph</hi>,— Beauty! your joy and care, </l>
        <l>The crown of Peace, and the reward of War. </l>
        <l>Ladies, Your int'rest your assistance calls; </l>
        <l>Your Empire's lost if <hi>Beauties Triumph </hi>falls: </l>
        <l>If any Lover his applause denies, </l>
        <l>Kill the Rebel,— stab him with your eyes. </l>
        <l>Sound a charge,— we'l nor take no quarter, <stage xml:id="ep000537-e520">Musick flourish. </stage>
        </l>
        <l>She that falls is Educations Martyr. </l>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="masque" xml:id="ep000537-e550">
        <pb xml:id="ep000537-003-a"/>
        <pb n="1" xml:id="ep000537-003-b"/>
        <head>Beauties Triumph; A MASQUE. </head>
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000537-e570">
          <head>SCENE I. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e590">The Curtain being drawn, Fate is discover'd sitting on a Throne, dress'd in a dark-colour'd Robe, powder'd with Swords, Stars, Daggers, Books, Flames and Crowns, &amp;c.— a Crown on his head, a Globe at his feet, and a great Book open before him: near his feet sit the Three Fatal Sisters, one holding a Distaff, another Spinning and drawing out Threads, and the third cutting them. On the Stage stand a King and Queen crown'd, and richly habited; a Hero crown'd with Laurel, and a Slave chain'd:— near him a beautiful Lady, and a despairing Lover:— a man and woman, whose dress express Poverty and Misery: in the midst of all stands Death, threatning with his Dart and Hour-glass.— Thus all continue, while a solemn Ayr is play'd by Violins, Rechorders, &amp;c.— which done, all but Death kneel to Fate and the Three Sisters. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e640">The King and Queen sing together. </stage>
          <l>STern Fate relent, change thy obdurate will, </l>
          <l>Canst thou without remorse see Monarchs kneel? </l>
          <l>For ev'ry moment added to our breath, </l>
          <l>We'l send whole Hecatombs of Slaves to death. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e700">This repeated by a full Chorus of Voices, and Musick. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e710">
            <pb n="2" xml:id="ep000537-004-a"/>The Lady sings alone. </stage>
          <l>O gentle Fate my beauty spare; </l>
          <l>Is there no pity for the Fair? </l>
          <l>All the Stars and the Glories my Lovers e're gave, </l>
          <l>I'le part from to buy a release from the Grave. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e770">The Heroe rises up and sings. </stage>
          <l>Shall a Heroe whose valour no force e're o'recame, </l>
          <l>Submit his great heart to an Aiery name? </l>
          <l>Thou Deity of slaves and fools, </l>
          <l>Let me and my Subjects alone, </l>
          <l>Or I'le pull thee from thy gloomy Throne, </l>
          <l>And make thy Spinsters quit their tools. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e840">The Lover sings, and one of the Unfortunate. </stage>
          <l>We court the fate from which they fly, </l>
          <l>For death, for death the wretched cry, </l>
          <l>Oh change our doom, Oh change our doom, Oh change our doom </l>
          <l>Or let us dye. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e890">Chorus of the Lover, Slave, and the two Unfortunate. </stage>
          <l>We court, &amp;c. </l>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e920">
            <speaker>Fate </speaker>
            <stage xml:id="ep000537-e940">sings. </stage>
            <l>Mortals give o're, </l>
            <l>In vain like raging Seas your passions roar, </l>
            <l>In vain for pity you implore: </l>
            <l>The fix'd decrees which Fate has pass'd, </l>
            <l>No threats or pray'rs can stop or hast; </l>
            <l>The Vassal shall tread </l>
            <l>On the Conquerour's head; </l>
            <l>And the Beggar that lies </l>
            <l>In the dust shall arise </l>
            <l>To a Crown, </l>
            <l>While Vsurpers and Tyrants fall down: </l>
            <pb n="3" xml:id="ep000537-004-b"/>
            <l>Fate crops the gayest, sweetest Rose, </l>
            <l>While the prickly Thistle grows; </l>
            <l>The creeping Bramble still looks green, </l>
            <l>When he lops the lofty Pine: </l>
            <l>Some shall love and sigh in vain, </l>
            <l>For her that is by others slighted, </l>
            <l>And the coyest Nymphs disdain </l>
            <l>Shall be requited </l>
            <l>By as proud a Swain. </l>
            <l>Some shall dye laughing, and some shall dye sad, </l>
            <l>For the deformed the fair shall be mad, </l>
            <l>And the glittering Scepter be chang'd to a Spade. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000537-e1190">Chorus of Fate and the Three Sisters. </stage>
            <l>Some shall, &amp;c. </l>
            <l>For the deformed, &amp;c. </l>
            <l>And the glittering, &amp;c. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e1260">A Dance. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e1270">In which Death kills the King and Queen, the Slave stabs the Hero, the Unfortunate seize the Crowns, and the Lady courts her despis'd Lover. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e1280">
            <speaker>Fate </speaker>
            <stage xml:id="ep000537-e1300">sings. </stage>
            <l>With cares and contrivance their Fate to avoid, </l>
            <l>Men lose the short pleasures that may be enjoy'd; </l>
            <l>Their fears are too swift, and their wishes too late, </l>
            <l>For nothing can alter the dictates of Fate. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000537-e1350">Chorus by Fate and the Three Sisters. </stage>
            <l>With cares, &amp;c. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e1380">While the Chorus is singing, the Stage is clear'd of the rest. Fate spurns the Globe, throws down his Book, and rises in anger; the Three Sisters follow him. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e1400">
            <pb n="4" xml:id="ep000537-005-a"/>
            <speaker>Fate. </speaker>
            <l>Give o're— </l>
            <l>Spin no more lives, burn all the sacred Tow, </l>
            <l>Let hasty births to sudden fun'rals go, </l>
            <l>Till the vast world a second Chaos know. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e1460">
            <speaker>1 Sister. </speaker>
            <l>Dread King of all the skies great lights, disclose </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e1490">
            <speaker>2 Sister. </speaker>
            <l>What weighty cause </l>
            <l>Obstructs thy Laws, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e1530">
            <speaker>3 Sister. </speaker>
            <l>What does thy haughty spirit discompose? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e1560">
            <speaker>Fate. </speaker>
            <l>Juno and Pallas with proud Venus joyn, </l>
            <l>The awfull Throne of Fate to undermine: </l>
            <l>Ingratefull pow'rs! I'le break your close design. </l>
            <l>Hoe Discord! hoe!— <stage xml:id="ep000537-e1670">Enter Discord. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Whence com'st thou, Mignion, from the shades below? </l>
            <l>Or from dark caves where struggling winds do grow? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e1700">
            <speaker>Discord. </speaker>
            <l>Ah— no! </l>
            <l>In Courts and Cities now I dwell; </l>
            <l>The sullen man and wanton wife, </l>
            <l>Have more imployment found for strife, </l>
            <l>Then all the winds </l>
            <l>The Seaman finds, </l>
            <l>Or all the Fiends in Hell. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000537-e1800">Chorus. </stage>The sullen man, &amp;c. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e1820">
            <speaker>Fate. </speaker>
            <l>From the Hesperian Tree with nimble wing, </l>
            <l>The fairest, largest golden Apple bring: </l>
            <l>Hast! hast! I seal'd the watchfull Dragons eyes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e1880">
            <speaker>Discord. </speaker>
            <l>Great Ruler of the World, thy Servant flies. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e1910">Exit Discord. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e1920">
            <pb n="5" xml:id="ep000537-005-b"/>
            <speaker>Fate. </speaker>
            <l>When power and wisedom with beauty unite, </l>
            <l>Mankind will be drown'd in such Seas of delight, </l>
            <l>My frowns they'l despise, and my favours they'l slight. </l>
            <l>Proud Deities, dare you oppose my Yoke, </l>
            <l>When your poor petty Cobweb plots are broke? </l>
            <l>I'le make you cringe and tremble at my stroke. </l>
            <l>The fiercest Gods with all their Titles swell'd, </l>
            <l>Ev'n Jove himself to Destiny shall yield. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000537-e2040">Chorus of Fate and the Three Sisters. </stage>
            <l>The fiercest Gods, &amp;c. </l>
            <l>Ev'n <hi>Jove, &amp;c.</hi>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e2090">Enter Discord with a golden Apple; Fate writes on it, and gives it her again. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e2120">
            <speaker>Fate. </speaker>
            <l>Be gone, to Ida's flow'ry Mount make hast, </l>
            <l>There thou shalt find </l>
            <l>Three Goddesses joyn'd, </l>
            <l>And by Concord embrac'd; </l>
            <l>Before their eyes this guilded poison cast: </l>
            <l>Take all the Furies with fierce Adders curl'd, </l>
            <l>Let their envenom d●spight a' round be hurl'd, </l>
            <l>And ghastly mischief fright the sleepy world. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000537-e2250">Chorus. </stage>
            <l>Take all the <hi>Furies, &amp;c.</hi>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e2280">Exeunt Fate and the Three Sisters. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e2290">
            <speaker>Discord. </speaker>
            <l>What hoe! you dismal haggs,— </l>
            <l>What hoe! you dismal haggs,— that hate the light, </l>
            <l>Daughters of dreadful Styx, and dreary Night; </l>
            <l>You snakie Sisters rise with threatning hands, </l>
            <l>Shake your steel'd whips, and wave your smoakie brands. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e2360">
            <pb n="6" xml:id="ep000537-006-a"/>Enter the Three Furies. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e2370">
            <speaker>1 Fur. </speaker>
            <l>The news,— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e2400">
            <speaker>2. </speaker>
            <l>The news,— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e2430">
            <speaker>3. </speaker>
            <l>The news, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e2460">
            <speaker>All. </speaker>
            <l>The news, fierce Discord, quickly tell the news. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e2500">
            <speaker>Discord. </speaker>
            <l>Listen dire messengers of angry fate. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e2530">All whisper and mutter together. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e2540">
            <speaker>1 Fur. </speaker>
            <l>Enough, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e2570">
            <speaker>2. </speaker>
            <l>Enough, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e2600">
            <speaker>3. </speaker>
            <l>Enough, we will about it strait. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e2630">
            <speaker>All. </speaker>
            <l>Enough, we will about it strait. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e2660">A Song in two Stanza's. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e2670">
            <speaker>Disc. </speaker>
            <l>Lean Vertue shall down with her barren reward, </l>
            <l>When Discord comes on she'l no longer be heard. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e2720">
            <speaker>1 Fur. </speaker>
            <l>Great Power, and Wisedom, and Beauty we'l sever, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e2750">
            <speaker>2 Fur. </speaker>
            <l>And singly destroy what would conquer together: </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e2780">
            <speaker>3 Fur. </speaker>
            <l>The fair shall be foolish, the wise shall be mad, </l>
            <l>And by their delusions the great be misled. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000537-e2830">Chorus. </stage>The fair, &amp;c. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e2850">
            <speaker>Disc. </speaker>
            <l>The Gallant shall swear, and the Nymph shall be kind, </l>
            <l>But both shall prove false to the Love they design'd: </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e2890">
            <speaker>1 Fur. </speaker>
            <l>The wise shall for power and wealth be too zealous; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e2920">
            <speaker>2 Fur. </speaker>
            <l>The great of their plotting and pride shall be jealous. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e2950">
            <speaker>3 Fur. </speaker>
            <l>And when the whole World's in confusion again, </l>
            <l>The Furies and Discord shall pleasantly reign. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000537-e3020">Chorus. </stage>And when, &amp;c. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e3040">A Dance by Discord and the Furies. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e3070">Exeunt all. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e3080">The Scene is chang'd to a pleasant Landschape of a flowrie Mountain, <hi>&amp;c. Iuno, Pallas </hi>and Venus enter, attended by Iris and many Nymphs; the Goddesses lay their hands on a Garland of Laurel, Bayes and Myrtle.— It Thunders and Lightens.— </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e3120">
            <pb n="7" xml:id="ep000537-006-b"/>[<hi>All this Scene is spoken</hi>.] </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e3140">
            <speaker>Iuno. </speaker>
            <l>Our Sacred Union all the Gods approve, </l>
            <l>And send this thundring message from above, </l>
            <l>To grace the Sister and the Wife of Iove. </l>
            <l>Iris my swift Embassadress, be gone, </l>
            <l>Clap thy light wings and shining colours on, </l>
            <l>And let our Union round the world be known. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e3240">
            <speaker>Iris. </speaker>
            <l>Great Queen of Gods, and Empress of the Skies, </l>
            <l>Whose fair plum'd team adorn'd with Argus eyes, </l>
            <l>Eclipse the splendour of my brightest Dyes: </l>
            <l>My painted Throne with watry Clouds I'le build, </l>
            <l>Which with more various colours shall be fill'd, </l>
            <l>Then flowrie Springs, or gaudy Summers yield. </l>
            <l>When wondring Mortals from their houses run, </l>
            <l>To see my Glories far out-shine the Sun, </l>
            <l>The will of Royal Iuno shall be known. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e3370">
            <speaker>Iuno. </speaker>
            <l>Rich Embassies the wills of Kings declare: </l>
            <l>What then should mine, to whom great Monarchs are </l>
            <l>Like twinkling Glow-worms to the Morning-Star? </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e3420">Juno and Iris <hi>seem to talk together</hi>. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e3450">
            <speaker>Venus. </speaker>
            <l>Is this the Union, this the equal sway? </l>
            <l>I'le rather Fate's than Iuno's pow'r obey: </l>
            <l>The will of Royal Iuno— </l>
            <l>And is not Venus worthy of a name? </l>
            <l>My Beautie's greater, and as great my Fame. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e3560">
            <speaker>Pallas. </speaker>
            <l>Fair Queen of Love, let not the rash mistake </l>
            <l>Of that untutor'd Maid a diff'rence make; </l>
            <l>My honour is an equal suff'rer made, </l>
            <l>And with your fame shall Pallas shine or fade: </l>
            <l>But let not Passion be too fast obey'd. </l>
            <l>Passion commits more crimes then it can find, </l>
            <l>It shakes the soul like a tempestuous wind; </l>
            <l>The Senses slave, but Tyrant of the mind. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e3670">
            <speaker>Venus. </speaker>
            <l>Sister of much-lov'd Mars, Goddess of Arms, </l>
            <l>Thy Prudence conquers whom thy Beauty warms, </l>
            <l>I yield as all must to thy pow'rfull charms. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e3730">
            <pb n="8" xml:id="ep000537-007-a"/>
            <speaker>Pallas. </speaker>
            <l>Iuno does private pow'r in vain pursue, </l>
            <l>While Beauties Goddess is to Pallas true; </l>
            <l>Beauty and Wit the highest pow'rs subdue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e3800">
            <speaker>Iuno, </speaker>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000537-e3830">to Iris. </stage>Thou dost the full of our great purpose know, </l>
            <l>Ascend and from thy party-colour'd bow, </l>
            <l>Proclaim it to the list'ning world below. <stage xml:id="ep000537-e3860">Exit Iris. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Now Fate, deluded mortals shall no more </l>
            <l>Dread thy feign'd Laws, and thy fantastick pow'r, </l>
            <l>But with glad hearts our sacred Shrines adore. </l>
            <l>Our Rites were lost, our Temples were prophan'd, </l>
            <l>No Praise or Sacrifice our Altars gain'd, </l>
            <l>No pow'r, forsooth, could change what Fate ordain'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e3950">
            <speaker>Pallas. </speaker>
            <l>So far this wild Imposture has been hurl'd, </l>
            <l>Gypsies and Star-gazers command the world. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e3990">
            <speaker>Venus. </speaker>
            <l>Th'are Fate's Viceroys, dispose of ev'ry heart; </l>
            <l>From Sacred Love the giddy Youth depart, </l>
            <l>And marry by the Stars:— vain rules of Art. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e4050">
            <speaker>Iuno. </speaker>
            <l>Iuno's not call'd to kindle Hymen's fire, </l>
            <l>And bless the Nuptial-bed with chast desire, </l>
            <l>But Fate with Avarice base knots conspire. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e4140">
            <speaker>Pallas. </speaker>
            <l>Then bloudy Discord with a Hellish throng </l>
            <l>Of Furies, houl the Hymeneal Song, </l>
            <l>And make the hated Marriage-night seem long. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e4210">
            <speaker>Iuno. </speaker>
            <l>They rise, seek lawless Love in sev'ral rooms, </l>
            <l>And cry, Alas! who can avoid their dooms? </l>
            <l>Thus rigid Fate a gentle Bawd becomes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e4270">
            <speaker>Venus. </speaker>
            <l>Then with unhallow'd breath they spot my name, </l>
            <l>And on my Innocence would lay their shame; </l>
            <l>I cherish none but chast and virtuous flame. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e4320">
            <speaker>Iuno. </speaker>
            <l>The lazie drone lies stretch'd upon the floor, </l>
            <l>Cries, Destiny compels him to be poor: </l>
            <l>He lyes,— What am not I the Queen of Pow'r? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e4380">
            <speaker>Pallas. </speaker>
            <l>The wild debauch 'gainst Heav'n makes open War, </l>
            <l>And lays his crimes upon his harmless Star, </l>
            <l>As if that caus'd that did the guilt declare. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e4430">
            <speaker>Iuno. </speaker>
            <l>Mankind no more in slav'ry shall remain, </l>
            <l>Long banish'd Justice shall to Earth again, </l>
            <l>And Vertue o're insulting Fate shall reign. </l>
            <pb n="9" xml:id="ep000537-007-b"/>
            <l>I'le give her pow'r unlimited to share </l>
            <l>The highest blessings of the Field or Chair, </l>
            <l>Among the good, the painfull, chast and fair. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e4510">
            <speaker>Pall. </speaker>
            <l>Prudence I'le give, and an enlighten'd mind, </l>
            <l>To teach her where she may be wisely kind. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e4550">
            <speaker>Ven. </speaker>
            <l>Beauty I'le give in blooming youth enshrin'd; </l>
            <l>Beauty which Monarchs more than Empire prize, </l>
            <l>Which makes the Hero brave, and States-man wise; </l>
            <l>For which the wretched lives, and happy dies. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e4610">
            <speaker>Iuno. </speaker>
            <l>Fortune shall still command the ign'rant Fool, </l>
            <l>But those that live in spotless Virtue's School, </l>
            <l>O're the severest Destiny shall rule. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e4660">Enter Iris. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e4680">
            <speaker>Iris. </speaker>
            <l>Hail mighty Queens of conquer'd Fate. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e4710">
            <speaker>Iuno. </speaker>
            <l>Quickly thy progress and success relate. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e4740">
            <speaker>Iris. </speaker>
            <l>No sooner from my arched Throne, </l>
            <l>Which with unusual Beauties shone, </l>
            <l>Did I Fate's sudden fall proclaim, </l>
            <l>But ev'ry word by greedy Fame </l>
            <l>Was to a thousand ecchoes sent, </l>
            <l>And posted through each Element; </l>
            <l>Like Lightning 'twas dispers'd a-round, </l>
            <l>And Thunder eccho'd from the ground: </l>
            <l>Such joyfull shouts were upward sent, </l>
            <l>As shook Heav'ns lofty battlement: </l>
            <l>My painted bow their vigour felt, </l>
            <l>And to a pearlie show'r did melt. </l>
            <l>Heark! the impatient Crowd draws near, <stage xml:id="ep000537-e4890">Musick heard. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>To let their hasty joys appear; </l>
            <l>Two of Fate's notorious cheats, </l>
            <l>About the Mount the Rabble beats. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e4930">
            <speaker>Iuno. </speaker>
            <l>In yond bright cloud conceal'd let's lye, </l>
            <l>While the rejoycing Crowd pass by. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e4970">Exeunt omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e4980">
            <pb n="10" xml:id="ep000537-008-a"/>After a flourish of Violins, Rechorders, Flajolets, &amp;c. an Astrologer with a Globe in his hand, and a Fortune-telling woman enter, pursu'd by Shepherds and Shepherdesses. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e5000">Chorus of Shepherds and Shepherdesses, to which all Dance, and drive off the Astrologer and woman. </stage>
          <l>Be gone you Deluders, your Traffick is o're, </l>
          <l>Your Figures and Canting shall cheat us no more. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e5030">Song by a Shepherdess. </stage>
          <l>Come, come away, </l>
          <l>To solemnize this happy day; </l>
          <l>With joyfull cries </l>
          <l>Let's rend the skies, </l>
          <l>For Fortune's fall is Virtue's rise. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e5090">Chorus of all with Musick. <hi>Come, come away</hi>, &amp;c. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e5110">
            <speaker>2 Shepherdess </speaker>
            <stage xml:id="ep000537-e5130">sings. </stage>
            <l>Sing, sing aloud, </l>
            <l>And you that love the coy or proud, </l>
            <l>No more complain, </l>
            <l>But chuse again, </l>
            <l>For Fate must yield to Virtue's reign. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000537-e5200">Chorus. </stage>Sing, sing aloud, &amp;c. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e5220">Song by a Shepherd. </stage>
          <l>Fortune's a drab, though the fool and the knave </l>
          <l>Proclaim her a Goddess, and Court her; </l>
          <l>Because they deserve not the blessings they have, </l>
          <l>They think the blind Quean their supporter: </l>
          <l>But the wise and the brave </l>
          <l>Still make her a slave, </l>
          <l>They laugh at her frowns and her favour, </l>
          <pb n="11" xml:id="ep000537-008-b"/>
          <l>And now the deceiver </l>
          <l>Is ruin'd for ever, </l>
          <l>Her Cracks and her Cullies shall leave her. </l>
          <l>The Iilt to her own rouling-wheel shall be ty'd, </l>
          <l>And the three Fatal Sisters be hang'd in their thread. </l>
          <l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000537-e5360">Chorus. </stage>The Iilt, &amp;c. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e5380">A Dance by a Shepherd alone. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e5390">Song by a Shepherd. </stage>
          <lg>
            <l>I love and am lov'd, but dare not declare </l>
            <l>The beauty that reigns in my breast, </l>
            <l>She's smoother then Lillies, she's softer then Air, </l>
            <l>She's all that can make a man blest: </l>
            <l>But alas she's confin'd to the pleasure </l>
            <l>Of one more unhappy then I; </l>
            <l>An Indian that knows not the worth of his treasure, </l>
            <l>But slights that for which I would dye. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>The Dragon still wakes, and guards with fierce eyes </l>
            <l>The fruit which he cares not to tast, </l>
            <l>But Virtue and Honour are watchfuller spies, </l>
            <l>Their tyranny ever will last: </l>
            <l>When in secret our flames we discover, </l>
            <l>We bow to the Laws they ordain, </l>
            <l>How short are the joys of a virtuous Lover, </l>
            <l>But Ah there's no end of his pain! </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e5580">A Dance by a Shepherdess alone. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e5590">A Song by a Shepherd and Shepherdess. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e5600">
            <speaker>Shepherd. </speaker>
            <l>Ioy sits smiling on each brow, </l>
            <l>In each dimpl'd cheek's a furrow, </l>
            <l>Made by mirth to bury sorrow; </l>
            <l>All are happy,— All are happy now, </l>
            <pb n="12" xml:id="ep000537-009-a"/>
            <l>Only Celia's cruel, cruel, cruel eye, </l>
            <l>Dooms Amintor still to dye. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e5700">
            <speaker>1 Shep. </speaker>
            <l>Poor Amintor's doom'd to dye. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e5740">
            <speaker>2— </speaker>
            <l>Poor Amintor's doom'd to dye. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e5780">
            <speaker>3— </speaker>
            <l>Poor Amintor's doom'd to dye. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e5820">
            <speaker>All Shep. </speaker>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000537-e5850">Chorus. </stage>Only <hi>Celia &amp;c </hi>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e5870">
            <speaker>Shepherdess. </speaker>
            <l>Oh Amintor hide thy pains, </l>
            <l>If thy tempting tongue had won me, </l>
            <l>Lawless passion had undone me, </l>
            <l>Sacred Virtue,— Sacred Virtue reigns. </l>
            <l>All that Virtue, All that Virtue grants I'le give, </l>
            <l>For thy hopeless love I'le grieve, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e5960">
            <speaker>1 Shep. </speaker>
            <l>And Amintor still shall live. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e6000">
            <speaker>2— </speaker>
            <l>Celia bids Amintor live. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e6050">
            <speaker>3— </speaker>
            <l>Celia bids, &amp;c. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000537-e6110">Chorus. </stage>All that Virtue, &amp;c. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e6130">
            <speaker>Shepherd. </speaker>
            <l>Then the longing eyes may gaze, </l>
            <l>In each others beams uniting, </l>
            <l>And the trembling hands uniting, </l>
            <l>Break not Virtues,— Break not Virtues Laws. </l>
            <l>Chastest Vestals, Chastest Vestals thus may kiss, </l>
            <l>Thus may Saints repeat their bliss, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e6210">
            <speaker>1 Shep. </speaker>
            <l>Virtue will not blush at this. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e6240">
            <speaker>2— </speaker>
            <l>Virtue will, &amp;c. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e6280">
            <speaker>3— </speaker>
            <l>Virtue will, &amp;c. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000537-e6330">Chorus. </stage>Chastest Vestals, &amp;c. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e6350">
            <speaker>Shepherdess. </speaker>
            <l>Hold, fond Shepherd, keep thy vow, </l>
            <l>Love deny'd 's an humble waiter, </l>
            <l>But a bold insulting traytor, </l>
            <l>When the Virtuous,— when the Virtuous bow. </l>
            <pb n="13" xml:id="ep000537-009-b"/>
            <l>Dear Amintor, Dear Amintor pray give o're, </l>
            <l>Celia cannot grant thee more, </l>
            <l>Alas she would but has not pow'r. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e6470">
            <speaker>1 Shep. </speaker>
            <l>Virtue, makes thy Celia poor. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e6510">
            <speaker>2— </speaker>
            <l>Virtue, &amp;c. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e6550">
            <speaker>3— </speaker>
            <l>Virtue, &amp;c. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000537-e6600">Chorus. </stage>Dear <hi>Amintor, &amp;c.</hi>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e6620">A Dance to the following Song, the Rechorders and Flajolets playing. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e6630">Song. </stage>
          <lg>
            <l>Let's love, and let's laugh, let's dance, and let's sing, </l>
            <l>While shrill ecchoes ring, </l>
            <l>Our wishes agree, and from cares we are free, </l>
            <l>Then who are so happy, so happy as we. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>We press the soft Grass, each Swain with his Lass, </l>
            <l>Or follow the chase, </l>
            <l>When weary we be, we sleep under a Tree, </l>
            <l>And who are so happy, so happy as we. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>By flatt'ry or fraud no Shepherd's betray'd, </l>
            <l>Or cheats the fond Maid, </l>
            <l>No false supple knee to deceive us we see, </l>
            <l>Then who are so happy, so happy as we. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>We envy no pow'r, nor cannot be poor, </l>
            <l>Who wish for no more; </l>
            <l>Some richer may be, and of higher degree, </l>
            <l>But none are so happy, so happy as we. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e6840">The three Furies rise up in the middle of them, and fright them all off:— Then the Furies dance,— <hi>&amp; Exeunt</hi>. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e6860">
            <pb n="14" xml:id="ep000537-010-a"/>Enter Juno, Pallas and Venus, embracing: Discord <hi>enters observing them</hi>. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e6910">[Discord <hi>speaks this</hi>.] </stage>
          <l>Now injur'd Fate thy gloomy den forsake, </l>
          <l>Raise all thy forces from the Stygian Lake; </l>
          <l>Thy foes are mighty, and thy Crown's the stake. </l>
          <l>Burning Ambition and revengefull Pride, </l>
          <l>Heart-gnawing Envy, and all ill beside, </l>
          <l>Attend, and Hell and Furies be your guide. <stage xml:id="ep000537-e6990">Discord <hi>throws the Golden Apple, which the Goddesses strive for, and go off. </hi>
            </stage>
          </l>
          <l>Hoh, ho, ho, hoe, 'tis done, 'tis done: </l>
          <l>Methinks I see the frighted world look pale, </l>
          <l>And Nature to her secret mansion crawl, </l>
          <l>As if she fear'd an everlasting fall. </l>
          <l>To Ida's Mount the striving pow'rs retire, </l>
          <l>Prophetick Spirits my hot brains inspire, </l>
          <l>And swell my thoughts with ruine, blood and fire. </l>
          <l>Venus obtains the prize from Priam's Son: </l>
          <l>Good, good, then Rapes and Murthers shall be done, </l>
          <l>Whose stories shall make future Ages groan. </l>
          <l>Now Fate, let thy tormenting Furies rest, </l>
          <l>Since my wild Empire's fix'd in ev'ry breast, </l>
          <l>The Goddesses themselves shall do the rest. </l>
          <l>Virtue shall into several factions fall; </l>
          <l>Strictness, Pride; Freedom, it shall Looseness call: </l>
          <l>Where Discord raigns, swift ruine swallows all. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e7210">Exit Discord. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e7220">Musick plays. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e7230">Enter Paris and Oenone, crown'd with Garlands of Flowers, with Sheep-hooks in their hands, attended by Shepherds and Shepherdesses. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e7260">Song in Dialogue. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e7270">
            <speaker>Paris. </speaker>
            <l>Tell me dearest Oenone, </l>
            <l>Why such sadness clouds my Sun; </l>
            <pb n="15" xml:id="ep000537-010-b"/>
            <l>A pearly deluge from thy eyes, </l>
            <l>Spreads thy rosie cheeks around, </l>
            <l>Where poor Cupid mourning lyes, </l>
            <l>To see his World of beauty drown'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e7370">
            <speaker>Oenone. </speaker>
            <l>Oh my Paris, Oh my Swain, </l>
            <l>Thou darling of the flow'ry Plain, </l>
            <l>I fear— But Ah my grief's too much to speak, </l>
            <l>I fear, I fear my swelling heart will break. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e7440">
            <speaker>Paris. </speaker>
            <l>Has the fierce Woolf devour'd a bleating Lamb, </l>
            <l>Or robb'd the Fondling of his Dam? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e7480">
            <speaker>Oenone. </speaker>
            <l>Ah!— no, those losses are </l>
            <l>Which changing time or prudent care </l>
            <l>Would soon repair. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e7530">
            <speaker>Paris. </speaker>
            <l>Say what does thy heart invade, </l>
            <l>I conjure thee, charming Maid, </l>
            <l>By those secret Bowers, </l>
            <l>Which the twining Myrtles shade; </l>
            <l>By those banks of flowers, </l>
            <l>Where our sacred vows were made; </l>
            <l>By the Spring, and by the Grove, </l>
            <l>And by the soft delights of Love. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e7630">
            <speaker>Oenone. </speaker>
            <l>Among the sweets this Garland bears, </l>
            <l>Say which the greatest glory wears. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e7670">
            <speaker>Paris. </speaker>
            <l>That— </l>
            <l>Whose bright leaves round yellow seeds are grown, </l>
            <l>Like sparkling Gems about a Golden Crown. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e7720">
            <speaker>Oenone. </speaker>
            <l>That does my sudden sorrow move, </l>
            <l>It will I fear thy Emblem prove, </l>
            <l>That gaudy flower's call'd <hi>Shepherd's Love. </hi>
            </l>
            <pb n="16" xml:id="ep000537-011-a"/>
            <l>How far his sweet perfumes do spread, </l>
            <l>How proudly shines his painted head: </l>
            <l>A dazling Crown's less gay then this, </l>
            <l>And that excels Arabian Spice. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000537-e7840">Chorus. </stage>How far, &amp;c. </l>
            <l>How proudly, &amp;c. </l>
            <l>A dazling, &amp;c. </l>
            <l>And that, &amp;c. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e7920">
            <speaker>Paris. </speaker>
            <l>My Shepherdess more glorious shews, </l>
            <l>And sweeter breath perfumes her vows. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e7960">
            <speaker>Oenone. </speaker>
            <l>But e're yond' Sun the world survey, </l>
            <l>And chase a second night away, </l>
            <l>This glory of the Spring will fade, </l>
            <l>And shrink into perpetual shade. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e8020">
            <speaker>Paris. </speaker>
            <l>His stalk will stoop, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e8050">
            <speaker>Oenone. </speaker>
            <l>His head will droop, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e8080">
            <speaker>Paris. </speaker>
            <l>His fragrant scents will fly; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e8110">
            <speaker>Oenone. </speaker>
            <l>His beauteous leaves no more will shine, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e8140">
            <speaker>Paris. </speaker>
            <l>But this proud Shepherds love will die, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e8170">
            <speaker>Oenone. </speaker>
            <l>And so alas, and so I fear will thine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e8200">
            <speaker>Paris. </speaker>
            <l>The Sun shall be fix'd, the Earth shall remove, </l>
            <l>But never shall Paris be false to his Love. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e8250">
            <speaker>Oenone. </speaker>
            <l>And will you always be thus kind to me? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e8280">
            <speaker>Paris. </speaker>
            <l>By all those powers that our actions see </l>
            <l>I will.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e8320">
            <pb xml:id="ep000537-011-b"/>
            <speaker>Oenone. </speaker>
            <l>Yet! yet! yet you may deceive. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e8350">
            <speaker>Paris. </speaker>
            <l>O cruel! will you ne're believe? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e8380">
            <speaker>Oenone. </speaker>
            <l>I do, I do, and will no longer grieve. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e8410">
            <speaker>Paris. </speaker>
            <l>We'l love while we live, and we'l live without care, </l>
            <l>Together we'l dye, and we'l make but one Star, </l>
            <l>To which happy Lovers shall offer their pray'r. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000537-e8460">Chorus of all Voices and Instruments. </stage>
            <l>We'l love, &amp;c. </l>
            <l>Together, &amp;c. </l>
            <l>To which, &amp;c. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e8530">A Dance. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e8540">Enter Iris <hi>and speaks to </hi>Paris. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e8570">
            <speaker>Iris. </speaker>
            <l>Hail thou most beauteous youth, hail Princely Swain! </l>
            <l>Thou pride of Shepherds, glory of the Plain! </l>
            <l>The motto on this Golden Apple writ, </l>
            <l>Three pow'rfull Goddesses at strife has set; </l>
            <l>Let it be giv'n to her that is most fair, </l>
            <l>Thy prudent Judgment must their right declare. </l>
            <l>To thee their doubtfull Titles they submit, </l>
            <l>Thou now art Lord of Beauty, Pow'r, and Wit.. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e8670">Enter Juno, Pallas, and Venus, <hi>attended by a great Train</hi>. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e8710">
            <speaker>Iuno. </speaker>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000537-e8740">Spoken. </stage>If for Iuno thou declare, </l>
            <l>Crowns and Empire are thy share; </l>
            <l>Laurels on thy brow I'le show'r, </l>
            <l>And all the tempting sweets of pow'r. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e8790">
            <pb xml:id="ep000537-012-a"/>Enter a Spaniard, with a Crown in one hand and a Laurel in the other, he lays them at Paris's feet. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e8820">Song in praise of Power. </stage>
          <l>Oh how sweet it is to reign! </l>
          <l>How delightfull 'tis to see </l>
          <l>The begging eye and bended knee, </l>
          <l>To hear the guilded Palace ring </l>
          <l>With praises of the King: </l>
          <l>Kings are Gods, and from the lofty Throne, </l>
          <l>On all the rest of men look down; </l>
          <l>All bow to them, but they submit to none. </l>
          <l>With frowns they kill, </l>
          <l>And with a smile </l>
          <l>More ravishing delights they move, </l>
          <l>Then all the fading sweets of Love. </l>
          <l>Pleasure and Treasure and Beauty are theirs, </l>
          <l>To sweeten their Cares; </l>
          <l>All Nature gives or Art can find, </l>
          <l>To please the sense and ease the mind, </l>
          <l>The Gods for Monarchs did ordain: </l>
          <l>Oh how sweet it is to reign! </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e9010">The Spaniard dances a Saraband in honour of Iuno,— </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e9040">Et Exit. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e9050">Enter an Amazon with a Mitre and Sword, which she lays at Paris's feet. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e9080">
            <speaker>Pallas. </speaker>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000537-e9110">Spoken. </stage>If Pallas gain the envy'd prize, </l>
            <l>Though thou to Empire dost not rise, </l>
            <l>Great Monarchs shall yield </l>
            <l>To thy Counsel at home, and thy Sword in the field. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e9160">
            <pb xml:id="ep000537-012-b"/>Song in praise of Wisdom. </stage>
          <l>Why should short-liv'd mortals strive to gain </l>
          <l>Guilded cares and glorious pain, </l>
          <l>'Tis not powers boundless sway, </l>
          <l>Nor all the guards that wait upon </l>
          <l>A shining Throne, </l>
          <l>Can drive intruding care away. </l>
          <l>Wisdom's sacred pow'r can bind </l>
          <l>The raging passions of the mind, </l>
          <l>He that has attain'd to that, </l>
          <l>Is the Emperour of Fate. </l>
          <l>Rough tempests that make Kingdoms roul, </l>
          <l>Against his breast in vain do beat, </l>
          <l>They cannot shake his fixed soul, </l>
          <l>But must like vanquish'd waves retreat. </l>
          <l>No restless wish, no trembling fear, </l>
          <l>Or fierce despair can enter there; </l>
          <l>Vain love, cold death, or hasty time, </l>
          <l>Have neither darts nor wings for him; </l>
          <l>When life forsakes his quiet breast, </l>
          <l>He does but change his place of rest: </l>
          <l>'Tis he, 'tis he alone is blest. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e9380">The Amazon dances in honour of <hi>Pallas,— &amp; Exit</hi>. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e9410">Enter a beautifull well-dress'd Woman, with a Garland of Flowers, and a wounded Heart, which she lays at Paris his feet. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e9430">
            <speaker>Venus. </speaker>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000537-e9460">Spoken. </stage>If thou grant'st the prize to me, </l>
            <l>None shall be so blest as thee; </l>
            <l>Killing eyes and charming faces, </l>
            <l>Beauties deck'd with all the Graces, </l>
            <l>Shall submit to thy embraces. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e9510">
            <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000537-013-a"/>Song in praise of Beauty. </stage>
          <l>When Beauty arm'd with smiling eyes, </l>
          <l>And in betraying features drest, </l>
          <l>For wandring hearts in Ambush lyes, </l>
          <l>She beats the valiant, cheats the wise, </l>
          <l>And gains a Throne in ev'ry breast; </l>
          <l>To so many bright forms she varies her shape, </l>
          <l>No God nor no Hero can ever escape. </l>
          <l>Who pleasing looks and mirth disdain, </l>
          <l>She wounds with more Majestick Art, </l>
          <l>And where the haughty meen proves vain, </l>
          <l>Such pearlie show'rs of tears she'l rain, </l>
          <l>As can dissolve the hardest heart: </l>
          <l>So deep is her cunning, so sweet is hes stroke, </l>
          <l>That all must be subject to Beauties soft yoke. </l>
          <l>But Oh how sweet 'tis to possess </l>
          <l>The secret wishes beauty move, </l>
          <l>The joys no language can express, </l>
          <l>Nor any wretched mortal guess, </l>
          <l>That has not try'd successful love; </l>
          <l>Such raptures of pleasure from Beauty proceed, </l>
          <l>That none but true Lovers are happy indeed. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e9730">The Lady dances in honour of <hi>Venus,— &amp; Exit</hi>. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e9750">Song by Paris. </stage>
          <lg>
            <l>The wise and the great </l>
            <l>To Beauty submit, </l>
            <l>It reigns in the Study, and conquers in fight; </l>
            <l>Then let my fair Mistress for ever be true, </l>
            <l>And Beauty shall Power and Wisdom subdue. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>So sweet are her charms, </l>
            <l>I'le quit without terms, </l>
            <l>The splendour of Empire and Trophies of Arms; </l>
            <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000537-013-b"/>
            <l>Oh let me be blest in my dear Oenone, </l>
            <l>And give the Ambitious the Mitre and Crown. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e9900">Paris gives the Golden Apple <hi>to Venus, at which Iuno </hi>and Pallas seem to storm. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e9940">
            <speaker>Iuno. </speaker>
            <l>Thy fondness, silly Shepherd, shall destroy </l>
            <l>The late enlarged Monarchy of Troy; </l>
            <l>When Grecian Swords and Fire thy house devour, </l>
            <l>No God shall guard thee from my injur'd power. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e10020">
            <speaker>Pallas. </speaker>
            <l>I'le your infatuated minds prepare, </l>
            <l>To urge swift ruine and destructive War; </l>
            <l>Neglected Wisdom near that fatal hour, </l>
            <l>Shall leave the City, when I quit the Tow'r. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e10080">Exeunt Juno, &amp; Pallas. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e10110">
            <speaker>Venus. </speaker>
            <l>Saturn's proud daughter, to thy office hie, </l>
            <l>Go mind thy Match-making and Midwifrie. </l>
            <l>And what's dame Pallas with her pining train? </l>
            <l>A sordid Insect, bred of Iove's hot brain. </l>
            <l>Go threaten Children with your Bug-bear rods, </l>
            <l>My Son, my Husband, and Gallant are Gods. </l>
            <l>Love!— Love's thy Province!— let Fools and Stoicks care, </l>
            <l>I rule the mighty Gods of Fire, Love, and War. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e10240">Exit Venus. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e10260">Song between Paris and Oenone. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e10290">
            <speaker>Paris. </speaker>
            <l>To the Grove, gentle Love, let us be going, </l>
            <l>Where the kind spring and wind all day are wooing; </l>
            <l>He with soft sighing blasts strives to o'retake her, </l>
            <l>She would not, though she flies, have him forsake her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e10350">
            <speaker>Oenone. </speaker>
            <l>But in circling rings returning, </l>
            <l>And in purling whispers mourning, </l>
            <l>She swells and pants as if she'd say, </l>
            <l>Fain I would but dare not stay. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e10410">
            <speaker>Paris. </speaker>
            <l>Strait he gets all the sweets on the banks spreading, </l>
            <l>Which he brings on his wings where his Nymph's hiding, </l>
            <l>In some close hollow creek kind Nature shades her, </l>
            <l>In the green Willow tree he Serenades her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e10470">
            <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000537-014-a"/>
            <speaker>Oenone. </speaker>
            <l>— And to gain her chast embraces, </l>
            <l>Sends his notes to losty places; </l>
            <l>In calms they lye and seem to say, </l>
            <l>Stormy care drives love away. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e10530">
            <speaker>Paris. </speaker>
            <l>— There the loud busie Croud never shall part us, </l>
            <l>Nor no kind fawning friend from love divert us; </l>
            <l>We'l to each other be friends, fame and treasure, </l>
            <l>And no unruly thought shall stain our pleasure. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e10590">
            <speaker>Oenone. </speaker>
            <l>— Time and Nature ever smiling, </l>
            <l>Shall forget their Arts of killing; </l>
            <l>And all the Gods aloud shall say, </l>
            <l>Love so chast should ne're decay. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e10650">A Dance by Paris and Oenone. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e10680">Sung by several. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e10690">
            <speaker>1. </speaker>
            <l>Oh, how delightfull is Love, and how strong, </l>
            <l>When Beauty and Virtue are joyn'd in the young. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000537-e10740">Chorus. </stage>Oh how, &amp;c. </l>
            <l>When, &amp;c. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e10780">
            <speaker>2. </speaker>
            <l>The flashes of Vices intemperate joys, </l>
            <l>Are haunted with noise of Drunkards and Boys: </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e10820">
            <speaker>3. </speaker>
            <l>And when the short blaze of Beauty decays, </l>
            <l>With spight and contempt on the ashes they gaze. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000537-e10870">Chorus. </stage>Oh how, &amp;c. </l>
            <l>When, &amp;c. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e10910">
            <speaker>1. </speaker>
            <l>For the ruine of Virtuous Beauties are still, </l>
            <l>Ador'd like old Temples where Deities dwell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000537-e10950">
            <speaker>2. </speaker>
            <l>Fair Virtue keeps love still alive in the heart, </l>
            <l>When Age has o'recome Youth, Beauty and Art. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000537-e10990">Chorus of all Voices and Instruments. </stage>
            <l>Oh how, &amp;c. </l>
            <l>When, &amp;c. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000537-e11040">A Dance to this Chorus. </stage>
        </div>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="epilogue" xml:id="ep000537-e11070">
        <pb xml:id="ep000537-014-b"/>
        <head>Epilogue, spoken by a young Lady. </head>
        <l>LIke cloister'd Nuns with virtuous zeal inspir'd, </l>
        <l>From publick noise, and vicious ease retir'd, </l>
        <l>Here we have all that's by the good admir'd. </l>
        <l>While thus the loosest of our time is spent, </l>
        <l>'Tis advantageous, sweet, and innocent. </l>
        <l>And when our thoughts to serious things are bent, </l>
        <l>One in rich works with lively colours tells </l>
        <l>Lucretia's Rape, or mourning Philomels: </l>
        <l>Each chast beholder sighs and drops a tear, </l>
        <l>To burn the well-wrought Silk they scarce forbear, </l>
        <l>So sad and moving does the work appear: </l>
        <l>Oh that the Ravisher were here! one cries, </l>
        <l>Thus would I rend the bloudy Tyrant's eyes; </l>
        <l>Then for his crime some harmless Flower dyes, </l>
        <l>Whose falling head, as if indeed 'twere pain'd, </l>
        <l>Sheds dewie tears upon the murth'rers hand. </l>
        <l>Some Hero's praise in sacred Verse kept long, </l>
        <l>Another sings to th'Lute— </l>
        <l>While ev'ry string seems turn'd into a tongue, </l>
        <l>And sends soft ecchoes to the joyfull Song. </l>
        <l>Anothers diff'rent mind more pleasure takes, </l>
        <l>In various forms to mould the painted Wax; </l>
        <l>Such shape, such beauty in each piece is shown, </l>
        <l>Nature sits pale, or blushing on her own, </l>
        <l>To see her pride by curious Art out-done. </l>
        <l>While buzzing Infamy, with venom'd wing, </l>
        <l>Haunts clam'rous pleasures that in Cities ring, </l>
        <l>Thus we enjoy the sweets without the sting. </l>
        <l>When riper age with flatt'ring care's oppress'd, </l>
        <l>Toil'd with false joys, 'twill sadly be confess'd, </l>
        <l>Of all our lives these happy hours were best. </l>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
