<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000793" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Tragical Reign of Selimus</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Robert</forename>
            <surname>Greene</surname>
          </persName>
          <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q433651</idno>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A68114.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
        </bibl>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The tragedy of Selimus Emperour of the Turkes. Written T.G.</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2007 January (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">AUA3579</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 12310b</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 130(AII)</idno>
            <idno type="vid">3571</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68114</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2248577456</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The tragedy of Selimus Emperour of the Turkes. Written T.G.</title>
            <author>T. G., fl. 1638.</author>
            <author>Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592,</author>
            <author>Goffe, Thomas, 1591-1629.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[76] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed [by Thomas Creede, and Nicholas Okes] for Iohn Crooke and Richard Serger and are to be sold at their shop in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the Grey-hound,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date type="publication_date">1638.</date>
            <date type="creation_date">1591</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Selimus.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Sometimes attributed to Robert Greene. "The initials T.G. were presumably intended to suggest Thomas Goffe" (Greg), who, however, was not born until 1591.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>A reissue, with cancel title page printed by Nicholas Okes, of: The first part of the tragicall raigne of Selimus: London, 1594.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-KÛp4Ûs (-A1,K4).</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The last leaf was blank, and the first leaf blank except for signature-mark in the original issue, but they are not recorded in any extant copy of this reissue.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Running title reads: The first part of the tragicall raigne of Selimus, Emperour of the Turkes.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Identified as STC 12310a on UMI microfilm reel 298.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproductions of the originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery and the Bodleian Library.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Appears at reel 298 (Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery copy) and at reel 1574 (Bodleian Library copy).</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-bajazet">
            <persName>Bajazet</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-cherseoli">
            <persName>Cherseoli</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-mustaffa">
            <persName>Mustaffa</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-messenger">
            <persName>Messenger</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-selimus">
            <persName>Selimus</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-occhiali">
            <persName>Occhiali</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-sinam">
            <persName>Sinam</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-ottrante">
            <persName>Ottrante</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-acomat">
            <persName>Acomat</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-visir">
            <persName>Visir</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-regan">
            <persName>Regan</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-unassigned">
            <persName>Unassigned</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-cali">
            <persName>Cali</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-mahomet">
            <persName>Mahomet</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-belierbey">
            <persName>Belierbey</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-zonara">
            <persName>Zonara</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-aga">
            <persName>Aga</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-all">
            <persName>All</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-abraham">
            <persName>Abraham</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-bullithrumble">
            <persName>Bullithrumble</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-corcut">
            <persName>Corcut</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-page">
            <persName>Page</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-hali">
            <persName>Hali</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-solima">
            <persName>Solima</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-aladin">
            <persName>Aladin</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-amurath">
            <persName>Amurath</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-alinda">
            <persName>Alinda</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-tonombey">
            <persName>Tonombey</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000793-queen">
            <persName>Queen</persName>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
      <textClass>
        <classCode scheme="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q80930</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1591">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000793-e100030">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000793-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000793-001-b"/>
        <p>THE TRAGEDY OF SELIMVS Emperour of the Turkes. </p>
        <p>Written T. G. </p>
        <p>LONDON: Printed for Iohn Crooke and Richard Serger and are to be sold at their shop in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the GreyHound. 1638. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="play" xml:id="ep000793-e100080">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000793-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000793-002-b"/>
        <head>THE FIRST PART OF THE most tyrannicall Tragedie and raigne of Selimus, Emperour of the Turkes, and grandfather to him that now raigneth. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e100090">Enter Baiazet Emperour of Turkie, Mustaffa, Cherseoly, and the Iannisaries. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e100100">
          <speaker>Baiazet. </speaker>
          <l>LEaue me my Lords vntill I call you foor, </l>
          <l>For I am heauie and disconsolate. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e100130">Exeunt all but Baiazet. </stage>
          <lg>
            <l>So Baiazet, now thou remainst alone, </l>
            <l>Vnrip the thoughts that harbour in thy brest, </l>
            <l>And eate thee vp, for arbiter heres none, </l>
            <l>That may discrie the cause of thy vnrest, </l>
            <l>Vnlesse these walles thy secret thoughts declare, </l>
            <l>And Princes walles they say, vnfaithfull. </l>
            <l>Why thats the profit of great regiment, </l>
            <l>That all of vs are subiect vnto feares, </l>
            <l>And this vaine shew and glorious intent, </l>
            <l>Priuie suspition on each scruple reares, </l>
            <l>I, though on all the world we make extent, </l>
            <l>From the South-pole vnto the Northren beares, </l>
            <l>And stretch our raign from East to Western shore, </l>
            <l>Yet doubt and care are with vs euermore. </l>
            <l>Looke how the earth clad in her sommers pride, </l>
            <l>Embroydereth her mantle gorgiously, </l>
            <l>With fragrant hearbes, and flowers gaily dide, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-003-a"/>
            <l>Spreading abroad her spangled Tapistrie: </l>
            <l>Yet vnder all a loathsome snake doth hide. </l>
            <l>Such is our life, vnder Crownes, cares do lie, </l>
            <l>And feare the scepter still attends vpon, </l>
            <l>Oh who can take delight in kingly throne </l>
            <l>Publike disorders ioyn'd with priuate carke, </l>
            <l>Care of our friends, and of our children deare, </l>
            <l>Do tosse our liues, as waues a silly barke. </l>
            <l>Though we be fearelesse, tis not without feare, </l>
            <l>For hidden mischiefe lurketh in the darke: </l>
            <l>And stormes may fall, be the day nere so cleare. </l>
            <l>He knowes not what it is to be a King, </l>
            <l>That thinks a scepter is a pleasant thing. </l>
            <l>Twice fifteene times hath faire Latonaes sonne </l>
            <l>Walked about the world with his great light: </l>
            <l>Since I began, would I had nere begunne </l>
            <l>To sway this scepter. Many a carefull night </l>
            <l>When Cynthia in hast to bed did runne. </l>
            <l>Haue I with watching vext my aged spright? </l>
            <l>Since when what dangers I haue ouerpast, </l>
            <l>Would make a heart of adamant agast. </l>
            <l>The Persian Sophi mightie Ismaell, </l>
            <l>Tooke the Levante cleane away from mee, </l>
            <l>And Caraguis Bassa sent his force to quell, </l>
            <l>Was kild himselfe the while his men did flee. </l>
            <l>Poore Hali Bassa hauing once sped well, </l>
            <l>And gaind of him a bloodie victorie, </l>
            <l>Was at the last slaine fighting in the field, </l>
            <l>Charactering honor in his batt'red shield. </l>
            <l>Ramirchan the Tartarian Emperour, </l>
            <l>Gathering to him a number numberlesse, </l>
            <l>Of bigbond Tartars in a haplesse houre </l>
            <l>Encountred me, and there my chiefest blesse </l>
            <l>Good Alemshae (ah this remembrance soure) </l>
            <l>Was slaine the more t'augment my sad distresse, </l>
            <l>In leesing Alemshae poore, I lost more </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-003-b"/>
            <l>Then euer I had gained theretofore. </l>
            <l>Well may thy soule rest in her latest graue, </l>
            <l>Sweete Alemshae the comfort of my dayes, </l>
            <l>That thou might'st liue, how often did I craue? </l>
            <l>How often did I bootlesse praiers raise </l>
            <l>To that high power that life first to thee gaue? </l>
            <l>Trustie wast thou to me at all assaies, </l>
            <l>And deerest child thy father oft hath cride, </l>
            <l>That thou hadst liu'd, so he himselfe had dide. </l>
            <l>The Christian Armies, oftentimes defeated </l>
            <l>By my victorious fathers valiance, </l>
            <l>Haue all my Captaines famously confronted, </l>
            <l>And crackt in two our vncontrolled lance. </l>
            <l>My strongest garrisons they haue supplanted, </l>
            <l>And ouerwhelmed me in sad mischance: </l>
            <l>And my decrease so long wrought their increase, </l>
            <l>Till I was forc'd conclude a friendly peace. </l>
            <l>Now all these are but forraine dammages, </l>
            <l>Taken in warre whose die vncertaine is, </l>
            <l>But I shall haue more home-borne outrages, </l>
            <l>Vnlesse my diuination aimes amisse: </l>
            <l>I haue three sonnes all of vnequall ages, </l>
            <l>And all in diuerse studies set their blisse. </l>
            <l>Corcut my eldest a Philosopher, </l>
            <l>Acomat pompous, Selmi a warriour. </l>
            <l>Corcut in faire Magnesia leades his life, </l>
            <l>In learning Arts and Mahounds dreaded lawes: </l>
            <l>Acomat loues to court it with his wife, </l>
            <l>And in a pleasant quiet ioyes to pause: </l>
            <l>But Selmi followes warres in dismall strife, </l>
            <l>And snatcheth at my Crowne with greedy clawes: </l>
            <l>But he shall misse of that he aimeth at, </l>
            <l>For I reserue it for my Acomat. </l>
            <l>For Acomat? Alasse it cannot be, </l>
            <l>Stearne Selimus hath wonne my peoples hart, </l>
            <l>The Ianissaries loue him more then me: </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-004-a"/>
            <l>And for his cause will suffer any smart. </l>
            <l>They see he is a friend to chiualrie, </l>
            <l>And sooner will they from my faith depart, </l>
            <l>And by strong hand Baiazet pull thee downe, </l>
            <l>Then let their Selmi hop without the Crowne. </l>
            <l>Ah, if the souldiers ouerrule thy state, </l>
            <l>And nothing must be done without their will, </l>
            <l>If euery base and vpstart runnagate </l>
            <l>Shall crosse a Prince and ouerthwart him still. </l>
            <l>If Corcut, Selimus, and Acomat, </l>
            <l>With crowns and kingdoms shal their hungers fill? </l>
            <l>Poore Baiazet what then remaines to thee? </l>
            <l>But the bare title of thy dignitie. </l>
            <l>I, and vnlesse thou do dissemble all, </l>
            <l>And winke at Selimus aspiring thought: </l>
            <l>The Bassaes cruelly shall worke thy fall, </l>
            <l>And then thy Empire is but deerly bought. </l>
            <l>Ah that our sonnes thus to ambition thrall, </l>
            <l>Should set the law of Nature all at nought. </l>
            <l>But what must be, cannot chuse but be done, </l>
            <l>Come Bassaes enter, Baiazet hath done. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e101250">Enters againe. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-cherseoli" xml:id="ep000793-e101260">
          <speaker>Cherseoli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Dread Emperour, long may you happie liue, </l>
            <l>Lou'd of your subiects, and feard of your foes: </l>
            <l>We wonder much what doth your highnesse grieue, </l>
            <l>That you will not vnto your Lords disclose. </l>
            <l>Perhaps you feare least we your loyall Peeres, </l>
            <l>Would prooue disloyall to your Maiestie, </l>
            <l>And be rebellious in your dying yeeres. </l>
            <l>But mightie Prince the heauens can testifie, </l>
            <l>How dearly we esteeme your safetie. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mustaffa" xml:id="ep000793-e101370">
          <speaker>Mustaf. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Perhaps you thinke Mustaffa wil reuok </l>
            <l>And leaue your grace, and cleaue to Selimus, </l>
            <l>But sooner shall th'almighties thunderbolt </l>
            <l>Strike me downe to the caue tenebrious </l>
            <l>The lowest land, and damned spirits ho●t </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-004-b"/>
            <l>Then true Mustaffa prooue so treacherous: </l>
            <l>Your Maiestie then needs not much to feare, </l>
            <l>Since you are lou'd of subiect, Prince, and Peere. </l>
            <l>First shall the Sunne rise from the occident, </l>
            <l>And loose his steeds benighted in the East, </l>
            <l>First shall the sea become the continent, </l>
            <l>Ere we forsake our soueraignes beheast: </l>
            <l>We fought not for you gainst Persians Tent, </l>
            <l>Breaking our Launces on his sturdie creast. </l>
            <l>We fought not for you gainst the Christian hoast, </l>
            <l>To become traytors after all our cost. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e101550">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Heare me Mustaffa and Cherseoli, </l>
            <l>I am a father of a headstrong brood, </l>
            <l>Which if I looke not closely to my selfe, </l>
            <l>Will seeke to ruinate their fathers state, </l>
            <l>Euen as the vipers in great Neroes fenne, </l>
            <l>Eate vp the belly that first nourish'd them. </l>
            <l>You see the haruest of my life is past, </l>
            <l>And aged winter hath besprent my head, </l>
            <l>With a hoare frost of siluer coloured haires, </l>
            <l>The harbingers of honourable eld, </l>
            <l>These branchlike vaines which once did guide my armes </l>
            <l>To tosse the speare in battellous array, </l>
            <l>Now withered vp haue lost their former strength: </l>
            <l>My sonnes whom now ambition ginnes to pricke, </l>
            <l>May take occasion of my weakned age, </l>
            <l>And rise in rebell armes against my state. </l>
            <l>But staie, here comes a Messenger to vs. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e101740">Sound within. Enters a Messenger. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-messenger" xml:id="ep000793-e101750">
          <speaker>Messen. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Health and good hap to Baiazet, </l>
            <l>The great commander of all Asia, </l>
            <l>Selmi the Soldane of great Trebisond, </l>
            <l>Sends me vnto your grace, to signifie </l>
            <l>His alliance with the King of Tartary. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e101820">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Said I not Lords as much to you before, </l>
            <l>That mine own sonnes would seek my ouerthrow? </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-005-a"/>
            <l>And see here comes a lucklesse messenger </l>
            <l>To prooue that true which my mind did foretell. </l>
            <l>Does Selim make so small account of vs, </l>
            <l>That he dare marry without our consent, </l>
            <l>And to that diell too of Tartarie? </l>
            <l>And could he then vnkind, so soone forget </l>
            <l>The iniuries that Ramir did to me, </l>
            <l>Thus to consort himselfe with him gainst me? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-cherseoli" xml:id="ep000793-e101940">
          <speaker>Cher e </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Your maiestie misconsters Selimus, </l>
            <l>It cannot be, that he in whose high thoughts </l>
            <l>A map of many valures is enshrin'd, </l>
            <l>Should seeke his fathers ruine and decay. </l>
            <l>Selimus is a Prince of forward hope, </l>
            <l>Whose onely name affrights your enemies, </l>
            <l>It cannot be he should prooue false to you. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e102030">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Can it not be? Oh yes Cherseoli, </l>
            <l>For Selimus hands do itch to haue the Crowne, </l>
            <l>And he will haue it, or else pull me downe. </l>
            <l>Is he a Prince? ah no he is a sea, </l>
            <l>Into which runne nought but ambitious reaches, </l>
            <l>Seditious complots, murther, fraud and hate. </l>
            <l>Could he not let his father know his mind, </l>
            <l>But match himselfe when I least thought on it? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mustaffa" xml:id="ep000793-e102130">
          <speaker>Must. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Perhaps my Lord Selimus lou'd the dame, </l>
            <l>And feard to certifie you of his loue, </l>
            <l>Because her father was your enemie. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e102180">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>In loue Mustaffa, Selimus in loue? </l>
            <l>If he be, Lording tis not Ladies loue, </l>
            <l>But loue of rule, and kingly soueraigntie. </l>
            <l>for wherefore should he feare t'ask my consent </l>
            <l>Trully Mustaffa, if he had feard me, </l>
            <l>He neuer would haue lou'd mine enemie. </l>
            <l>But this his marriage with the Tartars daughter, </l>
            <l>Is but the prologue to his crueltie, </l>
            <l>And quickly shall we haue the Tragedie. </l>
            <l>Which though he act with meditated brauerie, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-005-b"/>
            <l>The world will neuer giue him plauditie. </l>
            <l>What yet more newes? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e102320">Sound within. Enters another Messenger. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-messenger" xml:id="ep000793-e102330">
          <speaker>Mess. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Dread Emperour, Selimus is at hand. </l>
            <l>Two hundreth thousand strong Tartarians </l>
            <l>Armed at all points dooes he lead with him, </l>
            <l>Besides his followers from Trebisond. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e102390">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>I thought so much of wicked Selimus, </l>
            <l>Oh forlorne hopes and haplesse Baiazet. </l>
            <l>Is dutie then exiled from his brest, </l>
            <l>Which nature hath inscrib'd with golden pen, </l>
            <l>Deepe in the hearts of honourable men? </l>
            <l>Ah Selim, Selim, wert thou not my sonne, </l>
            <l>But some strange vnacquainted forreiner, </l>
            <l>Whom I should honour as I honour'd thee: </l>
            <l>Yet would it greeue me euen vnto the death, </l>
            <l>If he should deale as thou hast dealt with me, </l>
            <l>And thou my sonne to whom I freely gaue </l>
            <l>The mightie Empire of great Trebisond, </l>
            <l>Art too vnnatural to requite me thus, </l>
            <l>Good Alemshae hadst thou liu'd till this day, </l>
            <l>Thou wouldst haue blushed at thy brothers minde </l>
            <l>Come sweete Mustaffa, come Cherseoli </l>
            <l>And with some good aduice recomfort me. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e102580">Exeunt. All. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e102590">Enter Selimus, Sinam Bassa, Otrante, Cochialie, and the souldiers. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e102600">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Now Selimus consider who thou art, </l>
            <l>Long hast thou marched in disguis'd attire </l>
            <l>But now vnmaske thy selfe and play thy part, </l>
            <l>And manifest the heate of thy desire: </l>
            <l>Nourish the coales of thine ambitious fire. </l>
            <l>And thinke that then thy Empire is most sure, </l>
            <l>When men for feare thy tyrannie endure </l>
            <l>Thinke that to thee there is no worse reproach, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-006-a"/>
            <l>Then filiall dutie in so high a place, </l>
            <l>Thou oughtst to set barrels of blood abroach, </l>
            <l>And seeke with swoord whole kingdomes to displace, </l>
            <l>Let Mahounds lawes be lockt vp in their case. </l>
            <l>And meaner men and of a baser spirit, </l>
            <l>In vertuous actions seeke for glorious merit. </l>
            <l>I count it sacriledge for to be holy </l>
            <l>Or reuerence this thred-bare name of good, </l>
            <l>Leaue to old men and babes that kind of follie, </l>
            <l>Count it of equall value with the mud: </l>
            <l>Make thou a passage for thy gushing floud, </l>
            <l>By slaughter, treason, or what else thou can, </l>
            <l>And scorne religion, it disgraces man. </l>
            <l>My father Baiazet is weake and old, </l>
            <l>And hath not much aboue two yeares to liue, </l>
            <l>The Turkish Crowne of Pearle and Ophir gold, </l>
            <l>He meanes to his deare Acomat to giue. </l>
            <l>But ere his ship can to her hauen driue, </l>
            <l>Ile send abroad my tempests in such sort, </l>
            <l>That she shall sinke before she get the port. </l>
            <l>Alasse, alasse, his highnesse aged head </l>
            <l>Is not sufficient to support a Crowne, </l>
            <l>Then Selimus take thou it in his leed, </l>
            <l>And if at this thy boldnesse he dare frowne, </l>
            <l>Or but resist thy will, then pull him downe: </l>
            <l>For since he hath so short a time t'enioy it, </l>
            <l>Ile make it shorter, or I will destroy him. </l>
            <l>Nor passe I what our holy votaries </l>
            <l>Shall here obiect against my forward minde, </l>
            <l>I wreake not of their foolish ceremonies, </l>
            <l>But meane to take my fortune as I finde, </l>
            <l>Wisedome commands to follow tide and winde: </l>
            <l>And catch the front of swift occasion, </l>
            <l>Before she be too quickly ouergone: </l>
            <l>Some man will say I am too impious, </l>
            <l>Thus to laie siege against my fathers life, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-006-b"/>
            <l>And that I ought to follow vertuous </l>
            <l>And godly sonnes that vertue is a glasse </l>
            <l>Wherein I may my errant life behold, </l>
            <l>And frame my selfe by it in auncient mould. </l>
            <l>Good sir, your wisedomes ouerflowing wit, </l>
            <l>Digs deepe with learnings wonder-working spade </l>
            <l>Perhaps you thinke that now forsooth you sit </l>
            <l>With some graue wisard in a pratling shade. </l>
            <l>Auant such glasses: let them view in me, </l>
            <l>The perfect picture of right tyrannie. </l>
            <l>I like a Lions looke not worth a leeke, </l>
            <l>When euery dog depriues him of his pray: </l>
            <l>These honest termes are farre inough to seeke. </l>
            <l>When angry Fortune menaceth decay, </l>
            <l>My resolution treads a nearer way. </l>
            <l>Giue me the heart conspiring with the hand, </l>
            <l>In such a cause my father to withstand. </l>
            <l>Is he my father? why I am his sonne: </l>
            <l>I owe no more to him then he to me, </l>
            <l>If he proceed as he hath now begunne, </l>
            <l>And passe from me the Turkish Seigniorie, </l>
            <l>To Acomat, then Selimus is free: </l>
            <l>And if he iniure me that am his sonne, </l>
            <l>Faith all the loue twixt him and me is done. </l>
            <l>But for I see the schoolemen are prepard, </l>
            <l>To plant gainst me their bookish ordinance, </l>
            <l>I meane to stand on a sentencious gard: </l>
            <l>And without any far fetcht circumstance, </l>
            <l>Quickly vnfold mine owne opinion, </l>
            <l>To arme my heart with irreligion. </l>
            <l>When first this circled round, this building faire, </l>
            <l>Some God tooke out of the confused masse, </l>
            <l>(What God I do not know, nor greatly care) </l>
            <l>Then euery man of his owne dition was, </l>
            <l>And euery one his life in peace did passe. </l>
            <l>Warre was not then, and riches were not knowne, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-007-a"/>
            <l>And no man said this● or this is mine owne, </l>
            <l>The plough-man with a furrow did not marke </l>
            <l>How farre his great possessions did reach: </l>
            <l>The earth knew not the share, nor seas the barke. </l>
            <l>The souldiers entred not the battred breach, </l>
            <l>Nor Trumpets the tantara loud did teach. </l>
            <l>There needed them no iudge nor yet no law, </l>
            <l>Nor any King of whom to stand in awe. </l>
            <l>But after Ninus, warlike Belus sonne, </l>
            <l>The earth with vnknowne armour did warray, </l>
            <l>Then first the sacred name of King begunne: </l>
            <l>And things that were as common as the day, </l>
            <l>Did then to set possessours first obey. </l>
            <l>Then they establisht lawes and holy rites </l>
            <l>To maintaine peace, and gouerne bloodie fights. </l>
            <l>Then some sage man, aboue the vulgar wise, </l>
            <l>Knowing that lawes could not in quiet dwell, </l>
            <l>Vnlesse they were obserued did first deuise </l>
            <l>The names of Gods, religion heauen and hell, </l>
            <l>And gan of paines, and faind rewards to tell. </l>
            <l>Paines for those men which did neglect the law, </l>
            <l>Rewards, for those that liu'd in quiet awe. </l>
            <l>Whereas indeed they were meer fictions, </l>
            <l>And if they were not Selim thinkes they were: </l>
            <l>And these religions obseruations, </l>
            <l>Onely bug-beares to keepe the world in feare, </l>
            <l>And make men quietly a yoake to beare, </l>
            <l>So that religion of it selfe a bable, </l>
            <l>Was onely found to make vs peaceable </l>
            <l>Hence in especiall come the foolish names, </l>
            <l>Of father, mother, brother and such like: </l>
            <l>For who so well his cogitation frames, </l>
            <l>Shall finde they serue but onely for to strike </l>
            <l>Into our minds a certaine kind of loue. </l>
            <l>For these names too are but a policie, </l>
            <l>To keepe the quiet of societie </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-007-b"/>
            <l>Indeed I must confesse they are not bad, </l>
            <l>Because they keepe the baser sort in feare? </l>
            <l>But we, whose minde in heauenly thoughts is clad, </l>
            <l>Whose bodie doth a glorious spirit beare, </l>
            <l>That hath no bounds, but flieth euery where. </l>
            <l>Why should we seeke to make that soule a slaue, </l>
            <l>To which dame Nature so large freedome gaue. </l>
            <l>Amongst vs men, there is some difference, </l>
            <l>Of actions tearmed by vs good or ill: </l>
            <l>As he that doth his father recompence, </l>
            <l>Differs from him that doth his father kill. </l>
            <l>And yet I thinke thinke other what they will, </l>
            <l>That Parricides, when death hath giuen them rest, </l>
            <l>Shall haue as good a part as the rest. </l>
            <l>And thats iust nothing, for as I suppose </l>
            <l>In deaths voyd kingdome raignes eternall night: </l>
            <l>Secure of euill, and secure of foes, </l>
            <l>Where nothing doth the wicked man affright, </l>
            <l>No more then him that dies in doing right. </l>
            <l>Then since in death nothing shall to vs fall, </l>
            <l>Here while I liue, Ile haue a snatch at all. </l>
            <l>And that can neuer, neuer be attaind, </l>
            <l>Vnlesse old Baiazet do die the death: </l>
            <l>For long inough the gray-beard now hath raign'd, </l>
            <l>And liu'd at ease, while others liu'd vneath. </l>
            <l>And now its time he should resigne his breath. </l>
            <l>T'were good for him if he were pressed out, </l>
            <l>T'would bring him rest, and rid him of his gout. </l>
            <l>Resolu'd to do it, cast to compasse it </l>
            <l>Without delay or long procrastination: </l>
            <l>It argueth an vnmanured wit, </l>
            <l>When all is readie for so strong inuasion, </l>
            <l>To draw out time, an vnlookt for mutation </l>
            <l>May soone preuent vs if we do delay, </l>
            <l>Quick speed is good, where wisedome leades the way. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000793-008-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000793-occhiali" xml:id="ep000793-e104130">
          <speaker>Occhi. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e104150">
          <speaker>Sel. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Lo flie boy to my father Baiazet </l>
            <l>And tell him Selim his obedient sonne, </l>
            <l>Desires to speake with him and kisse his hands, </l>
            <l>Tell him I long to see his gratious face, </l>
            <l>And that I come with all my chiualrie, </l>
            <l>To chase the Christians from his Signiorie </l>
            <l>In any wise say I must speake with him. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000793-e104250">Exit Occhiali. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Now Sinam if I speed. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-sinam" xml:id="ep000793-e104270">
          <speaker>Sinam. </speaker>
          <l>What then my Lord? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e104290">
          <speaker>Sel. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>What then? why Sinam thou art nothing woorth, </l>
            <l>I will endeuour to persuade him man, </l>
            <l>To giue the Empire ouer vnto me, </l>
            <l>Perhaps I shall attaine it at his hands: </l>
            <l>If I cannot, this right hand is resolu'd, </l>
            <l>To end the period with a fatall stabbe. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-sinam" xml:id="ep000793-e104370">
          <speaker>Sin. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>My gratious Lord giue Sinam leaue to speake, </l>
            <l>If you resolue to worke your fathers death, </l>
            <l>You venture life: thinke you the Ianissaries </l>
            <l>Will suffer you to kill him in their sight, </l>
            <l>And let you passe free without punishment? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e104440">
          <speaker>Sel. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>If I resolue? as sure as heauen is heauen, </l>
            <l>I meane to see him dead, or my selfe King: </l>
            <l>As for the Bassaes they are all my friends, </l>
            <l>And I am sure would pawne their dearest blood, </l>
            <l>That Selim might be Emperour of Turkes. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-sinam" xml:id="ep000793-e104510">
          <speaker>Sim. </speaker>
          <l>Yet Acomat and Corcut both suruiue, </l>
          <l>To be reuenged for their fathers death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e104540">
          <speaker>Sel. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Sinam if they or twentie such as they, </l>
            <l>Had twentie seuerall Armies in the field, </l>
            <l>If Selimus were once your Emperour </l>
            <l>Ide dart abroad the thunderbolts of warre, </l>
            <l>And mow their hartlesse squadrons to the ground. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-sinam" xml:id="ep000793-e104610">
          <speaker>Sin. </speaker>
          <l>Oh yet my Lord after your highnesse death, </l>
          <l>There is a hell and a reuenging God. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000793-008-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e104640">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Tush Sinam these are schoole conditions, </l>
            <l>To feare the diuell or his cursed damme: </l>
            <l>thinkst thou I care for apparitions, </l>
            <l>Of Sisiphus and of his backward stone, </l>
            <l>And poore Ixions lamentable mone? </l>
            <l>Now I thinke the caue of damned ghoasts, </l>
            <l>Is but a tale to terrifie yoong babes: </l>
            <l>Like diuels faces scor'd on painted poasts, </l>
            <l>Or fained circles in our astrolabes. </l>
            <l>Why theirs no difference when we are dead, </l>
            <l>And death once come, then all alike are sped. </l>
            <l>Or if there were, as I can scarce beleeue, </l>
            <l>A heauen of ioy, and hell of endlesse paine: </l>
            <l>Yet by my soule it neuer should me greeue: </l>
            <l>So I might on the Turkish Empire raigne, </l>
            <l>To enter hell, and leane on faire heauens gaine. </l>
            <l>An Empire Sinam, is so sweete a thing, </l>
            <l>As I could be a diuell to be a King. </l>
            <l>But go we Lords and solace in our campe, </l>
            <l>Till the returne of yoong Occhiali, </l>
            <l>And if his answere be to thy desire, </l>
            <l>Selim thy minde in kingly thoughts attire. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e104880">Exeunt. All. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e104890">Enter Baiazet, Mustaffa, Cherseoli, Occhiali, and the Ianissaries. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e104900">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Euen as the great Aegyptian Crocodile, </l>
            <l>Wanting his praye, with artificiall teares, </l>
            <l>And fained plaints his subtill tongue doth file, </l>
            <l>T'entrap the silly wandring traueller, </l>
            <l>And moue him to aduance his footing neare, </l>
            <l>That when he is in danger of his clawes, </l>
            <l>He may deuour him with his famished iawes, </l>
            <l>So plaieth craftie Selimus with me, </l>
            <l>His haughtie thoughts still wait on Diadems, </l>
            <l>And not a step but treads to maiestie. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-009-a"/>
            <l>The Phoenix gazeth on the Suns bright beames, </l>
            <l>The Echinaeis swimmes against the streames. </l>
            <l>Nought but the Turkish scepter can him please, </l>
            <l>And there I know lieth his chiefe disease. </l>
            <l>He sends his messenger to craue accesse, </l>
            <l>And saies he longs to kisse my aged hands: </l>
            <l>But howsoeuer he in shew professe, </l>
            <l>His meaning with his words but weakly stands. </l>
            <l>And sooner will the Syrteis boyling sands, </l>
            <l>Become a quiet roade for fleeting shippes, </l>
            <l>Then Selimus heart agree with Selims lippes </l>
            <l>Too well I know the Crocodiles fained teares, </l>
            <l>Are but nettes wherein to catch his pray: </l>
            <l>Which who so mou'd with foolish pitie heares, </l>
            <l>Will be the authour of his owne decay </l>
            <l>Then hie thee Baiazet from hence away: </l>
            <l>A fawning monster is false Selimus, </l>
            <l>Whose fairest words are most pernicious. </l>
            <l>Yoong man, would Selim come and speak with vs? </l>
            <l>What is his message to vs, canst thou tell? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-occhiali" xml:id="ep000793-e105220">
          <speaker>Occhi. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>He craues my Lord, another seigniorie, </l>
            <l>Nearer to you and to the Christians, </l>
            <l>That he may make them know, that Selimus </l>
            <l>Is borne to be a scourge vnto them all. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e105280">
          <speaker>Baia </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Hee's born to be a scourge to me &amp; mine, </l>
            <l>He neuer would haue come with such an hoast, </l>
            <l>Vnlesse he meant my state to vndermine, </l>
            <l>What though in word he brauely seeme to boast, </l>
            <l>The forraging of all the Christian coast? </l>
            <l>Yet we haue cause to feare when burning brands, </l>
            <l>Are vainly giuen into a mad mans hands. </l>
            <l>Well I must seeme to winke at his desire, </l>
            <l>Although I see it plainer then the light, </l>
            <l>My lenitie addes fuell to his fire, </l>
            <l>Which now begins to breake in flashing bright, </l>
            <l>Then Baiazet chastise his stubborne spright. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-009-b"/>
            <l>Least these small sparkles grow to such a flame, </l>
            <l>As shall consume thee and thy houses name. </l>
            <l>A lasse I spare when all my store is gone, </l>
            <l>And thrust my sickle where the corne is reapt, </l>
            <l>In vaine I send for the phisition, </l>
            <l>When on the patient is his graue dust heapt. </l>
            <l>In vaine, now all his veines in venome sleept </l>
            <l>Breake out in blisters that will poyson vs, </l>
            <l>We seeke to giue him an Antidotus. </l>
            <l>He that will stop the brooke, must then begin </l>
            <l>When sommers heate hath dried vp his spring, </l>
            <l>And when his pittering streames are low &amp; thin, </l>
            <l>For let the winter aide vnto him bring, </l>
            <l>He growes to be of watry flouds the King. </l>
            <l>And though you dam him vp with loftie rankes, </l>
            <l>Yet will he quickly ouerflow his bankes. </l>
            <l>Messenger, go and tell yoong Selimus, </l>
            <l>We giue to him all great Samandria, </l>
            <l>Bordring on Bulgrade of Hungaria, </l>
            <l>Where he may plague those Christian runnages, </l>
            <l>And salue the wounds that they haue giuen our states, </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-cherseoli" xml:id="ep000793-e105630">
          <speaker>Cherseo. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Go and prouide a gift, </l>
            <l>A royall present for my Selimus, </l>
            <l>And tell him messenger another time </l>
            <l>He shall haue talke inough with Baiazet. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000793-e105700">Exeunt Cherseoli and Occhiali. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>And now what counsell giues Mustaffa to vs? </l>
            <l>I feare this hastie reckoning will vndo vs. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mustaffa" xml:id="ep000793-e105730">
          <speaker>Must. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Make haste my Lord from Andrinople walles, </l>
            <l>And let vs flie to faire Bizantium, </l>
            <l>Least if your sonne before you take the towne, </l>
            <l>He may with little labour winne the crowne. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e105790">
          <speaker>Baia </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Then do so good Mustaffa, call our gard, </l>
            <l>And gather all our warlike Ianissaries, </l>
            <l>Our chiefest ayd is swift celeritie, </l>
            <l>Then let our winged coursers tread the winde, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-010-a"/>
            <l>And leaue rebellious Selimus behinde. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e105860">Exeunt. All. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e105870">Enter Selimus, Sinam, Occhiali, Ottrante, and their souldiers. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e105880">
          <speaker>Selim. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>And is his answere so Occhiali? </l>
            <l>Is Selim such a corsiue to his heart, </l>
            <l>That he cannot endure the sight of him? </l>
            <l>Forsooth he giues thee all Samandria, </l>
            <l>From whence our mightie Emperour Mahomet, </l>
            <l>Was driuen to his country backe with shame. </l>
            <l>No doubt thy father loues thee Selimus, </l>
            <l>To make thee Regent of so great a land, </l>
            <l>Which is not yet his owne: or if it were, </l>
            <l>What dangers wayt on him that should it stere. </l>
            <l>Here the Polonian he comes hurtling in, </l>
            <l>Vnder the conduct of some forraine prince, </l>
            <l>To fight in honour of his crucifix! </l>
            <l>Here the Hungarian with his bloodie crosse, </l>
            <l>Deales blowes about to win Belgrade againe. </l>
            <l>And after all, forsooth Basilius </l>
            <l>The mightie Emperour of Russia, </l>
            <l>Sends in his troupes of slaue-borne Muscouites, </l>
            <l>And he will share with vs, or else take all. </l>
            <l>In giuing such a land so full of strife, </l>
            <l>His meaning is to rid me of my life. </l>
            <l>Now by the dreaded name of Termagant, </l>
            <l>And by the blackest brooke in loathsome hell, </l>
            <l>Since he is so vnnaturall to me, </l>
            <l>I will prooue as vnnaturall as he. </l>
            <l>Thinks he to stop my mouth with gold or pearle? </l>
            <l>Or rustie iades ●et from Barbaria? </l>
            <l>No let his minion his philosopher, </l>
            <l>Corcut and Acomat be enrich'd with them. </l>
            <l>I will not take my rest, till this right hand </l>
            <l>Hath puld the Crowne from off his cowards head, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-010-b"/>
            <l>And on the ground his bastards gore-blood shead: </l>
            <l>Nor shall his flight to old Bizantium, </l>
            <l>Dismay my thoughts which neuer learnd to stoup. </l>
            <l>March Sinam, march in order after him: </l>
            <l>Were his light steeds as swift as Pegasus, </l>
            <l>And trode the ayrie pauement with their heeles, </l>
            <l>Yet Selimus would ouertake them soone. </l>
            <l>And though the heauens do nere so crosly frowne, </l>
            <l>In spight of heauen shall Selim weare the crowne. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e106300">Exeunt. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e106310">Alarum within. Enter Baiazet, Mustaffa, Cherseoli and the Ianissaries, at one doore. Selimus, Sinam, Ottrante, Occhiali, and their souldiers at another. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e106320">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Is this thy dutie sonne vnto thy father, </l>
            <l>So impiously to leuell at his life? </l>
            <l>Can thy soule wallowing in ambitious mire, </l>
            <l>Seeke for to reaue that brest with bloudie knife, </l>
            <l>From whence thou hadst thy being Selimus? </l>
            <l>Was this the end for which thou ioyndst thy selfe, </l>
            <l>With that mischieuous traytor Ramirchan? </l>
            <l>Was this thy drift to speake with Baiazet? </l>
            <l>Well hoped I (but hope I see is vaine) </l>
            <l>Thou wouldst haue bene a comfort to mine age, </l>
            <l>A scourge and terrour to mine enemies, </l>
            <l>That this thy comming with so great an hoast, </l>
            <l>Was for no other purpose and intent, </l>
            <l>Then for to chastise those base Christians </l>
            <l>Which spoile my subiects welth with fire &amp; sword </l>
            <l>Well hoped I the rule of Trebisond, </l>
            <l>Would haue increasde the valour of thy minde, </l>
            <l>To turne thy strength vpon thy Persians. </l>
            <l>But thou like to a craftie Polipus, </l>
            <l>Doest turne thy hungry iawes vpon thy selfe, </l>
            <l>For what am I Selimus but thy selfe? </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-011-a"/>
            <l>When courage first crept in thy manly brest, </l>
            <l>And thou beganst to rule the martiall sword, </l>
            <l>How oft said thou the sun shuld change his course, </l>
            <l>Water should turn to earth, &amp; earth to heauen </l>
            <l>Ere thou wouldst prooue disloyall to thy father. </l>
            <l>O Titan turne thy breathlesse coursers backe, </l>
            <l>And enterprise thy iourny from the East </l>
            <l>Blush Selim that the world should say of thee, </l>
            <l>That by my death thou gaindst the Emperie. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e106640">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Now let my cause be pleaded Baiazet, </l>
            <l>For father I disdaine to call thee now: </l>
            <l>I tooke not Armes to seaze vpon thy crowne, </l>
            <l>For that if once thou hadst bene layd in graue, </l>
            <l>Should sit vpon the head of Selimus </l>
            <l>In spight of Corcut and Acomat. </l>
            <l>I tooke not Armes to take away thy life, </l>
            <l>The remnant of thy dayes is but a span, </l>
            <l>And foolish had I bene to enterprize </l>
            <l>That which the gout and death would do for me. </l>
            <l>I tooke not armes to shed my brothers blood, </l>
            <l>Because they stop my passage to the crowne. </l>
            <l>For while thou liu'st Selimus is content </l>
            <l>That they shuld liue, but when thou once art dead </l>
            <l>Which of them both dares Selimus withstand? </l>
            <l>I soone should hew their bodies in peecemeale, </l>
            <l>As easie as a man would kill a gnat. </l>
            <l>But I tooke armes vnkind to honour thee, </l>
            <l>And winne againe the fame that thou hast lost. </l>
            <l>And thou thoughtst scorne Selim should speake with thee. </l>
            <l>But had it bene your darling Acomat, </l>
            <l>You would haue met him half the way your selfe. </l>
            <l>I am a Prince, and though your yoonger sonne, </l>
            <l>Yet are my merits better then both theirs: </l>
            <l>But you do seeke to disinherit me, </l>
            <l>And meane t'inuest Acomat with your crowne. </l>
            <l>So he shall haue a princes due reward, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-011-b"/>
            <l>That cannot shew a scarre receiu'd in field, </l>
            <l>We that haue fought with mighty Prester Iohn, </l>
            <l>And stript th' Aegyptian soldan of his camp, </l>
            <l>Venturing life and liuing to honour thee, </l>
            <l>For that same cause shall now dishonour'd be. </l>
            <l>Art thou a father? Nay ●al●e Baiazet </l>
            <l>Disclaime the title which thou doest not merit. </l>
            <l>A father would not thus flee from his sonne, </l>
            <l>As thou doest flie from loyall Selimus. </l>
            <l>A father would not iniure thus his sonne, </l>
            <l>As thou doest iniure loyall Selimus. </l>
            <l>Then Baiazet prepare thee to the fight, </l>
            <l>Selimus once thy sonne, but now thy foe, </l>
            <l>Will make his fortunes by the sword, </l>
            <l>And since thou fear'st as long as I do liue, </l>
            <l>Ile also feare, as long as thou doest liue. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e107090">Exeunt Selim and his company. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e107100">
          <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>My heart is ouerwhelm'd with fear &amp; grief, </l>
            <l>What dismall Comet blazed at my birth, </l>
            <l>Whose influence makes my strong vnbrideled sonnes </l>
            <l>In steed of loue to render hate to me? </l>
            <l>Ah Bassaies if that euer heretofore </l>
            <l>Your Emperour ought his safetie vnto you, </l>
            <l>Defend me now gainst my vnnaturall sonne: </l>
            <l>Non timeo mortem: mortis mihi displicet author. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e107200">Exit Baiazet and his company. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e107210">Alarum, Mustaffa beate Selimus in, then Ottrante and Cherseoli enter at diuerse doores. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-cherseoli" xml:id="ep000793-e107220">
          <speaker>Cherse. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Yeeld thee Tartarian or thou shalt die, </l>
            <l>Vpon my swords sharpe point standeth pale death </l>
            <l>Readie to riue in two thy caitiue brest. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-ottrante" xml:id="ep000793-e107270">
          <speaker>Ott. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Art thou that knight that like a lion fierce, </l>
            <l>Tiring his stomacke on a flocke of lambes, </l>
            <l>Hast broke our rankes &amp; put them cleane to flight? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000793-012-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000793-cherseoli" xml:id="ep000793-e107320">
          <speaker>Cherse. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>I and vnlesse thou looke vnto thy selfe, </l>
            <l>This swoord nere drunke in the Tartarian blood, </l>
            <l>Shall make thy carkasse as the outcast dung. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-ottrante" xml:id="ep000793-e107370">
          <speaker>Ottran. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Nay I haue matcht a brauer knight then you, </l>
            <l>Strong Alemshae thy maisters eldest sonne, </l>
            <l>Leauing his bodie naked on the plaines, </l>
            <l>And Turke, the selfesame end for thee remaines. </l>
            <l>They fight. He killeth Cherseoli, and flieth. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e107440">Alarum, enter Selimus. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e107450">
          <speaker>Selim. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Shall Selims hope be buried in the dust? </l>
            <l>And Baiazet triumph ouer his fall? </l>
            <l>Then oh thou blindfull mistresse of mishap, </l>
            <l>Chiefe pratronesse of Rhamus golden gates, </l>
            <l>I will aduance my strong reuenging hand, </l>
            <l>And plucke thee from thy euerturning wheele. </l>
            <l>Mars, or Minerua, Mahound, Termagaunt, </l>
            <l>Or who so ere you are that fight gainst me, </l>
            <l>Come and but shew your selues before my face, </l>
            <l>And I will rend you all like trembling reedes. </l>
            <l>Well Baiazet though Fortune smile on thee, </l>
            <l>And decke thy campe with glorious victorie, </l>
            <l>Though Selimus now conquered by thee, </l>
            <l>Is faine to put his safetie in swift flight: </l>
            <l>Yet so he flies, that like an angry ramme, </l>
            <l>Heele turne more fiercely then before he came. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e107630">Exit Selimus. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e107640">Enter Baiazet, Mustaffa, the souldier witth the bodie of Cherseoli, and Ottrante prisoner. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e107650">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Thus haue we gaind a bloodie victorie, </l>
            <l>And though we are the maisters of the field, </l>
            <l>Yet haue we lost more then our enemies: </l>
            <l>Ah lucklesse fault of my Cherseoli, </l>
            <l>As deare and dearer wert thou vnto me, </l>
            <l>Then any of my sonnes, then mine owne selfe. </l>
            <l>When I was glad, thy heart was full of ioy, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-012-b"/>
            <l>And brauely hast thou died for Baiazet. </l>
            <l>And though thy bloudlesse bodie here do lie, </l>
            <l>Yet thy sweet soule in heauen for euer blest, </l>
            <l>Among the starres enioyes eternall rest. </l>
            <l>What art thou warlike man of Tartarie, </l>
            <l>Whose hap it is to be our prisoner? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-ottrante" xml:id="ep000793-e107800">
          <speaker>Ottran. </speaker>
          <l>I am a prince, Ottrante is my name, </l>
          <l>Chiefe captaine of the Tartars mightie hoast. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e107830">
          <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
          <l>Ottrante? Wast not thou that slue my son? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-ottrante" xml:id="ep000793-e107850">
          <speaker>Ottran. </speaker>
          <l>I, and if fortune had but fauour'd me, </l>
          <l>Had sent the ●ire to keepe him company. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e107880">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Off with his head and spoyle him of his Armes, </l>
            <l>And leaue his bodie for the ayrie birds. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000793-e107930">Exit one with Ottrante. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>The vnreuenged ghoast of Alemshae, </l>
            <l>Shall now no more wander on Stygian bankes, </l>
            <l>But rest in quiet in th' Elysian fields. </l>
            <l>Mustaffa, and you worthie men at Armes, </l>
            <l>That left not Baiazet in greatest need, </l>
            <l>When we arriue at Constantines great Tour, </l>
            <l>You shalbe honour'd of your Emperour. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e108010">Exeunt All. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e108020">Enter Acomat Visir, Regan, and a band of souldiers. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e108030">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Perhaps you wonder why prince Acomat, </l>
            <l>Delighting heretofore in foolish loue, </l>
            <l>Hath chang'd his quiet to a souldiers state: </l>
            <l>And turnd the dulcet tunes of Himens song, </l>
            <l>Into Bellonas horrible outcries, </l>
            <l>You thinke it strange, that whereas I haue liu'd, </l>
            <l>Almost a votarie to wantonnesse, </l>
            <l>To see me low laie off effeminate robes, </l>
            <l>And arme my bodie in an iron wall. </l>
            <l>I haue enioyed quiet long enough, </l>
            <l>And surfeted with pleasures suquidrie </l>
            <l>A field of dainties I haue passed through, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-013-a"/>
            <l>And bene a champion to faire Cytheree. </l>
            <l>Now since this idle peace hath weeried me, </l>
            <l>Ile follow Mars and warre another while, </l>
            <l>And die my shield in dolorous vermeil. </l>
            <l>My brother Selim through his manly deeds, </l>
            <l>Hath lifted vp his fame vnto the skies, </l>
            <l>While we like earth wormes lurking in the weeds, </l>
            <l>Do liue inglorious in all mens eyes. </l>
            <l>What lets me then from this vaine slumber rise, </l>
            <l>And by strong hand atchieue eternall glorie, </l>
            <l>That may be talkt of in all memorie? </l>
            <l>And see how fortune fauours mine intent, </l>
            <l>Heard you not Lordings, how prince Selimus </l>
            <l>Against our royall father armed went, </l>
            <l>And how the Ianissaries made him flee </l>
            <l>To Ramir Emperour of Tartarie? </l>
            <l>This his rebellion greatly profits me, </l>
            <l>For I shall sooner winne my fathers minde, </l>
            <l>To yeeld me vp the Turkish Empire, </l>
            <l>Which if I haue, I am sure I shall finde </l>
            <l>Strong enemies to pull me downe againe, </l>
            <l>That faine would haue prince Selimus to raigne. </l>
            <l>Then ciuill discord, and contentious warre, </l>
            <l>Will follow Acomats coronation. </l>
            <l>Selim no doubt will broach seditious iarre, </l>
            <l>And Corcut too will seeke for alteration, </l>
            <l>Now to preuent all suddaine perturbation, </l>
            <l>We thought it good to muster vp our power, </l>
            <l>That danger may not take it vnprouided. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-visir" xml:id="ep000793-e108460">
          <speaker>Visir. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>I like your highnesse resolution well, </l>
            <l>For these should be the chiefe arts of a king, </l>
            <l>To punish those that furiously rebell, </l>
            <l>And honour those that sacred counsell bring, </l>
            <l>To make good lawes, ill customes to expell: </l>
            <l>To nourish peace from whence your riches spring, </l>
            <l>And when good quarrels call you to the field, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-013-b"/>
            <l>T'excell your men in handling speare &amp; shield. </l>
            <l>Thus shall the glory of your matchlesse name, </l>
            <l>Be registred vp in immortall lines: </l>
            <l>Whereas that prince that followes lustfull game </l>
            <l>And to fond toyes his captiue minde enclines, </l>
            <l>Shall neuer passe the temple of true fame, </l>
            <l>Whose worth is greater then the Indian mines. </l>
            <l>But is your grace assured certainly </l>
            <l>That Baiazet doth fauour your request? </l>
            <l>Perhaps you may make him your enemie, </l>
            <l>You know how much your father doth detest, </l>
            <l>Stout obedience and obstinacie. </l>
            <l>I speake not this as if I thought it best: </l>
            <l>Your highnesse should your right in it neglect, </l>
            <l>But that you might be close and circumspect. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e108700">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>We thanke thee Visir for thy louing care, </l>
            <l>As for my father Baiazets affection, </l>
            <l>Vnlesse his holy vowes forgotten are, </l>
            <l>I shall be sure of it by his election. </l>
            <l>By after Acomats erection, </l>
            <l>We must forecast what things be necessary, </l>
            <l>Least that our kingdome be too momentary. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-regan" xml:id="ep000793-e108790">
          <speaker>Reg. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>First let my Lord be seated in his throne, </l>
            <l>Enstalled by great Baiazets consent, </l>
            <l>As yet your haruest is not fully growne, </l>
            <l>But in the greene and vnripe blade is pent: </l>
            <l>But when you once haue got the regiment, </l>
            <l>Then may your Lords more easily prouide, </l>
            <l>Against all accidents that may betide. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e108880">
          <speaker>Acomat. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Then set we forward to Bizantium, </l>
            <l>That we may know what Baiazet intends. </l>
            <l>Aduise thee Acomat, whats best to do, </l>
            <l>The Ianissaries fauour Selimus, </l>
            <l>And they are strong vndanted enemies, </l>
            <l>Which will in Armes gainst thy election rise. </l>
            <l>Then will them to thy wil with precious gifts </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-014-a"/>
            <l>And store of gold: timely largition </l>
            <l>The stedfast persons from their purpose lifts: </l>
            <l>But then beware least Baiazets affection </l>
            <l>Change into hatred by such premunition. </l>
            <l>For then he thinke that I am factious, </l>
            <l>And imitate my brother Selimus. </l>
            <l>Besides, a prince his honour doth debase, </l>
            <l>That begs the common souldiers suffrages, </l>
            <l>And if the Bassaes knew I sought their grace, </l>
            <l>It would the more increase their insolentnesse. </l>
            <l>To resist them were ouerhardinesse, </l>
            <l>And worse it were to leaue my enterprize. </l>
            <l>Well how so ere, resolue to venture it, </l>
            <l>Fortune doth fauour euery bold assay, </l>
            <l>And t'were a trick of an vnsetled wit </l>
            <l>Because the bees haue stings with them alway, </l>
            <l>To fare our mouthes in honie to embay. </l>
            <l>Then resolution for me leades the dance, </l>
            <l>And thus resolu'd, I meane to trie my chance. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e109160">Exeunt all. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e109170">Enter Baiazet, Mustaffa, Calibassa, Halibassa, and the Ianizaries. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e109180">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>What prince so ere, trusts to his mightie pow'r, </l>
            <l>Ruling the reines of many nations, </l>
            <l>And feareth not least fickle fortune loure, </l>
            <l>Ar thinkes his kingdome free from alterations, </l>
            <l>If he were in the place of Baiazet, </l>
            <l>He would but litle by his scepter set. </l>
            <l>For what hath rule that makes it acceptable, </l>
            <l>Rather what hath it not worthie of hate: </l>
            <l>First of all is our state still mutable, </l>
            <l>And our continuance at the peoples rate, </l>
            <l>So that it is a slender thred, whereon </l>
            <l>Depends the honour of a princes throne. </l>
            <l>Then do we feare, more then the child new borne, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-014-b"/>
            <l>Our friends, our Lords, our subiects, &amp; our sonnes. </l>
            <l>Thus is our minde in sundry pieces torne </l>
            <l>By care, by feare, suspition, and distrust, </l>
            <l>In wine, in meate we feare pernicious poyson, </l>
            <l>At home, abroad, we feare seditious treason. </l>
            <l>Too true that tyrant Dionysius </l>
            <l>Did picture out the image of a King, </l>
            <l>When Daniocles was placed in his throne, </l>
            <l>And ore his head a threatning sword did hang, </l>
            <l>Fastned vp onely by a horses haire. </l>
            <l>Our chiefest trust is secretly distrust, </l>
            <l>For whom haue we whom we may safely trust, </l>
            <l>If our owne sonnes, neglecting awfull dutie, </l>
            <l>Rise vp in Armes against their louing fathers. </l>
            <l>Their heart is all of hardest marble wrought, </l>
            <l>That can laie wayt to take away their breath, </l>
            <l>From whom they first sucked this vitall ayre. </l>
            <l>My heart is heauie, and I needs must sleepe. </l>
            <l>Bassaes withdraw your selues from me awhile, </l>
            <l>That I may rest my ouerburdned soule. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e109530">They stand aside while the curtins are drawne. </stage>
          <l>Eunuchs plaie me some musicke while I sleepe. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e109550">Musicke within. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mustaffa" xml:id="ep000793-e109560">
          <speaker>Must. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Good Baiazet, who would not pitie thee, </l>
            <l>Whom thine owne sonne so vildly persecutes. </l>
            <l>More mildly do th'vnreasonable beasts </l>
            <l>Deale with their dammes, then Selimus with thee. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-unassigned" xml:id="ep000793-e109620">
          <speaker>Halibas. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Mustaffa we are princes of the land, </l>
            <l>And loue our Emperour as well as thou: </l>
            <l>Yet will we not for pitying his estate, </l>
            <l>Suffer our foes our wealth to ruinate. </l>
            <l>If Selim haue playd false with Baiazet, </l>
            <l>And ouerslipt the dutie of a sonne, </l>
            <l>Why he was mou'd by iust occasion. </l>
            <l>Did he not humbly send his messenger </l>
            <l>To craue accesse vnto his maiestie? </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-015-a"/>
            <l>And yet he could not get permission </l>
            <l>To kisse his hands, and speake his mind to him. </l>
            <l>Perhaps he thought his aged fathers loue </l>
            <l>Was cleane estrang'd from him: and Acomat </l>
            <l>Should reape the fruite that he had laboured for. </l>
            <l>Tis lawfull for the father to take Armes, </l>
            <l>I and by death chastize his rebell sonne. </l>
            <l>Why should it be vnlawfull for the sonne, </l>
            <l>To leauie Armes gainst his iniurious sire? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mustaffa" xml:id="ep000793-e109820">
          <speaker>Must. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>You reason Hali like a sophister. </l>
            <l>As if t'were lawfull for a subiect prince </l>
            <l>To rise in Armes gainst his soueraigne, </l>
            <l>Because he will not let him haue his will: </l>
            <l>Much lesse ist lawfull for a mans owne sonne. </l>
            <l>If Baiazet had iniur'd Selimus, </l>
            <l>Or sought his death, or done him some abuse, </l>
            <l>Then Selimus cause had bene more tollerable. </l>
            <l>But Baiazet did neuer iniure him, </l>
            <l>Nor sought his death, nor once abused him, </l>
            <l>Vnlesse because he giues him not the crowne, </l>
            <l>Being the yoongest of his highnesse sonnes. </l>
            <l>Gaue he not him an Empire for his part, </l>
            <l>The mightie Empire of great Trebisond? </l>
            <l>So that if all things rightly be obseru'd, </l>
            <l>Selim had more then euer he deseru'd. </l>
            <l>I speake not this because I hate the prince, </l>
            <l>For by the heauens I loue yoong Selimus, </l>
            <l>Better then either of his brethren. </l>
            <l>But for I owe alleagiance to my king, </l>
            <l>And loue him much that fauours me so much. </l>
            <l>Mustaffa, while old Baiazet doth liue, </l>
            <l>Will be as true to him as to himselfe. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-cali" xml:id="ep000793-e110070">
          <speaker>Cali. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Why braue Mustaffa, Hali and my selfe </l>
            <l>Were neuer false vnto his maiestie </l>
            <l>Our father Hali died in the field, </l>
            <l>Against the Sophi, in his highnesse warres. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-015-b"/>
            <l>And we will neuer be degenerate. </l>
            <l>Nor do we take part with prince Selimus, </l>
            <l>Because we would depose old Baiazet, </l>
            <l>But for because we would not Acomat </l>
            <l>That leads his life still in lasciuious pompe, </l>
            <l>Nor Corcut, though he be a man of woorth, </l>
            <l>Should be commander of our Empire. </l>
            <l>For he that neuer saw his foe mans face, </l>
            <l>But alwaies slept vpon a Ladies lap, </l>
            <l>Will scant endure to lead a souldiers life. </l>
            <l>And he that neuer handled but his penne, </l>
            <l>Will be vnskilfull at the warlike lance. </l>
            <l>Indeed his wisedome well may guide the crowne, </l>
            <l>And keepe that safe his predecessors got: </l>
            <l>But being giuen to peace as Corcut is, </l>
            <l>He neuer will enlarge the Empire: </l>
            <l>So that the rule and power ouer vs, </l>
            <l>Is onely fit for valiant Selimus. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mustaffa" xml:id="ep000793-e110310">
          <speaker>Must. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Princes, you know how mightie Baiazet </l>
            <l>Hath honoured Mustaffa with his loue. </l>
            <l>He gaue his daughter beautious Solima, </l>
            <l>To be the soueraigne mistresse of my thoughts. </l>
            <l>He made me captaine of the Ianissaries, </l>
            <l>And too vnnaturall should Mustaffa be, </l>
            <l>To rise against him in his dying age. </l>
            <l>Yet know, you warlike peere, Mustaffa is </l>
            <l>A loyall friend vnto prince Selimus, </l>
            <l>And ere his other brethren get the crowne, </l>
            <l>For his sake, I my selfe will pull them downe. </l>
            <l>I loue, I loue them dearly, but the loue </l>
            <l>Which I do beare vnto my countries good, </l>
            <l>Makes me a friend to noble Selimus, </l>
            <l>Onely let Baiazet while he doth liue, </l>
            <l>Enioy in peace the Turkish Diademe. </l>
            <l>When he is dead, and layd in quiet graue, </l>
            <l>Then none but Selimus our helpe shall haue. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e110510">
          <pb xml:id="ep000793-016-a"/>Sound within. A Messenger enters, Baiazet awaketh. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e110520">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>How now Mustaffa, what newes haue we there? </l>
            <l>Is Selim vp in Armes gainst me againe? </l>
            <l>Or is the Sophi entred our confines? </l>
            <l>Hath the Aegyptian snatch'd his crowne againe? </l>
            <l>Or haue the vncontrolled Christians </l>
            <l>Vnsheath'd their swords to make more war on vs? </l>
            <l>Such newes, or none will come to Baiazet. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mustaffa" xml:id="ep000793-e110610">
          <speaker>Must. </speaker>
          <l>My gratious Lord, heres an Embassador </l>
          <l>Come from your sonne the Soldan Acomat. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e110640">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <l>From Acomat? oh let him enter in. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e110660">Enter Regian. </stage>
        <l>Embassadour, how fares our louing sonne? </l>
        <sp who="#ep000793-regan" xml:id="ep000793-e110680">
          <speaker>Reg. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Mightie commander of the warlike Turks, </l>
            <l>Acomat Souldane of Amasia; </l>
            <l>Greeteth your grace by me his messenger. </l>
            <l>He giues him a Letter. </l>
            <l>And gratulates your highnesse good successe, </l>
            <l>Wishing good fortune may befall you still. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e110760">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Mustaffa reade. </l>
            <l>He giues the letter to Mustaffa, and speakes the rest to himself. </l>
            <l>Acomat craues thy promise Baiazet, </l>
            <l>To giue the Empire vp into his hands, </l>
            <l>And make it sure to him in thy life time. </l>
            <l>And thou shalt haue it louely Acomat, </l>
            <l>For I haue bene encombred long inough, </l>
            <l>And vexed with the cares of kingly rule, </l>
            <l>Now let the trouble of the Empirie </l>
            <l>Be buried in the bosome of thy sonne. </l>
            <l>Ah Acomat, if thou haue such a raigne </l>
            <l>So full of sorrow as thy fathers was, </l>
            <l>Thou wilt accurse the time, the day and houre, </l>
            <l>In which thou was establish'd Emperour. </l>
            <l>Sound. A Messenger from Corcut. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-016-b"/>
            <l>Yet more newes? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-messenger" xml:id="ep000793-e110940">
          <speaker>Mess. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Long liue the mightie Emperor Baiazet, </l>
            <l>Corcut the Soldan of Magnesia, </l>
            <l>Hearing of Selims worthie ouerthrow, </l>
            <l>And of the comming of yoong Acomat, </l>
            <l>Doth certifie your maiestie by me, </l>
            <l>How ioyfull he is of your victorie. </l>
            <l>And there withall he humbly doth require </l>
            <l>Your grace would do him iustice in his cause. </l>
            <l>His brethren both, vnworthie such a father, </l>
            <l>Do seeke the Empire while your grace doth liue, </l>
            <l>And that by vndirect sinister meanes. </l>
            <l>But Corcuts mind free from ambitious thoughts, </l>
            <l>And trusting to the goodnesse of his cause, </l>
            <l>Ioyned vnto yours highnesse tender loue </l>
            <l>Onely desires your grace should not inuest </l>
            <l>Selim nor Acomat, in the Diademe, </l>
            <l>Which appertaineth vnto him by right, </l>
            <l>But keepe it to your selfe the while you liue: </l>
            <l>And when it shall the great creator please, </l>
            <l>Who hath the spirits of all men in his hands, </l>
            <l>Shall call your highnesse to your latest home, </l>
            <l>Then will he also sue to haue his right. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e111180">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Like to a ship sayling without starres, </l>
            <l>Whom waues do tosse one way and winds another, </l>
            <l>Both without ceasing: euen so my poore heart </l>
            <l>Endures a combat betwixt loue and right. </l>
            <l>The loue I beare to my deare Acomat, </l>
            <l>Commands me giue my suffrage vnto him, </l>
            <l>But Corcuts title, being my eldest sonne, </l>
            <l>Bids me recall my hand, and giue it him. </l>
            <l>Acomat, he would haue it in my life, </l>
            <l>But gentle Corcut like a louing sonne, </l>
            <l>Desires me liue and die an Emperour, </l>
            <l>And at my death bequeath my crowne to him. </l>
            <l>Ah Corcut thou I see lou'st me indeed, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-017-a"/>
            <l>Selimus sought to thrust me downe by force, </l>
            <l>And Acomat seekes the kingdome in my life, </l>
            <l>And both of them are grieu'd thou liu'st so long. </l>
            <l>But Corcut numbreth not my dayes as they, </l>
            <l>O how much dearer loues he me then they. </l>
            <l>Bassaes, how counsell you your Emperour? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mustaffa" xml:id="ep000793-e111390">
          <speaker>Must. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>My gratious Lord, my self wil speak for al, </l>
            <l>For all I know are minded as I am. </l>
            <l>Your highnesse knowes the Ianissaries loue, </l>
            <l>How firme they meane to cleaue to your behest, </l>
            <l>As well you might perceiue in that sad fight, </l>
            <l>When Selim set vpon you in your flight. </l>
            <l>Then we do all desire you on our knees, </l>
            <l>To keepe the crowne and scepter to your selfe. </l>
            <l>How grieuous will it be vnto your thoughts, </l>
            <l>If you should giue the crowne to Acomat, </l>
            <l>To see the brethren disinherited, </l>
            <l>To flesh their anger one vpon another, </l>
            <l>And rend the bowels of this mightie raigne. </l>
            <l>Suppose that Corcut would be well content, </l>
            <l>Yet thinkes your grace if Acomat were king, </l>
            <l>That Selim ere long would ioine league with him? </l>
            <l>Nay he would breake from forth his Trebisond, </l>
            <l>And waste the Empire all with fire and sword. </l>
            <l>Ah then too weake would be poore Acomat, </l>
            <l>To stand against his brothers puissance, </l>
            <l>Or saue himselfe from his enhanced hand. </l>
            <l>While Ismael and the cruell Persians, </l>
            <l>And the great Soldane of th' Egyptians, </l>
            <l>Would smile to see our force dismembred so, </l>
            <l>I and perchance the neighbour Christians </l>
            <l>Would take occasion to thrust out their heads. </l>
            <l>All this may be preuented by your grace, </l>
            <l>If you will yeeld to Corcuts iust request, </l>
            <l>And keepe the kingdome to you while you liue, </l>
            <l>Meane time we that your graces subiects are, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-017-b"/>
            <l>May make vs strong, to fortify the man, </l>
            <l>Whom at your death your grace shal chuse as king. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e111730">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>O how thou speakest euer like thy selfe, </l>
            <l>Loyall Mustaffa: well were Baiazet </l>
            <l>If all his sonnes, did beare such loue to him. </l>
            <l>Though loth I am longer to weare the crowne, </l>
            <l>Yet for I see it is my subiects will, </l>
            <l>Once more will Baiazet be Emperour. </l>
            <l>But we must send to pacific our sonne, </l>
            <l>Or he will storme, as earst did Selimus. </l>
            <l>Come let vs go vnto our councell Lord, </l>
            <l>And there consider what is to be done. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e111850">Exeunt All. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e111860">Enter Acomat, Regan, Visir, and his souldiers. Acomat must read a letter, and then renting it say: </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e111870">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Thus will I rend the crowne from off thy head, </l>
            <l>False hearted and iniurious Baiazet, </l>
            <l>To mocke thy sonne that loued thee so deare. </l>
            <l>What? for because the head-strong Ianissaries </l>
            <l>Would not consent to honour Acomat, </l>
            <l>And their base Bassaes vow'd to Selimus, </l>
            <l>Thought me vnworthie of the Turkish crowne, </l>
            <l>Should he be rul'd and ouerrul'd by them, </l>
            <l>Vnder pretence of keeping it himselfe, </l>
            <l>To wipe me cleane for euer being king? </l>
            <l>Doth he esteeme so much the Bassaes words, </l>
            <l>And prize their fauour at so high a rate, </l>
            <l>That for to gratifie their stubborne mindes, </l>
            <l>He casts away all care, and all respects </l>
            <l>Of dutie, promise, and religious oathes? </l>
            <l>Now by the holy Prophet Mahomet, </l>
            <l>Chiefe president and patron of the Turkes, </l>
            <l>I meane to chalenge now my right by Armes, </l>
            <l>And winne by sword that glorious dignitie </l>
            <l>Which he iniuriously detaines from me. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-018-a"/>
            <l>Haply he thinkes because that Selimus </l>
            <l>Rebutted by his warlike Ianissaries, </l>
            <l>Was faine to flie in hast from whence he came: </l>
            <l>That Acomat by his example mou'd, </l>
            <l>Will feare to manage Armes against his sire. </l>
            <l>Or that my life forepassed in pleasures court, </l>
            <l>Promises weake resistance in the fight: </l>
            <l>But he shall know that I can vse my swoord, </l>
            <l>And like a lyon seaze vpon my praie. </l>
            <l>If euer Selim mou'd him heretofore, </l>
            <l>Acomat meanes to mooue him ten times more. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-visir" xml:id="ep000793-e112200">
          <speaker>Visir. </speaker>
          <l>T'were good your grace would to Amasia, </l>
          <l>And there increase your camp with fresh supply. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e112230">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Visir, I am impatient of delaie, </l>
            <l>And since my father hath incenst me thus, </l>
            <l>Ile quench those kindled flames with his hart blood. </l>
            <l>Not like a sonne, but a most cruell foe, </l>
            <l>Will Acomat henceforth be vnto him. </l>
            <l>March to Natolia, there we will begin </l>
            <l>And make a preface to our massacres. </l>
            <l>My nephew Mahomet sonne to Alemshae, </l>
            <l>Departed lately from Iconium, </l>
            <l>Is lodged there, and he shall be the first </l>
            <l>Whom I will sacrifice vnto my wrath. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e112360">Exeunt All. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e112370">Enter the yoong Prince Mahomet, the Belierbey of Natolia, and one or two souldiers. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mahomet" xml:id="ep000793-e112380">
          <speaker>Maho. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Lord Gouernour, what thinke you best to doo? </l>
            <l>If we receiue the Souldaine Acomat, </l>
            <l>Who knoweth not but his blood-thirstie swoord </l>
            <l>Shall be embowell'd in our country-men. </l>
            <l>You know he is displeasde with Baiazet, </l>
            <l>And will rebell, as Selim did to fore, </l>
            <l>And would to God with Selims ouerthrow. </l>
            <l>You know his angrie heart hath vow'd reuenge </l>
            <l>On all the subiects of his fathers land. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000793-018-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000793-belierbey" xml:id="ep000793-e112490">
          <speaker>Bel. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Yoong prince, thy vncle seekes to haue thy life, </l>
            <l>Because by right the Turkish crowne is thine, </l>
            <l>Saue thou thy selfe by flight or otherwise, </l>
            <l>And we will make resistance as we can. </l>
            <l>Like an Armenian tygre, that hath lost </l>
            <l>Her loued whelpes, so raueth Acomat: </l>
            <l>And we must be subiect to his rage, </l>
            <l>But you may liue to venge your citizens. </l>
            <l>Then flie good prince before your vncle come. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mahomet" xml:id="ep000793-e112600">
          <speaker>Maho. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Nay good my Lord, neuer shall it be said </l>
            <l>That Mahomet the sonne of Alemshae, </l>
            <l>Fled from his citizens for feare of death, </l>
            <l>But I will staie, and helpe to fight for you, </l>
            <l>And if you needs must die, ile die with you. </l>
            <l>And I among the rest with forward hand, </l>
            <l>Will helpe to kill a common enemie. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e112690">Exeunt All. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e112700">Enter Acomat, Visir, Regan, and the souldiers. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e112710">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Now faire Natolia, shall thy stately walles </l>
            <l>Be ouerthrowne and beaten to the ground. </l>
            <l>My heart within me for reuenge still calles. </l>
            <l>Why Baiazet, thought'st thou that Acomat </l>
            <l>Would put vp such a monstrous iniurie? </l>
            <l>Then had I brought my chiualrie in vaine, </l>
            <l>And to no purpose drawne my conquering blade, </l>
            <l>Which now vnsheath'd, shal not be sheath'd againe, </l>
            <l>Till it a world of bleeding soules hath made. </l>
            <l>Poore Mahomet, thou thought'st thy selfe too sure, </l>
            <l>In thy strong citie of Iconium, </l>
            <l>To plant thy Forces in Natolia, </l>
            <l>Weakned so much before by Selims swoord. </l>
            <l>Summon a parley to the citizens, </l>
            <l>That they may heare the dreadfull words I speak, </l>
            <l>And die in thought before they come to blowes. </l>
            <l>All. A parley Mahomet, Belierbey, and souldiers on the walles. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000793-019-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mahomet" xml:id="ep000793-e112900">
          <speaker>Maho. </speaker>
          <l>What craues our vncle Acomat of vs? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e112920">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>That thou &amp; all the citie yeeld themselues, </l>
            <l>Or by the holie rites of Mahomet </l>
            <l>His wondrous tomb, and sacred Alcoran, </l>
            <l>You all shall die: and not a common death, </l>
            <l>But euen as monstrous as I can deuise. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mahomet" xml:id="ep000793-e112990">
          <speaker>Maho. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Vncle, if I may call you by that name, </l>
            <l>Which cruelly hunt for your nephewes blood, </l>
            <l>You do vs wrong thus to besiege our towne, </l>
            <l>That nere deseru'd such hatred at your hands, </l>
            <l>Being your friends and kinsmen as we are. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e113060">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <l>In that thou wrongst me that thou art my kinsman. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mahomet" xml:id="ep000793-e113080">
          <speaker>Maho. </speaker>
          <l>Why for I am thy nephew doest thou frowne? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e113100">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <l>I that thou art so neare vnto the crowne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mahomet" xml:id="ep000793-e113120">
          <speaker>Maho. </speaker>
          <l>Why vncle I resigne my right to thee, </l>
          <l>And all my title were it nere so good. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e113150">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Wilt thou? then know assuredly from me, </l>
            <l>Ile seale the resignation with thy blood: </l>
            <l>Though Alemshae thy father lou'd me well, </l>
            <l>Yet Mahomet thy sonne shall downe to hell. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mahomet" xml:id="ep000793-e113210">
          <speaker>Mah. </speaker>
          <l>Why vncle doth my life put you in feare? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e113230">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <l>It shall not nephew, since I haue you here. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mahomet" xml:id="ep000793-e113250">
          <speaker>Maho. </speaker>
          <l>When I am dead mote hindrers shalt thou finde. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e113270">
          <speaker>Acom. </speaker>
          <l>When ones cut off, the fewer are behinde. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mahomet" xml:id="ep000793-e113290">
          <speaker>Maho. </speaker>
          <l>Yet thinke the gods do beare an equall eye. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e113310">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <l>Faith if they all were squint-ey'd, what care I. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mahomet" xml:id="ep000793-e113330">
          <speaker>Maho. </speaker>
          <l>Then Mahomet know we will rather die, </l>
          <l>Then yeeld vs vp into a tyrants hand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e113360">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Beshrew me but you be the wiser Mahomet, </l>
            <l>For if I do but catch you boy aliue, </l>
            <l>Twere better for you runne through Phlegiton. </l>
            <l>Sirs scale the walles, and pull the caitiues downe, </l>
            <l>I giue to you the spoyle of all the towne. </l>
            <l>Alarum. Scale the walles. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e113440">Enter Acomat, Visir and Regan, with Mahomet. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e113450">
          <speaker>Acom. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Now yoongster, you that brau'dst vs on the walles, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-019-b"/>
            <l>And shooke your plumed crest against our shield, </l>
            <l>What wouldst thou giue, or what wouldst thou not giue, </l>
            <l>That thou wert far inough from Acomat? </l>
            <l>How like the villaine is to Baiazet? </l>
            <l>Wel nephew for thy father lou'd me well, </l>
            <l>I will not deale extreemly with his sonne: </l>
            <l>Then heare a briefe compendium of thy death. </l>
            <l>Regan go cause a groue of steelehead speares, </l>
            <l>Be pitched thicke vnder the castle wall, </l>
            <l>And on them let this youthfull captaine fall. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mahomet" xml:id="ep000793-e113580">
          <speaker>Ma. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Thou shalt not fear me Acomat with death, </l>
            <l>Nor will I beg my pardon at thy hands. </l>
            <l>But as thou giu'st me such a monstrous death, </l>
            <l>So do I freely leaue to thee my curse: </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e113640">Exit Regan with Mahomet. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e113650">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <l>O, that wil serue to fil my fathers purse. </l>
          <l>Alarum. Enter a souldier with Zonara, sister to Mahomet. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-zonara" xml:id="ep000793-e113680">
          <speaker>Zon. </speaker>
          <l>Ah pardon me deare vncle, pardon me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e113700">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <l>No minion, you are too neare a kin to me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-zonara" xml:id="ep000793-e113720">
          <speaker>Zon. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>If euer pitie entered thy brest, </l>
            <l>Or euer thou wast touch'd with womans loue, </l>
            <l>Sweete vncle spare wretched Zonaras life. </l>
            <l>Thou once wast noted for a quiet prince, </l>
            <l>Soft-hearted, mild, and gentle as a lambe, </l>
            <l>Ah do not prooue a lyon vnto me. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e113800">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <l>Why would'st thou liue, when Mahomet is dead? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-zonara" xml:id="ep000793-e113820">
          <speaker>Ron. </speaker>
          <l>Ah who slew Mahomet? Vncle did you? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e113840">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <l>He thats prepar'd to do as much for you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-zonara" xml:id="ep000793-e113860">
          <speaker>Zon. </speaker>
          <l>Doest thou not pitie Alemshae in me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e113880">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <l>Yes that he wants so long thy companie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-zonara" xml:id="ep000793-e113900">
          <speaker>Zon. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Thou art not false groome son to Baiazet, </l>
            <l>He would relent to heare a woman weepe, </l>
            <l>But thou wast borne in desart Cavcasus, </l>
            <l>And the Hircanian tygres gaue thee sucke, </l>
            <l>Knowing thou wert a monster like themselues. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000793-020-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e113970">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Let you her thus to rate vs? Strangle her. </l>
            <l>They strangle her. </l>
            <l>Now scoure the streets, and leaue not one aliue </l>
            <l>To carrie these sad newes to Baiazet. </l>
            <l>That all the citizens may dearly say, </l>
            <l>This day was fatall to Natolia. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e114050">Exeunt All. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e114060">Enter Baiazet, Mustaffa, and the Ianissaries. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e114070">
          <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Mustaffa, if my minde deceiue me not, </l>
            <l>Some strange misfortune is not farre from me. </l>
            <l>I was not wont to tremble in this sort. </l>
            <l>Me thinkes I feele a cold run through my bones, </l>
            <l>As if it hastned to surprize my heart, </l>
            <l>Me thinkes some voice still whispereth in my eares </l>
            <l>And bids me to take heed of Acomat. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mustaffa" xml:id="ep000793-e114160">
          <speaker>Must. </speaker>
          <l>Tis but your highnesse ouercharged mind </l>
          <l>Which feareth most the things it least desires. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e114190">Enter two souldiers with the Belierbey of Natolia in a chaire, and the bodie of Mahomet and Zonara, in two coffins. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e114200">
          <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Ah sweet Mustaffa, thou art much deceiu'd, </l>
            <l>My minde presages me some future harme, </l>
            <l>And loe what dolefull exequie is here. </l>
            <l>Our chiefe commander of Natolia? </l>
            <l>What caitiue hand is it hath wounded thee? </l>
            <l>And who are these couered in tomblack hearse? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-belierbey" xml:id="ep000793-e114280">
          <speaker>Bel. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>These are thy nephewes mightie Baiazet, </l>
            <l>The sonne and daughter of good Alemshae, </l>
            <l>Whom cruell Acomat hath murdred thus. </l>
            <l>These eyes beheld, when from an ayrie toure, </l>
            <l>They hurld the bodie of yoong Mahomet, </l>
            <l>Whereas a band of armed souldiers, </l>
            <l>Receiued him falling on their speares sharp points. </l>
            <l>His sister poore Zonara, </l>
            <l>Entreating life and not obtaining it, </l>
            <l>Was strangled by his barbarous souldiers. </l>
            <l>Baiazet fals in a sownd, and being recouered say: </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000793-020-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e114410">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Oh you dispencers of our haplesse breath, </l>
            <l>Why do you glut your eyes, and take delight </l>
            <l>To see sad pageants of mens miseries? </l>
            <l>Wherefore haue you prolong'd my wretched life, </l>
            <l>To see my sonne my dearest Acomat, </l>
            <l>To lift his hands against his fathers life? </l>
            <l>Ah Selimus, now do I pardon thee, </l>
            <l>For thou did'st set vpon me manfully, </l>
            <l>And mou'd by an occasion, though vniust. </l>
            <l>But Acomat, iniurious Acomat, </l>
            <l>Is tentimes more vnnaturall to me. </l>
            <l>Haplesse Zonara, haplesse Mahomet, </l>
            <l>The poore remainder of my Alemshae, </l>
            <l>Which of you both shall Baiazet most waile? </l>
            <l>Ah both of you are worthie to be wailde. </l>
            <l>Happily dealt the froward fates with thee, </l>
            <l>Good Alemshae, for thou didst die in field, </l>
            <l>And so preuentedst this sad spectacle, </l>
            <l>Pitifull spectacle of sad dreeriment, </l>
            <l>Pitifull spectacle of dismall death. </l>
            <l>But I haue liu'd to see thee Alemshae, </l>
            <l>By Tartar Pirates all in peeces torne. </l>
            <l>To see yoong Selims disobedience. </l>
            <l>To see the death of Alemshaes poore seed. </l>
            <l>And last of all to see my Acomat </l>
            <l>Prooue a rebellious enemie to me. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-belierbey" xml:id="ep000793-e114690">
          <speaker>Beli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Ah cease your teares vnhappie Emperour, </l>
            <l>And shead not all for your poore nephews death. </l>
            <l>Six thousand of true-hearted citizens </l>
            <l>In faire Natolia, Acomat hath slaine: </l>
            <l>The channels run like riuerets of blood, </l>
            <l>And I escap'd with this poore compande, </l>
            <l>Bemangled and dismembred as you see, </l>
            <l>To be the messenger of these sad newes. </l>
            <l>And now mine eyes fast swimming in pale death, </l>
            <l>Bids me resigne my breath vnto the heauens, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-021-a"/>
            <l>Death stands before readie for to strike. </l>
            <l>Farewell deare Emperour and reuenge our losse, </l>
            <l>As euer thou doest hope for happinesse. He dies. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e114840">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Auernus iawes and loathsome Taenarus, </l>
            <l>From whence the damned ghoasts do often creep, </l>
            <l>Back to the world to punish wicked men. </l>
            <l>Black Demogorgon, grandfather of night, </l>
            <l>Send out thy furies from thy firie hall, </l>
            <l>The pitilesse Erynnies arm'd with whippes, </l>
            <l>And all the damned monsters of black hell, </l>
            <l>To powre their plagues on cursed Acomat. </l>
            <l>How shall I mourne, or which way shall I turne </l>
            <l>To powre my teares vpon my dearest friends? </l>
            <l>Couldst thou endue false-hearted Acomat, </l>
            <l>To kill thy nephew and thy sister thus, </l>
            <l>And wound to death so valiant a Lord? </l>
            <l>And will you not you al beholding heauens, </l>
            <l>Dart down on him your piercing lightning brand, </l>
            <l>Enrold in sulphur, and consuming flames? </l>
            <l>Ah do not Ioue, Acomat is my sonne, </l>
            <l>And may perhaps by counsell be reclaim'd, </l>
            <l>And brought to filiall obedience. </l>
            <l>Aga thou art a man of peirsant wit, </l>
            <l>Go thou and talke with my sonne Acomat, </l>
            <l>And see if he will any way relent </l>
            <l>Speake him faire Aga, least he kill thee too. </l>
            <l>And we my Lords will in, and mourne a while, </l>
            <l>Ouer these princes lamentable tombs. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e115110">Exeunt all. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e115120">Enter Acomat, Visir, Regan, and their souldiers. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e115130">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>As Tityus in the countrie of the dead, </l>
            <l>With restlesse cries doth call, vpon high Iove </l>
            <l>The while the vulture tireth on his heart, </l>
            <l>So Acomat, revenge still gnawes thy soule. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-021-b"/>
            <l>In sheading blood, and murthring innocents. </l>
            <l>I thinke my wrath hath bene too patient, </l>
            <l>Since ciuill blood quencheth not out the flames </l>
            <l>Which Baiazet hath kindled in my heart. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-visir" xml:id="ep000793-e115230">
          <speaker>Visir. </speaker>
          <l>My gratious Lord, here is a messenger </l>
          <l>Sent from your father the Emperour. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e115260">Enter Aga, and one with him. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e115270">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <l>Let him come in: Aga what newes with you? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-aga" xml:id="ep000793-e115290">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Great Prince, thy father mightie Baiazet, </l>
            <l>Wonders your grace whom he did loue so much, </l>
            <l>And thought to leaue possessour of the crowne, </l>
            <l>Would thus requite his loue with mortall hate, </l>
            <l>To kill thy nephewes with reuenging sword, </l>
            <l>And massacre his subiects in such sort. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e115370">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Aga, my father traitrous Baiazet, </l>
            <l>Detaines the crowne iniuriously from me, </l>
            <l>Which I will haue if all the world say nay. </l>
            <l>I am not like the vnmanured land, </l>
            <l>Which answeres not his honours greedie mind: </l>
            <l>I sow not seeds vpon the barren sand, </l>
            <l>A thousand wayes can Acomat soone finde, </l>
            <l>To gaine my will, which if I cannot gaine, </l>
            <l>Then purple blood my angry hands shall staine. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-aga" xml:id="ep000793-e115480">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>Acomat, yet learne by Selimus, </l>
          <l>That hastie purposes haue hated endes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e115510">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Tush Aga, Selim was not wise inough </l>
            <l>To set vpon the head at the first brunt: </l>
            <l>He should haue done as I do meane to do, </l>
            <l>Fill all the confines, with fire, sword, and blood▪ </l>
            <l>Burne vp the fields, and ouerthrow whole townes, </l>
            <l>And when he had endammaged that way, </l>
            <l>Then teare the old man peecemeale with my teeth, </l>
            <l>And colour my strong hands with his gore-blood. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-aga" xml:id="ep000793-e115610">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>O see my Lord, how fell ambition </l>
            <l>Deceiues your sences and bewitches you, </l>
            <l>Could you vnkind performe so foule a deed, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-022-a"/>
            <l>As kill the man that first gaue life to you? </l>
            <l>Do you not feare the peoples aduerse fame? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e115680">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>It is the greatest glorie of a king </l>
            <l>When, though his subiects hate his wicked deeds </l>
            <l>Yet are they forst to beare them all with praise. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-aga" xml:id="ep000793-e115730">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>Whom feare constraines to praise their princes deeds, </l>
          <l>That feare, eternall hatred in them feeds. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e115760">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>He knowes not how to sway the kingly mace, </l>
            <l>That loues to be great in his peoples grace: </l>
            <l>The surest ground for kings to build vpon, </l>
            <l>Is to be fear'd and curst of euery one. </l>
            <l>What though the world of nations me hate? </l>
            <l>Hate is peculiar to a princes state. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-aga" xml:id="ep000793-e115840">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Where ther's no shame, no care of holy law, </l>
            <l>No faith, no iustice, no integritie, </l>
            <l>That state is full of mutabilitie. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e115890">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Bare faith, pure vertue, poore integritie, </l>
            <l>Are ornaments fit for a priuate man, </l>
            <l>Beseemes a prince for to do all he can. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-aga" xml:id="ep000793-e115940">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>Yet know it is a sacrilegious will, </l>
          <l>To slaie thy father were he nere so ill. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e115970">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Tis lawfull gray-beard for to do to him, </l>
            <l>What ought not to be done vnto a father. </l>
            <l>Hath he not wip't me from the Turkish crowne? </l>
            <l>Preferr'd he not the stubborne Ianizaries, </l>
            <l>And heard the Bassaes stout petitions, </l>
            <l>Before he would giue eare to my request? </l>
            <l>As sure as day, mine eyes shall nere tast sleepe, </l>
            <l>Before my sword haue riuen his periur'd brest. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-aga" xml:id="ep000793-e116070">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>Ah let me neuer liue to see that day. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e116090">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Yes thou shalt liue, but neuer see that day, </l>
            <l>Wanting the tapers that should giue thee light: </l>
            <l>Puls out his eyes. </l>
            <l>Thou shalt not see so great felicitie, </l>
            <l>When I shall rend out Baiazets dimme eyes, </l>
            <l>And by his death install my selfe a king. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000793-022-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000793-aga" xml:id="ep000793-e116170">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Ah cruell tyrant and vnmercifull, </l>
            <l>More bloodie then the Anthropomphagi, </l>
            <l>That fill their hungry stomachs with mans flesh. </l>
            <l>Thou shouldst haue slaine me barbarous Acomat, </l>
            <l>Not leaue me in so comfortlesse a life </l>
            <l>To liue on earth, and neuer see the sunne. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e116250">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <l>Nay let him die that liueth at his ease, </l>
          <l>Death would a wretched caitiue greatly please. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-aga" xml:id="ep000793-e116280">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>And thinkst thou then to scape vnpunished, </l>
            <l>No Acomat, though both mine eyes be gone, </l>
            <l>Yet are my hands left on to murther thee. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e116330">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>T'was wel remembred: Regan cut them off. </l>
            <l>They cur of his hands and giue them Acomat. </l>
            <l>Now in that sort go tell thy Emperour </l>
            <l>That if himselfe had but bene in thy place, </l>
            <l>I would haue vs'd him crueller then thee: </l>
            <l>Here take thy hands: I know thou lou'st them wel. </l>
            <l>Opens his bosome, and puts them in. </l>
            <l>Which hand is this? right? or left? canst thou tell? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-aga" xml:id="ep000793-e116430">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>I know not which it is, but tis my hand. </l>
            <l>But oh thou supreme architect of all, </l>
            <l>First mouer of those tenfold christall orbes, </l>
            <l>Where all those mouing, and vnmouing eyes </l>
            <l>Behold thy goodnesse euerlastingly: </l>
            <l>See, vnto thee I lift these bloudie armes, </l>
            <l>For hands I haue not for to lift to thee, </l>
            <l>And in thy iustice dart thy smouldring flame </l>
            <l>Vpon the head of cursed Acomat. </l>
            <l>Oh cruell heauens and iniurious fates, </l>
            <l>Euen the last refuge of a wretched man, </l>
            <l>Is tooke from me: for how can Aga weepe? </l>
            <l>Or ruine a brinish shew'r of pearled teares? </l>
            <l>Wanting the watry cesternes of his eyes? </l>
            <l>Come lead me backe againe to Baiazet, </l>
            <l>The wofullest, and sadd'st Embassadour </l>
            <l>That euer was dispatch'd to any King. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000793-023-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e116620">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Why so, this musicke pleases Acomat. </l>
            <l>And would I had my doating father here, </l>
            <l>I would rip vp his breast, and rend his heart, </l>
            <l>Into his bowels thrust my angry hands, </l>
            <l>As willingly, and with as good a mind, </l>
            <l>As I could be the Turkish Emperour. </l>
            <l>And by the cleare declining vault of heauen, </l>
            <l>Whither the soules of dying men do flee, </l>
            <l>Either I meane to dye the death my selfe, </l>
            <l>Or make that old false faitour bleed his last. </l>
            <l>For death no sorrow could vnto me bring, </l>
            <l>So Acomat might die the Turkish king. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e116760">Exeunt All. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e116770">Enter Baiazet, Mustaffa, Cali, Hali, and Aga led by a souldier, who keeling before Baiazet, and holding his legs shall say: </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-aga" xml:id="ep000793-e116780">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Is this the bodie of my soueraigne? </l>
            <l>Are these the sacred pillars that support </l>
            <l>The image of true magnanimitie? </l>
            <l>Ah Baiazet, thy sonne false Acomat </l>
            <l>Is full resolued to take thy life from thee: </l>
            <l>Tis true, tis true, witnesse these handlesse armes, </l>
            <l>Witnesse these emptie lodges of mine eyes, </l>
            <l>Witnesse the gods that from the highest heauen </l>
            <l>Beheld the tyrant with remorcelesse heart, </l>
            <l>Puld out mine eyes, and cut off my weake hands. </l>
            <l>Witnesse that sun whose golden coloured beames </l>
            <l>Your eyes do see, but mine can nere behold: </l>
            <l>Witnesse the earth that sucked vp my blood, </l>
            <l>Streaming in riuers from my tronked armes. </l>
            <l>Witnesse the present that he sends to thee, </l>
            <l>Open my bosome, there you shall it see. </l>
            <l>Mustaffa opens his bosome and takes out his hands. </l>
            <l>Those are the hands, which Aga once did vse, </l>
            <l>To tosse the speare, and in a warlike gyre </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-023-b"/>
            <l>To hurtle my sharpe sword about my head, </l>
            <l>Those sends he to the wofull Emperour, </l>
            <l>With purpose so cut thy hands from thee. </l>
            <l>Why is my soueraigne silent all this while? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e117030">
          <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Ah Aga, Baiazet faine would speak to thee, </l>
            <l>But sodaine sorrow eateth vp my words. </l>
            <l>Baiazet Aga, faine would weepe for thee, </l>
            <l>But cruell sorrow drieth vp my teares. </l>
            <l>Baiazet Aga, faine would die for thee, </l>
            <l>But griefe hath weakned my poore aged hands. </l>
            <l>How can he speak, whose tongue sorrow hath tide? </l>
            <l>How can he mourne, that cannot shead a teare? </l>
            <l>How shall he liue, that full of miserie </l>
            <l>Calleth for death, which will not let him die? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mustaffa" xml:id="ep000793-e117150">
          <speaker>Must. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Let women weep, let children powre ●oo●● </l>
            <l>And cowards spend the time in bootlesse mone. </l>
            <l>Wee'l load the earth with such a mightie hoast </l>
            <l>Of Ianizaries, sterne-borne sonnes of Mars, </l>
            <l>That Phaeb shall flie and hide him in the cloudes </l>
            <l>For feare our iauelins thrust him from his waine. </l>
            <l>Old Aga was a Prince among your Lords, </l>
            <l>His Councels alwaies were true oracles, </l>
            <l>And shall he thus vnmanly be misus'd, </l>
            <l>And he vnpunished that did the deed? </l>
            <l>Shall Mahomet and poore Zonaras ghoasts </l>
            <l>And the good gouernour of Natalia </l>
            <l>Wander in Stygian meadowes vneueng'd </l>
            <l>Good Emperour stir vp thy manly hearte </l>
            <l>And send forth all thy warlike Ianizaries </l>
            <l>To chastise that rebellious Acomat </l>
            <l>Thou knowst we cannot fight without a guide, </l>
            <l>And he must be one of the royall bloode </l>
            <l>Sprung from the loines of mightie Ottoman, </l>
            <l>And who remaines now, but yoong Selimus </l>
            <l>So please your grace to pardon his offence, </l>
            <l>And 〈…〉 </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000793-024-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e117390">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>I good Mustaffa, send for Selimus, </l>
            <l>So I may be reueng'd I care not how, </l>
            <l>The worst that can befall me is but death, </l>
            <l>That would end my wofull miserie. </l>
            <l>Selimus he must worke me this good turne, </l>
            <l>I cannot kill my selfe, hee'l do't for me. </l>
            <l>Come Aga, thou and I will weepe the while: </l>
            <l>Thou for thy eyes and losse of both thy hands, </l>
            <l>I for th'vnkindnesse of my Acomat. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e117500">Exeunt All. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e117510">Enter Selimus, and a messenger with a letter from Baiazet. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e117520">
          <speaker>Selim. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Will fortune fauour me yet once againe? </l>
            <l>And will she thrust the cards into my hands? </l>
            <l>Well if I chance but once to get the decke, </l>
            <l>To deale about and shufle as I would: </l>
            <l>Let Selim neuer see the day-light spring, </l>
            <l>Vnlesse I shuffle out my selfe a king. </l>
            <l>Friend let me see thy letter once againe, </l>
            <l>That I may read these reconciling lines. </l>
            <l>Reades the letter. </l>
            <l>Thou hast a pardon Selim granted thee. </l>
            <l>Mustaffa and the forward Ianizaries </l>
            <l>Haue sued to thy father Baiazet, </l>
            <l>That thou maist be their captaine generall </l>
            <l>Against th'attempts of Souldane Acomat. </l>
            <l>Why thats the thing that I requested most, </l>
            <l>That I might once th'imperiall armie leade: </l>
            <l>And since its offred me so willingly, </l>
            <l>Beshrew me but ile take their curtesie. </l>
            <l>Soft let me see is there no policie </l>
            <l>T'entrap poore Selimus in this deuice? </l>
            <l>It may be that my father feares me yet, </l>
            <l>Least I should once againe rise vp in armes, </l>
            <l>And like Antaeus queld by Hercules, </l>
            <l>Gather new forces by my ouerthrow: </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-024-b"/>
            <l>And therefore sends for me vnder pretence </l>
            <l>Of this, and that: but when he hath me there, </l>
            <l>Hee'll make me sure for putting him in feare </l>
            <l>Distrust is good, when theirs cause or distrust </l>
            <l>Read it againe, perchance thou doest mistake. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000793-e117840">Reade. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>O, heer's Mustaffas signet ●et thereto </l>
            <l>Then Selim cast all foolish feare aside, </l>
            <l>For hee's a Prince that fauours thy estate, </l>
            <l>And hateth treason worse then death it selfe. </l>
            <l>And hardly can I thinke he could be brought </l>
            <l>If there were treason, to subscribe his name. </l>
            <l>Come friend, the cause requires we shuld be gone, </l>
            <l>Now once againe haue at the Turkish throne </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e117930">Exeunt Both. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e117940">Enter Baiazet leading Aga, Mustaffa, Hali, Cali, Selimus, the Ianizaries. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e117950">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Come mournfull Aga, come and sit by me, </l>
            <l>Thou hast bene sorely grieu'd for Baiazet, </l>
            <l>Good reason then that he should grieue for thee. </l>
            <l>Giue me thy arm, though thou hast lost thy hands, </l>
            <l>And liu'st as a poore exile in this light, </l>
            <l>Yet hast thou wonne the heart of Baiazet, </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-aga" xml:id="ep000793-e118030">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Your graces words are verie comfortable, </l>
            <l>And well can Aga beare his grieuous losse, </l>
            <l>Since it was for so good a Princes sake. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e118080">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Father, if I may call thee by that name, </l>
            <l>Whose life I aim'd at with rebellious sword: </l>
            <l>In all humilitie thy reformed sonne, </l>
            <l>Offers himselfe into your graces hands, </l>
            <l>And at your feete laieth his bloodie sword, </l>
            <l>Which he aduanc'd against your maiestie. </l>
            <l>If my offence do seeme so odious </l>
            <l>That I deserue not longer time to liue, </l>
            <l>Behold I open vnto you my brest, </l>
            <l>Readie prepar'd to die at your command. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-025-a"/>
            <l>But if repentance in vnfained heart </l>
            <l>And sorrow for my grieuous crime forepast, </l>
            <l>May merit pardon at your princely hands. </l>
            <l>Behold where poore inglorious Selimus </l>
            <l>Vpon his knees begs pardon of your grace. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e118250">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Stand vp my son, I ioy to heare thee speak, </l>
            <l>But more to heare thou art so well reclaim'd. </l>
            <l>Thy crime was nere so odious vnto me, </l>
            <l>But thy reformed life and humble thoughts </l>
            <l>Are thrice as pleasing to my aged spirit. </l>
            <l>Selim we here pronounce thee by our will, </l>
            <l>Chiefe generall of the warlike Ianizaries </l>
            <l>Go lead them out against false Acomat, </l>
            <l>Which hath so grieuously rebell'd gainst me. </l>
            <l>Spare him not Selim, though he be my sonne, </l>
            <l>Yet do I now cleane disinherit him, </l>
            <l>As common enemy to me and mine. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e118390">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>May Selim liue to shew how dutifull </l>
            <l>And louing he will be to Baiazet. </l>
            <l>So now doth fortune smile on me againe </l>
            <l>And in regard of former iniuries </l>
            <l>Offer me millions of Diadems: </l>
            <l>I smile to see how that the good old man, </l>
            <l>Thinks Selims thoughts are broght to such an ebbe </l>
            <l>As he hath cast off all ambitious hope. </l>
            <l>But soone shall that opinion be remou'd, </l>
            <l>For if I once get mongst the Ianizaries </l>
            <l>Then on my head the golden crowne shall sit. </l>
            <l>Well Baiazet, I feare me thou wilt greeue, </l>
            <l>That ere thou didst thy faining sonne beleeue, </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e118540">Exit Selim, with all the rest saue Baiazet and Aga </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e118550">
          <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Now Aga, all the thoghts that troubled me, </l>
            <l>Do rest within the center of my heart, </l>
            <l>And thou shalt shortly ioy as much with me, </l>
            <l>Then Acomat by Selims consuming sword, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-025-b"/>
            <l>Shall leese that ghoast which made thee loose thy sight. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-aga" xml:id="ep000793-e118620">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Ah Baiazet, Aga lookes not for reuenge, </l>
            <l>But will powre out his praiers to the heauens, </l>
            <l>That Acomat may learne by Selimus, </l>
            <l>To yeeld himselfe vp to his fathers grace. </l>
            <l>Sound within, long liue Selimus Emperour of Turkes. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e118690">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <l>How now, what sodaine triumph haue we here? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mustaffa" xml:id="ep000793-e118710">
          <speaker>Must. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Ah gratious Lord, the captaines of the hoste, </l>
            <l>With one assent haue crown'd Prince Selimus, </l>
            <l>And here he comes with all the Ianizaries, </l>
            <l>To craue his confirmation at thy hands. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e118770">Enter Cali Bassa, Selimus, Hali Bassa, Sinam, and the Ianizaries. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-sinam" xml:id="ep000793-e118780">
          <speaker>Sinam. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Baiazet, we the captaines of thy hoast, </l>
            <l>Knowing thy weake and too vnwildie age, </l>
            <l>Vnable is longer to gouerne vs: </l>
            <l>Haue chosen Selimus thy yoonger sonne </l>
            <l>That he may be our leader and our guide, </l>
            <l>Against the Sophi and his Persians, </l>
            <l>Gainst the victorious Soldane Tonumbey. </l>
            <l>Their wants but thy consent, which we wil haue, </l>
            <l>Or hew thy bodie peece-meale with our swords. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e118890">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Needs must I giue, what is alreadie gone. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000793-e118930">He takes of his crowne. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Here Selimus, thy father Baiazet </l>
            <l>Weeried with cares that wait vpon a king, </l>
            <l>Resignes the crowne as willingly to thee, </l>
            <l>As ere my father gaue it vnto me. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000793-e118990">Sets it on his head. </stage>
            </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-all" xml:id="ep000793-e119000">
          <speaker>All. </speaker>
          <l>Long liue Selimus Emperour of Turkes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e119020">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Liue thou a long and a victorious raigne, </l>
            <l>And be triumpher of thine enemies </l>
            <l>Aga and I will to Dimoticum </l>
            <l>And liue in peace the remnant of our dayes. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e119080">Exit Baiazet and Aga. </stage>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000793-026-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e119090">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Now sit I like the arme strong son of loue, </l>
            <l>When after he had all his monsters quell'd </l>
            <l>He was recein'd in heauen mongst the gods, </l>
            <l>And had faire Hebe for his louely bride. </l>
            <l>As many labours Selimus hath had, </l>
            <l>And now at length attained to the crowne, </l>
            <l>This is my Hebe, and this is my heaven </l>
            <l>Baiazet goeth to Dimeticum, </l>
            <l>And there he purposes to liue at ease, </l>
            <l>But Selimus, as long as he is on earth, </l>
            <l>Thou shalt not sleep in rest without some broyle </l>
            <l>For Baiazet is vnconstant as the winde </l>
            <l>To make that sure I haue a platforme laid. </l>
            <l>Baiazet hath with him a cunning Iew, </l>
            <l>Professing phisicke, and so skill'd therein, </l>
            <l>As if he had pow'r ouer life and death. </l>
            <l>Withall, a man so stout and resolute, </l>
            <l>That he will venture any thing for gold </l>
            <l>This Iew with some intoxicated drinke, </l>
            <l>Shall poyson Baiazet and that blind Lord, </l>
            <l>Then one of Hydraes heads is cleane cut off. </l>
            <l>Go some and fetch Abraham the Iewe </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000793-e119340">Exit one for Abraham. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Corcut, thy pageant next is to be plaid. </l>
            <l>For though he be a graue Philosopher, </l>
            <l>Giuen to read Mahomets dread Iewes, </l>
            <l>And Razins toyes, and Auicennaes drugges </l>
            <l>Yet he may haue a longing for the crowne. </l>
            <l>Besides, he may by diuellish Negromancie </l>
            <l>Procure my death or worke my ouerthrow, </l>
            <l>The diuell still is readie to do harme. </l>
            <l>Hali, you and your brother presently. </l>
            <l>Shall with an armie to Magnesia, </l>
            <l>There you shall find the scholler at his booke, </l>
            <l>And hear'st thou Hali? strangle him. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000793-e119480">Exeunt Hali, and Cali. </stage>
            </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-026-b"/>
            <l>Corcut once dead, then Acomat remaines, </l>
            <l>Whose death wil make me certaine of the crowne. </l>
            <l>These heads of Hydra are the principall, </l>
            <l>When these are off, some other will arise, </l>
            <l>As Amurath and Aladin, sonnes to Acomat, </l>
            <l>My sister Solyma, Mustaffaes wife, </l>
            <l>All these shall suffer shipwrack on a shelfe, </l>
            <l>Rather then Selim will be drown'd himselfe. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000793-e119580">Enter Abraham the Iew. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Iew thou art welcome vnto Selimus, </l>
            <l>I haue a piece of seruice for you sir, </l>
            <l>But on your life be secret in the deed. </l>
            <l>Get a strong poyson, whose enuenom'd taste </l>
            <l>May take away the life of Baiazet, </l>
            <l>Before he passe forth of Bizantium. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-abraham" xml:id="ep000793-e119650">
          <speaker>Abra. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>I warrant you my gratious soueraigne, </l>
            <l>He shall be quickly sent vnto his graue </l>
            <l>For I haue potions of so strong a force, </l>
            <l>That whosoeuer touches them shall die. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000793-e119720">Speakes aside. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>And wold your grace would once but tast of them </l>
            <l>I could as willingly affoord them you, </l>
            <l>As your aged father Baiazet. </l>
            <l>My Lord, I am resolu'd to do the deed. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e119770">Exit Abraham </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e119780">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>So this is well: for I am none of those </l>
            <l>That make a conscience for to kill a man. </l>
            <l>For nothing is more hurtfull to a Prince, </l>
            <l>Then to be scrupulous and religious. </l>
            <l>I like Lysanders counsell passing well, </l>
            <l>If that I cannot speed with lyons force, </l>
            <l>To cloath my complots in a foxes skin. </l>
            <l>For th'onely things that wrought our Empirie, </l>
            <l>Were open wrongs, and hidden trecherie. </l>
            <l>Oh, th'are two wings wherewith I vse to flie </l>
            <l>And soare aboue the common fort </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-027-a"/>
            <l>If any seeke our wrongs to remedie, </l>
            <l>With these I take his meditation short, </l>
            <l>And one of these shall stil maintaine my cause, </l>
            <l>Or foxes skin, or lions rending pawes. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e119950">Exeunt All. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e119960">Enter Baiazet, Aga, in mourning clokes, Abraham the Iew with a cup. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e119970">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Come Aga let sit us and mourne a while, </l>
            <l>For fortune neuer shew'd her selfe so crosse, </l>
            <l>To any Prince as to poore Baiazet. </l>
            <l>That wofull Emperour first of my name, </l>
            <l>Whom the Tartarians locked in cage, </l>
            <l>To be a spectacle to all the world, </l>
            <l>Was ten times happier then I am. </l>
            <l>For Tamberlaine the scourge of nations, </l>
            <l>Was he that puld him from his kingdome so. </l>
            <l>But mine owne sonnes, expell me from the throne, </l>
            <l>Ah where shall I begin to make my mone. </l>
            <l>Or what shall I first recken in my plaint, </l>
            <l>From my youth vp I haue bene drown'd in woe, </l>
            <l>And to my latest houre I shall be so. </l>
            <l>You swelling seas of neuer ceasing care, </l>
            <l>Whose waues my weather-beaten ship do tosse, </l>
            <l>Your boystrous billowes too vnruly are </l>
            <l>And threaten still my ruine and my losse: </l>
            <l>Like hugie mountaines do your waters reare, </l>
            <l>Their loftie toppes, and my weake vessell crosse. </l>
            <l>Alas at length allaie your stormie strife, </l>
            <l>And cruell wrath within me rages rise. </l>
            <l>Or else my feeble barke cannot endure </l>
            <l>Your slashing buffets and outragious blowes, </l>
            <l>But while thy foamie floud doth it immure, </l>
            <l>Shall soone be wrackt vpon the sandie shallowes </l>
            <l>Griefe my leaud boat-swaine stirreth nothing sure, </l>
            <l>But without stars gainst tide and wind he rowes, </l>
            <l>And cares not though vpon some rock we split </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-027-b"/>
            <l>A restlesse pilot for the charge vnfit. </l>
            <l>But out alasse, the god that vales the sea, </l>
            <l>And can alone this raging tempest slent, </l>
            <l>Will neuer blow a gentle gale of case, </l>
            <l>But suffer my poore vessell to be rent. </l>
            <l>Then ô thou blind procurer of mischance, </l>
            <l>That staist thy selfe vpon turning wheele, </l>
            <l>Thy cruel hand even when thou wilt enhance, </l>
            <l>And pierce my poore hart with thy chrillant steele </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-aga" xml:id="ep000793-e120370">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Cease Baiazet, now it is Agas turne, </l>
            <l>Rest thou a while and gather vp more teares, </l>
            <l>The while poore Aga tell his Tragedie. </l>
            <l>When first my mother brought me to the world, </l>
            <l>Some blazing Comet ruled in the skie, </l>
            <l>Portending miserable chance to me. </l>
            <l>My parents were but men of poore estate, </l>
            <l>And happie yet had wretched Aga bene, </l>
            <l>If Baiazet had not exalted him. </l>
            <l>Poore Aga, had it not bene much more faire, </l>
            <l>T'haue died among the cruell Persians </l>
            <l>Then thus at home by barbarous tyrannie </l>
            <l>To liue and neuer see the cheerfull day, </l>
            <l>And to want hands wherewith to feele the way. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e120530">
          <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Leaue weeping Aga, we haue wept inough, </l>
            <l>Now Baiazet will ban another while, </l>
            <l>And vtter curses to the concaue skie, </l>
            <l>Which may infect the regions of the ayre, </l>
            <l>And bring a generall plague on all the world. </l>
            <l>Night thou most antient grand-mother of all, </l>
            <l>First made by Ioue, for rest and quiet sleepe, </l>
            <l>When cheerful day is gon from th'earths wide hall. </l>
            <l>Henceforth thy mantle in blak Lethe sleepe, </l>
            <l>And cloath the world in darknesse infernall </l>
            <l>Suffer not once the ioyfull dailight peepe, </l>
            <l>But let thy pitchie steeds aye draw thy waine, </l>
            <l>And coaleblack silence in the world still raigne </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-028-a"/>
            <l>Curse on my parents that first brought me vp </l>
            <l>And on the cradle wherein I was rockt, </l>
            <l>Curse on the day when first I was created </l>
            <l>The chiefe commander of all Asia. </l>
            <l>Curse on my sonnes that drive me to this griefe, </l>
            <l>Curse on my selfe that can finde no reliefe. </l>
            <l>And curse on him, an euerlasting curse, </l>
            <l>That quench'd those lampes of euerburning light, </l>
            <l>And tooke away my Agas warlike hands. </l>
            <l>And curse on all things vnder the wide skie, </l>
            <l>Ah Aga, I haue curst my stomacke drie. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-abraham" xml:id="ep000793-e120790">
          <speaker>Abra. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>I haue a drinke my Lords of noble worth, </l>
            <l>Which soone will calme your stormie passions, </l>
            <l>And glad your hearts if so you please to taste it. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e120840">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <l>for who art thou that thus doest pitie vs? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-abraham" xml:id="ep000793-e120860">
          <speaker>Abra. </speaker>
          <l>Your highnesse humble seruant Abraham. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e120880">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <l>Abraham sit downe and drink to Baiazet. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-abraham" xml:id="ep000793-e120900">
          <speaker>Abra. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Faith I am old as well as Baiazet, </l>
            <l>And haue not many months to liue on earth, </l>
            <l>I care not much to end my life with him. </l>
            <l>Heer's to you Lordings with a full carouse. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e120960">He drinkes. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e120970">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <l>Here Aga, wofull Baiazet drinkes to thee. </l>
          <l>Abraham, hold the cup to him while he drinkes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-abraham" xml:id="ep000793-e121000">
          <speaker>Abra. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Now know old Lords, that you haue drunk your last: </l>
            <l>This was a potion which I did prepare </l>
            <l>To poyson you, by Selimus instigation, </l>
            <l>And now it is dispersed through my bones, </l>
            <l>And glad I am that such companions </l>
            <l>Shall go with me downe to Proserpina. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e121080">He dies. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bajazet" xml:id="ep000793-e121090">
          <speaker>Baia. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Ah wicked Iew, ah cursed Selimus, </l>
            <l>How haue the destins dealt with Baiazet, </l>
            <l>That none shuld cause my death but mine own son? </l>
            <l>Had Ismael and his warlike Persians </l>
            <l>Pierced my bodie with their iron speares, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-028-b"/>
            <l>Or had the strong vnconquer'd Tonumbey </l>
            <l>With his Aegyptians tooke me prisoner, </l>
            <l>And sent me with his valiant Mammalukes, </l>
            <l>To be praie vnto the Crocodilus. </l>
            <l>It neuer would haue grieu'd me halfe so much. </l>
            <l>But welcome death into whose calmie port, </l>
            <l>My sorrow-beaten soule ioyes to arriue. </l>
            <l>And now farewell my disobedient sonnes, </l>
            <l>Vnnaturall sonnes vnworthie of that name. </l>
            <l>Farewell sweete life, and Aga now farewell, </l>
            <l>Till we shall meete in the Elysian fields. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e121270">He dies. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-aga" xml:id="ep000793-e121280">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>What greater griefe had mournful Priamus, </l>
            <l>Then that he liu'd to see his Hector die, </l>
            <l>His citie burnt downe by reuenging flames, </l>
            <l>And poore Polites slaine before his face? </l>
            <l>Aga, thy griefe is matchable to his, </l>
            <l>For I haue liu'd to see my soueraignes death, </l>
            <l>Yet glad that I must breath my last with him. </l>
            <l>And now farewell sweet light, which my poore eyes </l>
            <l>These twice six moneths neuer did behold: </l>
            <l>Aga will follow noble Baiazet, </l>
            <l>And beg a boone of louely Proserpine, </l>
            <l>That he and I may in the mournfull fields, </l>
            <l>Still weepe and waile our strange calamities. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e121430">He dies </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e121440">Enter Bullithrumble, the shepheard running in hast, and laughing to himselfe. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bullithrumble" xml:id="ep000793-e121450">
          <speaker>Bulli. </speaker>
          <p>Ha, ha, ha, married quoth you? Marry and Bullithrumble were to begin the world againe, I would set a tap abroach, and not liue in daily feare of the breach of my wiues ten-commandemens. Ile tell you what, I thought my selfe as proper a fellow at wasters, as any in all our village, and yet when my wife begins to plaie clubbes trumpe with me, I am faine to sing: </p>
          <lg>
            <l>What hap had I to marry a shrew, </l>
            <l>For she hath giuen me many a blow, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-029-a"/>
            <l>And how to please her alas I do not know. </l>
            <l>From morne to euen her toong ne'r lies, </l>
            <l>Sometime she laughs, sometime she cries: </l>
            <l>And I can scarce keep her talents fro my eies. </l>
            <l>When from abroad I do come in, </l>
            <l>Sir knaue she cries, where haue you bin? </l>
            <l>Thus please, or displease, she laies it on my skin </l>
            <l>Then do I crouch, then do I kneele, </l>
            <l>And wish my cap were furr'd with steele, </l>
            <l>To beare the blows that my poore head doth feele. </l>
            <l>But our sir Iohn beshrew thy hart, </l>
            <l>For thou hast ioynd vs we cannot part, </l>
            <l>And I poore foole, must euer beare the smart. </l>
          </lg>
          <p>Ile tell you what, this morning while I was making me readie, she came with a holly wand, and so blest my shoulders that I was faine to runne through a whole Alphabet of faces: now at the last seeing she was so cramuk with me, I began to sweare all the crisse crosse row ouer, beginning at great A, litle a, til I cam to w, x, y. And snatching vp my sheephooke, &amp; my bottle and my bag, like a desperate fellow ranne away, and here now ile sit downe and eate my meate. </p>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e121640">While he is eating, Enter Corcut and his Page, disguised like mourners. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-corcut" xml:id="ep000793-e121650">
          <speaker>Cor. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>O hatefull hellish snake of Tartary, </l>
            <l>That feedest on the soule of noblest men, </l>
            <l>Damned ambition, cause of all miserie, </l>
            <l>Why doest thou creep from out thy loathsome fen, </l>
            <l>And with thy poyson animatest friends, </l>
            <l>And gape and long one for the others ends. </l>
            <l>Selimus, could'st thou not content thy mind, </l>
            <l>With the possession of the sacred throne, </l>
            <l>Which thou didst get by fathers death vnkind: </l>
            <l>Whose poison'd ghost before high God doth grone. </l>
            <l>But thou must seeke poore Corcuts ouerthrow, </l>
            <l>That neuer iniured thee, so, nor so? </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-029-b"/>
            <l>Old Halies sonnes with two great companie </l>
            <l>Of barded horse, were sent from Selimus, </l>
            <l>To take me prisoner in Magnesia, </l>
            <l>And death I am sure should haue befell to me, </l>
            <l>If they had once but set their eyes on me. </l>
            <l>So thus disguised my poore Page and I, </l>
            <l>Fled fast to Smirna, where in a darke caue </l>
            <l>We meant t'await th'arriuall of some ship </l>
            <l>That might trans●●eit vs safely vnto Rhodes. </l>
            <l>But see how fortune crost my enterprise. </l>
            <l>Bostangi Bassa, Selims sonne in law, </l>
            <l>Kept all the sea coasts with his Brigandines, </l>
            <l>That if we had but ventured on the sea, </l>
            <l>I presently had bene his prisoner. </l>
            <l>These two dayes haue we kept vs in the caue, </l>
            <l>Eating such hearbes as the ground did affoord: </l>
            <l>And now through hunger are we both constrain'd </l>
            <l>Like fearefull snakes to creep out step by step, </l>
            <l>And see if we may get vs any food. </l>
            <l>And in good time, see yonder sits a man, </l>
            <l>Spreading a hungry dinner on the grasse. </l>
            <l>Bullithrumble spies them, and puts vp his meate. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bullithrumble" xml:id="ep000793-e122010">
          <speaker>Bull. </speaker>
          <p>These are some felonians, that seeke to rob me, well, ile make my selfe a good deale valianter then I am indeed, and if they will needes creep into kindred with me, ile betake me to my old occupation, and runne away. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-corcut" xml:id="ep000793-e122030">
          <speaker>Corcut. </speaker>
          <l>Haile groome. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bullithrumble" xml:id="ep000793-e122050">
          <speaker>Bull. </speaker>
          <p>Good Lord sir, you are deceiued, my names master Bullithrumble: this is some cousoning conicatching crosbiter, that would faine perswade me he knowes me, and so vnder a tence of familiaritie and acquaintance, vncle me of victuals. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-corcut" xml:id="ep000793-e122070">
          <speaker>Corcut. </speaker>
          <l>Then Bullithrumble, if that be thy name: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bullithrumble" xml:id="ep000793-e122090">
          <speaker>Bull. </speaker>
          <p>My name sir ô Lord yes, and if you wil not beleeue me, I wil bring my godfathers and godmothers, and they shal swear it vpon the font-stone, and vpon the church booke too, where it is written. </p>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000793-030-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bullithrumble" xml:id="ep000793-e122110">
          <speaker>Bull. </speaker>
          <p>Masse, I thinke he be some Iustice of peace, ad quorum, and omnium populorum, how he famines me: a christian, yes marrie am I sir, yes verely and do beleeue: and it please you ile goe forward in my catechisme. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-corcut" xml:id="ep000793-e122130">
          <speaker>Corcut. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Then Bullithrumble, by that blessed Christ, </l>
            <l>And by the tombe where he was buried, </l>
            <l>By soueraigne hope which thou conceiu'st in him, </l>
            <l>Whom dead, as euerliuing thou adorest. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bullithrumble" xml:id="ep000793-e122190">
          <speaker>Bull. </speaker>
          <p>O Lord helpe me, I shall be torne in peeces with diuels and goblins. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-corcut" xml:id="ep000793-e122210">
          <speaker>Corcut. </speaker>
          <l>By all the ioyes thou hop'st to haue in heauen, </l>
          <l>Giue some meate to poore hunger-starued men. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bullithrumble" xml:id="ep000793-e122240">
          <speaker>Bulli. </speaker>
          <p>Oh, these are as a man should say beggars: Now will I be as stately to them as if I were maister Pigwiggen our constable: well sirs come before me, tell me if I should entertain you, would you not steale? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-page" xml:id="ep000793-e122260">
          <speaker>Page. </speaker>
          <p>If we did meane so sir, we would not make your worship acquainted with it. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bullithrumble" xml:id="ep000793-e122280">
          <speaker>Bulli. </speaker>
          <p>A good well nutrimented lad: well if you will keepe my sheepe truly and honestly, keeping your hands from lying and slandering, and your tongues from picking and stealing, you shall be maister Bullithrumbles seruitures. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-corcut" xml:id="ep000793-e122300">
          <speaker>Corcut. </speaker>
          <l>With all our hearts. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bullithrumble" xml:id="ep000793-e122320">
          <speaker>Bulli. </speaker>
          <p>Then come on and follow me, we will haue a hogges cheek, and a dish of tripes, and a societie of puddings, &amp; to field: a societie of puddings, did you marke that well vsed metaphor? Another would haue said, a company of puddings: if you dwel with me long sirs, I shall make you as eloquent as our parson himselfe. </p>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e122340">Exeunt Corcut, and Bullithrumble. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-page" xml:id="ep000793-e122350">
          <speaker>Page. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Now is the time when I may be enrich'd. </l>
            <l>The brethren that were sent by Selimus </l>
            <l>To take my Lord, Prince Corcut prisoner, </l>
            <l>Finding him fled, proposed large rewards </l>
            <l>To them that could declare where he remaines. </l>
            <l>Faith ile to them and get the portagues, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-030-b"/>
            <l>Though by the bargain Corcut loose his head. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e122440">Exit Page. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e122450">Enter Selimus, Sinam-bassa, the courses of Mustaffa and Aga, with funerall pompe, Mustaffa, and the Ianizaries. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e122460">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Why thus must Selim blind his subiect eies, </l>
            <l>And straine his owne to weep for Baiazet. </l>
            <l>They will not dreame I made him away, </l>
            <l>When thus they see me with religious pompe, </l>
            <l>To celebrate his tomb-blacke mortarie. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000793-e122540">(To himselfe. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>And though my heart cast in an iron mould, </l>
            <l>Cannot admit the smallest dramme of griefe. </l>
            <l>Yet that I may be thought to loue him well, </l>
            <l>Ile mourne in shew, though I reioyce indeed. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000793-e122600">To the courses. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Thus after he hath fiue long ages liu'd, </l>
            <l>The sacred Phoenix of Arabia, </l>
            <l>Loadeth his wings with pretious perfumes </l>
            <l>And on the altar of the golden sunne, </l>
            <l>Offers himselfe a gratefull sacrifice. </l>
            <l>Long didst thou liue triumphant Baiazet, </l>
            <l>A feare vnto thy greatest enemies, </l>
            <l>And now that death the conquerour of Kings, </l>
            <l>Dislodged hath thy neuer dying soule, </l>
            <l>To flee vnto the heauens from whence she came </l>
            <l>And leaue her fraile, earth pauilion, </l>
            <l>Thy bodie in this auntient monument, </l>
            <l>Where our great predecessours sleep in rest: </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000793-e122750">Suppose the Temple of Mahomet. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Thy wofull sonne Selimus thus doth place. </l>
            <l>Thou wert the Phoenix of this age of ours, </l>
            <l>And diedst wrapped in the sweete perfumes, </l>
            <l>Of thy magnifick deeds, whose lasting praise </l>
            <l>Mounteth to highest heauen with golden wings. </l>
            <l>Princes come beare your Emperour companie </l>
            <l>In, till the dayes of mourning be ore past, </l>
            <l>And then we meane to rouze false Acomat, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-031-a"/>
            <l>And cast him foorth of Macedonia. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e122850">Exeunt All. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e122860">Enter Hali, Cali, Corcuts Page, and one or two souldiers. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-page" xml:id="ep000793-e122870">
          <speaker>Page. </speaker>
          <p>My Lords, if I bring you not where Corcut is, then let me be hanged, but if I deliuer him vp into your hands, then let me haue the reward due to so good a deed. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-hali" xml:id="ep000793-e122890">
          <speaker>Hali. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Page, if thou shew vs where thy maister is, </l>
            <l>Be sure thou shalt be honoured for the deed, </l>
            <l>And high exalted aboue other men. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e122940">Enter Corcut, and Bullithrumble. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-page" xml:id="ep000793-e122950">
          <speaker>Page. </speaker>
          <l>That same is he, that in disguised robes, </l>
          <l>Accompanies yon shepheard to the fields. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-corcut" xml:id="ep000793-e122980">
          <speaker>Cor. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>The sweet content that country life affoords, </l>
            <l>Passeth the royall pleasures of a King: </l>
            <l>For there our ioyes are interlaced with feares: </l>
            <l>But here no feare nor care is harboured, </l>
            <l>But a sweete calme of a most quiet state. </l>
            <l>Ah Corcut, would thy brother Selimus </l>
            <l>But let thee liue, here should'st thou spend thy life, </l>
            <l>Feeding thy sheep among these grassie lands. </l>
            <l>But sure I wonder where my Page is gone. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-hali" xml:id="ep000793-e123090">
          <speaker>Hali. </speaker>
          <l>Corcut. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-corcut" xml:id="ep000793-e123110">
          <speaker>Corcut. </speaker>
          <l>A y-me, who nameth me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-hali" xml:id="ep000793-e123130">
          <speaker>Hali. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Hali, the gouernour of Magnesia. </l>
            <l>Poore prince, thou thoughtst in these disguised weeds, </l>
            <l>To maske vnseene: and happily thou might'st, </l>
            <l>But that thy Page betraied thee to vs. </l>
            <l>And be not wrath with vs vnhappie prince, </l>
            <l>If we do what our soueraigne commands. </l>
            <l>Tis for thy death that Selim sends for thee. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-corcut" xml:id="ep000793-e123220">
          <speaker>Cor. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Thus I like poore Ampharaus, sought </l>
            <l>By hiding my estate in shepheards coate, </l>
            <l>T escape the angry wrath of Selimus. </l>
            <l>But as his wife false Eriphyle did </l>
            <l>Betray his safetie for a chaine of gold, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-031-b"/>
            <l>So my false Page hath vilely dealt with me, </l>
            <l>Pray God that thou maist prosper so as she. </l>
            <l>Hali, I know thou sorrowest for my case, </l>
            <l>But it is bootlesse, come and let vs go, </l>
            <l>Corcut is readie, since it is must be so. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-cali" xml:id="ep000793-e123340">
          <speaker>Cali. </speaker>
          <l>Shepheard. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bullithrumble" xml:id="ep000793-e123360">
          <speaker>Bulli. </speaker>
          <l>That's my profession sir. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-cali" xml:id="ep000793-e123380">
          <speaker>Cali. </speaker>
          <l>Come, you must go with vs. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bullithrumble" xml:id="ep000793-e123400">
          <speaker>Bulli. </speaker>
          <p>Who I? Alasse sir, I haue a wife and seuenteene cradles rocking, two ploughs going, two barnes filling, and a great heard of beasts feeding, and you should vtterly vndo me to take me to such a great charge. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-cali" xml:id="ep000793-e123420">
          <speaker>Cali. </speaker>
          <l>Well there is no remedie. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e123440">Exeunt all, but Bullithrumble stealing from them closely away. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-bullithrumble" xml:id="ep000793-e123450">
          <speaker>Bulli. </speaker>
          <p>The mores the pitie Go with you quoth he, marrie that had bene the way to preferment, downe Holburne vp Tiburne: well ile keepe my best ioynt from the strappado as well as I can hereafter, Ile haue no more seruants. </p>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e123470">Exit running away. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e123480">Enter Selimus, Sinam-Bassa, Mustaffa, and the Ianizaries. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e123490">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Sinam, we heare our brother Acomat </l>
            <l>Is fled away from Macedonia, </l>
            <l>To aske for aide of Persian Ismael, </l>
            <l>And the Aegyptian Soldane our chiefe foes. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-sinam" xml:id="ep000793-e123550">
          <speaker>Sinam. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Herein my Lord I like his enterprise, </l>
            <l>For if they giue him aide as sure they will, </l>
            <l>Being your highnesse vowed enemies, </l>
            <l>You shall haue iust cause for to warre on them, </l>
            <l>For giuing succour gainst you, to your foe. </l>
            <l>You know they are two mightie Potentates, </l>
            <l>And may be hurtfull neighbours to your grace, </l>
            <l>And to enrich the Turkish Diademe. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-032-a"/>
            <l>With two so worthie kingdomes as they are, </l>
            <l>Would be eternall glorie to your name. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e123670">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>By heauens Sinam, th'art a warriour, </l>
            <l>And worthie counceller vnto a King. </l>
            <l>Sound within. <stage xml:id="ep000793-e123720">Enter CaliHali and Hali, with Corcut and his Page. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>How now, what newes? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-cali" xml:id="ep000793-e123740">
          <speaker>Cali. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>My gratious Lord, we here present to you </l>
            <l>Your brother Corcut, whom in Smirna coasts </l>
            <l>Feeding a flocke of sheepe vpon a downe, </l>
            <l>His traitrous Page betraied to our hands. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e123800">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <l>Thanks ye bold brethren, but for that false part, </l>
          <l>Let the vile Page be famished to death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-corcut" xml:id="ep000793-e123830">
          <speaker>Corcut. </speaker>
          <l>Selim, in this I see thou art a Prince, </l>
          <l>To punish treason with condigne reward. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e123860">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>O sir, I loue the fruite that treason brings, </l>
            <l>But those that are the traitors, them I hate. </l>
            <l>But Corcut, could not your Philosophie </l>
            <l>Keepe you safe from my Ianizaries hands. </l>
            <l>We thought you had old Gyges wondrous ring, </l>
            <l>That so you were inuisible to vs. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-corcut" xml:id="ep000793-e123940">
          <speaker>Cor. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Selim, thou dealst vnkindly with thy brother, </l>
            <l>To seeke my death, and make a iest of me. </l>
            <l>vpbraid'st thou me with my philosophie? </l>
            <l>Why this I learn'd by studying learned arts, </l>
            <l>That I can beare my fortune as it falles, </l>
            <l>And that I feare no whit thy crueltie, </l>
            <l>Since thou wilt deale no otherwise with me, </l>
            <l>Then thou hast dealt with aged Baiazet. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e124040">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <l>By heauens Corcut, thou shalt surely die, </l>
          <l>For slandring Selim with my fathers death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-corcut" xml:id="ep000793-e124070">
          <speaker>Cor. </speaker>
          <l>Then let me freely speak my mind this once, </l>
          <l>For thou shalt neuer heare me speake againe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e124100">
          <speaker>Sel. </speaker>
          <l>Nay we can giue such loosers leaue to speak. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-corcut" xml:id="ep000793-e124120">
          <speaker>Cor. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Then Selim, heare thy brothers dying words, </l>
            <l>And marke them well, for ere thou die thy selfe, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-032-b"/>
            <l>Thou shalt perceiue all things will come to passe, </l>
            <l>That Corcut doth diuine before his death. </l>
            <l>Since my vaine flight from faire Magnesia, </l>
            <l>Selim I haue conuerst with Christians, </l>
            <l>And learn'd of them the way to saue my soule, </l>
            <l>And please the anger of the highest God. </l>
            <l>Tis he that made this pure Christalline vault </l>
            <l>Which hangeth ouer our vnhappie heads, </l>
            <l>From thence he doth behold each sinners fault: </l>
            <l>And though our sinnes vnder our feete he treads, </l>
            <l>And for a while seeme for to winke at vs, </l>
            <l>But is to recall vs from our wayes. </l>
            <l>But if we do like head-strong sonnes neglect </l>
            <l>To hearken to our louing fathers voyce, </l>
            <l>Then in his anger will he vs reiect, </l>
            <l>And giue vs ouer to our wicked choyce. </l>
            <l>Selim before his dreadfull maiestie, </l>
            <l>There lies a booke written with bloudie lines, </l>
            <l>Where our offences all are registred. </l>
            <l>Which if we do not hastily repent, </l>
            <l>We are reseru'd to lasting punishment. </l>
            <l>Thou wretched Selimus hast greatest need </l>
            <l>To ponder these things in thy secret thoughts, </l>
            <l>If thou consider what strange massacres </l>
            <l>And cruell murthers thou hast caus'd be done. </l>
            <l>Thinke on the death of wofull Baiazet. </l>
            <l>Doth not his ghoast stil haunt thee for reuenge? </l>
            <l>Selim in Chiurlu didst thou set vpon </l>
            <l>Our aged father in his sodaine flight: </l>
            <l>In Chiurlu shalt thou die a greeuous death. </l>
            <l>And if thou wilt not change thy greedie mind, </l>
            <l>Thy soule shall be tormented in darke hell, </l>
            <l>Where woe, and woe, and neuer ceasing woe, </l>
            <l>Shall sound about thy euer-damned soule. </l>
            <l>Now Selim I haue spoken, let me die: </l>
            <l>I neuer will intreate thee for my life. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-033-a"/>
            <l>Selim farewell: thou God of Christians, </l>
            <l>Receiue my dying soule into thy hands. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e124540">(Strangles him. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e124550">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>What is he dead? then Selimus is safe, </l>
            <l>And hath no more corriuals in the crowne. </l>
            <l>For as for Acomat he soone shall see, </l>
            <l>His Persian aide cannot saue him from me. </l>
            <l>Now Sinam march to faire Amasia walles, </l>
            <l>Where Acomats stout Queene immures her selfe, </l>
            <l>And girt the citie with a warlike siege, </l>
            <l>For since her husband is my enemy, </l>
            <l>I see no cause why she shou'd be my friend. </l>
            <l>They say yoong Amurath and Aladin, </l>
            <l>Her bastard brood, are come to succour her. </l>
            <l>But Ile preuent this their officiousnesse, </l>
            <l>And send their soule downe to their grandfather. </l>
            <l>Mustaffa you shall keepe Bizantium, </l>
            <l>While I and Sinam girt Amasia. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e124720">Exit Selimus, Sinam, Ianizaries all saue one. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mustaffa" xml:id="ep000793-e124730">
          <speaker>Must. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>It grieue my soule that Baiazets faire line, </l>
            <l>Should be eclipsed thus by Selimus, </l>
            <l>Whose cruell soule will neuer be at rest </l>
            <l>Till none remaine of Ottomans faire race </l>
            <l>But he himselfe: yet for old Baiazet </l>
            <l>Loued Mustaffa deare vnto his death, </l>
            <l>I will shew mercy to his familie. </l>
            <l>Go sirra, poast to Acomats yoong sonnes, </l>
            <l>And bid them as they meane to saue their liues, </l>
            <l>To flie in haste from faire Amasia, </l>
            <l>Least cruell Selim put them to the sword. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000793-e124870">Exit one to Amurath and Aladin. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>And now Mustaffa, prepare thou thy necke, </l>
            <l>For thou art next to die by Selims hands. </l>
            <l>Stearne Sinam Bassa grudgeth still at thee, </l>
            <l>And crabbed Hali stormeth at thy life, </l>
            <l>Al repine that thou art honour'd so, </l>
            <l>To be the brother of their Emperour. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000793-e124950">
                <pb xml:id="ep000793-033-b"/>Enter Solyma. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>But wherefore comes my louely Solyma? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-solima" xml:id="ep000793-e124970">
          <speaker>Soly. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Mustaffa I am come to seeke thee out, </l>
            <l>If euer thy distressed Solyma, </l>
            <l>Found grace and fauour in thy manly heart: </l>
            <l>Flie hence with me vnto some desert land, </l>
            <l>For if we tarry here we are but dead. </l>
            <l>This night when faire Lucinaes shining waine, </l>
            <l>Was past the chaire of bright Cassiopey, </l>
            <l>A fearefull vision appear'd to me. </l>
            <l>Me thought Mustaffa, I beheld thy necke </l>
            <l>So often folded in my louing armes, </l>
            <l>In foule disgrace of Bassaes faire degree, </l>
            <l>With a vile haltar basely compassed. </l>
            <l>And while I powr'd my teares on thy dead corpes, </l>
            <l>A greedie lyon with wide gaping throate, </l>
            <l>Seaz'd on my trembling bodie with his feete, </l>
            <l>And in a moment rent me all to nought. </l>
            <l>Flie sweet Mustaffa, or we be but dead. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mustaffa" xml:id="ep000793-e125160">
          <speaker>Must. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Why should we flie beauteous Solyma, </l>
            <l>Mou'd by a vaine and a fantastique dreame? </l>
            <l>Or if we did flie whither should we flie? </l>
            <l>If to the farthest part of Asia, </l>
            <l>Know'st thou not Solyma, kings haue long hands? </l>
            <l>Come, come, my ioy, returne againe with me, </l>
            <l>And banish hence these melancholy thoughts. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e125250">(Exeunt. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e125260">Enter Aladin, Murath, the messenger. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-aladin" xml:id="ep000793-e125270">
          <speaker>Aladin. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Messenger is it true that Selimus </l>
            <l>Is not far hence encamped with his hoste? </l>
            <l>And meanes he to disioyne the haplesse sonnes </l>
            <l>From helping our distressed mothers towne? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-messenger" xml:id="ep000793-e125330">
          <speaker>Mess. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Tis true my Lord, and if you loue your liues </l>
            <l>Flie from the bounds of his dominions, </l>
            <l>For he you know is most vnmercifull. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-amurath" xml:id="ep000793-e125380">
          <speaker>Amu. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Here messenger take this for thy reward. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000793-e125420">Exit mess. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>But we sweet Aladin, let vs depart, </l>
            <l>Now in the quiet silence of the night </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-034-a"/>
            <l>That ere the windowes of the morne be ope, </l>
            <l>We may be far inough from Selimus. </l>
            <l>Ile to Aegyptus. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-alinda" xml:id="ep000793-e125480">
          <speaker>Alinda. </speaker>
          <l>I to Persia. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e125500">(Exeunt. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e125510">Enter Selimus, Sinam, Hali, Cali, Ianizaries. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e125520">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <l>But is it certaine Hali they are gone? </l>
          <l>And that Mustaffa moued them to flie? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-hali" xml:id="ep000793-e125550">
          <speaker>Hali. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Certaine my Lord, I met the messenger </l>
            <l>As he returned from yoong Alinda: </l>
            <l>And learned of them, Mustaffa, was the man </l>
            <l>That certified the Princes of your will. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e125610">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>It is inough: Mustaffa shall abie </l>
            <l>At a deare price his pitifull intent. </l>
            <l>Hali go fetch Mustaffa and his wife. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000793-e125670">(Exit Hali. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>For though she be sister to Selimus, </l>
            <l>Yet loues she him better then Selimus. </l>
            <l>So that if he do die at our command, </l>
            <l>And she should liue: soone wold she worke a mean </l>
            <l>To worke reuenge for her Mustaffas death. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000793-e125740">Enter Hali, Mustaffa, and Solima. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>False of thy faith, and traitor to thy king, </l>
            <l>Did we so highly alway honour thee, </l>
            <l>And doest thou thus requite our loue with treason, </l>
            <l>For why should'st thou send to yoong Alinda, </l>
            <l>And Amurath, the sonnes of Acomat, </l>
            <l>To giue them notice of our secrecies, </l>
            <l>Knowing they were my vowed enemies? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-mustaffa" xml:id="ep000793-e125820">
          <speaker>Must. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>I do not seeke to lesson my offence </l>
            <l>Great Selimus, but truly do protest </l>
            <l>I did it not for hatred of your grace, </l>
            <l>So helpe me God and holy Mahomet. </l>
            <l>But for I grieu'd to see the famous stocke </l>
            <l>Of worthie Baiazet fall to decay, </l>
            <l>Therefore I sent the Princes both away. </l>
            <l>Your highnesse knowes Mustaffa was the man </l>
            <l>That sau'd you in the battell of Churlu, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-034-b"/>
            <l>When I and all the warlike Ianizaries </l>
            <l>Had hedg'd your person in a dangerous ring. </l>
            <l>Yet I tooke pitie on your daunger there, </l>
            <l>And made a way for you to scape by flight. </l>
            <l>But those your Bassaes haue incensed you, </l>
            <l>Repining at Mustaffas dignitie. </l>
            <l>Stearne Sinam grindes his angry teeth at me. </l>
            <l>Old Halies sonnes do bend their browes at me </l>
            <l>And are agrieued that Mustaffa hath </l>
            <l>Shewed himselfe a better man then they. </l>
            <l>And yet the Ianizars mourne for me, </l>
            <l>They know Mustaffa neuer proued false. </l>
            <l>I, I haue bene as true to Selimus, </l>
            <l>As euer subiect to his soueraigne, </l>
            <l>So helpe me God and holy Mahomet. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e126080">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>You did it not because you hated vs, </l>
            <l>But for you lou'd the sonnes of Acomat. </l>
            <l>Sinam, I charge thee quickly strangle him, </l>
            <l>He loues not me that loues mine enemies. </l>
            <l>As for your holy protestation, </l>
            <l>It cannot enter into Selims eares: </l>
            <l>For why Mustaffa? euery marchant man </l>
            <l>Will praise his own ware be it ne'r so bad. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-solima" xml:id="ep000793-e126180">
          <speaker>Solima. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>For Solimas sake mightie Selimus, </l>
            <l>Spare my Mustaffas life, and let me die: </l>
            <l>Or if thou wilt not be so gratious, </l>
            <l>Yet let me die before I see his death. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e126240">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Nay Selima, your selfe shall also die, </l>
            <l>Because you may be in the selfesame fault. </l>
            <l>Why stai'st thou Sinam? strangle him I say. </l>
            <l>Sinam <stage xml:id="ep000793-e126300">strangles him. </stage>
            </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-solima" xml:id="ep000793-e126310">
          <speaker>Soli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Ah Selimus, he made thee Emperour, </l>
            <l>And wilt thou thus requite his benefits? </l>
            <l>Thou art a cruell tygre and no man, </l>
            <l>That coul'st endure to see before thy face, </l>
            <l>So braue a man as my Mustaffa was, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-035-a"/>
            <l>Cruelly strangled for so small a fault. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e126390">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Thou shalt not after liue him Solima. </l>
            <l>Twere pitie thou shouldst want the company </l>
            <l>Of thy deare husband: Sinam strangle her. </l>
            <l>And now to faire Amasia let vs march. </l>
            <l>Acomats wife, and her vnmanly hoast, </l>
            <l>Will not be able to endure our sight, </l>
            <l>Much lesse make strong resistance in hard fight. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e126480">Exeunt. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e126490">Enter Acomat, Tonombeius, Visir, Regan, and their souldiers. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e126500">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Welcome my Lords into my natiue soyle, </l>
            <l>The crowne whereof by right is due to me: </l>
            <l>Though Selim by the Ianizaries choyce, </l>
            <l>Through vsurpation keep the same from me. </l>
            <l>You know contrary to my fathers mind, </l>
            <l>He was enthronized by the Bassaes will, </l>
            <l>And after his enstalling, wickedly </l>
            <l>By poyson made good Baiazet to die. </l>
            <l>And strangled Corcut, and exiled me. </l>
            <l>These iniuries we come for to reuenge, </l>
            <l>And raise his siege from faire Amasia walles. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-tonombey" xml:id="ep000793-e126630">
          <speaker>Tonom. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Prince of Amasia, and the rightful heire </l>
            <l>Vnto the mightie Turkish Diadem: </l>
            <l>With willing heart great Tonombey hath left </l>
            <l>Aegyptian Nilus and my fathers court, </l>
            <l>To aide thee in thy vndertaken warre, </l>
            <l>And by the great Vsancassanos ghoast, </l>
            <l>Companion vnto mightie Tamberlaine, </l>
            <l>From whom my father lineally descends, </l>
            <l>Fortune shall shew her selfe too crosse to me, </l>
            <l>But we will thrust Selimus from his throne, </l>
            <l>And reuest Acomat in the Empirie. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e126760">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Thanks to the vncontrolled Tonombey. </l>
            <l>But let vs haste vs to Amasia, </l>
            <l>To succour my besieged citizens. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-035-b"/>
            <l>None but my Queene is ouerseer there, </l>
            <l>And too too weake is all her pollicie, </l>
            <l>Against so great a foe as Selimus. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e126840">Exeunt All </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e126850">Enter Selimus, Sinam, Hali, Cali, and the Ianizaries. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e126860">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Summon a parley sirs that we may know </l>
            <l>Whether these Mushroms here will yeeld or no. </l>
            <l>A parley: Queene of Amasia, and her souldiers on the walles. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-queen" xml:id="ep000793-e126910">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>What crauest thou bloud-thirstie parricide? </l>
            <l>Ist not inough that thou hast foulely slaine, </l>
            <l>Thy louing father noble Baiazet, </l>
            <l>And strangled Corcut thine vnhappie brother </l>
            <l>Slaine braue Mustaffa, and faire Selima? </l>
            <l>Because they fauoured my vnhappie sonnes, </l>
            <l>But thou must yet seeke for more massacres▪ </l>
            <l>Go, wash thy guiltie hands in luke-warme blood. </l>
            <l>Enrich thy souldiers with robberies: </l>
            <l>Yet do the heauens still beare an equall eye, </l>
            <l>And vengeance followes thee euen at the heeles. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e127040">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <l>Queene of Amasia, wilt thou yeeld thy selfe? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-queen" xml:id="ep000793-e127060">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>First shall the ouer-flowing Euripus </l>
            <l>Of swift Euboea stop his restlesse course </l>
            <l>And Phoebs bright globe bring the day from the west, </l>
            <l>And quench his hot flames in the Esterne sea. </l>
            <l>Thy bloudie sword vngratious Selimus </l>
            <l>Sheath'd in the bowels of thy dearest friends: </l>
            <l>Thy wicked gard which still attends on thee, </l>
            <l>Fleshing themselues in murther, lust, and rape: </l>
            <l>What hope of fauour? what securitie? </l>
            <l>Rather what death do they not promise me? </l>
            <l>Then thinke not Selimus that we will yeeld, </l>
            <l>But looke for strong resistance at our hands. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e127200">
          <speaker>Seli, </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Why then you neuer danted lanizaries, </l>
            <l>Aduance your shields and vncontrolled speares, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-036-a"/>
            <l>Your conquering hands in foe-mens blood embay, </l>
            <l>For Selimus himselfe will lead the way. </l>
            <l>Allarum, beats them off the walles. Allarum. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e127270">Enter Selimus, Sinam, Hali, Cali, Ianizaries, with Acomats Queene prisoner. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e127280">
          <speaker>Se. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Now sturdie dame, where are your men of war </l>
            <l>To gard your person from my angry sword? </l>
            <l>What? though brau'd vs on your citie walles, </l>
            <l>Like to that Amanonian Menalip, </l>
            <l>Leauing the bankes of swift-stream'd Thermodon </l>
            <l>To challenge combat with great Hercules: </l>
            <l>Yet Selimus hath pluckt your haughtie plumes, </l>
            <l>Nor can your spouse rebellious Acomat, </l>
            <l>Nor Alinda, or Amurath your sonnes, </l>
            <l>Deliuer you from our victorious hands. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-queen" xml:id="ep000793-e127400">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Selim I scorne thy threatnings as thy selfe. </l>
            <l>And though ill hap hath giuen me to thy hands, </l>
            <l>Yet will I neuer beg my life of thee. </l>
            <l>Fortune may chance to frowne as much on thee. </l>
            <l>And Acomat whom thou doest scorne so much, </l>
            <l>May take thy base Tartarian concubine, </l>
            <l>As well as thou hast tooke his loyall Queene. </l>
            <l>Thou hast not fortune tied in a chaine, </l>
            <l>Nor doest thou like a warie pilot sit, </l>
            <l>And wisely stir this all conteining barge. </l>
            <l>Thou art a man as those whom thou hast slaine, </l>
            <l>And some of them were better far then thou. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e127540">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Strangle her Hali, let her scold no more. </l>
            <l>Now let vs march to meet with Acomat, </l>
            <l>He brings with him that great Aegyptian bug, </l>
            <l>Strong Tonombey, Vsan-Cassanos sonne. </l>
            <l>But we shall soone with our fine tempered swords, </l>
            <l>Engraue our prowesse on their buganets, </l>
            <l>Were they as mightie and as fell of force, </l>
            <l>As those old earth-bred brethren, which once </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-036-b"/>
            <l>Heape hill on hill to scale the starrie skie, </l>
            <l>When Briareus arm'd with a hundreth hands, </l>
            <l>Flung foorth a hundreth mountaines at great Ioue, </l>
            <l>And when the monstrous giant Monichus </l>
            <l>Hurld mount Olimpus at great Mars his targe, </l>
            <l>And darted cedars at Mineruas shield. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e127700">Exeunt All. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e127710">Allarum Enter Selimus, Sinam, Cali, Hali, and the Ianizaries, at one doore, and Acomat, Tonombey, Regan, Vissr, and their souldiers at another. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e127720">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>What are the vrchins crept out of their dens, </l>
            <l>Vnder the conduct of this porcupine? </l>
            <l>Doest thou not tremble Acomat at vs, </l>
            <l>To see how courage masketh in our lookes, </l>
            <l>And white-wing'd victorie sits on our swordes? </l>
            <l>Captaine of Aegypt, thou that vant'st thy selfe </l>
            <l>Sprung from great Tamberlaine the Scythia theefe, </l>
            <l>Who bad the enterprise this bold attempt, </l>
            <l>To set thy feete within the Turkish confines </l>
            <l>Or lift thy hands against our maiestie? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e127840">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Brother of Trebisond, your squared words, </l>
            <l>And broad-mouth'd tearmes, can neuer conquer vs. </l>
            <l>We come resolu'd to pull the Turkish crowne, </l>
            <l>Which thou doest wrongfully detaine from me, </l>
            <l>By conquering sword from of thy coward crest. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e127910">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <l>Acomat, sith the quarrell toucheth none </l>
          <l>But thee and me: I dare, and challenge thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-tonombey" xml:id="ep000793-e127940">
          <speaker>Tonum. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Should he accept the combat of a boy? </l>
            <l>Whose vnripe yeares and farre vnriper wit </l>
            <l>Like to the bold foole-hardie Phaetun </l>
            <l>That sought to rule the chariot of the sunne, </l>
            <l>Hath mou'd thee t'vndertake an Empirie. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e128010">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Thou that resoluest in peremptorie tearmes, </l>
            <l>To call him boy that scornes to cope with thee: </l>
            <l>But thou canst better vse thy bragging blade, </l>
            <l>Then thou canst rule thy ouerflowing tongue, </l>
            <l>Soone shalt thou know that Selims mightie arme </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-037-a"/>
            <l>Is able to ouerthrow poore Tonombey. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e128090">Allarum, Tonombey beates Hali and Cali in. Selim beats Tonombey in Allarum, Exit Tonombey. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-tonombey" xml:id="ep000793-e128100">
          <speaker>Tonom. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>The field is lost, and Acomat is taken. </l>
            <l>Ah Tonombey, how canst thou shew thy face </l>
            <l>To thy victorious sire, thus conquered. </l>
            <l>A matchlesse knight is warlike Selimus. </l>
            <l>And like a shepheard mongst a swarme of gnats, </l>
            <l>Dings downe the flying Persians with their swords. </l>
            <l>Twice I encountred with him hand to hand, </l>
            <l>And twice returned foyled and asham'd. </l>
            <l>For neuer yet since I could manage Armes, </l>
            <l>Could any match with mightie Tonombey, </l>
            <l>But this heroicke Emperour Selimus. </l>
            <l>Why stand I still, and rather do not flie </l>
            <l>The great occision which the victors make? </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e128250">Exit Tonombey. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000793-e128260">Allarum. Enter Selimus, Sinam Bassa, with Acomat prisoner, Hali, Cali, Ianizaries. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e128270">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Thus when the coward Greeks fled to their ships, </l>
            <l>The noble Hector all besmear'd in blood, </l>
            <l>Return'd in triumph to the walles of Troy. </l>
            <l>A gallant trophee, Bassaes haue we wonne, </l>
            <l>Beating the neuer-foyled Tonombey, </l>
            <l>And hewing passage through the Persians. </l>
            <l>As when a lyon rauing for his praie, </l>
            <l>Falleth vpon a droaue of horned balles, </l>
            <l>And rends them strongly in his kingly pawes. </l>
            <l>Or Mars arm'd in his adamantiue coate, </l>
            <l>Mounted vpon his firie-shining waine, </l>
            <l>Scatters the troupes of warlike Thracians, </l>
            <l>And warmes cold Hebras with hot streams of blood. </l>
            <l>Braue Sinam, for thy noble prisoner, </l>
            <l>Thou shalt be generall of my Ianizaries. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-037-b"/>
            <l>And Belierbey of faire Natalia. </l>
            <l>Now Acomat, thou monster of the world, </l>
            <l>Why stoup'st thou not with reuerence to thy king? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-acomat" xml:id="ep000793-e128470">
          <speaker>Aco. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Selim if thou haue gotten victorie, </l>
            <l>Then vse it to thy contentation. </l>
            <l>If I had conquer'd, know assuredly </l>
            <l>I would haue said as much and more to thee. </l>
            <l>Know I disdaine them as I do thy selfe, </l>
            <l>And scorne to stoupe or bend my Lordly knee, </l>
            <l>To such a tyrant as is Selimus. </l>
            <l>Thou slew'st my Queene without regard or care, </l>
            <l>Of loue or dutie, or thine owne good name. </l>
            <l>Then Selim take that which thy hap doth giue, </l>
            <l>Disgra'st, displai'st, I longer loath to liue. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000793-selimus" xml:id="ep000793-e128600">
          <speaker>Seli. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Then Sinam strangle him: now he is dead, </l>
            <l>Who doth remaine to trouble Selimus? </l>
            <l>Now am I King alone and none but I. </l>
            <l>For since my fathers death vntill this time, </l>
            <l>I neuer wanted some competitors. </l>
            <l>Now as the weerie wandring traueller </l>
            <l>That hath his steppes guided through many lands, </l>
            <l>Through boiling soile of Affrica and Ind, </l>
            <l>When he returnes vnto his natiue home: </l>
            <l>Sits downe among his friends, and with delight </l>
            <l>Declares the trauels he hath ouerpast. </l>
            <l>So maist thou Selimus, for thou hast trode </l>
            <l>The monster-garden paths, that lead to crownes. </l>
            <l>Ha, ha, I smile to thinke how Selimus </l>
            <l>Like the Aegyptian Ibis hath expelled </l>
            <l>Those swarming armies of swift-winged snakes, </l>
            <l>That sought to ouerrun my territories, </l>
            <l>When soultring heat the earths green children spoiles </l>
            <l>From foorth the fennes of venemous Affrica, </l>
            <l>The generation of those flying snakes, </l>
            <l>Do band themselues in troupes, and take their way </l>
            <l>To Nilus bounds: but those industrious birds, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000793-038-a"/>
            <l>Those Ibides meete them in set array, </l>
            <l>And eate them vp like to a swarme of gnats, </l>
            <l>Preuenting such a mischiefe from the land. </l>
            <l>But see how vnkind nature deales with them: </l>
            <l>From out their egges rises the basiliske, </l>
            <l>Whose onely sight killes millions of men. </l>
            <l>When Acomat lifted his vngratious hands </l>
            <l>Against my aged father Baiazet. </l>
            <l>They sent for me, and I like Aegipts bird </l>
            <l>Haue rid that monster, and his fellow mates. </l>
            <l>But as from Ibis springs the Basilisk. </l>
            <l>Whose onely touch burneth vp stones and trees. </l>
            <l>So Selimus hath prou'd a Cocatrice, </l>
            <l>And cleane consumed all the familie </l>
            <l>Of noble Ottoman, except himselfe. </l>
            <l>And now to you my neighbour Emperours, </l>
            <l>That durst lend ayd to Selims enemies, </l>
            <l>Sinam those Soldanes of the Orient, </l>
            <l>Aegipt and Persia, Selimus will quell, </l>
            <l>Or he himselfe will sincke to lowest hell. </l>
            <l>This winter will we rest and breath our selues: </l>
            <l>But soone as Zephyrus sweete smelling blast </l>
            <l>Shall greatly creep ouer the flourie meades, </l>
            <l>Wee'll haue a fling at the Aegyptian crowne, </l>
            <l>And ioyne it vnto ours, or loose our owne. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000793-e129090">Exeunt. </stage>
        </sp>
      </div>
      <div type="conclusion" xml:id="ep000793-e129100">
        <pb xml:id="ep000793-038-b"/>
        <head>Conclusion. </head>
        <lg>
          <l>Thus haue we brought victorious Selimus, </l>
          <l>Vnto the Crowne of great Arabia: </l>
          <l>Next shall you see him with triumphant sworde </l>
          <l>Diuiding kingdomes into equall shares, </l>
          <l>And giue them to their warlike followers. </l>
          <l>If this first part Gentles, do like you well, </l>
          <l>The second part, shall greater murthers tell. </l>
        </lg>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back></back>
  </text>
</TEI>
