<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000065" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>2 The Iron Age</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Thomas</forename>
            <surname>Heywood</surname>
          </persName>
          <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q2073027</idno>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A03223_02.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull n="TCP source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">The iron age contayning the rape of Hellen: the siege of Troy: the combate between Hector and Aiax: Hector and Troilus slayne by Achilles: Achilles slaine by Paris: Aiax and Vlisses contend for the armour of Achilles: the death of Aiax, &amp;c. Written by Thomas Heyvvood.</title>
                <author>Heywood, Thomas, d. 1641.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>83 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
                <date>2006 June (TCP phase 1)</date>
                <idno type="marc">99839789</idno>
                <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 13340.</idno>
                <idno type="stc">Greg, II, 467(AI), 468.</idno>
                <idno type="vid">4241</idno>
                <idno type="DLPS">A03223</idno>
                <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2248561819</idno>
                <availability>
                  <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
                </availability>
              </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
            <biblFull n="printed source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">The iron age contayning the rape of Hellen: the siege of Troy: the combate between Hector and Aiax: Hector and Troilus slayne by Achilles: Achilles slaine by Paris: Aiax and Vlisses contend for the armour of Achilles: the death of Aiax, &amp;c. Written by Thomas Heyvvood.</title>
                <title type="alt">Second part of the iron age.</title>
                <author>Heywood, Thomas, d. 1641.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[168] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>By Nicholas Okes,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication_date">1632.</date>
                <date type="creation_date">1612</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>
                  <p>In verse.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Signatures: A-L4; 2A-K4.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>The first leaf is blank.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>"The second part of the iron age" has separate dated title page and register.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>In this issue the title page bears an oval printer's mark.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Title page from STC 13340.5 bound at beginning.</p>
                </note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-agamemnon">
            <persName>Agamemnon</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-diomede">
            <persName>Diomede</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-ulysses">
            <persName>Ulysses</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-menelaus">
            <persName>Menelaus</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-pyrrhus">
            <persName>Pyrrhus</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-synon">
            <persName>Synon</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-pylades">
            <persName>Pylades</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-thersites">
            <persName>Thersites</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-penthesilea">
            <persName>Penthesilea</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-paris">
            <persName>Paris</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-cressida">
            <persName>Cressida</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-amazon">
            <persName>Amazon</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-omnes">
            <persName>Omnes</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-aeneas">
            <persName>Aeneas</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-chorebus">
            <persName>Chorebus</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-priam">
            <persName>Priam</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-hecuba">
            <persName>Hecuba</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-helen">
            <persName>Helen</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-laocoon">
            <persName>Laocoon</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-soldier">
            <persName>Soldier</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-trojan">
            <persName>Trojan</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-wife">
            <persName>Wife</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-trojan_2">
            <persName>Trojan 2</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-hector">
            <persName>Hector</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-all">
            <persName>All</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-cassandra">
            <persName>Cassandra</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-astianax">
            <persName>Astianax</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-andromache">
            <persName>Andromache</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-cethus">
            <persName>Cethus</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-clytemnestra">
            <persName>Clytemnestra</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-orestes">
            <persName>Orestes</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-hermione">
            <persName>Hermione</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-egistus">
            <persName>Egistus</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-electra">
            <persName>Electra</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-lord">
            <persName>Lord</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000065-guard">
            <persName>Guard</persName>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
      <textClass>
        <classCode scheme="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q192881</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1612">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000065-e100030">
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-044-a"/>
        <p>THE Second Part of the Iron Age Which contayneth the death of Penthesilea, Paris Priam, and Hecuba: The burning of Troy: The deaths of Agamemnon, Menelaus, Clitemnestra, Hellena, Orestes, Egistus, Pillades, King Diomed, Pyrhus, Cethus, Synon, Thersites, &amp;c. Written by THOMAS HEYWOOD. </p>
        <quote>Aut prodesse solent aut Delectare. </quote>
        <p>
          <figure/>
        </p>
        <p>Printed at London by Nicholas Okes. 1632. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="ep000065-e100090">
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-045-a"/>
        <head>Drammatis personae. </head>
        <list>
          <head>New persons not presented in the former part of this History. </head>
          <item>Pyrhus the sonne of Achilles, </item>
          <item>surnamed Neoptolemus. </item>
          <item>Synon a periured Greeke, by whose teares Troy was set on fire. </item>
          <item>Chorebus a Prince, who came to the warres for the loue of Cassandra. </item>
          <item>Laocoon, a priest of Apollo. </item>
          <item>Polites, a young sonne of King </item>
          <item>Priam, and Queene Hecuba. </item>
          <item>A Troian Citizen. &amp; his wife. </item>
          <item>A second Troian. </item>
          <item>Souldiers of Greece. </item>
          <item>Souldiers of Troy. </item>
          <item>The Ghost of Hector. </item>
          <item>A Lord of Mycena. </item>
          <item>A Guard. </item>
          <item>Penthesilea Queene of the Amazons, with her trayne of Viragoes. </item>
          <item>Cethus sonne to King Naulus, and brother of Palamides. </item>
          <item>Pillades the friend of Orestes. </item>
          <item>Orestes sonne to King Agamemnon, and his Queene Clitemnestra. </item>
          <item>Electra, sister to Orestes. </item>
          <item>Hermione daughter to King </item>
          <item>Menelaus and Q. Hellen. </item>
          <item>Clitemnestra wife and Queene to Agamemnon. </item>
          <item>Egistus a fauorite to Queene Clitemnestra. </item>
          <item>The Priest of Apollo▪ Attendants. </item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="to_the_reader" xml:id="ep000065-e100350">
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-045-b"/>
        <head>To the Reader. </head>
        <p>COurteous Reader: I commend vnto thee an intire History, from Iupiter and Saturne, to the vtter subuersion of Troy▪ with a faithfull account of the Deathes of all these Princes of Greece, who had hand in the Fate thereof, (Vlisses only excepted, to whom belongeth a further History.) Reade freely, and censure fauourably. These Ages haue beene long since Writ, and suited with the Time then: I know not how they may bee receiued in this Age, where nothing but Satirica Dictaeria, and Comica Scommata are now in request: For mine owne part, I neuer affected either▪ when they stretched to the abuse of any person publicke, or priuate. If the three former Ages (now out of Print,) bee added to these (as I am promised) to make vp an handsome Volumne; I purpose (Deo Assistente,) to illustrate <pb xml:id="ep000065-046-a"/>the whole Worke, with an Explanation of all he difficulties, and an Historicall Comment of euery hard name, which may appeare obscure or intricate to such as are not frequent in Poetry: Which (as the rest) I shall freely deuote to thy fauorable perusall, in this as all the rest industrious to thy pleasure and profit: </p>
        <closer>
          <signed>Thomas Heywood </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000065-e100390">
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-046-b"/>
        <head>to my Worthy and much Respected Friend, Mr. Thomas Mannering Esquire. </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Worthy Sir, </salute>
        </opener>
        <p>ANd my much respected Friend: The Impression of your Loue, after so many yeares acknowledgment, inforceth me that I cannot chuse, but in my best recollection, to number you in the File and List of my best and choycest Well-wishers. True it is, that my vnable merit hath euer come much short of your ample acknowledgement: Howsoeuer, though you bee now absent in the Countrey, vppon a necessary retyrement; yet let this witnesse in my behalfe, that you are not altogether vnremembred in the Citty: Nor take it vnkindly at my hands that I haue reserued your name to the Catastrophe and conclusion of this Worke: Since being Scoena nouissima, <pb xml:id="ep000065-047-a"/>It must be consequently the fresher in memory; as you haue had euer a charitable and indulgent censure of such poore peeces of mine, as haue come accedentally vnto your view. So I intreate you now, (as one better able to iudge, then I to determine) to receiue into your fauourable patronage, this second part of the Iron Age. I much deceiue my selfe, if J heard you not once commend it, when you saw it Acted; if you persist in the same opinion, when you shall spare some sorted houres to heare it read, in your paynes, I shal hold my selfe much pleased: ouer remaining </p>
        <closer>
          <signed>Yours, not to be chang'd: Thomas Heywood. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <head>
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-047-b"/>The second Part of the IRON AGE: With the Destruction of TROY. </head>
      <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="ep000065-e100460">
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e100470">Enter Agamemnon, Menelaus, Vlisses, Diomed, Thersites. Drum, Colours, Souldiers, &amp;c. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e100480">
          <speaker>Agamemnon. </speaker>
          <l>YOu Terrors of the Asian Monarchy, </l>
          <l>And Europes glory: Warlike Lords of Greece: </l>
          <l>Although the great Prince of the Mirmidons, </l>
          <l>And arme-strong Aiax, our best Champions, </l>
          <l>Be by the gods bereft vs: yet now comes </l>
          <l>A Phoenix out of their cold ashes rising: </l>
          <l>Pyrhus, sirnamed Neoptolemus: </l>
          <l>On whom for his deceased fathers sake, </l>
          <l>Wee must bestow some honours. Menelaus, </l>
          <l>Vlisses, Diomed, giue the Prince meeting, </l>
          <l>And be his conduct to the Generall. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e100600">A flourish. Enter the Kings before named, bringing in Pyrhus, Synon, with attendants. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e100610">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>Pyrhus kneele downe, we girt thee with this sword, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-048-a"/>
          <l>It was thy fathers. In his warlike hand </l>
          <l>It hath cleft Troians to the nauell downe, </l>
          <l>Par'd heads off faster then the haruest Sithe </l>
          <l>Doth the thin stalkes, or bending eares of graine: </l>
          <l>Weare it, and draw it to reuenge his death. </l>
          <l>Princes, performe your seuerall ceremonies. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-diomede" xml:id="ep000065-e100690">
          <speaker>Did </speaker>
          <l>These golden spurs I fasten to thine heeles, </l>
          <l>The same thy warlike father wonne in field, </l>
          <l>When Hector tide with thonges to his steeds fet-locks, </l>
          <l>Was drag'd about the high built wals of Troy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-ulysses" xml:id="ep000065-e100740">
          <speaker>Ulis. </speaker>
          <l>This Armour, and this plumed Burgonet, </l>
          <l>In which thy father, like a rampier'd wall, </l>
          <l>Opposde the fury of his enemies, </l>
          <l>(By generall consent of all these Princes </l>
          <l>Attributed to me) loe I surrender </l>
          <l>To youthful Neoptolemus, weare it Prince, </l>
          <l>Not all the world yeeldes a more strong defence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e100820">
          <speaker>Mene. </speaker>
          <l>Achilles Tent, his Treasure, and his iewels, </l>
          <l>We haue reseru'd, inioy them noble Pyrhus; </l>
          <l>And lastly his strong guard of Mirmidons, </l>
          <l>And with the honour hee with these haue wonne, </l>
          <l>His Sword, Spurs, Armour, Guard, Pauileon, </l>
          <l>Be by his valiant sonne much dignified. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e100890">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Before I touch the handle of his sword, </l>
          <l>Or to my Knightly spurres direct my eyes, </l>
          <l>Lace this rich Armour to my youthfull sides, </l>
          <l>Or roofe mine head within this warlike Tent, </l>
          <l>Make proofe of this his plumed Burgonet, </l>
          <l>Or take on me the leading of his Guard: </l>
          <l>Witnesse you Grecian Princes, what I vow: </l>
          <l>By Saturnes sonne, the sire of Aeacus, </l>
          <l>Begot on faire Europa; by their issue, </l>
          <l>The second Iudge, plac'd on the infernall bench </l>
          <l>I will discend to Peleus, and from him, </l>
          <l>Euen to my naturall father, with whose honours </l>
          <l>I ioyne my mother Deidamiaes </l>
          <l>And in my vengefull oath include them all, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-048-b"/>
          <l>Till Priam be compel'd to shut his Gates </l>
          <l>For want of men: Ile be as mercilesse </l>
          <l>As vntam'd Lyons, and the flesh-fed Beares, </l>
          <l>Blood shall looke brighter in young Pyrhus eyes </l>
          <l>Then dissolued Christall, till old Priams haires </l>
          <l>Be dy'de in goare: till Hecub's reuerent lockes </l>
          <l>Be Beguil'd in slaughter; all their sonnes and daughters, </l>
          <l>Subiects, and Citty quite confus'd in ruine, </l>
          <l>Bow to our mercilesse fury: Ile not leaue </l>
          <l>This blacke and fatall siege; and this I sweare </l>
          <l>As I am Prince, and great Achilles heire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e101150">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>Euen in thy lookes I read the sack of Troy, </l>
          <l>And Priams Tragedy: welcome sweete Pyrhus, </l>
          <l>And welcome you his warlike followers. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e101190">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>where be these Troians? I would faine behold </l>
          <l>Their wing'd battalions grapple? I would see </l>
          <l>The batter'd center flye about their eares </l>
          <l>In cloudes of dust: I would haue horses hoofes </l>
          <l>Beate thunder out of earth: the chariot Trees </l>
          <l>I would see drown'd in blood, Scamander plaines </l>
          <l>Ore-spread with intrailes bak'd in blood and dust: </l>
          <l>With terrour I would haue this day as blacke, </l>
          <l>As when Hyperion leaping from his Spheare, </l>
          <l>Cast vgly darknesse from his Chariot wheeles, </l>
          <l>And in this vail'd confusion the faint Troians </l>
          <l>Beate backe into the Towne: I'de see their Gates </l>
          <l>Entred, and fire by their high Battlements </l>
          <l>Climing toward heauen: the pauement of th'streets </l>
          <l>I'de see pau'd ore with faces: infants tost </l>
          <l>On Lances poynts: big-bellied Ladies flung </l>
          <l>From out their casements: I'd haue all their soules </l>
          <l>Set vpon wings, and Troy, no Troy, but fire, </l>
          <l>As if ten thousand Comets ioyn'd in one, </l>
          <l>To close the world in red confusion. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pylades" xml:id="ep000065-e101400">
          <speaker>Py. </speaker>
          <l>Wel spake bold Synon; and my Lords of Greece, </l>
          <l>This fellow boasts no more then with his sword, </l>
          <l>Hee will aduenture for, and should that fayle, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-049-a"/>
          <l>He'le set his braine to worke. I tell you Princes, </l>
          <l>My Grandsire Lycomedes hath made proofe </l>
          <l>Of Synons pollicies, state-quaking proiects </l>
          <l>Are hand-maides to his braine; and he hath spirit </l>
          <l>To driue his plots euen to the doore of Death, </l>
          <l>With rare effects, and then not all the world </l>
          <l>Affoords a villaine more incomparable, </l>
          <l>Then Synon my attendant. Warlike Princes, </l>
          <l>I speake this to his prayse: and I professe </l>
          <l>My selfe as sterne, bloody, and mercilesse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e101540">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>I haue not heard a brauer Character </l>
          <l>Giuen to a Greeke: and had hee but my rayling▪ </l>
          <l>He were a man compleate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e101580">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Sure there is something </l>
          <l>Aboue a common man in yon same fellow, </l>
          <l>Whom nature hath so markt, and were his mind </l>
          <l>As crooked as his body, hee were one </l>
          <l>I could bee much in loue with. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e101640">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>Hee hath a feature </l>
          <l>That I could court, nay will: I would not loose </l>
          <l>His friendship and acquaintance for the world. </l>
          <l>Mee thinkes you are a comely Gentleman. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e101690">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>I euer held my selfe so: and mine eye </l>
          <l>Giues you no lesse: of all the Grecians here </l>
          <l>Thou hast a face like mine, that feares no weather▪ </l>
          <l>A shape that warre it selfe cannot deforme: </l>
          <l>I best loue such complexions. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e101750">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>By the gods </l>
          <l>Wee haue two meeting soules: be my sweete Vrchin▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e101780">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>I will, </l>
          <l>An thou shalt bee mine vgly Toade. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e101810">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>A match: be wee hence forth brothers and friends. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e101830">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Imbrace then friend and brother: my deare Toade▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e101850">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>My amiable Vrchin. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e101870">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>I long for worke, will not these Troians come, </l>
          <l>To welcome Pyrhus, great Achilles sonne? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-ulysses" xml:id="ep000065-e101900">
          <speaker>Vlyss. </speaker>
          <l>Their drummes proclayme them ready for the field. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e101920">
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-049-b"/>Enter Priam, Paris, Penthesilea, and her traine of Viragoes, Aeneas, Chorebus, Laocoon, Anthenor, &amp;c. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e101930">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>Perhaps King Priam hath not yet related </l>
          <l>The newes of Neoptolemus arriue, </l>
          <l>That hee presumes thus, weakned as he is, </l>
          <l>To ope his Gates, and meete vs in the field. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e101980">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Tis like hee hath, because for want of men </l>
          <l>Hee brings a troope of Women to the field: </l>
          <l>Most sure hee thinkes, wee (like our warlike father) </l>
          <l>Will be insnar'd with beauty: Priam no, </l>
          <l>We for his death, are sworne vaine beauties foe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-penthesilea" xml:id="ep000065-e102040">
          <speaker>Penth. </speaker>
          <l>Art thou Achilles sonne, beneath whose hand </l>
          <l>Assisted by his bloody Mirmidons, </l>
          <l>The valiant Hector fell? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e102080">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Woman I am. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-penthesilea" xml:id="ep000065-e102100">
          <speaker>Penth. </speaker>
          <l>Thou shouldst be then a Coward. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e102120">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>How? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-penthesilea" xml:id="ep000065-e102140">
          <speaker>Penth. </speaker>
          <l>Euen so: </l>
          <l>Thy father was a foe dishonourable▪ </l>
          <l>And so the world reputes him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e102180">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>By all the gods— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-penthesilea" xml:id="ep000065-e102200">
          <speaker>Pent. </speaker>
          <l>Sweare not, for ere the closure of the battaile, </l>
          <l>If both the Generals please, with my good sword, </l>
          <l>In single combate Ile make good my word. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e102240">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>O that thou wert a man! but womens tongues </l>
          <l>Are priuiledg'd: come Priam, all his sonnes, </l>
          <l>The whole remayne of fifty, Ile make good </l>
          <l>My fathers honour gainst sufficient oddes. </l>
          <l>But for these scoulds, we leaue them to their sexe▪ </l>
          <l>What make they amongst souldiers. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-penthesilea" xml:id="ep000065-e102310">
          <speaker>Penth. </speaker>
          <l>Scorne not proud Pyrhus </l>
          <l>Our presence in the field; I tell thee Prince, </l>
          <l>I am a Queene, the Queene of Amazons, </l>
          <l>A warlike Nation disciplin'd in Armes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e102360">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Are you those Harlots famous through the world, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-050-a"/>
          <l>That haue vsurpt a Kingdome to your selues, </l>
          <l>And pent your sweete hearts in a barren isle, </l>
          <l>Where your adulterate sportes are exercis'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-penthesilea" xml:id="ep000065-e102410">
          <speaker>Pent. </speaker>
          <l>Curbe thy irregular tong: we are those women </l>
          <l>That practise armes, by which we purchase fame. </l>
          <l>All the yeare long, onely three monethes excepted, </l>
          <l>Those wherein Phoebus driues his Chariot, </l>
          <l>In height of splendor through the burning Cancer, </l>
          <l>The fiery Lyon, and the Virgins signe: </l>
          <l>Then we forsake our Sun-burnt Continent, </l>
          <l>And in a cooler clime, sport with our men, </l>
          <l>And then returne▪ if we haue issue male, </l>
          <l>Wee nurse them vp, then send them to their Fathers. </l>
          <l>If females, we then keepe them, and with irons </l>
          <l>Their right paps we seare off, with better ease </l>
          <l>To couch their speares, and practise feates of armes. </l>
          <l>We are those women, who expel'd our Land </l>
          <l>By Aegypts Tyrant: Conquered Asia, </l>
          <l>Aegypt and Cappadocia: these two Ladies </l>
          <l>Discend from Menelippe and Hyppolita, </l>
          <l>Who in Antiopes raigne▪ fought hand to hand </l>
          <l>With Hercules and Theseus; we are those </l>
          <l>That came for loue of hector to the field, </l>
          <l>And (being murdred) to reuenge his death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pylades" xml:id="ep000065-e102630">
          <speaker>Py. </speaker>
          <l>Then welcome Amazonians, as I liue </l>
          <l>I loue you though I hate you: but beware, </l>
          <l>Hate will out-way my loue, and Ile not spare </l>
          <l>Your ●usl ind squadrons: for my fathers fall, </l>
          <l>Troians, and Amazonians perish all. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e102690">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e102700">Alarum. Enter Pyrhus and Penthesilea. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pylades" xml:id="ep000065-e102710">
          <speaker>Py. </speaker>
          <l>Now Queene of Amazons, by the strong spirit </l>
          <l>Achilles left his sonne, I let thee know </l>
          <l>My father was an honourable Foe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-penthesilea" xml:id="ep000065-e102750">
          <speaker>Pent. </speaker>
          <l>Defiance Pyrhus, Ile to death proclaime, </l>
          <l>Hector was by Achilles basely slayne: </l>
          <l>And on his sonnes head, with my keene edg'd sword, </l>
          <l>And thundring stroaks, I will make good my word. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e102800">
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-050-b"/>Alarum. They are both wounded, and diuided by the two armies, who confusedly come betwixt them: to Pyrhus enter Agamemnon, Vlisses, and Menelaus. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-ulysses" xml:id="ep000065-e102810">
          <speaker>Vlis. </speaker>
          <l>What? wounded noble Pirhus? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e102830">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Wounded? no, </l>
          <l>I haue not met one that can raze the skinne </l>
          <l>Of great Achilles sonne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e102870">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>Yet blood drops from your arme. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e102890">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Not possible! </l>
          <l>Tis sure the blood of some slayne enemy. </l>
          <l>Come lets vs breake into the battailes center, </l>
          <l>And too't pel mel. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e102940">
          <speaker>Mene. </speaker>
          <l>But Neoptolemus, </l>
          <l>Wee prise thy safety more then all aduantage: </l>
          <l>Retire thy selfe to haue thy wounds bound vp, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e102980">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Cowards feare death, </l>
          <l>Ile venge my blood, though with the losse of breath. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000065-e103010">Alarum. Enter Paris. </stage>
          <l>Art thou a mad-man fellow, that aduenturest </l>
          <l>So neere the blood of Neoptolemus, </l>
          <l>Whose smallest drop must cost a Troians life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-paris" xml:id="ep000065-e103050">
          <speaker>Par. </speaker>
          <l>Art thou the bleeding issue of that Greeke? </l>
          <l>I, in reuenge of noble Hectors death, </l>
          <l>Slew in Apolloes Temple. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e103090">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Art thou then </l>
          <l>That coward and effeminate Troian boy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-paris" xml:id="ep000065-e103120">
          <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
          <l>Arme wounded Greek, I slew the false Achilles, </l>
          <l>An act which I am proud of. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e103150">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>Fall on the murderer, </l>
          <l>And flake him smaller then the Lybean sand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e103180">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>If any but my selfe offer one blow, </l>
          <l>Ile on the Troians party oppose him. </l>
          <l>Come Paris, though against the oddes of breath, </l>
          <l>Achilles wounded sonne, will venge his death. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e103230">Paris is slayne by Pyrhus. A retreate sounded. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e103240">
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-051-a"/>Enter then King Diomed, and Synon. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-diomede" xml:id="ep000065-e103250">
          <speaker>Dio. </speaker>
          <l>Why sound the Troians this retreate? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e103270">
          <speaker>Syn </speaker>
          <l>Paris is slayne, and Penthisilea </l>
          <l>Wounded by Pyrhus. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-diomede" xml:id="ep000065-e103300">
          <speaker>Dio. </speaker>
          <l>Come then Synon </l>
          <l>Goe with me to my Tent, this night we'le reuell </l>
          <l>With beauteous Cressida. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e103340">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Not I, I hate all women, painted beauty </l>
          <l>And I am opposites: I loue thee lesse </l>
          <l>Because thou doat'st on Troian Cressida. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-diomede" xml:id="ep000065-e103380">
          <speaker>Dio. </speaker>
          <l>She's worthy of our loue: I tell thee Synon, </l>
          <l>Shee is both constant, wise, and beautifull. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e103410">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>She's neither constant, wise, nor beautifull, </l>
          <l>Ile prooue it Diomed: foure Elements </l>
          <l>Meete in the structure of that Cressida, </l>
          <l>Of which there's not one pure: she's compact </l>
          <l>Meerely of blood, of bones and rotten flesh, </l>
          <l>Which makes her Leaprous, where the Sun exhales </l>
          <l>The moyst complexion, it doth putrifie </l>
          <l>The region of th'ayre: there's then another, </l>
          <l>Sometimes the Sunne sits muffled in his Caue, </l>
          <l>Whilst from the Clouds flye hideous showers of raine, </l>
          <l>Which sweepes the earths corruption into Brookes, </l>
          <l>Brookes into riuers, Riuers send their tribute, </l>
          <l>As they receiue it to their Soueraigne </l>
          <l>The seething Ocean: Thus Earth, Ayre, and Water, </l>
          <l>Are all infected, she then fram'd of these, </l>
          <l>Can she be beautefull? No Diomed, </l>
          <l>If they seeme faire, they haue the helpe of Arte, </l>
          <l>By nature they are vgly. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-diomede" xml:id="ep000065-e103600">
          <speaker>Dio. </speaker>
          <l>Leaue this detraction. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e103620">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Now for this Cressids wisedome, is she wise, </l>
          <l>Who would forsake her birth-right, her braue friend, </l>
          <l>The constant Troylus, for King Diomed; </l>
          <l>To trust the faith of Greekes, and to loue thee </l>
          <l>That art to Troy a profest enemy? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-diomede" xml:id="ep000065-e103680">
          <speaker>Dio. </speaker>
          <l>Canst thou disproue her constancy? </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-051-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e103700">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>I can. </l>
          <l>Neuer was woman constant to one man: </l>
          <l>For proofe, doe thou but put into one scale </l>
          <l>A feather, in the other Cressids truth, </l>
          <l>The feather shall downe weigh it: Diomed </l>
          <l>Wilt thou beleeue me, if I win not Cressid </l>
          <l>To be my sweete heart: yet haue no such face, </l>
          <l>No such proportion, to bewitch a Lady▪ </l>
          <l>I neuer practis'd court-ship, but am blunt; </l>
          <l>Nor can I file my tongue: yet if I winne not </l>
          <l>The most chast woman, I will cut it out. </l>
          <l>Shall I make proofe with her? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e103830">Enter Cressida. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-diomede" xml:id="ep000065-e103840">
          <speaker>Dio. </speaker>
          <l>There shee comes, </l>
          <l>Affront her Synon, Ile with-draw vnseene▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e103870">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>A gallant Lady, who but such a villaine▪ </l>
          <l>As Synon would betray her: but my vowe </l>
          <l>Is past, for she's a Troian. Cressida, </l>
          <l>You are well incountred: whether away sweet Lady? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e103920">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>To meete with Kingly Diomed, and with kisses </l>
          <l>Conduct him to his Tent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e103950">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Tis kindly done: </l>
          <l>You loue King Diomed then? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e103980">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>As mine owne life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e104000">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>What seest thou in him that is worth thy loue▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e104020">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>He's of a faire and comely personage. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e104040">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Personage? ha, ha. </l>
          <l>I prithee looke on me▪ and view me well, </l>
          <l>And thou wilt find some difference. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e104080">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>True, more oddes </l>
          <l>Twixt him and thee, then betwixt Mercury </l>
          <l>And limping Vulcan. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e104120">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Yetas fayre a blowse </l>
          <l>As you, sweete Lady, wedded with that Smith▪ </l>
          <l>And bedded too, a blacke complexion </l>
          <l>Is alwayes precious in a womans eye: </l>
          <l>Leaue Diomed, and loue me Cressida. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-052-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e104180">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>Thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e104200">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Mee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e104220">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>Deformity forbeare, I will to Diomed </l>
          <l>Make knowne thine insolence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e104250">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>I care not, for I, not desire to liue, </l>
          <l>If not belou'd of Cressid: tell the King </l>
          <l>If hee stood by, I would not spare a word. </l>
          <l>For thine owne part, rare goddesse, I adore thee, </l>
          <l>And owe thee diuine reuerence: Diomed </l>
          <l>Indeed's Aetolians King, and hath a Queene. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e104320">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>A Queene? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e104340">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>A Queene, that shal hereafter question thee: </l>
          <l>Or canst thou thinke hee loues thee really </l>
          <l>Beeing a Troian, but for present vse: </l>
          <l>Can Greekes loue Troians, are they not all sworne </l>
          <l>To do them outrage? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e104400">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>How canst thou then loue me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e104420">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>I am a pollitician, oathes with me </l>
          <l>Are but the tooles I worke with, I may breake </l>
          <l>An oath by my profession. Heare me further, </l>
          <l>Think'st thou King Diomed, forgets thy breach </l>
          <l>Of loue with Troylus? Ey or that he hopes </l>
          <l>Thou canst be constant to a second friend, </l>
          <l>That wast so false vnto thy first belou'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e104500">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>Synon thou art deceiu'd 'thou knowst I neuer </l>
          <l>Had left Prince Troylus, but by the command </l>
          <l>Of my old father Calchas. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e104540">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Then loue Diomed; </l>
          <l>Yes, do so still, but Cressid marke the end▪ </l>
          <l>If euer hee transport thee to Aetolia, </l>
          <l>His Queene wil bid thee welcome with a vengance: </l>
          <l>Hast thou more eyes then these? she'le fal to work▪ </l>
          <l>For such an other Vixen thou nere knewest▪ </l>
          <l>Come Cressida bee wise. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e104620">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>What shall I doe? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e104640">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Loue me, loue Synon. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e104660">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>Synon loues not mee▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-052-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e104680">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Ile sweare I do. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e104700">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>I heard thee say, that thou wouldst breake thine oath▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e104720">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Then Ile not sweare, because I will not breake it: </l>
          <l>But yet I loue thee Cressida, loue mee, </l>
          <l>Ile leaue the warres vnfinisht, Troy vnsackt; </l>
          <l>And to my natiue Country beare thee hence: </l>
          <l>Nay wench Ile do't; come kisse me Cressida. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e104780">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>Well, you may vse your pleasure; </l>
          <l>But good Synon keep this from Diomed. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e104810">Enter King Diomed. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-diomede" xml:id="ep000065-e104820">
          <speaker>Dio. </speaker>
          <l>Oh periured strumpet, </l>
          <l>Is this thy faith? now Synon Ile beleeue </l>
          <l>There is no truth in women. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e104860">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>Am I betrayed? oh thou base vgly villaine, </l>
          <l>Ile pull thine eyes out. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e104890">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Ha, ha, King Diomed, </l>
          <l>Did I not tell thee what thy sweet heart was. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e104920">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>Thou art a Traytor to all woman kinde. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e104940">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>I am, and nought more grieues me then to </l>
          <l>Thinke, a woman was my mother. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e104970">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>A villaine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e104990">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Right. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e105010">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>A Diuell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e105030">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Little better. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-diomede" xml:id="ep000065-e105050">
          <speaker>Dio. </speaker>
          <l>Go get you backe to Troy, away, begon, </l>
          <l>You shall no more be my Companion. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e105080">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>And now faire Trojan Weather-hen adew▪ </l>
          <l>And when thou next louest, thinke to be more true▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e105110">Exit. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e105120">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>Oh all you powers, aboue looke downe and see▪ </l>
          <l>How I am punisht for my periury. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e105150">Alarum. Enter Penthesilea with her Amazonians. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-penthesilea" xml:id="ep000065-e105160">
          <speaker>Penth. </speaker>
          <l>Stay, what sad Lady's this? whence are you woman? </l>
          <l>Of Troy or Greece? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e105190">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>I was of Troy till loue drew me from thence, </l>
          <l>But since haue soiourn'd in the Tents of Greece, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-053-a"/>
          <l>With Diomed King of Etolin: </l>
          <l>Oh had I neuer knowne him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-penthesilea" xml:id="ep000065-e105240">
          <speaker>Pent. </speaker>
          <l>Would you trust </l>
          <l>You honour amongst strangers? but sweete Lady </l>
          <l>Discourse your wrongs. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e105280">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>I was betray'd: </l>
          <l>It shames mee to relate the circumstance, </l>
          <l>By a false Greeke, one that doth hate our sexe, </l>
          <l>One Synon, if you meete him in the battaile, </l>
          <l>I with my teares intreate you be reueng'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-penthesilea" xml:id="ep000065-e105340">
          <speaker>Pent. </speaker>
          <l>How might wee know him? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e105360">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>His visage swart, and earthy ore his shoulder </l>
          <l>Hangs lockes of hayre, blacke as the Rauens plumes: </l>
          <l>His eyes downe looking, you shall hardly see </l>
          <l>One in whose shape appeares more treachery. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-penthesilea" xml:id="ep000065-e105410">
          <speaker>Pent. </speaker>
          <l>We loose much time: Lady hast you to Troy, </l>
          <l>And if we meete a fellow in the battaile </l>
          <l>Of your description, by our honor'd names, </l>
          <l>We'le haue his blood to recompence our shames. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e105460">Alarum. Enter Thersites. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-amazon" xml:id="ep000065-e105470">
          <speaker>Amaz. </speaker>
          <l>By her description this should be the man </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e105490">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>Compast with smockes and long coates: </l>
          <l>Now you whoores. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-penthesilea" xml:id="ep000065-e105520">
          <speaker>Pent. </speaker>
          <l>Is thy name Synon? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e105540">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>No, but I know Synon. </l>
          <l>Hee is my friend and brother. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-amazon" xml:id="ep000065-e105570">
          <speaker>Ama. </speaker>
          <l>For Synons sake, prepare thy selfe for slaughter▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e105590">Enter Synon. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e105600">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>He▪ who names Synon? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e105620">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>Brother thou nere couldst come in better time: </l>
          <l>See, see, how I am rounded. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-penthesilea" xml:id="ep000065-e105650">
          <speaker>Pent. </speaker>
          <l>Were euer such a payre of Diuels seene? </l>
          <l>They are so like, they needes must bee allied. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e105680">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>What can their Dammes say to vs? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-penthesilea" xml:id="ep000065-e105700">
          <speaker>Pent. </speaker>
          <l>You betray Ladies, enuy all our sexe, </l>
          <l>And that you now shall pay for girt him round. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e105730">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>I recant nothing, backe me sweete fac'd brother: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-053-b"/>
          <l>And now you witches▪ varlets, drabes, and queanes, </l>
          <l>We'le cut you all to fragments. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e105770">Alarum. Synon and Thersites beaten off by the Amazons. Pyrhus enters, fights with Penthesilea, after this a retreate sounded, then enters Menelaus, Agamemnon, Vlisses, Diomed. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e105780">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>The Troians sound retreate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-ulysses" xml:id="ep000065-e105800">
          <speaker>Vliss. </speaker>
          <l>Who saw young Pyrhus? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e105820">
          <speaker>Mene. </speaker>
          <l>I feare his too much rage hath spur'd him on </l>
          <l>Too farre amongst the Amazonian troopes. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e105850">Enter Synon and Thersites. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e105860">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Why stand you idle here, and let the Troians </l>
          <l>Lead warlike Pyrhus prisoner to the Towne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e105890">
          <speaker>Agam. </speaker>
          <l>How Pyrhus prisoner? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e105910">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>Wee saw him compast by the Amazous: </l>
          <l>Penthesilea with her bustain troopes. </l>
          <l>Layd load vpon his Helme. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-ulysses" xml:id="ep000065-e105950">
          <speaker>Ulis. </speaker>
          <l>Then this retreate </l>
          <l>Vpon the suddaine argues that they lead him </l>
          <l>Captiue to Troy. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e105990">Enter Pyrhus. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e106000">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Courage braue Princes, I haue got a prise </l>
          <l>Worthy the purchase, on my Launces poynt </l>
          <l>Sits pearcht the Amazonians lopt off head, </l>
          <l>Vpon my warlike sword her bleeding arme, </l>
          <l>At sight of which the Troians sound retreate: </l>
          <l>The honour of this day belongs to vs. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-omnes" xml:id="ep000065-e106070">
          <speaker>Omnes. </speaker>
          <l>To none but Neoptolemus. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e106090">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Synon you play'd the coward: so Thersites. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e106110">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>If not so. </l>
          <l>I had not liu'd to see Troyes ouerthrow </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e106140">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>When didst thou euer see a villaine valiant? </l>
          <l>What's past remember not, but what's to come: </l>
          <l>Priam hath shut his Gates, and will no more </l>
          <l>Meete him in armes: can you with all your valour </l>
          <l>Glide through the wals, if not what are you neerer </l>
          <l>For all your Ten yeares siege? </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-054-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e106210">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Tis true, some stratagem to enter Troy </l>
          <l>Were admirable: for Princes till I see </l>
          <l>The Temple burne wherein my father dyde, </l>
          <l>And Troy no Troy but ashes; my reuenge </l>
          <l>Will haue no sterne aspect, till I behold </l>
          <l>Troyes ground-sils swim in pooles of crimson goare </l>
          <l>Ramnusia's Alter fild with flowing helmes </l>
          <l>Of blood and braines: Priam and Hecuba </l>
          <l>Drag'd by this hand to death, and this my sword </l>
          <l>Rauish the brest of faire Polixena, </l>
          <l>I shall not thinke my fathers death reueng'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e106330">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>To him that can contriue </l>
          <l>A stratagem by which to enter Troy, </l>
          <l>Ile giue the whole spoile of Apolloes Temple. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e106370">
          <speaker>Mene. </speaker>
          <l>I my rich Tent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-ulysses" xml:id="ep000065-e106390">
          <speaker>Ulis. </speaker>
          <l>I the Palladium that I brought from Troy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-diomede" xml:id="ep000065-e106410">
          <speaker>Dio. </speaker>
          <l>I all my birth-right in Aetolia. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e106430">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Peace, tis here: I ha't. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e106450">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Ile hugge thee Synon. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e106470">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Touch me not, away: </l>
          <l>There'r's more hammers beating in my braine </l>
          <l>Then euer toucht Vulcans Anuile, more Ideaes </l>
          <l>Then Attomes, Embrions innumerable▪ </l>
          <l>Growing to perfect shape; and now 'tis good. </l>
          <l>Call for Endimions bastard, where's Epeus? </l>
          <l>Ile set him straight a worke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e106550">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Vpon some Engine Synon. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e106570">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>A horse, a horse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e106590">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Ten Kingdomes for a horse to enter Troy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e106610">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Stay, let me see: </l>
          <l>Vlisses you haue the Palladium. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-ulysses" xml:id="ep000065-e106640">
          <speaker>Vlis. </speaker>
          <l>I haue so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e106660">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Call for Epeus then, the Generall </l>
          <l>Hath no command in him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e106690">
          <speaker>Agam. </speaker>
          <l>Lets know the proiect. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e106710">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>And that Palladium stood in Pallas Temple, </l>
          <l>And Consecrate to her. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-054-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000065-ulysses" xml:id="ep000065-e106740">
          <speaker>Vlis. </speaker>
          <l>It did so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e106760">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Call for Epeus then. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e106780">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Lets heare what thou intendest. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e106800">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Ile haue an Horse built with so huge a bulke, </l>
          <l>As shall contayne a thousand men in Armes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e106830">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>And enter Troy with that? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e106850">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Doo't you, you trouble mine inuention, </l>
          <l>I am growne muddy with your interruption: </l>
          <l>Good young man lend more patience, heare me out: </l>
          <l>This Engine fram'd, and stuft with armed Greekes. </l>
          <l>(Will you take downe your Tents, march backe to Tenedos?) </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e106910">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>What shall the Horse doe then? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e106930">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Not gallop as your tongue doth: good Vlisses </l>
          <l>Lend me your apprehension; when the Troians </l>
          <l>Finde you are gone aboord, theyle straight suppose </l>
          <l>You'l not weigh Anchor: till the gods informe you </l>
          <l>Of your successe at Sea: if then a villaine </l>
          <l>Can driue into their eares, the goddesse Pallas </l>
          <l>Offended for her stolne Palladium: </l>
          <l>(Will you erect this Machine to her honour?) </l>
          <l>Withall that were it brought into her Temple, </l>
          <l>It would retayne the gilt Palladiums vertue. </l>
          <l>Might not the forged tale mooue aged Priam, </l>
          <l>To hale this Engine presently to Troy, </l>
          <l>Pull downe his wals for entrance, leaue a breach </l>
          <l>Where in the dead of night, all your whole Army </l>
          <l>May enter, take them sleeping in their beds, </l>
          <l>And put them all to sword. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e107100">
          <speaker>Agam. </speaker>
          <l>Tis rare! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e107120">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Tis admirable, I will aduenture </l>
          <l>My person in the Horse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e107150">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Do so, and get a thousand spirits more. </l>
          <l>King Agamemnon, if you like the proiect, </l>
          <l>Downe with your Tent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e107190">
          <speaker>Agam. </speaker>
          <l>Synon, wee will, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e107210">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Ile set a light vpon the wals of Troy </l>
          <l>Shall giue the summons when you shall returne▪ </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-055-a"/>
          <l>About it Princes: Pyrhus get you men </l>
          <l>In readinesse, I will expose my selfe </l>
          <l>To bewitch Priam with a weeping tale, </l>
          <l>I cannot to the life describe in words, </l>
          <l>What Ile expresse in action. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e107290">
          <speaker>Agam. </speaker>
          <l>Downe with our Tents. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e107310">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Ile to picke out bold Greeks to fil the horse: </l>
          <l>Shine bright you lampes of Heauen, for ere't be long </l>
          <l>We'le dim your radiant beames with flaming lights </l>
          <l>And bloody meteors, from Troyes burning streetes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e107360">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Such sights are glorious sparks in Synons eies, </l>
          <l>Who longs to feast the Diuell with Tragedies. </l>
        </sp>
        <trailer>Explicit Actus primus. </trailer>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="ep000065-e107400">
        <head>Actus Secundus: Scoena prima. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e107410">Enter Aeneas, and Chorebus. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-aeneas" xml:id="ep000065-e107420">
          <speaker>Aeneas </speaker>
          <l>The Grecians gone? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-chorebus" xml:id="ep000065-e107440">
          <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
          <l>All their tents rais'd, their ten yeares siege remoou'd▪ </l>
          <l>Now Troy may rest securely. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-aeneas" xml:id="ep000065-e107470">
          <speaker>Aene. </speaker>
          <l>They may report at their returne to Greece </l>
          <l>The welcome they haue had: what haue they wonne? </l>
          <l>But wounds, Times losse, shame, and confussion. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e107510">Enter K. Priam, Anthenor, young Polytes, Polixena, Hecuba, and Hellen, with attendance. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e107520">
          <speaker>Pri. </speaker>
          <l>We now are Lord of our owne Territories, </l>
          <l>Ten yeares kept from vs by th'inuading Greekes▪ </l>
          <l>Now wee may freely take a full suruey </l>
          <l>Of all Scamander plaine, drunke with the mixture </l>
          <l>Of th'opposite bloods of Troians and of Greekes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-hecuba" xml:id="ep000065-e107580">
          <speaker>Hecu. </speaker>
          <l>And royall Husband we haue cause to ioy, </l>
          <l>That after so long siege the Greekes are fled, </l>
          <l>And you in peace may rest your aged head. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-055-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000065-aeneas" xml:id="ep000065-e107620">
          <speaker>Aene. </speaker>
          <l>Vpon this East-side stood Vlisses Tent, </l>
          <l>The polliticke Greeke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-chorebus" xml:id="ep000065-e107650">
          <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
          <l>There was old Nestors quarter, </l>
          <l>And Agamemnons that; the Generall. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e107680">
          <speaker>Pria. </speaker>
          <l>Vpon the north-side of the field, Achilles </l>
          <l>That bloody Greeke pitcht, and vpon this plaine, </l>
          <l>I well remember, was my Hector slayne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-helen" xml:id="ep000065-e107720">
          <speaker>Hel. </speaker>
          <l>This empty place being South from all the rest, </l>
          <l>The valiant Diomed hath oft made good, </l>
          <l>And here, euen here, his rich Pauillion stood. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-hecuba" xml:id="ep000065-e107760">
          <speaker>Hecu. </speaker>
          <l>But here, euen here, neere to Duke Aiax tent, </l>
          <l>Round girt with Mirmidons, my Troilus fell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-chorebus" xml:id="ep000065-e107790">
          <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
          <l>Then was this place a standing Lake of blood, </l>
          <l>Part of which moysture the bright Sunne exhald; </l>
          <l>And part the thirsty earth hath quaft to Mars: </l>
          <l>But now the swords on eyther part are sheath'd, </l>
          <l>And after ten yeares tumults warres surcease, </l>
          <l>They layding their ships home with shamefull peace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e107860">
          <speaker>Pria. </speaker>
          <l>For which we'le prayse the gods, banquet and feast, </l>
          <l>Since by their flight, our glorious fame's increast. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e107890">The Horse is discouered. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-aeneas" xml:id="ep000065-e107900">
          <speaker>Aene. </speaker>
          <l>Soft, what huge Engine's that left on the strond, </l>
          <l>That beares the shape and figure of an Horse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-chorebus" xml:id="ep000065-e107930">
          <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
          <l>What, shal we hew it peace-meale with our swords? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e107950">
          <speaker>Pria. </speaker>
          <l>Oh be not rash, sure tis some mistery </l>
          <l>That this great Architecture doth include. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-chorebus" xml:id="ep000065-e107980">
          <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
          <l>But mine opinion is, this Steedes huge bulke </l>
          <l>Is stuft with Greekish guile. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-aeneas" xml:id="ep000065-e108010">
          <speaker>Aene. </speaker>
          <l>I rather thinke </l>
          <l>It is some monumentall Edifice </l>
          <l>Vnto the goddesse Pallas consecrate: </l>
          <l>Then spare your fury. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e108060">Enter Laocoon with a Iauelin. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-laocoon" xml:id="ep000065-e108070">
          <speaker>Law </speaker>
          <l>Why stand you gazing at this horrid craft, </l>
          <l>Forg'd by the flye Vlisses, is his braine </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-056-a"/>
          <l>Vnknowne in Troy? or can you looke for safety </l>
          <l>From those who ten yeares haue besieg'd your wals? </l>
          <l>Either this huge swolne bulke is big with souldiers, </l>
          <l>Longing to be deliuer'd of arm'd Greekes, </l>
          <l>Whose monstrous fatall and abhorred birth, </l>
          <l>Will be Troyes ruine: else this hill of timber </l>
          <l>This horse-like structure stabled vp in Troy, </l>
          <l>Wil spurne down these our wals, our towers demolish, </l>
          <l>Which it shall neuer: come you Troian youth </l>
          <l>That loue the publicke safety, no proud Greeke </l>
          <l>Vpon this Steedes backe, o're 'Troyes wall shall ride. </l>
          <l>First with this Iauelin Ile transpearce his side. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e108220">
          <speaker>Pria. </speaker>
          <l>What meanes Laocoon? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-aeneas" xml:id="ep000065-e108240">
          <speaker>Aene. </speaker>
          <l>Princes stay his fury. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-laocoon" xml:id="ep000065-e108260">
          <speaker>Lao. </speaker>
          <l>Harke Troians, if a iarring noyse of Armes, </l>
          <l>Sighed not throw these deep Cauernes, I devine </l>
          <l>This gluttenous wombe hath swallowed a whole band </l>
          <l>Of men in steele, then with your swords and glaues </l>
          <l>Rip vp his tough sides, and imbowell him, </l>
          <l>That we may prooue how they haue lin'd his intrailes. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e108330">Enter two souldiers bringing in Synon bound. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-soldier" xml:id="ep000065-e108340">
          <speaker>Soul. </speaker>
          <l>Stay, and proceed, no further in your rage, </l>
          <l>Till we haue learnt some nouell from this Greeke, </l>
          <l>Whom in a ditch we found fast giu'd and bound. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e108380">
          <speaker>Pria. </speaker>
          <l>Laocoon cease thy violence till we know </l>
          <l>From that poore Grecian, what that Machine meanes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e108410">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Oh me, (of all on earth most miserable,) </l>
          <l>Whom neither Heauens will succour, earth preserue, </l>
          <l>Nor seas keepe safe, I, whom the Heauens dispise, </l>
          <l>The Earth abandons, and the Seas disdaine: </l>
          <l>Where shal I shroud me? whom, but now the Greekes </l>
          <l>Threatned with vengeance; and escap'd from them, </l>
          <l>Falne now into the hands of Troians, menacing death: </l>
          <l>The world affoords no place, to wretched Synon, </l>
          <l>Of comfort, for where ere I fixe my foote, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-056-b"/>
          <l>I tread vpon my graue: the foure vast corners </l>
          <l>Of this large Vniuerse, in all their roomes </l>
          <l>And spacious emptinesse, will not affoord me </l>
          <l>My bodies length of rest: where ere I flye, </l>
          <l>Or stay, or turne, Death's th'obiect of mine eye! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e108560">
          <speaker>Pria. </speaker>
          <l>What art thou? or whence com'st thou? briefly speake? </l>
          <l>Thou wretched man, thou moou'st vs with thy teares: </l>
          <l>Vnbind him souldiers. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e108600">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Shall I deny my selfe to be of Greece? </l>
          <l>Because I am brought Captiue into Troy? </l>
          <l>No Synon cannot lye: Heauen, Earth, and Sea, </l>
          <l>From all which I am out-cast, witnesse with me </l>
          <l>That Synon cannot lye: thrice damn'd Vlisses, </l>
          <l>The black-hair'd Pyrhus, and horned Menelaus </l>
          <l>Grook-back'd Thersites, luxurious Diomed, </l>
          <l>And all the rable of detested Greekes, </l>
          <l>I call to witnesse, Synon cannot lye. </l>
          <l>Could I haue oyl'd my tongue, and cring'd my ham, </l>
          <l>Suppled mine humble knee to croutch and bend, </l>
          <l>Heau'd at my bonnet, shrugg'd my shoulders thus, </l>
          <l>Grin'd in their faces, Synon then had stood, </l>
          <l>Whom now this houre must stue in his own blood. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-aeneas" xml:id="ep000065-e108750">
          <speaker>Aene. </speaker>
          <l>The perfect image of a wretched creature, </l>
          <l>His speeches begge remorse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e108780">
          <speaker>Pria. </speaker>
          <l>Alas good man, </l>
          <l>Shake off the timerous feare of seruile death, </l>
          <l>Though 'mongst vs Troians, and thy selfe a Greeke, </l>
          <l>Thou art not now amongst thine enemies, </l>
          <l>Thy life Ile warrant, onely let vs know </l>
          <l>What this Horse meanes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e108850">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Greece I renounce thee, thou hast throwne me off, </l>
          <l>Faire Troy● am thy creature. Now Ile vnrip </l>
          <l>Vlisses craft, my fatall enemy. </l>
          <l>Who sold to death the Duke Palamides, </l>
          <l>My Kinsman Troians (though in garments torne) </l>
          <l>Synon stands here, yet is he nobly borne: </l>
          <l>For that knowne murder did I haint his Tent </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-057-a"/>
          <l>With rayling menaces, horrible exclaimes, </l>
          <l>Many a blacke-saint, of wishes, oathes, and curses </l>
          <l>Haue I sung at his window, then demaunding </l>
          <l>Iustice of Agamemnon, Diomed, </l>
          <l>Duke Nestor with the other Lords of Greece, </l>
          <l>For murder of the Prince Palamides, </l>
          <l>And being denide it in my most vexation, </l>
          <l>My bitter tongue spar'd not to barke at them: </l>
          <l>For this I was obseru'd, lookt through and through </l>
          <l>Ulisses braine had markt me, for my tongue </l>
          <l>And fatted me for death by Calchas meanes, </l>
          <l>He wrought so farre that I should haue bin offred </l>
          <l>Vnto the gods for sacrifice, the Priest </l>
          <l>Lifting his hand aloft to strike me dead, </l>
          <l>I lept downe from the Altar, and so fled, </l>
          <l>Pursuite and search was made, but I lay safe </l>
          <l>In a thicke tuft of sedge, till I was found </l>
          <l>By these your souldiers, who thus brought me bound. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e109110">
          <speaker>Pria. </speaker>
          <l>Thou now art free secur'd from all their tyrannys </l>
          <l>Now tell vs what's the meaning of this Horse? </l>
          <l>Why haue they left him here, themselues being gon? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e109150">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>My new releas'd hands, thus I heaue on hye, </l>
          <l>Witnesse you gods, that Synon cannot lye, </l>
          <l>But as a new adopted Troian now </l>
          <l>By Priams grace; I here protest by Ioue, </l>
          <l>By these eternall fires that spangle Heauen, </l>
          <l>The Alter, and that sacrificing sword, </l>
          <l>Beneath whose stroake I lay, since my base Country </l>
          <l>Casts me away to death, I am now borne </l>
          <l>A sonne of Troy: not Hector whilst he liu'd </l>
          <l>More dammag'd Greece by his all wounding arme, </l>
          <l>Then I by my discouery: Well, you know </l>
          <l>How the Greekes honour Pallas, who incenst </l>
          <l>Because Vlisses the Palladium stole </l>
          <l>Out of her Temple, and her Warders slew, </l>
          <l>In rage she threatned ruine to all Greece: </l>
          <l>Therefore to her hath Calchas built this Horse. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-057-b"/>
          <l>(Greece pardon me, and all my Countrey gods </l>
          <l>Be deafe to Synons tale, and let it bee </l>
          <l>Henceforth forgot that I was borne in Greece, </l>
          <l>Least times to come record what I reueale, </l>
          <l>The blacke confusion of my Natiue weale. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e109370">
          <speaker>Priam. </speaker>
          <l>And what's that Synon? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e109390">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Where left I? at the Horse, built of that size, </l>
          <l>Lēast you should giue it entrance at your Gates: </l>
          <l>For know should your rude hands dare to prophan </l>
          <l>This gift sacred to Pallas; Rots and diseases, </l>
          <l>Pests and infections shall depopulate you, </l>
          <l>And in a small short season, they returning, </l>
          <l>Shal see thy subiects slain, faire Troy bright burning. </l>
          <l>I'm euen with thee Vlisses, and my breath </l>
          <l>Strikes all Greece home for my intended death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e109490">
          <speaker>Pria. </speaker>
          <l>Thankes Synon, we shall bounteously reward thee, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-aeneas" xml:id="ep000065-e109510">
          <speaker>Aene. </speaker>
          <l>And see my Leige, to make good his report, </l>
          <l>Laocoon, he that with his Iauelin pierst </l>
          <l>This gift of Pallas, round embrac'd with Snakes, </l>
          <l>That winde their traines about his wounded wast, </l>
          <l>And for his late presumption sting him dead. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e109570">
          <speaker>Pria. </speaker>
          <l>We haue not seene so strange a prodigy, </l>
          <l>Laocoon hath offended all the gods, </l>
          <l>In his prophane attempt. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e109610">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Then lend your helping hands, </l>
          <l>To lift vp that Pallad an monument </l>
          <l>Into Troyes Citty: Leauers, Cables, Cords. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-chorebus" xml:id="ep000065-e109650">
          <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
          <l>It cannot enter through the Citty Gates. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e109670">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Downe with the wals then. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-chorebus" xml:id="ep000065-e109690">
          <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
          <l>These wals that ten yeares haue defended Troy, </l>
          <l>For all their seruice shall wee ruine them. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e109720">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>But this shall not defend you for ten yeares, </l>
          <l>But make your Towne impregnable for euer. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e109750">
          <speaker>Pria. </speaker>
          <l>Downe with the wals then, each man lend a hand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-chorebus" xml:id="ep000065-e109770">
          <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
          <l>I heare a noyse of Armour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-aeneas" xml:id="ep000065-e109790">
          <speaker>Aene. </speaker>
          <l>Ha, what's that? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-chorebus" xml:id="ep000065-e109810">
          <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
          <l>I feare some treason in that Horse inclosed: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-058-a"/>
          <l>Nor will I lend an hand to hale him in. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-omnes" xml:id="ep000065-e109840">
          <speaker>Omnes. </speaker>
          <l>Downe with the Wals. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-aeneas" xml:id="ep000065-e109860">
          <speaker>Aene. </speaker>
          <l>And Troians now after your ten years toile, </l>
          <l>Dayes battailes, the fields trouble, and nights watch, </l>
          <l>This is the first of all your rest, feast, banquet, ioy and play, </l>
          <l>Pallas is ours, the Greekes sayl'd hence away. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e109910">
          <speaker>Pria. </speaker>
          <l>Here we release all Centries and commit </l>
          <l>Our broken wals to her Celestiall guard: </l>
          <l>We will reward thee Synon, the Greekes gone, </l>
          <l>Priam. may ● est his age, in his soft throne. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e109960">Exe. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e109970">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>So, so, so, </l>
          <l>Synon I hope shall warme his hands annon, </l>
          <l>At a bright goodly bone-fire: Here's the Key </l>
          <l>Vnto this Machine by Epeus built, </l>
          <l>Which hath already with his brazen brest, </l>
          <l>Tilted Troies wall downe, and annon being drunke </l>
          <l>With the best blood of Greece, in dead of night </l>
          <l>Hauing surcharg'd his stomacke, will spew out </l>
          <l>A thousand men in Armes: sweet mid-night come, </l>
          <l>I long to maske me in thy sable Wings, </l>
          <l>That I may do some mischiefe and blacke deedes: </l>
          <l>We shall haue rare sport, admirable spoyle, </l>
          <l>Cutting of throats, with stabbing, wounding, killing </l>
          <l>Some dead a sleep, and some halfe sleep, halfe wakes </l>
          <l>Some dancing Antickes in their bloody shirts, </l>
          <l>To which their wiues cries, &amp; their infants shreeks, </l>
          <l>Play musicke, braue mirth, pleasing harmony: </l>
          <l>Then hauing spitt young children on our speares, </l>
          <l>We'le rost them at the scorching flames of Troy: </l>
          <l>Flye swift you winged minutes till you catch </l>
          <l>That long-wisht houre of stilnes: in which Troy </l>
          <l>Sleeps her last sleep, made drunk with wine and ioy. </l>
          <l>In the receiuing of this fatall Steede, </l>
          <l>Sicke Troy this day hath swallowed such a pill, </l>
          <l>Shall search her intrayles, and her ●iues blood spill. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e110230">Exit. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e110240">Enter Agamemnon, Menelaus, Vlisses, with souldiers in a soft march, without noise. </stage>
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-058-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e110250">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>Soft, soft, and let your stilnesse suite with night, </l>
          <l>Faire Phebe keepe thy siluer splendor in, </l>
          <l>And be not seene to night. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e110290">
          <speaker>Mene. </speaker>
          <l>Were Phebe in my case, </l>
          <l>She soone would blush to show her horned face. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-ulysses" xml:id="ep000065-e110320">
          <speaker>Vliss. </speaker>
          <l>We would not haue a starre cast it's cleare eye </l>
          <l>On our darke enterprise: too fast: so, still. </l>
          <l>Here Ambush, till you see the flaming Torch, </l>
          <l>Synon this night vpon the wals of Troy, </l>
          <l>Will tosse about his eares, as a true signall, </l>
          <l>The great Epean structure is receiu'd, </l>
          <l>And we may find safe entrance by the breach. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e110400">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>A stand, the word through all the Regiment, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e110420">
          <speaker>Mene. </speaker>
          <l>A stand. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e110440">Enter Synon with a torch aboue. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e110450">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Thy euerlasting sleepe sleepe carelesse Troy, </l>
          <l>This horrid night buried in Wine and mirth, </l>
          <l>This fatall Horse spur'd by the braine of Synon, </l>
          <l>Hath lept ore Troys high bulwarks great with Greeks, </l>
          <l>Foure times in raysing vp the monument, </l>
          <l>A shaking sound of Armour harshly iar'd </l>
          <l>In all the Princes eares, and had they not </l>
          <l>Beene drunk in Synons teares, they'd found our guile. </l>
          <l>It is now mid-night. The blacke darknesse falne, </l>
          <l>And rould o're all the world, as well the Poles, </l>
          <l>As the great Ocean, and the earth: now's the time </l>
          <l>For tragicke slaughter, clad in gules and sables, </l>
          <l>To spring out of Hels iawes, and play strang reakes </l>
          <l>In sleepy Troy, this bright and flaming brand </l>
          <l>Which I so often gire about mine eares, </l>
          <l>Is signall for the Armies quicke returne, </l>
          <l>And make proud Illium like my bright torch burne, </l>
          <l>Winke all you eyes of Heauen, or you shall be </l>
          <l>Blood-shot to view Troyes dismall Tragedy. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e110650">Exit. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e110660">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>The signals on the war: forward braue souldiers, </l>
          <l>The Horse is entred, Synons Tale beleeu'd. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-059-a"/>
          <l>And wee this night shall see the sacke of Troy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e110700">
          <speaker>Men. </speaker>
          <l>March on then, the black darknes couers vs, </l>
          <l>And we without suspition easily may </l>
          <l>Disperse our selues about these high built wals: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-ulysses" xml:id="ep000065-e110740">
          <speaker>Vlis. </speaker>
          <l>Now with a soft march enter at this breach </l>
          <l>But giue no token of a loud Alarme, </l>
          <l>Till we haue met with Pyrhus and the rest, </l>
          <l>Whom the Steedes bulke includes. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e110790">They march softly in at one doore, and presently in at another. Enter Synon with a stealing pace, holding the key in his hand. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e110800">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Soft, soft, ey so, hereafter Ages tell, </l>
          <l>How Synons key vnlockt the gates of Hell. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e110830">Pyrhus, Diomed, and the rest, leape from out the Horse. And as if groping in the darke, meete with Agamemnon and the rest: who after knowledge imbrace. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e110840">
          <speaker>Pyrhus. </speaker>
          <l>The Generall? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e110860">
          <speaker>Agam. </speaker>
          <l>Pyrhus? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-diomede" xml:id="ep000065-e110880">
          <speaker>Dio. </speaker>
          <l>Menelaus? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e110900">
          <speaker>Mene. </speaker>
          <l>Diomed? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e110920">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>My Vrchin? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e110940">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>What my Toade? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e110960">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Well met in Troy great Lords. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-ulysses" xml:id="ep000065-e110980">
          <speaker>Vlis. </speaker>
          <l>Where are wee now? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e111000">
          <speaker>Sy. </speaker>
          <l>In the high street, nere to the Church of Pallas, </l>
          <l>And this you past, the gate cal'd Dardanus. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e111030">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Then here begins Troyes fatall tragedy: </l>
          <l>Princes of Greece, at once vnsheath your swords, </l>
          <l>And heare protest with Neoptolemus, </l>
          <l>By our fore-father Peleus, grandam Thetis, </l>
          <l>The Emperious goddesse of the Sea, that made </l>
          <l>Achilles, saue in th'heele, invulnerable, </l>
          <l>And by my father great Aeacides, </l>
          <l>His glorious name, his Armour which I weare, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-059-b"/>
          <l>His bloody wounds, and his blacke sepulchre; </l>
          <l>I here abiure all respite, mercy, sleepe, </l>
          <l>Vntill this Citty be a place confus'd: </l>
          <l>This murall girdle that begirts it round </l>
          <l>A Cawsey for the Greekes to trample on, </l>
          <l>The place a stone-heape swimming in an Ocean </l>
          <l>Of Troian blood, which shall from farre appeare </l>
          <l>Like an high Rocke in the red Sea. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e111200">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>A braue show, </l>
          <l>To see full Boates in blood of Troians rowe, </l>
          <l>And the poore labouring Snakes with armes spread swimms </l>
          <l>In luke-warme blood of their allyes and kin. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e111250">
          <speaker>Men. </speaker>
          <l>Whence must this Ocean flowe? </l>
          <l>From thousand Springs </l>
          <l>Of gentle and ignoble, base and Kings. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e111290">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Set on then, none retire; </l>
          <l>Waue in the one hand steele, in the other fire. </l>
          <l>Loude Drummes and Trumpets ring Troyes fatall peale, </l>
          <l>That now lyes drawing on, the word be vengeance, </l>
          <l>Alarum, at that watch-word fire, and kill, </l>
          <l>And wide-mouth'd Orchus with whole legions fill▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e111360">Aloude Alarum. Enter a Troian in his night-gowne all unready. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-trojan" xml:id="ep000065-e111370">
          <speaker>Tro. </speaker>
          <l>T'was an alarum sure that frighted mee </l>
          <l>In my dead sleepe, 'twas neare the Dardan port: </l>
          <l>Ioue grant that all be well. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e111410">Enter his wife as from bed. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-wife" xml:id="ep000065-e111420">
          <speaker>Wife. </speaker>
          <l>Oh Heauen! what tumult's this </l>
          <l>That hurryes through the fatall streetes of Troy▪ </l>
          <l>I feare some treason. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-trojan" xml:id="ep000065-e111460">
          <speaker>Tro. </speaker>
          <l>Stay Wife, lay thine eare </l>
          <l>Vnto the ground and list, if we can gather </l>
          <l>Of what condition this strange vproare is </l>
          <l>That riots at this late vnseasoned houre? </l>
          <l>Sure 'tis the noise of war, whence should it grow? </l>
          <l>The Greekes are sayl'd hence, Troy needes feare no foe. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-060-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000065-wife" xml:id="ep000065-e111530">
          <speaker>Wife. </speaker>
          <l>The horrid stirre comes on this way towards vs. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-trojan" xml:id="ep000065-e111550">
          <speaker>Troi. </speaker>
          <l>Oh whither shall we turne? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e111570">A great cry within. Alarum, Enter Pyrhus with the rest their weapons draw and torches. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-wife" xml:id="ep000065-e111580">
          <speaker>Wife. </speaker>
          <l>Oh saue mee husband. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-trojan" xml:id="ep000065-e111600">
          <speaker>Troi. </speaker>
          <l>Succour me deere wife. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-omnes" xml:id="ep000065-e111620">
          <speaker>Omnes. </speaker>
          <l>Vengeance for Greece and Neoptolemus. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e111640">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>So flye the word along, dye old and young, </l>
          <l>Mourne Troy in ashes for Achilles losse, </l>
          <l>Steele in one hand, in th'other fire-brands tosse. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e111680">Exeunt: </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e111690">Enter Chorebus at one doore, at another Aeneas with their weapons drawne. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-chorebus" xml:id="ep000065-e111700">
          <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
          <l>This horrid clamour that hath cal'd mee vp </l>
          <l>From my deepe rest, much, much amazeth mee; </l>
          <l>Tis on the right hand, now vpon the left, </l>
          <l>It goes before me and it followes mee: </l>
          <l>Oh Ioue expound the meaning of this horrour </l>
          <l>Which the darke mid-night makes more terrible. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-aeneas" xml:id="ep000065-e111770">
          <speaker>Aene. </speaker>
          <l>this streete is cleare, but now I climb'd a Turret, </l>
          <l>And I might well discerne halfe Troy in fire, </l>
          <l>And by the flame the burnisht Helmets glister </l>
          <l>Of men in Armes, whence Ioue Olympicke knowes. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e111820">Enter a second Troian. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-trojan_2" xml:id="ep000065-e111830">
          <speaker>2. Tro. </speaker>
          <l>Where shall I hide me? Treason, Troyes betray'd; </l>
          <l>The fatall horse was full of armed Greekes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-chorebus" xml:id="ep000065-e111860">
          <speaker>Chore. </speaker>
          <l>Of Greekes? damn'd Synon. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-trojan_2" xml:id="ep000065-e111880">
          <speaker>2. Tro. </speaker>
          <l>Prince Chorebus fly, </l>
          <l>Fly great Aeneas. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-chorebus" xml:id="ep000065-e111910">
          <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
          <l>Which way? where? or how? </l>
          <l>Are we not rounded with a quick-set hedge </l>
          <l>Of pointed steele? are not the gates possest </l>
          <l>And strongly man'd with Greekes? death euery where, </l>
          <l>Then whither should we flye? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-aeneas" xml:id="ep000065-e111970">
          <speaker>Aene. </speaker>
          <l>Into the throng. </l>
          <l>Where blowes are dealt, where our inflamed Turrets </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-060-b"/>
          <l>Burne with most fury. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-chorebus" xml:id="ep000065-e112010">
          <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
          <l>Nobly speakes Aeneas. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-aeneas" xml:id="ep000065-e112030">
          <speaker>Aene. </speaker>
          <l>Then whither flames, and furies, shreiks and clamors, </l>
          <l>Death, danger, and the deuils hurry vs, </l>
          <l>Thither will we: follow where I shall lead, </l>
          <l>Thousands shall fall by vs ere we be dead. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e112080">Enter Thersites with other Greekes. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e112090">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>Charge on these naked Troians, and cry thus, </l>
          <l>Vengeance for Greece and Neoptolemus. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-chorebus" xml:id="ep000065-e112120">
          <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
          <l>Charge on these armed Grecians, and thus cry, </l>
          <l>We may yet liue to see ten thousand dye. </l>
          <l>They charge the Greekes and kill them, Thersites runs away. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-chorebus" xml:id="ep000065-e112160">
          <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
          <l>Well fought braue spirits in our vtter ruine, </l>
          <l>We are Conquerours yet: let's don these Greekish habits, </l>
          <l>And mixe our selues amongst their Armed ranks; </l>
          <l>So vnexpected murder all we meete: </l>
          <l>The darkenesse will assist our enterprise. </l>
          <l>These Greekish Armes this night by Troians Worne </l>
          <l>Shall to the fall of many Grecians turne. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e112240">Enter all the Greekes. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-omnes" xml:id="ep000065-e112250">
          <speaker>Omnes. </speaker>
          <l>Burne fire, and kill, as you wound cry thus, </l>
          <l>Vengeance for Greece and Neoptolemus. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e112280">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e112290">Enter Aeneas followed by Hectors ghost </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-aeneas" xml:id="ep000065-e112300">
          <speaker>Aene. </speaker>
          <l>What art thou that with such a grim aspect, </l>
          <l>In this black night so darke and turbulent, </l>
          <l>Haunts me in euery corner of my house </l>
          <l>Which yet burnes o're mine eares? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-hector" xml:id="ep000065-e112350">
          <speaker>Hect. </speaker>
          <l>Doest thou not know me? </l>
          <l>Or can Aeneas so forget his friend? </l>
          <l>This face did fright Achilles in the field, </l>
          <l>And when I shooke these lockes, now knotted all, </l>
          <l>As bak't in blood; all Greece hath quak't and trembled. </l>
          <l>Looke on mine Heeles, and thou maist see those thongs </l>
          <l>By which so often I was dragg'd 'bout Troy, </l>
          <l>My body made an vniuersall Wound </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-061-a"/>
          <l>By the vnnumbred hands of Mirmidons, </l>
          <l>This th'hand that tost so many wild-fire balls </l>
          <l>Into the Argiue fleete, and this the body </l>
          <l>That deck't in Aiax and Ac illes spoyles </l>
          <l>Ridde from the fields triumphant thorow Troy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-aeneas" xml:id="ep000065-e112490">
          <speaker>Aene. </speaker>
          <l>Prince Hector? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-hector" xml:id="ep000065-e112510">
          <speaker>Hect. </speaker>
          <l>Hence Aeneas post from Troy, </l>
          <l>Reare that abroad the gods at home destroy. </l>
          <l>The Citty burnes, Priam and Priams glory </l>
          <l>Is all expir'd, and tumbled headlong downe: </l>
          <l>Cassandraes long neglected prophesies </l>
          <l>This night fulfils. If either strength or might </l>
          <l>Could haue protected Troy, this hand, this arms </l>
          <l>That sau'd it oft, had kept it still from harme. </l>
          <l>But Troy is doom'd, here gins the fatall Story </l>
          <l>Of her sad sacke and fall of all her glory. </l>
          <l>Away, and beare thy Country gods along, </l>
          <l>Thousands shall issue from thy sacred seede, </l>
          <l>Citties more rich then this the Grecian spoyle, </l>
          <l>In after times shall thy successors build, </l>
          <l>Where Hectors name shall liue eternally. </l>
          <l>One Romulus, another Bruite shall reare, </l>
          <l>These shall nor Honours, nor iust Rectors want, </l>
          <l>Lumbardies roome, great Britaines Troy-nouant. </l>
          <l>Heu fuge nate Dea, teque his pater eripe flammis; </l>
          <l>Hostis habet muros, ruit alto a culmine Troia </l>
          <l>Sacra, suosque tibi commendat Troia penates </l>
          <l>Hos cape fatorum comites, his moenia quaere </l>
          <l>Magna: pererrato statues quae denique ponto. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e112750">Exit. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-aeneas" xml:id="ep000065-e112760">
          <speaker>Aene. </speaker>
          <l>Soft lie thy bones and sweetly may they rest </l>
          <l>Thou wonder of all worthyes, but Troy burnes: </l>
          <l>Thousands of Troian Corses blocke the streetes, </l>
          <l>Some flying fall, and some their killers kill: </l>
          <l>Where shall I meete thee death? before I flye, </l>
          <l>Some Conquerours yet, shall brauely conquered die. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e112830">Exit. </stage>
        <trailer>Explicit Actus secundus. </trailer>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="ep000065-e112850">
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-061-b"/>
        <head>Acius Secundus: Scoena prima. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e112860">Enter Priam in his night-gowne and slippers, after him Hecuba, Hellena, Andromache, Hellena, Cassandra, Polyxena, Polites, Astianax. An Alarum. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-all" xml:id="ep000065-e112870">
          <speaker>All La. </speaker>
          <l>Oh helpe vs father Priam, Oh the Greeks. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e112890">
          <speaker>Fri. </speaker>
          <l>I haue done more then age would suffer me </l>
          <l>They haue tilted masts against my Pallace gates, </l>
          <l>And burst them open. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-all" xml:id="ep000065-e112930">
          <speaker>All La. </speaker>
          <l>Oh father Priam, whether shall we flye? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e112950">
          <speaker>Pri. </speaker>
          <l>We are incompast round with sword &amp; fire, </l>
          <l>'Las Daughters, 'las my young Astianax. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-all" xml:id="ep000065-e112980">
          <speaker>All La. </speaker>
          <l>Oh heauen, they come, where may we hide vs safe? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e113000">
          <speaker>Pri. </speaker>
          <l>Safety and helpe are both fled out of Troy, </l>
          <l>And left behind nothing but massacre: </l>
          <l>My Pallace is surpris'd my guard all slaine, </l>
          <l>My selfe am wounded, but more with your shreeks, </l>
          <l>Then by the swords of Grecians: come let's flie. </l>
          <l>Vnto the sacred Altar of the gods. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-all" xml:id="ep000065-e113070">
          <speaker>All La. </speaker>
          <l>May we be safe there father? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e113090">
          <speaker>Pri. </speaker>
          <l>Safe? Oh no; </l>
          <l>Safety is fled. Death hath our liues in chase, </l>
          <l>And since we needes must dye, let's chuse this place. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e113130">Exeunt </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e113140">Alarum. Enter at the one doore Hellen, at the other Cresida. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e113150">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>Whither runnes Hellen? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-helen" xml:id="ep000065-e113170">
          <speaker>Hel. </speaker>
          <l>Whither should I fly? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e113190">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>See, Troy is not it selfe, oh wretched Hellen! </l>
          <l>To shunne the Greekes to run into the fire, </l>
          <l>Or flying fire, perish by Greekish steele: </l>
          <l>Which hadst thou rather chuse? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-helen" xml:id="ep000065-e113240">
          <speaker>Hel. </speaker>
          <l>Death, in what shape soeuer hee appeares </l>
          <l>To me is welcome, I'le no longer shun him; </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-062-a"/>
          <l>But here with Cresida abide him: here, </l>
          <l>Oh, why was Hellen at the first so faire, </l>
          <l>To be come subiect to so foule an end? </l>
          <l>Or how hath Cresids beauty sinn'd 'gainst Heauen, </l>
          <l>That it is branded thus with leprosie? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e113320">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>I in conceit thought that I might contend </l>
          <l>Against Heauens splendor, I did once suppose, </l>
          <l>There was no beauty but in Cresids lookes, </l>
          <l>But in her eyes no pure diuinity: </l>
          <l>But now behold mee Hellen. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-helen" xml:id="ep000065-e113380">
          <speaker>Hel. </speaker>
          <l>In her I see </l>
          <l>All beauties frailty, and this obiect makes </l>
          <l>All fairenesse to show vgly in it selfe: </l>
          <l>But to see breathlesse Virgins pil'd on heape, </l>
          <l>What lesse can Hellen doe then curse these Starres </l>
          <l>That shin'd so bright at her natiuity, </l>
          <l>And with her nayles teare out these shining balls </l>
          <l>That haue set Troy on fire? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e113470">Enter Pyrhus, Agamemnon, Menelaus, &amp;c. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e113480">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Pierce all the Troian Ladies with your swords, </l>
          <l>Least 'mongst them you might spare Polixena. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e113510">
          <speaker>Agam. </speaker>
          <l>Stay, I should know that face, tis Helena? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e113530">
          <speaker>Mene. </speaker>
          <l>My Queene? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-helen" xml:id="ep000065-e113550">
          <speaker>Hel. </speaker>
          <l>I am not Hellen, but Polixena: </l>
          <l>Therefore reuengfull Neoptolemus </l>
          <l>Doe Justice on me for thy fathers death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e113590">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Polixena? by all Achilles honours </l>
          <l>Ile part thee limbe from limbe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cressida" xml:id="ep000065-e113620">
          <speaker>Cres. </speaker>
          <l>Pyrhus forbeare, </l>
          <l>It's the Spartan Queene. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e113650">
          <speaker>Men. </speaker>
          <l>If Hellen, the adultorous strumpet dyes, </l>
          <l>Ile be her deaths-man. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-helen" xml:id="ep000065-e113680">
          <speaker>Hel. </speaker>
          <l>Strike home Menelaus, </l>
          <l>Death from thy hand is welcome. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e113710">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>Hold I say, </l>
          <l>Shee's Clitemnestras sister, for her sake </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-062-b"/>
          <l>Hellen shall liue, and Kingly Menelaus </l>
          <l>Receiue her into fauour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e113760">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Agamemnon </l>
          <l>Is too remisse, I haue sworne all blood to spill </l>
          <l>I meet with, and this one will Pyrhus kill. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e113800">
          <speaker>Men. </speaker>
          <l>And I this other. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e113820">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>For our sake Menelaus let her liue. </l>
          <l>Was not our sister borne against her will </l>
          <l>From Sparta? for that wrong done by the Troians </l>
          <l>Doth not Troy burne? and are not all our swords </l>
          <l>Stain'd in the blood of Paris slaughtered friends? </l>
          <l>You shall be reconcil'd to Helend, </l>
          <l>And beare her backe to Greece. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e113900">Enter Thersites. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e113910">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>Hellen at shrift▪ alas poore penitent Queane, </l>
          <l>Dost heare me Menelaus? pardon her, </l>
          <l>Take her againe to Sparta, thou'lt else want </l>
          <l>So kind a bed-fellow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e113960">
          <speaker>Men. </speaker>
          <l>Take backe my shame? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e113980">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>Yes for thy pleasure. </l>
          <l>There's in the world as rich and honourable </l>
          <l>As thou, who lend the pleasures of their bed </l>
          <l>To others, and then take them backe agayne </l>
          <l>As they can get them. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e114040">
          <speaker>Men, </speaker>
          <l>My brow shall neuer beare </l>
          <l>Such Characters of shame. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e114070">
          <speaker>Ther, </speaker>
          <l>Thy browes beares hornes already, but who sees them? </l>
          <l>When thou return'st to Sparta, some will thinke </l>
          <l>Thou art a Cuckold, but who is't dare say so? </l>
          <l>Thou art a King, thy sinnes are clouded o're, </l>
          <l>Where poore mens faults by tongues are made much more. </l>
          <l>Of all men liuing, Kings are last shall heare </l>
          <l>Of their dishonours. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e114150">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>What inferiour Beast </l>
          <l>Dares tell the Lyon of his Tyranny, </l>
          <l>Who is not torne asunder with his pawes? </l>
          <l>The King of Sparta therefore needs not feare </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-063-a"/>
          <l>The tongues of subiects bid our sister rise </l>
          <l>To safety in thine armes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e114220">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>Doe Menelaus. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e114240">
          <speaker>Mene. </speaker>
          <l>But will my Hellen then by future vertue </l>
          <l>Redeeme her long lost honour? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-helen" xml:id="ep000065-e114270">
          <speaker>Hel. </speaker>
          <l>If with teares </l>
          <l>The Heauens may be appeas'd for Hellens sinnes, </l>
          <l>They shall haue penitent showers: If Menelaus </l>
          <l>May with the spirit of loue be satisfied, </l>
          <l>He ten times rectifie my forfet honour </l>
          <l>Before I touch his bed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e114340">
          <speaker>Men. </speaker>
          <l>Arise then Hellen, Menelaus armes </l>
          <l>Thus welcome thee to safety. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e114370">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>Ha, ha, ha, </l>
          <l>Why this is well, for he that's borne to dye </l>
          <l>A branded Cuckhold, huggs his destiny: </l>
          <l>Goe, get you after Pyrhus to the slaughter, </l>
          <l>Ile looke to Hellen. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e114430">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>Conueigh her to our guard. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e114450">Exit. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e114460">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>Hellen, hereafter see thou proou'st more wise, </l>
          <l>If not more honest, yet be more precise, </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e114490">Exit. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e114500">Enter Prince Chorebus with other Troians in Greekish habits. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-chorebus" xml:id="ep000065-e114510">
          <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
          <l>These shapes thriue well, we haue guilt our Greekish arme </l>
          <l>With blood of their owne nation▪ some we haue sent </l>
          <l>To euerlasting darknesse, some repulst </l>
          <l>Backe to their ships: some we haue made to flye </l>
          <l>Into their horses bulke, whence Pyrhus first </l>
          <l>Lept downe vpon his speare. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e114580">Enter Synon, Thersites, and the Greekes dragging in Cassandra. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e114590">
          <speaker>Syn, </speaker>
          <l>Come souldiers, this is stately tragicall, </l>
          <l>The Greekes wade vp euen to the brawny thighes </l>
          <l>In luke-warme blood of our despoyled foes. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-063-b"/>
          <l>Aboue Melpomene's huge buskind top </l>
          <l>We plunge at euery stepp, and brauely fought </l>
          <l>By Troyes bright burning flame: that's now our light. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e114660">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>More of our valiant mates, let's ioyne with them, </l>
          <l>This streete yet's vnassaulted and vnfir'd: </l>
          <l>Some balls of wild-fire streight, and hurle this Lady </l>
          <l>Into the fury of the burning flame. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-chorebus" xml:id="ep000065-e114710">
          <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
          <l>My wife Cassandra? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e114730">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Courage, let none scape </l>
          <l>Fire, vengeance, blood, death, murder, spoyle and rape. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-chorebus" xml:id="ep000065-e114760">
          <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
          <l>All these on Greece and twenty thousand more, </l>
          <l>Till they like Troy be drown'd in teares and goare. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e114790">Chorebus and therest beate off the Greekes, and rescue Cassandra. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cassandra" xml:id="ep000065-e114800">
          <speaker>Cass. </speaker>
          <l>From Greekes to Greeks, from fire kept for the sword, From one death to another. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-chorebus" xml:id="ep000065-e114820">
          <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
          <l>Cassandra no. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cassandra" xml:id="ep000065-e114840">
          <speaker>Cass. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord the Prince Chorebus? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-chorebus" xml:id="ep000065-e114860">
          <speaker>Cho. </speaker>
          <l>Yes the same, </l>
          <l>Who hath preseru'd thee both from sword and flame. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e114890">Enter Aeneas with his father, who taking Chorebus for a Grecian by reason of his habite, fights with him and kils him. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-aeneas" xml:id="ep000065-e114900">
          <speaker>Aene. </speaker>
          <l>More Greekes and see Cassandra captiue made, </l>
          <l>Assault them Troians, rescue the faire Princesse; </l>
          <l>This way deare father mount my backe againe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cassandra" xml:id="ep000065-e114940">
          <speaker>Cass. </speaker>
          <l>Oh false Aeneas, thou hast slaine thy friend: </l>
          <l>Many a Greeke (thus shapt) he sent to hell, </l>
          <l>And being a Troian by a Troian fell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-aeneas" xml:id="ep000065-e114980">
          <speaker>Aene. </speaker>
          <l>He dy'd not by my hand, but his owne fate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cassandra" xml:id="ep000065-e115000">
          <speaker>Cass. </speaker>
          <l>And I forgiue thee good Aeneas, flie, </l>
          <l>Thou shalt suruiue, but Troy and wee must fall: </l>
          <l>The hope of all our future memories </l>
          <l>Are stor'd in thee, take vp thy sacred load </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-064-a"/>
          <l>Reuerent Anchises bed-rid through his age, </l>
          <l>We are all doom'd, faire Troy must perish here, </l>
          <l>But thou art borne a greater Troy to reare. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-aeneas" xml:id="ep000065-e115080">
          <speaker>Aene. </speaker>
          <l>The Heauens haue hand in all things, to their pleasure </l>
          <l>Wee must subscribe: Creusa, where's my wife? </l>
          <l>In loosing her I saue but halfe my life. </l>
          <l>Come reuerent father, on my shoulders mount, </l>
          <l>Though thousand dangers dogge vs at the heeles, </l>
          <l>Yet will wee force our passage. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e115150">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e115160">King Priam discouered kneeling at the Altar, with him Hecuba, Polixena, Andromache, Aftianax: to them enter Pyrhus, and all the Greekes, Pyrhus killing Polytes Priams sonne before the Altar. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e115170">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Still let your voyces to hye Heauen aspire </l>
          <l>For Pyrhus vengeance, murdring steele and fire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-all" xml:id="ep000065-e115200">
          <speaker>All the Ladies. </speaker>
          <l>Oh, oh. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e115220">
          <speaker>Pri. </speaker>
          <l>My sonne Polytes? oh thou more hard hearted </l>
          <l>Then fatall Pyrhus or his fathers guard, </l>
          <l>That in the shadow of this sacred place </l>
          <l>Durst sprinke the childs blood in the fathers face. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e115270">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Priam? thanks sweet reuenge, through swords &amp; armour, </l>
          <l>Through mures, and Counter-mures of men and steele; </l>
          <l>Through many a corner, and blind entries mouth </l>
          <l>I haue followed this thy bleeding sonne to death, </l>
          <l>Whose swift persuite hath traind me to this Altar </l>
          <l>To be reueng'd on thee for the sad fate </l>
          <l>Of great Achilles. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e115350">
          <speaker>Pri. </speaker>
          <l>Thou art Pyrhus then? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e115370">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>My acts shall speake my name, </l>
          <l>I am that Pyrhus who did mount you Horse </l>
          <l>Hyding mine armour in his deepe vast bulke, </l>
          <l>The first that lept out of his spacious side, </l>
          <l>And tost consuming fire in euery street, </l>
          <l>Which climb'd, as if it meant to meete the stars, </l>
          <l>I am that Pyrhus before whom Troy falls: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-064-b"/>
          <l>Before whom all the Vanes and Pinacles </l>
          <l>Bend their high tops, and from the battlements </l>
          <l>On which they stand, breake their aspiring necks. </l>
          <l>The proudest roofe and most imperious spyre </l>
          <l>Hath vaild to vs and our all wasting fire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e115500">
          <speaker>Pri. </speaker>
          <l>Pyrhus, I know thee for my destin'd plague, </l>
          <l>I know the gods haue left vs to our weaknesse, </l>
          <l>I see our glories ended and extinct, </l>
          <l>And I stand ready to abide their doome; </l>
          <l>Onely for pitty and for pieties sake </l>
          <l>Be gracious to these Ladies. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e115570">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Pyrhus no, </l>
          <l>Such grace as they did to Achilles shew, </l>
          <l>Let them all tast; let grace be farre exil'd, </l>
          <l>Kill from the elder to the sucking child. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e115620">
          <speaker>Pri. </speaker>
          <l>Hee's prone enough to mischiefe of himselfe, </l>
          <l>Spurre not that fury on which runnes too fast, </l>
          <l>Nor adde thou to old Priams misery </l>
          <l>Which scarce can be augmented tis so great. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e115670">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Dye in thy tortures then. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-hecuba" xml:id="ep000065-e115690">
          <speaker>Hecu. </speaker>
          <l>Oh spare his life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-astianax" xml:id="ep000065-e115710">
          <speaker>Asti. </speaker>
          <l>Good man kill not my Grandsire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e115730">
          <speaker>Pri. </speaker>
          <l>Good man doe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-hecuba" xml:id="ep000065-e115750">
          <speaker>Hecu. </speaker>
          <l>Kill mee for him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-astianax" xml:id="ep000065-e115770">
          <speaker>Asti. </speaker>
          <l>No, shee's my Grandam too, </l>
          <l>Indeed shee's a good woman, chuse some other </l>
          <l>If you must needes kill. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e115810">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>This then. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-astianax" xml:id="ep000065-e115830">
          <speaker>Asti. </speaker>
          <l>Shee's my Mother, you shall not hurt her. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e115850">
          <speaker>Pri. </speaker>
          <l>This boy had a father, </l>
          <l>Hector his name, who had hee liu'd to see </l>
          <l>A sword bent 'gainst his wife, this Queene, or me, </l>
          <l>He would haue made all Greece as hot to hold him </l>
          <l>As burning Troy is now to shelter vs. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-astianax" xml:id="ep000065-e115910">
          <speaker>Asti. </speaker>
          <l>Good Grandsire weepe not, Grandam, Mother, Aunt </l>
          <l>Alas, what meane you? If you be good men </l>
          <l>Put vp your swords and helpe to quench these flames, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-065-a"/>
          <l>Or if in killing you such pleasure haue, </l>
          <l>Practise on him, kill that ill fauoured knaue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e115970">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Mee bratt? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e115990">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Ulysses, Agamemnon. Menelaus, </l>
          <l>Synon, Thersites, and you valiant Greekes; </l>
          <l>Behold the vengeance wrathfull Pyrhus takes </l>
          <l>On Priams body for Achilles death: </l>
          <l>Synon, take thou that Syren Polixene, </l>
          <l>And hew her peece-meale on my fathers Tombe. </l>
          <l>Thersites, make the wombe of fifty Princes </l>
          <l>A royall sheath for thy victorious blade: </l>
          <l>Diomed, let Cassandra dye by thee, </l>
          <l>And Agamemnon kill Andromache: </l>
          <l>And as my sword through Priams bulke shall flie, </l>
          <l>Let them in death consort him, and so dye. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e116120">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>When, when, for Ioues sake when? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e116140">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Some expeditious fate this motion further, </l>
          <l>Me thinks tis long since that I did a murder. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e116170">
          <speaker>Pri. </speaker>
          <l>Oh Heauen, oh Ioue, Stars, Planets, fortune, fate, </l>
          <l>To thinke what I haue beene, and what am now; </l>
          <l>Father of fifty braue Heroick sonnes, </l>
          <l>But now no Father, for they all are slaine. </l>
          <l>Queene Hecuba the Mother of so many, </l>
          <l>But now no Mother: for her barren wombe </l>
          <l>Hath not one child to shew, these fatall warres </l>
          <l>Haue eate vp all our issue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-astianax" xml:id="ep000065-e116260">
          <speaker>Asti. </speaker>
          <l>My deare Father, </l>
          <l>And all my princely Vnkles. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-andromache" xml:id="ep000065-e116290">
          <speaker>Andr. </speaker>
          <l>My deare Husband, </l>
          <l>And all my royall brothers. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-hecuba" xml:id="ep000065-e116320">
          <speaker>Hecu. </speaker>
          <l>Worthy Hector, </l>
          <l>And all my valiant sonnes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-priam" xml:id="ep000065-e116350">
          <speaker>Pri. </speaker>
          <l>And now that Priam that commanded Asia, </l>
          <l>And sate inthron'd aboue the Kings of Greece, </l>
          <l>Whose dreaded Nauy scowerd the Hellespont, </l>
          <l>Sees the rich towers hee built now burnt to ashes: </l>
          <l>The stately walls he reard, leuel'd and euen'd; </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-065-b"/>
          <l>His Treasures rifled and his people spoyl'd: </l>
          <l>All that he hath on earth beneath the Sunne </l>
          <l>Bereft him, sauing his owne life and these, </l>
          <l>And my poore life with these, are (as you see) </l>
          <l>Worse then the rest: they dead, we dying bee. </l>
          <l>Strike my sterne foe, and proue in this my friend, </l>
          <l>One blow my vniuersall cares shall end. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e116480">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>And that blow Pirhus strikes, at once strike all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e116500">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Why so, so, this was stately tragicall. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e116520">They are all sleine at once. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-astianax" xml:id="ep000065-e116530">
          <speaker>Asti. </speaker>
          <l>Where shall I hide me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e116550">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>So nimble Hectors bastard? </l>
          <l>My father slew thy father, I the sonne: </l>
          <l>Thus will I tosse thy carkas vp on hie, </l>
          <l>The brat aboue his fathers fame shall flie. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e116600">He tosseth him about his head and kills him. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e116610">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>No, somewhat doth remayne, </l>
          <l>Alarum still, the people's not all slaine, </l>
          <l>Let not one soule suruiue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e116650">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Then Trumpets sound </l>
          <l>Till burning Troy in Troian blood be drown'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e116680">Exeunt </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e116690">The Alarum continued, shreiks and clamours are heard within. Enter with Drumme, Colours, and Souldiers Agamemnon, Pyrhus, Vlysses, Diomed, Menelaus, Hellen, Thersites, Synon, &amp;c. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e116700">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>What more remaines t'accomplish our reuenge? </l>
          <l>The proudest Nation that great Asia nurst </l>
          <l>Is now extinct in Lethe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e116740">
          <speaker>Mene. </speaker>
          <l>All by Hellen, </l>
          <l>Oh had that tempting beauty ne're beene borne, </l>
          <l>By whom so many worthies now lie dead. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e116780">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>A hot Pest take the strumpet. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e116800">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>And a mischiefe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e116820">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Twas this hot whore that set all Troy a fire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-helen" xml:id="ep000065-e116840">
          <speaker>Hel. </speaker>
          <l>Forgiue me Pyrhus for thy fathers death, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-066-a"/>
          <l>Troy for thy sack, King Priam for thy sonnes, </l>
          <l>Greece for an infinite slaughter, and you Husband or all your nuptiall wrongs, King Menelaus, </l>
          <l>I must confesse, my inconsiderate deed </l>
          <l>Haue made a world of valiant hearts to bleed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-diomede" xml:id="ep000065-e116900">
          <speaker>Dio. </speaker>
          <l>What, note is that which Pyrhus eye dwels on? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e116920">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>The perfect number </l>
          <l>Of Greekes and Troians slayne on either part. </l>
          <l>The siege ten yeares, ten moneths, ten dayes indur'd, </l>
          <l>In which there perish't of the Greekes 'fore Troy </l>
          <l>Eight hundred thousand &amp; sixe thousand fighting men: </l>
          <l>Of Troians fell sixe hundred sixe and fifty thousand, </l>
          <l>All souldiers; besides women, children, babes, </l>
          <l>Whom this night massacred. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-helen" xml:id="ep000065-e117010">
          <speaker>Hel. </speaker>
          <l>All these I slew. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e117030">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Nay, some this hand sent packing, that's not true. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-ulysses" xml:id="ep000065-e117050">
          <speaker>Vlys. </speaker>
          <l>Aeneas, with twenty two ships well furnish't, </l>
          <l>(The selfe same ships in which young Paris sayl'd </l>
          <l>When hee from Sparta stole faire Helena,) </l>
          <l>Is fled to Sea. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-diomede" xml:id="ep000065-e117100">
          <speaker>Dio. </speaker>
          <l>Anthenor with fiue hundred Troians more Scap't through the gate cal'd Dardan. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e117120">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Let them goe, </l>
          <l>That of Troyes sack the world by them may know, </l>
          <l>Where aboue thirty braue Heroick Kings </l>
          <l>Haue breath'd their last: besides inferior Princes, </l>
          <l>Barons and Knights, eighteene imperiall Monarches </l>
          <l>With his owne hands renowned Hector slew: </l>
          <l>My father besides Troilus and that Hector, </l>
          <l>Eight famous Kings that came in ayd of Troy. </l>
          <l>Three Troian Paris with his Arrowes slew, </l>
          <l>Of which one was my father: Diomed </l>
          <l>Foure Monarches with his bright sword sent to death. </l>
          <l>Our selfe the warlike Queene of Aemazons, </l>
          <l>And aged Priam. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e117260">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>Brauely boast he can, </l>
          <l>A wretched woman and a weake old man. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-066-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e117290">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>And now Troyes warres are ended, we in peace </l>
          <l>With glorious conquest to sayle backe to Greece. </l>
          <l>Their Nation's vanish'd like their Citties smoake, </l>
          <l>Our enemies are all ashes: worlds to come </l>
          <l>Shall Cronicle our pittilesse reuenge </l>
          <l>In Bookes of Brasse and leaues of Adamant. </l>
          <l>Towards Greece victorious Leaders, our toyle's past; </l>
          <l>Troy and Troyes people we haue burn't in flames, </l>
          <l>And of them both left nothing but their names. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e117390">Exeunt▪ </stage>
        <trailer>Explicit Actus tertius. </trailer>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="ep000065-e117410">
        <head>Actus Quartus: Scoena prima. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e117420">Enter Prince Cethus the sonne of King Naulus, and brother to Palamides. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e117430">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>With wondrous ioy they say, the Greekes returne </l>
          <l>With Triumphes and ouations piercing Heauen, </l>
          <l>Where e're they set but foot loude Paeans sung, </l>
          <l>And Oades to spheare-like Notes tun'd in their prayse: </l>
          <l>Whil'st Cethus like a forlorne shadowe walkes </l>
          <l>Dispis'd, disgrac't, neglected and debosht; </l>
          <l>Playing his melancholly, cares and sorrowes </l>
          <l>On his discordant Hart-strings. Oh my fate! </l>
          <l>Shall I, that haue this body aud this braine, </l>
          <l>A royalty stampt on mee in my birth: </l>
          <l>Whose wrongs haue beene of marke through all the World </l>
          <l>Troubling each eare, and being disputable </l>
          <l>By euery tongue that hath beene taught to speake, </l>
          <l>Euen in the mouthes of Babes, all rating mee </l>
          <l>Of cowardesie and sloth: sleepe, an occasion </l>
          <l>Being fairely offered? No, awake reuenge, </l>
          <l>Ile bring the now to action. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e117610">Enter Pilades. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pylades" xml:id="ep000065-e117620">
          <speaker>Pil. </speaker>
          <l>Heare you the newes </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-067-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e117640">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Orestes friend, the noble Filades? </l>
          <l>Instruct mine ignorance, I know of none. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pylades" xml:id="ep000065-e117670">
          <speaker>Pil. </speaker>
          <l>This day the Prince, great Agamemnons heire </l>
          <l>Orestes whom you truely call your friend, </l>
          <l>Betroths the young and faire Hermione </l>
          <l>Daughter to beauteous Hellen. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e117720">
          <speaker>Ceth </speaker>
          <l>Hymens ioyes. </l>
          <l>Crowne them with all true pleasure. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pylades" xml:id="ep000065-e117750">
          <speaker>Pil. </speaker>
          <l>Shall we haue your presence at the Contract? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e117770">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Who's within? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pylades" xml:id="ep000065-e117790">
          <speaker>Pil. </speaker>
          <l>Onely Egistus, Clitemnestras friend, </l>
          <l>The Queene and faire Electra. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e117820">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Witnesse enough, </l>
          <l>Then spare me for this time good Pilades, </l>
          <l>Wee'le owe them greater seruice. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pylades" xml:id="ep000065-e117860">
          <speaker>Pyl. </speaker>
          <l>But tis a duty that I owe my friend, </l>
          <l>My absence would distast him. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e117890">Exit. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e117900">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Fare you well. </l>
          <l>Doe, doe, contract and marry, ayme at Heauen, </l>
          <l>But Hell is that they plunge in: Oh Palamedes </l>
          <l>My basely betray'd brother, sold at Troy </l>
          <l>As we would cheapen Horses, yet a Prince: </l>
          <l>A Prince? nay Generall of the Greekish host. </l>
          <l>Emperour and Keyser, chose to that command </l>
          <l>By a full Iury of Kings, and by them rated </l>
          <l>The prime &amp; worthiest: who being far from equal </l>
          <l>Could find in whole Greece no competitor. </l>
          <l>Yet this peculiar man, this God of men, </l>
          <l>By false Vlysses and Atreus sonnes </l>
          <l>Agamemnon and Menelaus, basely supplanted; </l>
          <l>Who, for they would conferre amongst themselues </l>
          <l>The soueraignty forg'd letters sent from Troy, </l>
          <l>And coine withall mark't with King Priams stamp, </l>
          <l>As if this father of his fame and Nation </l>
          <l>Whose onely ends were aymd to honour Greece </l>
          <l>Would haue betrayde his people: this suggested, </l>
          <l>My brother was arraign'd, conuict, condemn'd; </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-067-b"/>
          <l>For which I haue vow'd the vniuersall ruine </l>
          <l>Of all the Kings of that corrupted bench. </l>
          <l>Palamides thy blood in Asia shed </l>
          <l>Shall make all Europe mourne since thou art dead. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e118150">Enter Egistus, Clitemnestra, Orestes, Pilades, Hermione, and Electra. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e118160">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Mecenaes King and Sparta's would be proud </l>
          <l>To see this happy and blest vnion made </l>
          <l>Betweene their royall Familyes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e118200">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>This faire Virgine, </l>
          <l>Second from Laeda to whom Ioue vouchsaf't </l>
          <l>The strict Imbrace of his immortall arme, </l>
          <l>Vnspotted with her mothers prostitution, </l>
          <l>Wee'le thus receiue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-hermione" xml:id="ep000065-e118260">
          <speaker>Hermi. </speaker>
          <l>May my chast innocence </l>
          <l>Breake through the Cloud which hath ecclips'd her fame▪ </l>
          <l>Whose luster may out-shine my mothers fraileties, </l>
          <l>And they through me may bee forgot in Greece. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e118310">
          <speaker>Egi. </speaker>
          <l>Hermione, your words tast of your breeding </l>
          <l>Vnder this Queene your faire and Princely Aunt, </l>
          <l>were young Electra but so well bestowed, </l>
          <l>Great Agamemnon in so braue a match </l>
          <l>Would thinke himselfe more grac'd, then in fruition </l>
          <l>Of all the forraigne Trophies. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e118380">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>May shee prooue? </l>
          <l>A whore like to her Mother: Prince Orestes, </l>
          <l>And you bright Lady Spartans second light, </l>
          <l>May all the vertues of this potent Queene </l>
          <l>Take life in you, to prooue hereditary </l>
          <l>That the great Arch-duke crown'd with fame and honour. </l>
          <l>In his returne may adde a surplusadge </l>
          <l>To his already surfet: find his bed </l>
          <l>By this adultresse basely strumpetted, </l>
          <l>And make the Downe they lye on quaffe their blood. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e118490">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>How doe you faire Electra in your iudgement </l>
          <l>Applaude your brothers choyce? </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-068-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000065-electra" xml:id="ep000065-e118520">
          <speaker>Elect. </speaker>
          <l>As of a contract. </l>
          <l>Made by the gods aboue, and now by Princes </l>
          <l>Here ratified on earth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e118560">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>I would my friend </l>
          <l>Were to you sister, but as fast betroth'd </l>
          <l>As I to Hellens daughter: But deare Pilades, </l>
          <l>Tis Time must perfect all things. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pylades" xml:id="ep000065-e118610">
          <speaker>Pil. </speaker>
          <l>Madam you heare▪ </l>
          <l>This motion from your brother. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-electra" xml:id="ep000065-e118640">
          <speaker>Elect. </speaker>
          <l>And I craue </l>
          <l>Time to consider on't. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e118670">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>Tis on foote, </l>
          <l>Pursue it then with all aduantages, </l>
          <l>Command my free assistance to beginne▪ </l>
          <l>Had you Electra friend, as I Hermione; </l>
          <l>We were at first as forraigne as you two, </l>
          <l>And euery way as strange, but opportunity </l>
          <l>That hath vnited vs, may make you one. </l>
          <l>After some amorous parliance, let vs now </l>
          <l>Vnto the Temple and there sacrifice </l>
          <l>Vnto the gods, that Greece▪ no more may mourne </l>
          <l>But glory in our fathers safe returne▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e118790">
          <speaker>Egist, </speaker>
          <l>His safety is our danger▪ for know Madam▪ </l>
          <l>Our loue hath bin too publick. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e118820">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>That's the ground </l>
          <l>On which to build my proiect. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e118850">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Grant it hath. </l>
          <l>Cannot a more then nine yeares widdow-head </l>
          <l>Excuse mee being a woman? thinks the King </l>
          <l>Wee can forget that lesson in our age, </l>
          <l>Which was by him first taught vs in our youth? </l>
          <l>Or was't his ayme to shew vs choyce delights, </l>
          <l>Then barre vs their fruition? First to tast </l>
          <l>Our pallat, next to make vs appetite; </l>
          <l>And when our stomacks are prepar'd and sharpen'd </l>
          <l>For Costly vionds plac't before our eyes, </l>
          <l>Then to remooue the table? hee's vnkind; </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-068-b"/>
          <l>And as hee hath dealt with vs, so must find. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e118980">Enter Synon. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e118990">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>The Queene? to her my speed is. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e119010">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Speake on souldier. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e119030">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>I am the herald of most happy newes, </l>
          <l>Troy with the earth is leueld, sackt, and burnt; </l>
          <l>Priam with all his memory extinct, </l>
          <l>Queene, daughters, sonnes, and subiects ruin'd all. </l>
          <l>Now like the vapour of their Citties smoake, </l>
          <l>And of them no more found: And Madam now </l>
          <l>The King your Lord, the Elder of the Atryd's, </l>
          <l>Duke of the puissant and all conquering Host, </l>
          <l>His temples archt in a victorious orbe, </l>
          <l>And wreth'd in all the glories earth can yeeld </l>
          <l>Is landed in Mycene a Conquerour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e119150">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>How could they scape those fierce fires Naulus made </l>
          <l>In vengeance of his sonne Palamides </l>
          <l>To split their cursed Fleete vpon the rocks. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e119190">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Make repetition of their ioyes againe, </l>
          <l>Beeing things that I cannot heare too oft▪ </l>
          <l>And adde to them: Is Menelaus safe </l>
          <l>My husbands brother? Hellen how fares shee? </l>
          <l>Or is shee thence repurchast? fill mine eares </l>
          <l>With such sweete Tones, 'tis all I can desire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e119260">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Take your full longing then, for though the Seas </l>
          <l>With tempests, stormes, rocks, shipwracks, shelues and sands </l>
          <l>More dammag'd them then all the Troian siege. </l>
          <l>Although the Beacons fir'd to draw their Fleete </l>
          <l>Distressed and disperst vpon the rocks </l>
          <l>Sunke many a goodly bottome: Yet the Generall </l>
          <l>Scap't by the hand of Ioue, with him King Diomed, </l>
          <l>Vlysses, and great Neoptolimus, </l>
          <l>With Spartan Menelaus late attend </l>
          <l>With beauteous Hellen cause of all these broyles: </l>
          <l>All these attend vpon the Generall </l>
          <l>To bring him home victorious, and this night </l>
          <l>Will lodge in the Kings Pallace, </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-069-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e119400">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Souldier thanks, </l>
          <l>These twice fiue yeares I haue a widdow beene, </l>
          <l>Thy newes haue now new married mee: giue order </l>
          <l>For the Kings intertainment, all the state </l>
          <l>Mycene can yeeld shall freely be expos'd </l>
          <l>In honour of these Princes: your great hast </l>
          <l>Doth aske some rest, therefore repose your selfe, </l>
          <l>And for your fortunate newes expect reward. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e119490">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>The Queene is royall. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e119510">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>And now to that diuell </l>
          <l>Which I must coniure vp: Is the Queene mad? </l>
          <l>Or thou Egistus sottish? see you not </l>
          <l>The stake and scaffold, nay the Hang-man too; </l>
          <l>And will you blind-fold run vpon your deaths </l>
          <l>When there is way to'scape them? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e119580">
          <speaker>Egist. </speaker>
          <l>What horrid fright </l>
          <l>Is this propos'd by Cethus? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e119610">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>The King's return'd, </l>
          <l>And doth not your veines gush out of your temples </l>
          <l>In sanguine blushes? are not your adulteries </l>
          <l>Famous as Hellens? nay, more infamous, </l>
          <l>There was a rape to countenance what shee did, </l>
          <l>You nought saue corrupt lust and idlenesse: </l>
          <l>Tis blab'd in the Citty, talk't on in the Court, </l>
          <l>All tongues surcharg'd, all eyes are fix't on you, </l>
          <l>To see what fearefull vengeance he will take </l>
          <l>For that your prostitution. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e119720">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Hee's a King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e119740">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>True Clitemnestra, so he went from hence, </l>
          <l>But is return'd a Tyrant flesht in blood: </l>
          <l>Think'st thou that he who queld his foes abroad, </l>
          <l>Will spare at home domestick enemies? </l>
          <l>That was so prone to punish others wrongs, </l>
          <l>And can forget his owne? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e119810">
          <speaker>Cli, </speaker>
          <l>If Menelaus </l>
          <l>Haue pardon'd Hellen, may not he his brother </l>
          <l>Make Spartaes King his noble president, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-069-b"/>
          <l>To doe the like to me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e119860">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Tush shallow Queene, </l>
          <l>How you mistake; see imminent fate affront you, </l>
          <l>And will not shun it comming? If his brother </l>
          <l>Be branded as a scandall to the world, </l>
          <l>What consequence is it that he will grone </l>
          <l>Vnder the selfe same burden? rather thinke </l>
          <l>He hath propos'd a vengeance dire and horrid </l>
          <l>To terrifie, not countenance such misdeeds: </l>
          <l>And this must fall on you, lest time to come </l>
          <l>Should Chronicle his family for a broode </l>
          <l>Of Cuckolds and of Strumpets: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e119980">
          <speaker>Egist. </speaker>
          <l>This thy language </l>
          <l>Strikes me with horrour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e120010">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>And affrights mee too. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e120030">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Is hee not King? hath he not Linxes eyes, </l>
          <l>And Gyants armes, the first to see farre off, </l>
          <l>The last as farre to punish? was hee so poore </l>
          <l>In friends at home, to leaue no Argus here </l>
          <l>To keepe his eyes still waking? thinke it not </l>
          <l>But that he knew the treason of his bed, </l>
          <l>Hee had not faire Briseis snatcht perforce </l>
          <l>From th'armes of great Achilles. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e120120">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>That I heard. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e120140">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Why hath he a new mistresse brought from Troy, </l>
          <l>But to state her in Clitemnestraes stead, </l>
          <l>And make her Micenes Queene whilst you poore wretches </l>
          <l>Like malefactors suffer, mark't for the Stag </l>
          <l>And most ridiculous spectacles. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e120200">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>You shew the danger, </l>
          <l>But teach vs no preuention▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e120230">
          <speaker>Egist. </speaker>
          <l>See before vs </l>
          <l>The obiects of our feares and difficulties, </l>
          <l>But not the way to auoyde them. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e120270">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Heare me then, </l>
          <l>Preuent your death's by his. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e120300">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>How? kill the King? </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-070-a"/>
          <l>So we heape sinne on sinne and basely adde </l>
          <l>Vnto adultery murder. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e120340">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Per scelus semper tutum sceleribus iter. </l>
          <l>Boldly you haue begun, and being once in, </l>
          <l>Blood will cure lust, and mischiefe phisicke sinne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e120380">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Perhaps our guilt lies hid. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e120400">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>In a Kings Pallace </l>
          <l>Can lust in such great persons be conceald? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e120430">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>The first offence repents mee, and to that </l>
          <l>I should but adde a greater. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e120460">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Perish, doe. </l>
          <l>Or what concernes this mee? I shall be safe, </l>
          <l>I haue strumpetted no Agamemnons Queene, </l>
          <l>Nor bastarded the issue of the Atrides: </l>
          <l>Or why should I thus labour their securities </l>
          <l>Who study not their owne? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e120530">
          <speaker>Egist. </speaker>
          <l>Resolue then Queene, </l>
          <l>The Kings austeere, and will extend his Iustice </l>
          <l>Vnto some sad example. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e120570">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Oh but my husband. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e120590">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>After ten yeares widdow-hood </l>
          <l>Can Clitemnestra thinke of such a name? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e120620">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>You haue halfe wone me, when shall this be done? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e120640">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>When but this night? delayes are ominous: </l>
          <l>Ere he haue time to thinke vpon his wrongs, </l>
          <l>Or finde a tongue to whisper, ere suspicion </l>
          <l>Can further be instructed or least censure, </l>
          <l>To call his wrongs in question: instantly, </l>
          <l>Euen in his height of ioy, fulnesse of complement </l>
          <l>With th' Argiue Kings: whilst cups are brim'd with healths, </l>
          <l>Whilst iealousies are drown'd in Bacchus boles. </l>
          <l>This night before he sleepe, or that his pillowe </l>
          <l>Can giue him the least counsell, ere he can spare </l>
          <l>A minute for the smallest intelligence, </l>
          <l>Or moment to consider: I haue done </l>
          <l>If you haue either grace in apprehension </l>
          <l>Or spirit in performance. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-070-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e120790">
          <speaker>Egist. </speaker>
          <l>I haue both, </l>
          <l>What answers Clitemnestra? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e120820">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>I am swayd, </l>
          <l>And though I know there's difference of Justice </l>
          <l>In Princes sitting on the skarlet bench, </l>
          <l>And husbands dallying in the priuate bed: </l>
          <l>I'le hold him as one sits vpon my life, </l>
          <l>Not one that lies inclos'd within mine armes; </l>
          <l>Hee's now my Iudge, not Husband, here I vow </l>
          <l>Assistance in his death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e120910">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>And so suruiue </l>
          <l>Secure and fortunate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e120940">
          <speaker>Egist. </speaker>
          <l>This night? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e120960">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Tis done. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e120980">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>The proiect I haue cast with all security. </l>
          <l>And safety for your person: smooth your browes, </l>
          <l>And let there shine a welcome in your lookes </l>
          <l>At the Kings intertainment: nay begone, </l>
          <l>By this time you are expected; what remaines </l>
          <l>Is mine in forme, but yours in action. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000065-e121050">Exeunt. </stage>
          <l>Now father stile me a most worthy sonne </l>
          <l>Palamides, a brother, what neither fires, </l>
          <l>Nor rocks could doe, what neither Neptunes rage, </l>
          <l>Nor Mars his fury, what the turbulent Seas, </l>
          <l>Nor the combustious Land▪ that Cethus can: </l>
          <l>Hee that succeedes my brother in his rule, </l>
          <l>Shall first succeede in death: none that had hand </l>
          <l>Or voyce in his subuersion that shall stand. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e121140">Exit: </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e121150">Enter Thersites and Synon. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e121160">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>Well met on Land kind brother, wee are now </l>
          <l>Victorious: let's be proud on't. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e121190">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Thou say'st true, </l>
          <l>Wee are Conquerours in our basest cowardise, </l>
          <l>Wee had not beene here else. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e121230">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>Valiant Hector, </l>
          <l>Achilles, Troilus, Paris, Aiax too. </l>
          <l>They are all falne, we stand. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-071-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e121270">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Yes, and will stiffe </l>
          <l>When all the Grecian Princes that suruiue </l>
          <l>Are crampt and ham-string'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e121310">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>Wast thou not sea-sicke brother? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e121330">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Horribly, and fear'd </l>
          <l>In the rough seas to haue disgorg'd my heart, </l>
          <l>And there to haue fed Haddocks. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e121370">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>Troians were fellowes </l>
          <l>In all their fury to be parlied with: </l>
          <l>But with the tempests, gusts, and Furicanes, </l>
          <l>The warring windes, the billowes, rocks and fires </l>
          <l>There was no talking: these few times we pray'd, </l>
          <l>The gods would heare no reason. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e121440">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Twas because </l>
          <l>The billowes with their roaring, and the winds </l>
          <l>Did with their. whistling keepe them from their eares: </l>
          <l>But now all's husht, could wee finde time to pray, </l>
          <l>They might find time to heare vs. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e121500">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>Shall wee be </l>
          <l>Spectators of the royall inter-view </l>
          <l>Betwixt the King and Queene? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e121540">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Ten yeares diuorst </l>
          <l>Should challenge a kind meeting, let's obserue </l>
          <l>The forme and state of this Court-complement, </l>
          <l>(things I did neuer trade with:) Harke loud musicke </l>
          <l>Giues warning of their comming. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e121600">Loud musicke. Enter at one doore Agamemnon, Vlysses, Diomed, Pyrhus, Menelaus: Synon and Thersites falling into their trayne. At the other Egistus, Clitemnestra, Cethus, Orestes, Pylades, Hermione, Electra, &amp;c. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e121610">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>Vnto our Country and our Houshold-gods </l>
          <l>Wee are at length return'd, trophied with honours, </l>
          <l>With Troyes subuersion and rich Asiaes spoyles, </l>
          <l>This is a sacred day. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e121660">
          <speaker>Egist. </speaker>
          <l>Such Troy had once. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-071-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e121680">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>Vnto the gods wel'e sacrifice. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e121700">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>So Priam fell </l>
          <l>Before the holy Altar. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e121730">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>This Citty is not Troy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e121750">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Where Hellen treades, </l>
          <l>I hold the place no better. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e121780">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>See our Queene, </l>
          <l>Orestes and Electra, for our sake. </l>
          <l>Princes of Greece daigne them your best salutes▪ </l>
          <l>Deare Clitemnestra. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e121830">
          <speaker>Clit. </speaker>
          <l>Royall King and Husband. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e121850">After their salute. All the rest complement as strangers, but especially Pyrhus and Orestes▪ </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e121860">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>What's he that kneeles so close vnto our Queene </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e121880">
          <speaker>Clit. </speaker>
          <l>Egistus and your seruant. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e121900">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>Hee was young </l>
          <l>When we at first set sayle from Aulis Gulfe, </l>
          <l>Now growne from my remembrance: we shall finde </l>
          <l>Fit time to search him further, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e121950">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Marke you that. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e121970">
          <speaker>Egist. </speaker>
          <l>Yes, and it toucht me deepely. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e121990">
          <speaker>Mene. </speaker>
          <l>Our sister, and this young Hermione, </l>
          <l>Daughter to vs aud Hellen. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e122020">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>Prity puppy. </l>
          <l>Of such a common brach. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e122050">
          <speaker>Men. </speaker>
          <l>Young Neoptolemus, </l>
          <l>This is the Lady promist you at Troy, </l>
          <l>For your great seruice done there: she's your owne, </l>
          <l>Freely imbrace her then. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e122100">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>I see we are like </l>
          <l>To haue a iolly kindred. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e122130">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>Pyrhus, inioy </l>
          <l>Her whom I haue in contract? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e122160">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Beauteous Lady, </l>
          <l>The great'st ambition Pyrhus aymes at now, </l>
          <l>Is how to know you farther. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-072-a"/>
          <l>Hath beene so mighty to reuenge the wrongs </l>
          <l>Of my faire mother, can from Hermione </l>
          <l>Challenge no lesse then welcome. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e122230">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>Oh you gods, </l>
          <l>Pyrhus, thou wert more safe in burning Troy </l>
          <l>With horrour, fury blood, fires, foes about them. </l>
          <l>Then in my fathers court. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e122280">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Another Collumne </l>
          <l>On which to build my slaughters. Patience Prince, </l>
          <l>This is no time for braues and Menaces, </l>
          <l>I further shall instruct you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e122330">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>I haue done. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e122350">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>See now the two Queenes meete, &amp; smack in publick, </l>
          <l>That oft haue kist in corners▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e122380">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Thersites? </l>
          <l>Thou art growne a monster, a strange thing scarce knowns </l>
          <l>'Mongst souldiers, wiues and daughters. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e122420">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>They are two sisters. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e122440">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Yes, and the two King-brothers royally </l>
          <l>Betweene them two cornuted▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e122470">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>We are to loud. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-diomede" xml:id="ep000065-e122490">
          <speaker>Dio. </speaker>
          <l>Princes of Greece, since we haue done a duty </l>
          <l>To see our Generall mid'st his people safe, </l>
          <l>And after many dreadfull warres abroad </l>
          <l>In peace at home. 'Tis fit we should disperse </l>
          <l>Vnto our seuerall Countries instantly, </l>
          <l>I purpose for Aetolia, where my Queene </l>
          <l>With longing waites my comming. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e122570">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>Not King Diomed, </l>
          <l>Till you haue seene Mecena's pompe and state </l>
          <l>In ampliest royalty exprest at full, </l>
          <l>Both tasted of our feasts and Princely gifts. </l>
          <l>The faire Aegiale, who hath so long </l>
          <l>Forborne your presence, will not I presume </l>
          <l>Deny to spare you to vs some few dayes, </l>
          <l>To adde to the yeares number, though not as Generall </l>
          <l>Yet will I lay on you a friends command▪ </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-072-b"/>
          <l>Which must not be deny'de. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-diomede" xml:id="ep000065-e122680">
          <speaker>Dio. </speaker>
          <l>Great Agamemnon </l>
          <l>With mee was euer powerfull, I am his. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e122710">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>And now faire sister welcome back from Troy, </l>
          <l>Be euer henceforth Spartaes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-helen" xml:id="ep000065-e122740">
          <speaker>Hei. </speaker>
          <l>Your great care </l>
          <l>In my enforced absence (gracious Queene) </l>
          <l>Exprest vnto my deare Hermione, </l>
          <l>Hath much obliged me to you. Oh my fate, </l>
          <l>How swift time runnes: Orestes growne a man, </l>
          <l>Whom I left in the Cradle! Young Electra </l>
          <l>Then (as I tak't) scarce borne, and now growne ripe, </l>
          <l>Euen ready for an husband! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e122830">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>In whose absence </l>
          <l>If but one handsome sweete-heart come in place, </l>
          <l>Shee'l not turne tayle for't, if shee doe but take </l>
          <l>After mine old Naunt Hellen. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e122880">Enter a Lord. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-lord" xml:id="ep000065-e122890">
          <speaker>Lord. </speaker>
          <l>The great and solemne preparation </l>
          <l>Of the Court, state and glory mighty Princes, </l>
          <l>Attend for you within. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e122930">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>All are consecrated </l>
          <l>Vnto your royall welcomes, enter then, </l>
          <l>Wee'l feast like earthy gods, or god-like men▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e122970">Loud musick. They possesse the Stage in all state, Cathus stayeth behind. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e122980">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>My brayne about againe, for thou hast found </l>
          <l>New proiect now to worke on, and 'tis here, </l>
          <l>Orestes hath receiu'd Hermione </l>
          <l>From Clitemnestra's hand, her soule is his▪ </l>
          <l>And hee her Genius, two combind in one: </l>
          <l>Yet shee is by the fathers Oath conferd </l>
          <l>On Pyrhus, which shall breede a stormy flawe </l>
          <l>Ne're to be peec't againe, but by the deaths </l>
          <l>Of the two hopefull youths: perhaps the hazard </l>
          <l>Of all these Kings if my reuenge strike home. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-073-a"/>
          <l>(Of that at leasure) but the bloody stage </l>
          <l>On which to act, Generall this night is thine, </l>
          <l>Thou lyest downe mortall, who must rise diuine. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e123120">Enter Orestes to Cethus. Musicke and healthing within. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e123130">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>Oh Cethus what's this musicke vnto me, </l>
          <l>That are compos'd of discords? what are healths </l>
          <l>To him that is strucke heart-sicke? all those ioyes </l>
          <l>Whose leaders seeme to pierce against the roofes </l>
          <l>Of these high structures, to him that is struct downe </l>
          <l>Halfe way below the Center? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e123200">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Were you lower, </l>
          <l>Yet here's a hand can rayse you, deeper cast </l>
          <l>Then to the lowest Abisme: It lyes in me </l>
          <l>To aduance you to the height of happinesse, </l>
          <l>Where you shall liue eternis'd from the reach </l>
          <l>Of any humane malice. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e123270">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>Hadst thou seene </l>
          <l>Her, in whose breast my heart was paradis'd, </l>
          <l>Kist, courted, and imbrac'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e123310">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>By Pyrhus. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e123330">
          <speaker>Orest▪ </speaker>
          <l>Him: </l>
          <l>What passionate and insidiating lookes </l>
          <l>Hee cast on her, as if in scorne of me: </l>
          <l>Shall hee inioy my birth-right, or inherite </l>
          <l>Where I am heire apparant? shall he vsurpe▪ </l>
          <l>Or pleade my interest, where I am possest? </l>
          <l>Rule where I raigne? where I am stated, sit? </l>
          <l>Braue me in my peculiar Soueraignty? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e123420">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Hee must not, shall not. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e123440">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>Show mee to depose. </l>
          <l>The proud Vsurper then. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e123470">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Prince, make't my charge. </l>
          <l>In the meane time, from your distracted from </l>
          <l>Exile all discontent, let not least rage </l>
          <l>Raigne in your eye, or harshnesse in your tongue, </l>
          <l>Smooth waters are still deep'st▪ waite on the King, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-073-b"/>
          <l>And be no stranger to your mothers eye, </l>
          <l>Or forraigne to your Kindred: the feast spent, </l>
          <l>And night with it: the morrow shall beget </l>
          <l>Proiect of more import (scarse thought on now.) </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e123570">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>I build vpon thy Counsell. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e123590">Exit Orestes. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e123600">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Which hath proou'd, </l>
          <l>Fixt as a rocke, still constant, and vnmoou'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e123630">Enter Egistus. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e123640">
          <speaker>Egist. </speaker>
          <l>What Cethus here? why no such matter now </l>
          <l>No cause of feare, or least suspicion. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e123670">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Your reason? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e123690">
          <speaker>Egist. </speaker>
          <l>Tush, presume it, we are safe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e123710">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Obserue it, they are still securest, whom </l>
          <l>The Diuell driues to ruine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e123740">
          <speaker>Egist. </speaker>
          <l>Harke, their healths </l>
          <l>Carrowsing to the Generals Victories, </l>
          <l>In all thy heate of ioy, and fire of wine, </l>
          <l>No sparke of iealously, all th' Argument </l>
          <l>Of their discourse, what they haue done at Troy. </l>
          <l>Still health on health, and the great Generall </l>
          <l>So farre from seeming to haue least distaste, </l>
          <l>That in all affable tearmes hee courts his Queene, </l>
          <l>Nay more, cuts off all banquet Ceremonies, </l>
          <l>To hasten his bed-pleasures, as if times distance </l>
          <l>Betwixt his boord and pallade, seemed more tedious </l>
          <l>Then all his Ten yeares siege. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e123870">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Goe, lost man, </l>
          <l>Sinke on firme ground, be shipwrackt in a Calme. </l>
          <l>These healthes are to your ruines, his reuenge: </l>
          <l>Hath not Egistus read of a disease </l>
          <l>Where men dye laughing: others that haue drunke </l>
          <l>Poyson in steed of Cordials, perish so? </l>
          <l>To dye tis nothing, since tis all men due: </l>
          <l>But wretchedly to suffer, fall vnpittied, </l>
          <l>Vnpittied? nay derided, mockt, and curst: </l>
          <l>To dye as a base Traytor, and a Thiefe, </l>
          <l>The adulterator of his Soueraignes bed, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-074-a"/>
          <l>The poyson of the Atredas family, </l>
          <l>And scandall of his issue, so to dye? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e124010">
          <speaker>Egi. </speaker>
          <l>Egistus will preuent, he by this hand </l>
          <l>Must fal, 'fore whom all Asia could not stand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e124040">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>The banquet is broke vp, sleep cals to rest, </l>
          <l>And mid-nights houre for murther, still showes best▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e124070">Exit. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e124080">Loud musicke. Enter Egistus with his sword drawne, hideth himselfe in the chamber behind the Bed-curtaines: all the Kings come next in, conducting the Generall and his Queene to their Lodging, and after some complement leaue them, enery one with torches vshered to their seuerall chambers, &amp;c. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e124090">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>Methinkes this night, we Clitemnestra meete, </l>
          <l>At a new bridall; all Attendants leaue vs, </l>
          <l>Wee now are onely for bed-priuacies. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e124130">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Great sir, I that so long haue bin your widdow, </l>
          <l>Will be this night your hand-mayde. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e124160">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>You told me, Queene, </l>
          <l>Orestes was a cunning horse-man growne: </l>
          <l>It pleasde me much to heare it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e124200">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Greece reports </l>
          <l>No Centare can ride better▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e124230">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>And young Electra, </l>
          <l>In all th' indowments that may best become </l>
          <l>A Princesse of her breeding, most compleate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e124270">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>It was in your long absence, all my care, </l>
          <l>(Being my charge) that you at your returne </l>
          <l>Might finde them to your wishes, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e124310">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>Thankes for that. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e124330">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>How cunningly he seemes to carry it▪ </l>
          <l>But we must finde preuention. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e124360">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>Who's without there? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e124380">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Why started you? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e124400">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>Not all the Asian Legions, no not Hector </l>
          <l>Arm'd with his bals of wild-fire, had the power </l>
          <l>To shake me like this tremor: Is our Pallace </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-074-b"/>
          <l>Lesse safe in Greece, amidst our subiects here, </l>
          <l>Then were our Tents in Asia? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e124460">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Where, if not here in Clitemnestraes armes, </l>
          <l>Can safety dwell? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e124490">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>And faire Queene, it should bee so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e124510">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>But why sir cast you such suspicious eyes </l>
          <l>About your Chamber? are wee not alone? </l>
          <l>Or will you to the priuate sweetes of night, </l>
          <l>Call tell tale witnesse? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e124560">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>Now tis gone agayne. Shall we to rest? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e124580">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>So please you royall Sir. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e124600">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>How hard this Doune feeles, like a monument </l>
          <l>Cut out of marble. Beds resemble Graues, </l>
          <l>And these me-thinkes appeare like winding sheets, </l>
          <l>Prepar'd for corses. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e124650">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Oh how ominously </l>
          <l>Doe you presage: you much affright me sir </l>
          <l>In this our long-wisht meeting. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e124690">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>All's shooke off. </l>
          <l>I now am arm'd for pleasure: you commended </l>
          <l>Late one Egistus to me, prithee Queene </l>
          <l>Of what condition is he? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e124740">They both wound him, at which there is a greate thunder crack. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e124750">
          <speaker>Egist. </speaker>
          <l>Tyrant this. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e124770">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>And I am thus his second. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-agamemnon" xml:id="ep000065-e124790">
          <speaker>Aga. </speaker>
          <l>Treason, murder, Treason: </l>
          <l>This showes, we Princes are no more then men. </l>
          <l>Thankes Ioue tis fit when Monarches fall by Treason, </l>
          <l>Thunder to all the world, would show some reason. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000065-e124840">he dies. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e124850">
          <speaker>Egi. </speaker>
          <l>The deede is done, lets flye to some strong Cittadell, </l>
          <l>For our more safety. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e124880">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Hee thus made diuine: </l>
          <l>Now my Egistus, I am soly thine. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e124910">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e124920">Anoyse of vproare within. Enter all the Kings with other Seruants halfe vnready, as newly started from their Beds. Orestes, Hermione, Pillades, Electra, &amp;c. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e124930">
          <speaker>Mene. </speaker>
          <l>What strange tumultuous noyse is this so late▪ </l>
          <l>To rouse vs from our beds? </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-075-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e124960">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Prodigious sure, </l>
          <l>Since 'tis confirm'd by Thunder. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e124990">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>In mine eares </l>
          <l>Did neuer sound seeme halfe to terrible. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-helen" xml:id="ep000065-e125020">
          <speaker>Hel. </speaker>
          <l>Nor to your eyes, as this sad obiect is, </l>
          <l>See great Atrides groueling. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e125050">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>What damn'd Villaine </l>
          <l>Was auther of this proiect? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-omnes" xml:id="ep000065-e125080">
          <speaker>Omnes. </speaker>
          <l>Horrid sight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e125100">
          <speaker>Ore. </speaker>
          <l>Rest you amazed all, as thunder struke, </l>
          <l>And without sence or motion Apoplext, </l>
          <l>And onely heare me speake: Orestes, he </l>
          <l>Who as if marbled by Medusaes head, </l>
          <l>Hath not one teare to fall, or sigh to spend, </l>
          <l>Till I finde out the murderer, and on him </l>
          <l>Inflict remarkable vengance: for I vowe </l>
          <l>Were it my father, brother, or his Queene, </l>
          <l>Hadst thou my weeping sister hand in it. </l>
          <l>If hee? whom equall, (if not rankt aboue) </l>
          <l>I euer did, and shall loue Pylades? </l>
          <l>Wert she whose wombe did beare me, where I lay </l>
          <l>Full nine moneths bedded ere I saw the Sunne, </l>
          <l>Or the most abiect Traytor vnder Heauen, </l>
          <l>Their doomes were all alike, and this I vowe. </l>
          <l>Now you whom this silent and speechlesse King </l>
          <l>Hath oft commanded, this now sencelesse braine </l>
          <l>As oft directed, this now strengthlesse hand </l>
          <l>More oft protected in a warre, that shall </l>
          <l>Be to all times example: Lend your shoulders </l>
          <l>To beare him, who hath kept you all in life, </l>
          <l>This is a blacke and mourning funerall right, </l>
          <l>Deedes of this nature must be throughly searcht, </l>
          <l>Nay be reueng'd: the gods haue sayd tis good, </l>
          <l>The morning Sunne shall rise and blush in blood. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e125360">They beare him off with a sad and funerall march, &amp;c. </stage>
        <trailer>Explicit Actus quartus. </trailer>
      </div>
      <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="ep000065-e125380">
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-075-b"/>
        <head>Actus Quintus: Scoena prima. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e125390">Enter Pyrhus, Hermione, Thersites, and Synon. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e125400">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Sweete Lady, can you loue: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-hermione" xml:id="ep000065-e125420">
          <speaker>Her. </speaker>
          <l>Forbeare my Lord, </l>
          <l>Can such a thing as loue be once nam'd here, </l>
          <l>Where euery Marble that supports this roofe, </l>
          <l>In emulation doth vye teares with vs? </l>
          <l>Nay where the wounds of such a mighty King </l>
          <l>Haue yet scarse bled their last. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e125490">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Tush faire Hermione, </l>
          <l>These sights that seeme to ladies terrible, </l>
          <l>Are common to vs souldiers; when from field returning </l>
          <l>All smear'd in blood, where Dukes and Kings lie slaine, </l>
          <l>Yet in our Tents at mid-night it frights not vs </l>
          <l>From courting a sweete Mistresse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e125560">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Hee sayth right, </l>
          <l>And note of this how I can poetise: </l>
          <l>This his great father of his Loue desir'd. </l>
          <l>When from the slaughter of his foes retyr'd </l>
          <l>Hee doft his Cushes and vnarm'd his head, </l>
          <l>To tumble with her on a soft day bed: </l>
          <l>It did reioyce Brifois to imbrace </l>
          <l>His bruised armes, and kisse his blood-stain'd face. </l>
          <l>These hands which he so often did imbrew </l>
          <l>In blood of warlike Troians whom hee slew, </l>
          <l>Were then imploy'd to tickle, touch and feele, </l>
          <l>And shake a Lance that had no print of steele. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e125690">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>Continue in that veine, I'le feed thy Muse </l>
          <l>With Crafish, Praunes and Lobsters. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-hermione" xml:id="ep000065-e125720">
          <speaker>Her. </speaker>
          <l>You brought these of purpose to abuse mee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e125740">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Peace Thersites, </l>
          <l>And Synon you no more. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-076-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e125770">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Wee see by Agamemnon all are mortall, </l>
          <l>And I but shew his neece Hermione </l>
          <l>The way of all flesh. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e125810">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>Tis an easie path, </l>
          <l>(The Mother and the Aunt haue troad it both) </l>
          <l>If shee haue wit to follow. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e125850">Enter Vlysses, Menelaus, Diomed with others. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e125860">
          <speaker>Mene. </speaker>
          <l>If it be so, Egistus is a traytor, </l>
          <l>And shee no more our sister. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-ulysses" xml:id="ep000065-e125890">
          <speaker>Vlys. </speaker>
          <l>Tis not possible </l>
          <l>A Queene of her high birth and parentage </l>
          <l>Should haue such base hand in her husbands death, </l>
          <l>Her husband and her soueraigne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-diomede" xml:id="ep000065-e125940">
          <speaker>Dio. </speaker>
          <l>Double treason, </l>
          <l>Could it be proou'd against her. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e125970">
          <speaker>Men. </speaker>
          <l>It appeares </l>
          <l>So farre against humanity and nature </l>
          <l>We dare not once suspect it, but till proofe </l>
          <l>Explaine it further, hold it in suspence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-ulysses" xml:id="ep000065-e126020">
          <speaker>Vlys. </speaker>
          <l>Oh but their suddaine flight and fortifying. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e126040">
          <speaker>Mene. </speaker>
          <l>These are indeed presumptions, but leaue that </l>
          <l>To a most strict inquiry euen for reuerence </l>
          <l>Of Maiesty and Honour to all Queenes, </l>
          <l>For loue of vs because shee was our sister, </l>
          <l>Both for Orestes and Electra's sake </l>
          <l>Whose births are branded in so foule a deede </l>
          <l>Till wee examine further circumstances </l>
          <l>Spare your seuerer censures. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-ulysses" xml:id="ep000065-e126130">
          <speaker>Vlis. </speaker>
          <l>Tis a businesse </l>
          <l>That least concernes vs, but for Honours sake </l>
          <l>And that hee was our Generall. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e126170">
          <speaker>Mene. </speaker>
          <l>What, prince ly Pyrhus courting our faire daughter? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-hermione" xml:id="ep000065-e126190">
          <speaker>Her. </speaker>
          <l>Yes sir, but in a time vnseasonable </l>
          <l>Euen as the suite it selfe is. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e126220">
          <speaker>Mene. </speaker>
          <l>All delayes </l>
          <l>Shall be cut off and she be swayd by vs. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-076-b"/>
          <l>These Royall Princes ere they leaue Mycena, </l>
          <l>Shall see these nuptiall rights solemnized, </l>
          <l>Weele keepe our faith with Pyrhus. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e126280">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Wee our vowes </l>
          <l>As constant to the bright Hermione. </l>
          <l>First see the royall Generall here interr'd </l>
          <l>And buried like a souldier, 'tis his due: </l>
          <l>To question of his death concernes not vs, </l>
          <l>Wee leaue it to Heauens iustice and reuenge. </l>
          <l>The rights perform'd with faire Hermione, </l>
          <l>Then to our seuerall Countries each man post, </l>
          <l>Captaines disperse still when the General's lost. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e126380">Enter Cethus, Orestes, and Pylades. disguis'd. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e126390">Exeunt </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e126400">
          <speaker>Ore. </speaker>
          <l>Egistus? and our Mother? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e126420">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Am I Cethus, </l>
          <l>Are you Orestes, and this Pyllades, </l>
          <l>So sure they were his murderers: this disguise </l>
          <l>Will suite an act of death, full to the life </l>
          <l>Hee stands vpon a strict and secure guard, </l>
          <l>I haue plotted your admittance, it will take </l>
          <l>Doubt not, it cannot fayle, I haue cast it so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e126500">
          <speaker>Ore. </speaker>
          <l>As sent from Menelaus? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e126520">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Whose name else </l>
          <l>Can breake through such strong guards, where feare and guilt </l>
          <l>Keepe hourely watch? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e126560">
          <speaker>Ore. </speaker>
          <l>It is enough, I haue't, </l>
          <l>And thou the faithful'st of all friends deare Pillades, </l>
          <l>Doe but assist mee in my vowed reuenge </l>
          <l>And inioy faire Electra. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pylades" xml:id="ep000065-e126610">
          <speaker>Pyl. </speaker>
          <l>Next your friendship </l>
          <l>It is the prise I ayme at, I am yours. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e126640">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>What slip you time and opportunity, </l>
          <l>Or looke you after dreames? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e126670">
          <speaker>Ore. </speaker>
          <l>I am a wake. </l>
          <l>And to send them to their eternall sleepe. </l>
          <l>In expedition there is still successe, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-077-a"/>
          <l>In all delayes defect: the traytor dyes </l>
          <l>Were hee in league with all the destinies. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000065-e126730">Exe. Pilad. Orest. </stage>
          <l>And tis a fruitfull yeare for villany, </l>
          <l>And I a thriuing Farmer. In this interim </l>
          <l>I haue more plots on foote: King Menelaus: </l>
          <l>I haue incenc'd against proud Diamed▪ </l>
          <l>Fyrhus against Orestes, hee 'gainst him, </l>
          <l>Ulysses without parralell for wit </l>
          <l>Against them all: so that the first combustion </l>
          <l>Shall burne them vp to ashes. Oh Palamides, </l>
          <l>So deare was both thy loue and memory, </l>
          <l>Not Hellen by her whoredome caus'd more blood </l>
          <l>Streaming from Princes brests, then Cethus shall </l>
          <l>(Brother) for thine vntimely funerall. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e126860">Exit. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e126870">Enter Egistus, Clitemnestra with a strong guard. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e126880">
          <speaker>Egist. </speaker>
          <l>Let none presume to dare into our presence </l>
          <l>Or passe our guard, but such well knowne to vs and to our Queene. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-guard" xml:id="ep000065-e126910">
          <speaker>Guard. </speaker>
          <l>The charge hath past vs round▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e126930">
          <speaker>Egist. </speaker>
          <l>When sinnes of such hye nature 'gainst vs rise, </l>
          <l>Tis fit wee should be kept with heedfull eyes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e126960">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Presume it my Egistus, we are safe, </l>
          <l>The Fort wherein we liue impregnable: </l>
          <l>Or say we were surpris'd by stratagem, </l>
          <l>Or should expose our liues vnto the censure </l>
          <l>Of Law and Iustice, euen in these extreames </l>
          <l>There were not the least feare of difficulty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e127030">
          <speaker>Egist. </speaker>
          <l>Your reason Madam. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e127050">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Whom doth this concerne </l>
          <l>But our owne blood? should Pyrhus grow inrag'd▪ </l>
          <l>I haue at hand my neece Hermione </l>
          <l>To calme his fury: what doth this belong to </l>
          <l>Vlysses, or Aetolian Diomed? </l>
          <l>Are they not strangers? If it come in question </l>
          <l>By Menelaus, is hee not our brother▪ </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-077-b"/>
          <l>Our sister Hellen in his bosome sleepes, </l>
          <l>And can with him doe all things, feare not then, </l>
          <l>Wee are euery way secure. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e127160">
          <speaker>Egist. </speaker>
          <l>Oh but Orestes </l>
          <l>His ey's to mee like lightning, and his arme </l>
          <l>Vp heau'd thus, shewes like Iones thunder-bolt </l>
          <l>Aym'd against lust and murder. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e127210">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Hee's our sonne, </l>
          <l>The filiall duty that's hereditary </l>
          <l>Vnto a mothers name preuents these feares: </l>
          <l>Electra's young, and childish Pilades </l>
          <l>Swai'd by his friend: It rests, could we but worke </l>
          <l>Hellen and Menelaus to our faction, </l>
          <l>Egistus should be stated in Mycene, </l>
          <l>Wee liue his Queene and bride. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e127300">
          <speaker>Egist. </speaker>
          <l>Feare's still suspicious. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e127320">Enter one of the guard. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-guard" xml:id="ep000065-e127330">
          <speaker>Guard. </speaker>
          <l>A Letter sir. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e127350">
          <speaker>Egi. </speaker>
          <l>From whence? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-guard" xml:id="ep000065-e127370">
          <speaker>Guard. </speaker>
          <l>Tis superscrib'd from the great Spartae's King, </l>
          <l>And the Queene Hellen. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e127400">
          <speaker>Egi. </speaker>
          <l>Who the messenger? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-guard" xml:id="ep000065-e127420">
          <speaker>Guard. </speaker>
          <l>Two Gentlemen who much importune you </l>
          <l>For speedy answer. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e127450">
          <speaker>Egi. </speaker>
          <l>Bidde them waite without, </l>
          <l>Now fates proue but propitious, then my kingdome </l>
          <l>I shall presume establish't. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e127490">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>There's no feare, </l>
          <l>Orestes once remoou'd, and that's my charge </l>
          <l>Either by sword or poyson. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e127530">
          <speaker>Egi. </speaker>
          <l>See faire Queene, </l>
          <l>Reade what your brother writes, by this we are </l>
          <l>Eternis'd in our happinesse, and our liues </l>
          <l>Rooted in sweete security. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e127580">The Queene reades. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e127590">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Wee not suspect you in our brothers death, </l>
          <l>A deede too base for any Noble brest. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-078-a"/>
          <l>Therefore in this necessity of state, </l>
          <l>And knowing in this forced vacancy </l>
          <l>So great a kingdome cannot want a guide: </l>
          <l>The soueraignty we thought good to conferre </l>
          <l>On Clitemnestra, or what substitute </l>
          <l>Shee in her best discretion shall thinke fit, </l>
          <l>The vnited Kings of Greece haue thus decreed. </l>
          <l>Your brother Menelaus. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e127700">
          <speaker>Egist. </speaker>
          <l>We are happied euer. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e127720">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>A ioy ratified▪ </l>
          <l>And subiect to no change. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e127750">
          <speaker>Egist. </speaker>
          <l>Call in the messengers, </l>
          <l>Orestes and Electra once remoou'd, </l>
          <l>Wee haue no riuall, no competitor, </l>
          <l>Therefore no iealousie at all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e127800">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>None, none. </l>
          <l>The gods haue with these Kings of Greece agreed </l>
          <l>In his supplanting and instating thee, </l>
          <l>Thee my most deare Egistus. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e127850">Orestes and Pyllades disguised are conducted in. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e127860">
          <speaker>Egist. </speaker>
          <l>You the men? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e127880">
          <speaker>Ore. </speaker>
          <l>Those, whom the Spartan King made speciall choice of </l>
          <l>To trust this great affaire with. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e127910">
          <speaker>Egist. </speaker>
          <l>And y'are welcome, </l>
          <l>But are you men of action: such I meane, </l>
          <l>As haue beene Souldiers bred, whose eyes inur'd </l>
          <l>To slaughter and combustions: at the like </l>
          <l>Would not change face, or tremble? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pylades" xml:id="ep000065-e127970">
          <speaker>Pil. </speaker>
          <l>They that to see </l>
          <l>Legges, armes, and heads strowed on Scamander Plaine, </l>
          <l>Kings by the common souldiers stew'd in goare, </l>
          <l>And three parts hid with their imboweld Steedes, </l>
          <l>Shadowing their mangled bodies from the Sunne, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-078-b"/>
          <l>As if aboue the earth to bury them: </l>
          <l>They that to see an Asian Potentate </l>
          <l>Kil'd at the holy Altar, his owne blood </l>
          <l>Mixt with his sonnes and daughters, Towers demolisht </l>
          <l>Crushing whole thousands, of each sexe and age </l>
          <l>Beneath their ruines: and these horrid sights </l>
          <l>Lighted by scathe- fires, they that haue beheld </l>
          <l>These and more dreadfull obiects; can their eyes </l>
          <l>Moue at a private slaughter? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e128120">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Y'are for vs, </l>
          <l>Will you for hire, for fauour, or aduancement, </l>
          <l>(Now warres are done) to be made great in Court, </l>
          <l>And vndertake that one man easily spar'd </l>
          <l>Amongst so many millions (now suruiuing) </l>
          <l>That such a creature, no way necessary </l>
          <l>But a meere burden to the world wee liue in, </l>
          <l>Hee might no longer liue? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e128210">
          <speaker>Ore. </speaker>
          <l>But name the man, </l>
          <l>And as I loue Egistus, honour you </l>
          <l>And al that glory in such noble deeds. </l>
          <l>Be what hee will; hee's lost. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e128260">
          <speaker>Egist. </speaker>
          <l>Orestes, then? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e128280">
          <speaker>Ore. </speaker>
          <l>Is there none then the world so well may spare </l>
          <l>As young Orestes? Hee to doe't? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e128310">Hee kils Egistus, first discouering himselfe. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-egistus" xml:id="ep000065-e128320">
          <speaker>Egist. </speaker>
          <l>Vaine world farewell, </l>
          <l>My hopes withall, no building long hath stood </l>
          <l>Whose sleight foundation hath bin layd in blood. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e128360">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>I'le dye vpon his bosome. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e128380">
          <speaker>Ore. </speaker>
          <l>Secure the Fort my deare friend Pillades, </l>
          <l>And to your vtmost pacifie the guard: </l>
          <l>Tell them we are Orestes and their Prince, </l>
          <l>And what wee did was to reuenge the death </l>
          <l>Of their dead Lord and Soueraigne▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pylades" xml:id="ep000065-e128440">
          <speaker>Pil. </speaker>
          <l>Sir I'le doe't. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e128460">Exit. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e128470">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Oh mee, that thinking to haue catcht at Heauen, </l>
          <l>Am plung'd into an hell of misery. </l>
          <l>Egistus dead? what comfort can I haue, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-079-a"/>
          <l>One foote Inthron'd, the tother in the graue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e128520">
          <speaker>Ore. </speaker>
          <l>Can you finde teares for such an abiect Groome, </l>
          <l>That had not for an husband one to shed? </l>
          <l>Oh monstrous, monstrous woman▪ is this carrion, </l>
          <l>Is this dead Dog, (Dog said I?) nay what's worse, </l>
          <l>Worthy the sigh or mourning of a Queene, </l>
          <l>When a King lies vnpittied? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e128590">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Thou a sonne? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e128610">
          <speaker>Ore. </speaker>
          <l>The name I am asham'd of: oh Agamemnon, </l>
          <l>How sacred is thy name and memory! </l>
          <l>Whose acts shall fill all forraigne Chronicles </l>
          <l>With admiration, and most happy hee </l>
          <l>That can with greatest Art but booke thy deeds: </l>
          <l>Yet whilst this rottennesse, this gangreen'd flesh </l>
          <l>Whose carkas is as odious as his name </l>
          <l>Shall stinking lie, able to breede a Pest, </l>
          <l>Hee with a Princesse teares to be imbalm'd, </l>
          <l>And a King lie neglected? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e128720">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Bastard. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e128740">
          <speaker>Ore. </speaker>
          <l>If I be, </l>
          <l>Damn'd be the whore my Mother, I, I am sure </l>
          <l>Nor my dead father had no hand in it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e128780">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Oh that I could but lengthen out my yeares </l>
          <l>Onely to spend in curses. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e128810">
          <speaker>Ore. </speaker>
          <l>Vpon whom? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e128830">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>On whom but thee for my Egistus death? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e128850">
          <speaker>Ore. </speaker>
          <l>And I could wish my selfe a Nesturs age </l>
          <l>To curse both him and thee for my dead father. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e128880">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Doest thou accuse mee for thy fathers death? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e128900">
          <speaker>Ore. </speaker>
          <l>Indeede 'twould ill become me being a sonne, </l>
          <l>But were I sure it were so, then I durst; </l>
          <l>Nay, more then that, reuenge it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e128940">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Vpon mee? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e128960">
          <speaker>Ore. </speaker>
          <l>Were all the mothers of the earth in one, </l>
          <l>All Empresses and Queenes cast in one mould, </l>
          <l>And I vnto that one a onely sonne, </l>
          <l>My sword should rauish that incestuous breast </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-079-b"/>
          <l>Of nature, and of state▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e129020">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>I am as innocent of that blacke deede, </l>
          <l>As was this guiltlesse Gentleman here dead. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e129050">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>Oh all you powers of Heauen I inuocate, </l>
          <l>And if you will not heare me, let Hell do't: </l>
          <l>Giue me some signe from eyther feinds or angell, </l>
          <l>I call you both as testates. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000065-e129100">Enter the Ghost of Agamemnon, poynting vnto his wounds: and then to Egistus and the Queene, who were his murderers, which done, hee vanisheth. </stage>
          <l>Godlike shape, </l>
          <l>Haue you (my father) left the Elizium fieldes, </l>
          <l>Where all the ancient Heroes line in blisse, </l>
          <l>To bring your selfe that sacred testimony, </l>
          <l>To crowne my approbation: Lady see. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e129160">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>See what? thy former murder makes thee mad, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e129180">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>Rest Ghost in peace, I now am satisfied, </l>
          <l>And neede no further witnesse: saw you nothing? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e129210">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>What should I see saue this sad spectacle, </l>
          <l>Which blood-shootes both mine eyes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e129240">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>And nothing else? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e129260">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Nothing. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e129280">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>Mine eyes are clearer sighted then, and see </l>
          <l>Into thy bosome. Murdresse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e129310">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>How? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e129330">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>Incestuous strumpet, whose adulteries, </l>
          <l>When Treason could not hide, thou thoughts to couer, </l>
          <l>With most inhumane murder. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e129370">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Meaning vs? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e129390">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>Then, monster, thou didst first instruct mine hand, </l>
          <l>How to write blood, when being a Wife and Queene, </l>
          <l>Thou kildst a King and husband, and hast taught </l>
          <l>Mee being a sonne, how to destroy a mother. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e129440">He wounds her. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e129450">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Oh most vnnaturall. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e129470">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>That I learnt of thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-clytemnestra" xml:id="ep000065-e129490">
          <speaker>Cli. </speaker>
          <l>Vnheard of cruelty, but heauens are iust. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-080-a"/>
          <l>And all remarkeable sinnes punish with marke, </l>
          <l>One mischiefe still another doth beget, </l>
          <l>Adultery murder: I am lost, vndone. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e129540">Shee dyes. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e129550">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>Being no wife, Orestes is no sonne. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e129570">Enter Cethus and Pillades with the guard. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pylades" xml:id="ep000065-e129580">
          <speaker>Pil. </speaker>
          <l>The guard all stand for you, acknowledging </l>
          <l>Orestes Prince and King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e129610">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>I now am neither. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e129630">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>What obiect's this? Queene Clitemnestra slaine? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pylades" xml:id="ep000065-e129650">
          <speaker>Pil. </speaker>
          <l>I hope no sonnes hand in't </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e129670">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>Orestes did it, </l>
          <l>The other title's lost. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e129700">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>All my plots take </l>
          <l>Beyond my apprehension. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pylades" xml:id="ep000065-e129730">
          <speaker>Pil. </speaker>
          <l>This is an age </l>
          <l>Of nothing but portents and prodigies. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e129760">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>The fathers hand as deepe was in her death </l>
          <l>As was the sonnes, hee pointed, and I strooke: </l>
          <l>Was hee not then as vnkind to a Wife, </l>
          <l>As I was to a Mother? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pylades" xml:id="ep000065-e129810">
          <speaker>Pil. </speaker>
          <l>Oh my friend, </l>
          <l>What haue you done? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e129840">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>There is a Plasma, or deepe pit </l>
          <l>Iust in the Center fixt for Parricides, </l>
          <l>I'l keepe my Court there, and Erinnis, shee </l>
          <l>In stead of Hebe, shall attend my Cup, </l>
          <l>Charon the Ferri-man of Hell shall bee </l>
          <l>My Ganimed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pylades" xml:id="ep000065-e129910">
          <speaker>Pil. </speaker>
          <l>The Prince is sure distracted. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e129930">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>New proiect still for me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e129950">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>I'le haue a guard of Furies which shall light mee </l>
          <l>Vnto my nuptiall bed with funerall Teades, </l>
          <l>The fatall sisters shall my hand-maides bee, </l>
          <l>And waite vpon the faire Hermione. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e130000">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Hermione? shee is betroth'd to Pyrhus, </l>
          <l>And (mourning for your absence) all the way </l>
          <l>Vnto the Temple shee will strowe with teares. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-080-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e130040">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>Ha? Pyrhus rape my deare Hermione? </l>
          <l>Hee that shall dare to interpose my purpose▪ </l>
          <l>Or crosse mee in mine Hymineall rights, </l>
          <l>I'le make him lie as flat on the cold earth </l>
          <l>As doth this hound Egistus. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e130100">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>And I would so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e130120">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>Would? Nay I will, his father woare a smocks, </l>
          <l>And in that shape rap't Deiadamia. </l>
          <l>Hee shall not vse my Loue so, oh my Mother; </l>
          <l>Friend take that obiect hence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e130170">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>But you Hermione, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e130190">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>My hand's yet deepe in blood, but to the wrist, </l>
          <l>It shall shall be to the elbowe: gods, nor men, </l>
          <l>Angels, nor Furies shall my rage withstand, </l>
          <l>Not the graue Honour of th' assembled Kings, </l>
          <l>Not Reuerence of the Altar, nor the Priest: </l>
          <l>No superstition shall my fury slay▪ </l>
          <l>Till Pyrhus from the earth be swept away, </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e130270">Exit. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e130280">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Pillades attend your friend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pylades" xml:id="ep000065-e130300">
          <speaker>Pil. </speaker>
          <l>Hee's all my charge, </l>
          <l>My life and his are twinnes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e130330">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Their mines are countermin'd, Cethus, thy fall </l>
          <l>Is either plotted, or to blowe vp all. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e130360">Exit. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e130370">Enter Synon and Thersites. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e130380">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>My head akes brother. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e130400">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>What a batchiler, </l>
          <l>And troubled with the Spartan Kings disease? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e130430">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>No, there's a wedding breeding in my braine, </l>
          <l>Pyrhus the Bride-groome: thou strange creature woman▪ </l>
          <l>To what may I compare thee? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e130470">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>Canst thou deuise ought bad inough? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e130490">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Tis sayd they looke like Angels, and of light▪ </l>
          <l>But for the most part, such light Angels prooue, </l>
          <l>Ten hundred thousand of their honesties </l>
          <l>Will scarce weigh eleauen Dragmaes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e130540">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>Clitemnestra, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-081-a"/>
          <l>And Hellen for example. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e130570">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Young Hermione </l>
          <l>Hath face from both. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e130600">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>The sharpe shrewes nose, they hate hereditary. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e130620">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Thersites, I commend that fellowes wit </l>
          <l>Proffred a wife young, beautifull and rich, </l>
          <l>Onely one fault she had, she wanted braine: </l>
          <l>Who answered in a creature of that sexe, </l>
          <l>I nere desire more wisedome; then to know </l>
          <l>Her husbands bed from anothers. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e130690">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>I commend him, </l>
          <l>But tis not in th' Atrides family, </l>
          <l>To finde out such a woman. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e130730">An Altar set foorth, Enter Pyrhus Lending Hermione as a bride, Menelaus, Vlisses, Diomed. A great trayne, Pyrhus and Hermione kneele at the altar. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e130740">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>See now the sacred nuptiall rights proceede▪ </l>
          <l>The Priests prepare the Alter. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e130770">
          <speaker>Fyr. </speaker>
          <l>Hymen to whom my vowes I consecrate </l>
          <l>As all my loue. To thee Hermione, </l>
          <l>Whom in the presence of these Argiue Kings, </l>
          <l>I heare contract, be thou auspitious to vs: </l>
          <l>This flamming substitute to Saturnes sonne, </l>
          <l>Within whose sacred Temple wee are rooft▪ </l>
          <l>And before all these high Celestiall gods </l>
          <l>And goddesses, in whose eyes now we kneele: </l>
          <l>Especially you Iuno Queene of marriage, </l>
          <l>And faire Lucina, who haue child-births charge, </l>
          <l>Your fauours I inuoake: Let your chast fires </l>
          <l>Drye vp this Virgins teares; make her so fruitefull </l>
          <l>That in her issue great Achilles name </l>
          <l>And fame withall, may liue eternally▪ </l>
          <l>Proceede Priest to your other Ceremonies▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e130930">Enter Orestes, Cethes, and Pilades, with the guard, all their weapons drawne, Orestes runnes at Pyrhus. </stage>
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-081-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000065-orestes" xml:id="ep000065-e130940">
          <speaker>Orest. </speaker>
          <l>Priam before the holy Alter fell, </l>
          <l>Before the Alter bid thy life farwell: </l>
          <l>Rescue Hermione. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pyrrhus" xml:id="ep000065-e130980">
          <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
          <l>Achilles sonne </l>
          <l>Cannot reuengelesse dye, then witnesse all, </l>
          <l>Blood must flow high where such great Princes fal. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-pylades" xml:id="ep000065-e131020">
          <speaker>Pil. </speaker>
          <l>Orestes is in danger. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-menelaus" xml:id="ep000065-e131040">
          <speaker>Mene. </speaker>
          <l>Saue Prince Pyrhus. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e131060">Cethus whispers with Diomed. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e131070">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>This plot was layd </l>
          <l>Both for your life and Kingdome. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-diomede" xml:id="ep000065-e131100">
          <speaker>Dio. </speaker>
          <l>Menelaus: shall neuer beare it so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-ulysses" xml:id="ep000065-e131120">
          <speaker>Vlys. </speaker>
          <l>Fy Thersites, </l>
          <l>Thy sword against me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-thersites" xml:id="ep000065-e131150">
          <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
          <l>Curse vpon all whoores. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e131170">A confused scuffle, in which Orestes kils Pyrhus: Pyrhus, Orestes: Cethus wounds Pillades, Diomed, Menelaus, Vlisses, Thersites, &amp;c. All fall dead sane Vlisses, who beareth thence Hermione: which done, Cethus riseth vp from the dead bodies and speakes. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e131180">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>What all asleepe? and are these gossiping tongues, </l>
          <l>That boasted nought save Warre and Victory, </l>
          <l>Now mute and silent? Oh thou vgly rogue, </l>
          <l>Where's now thy rayling? and thou parracide, </l>
          <l>Thy madnesse is now tam'd, thou need'st no chaines </l>
          <l>To bring thee to thy wits, darknesse hath don't. </l>
          <l>This Diomed? who dar'd to encounter Mars, </l>
          <l>And sayd to wound faire Venus in the hand: </l>
          <l>Where's your valour now? Aegiale, </l>
          <l>Vnlesse (as some say) she be better stor'd, </l>
          <l>Is like to lye without a bed-fellow: </l>
          <l>Rise Pillades, and helpe to awake thy friend, </l>
          <l>What doth your friendship sleepe now? Menelaus </l>
          <l>Hellen's with a new sweete-heart ith' next roome, </l>
          <l>Wilt thou be still a Cuckold? winke at errors </l>
          <l>As pandors do and wittoles? Cethus now </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-082-a"/>
          <l>Be crown'd in Hystory for a reuenge, </l>
          <l>Which in the former World wants president: </l>
          <l>Methinks, as when the Giants warr'd 'gainst heauen, </l>
          <l>And dar'd for primacy with Ioue himselfe▪ </l>
          <l>Hee darting 'gainst their mountaines thunder-boles▪ </l>
          <l>Which shattred them to peeces: the warre done, </l>
          <l>I like the great Olimpicke Iupiter, </l>
          <l>Walke ore my ruines, tread vpon my spoyles </l>
          <l>With maiesty, I pace vpon this floore </l>
          <l>Pan'd with the trunkes of Kings and Potentates, </l>
          <l>For what lesle could haue sated my reuenge? </l>
          <l>This arch-rogue falne amongst them? he whose eies </l>
          <l>Had the preposterous vertue to fire Troy. </l>
          <l>Now is thy blacke soule for thy periuries </l>
          <l>Swimming in red damnation. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e131500">Synon who had before counterfeited death, riseth vp, and answereth. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e131510">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Sir, not yet, </l>
          <l>All pollicies liue not in Cethus brayne, </l>
          <l>Synon hath share, and know if thou hast craft, </l>
          <l>I haue reseru'd some cunning: see my body </l>
          <l>Free and vntoucht from wounds. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e131570">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Speake, shall we then </l>
          <l>Diuide these dead betwixt vs, and both liue? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e131600">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>If two Sunnes cannot shine within one spheare, </l>
          <l>Then why should two arch-villaines? thou hast discouered </l>
          <l>Projects almost beyond me, and for which </l>
          <l>I haue ingrost a mortall enuy here, </l>
          <l>I will be sole, or none. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e131660">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>Cease then to be, </l>
          <l>That I may liue without Competitor. </l>
          <l>Cause Synons name be rac'd out of the World, </l>
          <l>And onely mine remembred. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e131710">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>Thine's but frailty, </l>
          <l>My fame shall be immortall; made more glorious </l>
          <l>In treading vpon thee, as thou on these; </l>
          <l>Stoope thou my Vnderling. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000065-082-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e131760">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>I still shall stand </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000065-e131780">They fight, and kill one another. </stage>
          <l>Rooted. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e131800">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>And yet cut downe by Synons hand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-cethus" xml:id="ep000065-e131820">
          <speaker>Ceth. </speaker>
          <l>I now am dust like these. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-synon" xml:id="ep000065-e131840">
          <speaker>Syn. </speaker>
          <l>One single fight </l>
          <l>Ends him, who millions ruin'd in one night. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e131870">Enter Hellena, Electra, and Hermione. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-hermione" xml:id="ep000065-e131880">
          <speaker>Her. </speaker>
          <l>Can you behold this slaughter? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000065-helen" xml:id="ep000065-e131900">
          <speaker>Hel. </speaker>
          <l>Yes, and dye </l>
          <l>At sight of it: for why should Hellen liue▪ </l>
          <l>Hellen the cause of all these Princes deaths▪ </l>
          <l>Cease to lament, reach me my Glasse Hermione, </l>
          <l>Sweete Orphant do; thy father's dead already, </l>
          <l>Nor will the fates lend thee a mother long. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000065-e131970">Enter Hermione with a looking glasse, then exit. </stage>
          <l>Thankes, and so leaue me. Was this wrinkled fore-head </l>
          <l>When 'twas at best, worth halfe so many liues? </l>
          <l>Where is that beauty? liues it in this face </l>
          <l>Which hath set two parts of the World at warre, </l>
          <l>Beene ruine of the Asian Monarchy, </l>
          <l>And almost this of Europe? this the beauty </l>
          <l>That launch'd a thousand ships from Aulis gulfe? </l>
          <l>In such a poore repurchase, now decayde? </l>
          <l>See fayre ones, what a little Time can doe; </l>
          <l>Who that considers when a seede is sowne, </l>
          <l>How long it is ere it appeare from th'earth, </l>
          <l>Then ere it stalke, and after ere it blade, </l>
          <l>Next ere it spread in leaues, then bud, then flower: </l>
          <l>What care in watring, and in weeding tooke, </l>
          <l>Yet crop it to our vse: the beauties done, </l>
          <l>And smel: they scarse last betwixt Sunne and Sunne▪ </l>
          <l>Then why should these my blastings still suruiue, </l>
          <l>Such royall ruines: or I longer liue, </l>
          <l>Then to be termed Hellen the beautifull. </l>
          <l>I am growne old, and Death is ages due, </l>
          <l>When Courtiers sooth, our glasses will tell true. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000065-083-a"/>
          <l>My beauty made me pittied, and still lou'd, </l>
          <l>But that decay'd, the worlds assured hate </l>
          <l>Is all my dowre, then Hellen yeeld to fate▪ </l>
          <l>Here's that, my soule and body must diuide, </l>
          <l>The guerdon of Adultery, Lust, and Pride. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000065-e132240">Shee strangles her selfe </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000065-e132250">Enter Ulysses. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000065-ulysses" xml:id="ep000065-e132260">
          <speaker>Vlys. </speaker>
          <l>In thee they are punisht: of all these Princes, </l>
          <l>And infinite numbers that opposed Troy, </l>
          <l>And came in Hellens quarrell (saue my selfe). </l>
          <l>Not one suruiues, (thankes to the immortall powers) </l>
          <l>And I am purposde now to acquire by Sea, </l>
          <l>My Kingdome and my deare Penelope, </l>
          <l>And since I am the man soly reseru'd, </l>
          <l>Accept me for the Authors Epilogue. </l>
          <l>If hee haue beene two bloody? tis the Story, </l>
          <l>Truth claimes excuse, and seekes no farther glory, </l>
          <l>Or if you thinke he hath done your patience wrong </l>
          <l>(In teadious Sceanes) by keeping you so long, </l>
          <l>Much matter in few words, hee bad me say </l>
          <l>Are hard to expresse, that lengthned out his Play. </l>
        </sp>
        <trailer>Explicit Actus quintus. </trailer>
      </div>
      <trailer>Here ends the whole History of the destruction of TroyTroy </trailer>
    </body>
    <back></back>
  </text>
</TEI>
