<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000067" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Londini artium &amp; scientiarum scaturigo. Or, Londons fountaine of arts and sciences Exprest in sundry triumphs, pageants, and showes, at the initiation of the Right Honorable Nicholas Raynton into the Maiorty of the famous and farre renowned city London. All the charge and expence of the laborious proiects both by water and land, being the sole vndertaking of the Right Worshipfull Company of the Haberdashers. Written by Thomas Hayvvood.</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Thomas</forename>
            <surname>Heywood</surname>
          </persName>
          <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q2073027</idno>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A03228.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <p>
            This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is available for reuse, according to the terms of
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>
            . The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
          </p>
          </availability>
        </bibl>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Londini artium &amp; scientiarum scaturigo. Or, Londons fountaine of arts and sciences Exprest in sundry triumphs, pageants, and showes, at the initiation of the Right Honorable Nicholas Raynton into the Maiorty of the famous and farre renowned city London. All the charge and expence of the laborious proiects both by water and land, being the sole vndertaking of the Right Worshipfull Company of the Haberdashers. Written by Thomas Hayvvood.</title>
            <author>Heywood, Thomas, d. 1641.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[20] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>By Nicholas Okes,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1632.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>Partly in verse.</note>
            <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ C² .</note>
            <note>Running title reads: Londons scaturigo.</note>
            <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc/>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="print" when="1632">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000067-e10">
        <pb xml:id="ep000067-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000067-001-b"/>
        <p>Londini Artium &amp; Scientiarum Scaturigo. OR, Londons Fountaine of Arts and Sciences. </p>
        <p>Exprest in sundry Triumphs, Pageants, and Showes, at the Initiation of the Right Honorable NICHOLAS RAYNTON into the Maiorty of the famous and farre renowned City LONDON. </p>
        <p>All the Charge and Expence of the laborious Proiects both by Water and Land, being the sole vndertaking of the Right Wersoipfull Company of the Haberdashers, </p>
        <p>Written by <hi>THOMAS HAYWOOD</hi>. </p>
        <p>— Redeunt Spectacula.— </p>
        <figure>
          <head>SERVE AND OBEY. </head>
          <figDesc>coat of arms or blazon</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <p>Printed at London by <hi>Nicholas 〈◊〉 </hi>1632. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000067-e140">
        <pb xml:id="ep000067-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000067-002-b"/>
        <head>❧ To the Right Honorable <hi>Nicholas Raynton</hi>, Lord Maior of this renowned Metropolis LONDON. </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Right honourable, </salute>
        </opener>
        <p>COncerning the Dignity of your place, and Magnificence of your Inauguration: The first equaling, the latter precelling all the famous Magistracies in Christendome. I shall not much stand to dispute, as being a Maxim already granted: yet one thing I cannot omit, as most worthy remarke; namely, how many of like Iudicature haue borne the Sword in this famous and florishing Citty, who breathed their first ayre in the County of Lincolne; from whence you deriue your selfe, as Sir <hi>Iohn Stockton </hi>Mercer, borne at Bratost, L. Maior 1470. Sir <hi>Nicholas Aldwin </hi>Mercer, borne at Spalding, L. Maior 1499. Sir <hi>William Rennington </hi>Fishmonger, at Bosten, L. Maior 1500. Sir <hi>William Forman </hi>Haberdasher, at Gainsborow, L. Maior 1538. Sir <hi>Henry Hobbershorne </hi>Merchant-Tayler, at Wadingworth, L. Maior 1546. Sir <hi>Henry Amcoats </hi>Fishmonger, at Astrop, L. Maior 1548. Sir <hi>Iohn Langley </hi>Goldsmith, at Althrop, L. Maior 1576. Sir <hi>Iohn Aldot </hi>Fishmonger, at Limbergh, L. Maior 1590. Sir <hi>George Bowles </hi>Grocer, at Gosperton, L. Maior 1617. and now in present your Honored selfe <hi>Nicholas Raynton </hi>borne at Heighington, L. Maior 1632. not so many hauing attained to the same Dignity bred in any one County, the City of London <pb xml:id="ep000067-003-a"/>excepted. Worthy obseruation it is also, that at one time in the raigne of Queene Elizabeth, most of the Prime Officers of State, were Country-men of the same County: As the Archbishop of <hi>Canterbury, Whitguist</hi>: the L. High Treasurer of England, L. <hi>Burbeigh Cecill</hi>, the L. Keeper of the Great Seale, Sir <hi>John ●uckering</hi>, Viz. Chamberlaine and Chancellor of the Dutchy, Sir <hi>Thomas Hennidge </hi>one of her Maiesties Priuy Councell: The Lord Chiefe Iustice, Iudge Wraye, &amp;c. Moreouer it may be iustly spoken of you to your great Reputation and Honour, that since the yeere 1209. from <hi>Henry Fitzalwin </hi>the first L. Maior of this Honourable City, and <hi>Reter Duke</hi>, and <hi>Thomas Necle </hi>the first Sheriffes of the same, neuer had any Magistrate a more generall, free, and affectionate Election euen to this present Yeere 1632. Now Time and your owne Demerit Right Honourable, haue raysed you to this Eminence and Dignity, the vniversall eye and expectation of all men is vpon you, who well know, that a wise Magistrate preferres consideration before Conclusion: And (according to the saying of King Agesilaus) Magistrates who gouerne by iust Lawes, must strengthen them by good example: iudge by Prouidence, Wisedome and Iustice, and defend by Power, Care and Vigilance; and thus I humbly take my leaue of your Lordship with this Sentence, <foreign xml:lang="lat">Non sat est te tuum officium fecisse, si non id fama approbat. </foreign>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <signed>Your Lordships Countrey-man and Seruant, THOMAS HEYWOOD. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000067-e580">
        <pb xml:id="ep000067-003-b"/>
        <head>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull <hi>Hugh Perry</hi>, and <hi>Henry Andrewes; </hi>the two Sheriffes of the <hi>Honourable City </hi>London, last Elected. </head>
        <p>Right Worshipfull, and euery way worthy; Your Armes display'd in the Front of this Show, approue your Gentry, and your Trafficke and Commerce, (being free Merchant-aduentures) testifis to the World your Noble Profession; as Trading in the <hi>East-Indies, Turkey, Italy, Spayne, </hi>and France, &amp;c. to the Honour of our Nation abroad, and singular Profits redounding to the Realme at home. Your more priuate Imployments heretofore, aswell in furthering Arts, as incoureging Armes, adding no common Luster to these Offices, vnto which Time and your owne Demerits haue at this present called you. Then as that Publicke weale is most blest and flourishing where the Gouernours are aswell beloued in their Persons, as feared in their Places: So likewise it belongeth to all such as are in Authority, to fieare themselues <pb xml:id="ep000067-004-a"/>by the rule of Socrates, that is, <hi>To heare courteously, answere discreetly, consider seriously, and sentence vnpartially. </hi>But I presume not to aduise, where I rather desire to be instructed; shatting vp my present Seruice with that of <foreign xml:lang="lat">Seneca, Id facere laus est quod decet, non quod licet. </foreign>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <signed>Your Worships to bee commanded. <hi>Thomas Heywood</hi>. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="text" xml:id="ep000067-e760">
        <pb xml:id="ep000067-004-b"/>
        <head>Londons Scaturigo. </head>
        <p>THe Title of the Show is <hi>Scaturigo, 〈◊〉 </hi>the Fountaine and Well-spring of all the Liberall Arts, and Sciences, or Mysteries whatsoeuer; which as they haue beene long since planted, and incouraged: so they are at this time the more liberally watered, and therefore more plenteously inriched by their blessed Mother and bountifull Nurse, the most illustrious Citty London: For the first, namely, the Arts and Studies of the Braine; How many Grammer Schooles haue beene by her and her indulgent Children erected (through all, or most of all) the Shieres and Counties of England, to the propagation and aduancement of Learning, to the furnishing of the Accademies with Students, and from them, the foure flourishing Kingdomes (now vnder the Sword and Scepter of his most Sacred Maiesty) with profound Theologists, expert Phisitians, learned Philosophers, skilfull Mathematicians, &amp;c. If any man desire to bee further instructed, in the number of their Free-schooles, Hospitals, Almes-houses, Lectures, Exercises, (scarce to be numbred) with the names of the founders, and the Annuall reuenewes still continued, and dayly inlarged? for <pb xml:id="ep000067-005-a"/>their perpetuall maintenance? I referre them vnto our English Annalls, where they may be plenteously satisfied; neither can these few Sheets of Paper containe them, much rather require a Volumne. </p>
        <div type="part" xml:id="ep000067-e820">
          <head>So much for the Studies of the Braine. </head>
          <p>Now for all other Sciences, Mysteries, Trades, and Manufactures, (including aswell Merchants as Mechannicks) What City in Europe yeeldeth more plenty? more variety? In so much that by reason of Bartering, Bargening, Trade and Commerce▪ (besides the Bosse or Exchange, dayly throngd with Merchants of all Countries.) The populous Streets rather appeare an open Matt, then an ordinary Market; shee not fauouring and fostering her owns Natiues onely, but Strangers, and of all forraigne Nations whatsoeuer. Here they sucke the Milke of her brests, here they are fed, here cherished by this excellent City, and therefore neither impertinently, nor vnproperly may shee be stiled: <foreign xml:lang="lat">Artium &amp; Scientiarum inundans Scatarigo</foreign>. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="ep000067-e870">
          <head>The show by Water. </head>
          <p>It representeth Arion with his Harpe in his hand, riding vpon the backe of a Dolphin, behinde him for ornament old Oceanus and Amphetrite, mounted vpon two Sea horses, holding each of them a Staffe and a Banner, wherein are displayde the Armes of the two Sheriues now in place, of him it is thus commented. </p>
          <p>Arion was borne in Methimnus, whom Pyranthus, (or as Gellius and Herodatus please to name him) Periander, for his excellent skill vpon the Harpe, greatly delighted <pb xml:id="ep000067-005-b"/>in: Dycaearohus describeth him for a noble Ditherambick <ref target="A03228-e1020-b"/>
            <note corresp="A03228-e1020-a" place="margin">Lib. de Dionis. Certaminib. </note>Poet. He having got great store of Treasure, was desirous to crosse from Corinth into Sicilia and Italy, to whom Apollo appeares (the night before his imbarking) in a Dreame, and willed him to attire himselfe in his Robe and Lawrell, and to be ready in any danger to sing vnto his Harpe, and not to feare any thing. The next day (being farre from shoare) the Marriners hauing notice what Treasure hee had aboord, conspired amongst themselues to cast him into the Sea, which hee perceiuing, begged of them so much respite, that habited as hee was, hee might sing one funerall farewell to his Harpe, which granted, so sweete was his Harmony, that the Dolphins came sporting about the shippe, as much delighted with his Musicke: amongst whom hee cast himselfe, and they supported him, and bore him backe vnto Corinth; where hauing told this wondermeat, the King graciously entertayned him; soone after the same Barke being by a tempest drouen into the same Harbour, notice thereof beeing giuen vnto the King, hee strictly questioned them concerning Arion, they affirm'd him to bee dead at Sea, to which when they had sworne, hee caused Arion suddenly to appeare before them, who confounded with shame, were commanded to death: Appollo after translated Arion for his Musicke, and the Dolphin for his Pitty amongst the Starres. </p>
          <floatingText>
            <body>
              <div type="speech" xml:id="ep000067-e1150">
                <head>Arions Speech directed to the Riuer Thames. </head>
                <sp xml:id="ep000067-e1190">
                  <l>
                    <ref target="A03228-e1210-b"/>
                    <note corresp="A03228-e1210-a" place="margin">The first speech by Water. </note>Faire Thamesis, vpon whose siluer brest </l>
                  <l>Arion with his Dolphin new doth rest. </l>
                  <l>How I admire thy Glory, State, and Pride, </l>
                  <l>Vpon this Solemne day thus beautified? </l>
                  <l>Ganges renowned in all forraigne Lands, </l>
                  <l>Nor Tagus boasting of her golden Sands </l>
                  <pb xml:id="ep000067-006-a"/>
                  <l>Can paralell thy Riches; Not Caister </l>
                  <l>Famous for Swannes, nor Po her cleere stream'd Sister: </l>
                  <l>Winding Meander, nor yet Simois Flood, </l>
                  <l>Which Fame saith, at the Troian Seige van blood. </l>
                  <l>Swift Rubicon, whose memory shall last, </l>
                  <l>Because it, Caesar with his Army post. </l>
                  <l>Choaspes, that almost guirts Persia round: </l>
                  <l>Nor Issa, by Darius aeath renown'd. </l>
                  <l>The Amazonian Thermedon, the Nyle </l>
                  <l>That breeds in it the weeping Crocadile. </l>
                  <l>The Euphrates, the Volga, and the Ryne, </l>
                  <l>Nay Iordan too, that waters Palestine: </l>
                  <l>What Paris Some, or Romes swift Tyber bee, </l>
                  <l>The one a Brooke, the other a Ditch to thee, </l>
                  <l>And my Crownd Dolphin doth proclaime thee thus, </l>
                  <l>Th'art the choyse Darling of Oceanus. </l>
                  <l>And if thou hast a Genius, (as t'is guest </l>
                  <l>All Riuers haue?) know wherein th'art most blest. </l>
                  <l>Not that thy Bankes are so defenc't and stable, </l>
                  <l>Nor within Land th'art so far nauigable, </l>
                  <l>Not for thy Flux and Refluxe, (Ebbs and Tydes) </l>
                  <l>Or the rich Meddowes bordering round thy sides. </l>
                  <l>Not that being pleas'd, th'art smooth, being angry, curl'd, </l>
                  <l>Nor thy rare Bridge not equald through the World. </l>
                  <l>Not for those goodly Buildings reard so bye, </l>
                  <l>To make thes line to perpetuity. </l>
                  <l>Not for thy spacious Limits and Extents, </l>
                  <l>(And yet all those vnriuald Ornaments.) </l>
                  <l>But if I truely shall to thee commend, </l>
                  <l>That blisse wherein thou others dost transcend, </l>
                  <l>Behold this Day the Honour and the State </l>
                  <l>Of this thy Great and God like Magistrate. </l>
                  <l>Not waited on by Boats made of the Trunks </l>
                  <pb xml:id="ep000067-006-b"/>
                  <l>Of Canes, or hollowed Trees, or petty Iunks, </l>
                  <l>Or wanton Gondelaes: but Barges, strong, </l>
                  <l>And richly deckt, who as they plowe along </l>
                  <l>Thy brest, with their smooth keeles to make their way, </l>
                  <l>See how the Wind doth with their streamers play, </l>
                  <l>How beautiful thy Waues how throngd thy shoares, </l>
                  <l>And what a Musick's when they strike their Oares▪ </l>
                  <l>To see them with Graue Magistrates so Man'd, </l>
                  <l>Powerfull by Sea, and potent too by Land. </l>
                  <l>So many Sciences, and Misteries </l>
                  <l>Distinguisht into seuerall Companies, </l>
                  <l>In sundry bottomes: and each Art and Trade </l>
                  <l>Knowne by the Flags and Pendants here displaid. </l>
                  <l>And London which Metropolis we call, </l>
                  <l>The Fount and Scaturigo of them all. </l>
                  <l>Graue Praetor, now this Day to be inuested </l>
                  <l>The Head of al these, passe on vnmolested, </l>
                  <l>In your great Inauguration proceede, </l>
                  <l>Which to your lasting Honour is decreed. </l>
                  <l>In your returne baske you shall vnderstand, </l>
                  <l>Those Triumphs that attend on you by Land. </l>
                </sp>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
          <p>
            <hi>Perseus, Andromeda </hi>with the Sea-monster are onely shewed vpon the Water, but their expression I referre to their place by Land. </p>
          <p>
            <ref target="A03228-e2190-b"/>
            <note corresp="A03228-e2190-a" place="margin">The first show by Land. </note>Of which the first presentment is in Pauls Church-yard: Namely, St. Katherine, Patronesse of this Worshipfull Company, vpon a Lyon, bordered about with the Sea-waues▪ (the Armes of the Haberdashers) shee is Crowned as being a Queene, bearing a Wheele in her hand, full of sharpe cutting Irons, the Embleame of her Martyrdome: Her attendants to beautifie the plat-forme, are foure Virgins, Humility the first: Of which Vertue <ref target="A03228-e2230-b"/>
            <note corresp="A03228-e2230-a" place="margin">Senec. i● Thiess. </note>Seneca thus speaketh, <foreign xml:lang="lat">Laus vera humili sepe contingit vito. </foreign>
            <pb xml:id="ep000067-007-a"/>The second Truth, which scaleth the Heauens, illustateth the Earth, maintaineth Iustice, gouerneth Cities, kils Hatred, cherisheth Loue, and discouereth Treasons: The third Zeale, of which it is thus layd; <hi>Office is strengthned by Zeale, and Zeale maketh authority invincible. </hi>The fourth, Constancy: according with that of <q>
              <l>
                <ref target="A03228-e2320-b"/>
                <note corresp="A03228-e2320-a" place="margin">Lib. 5. de bell. Civil. </note>Lucan, Intrepidus quicunque datis mihi Numina mortem Accipiam— </l>
            </q>All which are necessary in a Magistrate, as needfull in a Martyr: Of the Etymologie of her Name, her Royal Birth, her Breeding, her Life and Death, in the last yeeres Discourse I gaue a large Charactar, and therefore preceede to her Speech, which is as followeth. </p>
          <floatingText>
            <body>
              <div type="speech" xml:id="ep000067-e2370">
                <head>St. Katherines Speech. </head>
                <sp xml:id="ep000067-e2400">
                  <l>DOth any wonder, why St. Katherine, shee </l>
                  <l>
                    <ref target="A03228-e2440-b"/>
                    <note corresp="A03228-e2440-a" place="margin">St. Katherins speech. </note>The Patronesse of this faire Companie </l>
                  <l>Is mounted on a Lyon? Let such know, </l>
                  <l>That (being a Queeney this kingly beast doth owe </l>
                  <l>Mee duty by instinct: Besides I come </l>
                  <l>Both with Virginity and Martyrdome, </l>
                  <l>Sainted moreouer, and (of these) the least </l>
                  <l>Able to tame the most insulting Beast. </l>
                  <l>But this is hee the billowes doth deuide, </l>
                  <l>And therefore iustly on his backe I ride: </l>
                  <l>All these belonging to this Worthy Trade, </l>
                  <l>The Lyon, Sea-waues, <hi>and the </hi>Princely Mayde: </l>
                  <l>That for the Armes: note next what I display </l>
                  <l>In this my Banner here, <hi>Serue and obey: </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Rare Morall in this Motto, (if well scand) </l>
                  <l>For Kings are Gods, Viz-gerents, and command </l>
                  <l>By Sword and Scepter: and by their good Grace </l>
                  <l>Can preferre others both to power and place. </l>
                  <l>As you this Day behold this Scarlet worne, </l>
                  <pb xml:id="ep000067-007-b"/>
                  <l>And Sword of Iustice thus in publike borne; </l>
                  <l>The Cap of Maintenance, Coller of Esses, </l>
                  <l>(Which Trauellers in all their large progresses </l>
                  <l>Can in no City parallell, that's scite </l>
                  <l>In th' earths deuision, knowne quadrupertite:) </l>
                  <l>So, whosoeuer shall himselfe oppose </l>
                  <l>Against this Magistrate, (as one of those </l>
                  <l>The King deputes as Chiefe) himselfe hee brings </l>
                  <l>To bee a rebell to the King of Kings: </l>
                  <l>Far be it an arch-traytor in that kind </l>
                  <l>'Mongst all these goodly Companies, (combind </l>
                  <l>In mutuall loue and league:) should dare to appeare </l>
                  <l>In the faire Progresse of this Praetors yeare. </l>
                  <l>Behold, and view who my attendants bee, </l>
                  <l>Constancy, Zeale, Truth, and Humility. </l>
                  <l>Be constant then vnto this Graue Lord Maior, </l>
                  <l>And the two Shrieues that his assistants are; </l>
                  <l>Chose by the publicke Voyce and Senats Doome, </l>
                  <l>As Censors, and the Tribunes were in Rome; </l>
                  <l>Doe it in Zeale, in Truth, and all submission, </l>
                  <l>That their be found no crosse interposition </l>
                  <l>Betwixt Power and Obedience, so shall all </l>
                  <l>Arts, Mysteries, and Trades Mechannicali, </l>
                  <l>Thriue, prosper, and increase, so long as they </l>
                  <l>Honour the King, the Magistrate obey. </l>
                </sp>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="ep000067-e3000">
          <head>The second show by Land. </head>
          <p>This discouereth Andromeda the Daughter of King Cepheus, and Cassiopeia, tide to a Rocke, and ready to bee deuoured by a Sea-monster: But rescued by Perseus the Sonne of Iupiter and Danae, who is mounted vpon a Pegasus, or Winged-horse, who is sayd to bee bred from Neptune and Medusa, and in Hellicon a Mountaine in Boetia, striking a Stone with his hoofe, opend that Fountaine. <pb xml:id="ep000067-008-a"/>called (from him) Hyppocrene, much celebrated by the <hi>Muses. Perseus </hi>in one hand hath an Harpe or crooked Sword, and vpon his left arme a Shield with a Gorgons head figured therein: In Perseus are comprehended all the prime Vertues acquired in a Noble Magistrate: In <hi>Andromeda Chastity </hi>and Innocence: I cannot heere insist <ref target="A03228-e3220-b"/>
            <note corresp="A03228-e3220-a" place="margin">Meta- </note>vpon the Hystory, but rather referre the Reader to Ouid, who hath most elegantly expressed it; but come to the Speech deliuered by Perseus. </p>
          <floatingText>
            <body>
              <div type="speech" xml:id="ep000067-e3280">
                <head>Perseus his Speech. </head>
                <sp xml:id="ep000067-e3310">
                  <l>
                    <hi>I Perseus, Ioues </hi>sonne, borne of Heauenly Stede, </l>
                  <l>Mounted vpon a swist Pegasian Steede, </l>
                  <l>Who with his hoofe strooke vp the Muses Well, </l>
                  <l>Whence Euthusiasma's and hie Ruptures swell. </l>
                  <l>As through the ayery tract I forc't my way, </l>
                  <l>Spyde here the Louely Maide Andromeda, </l>
                  <l>Cheynd to a Rocke, on whom (so Fate hath lowerd) </l>
                  <l>Ready by a Sea-whale to be deuourd. </l>
                  <l>Know there is figured in this <hi>Princely Maide</hi>, </l>
                  <l>Chastity, and Innocence, which Diuine ayde </l>
                  <l>Is ready to assist still from aboue, </l>
                  <l>By one or other of the Sonnes of Ioue. </l>
                  <l>Of which denomination, none, more Grace </l>
                  <l>Can claime than you, who are in power and place, </l>
                  <l>And hold this Day in chiefe; then Perseus like, </l>
                  <l>Keepe that your Sword still drawne, ready to strike; </l>
                  <l>Making such Monsters of your Iustice tast, </l>
                  <l>Who insidiate the Innocuous and the Chaste. </l>
                  <l>Obserue <hi>(Graue Sir</hi>) the Atmes and Shield I beare, </l>
                  <l>Such as your selfe, and others ought to weare, </l>
                  <l>Both for Defence and Offence: and in me </l>
                  <l>Embleam'd, all those prime Vertues that should be </l>
                  <l>In Persons of your Power, my Sword resembles </l>
                  <pb xml:id="ep000067-008-b"/>
                  <l>
                    <hi>Vnpartiall Iustice</hi>, at which guilt still trembles; </l>
                  <l>My Winged-horse, Celerity and Speed: </l>
                  <l>In doing it, that no illegal deed </l>
                  <l>May passe vnscourged, and there be tooke no rest, </l>
                  <l>Vntil reliefe be giuen to the opprest. </l>
                  <l>This Shield that beares the Gorgons head imblaz'd, </l>
                  <l>Vpon whose Snaky locks who euer gaz'd, </l>
                  <l>Were turn'd to statues of cold senselesse stone, </l>
                  <l>Is that <hi>(Graue Magistrate</hi>) you now put on. </l>
                  <l>Whilst on your Arme you weare this constant Targe, </l>
                  <l>Bearing your selfe vprightly in your Charge. </l>
                  <l>All such as shal in Malice or in Pride </l>
                  <l>Your Purple State detract from, or deride, </l>
                  <l>Discouer this before them, it hath power </l>
                  <l>To freeze them into Marble the same houre </l>
                  <l>Striue you to imitate what I haue done, </l>
                  <l>Since you this day, are Perseus and Ioues sonne. </l>
                </sp>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="ep000067-e3930">
          <head>The third show by Land. </head>
          <p>
            <ref target="A03228-e3960-b"/>
            <note corresp="A03228-e3960-a" place="margin">〈…〉 </note>This is more Mimicall then Materiall, and inserted for the Vulgar, who rather loue to feast their eyes, then to banquet their cares: and therefore though it bee allowed place amongst the rest: (as in all Professions wee see Dunces amongst Doctors, Simple amongst Subtle, and Fooles intermixt with Wisemen to fill vp number) as doubting whether it can wel appollogy for it selfe or no, at this time I affoord it no tongue. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="ep000067-e3970">
          <head>The fourth show by Land. </head>
          <p>The Right Honourable the Lord Maior in present, though free of this Worshipfull Company of the Haberdashers, (at whose sole charge, the High Solemnity of this Day is celebrated) yet was by Profession a Mercer, and his chiefe Trading was in Florence for Sattins, Taffaties, and Sarsnets; in Luca for Taffaties and Sarsnets, in <pb xml:id="ep000067-009-a"/>Gene for Gene Veluets, Damasks, &amp;c. In Bolognia for Sattins, Cypresse, and Sarsnets. As also in Pysa, now because the materialls of which these Stuffes are made, are brought from the farthest remote Countries vpon the backs of Cammels, Mules, Dromidaries and Elephants: I made choice of this Beast, especially, of whose incomparable strength and most pregnant vnderstanding, if any desire to be fully satisfied, I must referre them to <hi>Pliny, Gesner</hi>, but more essentially to <hi>Don Sebastian dè Cobarruias Orozco En el Tesoro de la Lengua Castellana, </hi>(from whom Minshaw borrowed his Etymologicall Spanish Dictionary) vpon the word Elephante, where are diuers Stories of them, which but for the Grauity of the Author, might almost appeare incredible. The Elephant is guided by an Indian, vpon his backe is a faire Castle furnisht with change and variety of obiects, &amp;c. the Speech deliuered by the Indian as followeth. </p>
          <floatingText>
            <body>
              <div type="speech" xml:id="ep000067-e4150">
                <head>The Indians Speech. </head>
                <sp xml:id="ep000067-e4170">
                  <l>No beast of all the Wildernesse can vant </l>
                  <l>Like Srength or Wisedome with the Elephant. </l>
                  <l>And therefore, (if considerd wel) none may </l>
                  <l>Better become the Triumphs of this Day. </l>
                  <l>What Hieroglificke can a man inuent, </l>
                  <l>Embleame or Symbole, for a Gouernment </l>
                  <l>In this high nature, apter or more fit </l>
                  <l>Deuis'd before, or to be thought of yet. </l>
                  <l>He beares a Castle (as this day wee see, </l>
                  <l>But of what strength and puissance must you bee </l>
                  <l>Supporting this great Citty? who must lay </l>
                  <l>Your shoulders to a burden; such as may </l>
                  <l>Make Atlas shrinke bencath it; Temples, Towers </l>
                  <l>Rialtoes, spacious Mansions, Suburbe bowers. </l>
                  <l>A weight to make th' Hesperian Giant droope </l>
                  <pb xml:id="ep000067-009-b"/>
                  <l>And Hercules, (who bore vp Heauen) to stoope. </l>
                  <l>Next, of what Vnderstanding, Apprehension, </l>
                  <l>What Iudgement, Knowledge, Wisedome and Retention? </l>
                  <l>Of what Fore-sight? what Body and what Braine? </l>
                  <l>What an Antomedan to guide the raine <ref target="A03228-e4460-b"/>
                    <note corresp="A03228-e4460-a" place="margin">Antomed. Hectors Charister. Palinur: <hi>Pi lot to </hi>Aenea </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of Steedes vnmannag'd? what a Palinure </l>
                  <l>To steare this Helme? and such a Barke assure </l>
                  <l>In a Sea troubled, where can be no trust </l>
                  <l>In an vnconstant Surge or angry Gust? </l>
                  <l>Yet such an Elephant we hope to finde </l>
                  <l>Of you, both in th' ability of Minde </l>
                  <l>And strength of Arme, by that incouragement </l>
                  <l>The former passage of your life hath lent: </l>
                  <l>Showed in your Iudgement and Experience, </l>
                  <l>Your Grauity, and vnchang'd Temperance; </l>
                  <l>All generall Vertues that become such State, </l>
                  <l>Behouefull in so Great a Magistrate: </l>
                  <l>So after Times vnto your Fame shall story </l>
                  <l>How you haue borne vp in her pristine Glory </l>
                  <l>This flourishing City, not once shrinking vnder </l>
                  <l>So great a burden, (to successiue wonder) </l>
                  <l>Since no skild Pilot better could command </l>
                  <l>By Sea, or expert Charicter by Land. </l>
                </sp>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="ep000067-e4730">
          <head>The fist show by Land. </head>
          <p>Is the Scaturigo or Fountaine of Vertue, from which all Arts and Sciences are watered: I neede not to spend Time in the description thereof, it being able sufficiently to expresse it selfe, the nature thereof being in the Poeme layd open euen vnto the meanest capacity. There are twelue sundry persons to beautifie the Modell, suiting with the number of the twelue Companies as the Saints that pancrize them; and euery of them a Shield on their arme, bearing their seueral Scutchions properly belonging to the <pb xml:id="ep000067-010-a"/>Halls. The Speech from the Fountaine is thus deliuered. </p>
          <floatingText>
            <body>
              <div type="speech" xml:id="ep000067-e4800">
                <head>The Speech vpon the Fountaine. </head>
                <sp xml:id="ep000067-e4820">
                  <l>TWelue houres twice told, distinguish night and Day, </l>
                  <l>Twelue Caesars of the Iulian Line did sway </l>
                  <l>Romes Empire, and in cuery case of striffe </l>
                  <l>Where Action's tryde or if concerning life, </l>
                  <l>Twelue makes the Iury full: the Zodaiacke Lines </l>
                  <l>Are likewise fild by twelue Celestiall Signes, </l>
                  <l>Amongst which one in your Emblazons borne </l>
                  <l>Is numbred by the name of Capricorne. </l>
                  <l>Twelue Sibills we account, and they fore-told </l>
                  <l>Things hapned since, although they spake of old </l>
                  <l>By twelue: the blest Word in the Church instated </l>
                  <l>Was at the first divuldg'd and propagated. </l>
                  <l>Twelue Companies you are in Chiefe, 13. heere </l>
                  <l>Present that number with those Armes they beare. </l>
                  <l>And hence the Inundant Scaturigo growes, </l>
                  <l>Which through our Kingdomes large Dominions flowes, </l>
                  <l>By founded Schooles, by Colledges, by <hi>Trade, </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By Trafficke, by Commerce, by Proiect layd. </l>
                  <l>For thrifty Bargaine and all competent Gayne, </l>
                  <l>Asswell arising from the Hand as Brayne. </l>
                  <l>London the Mother and the Fountaine stil'd. </l>
                  <l>And you of all her Sonnes new eldest Child; </l>
                  <l>(Heire to her great good Workes) incourage still </l>
                  <l>These pious Acts, and by Example fill </l>
                  <l>Voide places with the like, and in this State </l>
                  <l>You beare, as being now chiefe Magistrate: </l>
                  <l>So order this your numerous Charge, that they </l>
                  <l>May God, the King, Your selfe Serue and Obey. </l>
                </sp>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
          <p>
            <ref target="A03228-e5340-b"/>
            <note corresp="A03228-e5340-a" place="margin">●● the Supporters of 〈◊〉 Armes </note>A word or two concerning the supporters of the Armes of this Worshipfull Company. Parmentsius a Greeke Author thus relates, King Melliseus who ruled in Creete, had <pb xml:id="ep000067-010-b"/>two Daughters, to whom Iupiter in his Infancy was sent <ref target="A03228-e5390-b"/>
            <note corresp="A03228-e5390-a" place="margin">of the Company. </note>to be nursed, to preserue him from the fury of his Father Saturne: but they being at that time dry-brested, caused him to sucke of a Goate called Amalthaea, by whose Milke hee was nourished, till the time that hee came to be weyned, (this Goate vsually brought forth two twins) Iupiter after in requitall of so great a benefit receiued by her, translated her amongst the Starres. This Goate is that Capricornus one of the 12. Celestiall Signes, The two Kidds (her twins) placed in the Heauensolso, were first obserued by the great Astrologer <hi>Cleostrates Tenedius</hi>. The last Speech at Night is deliuered by Arion, which is a short commemoration of the former passages of the Dayes Triumph in these wordes following. </p>
          <q>
            <lg>
              <l>Now hath the Sun put off his golden beames, </l>
              <l>Watring his hot Steeds in cold Ister streames, </l>
              <l>And tyr'd with his dayes trauell, in the West </l>
              <l>Tooke vp his Inne: But ere you goe to rest, </l>
              <l>Remember what Arion still proclaimes </l>
              <l>In the due honour of the noble Thames. </l>
              <l>Next, how your Queene-like Saint directs the way </l>
              <l>For you to rule, for others to obey. </l>
              <l>Then to be cal'd Ioues Sonne you haue the Grace, </l>
              <l>And that in Persaus figured is your Place. </l>
              <l>That in this able Elephant's implyde </l>
              <l>Your Strength to beare, your Iudgement to decyde. </l>
              <l>Last, that you are the Spring and Fountaine made </l>
              <l>To water enery Science, Art, and Trade; </l>
              <l>Obseruing those, your Honour shall shine bright, </l>
              <l>And so a happy and most blest good-night. </l>
            </lg>
          </q>
          <p>I come last to the Artist, the Moddellor and Composer of these seuerall Peeces, Maister <hi>Gerard Christmas</hi>, of whom <foreign xml:lang="lat">(si paruis componert, magnalicet) </foreign>as <hi>Augustus Caesar</hi>, <pb xml:id="ep000067-011-a"/>speaking of Rome, boasted, that hee found it of Bricke, but hee left it built of Marble: So he who found these Pageants and showes of Wicker and Paper, rather appearing monstrous and prodigious Births, then any Beast (presented in them) in the least kind imitating Nature: hath reduc't them to that sollidity and substance for the Materialls, that they are so farre from one dayes washing to deface them, that the weathering of many Winters can not impeach them: and for their excellent Figures and well-proportioned lineaments, (by none preceding him) that could be sayd to bee paralleld: In regard therefore there bee so many strangers of all Countries, and such as can iudge of Workemanship, come to be spectators of these Annuall Triumphs, I could wish that the vndertaking thereof might be hereafter conferd (for the Honour of the Citty) vpon men like able and sufficient. For his owne particular I conclude: <foreign xml:lang="lat">Hunc aliquis vix imitando superare potest. </foreign>
          </p>
          <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="supplied_by_editor">
        <head>Notes, typically marginal, from the original text</head>
        <div corresp="A03228-e760" xml:id="ep000067-e760-n">
          <head>Notes for div A03228-e760</head>
        </div>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
