<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000072" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Love's Mistress</title>
        <author>
<!--Heywood, Thomas-->
          <persName>
            <forename>Thomas</forename>
            <surname>Heywood</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A03235.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed
            under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull n="TCP source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">Loves maistresse: or, The Queens masque. As it was three times
              presented before their two Excellent Maiesties, within the space of eight dayes; in
              the presence of sundry forraigne ambassadors. Publikely acted by the Queens Comœdians,
              at the Phœnix in Drury-Lane. Written by Thomas Heywood.</title>
                <author>Heywood, Thomas, d. 1641.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>38 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
                <date>2003 January (TCP phase 1)</date>
                <idno type="marc">99841870</idno>
                <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 13352.</idno>
                <idno type="stc">Greg, II, 504(a).</idno>
                <idno type="vid">6485</idno>
                <idno type="DLPS">A03235</idno>
                <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2240870404</idno>
                <availability>
                  <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
                institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text
                Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is
                reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission
                must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this
                text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu
                for further information or permissions.</p>
                </availability>
              </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
            <biblFull n="printed source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">Loves maistresse: or, The Queens masque. As it was three times
              presented before their two Excellent Maiesties, within the space of eight dayes; in
              the presence of sundry forraigne ambassadors. Publikely acted by the Queens Comœdians,
              at the Phœnix in Drury-Lane. Written by Thomas Heywood.</title>
                <title type="alt">Loves mistresse</title>
                <title type="alt">Queens masque.</title>
                <title type="alt">Loves mistris.</title>
                <author>Heywood, Thomas, d. 1641.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[96] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Printed by Robert Raworth, for Iohn Crowch; and are to bee sold by Iasper
              Emery, at the signe of the Eagle and Child, in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication_date">1636.</date>
                <date type="creation_date">1634</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>
                  <p>In verse.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Signatures: pi2 A-L4 M2.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Running title reads: Loves mistris.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Quire B outer forme is in two settings; B1r caption title has (1) "Loues" or (2)
                "Loves".</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</p>
                </note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
      <profileDesc>
        <particDesc>
          <listPerson>
            <person xml:id="ep000072-midas">
              <persName>Midas</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000072-Apuleius">
              <persName>Apuleius</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000072-admetus">
              <persName>Admetus</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000072-unassigned">
              <persName>Unassigned</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000072-zelotes">
              <persName>Zelotes</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000072-astioche">
              <persName>Astioche</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000072-menetius">
              <persName>Menetius</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000072-petraea">
              <persName>Petraea</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000072-psiche">
              <persName>Psiche</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000072-venus">
              <persName>Venus</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000072-cupid">
              <persName>Cupid</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000072-pan">
              <persName>Pan</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000072-eccho">
              <persName>Eccho</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000072-evemore">
              <persName>Evemore</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000072-both">
              <persName>Both</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000072-clown">
              <persName>Clown</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000072-1_swain">
              <persName>1 Swain</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000072-2_swain">
              <persName>2 Swain</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000072-swain_1">
              <persName>Swain 1</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000072-xxxx_1">
              <persName>Xxxx 1</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000072-xxxx_3">
              <persName>Xxxx 3</persName>
            </person>
          </listPerson>
        </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1634">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000072-e100030">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000072-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000072-001-b"/>
        <p>Loves Maistresse: OR, The Queens Masque. </p>
        <p>As it was three times presented before their two Excellent MAIESTIES, within the space of eight dayes; In the presence of sundry Forraigne AMBASSADORS. </p>
        <p>Publikely Acted by the QUEENS Comoedians, At the Phoenix in Drury-lane. </p>
        <p>Written by THOMAS HEYWOOD. </p>
        <p>Autprodesse solent, aut delectare.— </p>
        <p>LONDON, Printed by Robert Raworth, for Iohn Crowch; and are to bee sold by Iasper Emery, at the signe of the Eagle and Child, In Pauls Church-yard. 1636. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000072-e100100">
        <pb xml:id="ep000072-002-a"/>
        <head> TO THE RIGHT Honorable, EDWARD, Earle of <hi>Dorset</hi>, Lord Chamberlaine to the
          QVEENES Most Excellent Majestie, Knight of the Noble order of the <hi>Garter</hi>, and one
          of His MAIESTIES most Honorable Privie Councell, &amp;c. </head>
        <p>
          <seg>RIGHT HONOVRABLE, _IT having pleased Her Most Excellent Majestie to grace this (though
          unworhy) Poem so often with her Royal presence, I was imboldened the rather (though I dare
          not commend) yet to commit it to your Noble Patronage, <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000072-002-b"/> neither are Dramma's of this nature, so despicable,
          as to be held unworthy the countenance of great men, </seg>
          <pb xml:id="ep000072-003-a"/>countenance of great men when there is frequent president, that the like have beene Dedicated too, and entertained by Emperours, and the most Potent Princes of their times. If your Honor shall dayne the acceptance of a playne mans love, and obseruance in this Presentment, as you grace the worke so you shall much incourage the Author, who humbly takes his leave of of your Lordship, with that borrowed from the excellent Poet Nemesianns. Egl. 1. </p>
        <epigraph>
          <quote>— <gap extent="2" n="3-a-0880" unit="lines"/>Concinerent— </quote>
        </epigraph>
        <closer>
          <signed>Thomas Heywood. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="to_the_reader" xml:id="ep000072-e100230">
        <pb xml:id="ep000072-003-b"/>
        <head>. </head>
        <opener>
          <salute> Generovs Reader </salute>
        </opener>
        <p>
          <seg> _FOr this Dramatick Poem, I neede not much Apologie;
          It having past so many Tests of Approbation, yet for commendable Customes sake I follow
          the tradition of all or most Authours, who never deficient in this kind of complement: The
          Argument is</seg>taken from Apuleius, an excellent Morrall, if truely understood, and may be called a golden Truth, conteined in a leaden fable, which though it bee not altogether conspicuous to the vulgar, yet to those of Learning and judgement, no lesse apprehended in the Paraphrase, then approved in the Originall: of which, if the perusers hereof were all Apuleians, and never a Midas amongst them, I should make no question: So much for the Subject it selfe, but for the rare decorements which new apparrell'd it, when it came the second time to the Royall viewe, (Her Gratious Majestie then entertaining His Highnesse at Denmarke-house, upon his Birth-day) I cannot pretermit to give a due Charractar to that admirable Artist, Mr. Inego Iones, Master surueyor of the Kings worke &amp;amp;c. Who to eery Act, nay almost to ever Sceane, by his excellent Inuentions, gave such an extraordinary Luster; upon every occasion changing the stage, to the admiration of all the Spectators: that, asI must Ingeniously confesse, It was above my apprehension to conceive, so their sacred Majesties, and the rest of the Auditory; It gave so generall a content, thatI presume they never parted from any object , presented in that kind, better please, or more plenally satisfied: But theseI leave to your Iudgements to gesse at; the thing it selfeI propose to your eyes, to censure, which if you Iudge as favourably asI expresse it freely,I shall ever remaine as heretofore </p>
        <closer>Studious of your best opinions.THO.HEYWOOD <signed>THO. HEYWOOD </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000072-004-a"/>
      <div type="prologue" xml:id="ep000072-e100340">
        <pb xml:id="ep000072-004-b"/>
        <head> The <hi>Prologue</hi> to this Play, the first time it was Presented on the Stage;
            <hi>Cupid</hi> discending in a cloude, the Speaker.</head>
        <lg>
          <l>_It was a Custome 'monst the <hi>Romanes</hi>, when</l>
          <l>State_ladies they inuited, or great men,</l>
          <l>As if their doores wer all too base, and vile</l>
          <l>To entertain them; their large Roofes to' untile,</l>
          <l>And their unbounded welcome more to crowne,</l>
          <l>In Artificiall Cloudes to let them downe;</l>
          <l>Their superstitious Love so farre extending,</l>
          <l>Receiving them as gods from heaven discending.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Although wee cannot meete you with like state,</l>
          <l>As entering hither at our publike gate,</l>
          <l>You are as welcome; 'Tis <hi>Love</hi> bids you so:</l>
          <l>And, as their use was, to their ghests to showe</l>
          <l>Their best, and Costliest Iewells (without boast,</l>
          <l>So <hi>Cupid</hi> will) what hee affecteth most,</l>
          <l>His sweete and dearest Mistris; or if ought</l>
          <l>Were more in valuation, or in thought,</l>
          <l>That you should see: Shee is both fresh, and new,</l>
          <l>Then bid her but as welcome, as I, you.</l>
        </lg>
      </div>
      <div type="part" xml:id="ep000072-e100420">
        <head> Her <hi>Majestie</hi> Inviting the <hi>King</hi> to <hi>Denmarke House</hi>, in the
            <hi>Strand</hi>, upon His Birth-day, being <hi>November</hi> the 19. <lb/> This Play
          (bearing from that time) the Title of the <hi>Queenes Masque</hi>, was againe presented
          before Him: <hi>Cupid</hi> speaking the Prologue. </head>
        <lg>
          <l>_VVHo's so un-read, doth not of <hi>Plato</hi> heare,</l>
          <l>His <hi>Annus Magnus</hi>, or his <hi>Vertent</hi> yeare;</l>
          <l>In which the Starres, and Planets, Moone, and Sunne,</l>
          <l>Tyr'd with continuall labour; having runne</l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000072-005-a"/>
          <l>So man Ages long peregrination,</l>
          <l>And returnes fresh and new to It's first station</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>This is that yeere sure; rather this the day,</l>
          <l>Abl to change <hi>November</hi> into <hi>May</hi>:</l>
          <l>This day's in heaven a <hi>Iubylee</hi> of <hi>Ioy</hi>.</l>
          <l>Where <hi>Angels</hi> sing in quires, <hi>Vive la Roy</hi>.</l>
          <l>This is the Royall Birth-day of a King,</l>
          <l>Then men with Angels <hi>Io paean</hi> sing.</l>
          <l/>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l> I'had almost lost my self, when my intent</l>
          <l>Was to tell why I come, and from whom sent:</l>
          <l>From One, to whom I'm but a shadow, Shee</l>
          <l>The very soule of <hi>Amabilitee</hi>.</l>
          <l>One; that without my quiver and my bow,</l>
          <l>Commands the hearts, and eyes , of high and low,</l>
          <l>Whose Name (Inscribed heere) did you but behold,</l>
          <l>'Twould change the sooty Inke, to liquid Gold</l>
          <l>Of fulgent beautie; but so pure a mind,</l>
          <l>As it tinctur'd from Heaven, and so devin'd</l>
          <l>I Love, from Love am sent, but <hi>She</hi> the right: </l>
          <l>Then grace (Great King) the Triumphs, of Loves night</l>
        </lg>
      </div>
      <div type="epilogue" xml:id="ep000072-e100530">
        <head>The Epilogue, spoken by Cupid, pointing to the severall Plannets. </head>
        <lg>
          <l/>
          <l>_NOw Royall Princes, let me turne to you,</l>
          <l>Daigne from <hi>Loves</hi> mouth, to take this nights adieu:</l>
          <l>Thinke all these Planets that on earth heere moove,</l>
          <l>(Shadowes of those Coelestialll ones above)</l>
          <l>Breath on you their best Influences; <hi>Vulcan</hi> hee,</l>
          <l>Shall henceforth take charge of your Armorie.</l>
          <l>
            <hi>Iuno</hi> the Marriage queene, shall blesse your bed:</l>
          <l>The <hi>Sunne</hi> shall take the bright beames from his head,</l>
          <l>To increase your glories lusture: and the <hi>Moone</hi>,</l>
          <l>Attend on ou, to make your Mid-night, noone:</l>
          <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000072-005-b"/>
          <l>And <hi>Mercury</hi> shall roame from shoare to shoare</l>
          <l>Vpoon your errands, proove your happy ranger,</l>
          <l>Home-bred to 'spie, and fore-see forraigne danger:</l>
          <l>
            <hi>Venus</hi> with sweetes and I, with <hi>Love</hi> will charme you;</l>
          <l>And after all these, <hi>Iove</hi> with Power shall arme you.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>I have kept you waking lon, and good night, 'tis late,</l>
          <l>And many Birth-dayes may you Celebrate.</l>
        </lg>
      </div>
      <div type="prologue" xml:id="ep000072-e100570">
        <head> The <hi>Prologue</hi> To the King and Queene, the Second time it was Acted, the same
          Weeke: Spoken by <hi>Cupid</hi>. </head>
        <lg>
          <l>_YEs; sure 'twas heere: where some few houers past,</l>
          <l>The very time that I descended last:</l>
          <l>I, heere it was, I know it by one face,</l>
          <l>To which my Mistris <hi>Psiche</hi> must give place.</l>
          <l>A Presence; that from <hi>Venus</hi> takes all power,</l>
          <l>And make each place shee comes in, Cupids bower.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l/>
          <l>Though in their severall spheares, each Planet ride,</l>
          <l>(With all the gods) to feast mee and my bride</l>
          <l>With <hi>Nectar</hi> and <hi>Ambrosia</hi>, yet, that wast</l>
          <l>Of godly Fare, could not my pallat tast:</l>
          <l>But I must all Caelestiall sweetes forbeare,</l>
          <l>To re-viewe Earthly <hi>Iove</hi>, and <hi>Iuno</hi> heere,</l>
          <l>Whom having seene; Haile to you once againe;</l>
          <l>Long as the spheares continue, may you Reigne</l>
          <l>In Maiestie, In power, in Issue blest,</l>
          <l>Bee all these with your fortunate yeeres Increast;</l>
          <l>Till <hi>Cupid</hi> (ever young) with <hi>Time</hi> grow old,</l>
          <l>And you, this Irone Age, changing to gold,</l>
          <l>(Repur'd by your two vertues) These etheriall,</l>
          <l>May change to brighter Chairs in th' Heavens Imperiall</l>
        </lg>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="ep000072-e100650">
        <pb xml:id="ep000072-006-a"/>
        <head>Dramatis Personae </head>
        <table>
          <row>
            <cell>Apuleus</cell>
            <cell rows="2">
              <hi>The Chorus.</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Midas</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Admetus</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi>King of</hi> Thessaly</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Astioche</cell>
            <cell rows="3">
              <hi>His three Daughters.</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Petrea</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Psiche</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Menetius</cell>
            <cell rows="2">
              <hi>Husbands to</hi> Petrea <hi>and</hi> Astioche</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Zelotes</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Venus.</cell>
            <cell>Rhadamant.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Cupid.</cell>
            <cell>Charon.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Pan.</cell>
            <cell>Cerberus</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Apollo.</cell>
            <cell>Zephirus.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Mercury.</cell>
            <cell>Boreas.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Vulcan.</cell>
            <cell>Furies.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Pluto.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi>Foure</hi> Ciclops.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Proserpine.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi>The</hi> Clowne</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Minos.</cell>
            <cell>Amarillis <hi>a she Swaine.</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Eacus.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi>Foure</hi> Swaines</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div>
    </front>
    <pb xml:id="ep000072-006-b"/>
    <body>
      <head>Loues Mistris. </head>
      <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="ep000072-e100900">
        <head>ACT. I. </head>
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000072-e100910">
          <head>SCENE. I. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000072-e100920">Enter Apuleius, with a paire of Asse eares in his hand. </stage>
          <sp>
            <lg>
              <l>HOw art thou Apuleius transform'd? </l>
              <l>Or else how cam'st thou metamorphis'd first </l>
              <l>Into an Asse? Why Why so dull a beast, </l>
              <l>Of slow, and so obtuse a memory? </l>
              <l>I had a brain aym'd at inscrutable things, </l>
              <l>Beyond the Moone; what was sublunarie, </l>
              <l>Me
                  thought was for my study all too meane; </l>
              <l>Therefore, I therefore was I thus transhap'd: </l>
              <l>That knowing man who keepes not in his bounds, </l>
              <l>But pries into Heavens hidden mysteries </l>
              <l>Further then leave; his dulnesse is increast </l>
              <l>Ceaseth to be a man and so turnes beast: </l>
              <l>And thus I fell, yet by the selfe same power </l>
              <l>That calls all humane wisedome foolishnesse, </l>
              <l>Am once more to my pristine shape restor'd; </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000072-006-b1"/>
              <l>Onely to shew how vaine my ambitions were, </l>
              <l>This follies crest I still about me beare:</l>
              <l>I faine would know the way to <hi>Helicon</hi>,</l>
              <l>Can none heere tell me? Will none silence breake?</l>
              <l>It seemes, these sit to heare then, not to speaker:</l>
              <stage>Enter <hi>Midas</hi>
              </stage>
              <l>Heere's one I hope can tell mee: Reverend father,</l>
              <l>How lies my journey to the <hi>Muses</hi> hill?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
            <l>Follow thy nose.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Ap.</speaker>
            <l>Thou most unreverend groome,</l>
            <l>(I hope my Asses shape is quite shooke off)</l>
            <l>Why in this churlish manner speak'st thou then?</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
            <l>The <hi>Muses</hi>? hang the <hi>Muses</hi>.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Ap.</speaker>
            <l>Can'st thou conduct</l>
            <l>My wandring stepps to <hi>Aganippes</hi> spring?</l>
            <l>To the <hi>Muses</hi> Temple I am travelling,</l>
            <l>And must to them performe a sacrifice.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
            <l>An Asse head of thy owne, thou must performe.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Ap.</speaker>
            <l>If men be growne thus savage, oh you powers, </l>
            <l>Remetamorphise mee into an asse;</l>
            <l>'Tis lesse inglorious, and lesse griefe to live</l>
            <l>A beast amongst wilde beasts, then to see man</l>
            <l>Bruite-like to blemish his creation.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
            <l>I tell the once againe, I know no <hi>Muses</hi>,</l>
            <l>No <hi>Muses</hi> hill, no <hi>Aganippes</hi> spring;</l>
            <l>And which is more, I care for no such toyes.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Ap.</speaker>
            <l>And which is worst, none wise will care for thee;</l>
            <l>Oh griefe, that silver haires should crowne his head,</l>
            <l>By whom the <hi>Muses</hi> are dishonoured;</l>
            <l>Say Idoll, what's thy name?</l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000072-006-b2"/>
          <sp>
            <l>What's that to thee?</l>
            <l>Yet was I sometime King of Phrigia,</l>
            <l>To whom God Baccus was beholding once:</l>
            <l>And therefore bad me aske what I would have,</l>
            <l>It should bee granted; Instantly I begg'd</l>
            <l>That whatsoere I touch'd might turne to Gold;</l>
            <l>At first it pleas'd mee: When I sate to eate,</l>
            <l>I touch'd the Table, and It straight was gold,</l>
            <l>All which I hugg'd; but when I came to carue,</l>
            <l>Even as the dishes, so the meate was gold;</l>
            <l>The liquid wine, but touch'd, was straight congeal'd;</l>
            <l>And had not <hi>Baccus</hi> freed mee from my wish,</l>
            <l>Amid'st my gold I had beene staru'd ere this,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Ap.</speaker>
            <l>Dull covetous foole.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
            <l>The shame of this made mee resigne my state;</l>
            <l>And where before I was a King of men,</l>
            <l>To flie the harshnes of fooles bitter jeasts,</l>
            <l>I made this wooll crowne, and am King of beasts,</l>
            <l>And my name's <hi>Midas</hi>.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Ap.</speaker>
            <l>Then oh King of beasts,</l>
            <l>Be this thy curse; When thy base life's out-worne,</l>
            <l>No sacred Poet name thee but in scorne:</l>
            <l>But wilt thou sit with silence?</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
            <l>Thou prat'st and bablest, what woud'st thou have mee doe?</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Ap.</speaker>
            <l>See'st thou this spheare spangled, with all these starres,</l>
            <l>All these Love-arts; nor shall they part from hence</l>
            <l>With unfeasted eares: My purpose was</l>
            <l>To expose to them the shapes of all those asses,</l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000072-007-a"/>
            <l>With whom my lost soule wandred in a mist, </l>
            <l>Knowing, of them thou art not counted least; </l>
            <l>But first Ile shew a story of mine owne, </l>
            <l>Of Cupids love to Psiche, sit and see't; </l>
            <l>Ile make thee then ingeniously confesse▪ </l>
            <l>Thy treason gainst the Muses majestie; </l>
            <l>Withall, not onely whatsoever mine mine, </l>
            <l>But all true Poets raptures are divine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-midas" xml:id="ep000072-e101170">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Thou hast prevail'd with mee, by Pan Ile stay; </l>
              <l>But take heede Poet that your rimes be sound, </l>
              <l>Else with thine owne Asse eares thou shalt be crown'd. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e101220">
            <speaker>Ap. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Wee two contend; Art heere, there Ignorance: </l>
              <l>Bee you the Iudges, wee inuite you all </l>
              <l>Vnto this banquet Accademicall. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000072-e101270">Exeunt. </stage>
        </div>
        <div type="scene">
          <stage xml:id="ep000072-e101280">Recorders. Enter Admetus, Menetius, Zelotis, Astioche, Petrea, Psiche. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000072-admetus" xml:id="ep000072-e101290">
            <speaker>Ad. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>You Peeres and Daughters to th' Arcadian King, </l>
              <l>Wee have past the great'st part of our pilgrimage; </l>
              <l>Listen, oh listen, for these sounds that guild </l>
              <l>The aires light wings, fanning through all our eares </l>
              <l>Immortall tunes; tell us we are ariv'd </l>
              <l>At sacred Delphos; see the burnish'd Spires </l>
              <l>Advance themselves to welcome our approach; </l>
              <l>The Temple gates stand ope, and that great Deitie </l>
              <l>Whose tongue speakes nothing lesse then Oracle, </l>
              <l>Attended by his Sibells, daines to appeare </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage>Enter Apollo. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000072-unassigned" xml:id="ep000072-e101450">
            <speaker>knees </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Oh teach our knees with a most reverent touch </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000072-007-b"/>
              <l>To kisse this hallowed earth. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-zelotes" xml:id="ep000072-e101490">
            <speaker>Zelo. </speaker>
            <p>Ladies kneele downe. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-astioche" xml:id="ep000072-e101510">
            <speaker>Astio. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>And sir relate to faire Latonaes Sonne </l>
              <l>Why this religious voyage was attempted. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-admetus" xml:id="ep000072-e101550">
            <speaker>Ad. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Daughters I shall: </l>
              <l>Sacred Apollo, god of Archerie, </l>
              <l>Of Arts, of Phisicke, and of Poetrie▪ </l>
              <l>
                <gap extent="1" n="7-b-0520" unit="lines"/>
              </l>
              <l>Like curled flames, hurling a most divine </l>
              <l>And dazling splendor on these lesser fires, </l>
              <l>Which from thy guilt beames, when thy Carre retires, </l>
              <l>Kindle those tapers that lend eyes to night: </l>
              <l>Oh thou that art the landlord of all light; </l>
              <l>Bridegroome to morning, dayes eternall King, </l>
              <l>To whom Nine Muses in a sacred ring, </l>
              <l>In dances sphericall, trip hand in hand, </l>
              <l>Whilst thy well-stringed Harpe their feet command; </l>
              <l>Great Delphian Priest, wee to adore thy name </l>
              <l>Have burnt fat thighs of Bulls in hallowed flame, </l>
              <l>Whose savor wrap'd in clowds of smoake and fire, </l>
              <l>To thy Starre-spangled pallace durst aspire; </l>
              <l>Tell us who shall untie the Virgin zone </l>
              <l>Of the white-handed Psiche thee alone </l>
              <l>Of three most faire, is most unfortunate, </l>
              <l>All love, but none her love will celebrate </l>
              <l>With nuptiall rights; what must of her betide </l>
              <l>Dread Phebus tell, to whom shall thee be. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e101810">
            <speaker>Apol. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Cloath Psiche in a mourning weede, </l>
              <l>Then leade and leave her on a hill, </l>
              <l>Where Venus Doves their young ones feede, </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000072-008-a"/>
              <l>Her husband not of Humane race; </l>
              <l>But one, whose flaming sight doth kill, </l>
              <l>And yet wants eyes; his serpents face </l>
              <l>If shee behold, shee must see hell; </l>
              <l>And yet by some notorious deede, </l>
              <l>Obtaine a Patent from that place </l>
              <l>Never to die: Psiche farewell, </l>
              <l>Much joy'd, much greev'd; unclaspe that spell. </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="ep000072-e101940">Ex. Apollo. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-admetus" xml:id="ep000072-e101950">
            <speaker>Ad. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Much griev'd, and yet much joy'd, poore girle, I feare </l>
              <l>The scale of griefe will weigh downe that of cheere. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-menetius" xml:id="ep000072-e101990">
            <speaker>Mene. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Shee must see hell; and yet shee neere shall die; </l>
              <l>True, for hells torments live eternally. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-astioche" xml:id="ep000072-e102030">
            <speaker>Asti. </speaker>
            <p>But father, no tongue shall her joyes expresse. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-petraea" xml:id="ep000072-e102050">
            <speaker>Petre. </speaker>
            <p>Phebus, thy words leave us all comfortlesse. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e102070">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <p>I must espouse a serpent, that's my hell. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-zelotes" xml:id="ep000072-e102090">
            <speaker>Zelo. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>But since you never shall behold his face, </l>
              <l>Your torments cannot bee too horrible. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-menetius" xml:id="ep000072-e102130">
            <speaker>Mene. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Is't possible, by deeds impossible </l>
              <l>To attaine the Crowne of immortality: </l>
              <l>It cannot bee; The mocking Phoebus leaves us, </l>
              <l>Alwayes in clowds of darkenesse to deceive us. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-admetus" xml:id="ep000072-e102190">
            <speaker>Ad. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Stay thy prophane tongue, least deserued wrath </l>
              <l>Strike thee with death from his revengefull spheare: </l>
              <l>Thou must be cloth'd in mourning, so thou art, </l>
              <l>A mourning habite, and a thought-sick heart; </l>
              <l>Thou must be left alone on Venus hill; </l>
              <l>The destinies decree, wee must fulfill: </l>
              <l>Thy husband must want sight, and yet have eyes </l>
              <l>That flame, and kill; oh leave these misteries </l>
              <l>Vntill the Gods reveale them; come, let's hence: </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000072-008-b"/>
              <l>Change your Arcadian tunes to Lidian sounds, </l>
              <l>Sad notes are sweetest, where deepe woe confounds. </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="ep000072-e102320">Exeunt omnes. </stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000072-e102330">Recorders. Enter Venus. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000072-venus" xml:id="ep000072-e102340">
            <speaker>Ven. </speaker>
            <p>Cupid my sonne, where's hee? </p>
            <stage xml:id="ep000072-e102360">Within. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e102370">
            <speaker>Cup. </speaker>
            <p>Anon-forsooth. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-venus" xml:id="ep000072-e102390">
            <speaker>Ven. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Ile gather rods of roses, if you mock mee </l>
              <l>With your anon-forsooth. </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="ep000072-e102430">Within. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e102440">
            <speaker>Cup. </speaker>
            <p>Anon-forsooth. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-venus" xml:id="ep000072-e102460">
            <speaker>Ven. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Shall I be still thus vext? still when my blood </l>
              <l>Boyles in the fire of anger, then this ape </l>
              <l>With purpose frets mee.— Boy. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000072-e102510">Enter Cupid. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e102520">
            <speaker>Cup. </speaker>
            <p>Anon-forsooth. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-venus" xml:id="ep000072-e102540">
            <speaker>Ven. </speaker>
            <p>Will Iuno come, or Ceres? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e102560">
            <speaker>Cup. </speaker>
            <p>Iuno lay lolling in my Vncles lapp. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-venus" xml:id="ep000072-e102580">
            <speaker>Ven. </speaker>
            <p>Which Vncle? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e102600">
            <speaker>Cup. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Vncle Iove: I laught out-right </l>
              <l>To see how (wanton-like) with both her armes </l>
              <l>Shee clung about his necke; gave him ten kisses, </l>
              <l>Toy'd with his locks, look'd babies in his eyes, </l>
              <l>And swore shee would not watch him when hee went </l>
              <l>Amongst his wenches, if hee'd turne away </l>
              <l>His sawcie page, the smooth-fac'd Ganimed; </l>
              <l>The boy by chance upon her fan had spilt </l>
              <l>A cup of Nectar; oh how Iuno swore: </l>
              <l>I told my Aunt I'de give her a new fan, </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000072-009-a"/>
              <l>To let Ioves page be Cupids seruing-man. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-venus" xml:id="ep000072-e102730">
            <speaker>Ven. </speaker>
            <p>What's this to Venus message, what said Iuno? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e102750">
            <speaker>Cu. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>I ask'd her when shee'd come, and in good sooth, </l>
              <l>shee answered nothing but anon-forsooth. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-venus" xml:id="ep000072-e102790">
            <speaker>Ven. </speaker>
            <p>And where was Ceres, what did shee replie? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e102810">
            <speaker>Cu. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Ceres was binding garlands for God Pan, </l>
              <l>Of Blew-bottles, and yellow pissabeds </l>
              <l>That grew amongst the Wheate, with which she crown'd </l>
              <l>His forked browes, and woed him with his horne </l>
              <l>To rouze the skipping Satirs, to goe hunt </l>
              <l>A heard of swine that rooted up her corne: </l>
              <l>I ask'd her when shee'd come, and in good sooth </l>
              <l>Shee sent me packing with anon forsooth. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-venus" xml:id="ep000072-e102910">
            <speaker>Ven. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>I sent for Pan, and for Apollo too, </l>
              <l>What news from them? </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e102950">
            <speaker>Cu. </speaker>
            <p>They said they would bee heere immediately. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000072-e102970">Enter Pan, and Apollo. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e102980">
            <speaker>Apo. </speaker>
            <p>Why in such haste hath Venus sent for us? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-venus" xml:id="ep000072-e103000">
            <speaker>Ven. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>I sent for Iuno, and for Ceres too, </l>
              <l>But they'le not come. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-pan" xml:id="ep000072-e103040">
            <speaker>Pan. </speaker>
            <p>Well, what's the news with you? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-venus" xml:id="ep000072-e103060">
            <speaker>Ven. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Have you not heard how Venus is contemn'd? </l>
              <l>Her Temples gaz'd at, but not troad upon, </l>
              <l>Her stately hangings, and her pillowes torne; </l>
              <l>Those rosie garlands that her statues crown'd, </l>
              <l>Are wither'd, or else trampled on the ground; </l>
              <l>Those troopes that flock'd to Paphos to adore mee, </l>
              <l>Shun Paphos now, and scornefully abhorre mee. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000072-009-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000072-unassigned" xml:id="ep000072-e103150">
            <speaker>Pan. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>That's strange, for all beards up to th eares in love; </l>
              <l>Boyes without beards get boyes, and girles beare girles, </l>
              <l>Fine little rattle-babies, scarce thus high, </l>
              <l>Are now call'd wives; If long this hot world stand, </l>
              <l>Wee shall have all the earth turne Pigmy-land. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-venus" xml:id="ep000072-e103220">
            <speaker>Ven. </speaker>
            <p>All honour Love, but none adore Loves Queene. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e103240">
            <speaker>Apol. </speaker>
            <p>The injury is great; but from whence springs it? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-venus" xml:id="ep000072-e103260">
            <speaker>Ven. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>From Psiche daughter to the Arcadian King; </l>
              <l>They call her Queene of Love, will know no other, </l>
              <l>And sweare my Sonne shall kneele and call her mother. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e103310">
            <speaker>Cup. </speaker>
            <p>But Cupid sweares to make the jacks forsworne. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e103330">
            <speaker>Apol. </speaker>
            <p>Will Citharea swallow this disgrace? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-unassigned" xml:id="ep000072-e103350">
            <speaker>Pan. </speaker>
            <p>What shall Pan doe in this? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-venus" xml:id="ep000072-e103370">
            <speaker>Ven. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Lend me your ayds: </l>
              <l>If you meete Psiche, charge young Mercury </l>
              <l>To send mee to her, or imprison her </l>
              <l>Till you have sent mee word. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e103430">
            <speaker>Apol. </speaker>
            <p>If this be all, Venus shall have her wish. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-unassigned" xml:id="ep000072-e103450">
            <speaker>Pan. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Pan by his vpright hornes and beard doth sweare </l>
              <l>To hunt out Psiche; but if I doe this, </l>
              <l>What will sweete Venus give mee? </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-venus" xml:id="ep000072-e103500">
            <speaker>Ven. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>A sweete kisse; </l>
              <l>And Phebus shall have one, Cupid another, </l>
              <l>Vpon condition they will right those wrongs </l>
              <l>Which Psiche in her great pride throwes on mee: </l>
              <l>Draw from thy quiver a dull leaden shaft, </l>
              <l>And stricke it through her bosome to her heart; </l>
              <l>Make her in Love, but let her proud eyes doate </l>
              <l>On some ill-shapen drudge, some ugly foole: </l>
              <l>Doe this; Ile weave for thee a Coronet </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000072-010-a"/>
              <l>Of Roses, mixt with Berenices haire; </l>
              <l>And give thee my best charriot, and my Doves </l>
              <l>To hunt with on the earth; or in the ayre; </l>
              <l>Wilt thou doe this my boy? </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e103650">
            <speaker>Cup. </speaker>
            <p>I will forsooth. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-venus" xml:id="ep000072-e103670">
            <speaker>Ven. </speaker>
            <p>Nay doe not mock mee, wilt thou? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e103690">
            <speaker>Cup. </speaker>
            <p>Yes indeede, Indeede I will forsooth. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-venus" xml:id="ep000072-e103710">
            <speaker>Ven. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Sweete lad adue then: </l>
              <l>Apollo, Pan, revenge poore Venus wrongs, </l>
              <l>Whilst I unyoke my siluer
                  coloured teame, </l>
              <l>To wanton on the bosome of yon streame. </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="ep000072-e103770">Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e103780">
            <speaker>Apol. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Now shee hath call'd me downe unto the earth, </l>
              <l>Ile try what pastimes dwell amongst the swaines. </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="ep000072-e103820">Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-pan" xml:id="ep000072-e103830">
            <speaker>Pan. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>And with my Satires I will have some sport </l>
              <l>Heere in the Arcadian vallyes. </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="ep000072-e103870">Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e103880">
            <speaker>Cup. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Shall Psiches beautious eyes gaze on base love? </l>
              <l>Noe, let my Mother storme, and chafe and lower, </l>
              <l>Shee shall be none but Cupids Paramoure: </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="ep000072-e103930">Enter Zephirus. </stage>
            <lg>
              <l>Ho Zephirus,—— how now thou puffing slave, </l>
              <l>Art thou growne proud, thou swell'st so? Gentle winde, </l>
              <l>Clap on thy smoothest feathers, sleekest wings, </l>
              <l>And mount thee to the top of yonder rocke, </l>
              <l>There shalt thou find anon, a forlorne maide, </l>
              <l>Conuey her gently downe into the vaile </l>
              <l>That borders on my bower; see this perform'd, </l>
              <l>And I will cloath thee in a grasse-greene roabe, </l>
              <l>Spotted with Dasies, Pincks, and Marigolds; </l>
              <l>Ile play the thiefe in Floraes treasurie, </l>
              <l>To make all eyes in love with Zephirus; </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000072-010-b"/>
              <l>Flie hence, doe this, and henceforth be thou King </l>
              <l>Of all the Windes, and father of the Spring. </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="ep000072-e104080">Exeunt. </stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000072-e104090">Enter Admetus, Menetius, Zelotis, Astioche, Petrea, Psiche. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000072-admetus" xml:id="ep000072-e104100">
            <speaker>Ad. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Behold the foote of that unhappy rocke, </l>
              <l>Vpon whose frozen top, by Phebus doome, </l>
              <l>Thou must abide thy most sinister hap. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-astioche" xml:id="ep000072-e104150">
            <speaker>Astio. </speaker>
            <p>Deare sister Psiche. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e104170">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Peace Astioche, </l>
              <l>Petrea, Father: you should all have mourn'd </l>
              <l>When the mad spirits of the multitude </l>
              <l>Kneel'd downe, and call'd mee Venus, then have wept, </l>
              <l>When Cithareas Altars were left bare, </l>
              <l>And I was call'd a goddesse; when these teares, </l>
              <l>Whose reeking makes my funerall lights burne dimme, </l>
              <l>Might have quench'd Venus wrath; but leave mee now </l>
              <l>To fight with death, or meete worse misery. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-menetius" xml:id="ep000072-e104280">
            <speaker>Mene. </speaker>
            <p>But lurkes that serpent in this fatall rocke? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-petraea" xml:id="ep000072-e104300">
            <speaker>Pet. </speaker>
            <p>So said Apollo. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-zelotes" xml:id="ep000072-e104320">
            <speaker>Zelo. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Then Menetius, </l>
              <l>Wee will conduct faire Psiche to the cave, </l>
              <l>And rip the monsters intrailes with our swords. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e104370">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Forbeare all force, I will ascend alone; </l>
              <l>Phebus will be displeas'd; Alone said hee, </l>
              <l>Distressed Psiche shall climbe up yon hill. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-admetus" xml:id="ep000072-e104420">
            <speaker>Ad. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>The way is dangerous, thou wilt loose thy selfe </l>
              <l>Without a guide. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000072-010-b1"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Psi.</speaker>
            <l>Death must my conduct bee,</l>
            <l>See where the pale hagge stands; vaine world adue;</l>
            <l>I am his bride, hee waites for none of you.</l>
          </sp>
          <stage>Shee climbes up the Rocke.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Ad.</speaker>
            <l>What paines the poore girle takes, see how shee strives</l>
            <l>Against the swelling bosome of the hill.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Mene.</speaker>
            <l>See the kind brambles, as enamor'd of her,</l>
            <l>Circle her beautie in her catching armes,</l>
            <l>Woeing her to come back; as who should say,</l>
            <l>Thou run'st too fast to death, sweete <hi>Psiche</hi> stay.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Ad.</speaker>
            <l>But all in vaine, shee now hath climb'd the Rock,</l>
            <l>And wafts her hand, doe you the like to her,</l>
            <l>Whose timelesse death prepares my sepulchre.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Petre.</speaker>
            <l>Sister with courage meete thy destinie,</l>
            <l>To morrow, if thou liu'st, wee'le visite thee.</l>
          </sp>
          <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
          <stage>Enter <hi>Cupid</hi> and <hi>Zephirus</hi>.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Cup.</speaker>
            <l>Flie <hi>Zephirus</hi>, on top of yonder mount</l>
            <l>My faire Love sits; on thy soft swelling wings</l>
            <l>Let <hi>Psiche</hi> ride — you Voyces that atend mee,</l>
            <stage>Ex. <hi>Zep</hi>.</stage>
            <l>Dance in the aire like wantons, to intice</l>
            <l>My love to dwell in <hi>Cupids</hi> Paradice:</l>
            <l>Musicke with ravishing tones inchant her eares;</l>
            <l>A banquet there: Shee that doth <hi>Cupid</hi> wed,</l>
            <l>Thus shall shee live, and thus be honoured.</l>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div type="scene">
          <stage>Enter <hi>Zephirus</hi> and takes <hi>Psiche</hi> from the Rocke, and Exit with her
            in his armes. A Banquet brought in.</stage>
          <pb xml:id="ep000072-010-b2"/>
          <stage>Enter <hi>Zephirus</hi> with <hi>Psiche</hi>, and places her at the Banquet, and
            Exit.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Psi.</speaker>
            <l>Where am I now? For through the cheerefull aire</l>
            <l>Hither I have beene brought, on unseene wings;</l>
            <l>What wonderous place is this? No serpent sure</l>
            <l>Lurkes in this pleasant bowre: my eare drinks sounds</l>
            <l>Of heaven-tun'd Instruments; I see no creature,</l>
            <l>And yet me thought soft fingers set me downe,</l>
            <l>And I am forc'd by sweete compulsion,</l>
            <stage>A Banquet first plaine, and presently set one with all Delicates.</stage>
            <l>To bee the onely guest of this faire board,</l>
            <l>Which emptie, is as soone new furnished;</l>
            <l>I faine would touch these sweetes, but feare to taste them.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Eccho.</speaker>
            <l>Taste them.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>2</speaker>
            <l>Taste them.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>3</speaker>
            <l>Taste them.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Psi.</speaker>
            <l>What voice is that? I dare no longer sit.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Eccho.</speaker>
            <l>Sit.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>2</speaker>
            <l>Sit.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>3</speaker>
            <l>Sit.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Psi.</speaker>
            <l>Who mock's mee? Are you devills, or are you gods.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Eccho.</speaker>
            <l>Gods.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>2</speaker>
            <l>Gods</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>3</speaker>
            <l>Gods</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Psi.</speaker>
            <l>The gods will doe no harme.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Eccho.</speaker>
            <l>No harme.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>2</speaker>
            <l>No harme.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>3</speaker>
            <l>No harme.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Psi.</speaker>
            <l>
              <hi>Psiche</hi> bee bold, and taste this heavenly foode.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Eccho.</speaker>
            <l>Ha ha ha. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>2</speaker>
            <l>Ha ha ha. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>3</speaker>
            <l>Ha ha ha.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Psi.</speaker>
            <l>These are no <hi>Ecchoes</hi>, for they shift their place,</l>
            <l>Nor catch they my last words as <hi>Ecchoes</hi> doe:</l>
            <l>For when I would have fed, they mock'd my pride,</l>
            <l>They laught aloud at my presumption:</l>
            <l>No, these are Fury-Elues, and will torment mee,</l>
            <stage>Enter <hi>Zephirus</hi> with Drinke.</stage>
            <pb xml:id="ep000072-011-a"/>
            <lg>
              <l>If thus I talke to them,— Who fills this wine, </l>
              <l>And tempts my eye with it? as who should say, </l>
              <l>Drinke Psiche. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-eccho" xml:id="ep000072-e104500">
            <speaker>Eccho. </speaker>
            <p>Drinke Psiche. 2. Drinke Psiche. 3. Drinke Psiche, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e104520">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Ile taste no drop of this inchanted wine: </l>
              <l>Faine from this magick circle would I rise, </l>
              <l>Yet dare not; oh let Psiche see your eyes, </l>
              <l>Or rid me hence, and set my feares in peace. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-eccho" xml:id="ep000072-e104580">
            <speaker>Ecch. </speaker>
            <p>Peace. 2. Peace. 3. Peace. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000072-e104600">Enter Cupid. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e104610">
            <speaker>Cup. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>How lovely is my Psiche; earth's too base </l>
              <l>To be possest of her Celestiall forme: </l>
              <l>My Mother hates her; for the gods I feare </l>
              <l>Would banish her from earth, my Love being there; </l>
              <l>And therefore shall shee live in Cupids Bower, </l>
              <l>For shee deserves to bee Loves Paramoure: </l>
              <l>Oh how my faire eyes wound mee; by this kisse, </l>
              <l>And this white hand. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e104710">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Oh mee! what voice is this </l>
              <l>I feele? besides, soft fingers, and a ring. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e104750">
            <speaker>Cup. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Long white fingers; soft white hand, </l>
              <l>Ring and all at thy command. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e104790">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <p>Is this my husband then? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e104810">
            <speaker>Cup. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Ho Zephirus, </l>
              <l>Remove hence these Ambrosian dishes straight. </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="ep000072-e104850">Zephirus takes off the Banquet. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e104860">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>My father much mistook the Oracle; </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000072-011-b"/>
              <l>To this sweete voice, could I enjoy the sight, </l>
              <l>I should my selfe then stile Queene of delight. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e104910">
            <speaker>Cup. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Pleasure shall bee thy lackie; wilt thou hunt, </l>
              <l>Then in an ayerie charriot drawne by birds, </l>
              <l>On the winds downie backe my love shall ride; </l>
              <l>Mild Zephirus shall be thy Waggoner; </l>
              <l>Who if the heate offend, his silver wings </l>
              <l>Shall fan coole ayre upon thee, yet my love, </l>
              <l>If thou commit'st one sinne, thou art not mine. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e105000">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <p>Name it, and Ile avoid it for your sake. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e105020">
            <speaker>Cu. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Thy mourning sisters shortly will returne, </l>
              <l>And seeke thee on the rocke from whence thou cam'st, </l>
              <l>But shun their sight and speech; Psiche doe this, </l>
              <l>Thou rob'st mee else of Love, thy selfe of blisse. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e105080">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Not speake nor see my sisters; oh what pleasure </l>
              <l>Can Psiche take, lock't in a golden Iayle? </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e105120">
            <speaker>Cup. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Runne not unto thy ruine gentle love; </l>
              <l>Yet if thou needs wilt see and speake with them, </l>
              <l>Command my seruant Zephirus to bring them </l>
              <l>From top of yonder rocke into this vaile; </l>
              <l>But if they make inquiry who I am, </l>
              <l>Fill both their laps with gold, and send them gon, </l>
              <l>Besides I woe thee by this nuptiall kisse, </l>
              <l>Doe not perswade me to disclose my shape, </l>
              <l>Attempting that, thou loosest this high state; </l>
              <l>I then must leave thee, thou live desolate. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e105240">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <p>In all these things, I will obey my love. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e105260">
            <speaker>Cup. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Then Psiche, in thine unseene husbands hand </l>
              <l>Claspe thy white fingers; Ile now crowne thy bed </l>
              <l>With the sweete spoiles of thy lost Maiden-head. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000072-e105310">Exeunt. </stage>
        </div>
        <div type="scene">
          <stage>Enter <hi>Apuleius</hi> and <hi>Midas</hi>.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Mid.</speaker>
            <l>Hand off, let goe my sheepe-hooke, Ile not stay,</l>
            <l>Ile hang my selfe, ere Ile see out thy Play:</l>
            <l>Call you this Poetry?</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Ap.</speaker>
            <l>If this displease thee <hi>Midas</hi>, then Ile shew thee</l>
            <l>Ere I proceede with <hi>Cupid</hi> and his Love,</l>
            <l>What kind of people I commerst withall</l>
            <l>In my transhape.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
            <l>That's when thou wert an Asse.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Ap.</speaker>
            <l>The very same.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Mi</speaker>
            <l>Yes, that I faine would see.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Ap.</speaker>
            <l>Sit then and view thine owne infirmitie.</l>
          </sp>
          <stage>A Dance. Enter a Proud Asse with eares.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
            <l>What fellowes that?</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Ap.</speaker>
            <l>A selfe-will'd insolent foole,</l>
            <l>Who spights at those above him, and those beneath</l>
            <l>Despiseth, and his equalls jets upon;</l>
            <l>Rich in his owne conceit, in judgement poore,</l>
            <l>Still carping, tho 'a coxcombe, and may passe,</l>
            <l>As these dayes goe, for a proud arogant Asse.</l>
          </sp>
          <stage>Dance. Enter a Prodigall Asse.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Mid.</speaker>
            <l>I this I like: What fellowes that?</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Ad.</speaker>
            <l>A fellow hee,</l>
            <l>Who riots that, which most penuriously</l>
            <l>His father hoorded, in drabs, drinke and play;</l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000072-011-b2"/>
            <l>Wearing fantastick habitts, and gay clothes,</l>
            <l>Till hee hath quite exhausted all his gold,</l>
            <l>And for a Prodigall Asse may bee enroul'd.</l>
          </sp>
          <stage>Dance. Enter a Drunken Asse.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
            <l>This gives me good content - What's hee?</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Ap.</speaker>
            <l>A pot-companion, brother to the glasse,</l>
            <l>That roares in's cupps, indeede a drunken Asse.</l>
          </sp>
          <stage>Dance. Enter an Usurer.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
            <l>He lookes like a good fellow — Now that gray-beard?</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Ap.</speaker>
            <l>One that doth pinch his belly in his life,</l>
            <l>And starue his owne guts to make others feede;</l>
            <l>Patcheth his owne clothes to make others proud,</l>
            <l>And for a covetous Asse may be alow'd.</l>
          </sp>
          <stage>Dance. A young Gentle-Woman.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
            <l>But so did never Midas - Now, that Minks.</l>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Ap.</speaker>
            <l>Her mothers darling shee, borne to good meanes;</l>
            <l>In love with all shee sees, yet truely, none;</l>
            <l>Who when great Heires are proffered, trifles them;</l>
            <l>And in the end, when with none else shee can,</l>
            <l>Shee marries with her fathers seruing-man:</l>
            <l>And that is a right shee-Asse.</l>
          </sp>
          <stage>Dance. An Ignorant Asse.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
            <l>What Reverend persons that of all the other?</l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000072-012-a"/>
            <l>I like him best. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e105330">
            <speaker>Ap. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>That Midas, is thy brother, </l>
              <l>A piece of mooving earth, illiterate, dull; </l>
              <l>Who having in himselfe naught commendable, </l>
              <l>Enuies what's good in others; and yet dare </l>
              <l>In his owne impudence, with Arts compare: </l>
              <l>A blocke, a stone, yet learning hee'le revile, </l>
              <l>And a dull Ignorant Asse wee will him stile. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-midas" xml:id="ep000072-e105420">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>But where's your Poet Asse among all these? </p>
            <stage xml:id="ep000072-e105440">Dance and Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e105450">
            <speaker>Ap. </speaker>
            <p>Ther's no such creature. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-midas" xml:id="ep000072-e105470">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Then what call'st thou those </l>
              <l>That let not men lie quiet in their graves, </l>
              <l>But hant their ghosts with ballatts, and bal'd rimes? </l>
              <l>Doe they not teach the very feinds in hill </l>
              <l>Speake in blanke verse; doe wee not daily see </l>
              <l>Every dull-witted Asse spit Poetrie: </l>
              <l>And for thy Scene; thou bring'st heere on the stage </l>
              <l>A young greene-sicknesse baggage to run after </l>
              <l>A little ape-fac'd boy thou tearm'st a god; </l>
              <l>Is not this most absur'd? </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e105590">
            <speaker>Ap. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Mis-understanding foole, thus much conceive, </l>
              <l>Psiche is Anima, Psiche is the Soule, </l>
              <l>The Soule a Virgin, longs to be a bride, </l>
              <l>The soule's Immortall, whom then can shee wooe </l>
              <l>But Heaven? whom wed, but Immortality: </l>
              <l>Oh blame not Psiche then, if mad with rage, </l>
              <l>Shee long for this so divine marriage. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-midas" xml:id="ep000072-e105680">
            <speaker>Mid. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>But tell mee then, why should Apollo say, </l>
              <l>All love her, and yet none will marry her. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000072-012-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e105720">
            <speaker>Ap. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>All love faire Psiche, all cast amorous eyes </l>
              <l>On the soules beautie, but who is't will wed her? </l>
              <l>None with the foule will leade so strict a life </l>
              <l>As heaven enjoynes, with such a blessed wife. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-midas" xml:id="ep000072-e105780">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Thou promp'st my understanding pretty well; </l>
              <l>But why should Venus being Queene of Love, </l>
              <l>Wish her sonne Cupid to enamour her </l>
              <l>On some base groome mis-shapen, and deform'd? </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e105840">
            <speaker>Ap. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>By Venus heere, is meant untemperate lust; </l>
              <l>Lust woes her sonne Desire, to inflame the soule </l>
              <l>With some base groome, that's to some ugly sinne; </l>
              <l>Desire is good and ill; the evill sweares </l>
              <l>To obay his mother Venus, and vexe Psiche: </l>
              <l>But Cupid representing true desire, </l>
              <l>Doates on the Soules sweete beauty, sends his seruant </l>
              <l>Zephirus; In whom, Celestiall pleasur's meant, </l>
              <l>To entice his love, the Soule, to his chast bed, </l>
              <l>Giving her heaven for her lost maiden-head. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-midas" xml:id="ep000072-e105960">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Onely one riddle more, and I have done; </l>
              <l>Why did the poore girle Psiche take such paines? </l>
              <l>What scrambling shift shee made to climbe the mountaine, </l>
              <l>And crawle through brakes and briers to get a husband. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e106020">
            <speaker>Ap. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>This shewes how many strong adversities, </l>
              <l>Crosses, Pricks, Thornes, and stings of conscience, </l>
              <l>Would throw the ambitious soule affecting heaven, </l>
              <l>Into dispaire, and fainting diffidence, </l>
              <l>Which Psiche must passe through; the Soule must flie </l>
              <l>Through thousand letts, to seeke eternitie. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-midas" xml:id="ep000072-e106100">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Thou hast made this somewhat plaine. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e106120">
            <speaker>Ap. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Kind Gentlemen, </l>
            </lg>
            <pb xml:id="ep000072-012-b1"/>
            <l>Winke at our strife, you may in pardoning this,</l>
            <l>Count this our talke a meere Parentesis.</l>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="act">
        <head>ACT. II.</head>
        <div n="1" type="scene">
          <head>SCENE. I.</head>
          <q type="ana">
            <stage>Enter <hi>Psiche</hi>, <hi>Astioche</hi>, and <hi>Petrea</hi>.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Psi.</speaker>
              <l>_WElcome deare sisters; with the breath of Love,</l>
              <l>Poore <hi>Psiche</hi> gives kind welcome to you both:</l>
              <l>Oh tell me then by what auspitious guide,</l>
              <l>You came conducted to this sacred place?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asti.</speaker>
              <l>Sister you shall: when many a weary step</l>
              <l>Had brought us to the top of yonder rocke,</l>
              <l>Mild <hi>Zephirus</hi> embrac'd us in his armes,</l>
              <l>And in a cloude of rich and strong perfumes,</l>
              <l>Brought's unto the skirts of this greene meade.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Psi.</speaker>
              <l>And happily ariv'd: Nature and Art</l>
              <l>Have strove to make this dale their treasurie;</l>
              <l>Windes flie on <hi>Psiches</hi> errands; shapes unseene</l>
              <l>Are my attendants, and to make mee sport,</l>
              <l>Will dance like nimble Ecchoes in the ayre,</l>
              <l>And mocke mee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Eccho.</speaker>
              <l>Mock me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>2.</speaker>
              <l>Mock me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>3.</speaker>
              <l>Mock me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Psi.</speaker>
              <l>Sisters, how like you this?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Eccho.</speaker>
              <l>This, ha ha ha. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>2.</speaker>
              <l>This, ha ha ha. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>3.</speaker>
              <l>This, ha ha ha. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Petre.</speaker>
              <l>They mock us, will they doe no harme to us?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Psi.</speaker>
              <l>Oh no.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Eccho.</speaker>
              <l>No. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>2.</speaker>
              <l>No. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>3.</speaker>
              <l>No. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000072-012-b2"/>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Psi.</speaker>
              <l>Bablers, be silent.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Eccho.</speaker>
              <l>Silent.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>2.</speaker>
              <l>Silent.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>3.</speaker>
              <l>Silent.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Psi.</speaker>
              <l>Or Ile punish you;</l>
              <l>And let me heare some musicke —Loud - And still.</l>
              <stage>Loude Musicke, and still Musicke.</stage>
              <l>Tell mee, how like you this?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asti.</speaker>
              <l>It flies the reach of Admiration.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Petr.</speaker>
              <l>But let us see the shapes of them that play,</l>
              <l>What are they, speake? or what's your husbands name?</l>
              <l>Let's know our brother, that wee may relate</l>
              <l>To th' King our father your high honour'd state.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Psi.</speaker>
              <l>My husband, sister, is now rid from home.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asti.</speaker>
              <l>Why, say he bee; I hope you know his name;</l>
              <l>Wee'le ransacke all the Pallace but wee'le find him:</l>
              <l>Is your sweete-heart so proud, hee'le not be seene?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Petr.</speaker>
              <l>Where is hee Psiche?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Psi.</speaker>
              <l>Trust mee, hee's from home.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asti.</speaker>
              <l>Let's see his Picture then?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Psi.</speaker>
              <l>Lasse I have none.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Petr.</speaker>
              <l>Describe his person.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Psi.</speaker>
              <l>I must shift them hence,</l>
              <l>My tongue will else breede my confusion.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asti.</speaker>
              <l>Nay sister, when?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Petr</speaker>
              <l>When sister will it bee?</l>
            </sp>
          </q>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Psi.</speaker>
            <q type="ana">
              <l>How should I give him shape I never saw?</l>
              <l>Hee's a faire lovely youth, upon each cheeke,</l>
              <l>Smiles lie in cheerefull dimples; on his brow</l>
              <l>Sits Love and Majestie in glorious pride;</l>
              <l>His eyes such beauty in their circles hold,</l>
              <l>That walking in the night, I have thought them starres:</l>
            </q>
            <pb xml:id="ep000072-013-a"/>
            <l>Long flaxen curled tresses crowne his head. </l>
            <l>Come, come, you shall not be enamored </l>
            <l>On my faire husband; this for all suffice, </l>
            <l>Hee's young and rich. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-astioche" xml:id="ep000072-e106190">
            <speaker>Asti. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Oh how my blood doth rise </l>
              <l>In enuy of her high felicitie; speake, what's his name? </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e106230">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <p>Home, Home; more musicke there, I must to rest: </p>
            <stage xml:id="ep000072-e106250">Recorders. Enter Zephirus with baggs. </stage>
            <lg>
              <l>Ho Zephirus, come foorth, and bring mee brim-full baggs of gold: </l>
              <l>Hold up your lapps; tho'them you cannot see </l>
              <l>That bring this gold, this larges take from mee; </l>
              <l>Adieu, adeiu: my duty to the King, </l>
              <l>I needs must stop mine eares when Syrens sing. </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="ep000072-e106320">Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-petraea" xml:id="ep000072-e106330">
            <speaker>Petr. </speaker>
            <p>Astioche. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-astioche" xml:id="ep000072-e106350">
            <speaker>Asti. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Petrea, oh, I am mad to note her pride; </l>
              <l>Her husband is no serpent as 'twas said, </l>
              <l>And false Apollo sung; hee is some god, </l>
              <l>And this his Temple, for no mortall hand </l>
              <l>Hath laid these Christiall pavements, cloath'd these meades </l>
              <l>In never-faiding liveries of greene; </l>
              <l>Flora you see cloathes all the ground with flowers, </l>
              <l>Flora is Psiches hand-maid; Zephirus </l>
              <l>Is but her foote-boy, lackeys at her becke. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-petraea" xml:id="ep000072-e106460">
            <speaker>Petr. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Yet shee's our sister, and it doth mee good </l>
              <l>To see rich worth in any of our blood. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-astioche" xml:id="ep000072-e106500">
            <speaker>Asti. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Thou art a foole Petrea, for I hate </l>
              <l>That any's fortune should transcend my state; </l>
              <l>Shee sends us hence in scorne, but wee'le returne, </l>
              <l>And never cease, till by some treachery, </l>
              <l>Her prid wee make a slave to misery. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000072-e106570">Exeunt. </stage>
        </div>
        <div>
          <stage xml:id="ep000072-e106580">
            <pb xml:id="ep000072-013-b"/>Enter Admetus, Menetius, and Zelotis, </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000072-menetius" xml:id="ep000072-e106590">
            <speaker>Mene. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Patience great sir, you have not lost them all, </l>
              <l>Doubtlesse the two last live. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-zelotes" xml:id="ep000072-e106630">
            <speaker>Zelo. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Sir though they be your daughters, th'are our wives, </l>
              <l>And wee are in no such despaire of them. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-admetus" xml:id="ep000072-e106670">
            <speaker>Ad. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Admit you were one for Astioche, </l>
              <l>And that another for Petrea wept, </l>
              <l>You two, but for two wives shed husbands teares; </l>
              <l>For you and them, I sorrow all: your feares </l>
              <l>Devided betwixt you; on me alone, </l>
              <l>Lies like a mountaine, and thus casteth downe </l>
              <l>Admetus wretched body, with his crowne; </l>
              <l>They followed Psiche and her destiny, </l>
              <l>hath given them death, us living misery. </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="ep000072-e106780">Enter Evemore. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-evemore" xml:id="ep000072-e106790">
            <speaker>Eve. </speaker>
            <p>Rise Royall Sir, your Daughters are return'd. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-admetus" xml:id="ep000072-e106810">
            <speaker>Ad. </speaker>
            <p>Oh where, which way; are my two daughters come? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-evemore" xml:id="ep000072-e106830">
            <speaker>Eve. </speaker>
            <p>Yes sir, and both their lapps are fill'd with gold. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000072-e106850">Enter Astioche and Petrea. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000072-admetus" xml:id="ep000072-e106860">
            <speaker>Ad. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Wellcome to both in one; oh can you tell </l>
              <l>What fate your sister hath? </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-both" xml:id="ep000072-e106900">
            <speaker>Both. </speaker>
            <p>Psiche is well. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-admetus" xml:id="ep000072-e106920">
            <speaker>Ad. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>So among mortalls, it is often sed, </l>
              <l>Children and friends are well, when they are dead. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-astioche" xml:id="ep000072-e106960">
            <speaker>Astio. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>But Psiche lives, and on her breath attends. </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000072-014-a"/>
              <l>Delights that farre surmount all earthly joy; </l>
              <l>Musicke, sweete voyces, and Ambrosian fare, </l>
              <l>Windes, and the light-wing'd creatures of the ayre; </l>
              <l>Cleere channel'd rivers, springs, and flowrie meades, </l>
              <l>Are proud when Psiche wantons on their streames, </l>
              <l>When Psiche on their rich Imbroidery treades, </l>
              <l>When Psiche guilds their Christall with her beames; </l>
              <l>Wee have but seene our sister; and behold </l>
              <l>She sends us with our lapps full brimm'd with gold. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-admetus" xml:id="ep000072-e107080">
            <speaker>Adm. </speaker>
            <p>Oh, you amaze me Daughters. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-petraea" xml:id="ep000072-e107100">
            <speaker>Pet. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Let joy banish amazement from your Kingly thoughts </l>
              <l>Psiche is wedded to some Deitie, </l>
              <l>And prayes withall, our quicke returne againe. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-admetus" xml:id="ep000072-e107150">
            <speaker>Ad. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Wee grant it; wee with you and these, will goe </l>
              <l>To Psiches bowre; desire inflames my minde, </l>
              <l>To sit on the bright wings of that blest winde. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-astioche" xml:id="ep000072-e107200">
            <speaker>Asti. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Oh but the god that governes Psiches thoughts; </l>
              <l>For sure hee is Immortall; charg'd my sister </l>
              <l>To talke with none but us. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-petraea" xml:id="ep000072-e107250">
            <speaker>Petr. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Yet by the magicke of our tongues wee'le try </l>
              <l>If wee can win you so much libertie. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-admetus" xml:id="ep000072-e107290">
            <speaker>Ad. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Goe my Astioche, but come againe </l>
              <l>To comfort him that must thy want complaine; </l>
              <l>Goe with my love Petrea, but returne </l>
              <l>With winged speede, whil'st wee your absence mourne; </l>
              <l>Goe with my blessing; blest those sisters bee, </l>
              <l>That live like you in bonds of unitie: </l>
              <l>Give Psiche this; give her thou this Petrea, </l>
              <l>Tell her shee is my selfe, my soules Idea, </l>
              <l>And say, whil'st shee is spotlesse, lovely white, <stage xml:id="ep000072-e107400">Kisseth them. </stage>
              </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000072-014-b"/>
              <l>Shee shall bee my sole comfort my delight: </l>
              <l>So part with my best wishes. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000072-e107430">Enter Clowne, with three or foure Swaines. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000072-clown" xml:id="ep000072-e107440">
            <speaker>Clo. </speaker>
            <p>And what might you call that yong gentleman, that rules and raignes, revells and roares in these walkes of Arcadia, that makes you borrow sheepes eyes from your flocks, and leaves you no more braines in your heads then in your sheepe-hookes? What might you call this gallant? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-1_swain" xml:id="ep000072-e107460">
            <speaker>1. Swa. </speaker>
            <p>
              <gap extent="4" n="14-b-0630" unit="lines"/>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-2_swain" xml:id="ep000072-e107490">
            <speaker>2. Swa. </speaker>
            <p>
              <gap extent="1" n="14-b-0680" unit="lines"/>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-clown" xml:id="ep000072-e107520">
            <speaker>Clo. </speaker>
            <p>Cupid Coxcombe: your Satyrs are all sots, your Fawnes fooles, and your Pan a pittifull poore fellow; had I their hornes( as I know not what I may have in time) I would <gap extent="1" n="14-b-1010" unit="lines"/>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-unassigned" xml:id="ep000072-e107550">
            <speaker>3 Swa. </speaker>
            <p>They say Bow and Arrowes. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-clown" xml:id="ep000072-e107570">
            <speaker>Clo. </speaker>
            <p>Bow and Bird-boults does he not; and how lies hee? where's his guard? what's his play? Can any of you all give me his true title </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-swain_1" xml:id="ep000072-e107590">
            <speaker>1 Swa. </speaker>
            <p>Not I 'tis farre beyond mee. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-clown" xml:id="ep000072-e107610">
            <speaker>Clo. </speaker>
            <p>Then harken oh you hoydes, and listen oh you Illiterates, whil'st I give you his stile in Folio: Hee is King of cares, <gap extent="1" n="14-b-1630" unit="lines"/>Prince of passions, prate-apaces, and pickled lovers; Duke of disasters, dissemblers, and drown'd eyes; Marquesse of moloncholy <pb xml:id="ep000072-015-a"/>and mad-folkes, grand Signior of griefes, and grones; Lord of lamentations, Heroe of hie-hos, Admirall of aymees, and Mounsier of mutton-lac'd. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-2_swain" xml:id="ep000072-e107640">
            <speaker>2. Swaine. </speaker>
            <p>Heere's a stile I shall never bee able to get over. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-clown" xml:id="ep000072-e107660">
            <speaker>Clo. </speaker>
            <p>And who doe you thinke maintaines this princox in his Pontificalibus? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-xxxx_1" xml:id="ep000072-e107680">
            <speaker>1. Swa </speaker>
            <p>Nay, it exceeds my capacitie. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-clown" xml:id="ep000072-e107700">
            <speaker>Clo. </speaker>
            <p>A company of pittifull fellowes call'd Poets; did you never heare of one Homer, and of the Tale of Troy, and of a ten yeeres siege, and many such trifles. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-2_swain" xml:id="ep000072-e107720">
            <speaker>2. Swa. </speaker>
            <p>Yes, and many things concerning them. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-clown" xml:id="ep000072-e107740">
            <speaker>Clowne. </speaker>
            <p>But heare mee, oh you misse of mis-understanding; This Troy was a Valliage of some Twenty houses; and Priam, as silly a fellow as I am, onely loving to play the good fellow, hee had a great many bowsing lads; whom hee called sonnes. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-xxxx_3" xml:id="ep000072-e107760">
            <speaker>3. Swa </speaker>
            <p>As wee have heere in Arcadia. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-unassigned" xml:id="ep000072-e107780">
            <speaker>Clo </speaker>
            <p>Iust the same; by this Troy ranne a small Brooke, that one might stride over; on the other side dwelt Menelaus a Farmer, who had a light wench to his Wife call'd Hellen, that kept his sheepe, whom Paris, one of Priams mad lads, seeing and liking, ticeth over the brooke, and lies with her in despight of her husbands teeth; for which wrong, he sends for one Agamemnon his brother, that was then high Cunstable of the hundred, and complaynes to him: hee sends to one Vlisses, a faire spoken fellow, and Towne-clarke, and to divers others, amongst whom was one stout fellow called Ajax, a Butcher, who upon a Holy-day, brings a payre of cudgells, and layes them downe in the mid'st, where the <pb xml:id="ep000072-015-b"/>Two Hundreds were then met, which Hector a Baker, another bould lad of the other side seeing, steps foorth, and takes them up; these two had a bowte or two for a broken pate; And heere was all the circumstance of the Trojan Warres. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-1_swain" xml:id="ep000072-e107800">
            <speaker>1. Swa. </speaker>
            <p>To see what these Poets can doe. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-clown" xml:id="ep000072-e107820">
            <speaker>Clowne. </speaker>
            <p>But listen to them, and they will fill your heads with a thousand fooleries; obserue one thing, there's none of you all sooner in love, but hee is troubled with their itch, for hee will bee in his Amorets, and his Canzonets, his Pastoralls, and his Madrigalls, to his Phillis, and his Amorillis. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-1_swain" xml:id="ep000072-e107840">
            <speaker>1. Swa. </speaker>
            <p>Oh beautious Amorillis. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-clown" xml:id="ep000072-e107860">
            <speaker>Clo. </speaker>
            <p>And what's Amorillis thinkst thou? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-1_swain" xml:id="ep000072-e107880">
            <speaker>1. Swa, </speaker>
            <p>A faire and lovely creature. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-clown" xml:id="ep000072-e107900">
            <speaker>Clo. </speaker>
            <p>Ile shew thee the contrary by her owne name, Amor is love, illis, is ill; is ill, cannot bee good; Ergo Amorillis is starke naught; let one or two examples serue for more, there's one of our fayrest Nimphes called Susanna; what is Susanna, but Sus and anna, which is in plaine Arcadia, Nan is a Sow. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-2_swain" xml:id="ep000072-e107920">
            <speaker>2. Swa. </speaker>
            <p>Well, you have taught us more then ever I understood before, concerning Poetrie. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-clown" xml:id="ep000072-e107940">
            <speaker>Clowne. </speaker>
            <p>Come to mee but one howre in a morning, and Ile reade deeper Philosiophie to you; good-morrow Neighbors; Poets, quoth a; What's Titule tu patule, but Titles and Pages; What's Propria que maribus, but a Propper man loves Mary-bons, or Feminno generi tribiunter, but the Feminine Gender is troublesome; what's Ovid, but quasi avoide; now should I be in love, with whom? with Doll, what's that but <pb xml:id="ep000072-016-a"/>Dole and lamentation, with Iugg, what 's shee, but sister to a black-pot, or what's Pegg, good for nothing but to drive into poste: no Cupid, I defie thee and all thy genealogie. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000072-e107960">Enter Cupid. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e107970">
            <speaker>Cup. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>What's hee that so prophanes our deitie? </l>
              <l>And scornes that power which all the gods adore; </l>
              <l>To whom Iove some-times bends, and Neptune kneeles, </l>
              <l>Mars homageth, and Phebus will submit, </l>
              <l>Slie Mercury obay, and Vulcan bow too; </l>
              <l>And all the rurall gods and goddesses, </l>
              <l>Saytirs and Nimphes, allow their soveraigne; </l>
              <l>Hee shall not scape unpunished. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-clown" xml:id="ep000072-e108070">
            <speaker>Clo. </speaker>
            <p>If I could but find one of these fantasticall Poets, or light upon that little god their Patron, I would so tickle them. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e108090">
            <speaker>Cup. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>This hobinall, this rusticke, this base clowne; </l>
              <l>I find him of a dull and braine-lesse eye, </l>
              <l>Such as I know a golden-headed shaft </l>
              <l>Will never enter; of a skinne so thicke, </l>
              <l>As pointed siluer hath no power to pierce: </l>
              <l>For such grosse fooles, I have a boult in store, </l>
              <l>Which though it cannot wound, shall give a blow, </l>
              <l>To startle all within him. </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="ep000072-e108190">Shootes. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-clown" xml:id="ep000072-e108200">
            <speaker>Clo. </speaker>
            <p>Oh me, hey-hoe. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e108220">
            <speaker>Cup. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Lie there base Midas bastard, that refuses </l>
              <l>All-honour'd love, and rayl'st against the Muses. </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="ep000072-e108260">Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-clown" xml:id="ep000072-e108270">
            <speaker>Clo. </speaker>
            <p>Oh coward, whatsoere thou art, to come behind a man <pb xml:id="ep000072-016-b"/>and strike him before, for I saw nobody— to shoote, and never give a man warning, oh coward, I am payd, I am pepper'd; the case is alter'd, for any one may gesse by the hugenesse of the blow, that I am mightily in love; ay—me, that any wench were heere, whose name is Ayme, now could I be in love with any madge, though she were an Howlet, or with any mayd, though she look't like a Malkin; Oh Poetry, I find that I am poyson'd with thee too; for me-thinks I could say my prayers in blanke-verse, nay let me see, I thinke I could rime for a neede; </p>
            <lg>
              <l>Cupid I yeeld, since so I know thy will is, </l>
              <l>And Ile goe seeke me out some Amarillis. </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="ep000072-e108320">Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000072-e108330">Enter Psiche alone. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e108340">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>There's at this time a combat in my soule, </l>
              <l>Whether to trust my well-knowne sisters better, </l>
              <l>Or my yet unseene husband; I have asked, </l>
              <l>Demanded, and enquired of all my traine, </l>
              <l>This fairy-traine that hourely waites on mee, </l>
              <l>Yet none of them will tell mee what hee is; </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="ep000072-e108420">Enter Cupid. </stage>
            <lg>
              <l>Besides, this sollitude to be alone, </l>
              <l>Begins to grow most tedious, and my feares </l>
              <l>Doe every way distract mee. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e108470">
            <speaker>Cup. </speaker>
            <p>Why how now Psiche? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e108490">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Oh let Mercies eyes </l>
              <l>Shine on my fault. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e108530">
            <speaker>Cup. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Are these thy heaven-bound vowes? </l>
              <l>Are all thy protestations guilded ayre? </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000072-017-a"/>
              <l>Hast thou no more regard to my command, </l>
              <l>Or thine owne safety? </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e108590">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <p>Deare love pardon mee. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e108610">
            <speaker>Cup. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Once more I doe; and still must pardon thee, </l>
              <l>And thou must still offend, still torture mee; </l>
              <l>Yet once againe Ile try thy constancy: </l>
              <l>Thy sisters are at hand. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e108670">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>But gentle Love, </l>
              <l>Shall I not speake to them? </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-cupid" xml:id="ep000072-e108710">
            <speaker>Cup. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Yes, but I woe thee </l>
              <l>To send them quickly hence, or they'le undoe thee; </l>
              <l>They now are at the Rock, bid the coole winde </l>
              <l>To please thee, bring them to the place assign'd. </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="ep000072-e108770">Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000072-e108780">Enter Zephirus with the two Sisters. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e108790">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Ho Zephirus, </l>
              <l>Tell me the cause of your so quicke returne? </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-astioche" xml:id="ep000072-e108830">
            <speaker>Asti. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Psiche wee come with danger of our lives, </l>
              <l>To save our sister from ensuing harme. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e108870">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <p>What harme? What danger? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-astioche" xml:id="ep000072-e108890">
            <speaker>Asti. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Danger eminent, </l>
              <l>Once you refused our Counsell, and deni'd </l>
              <l>To let us know your husband, or his name. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-petraea" xml:id="ep000072-e108940">
            <speaker>Petr. </speaker>
            <p>Come, let's see him. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e108960">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <p>Oh, what shall I doe? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-petraea" xml:id="ep000072-e108980">
            <speaker>Petr. </speaker>
            <p>Escape the danger you are fall'n into. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e109000">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <p>You cannot see him. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-astioche" xml:id="ep000072-e109020">
            <speaker>Asti. </speaker>
            <p>Give us then his shape? </p>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000072-017-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e109040">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>His shape, why hee's a man whose snowie head </l>
              <l>Bowes on his bosome, through the weight of age. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-astioche" xml:id="ep000072-e109080">
            <speaker>Asti. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>That cannot bee; you said hee was a youth </l>
              <l>Of comely stature, with long flaxen haire. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e109120">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <p>I am entrap'd. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-astioche" xml:id="ep000072-e109140">
            <speaker>Asti. </speaker>
            <p>Speake, did you ever see your husband? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e109160">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Why doe you aske, pray trouble me no more; </l>
              <l>Leave me, and I will fill your lapps with gold. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-astioche" xml:id="ep000072-e109200">
            <speaker>Asti. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Once thy gold tempted us to leave this place, </l>
              <l>And to betray thy life to misery, </l>
              <l>It shall not now; did not Appollo doome </l>
              <l>Thy fatall marriage to some hiddeous beast; </l>
              <l>How just is Phebus in his auguries; </l>
              <l>Last night, when wee went hence laden with gold, </l>
              <l>Wee spide a serpent gliding on the meade, </l>
              <l>Who at the sight of us, writhing his head </l>
              <l>Proudly into the ayre, first hist at heaven, </l>
              <l>Because it did not shade him from our eyes. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e109320">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <p>How did that serpent vanish from your sight? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-astioche" xml:id="ep000072-e109340">
            <speaker>Asti. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>In at these gates hee rowld, Psiche be wise, </l>
              <l>For tho' a while hee dally with thy beauty, </l>
              <l>Dulling thy taste with sweetes, thy eyes with shewes, </l>
              <l>Thy eares with musicke, and sweete lullabies, </l>
              <l>Hee will in time devoure thee. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e109410">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Miserable wretch, </l>
              <l>How shall I flie the fate that follows mee? </l>
              <l>Whose helpe shall I inuoke? </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-petraea" xml:id="ep000072-e109460">
            <speaker>Petr. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Tell us the trueth, </l>
              <l>And wee'le devise some meanes to succour thee. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e109500">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>You are my sisters, I confesse to you, </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000072-018-a"/>
              <l>I never saw his face, know not his shape, </l>
              <l>Yet have I touch'd his eyes, and felt his hands </l>
              <l>Oft have I kist his cheekesmore more his lipps lips; </l>
              <l>Eyes, hands, lipps, cheeksand face face so charm'd my touch, </l>
              <l>That I have sworne, save his, there were none such, </l>
              <l>Yet your strange story makes mee to suspect </l>
              <l>That hee's some serpent, for hee tells me still, </l>
              <l>To see his glorious shape, will ruine mee; </l>
              <l>Besides hee bids mee shun your company, </l>
              <l>Else you will breede my sorrow; this is that </l>
              <l>Which troubles mee. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-astioche" xml:id="ep000072-e109640">
            <speaker>Asti. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Heare then my counsell; Instantly provide </l>
              <l>A keene-edg'd raysor, and a burning lampe; </l>
              <l>At night, when sleepe sits on his monstrous eyes, </l>
              <l>Steale from his speckled side, step to your light, </l>
              <l>And without feare behold his horrid shape, </l>
              <l>And with the raysor cut his skalie throate; </l>
              <l>And so by death gaine life, and hee being dead, </l>
              <l>Psiche shall to some King be married. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-petraea" xml:id="ep000072-e109740">
            <speaker>Petr. </speaker>
            <p>How doth our sister relish this devise? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-psiche" xml:id="ep000072-e109760">
            <speaker>Psi. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>I doe embrace your councell, and this night </l>
              <l>Ile put the same in execution; </l>
              <l>Come, you have made mee resolute and bould, </l>
              <l>And now receive your lapps ore-swell'd with gold. </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="ep000072-e109820">Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-astioche" xml:id="ep000072-e109830">
            <speaker>Asti. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Swell in thy pride, untill thou break'st thy heart, </l>
              <l>Yet come, wee'le take her larges ere wee part. </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="ep000072-e109870">Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000072-e109880">Enter Midas and Apuleius. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000072-midas" xml:id="ep000072-e109890">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Poet no more; I have enough of Psiche; </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000072-018-b"/>
              <l>Her sisters and the serpent, all of them </l>
              <l>Most villanous lies, Ile proove it; and unlesse </l>
              <l>To please my selfe, and keepe eyes from sleepe sleepe, </l>
              <l>Thou'lt let mee shew thee some of our fine sport, </l>
              <l>Such as wee use heere in Arcadia, </l>
              <l>I will endure no longer. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e109980">
            <speaker>Ap. </speaker>
            <p>Well, I am pleas'd. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-midas" xml:id="ep000072-e110000">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Ile shew thee in a dance. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e110020">
            <speaker>Ap. </speaker>
            <p>Art some-times must give way to ignorance. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000072-e110040">A DANCE. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000072-e110050">Enter Pan, Clowne, Swaines, and Countrey-wenches; They Dance, and Exit. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000072-midas" xml:id="ep000072-e110060">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Was not this sport indeede? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e110080">
            <speaker>Ap. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>My modestie gives thee no reprehension, </l>
              <l>For I am well pleased with your Pastorall mirth, </l>
              <l>But as thou had'st a power over mine eyes, </l>
              <l>To sit it out with patience; so lend mee </l>
              <l>Thy atentive eares. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-midas" xml:id="ep000072-e110150">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>First cleere thy obsurdities, </l>
              <l>Nay, grose ones too; heere Psiche lyes abominably, </l>
              <l>And sayes shee has two husbands, the one young, </l>
              <l>The other old: How canst thou answere this? </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e110210">
            <speaker>Ap. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Though thy vaine doubts be most familiar </l>
              <l>To these Iudicious hearers, well experenc'd, </l>
              <l>As well in matters Morrall as Divine; </l>
              <l>To thee Ile make it plaine. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000072-019-a"/>
          <sp who="#ep000072-midas" xml:id="ep000072-e110270">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>I prethee doe. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e110290">
            <speaker>Ap. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Did Psiche lie to say shee had two loves? </l>
              <l>How like art thou to Psiche, shee to thee. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-midas" xml:id="ep000072-e110330">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>To me, I scorne her likenesse. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e110350">
            <speaker>Ap. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>In this poynt thou art, </l>
              <l>For rather then thy sisters shall grow angry, </l>
              <l>To make earths drossie pleasures stay for thee, </l>
              <l>Thou wilt exclaime with Psiche, Cupids young; </l>
              <l>The joyes of heaven are all too young, too little </l>
              <l>To be believ'd or look'd at; if that faile, </l>
              <l>Thou with the soule wil't say, my love is old, </l>
              <l>Divine delights are crooked like old age, </l>
              <l>Who will not vow, speake, nay sweare any thing, </l>
              <l>To have their vaine delights seru'd like a king. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-midas" xml:id="ep000072-e110470">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>'Tis prety, but your Ecchoes pleas'd me best; </l>
              <l>Oh if a man had seene them. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e110510">
            <speaker>Ap. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>With a mortall eye none can; in them is hid this mistery; </l>
              <l>Caelestiall raptures, that to allure the sight, </l>
              <l>Are seene no more then voices being on high, </l>
              <l>Subject unto no weake, and fleshly eye. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-midas" xml:id="ep000072-e110570">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>But why did Cupid hide himselfe from Psiche? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e110590">
            <speaker>Ap. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Oh who dares prie into those misteries, </l>
              <l>That heaven would have conceal'd; for this shee's charg'd </l>
              <l>Not to see Cupids face, to shun her sisters. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-midas" xml:id="ep000072-e110640">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Those gadding girles, what did'st thou meane by them? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e110660">
            <speaker>Ap. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>The restlesse sinnes that travell night and day, </l>
              <l>Enuying her blisse, the sweete soule to betray. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000072-midas" xml:id="ep000072-e110700">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Well, by this little I conceive the rest, </l>
              <l>I care not greately if I stay it out, </l>
              <l>But if not lik't, Ile either sleepe or flowte. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000072-019-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000072-Apuleius" xml:id="ep000072-e110750">
            <speaker>Alp. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>So will not these I hope, before they view </l>
              <l>What horrid dangers Cupids bride pursue. </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="ep000072-e110790">Exeunt. </stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
        <pb xml:id="ep000072-038-b"/>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back/>
  </text>
</TEI>
