<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000103" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">King James his Royal and Magnificent Entertainment through his Honorable City of London</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Ben</forename>
            <surname>Jonson</surname>
          </persName>
          <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q193857</idno>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A04637_01.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
        </bibl>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">B. Ion: his part of King Iames his royall and magnificent entertainement through his honorable cittie of London, Thurseday the 15. of March. 1603. so much as was presented in the first and last of their triumphall arch's. With his speach made to the last presentation, in the Strand, erected by the inhabitants of the Dutchy, and Westminster. Also, a briefe panegyre of his Maiesties first and well auspicated entrance to his high Court of Parliament, on Monday, the 19. of the same moneth. With other additions.</title>
            <author>Jonson, Ben, 1573?-1637.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>29 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 January (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99844829</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 14756.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 200-1(a).</idno>
            <idno type="vid">9675</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04637</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2240879885</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">B. Ion: his part of King Iames his royall and magnificent entertainement through his honorable cittie of London, Thurseday the 15. of March. 1603. so much as was presented in the first and last of their triumphall arch's. With his speach made to the last presentation, in the Strand, erected by the inhabitants of the Dutchy, and Westminster. Also, a briefe panegyre of his Maiesties first and well auspicated entrance to his high Court of Parliament, on Monday, the 19. of the same moneth. With other additions.</title>
            <title type="alt">B. Jon: his part of King James his royall and magnificent entertainement through his honorable cittie of London, Thurseday the 15. of March. 1603</title>
            <title type="alt">Particular entertainment of the Queene and Prince their Highnesse to Althrope.</title>
            <title type="alt">B. Jon: his part of King James his royall and magnificent entertainement through his honorable cittie of London, Thurseday the 15. of March. 1603.</title>
            <title type="alt">B.I his panegyre.</title>
            <title type="alt">B.J his panegyre.</title>
            <author>Jonson, Ben, 1573?-1637.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[48]; [2], 13, [1] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>By V[alentine] S[immes and George Eld] for Edward Blount,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
            <date type="publication_date">1604.</date>
            <date type="creation_date">1603</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>B. Jon. = Ben Jonson.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Mostly in verse.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Printers' names from STC; "Simmes pr[inted]. only 1st A-B; Eld the rest".</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: pi2 A-E4 F2; A-B4.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The first leaf is blank.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>"B.I his panegyre" has divisional title; register is continuous. "A particular entertainment of the Queene and Prince their Highnesse to Althrope" has separate divisional title and register, and is paginated.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <person xml:id="ep000103-genius">
            <persName>Genius</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000103-tamesis">
            <persName>Tamesis</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000103-flamin">
            <persName>Flamin</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000103-electra">
            <persName>Electra</persName>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1603">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="part" xml:id="ep000103-e100030">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000103-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000103-002-b"/>
        <head>❧ The Pegme at Fen-church </head>
        <p>PResented it selfe in a square and flat vpright, like to the side of a Citty: the top therof, aboue the Vent, and Crest, adorn'd with houses, towres, and steeples, set off in prospectiue. Vpon the Battlements in a great capitall Letters was inscribed, <quote>LONDINIVM :</quote>According to Tacitus: At Suetonius mira constantia, medios inter hosteis Londinium perrexit, <ref target="A04637-e100060-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e100060-a" place="margin">Annal. lib. 14. </note>cognomento quiàem Coloniae non insigne, sed copia Negotiatorum, &amp; commeatu maxime celebre. Beneath that, in a lesse and different Character, was written <quote>CAMERA REGIA </quote>Which Title immediately after the Norman Conquest it beganne to haue; <ref target="A04637-e100080-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e100080-a" place="margin">Camd. Brit. 374. </note>and by the indulgence of succeeding Princes, hath beene hitherto continued. In the Freeze ouer the gate, it seemeth to speake this verse: <quote>
            <l>PAR DOMVS HAEC COELO, </l>
            <l>SED MINOR EST DOMINO. </l>
          </quote>Taken out of Martiall, <ref target="A04637-e100120-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e100120-a" place="margin">Lib. 8. Epig. 36 </note>and implying, that though this Cittie (for the state, and magnificence) might (by Hyporbole) be saide to touch the starres, and reach vp to heauen, yet was it farre Inferior to the Maister thereof, who was his Maiestie; and in that respect vnworthy to receiue him. The highest person aduaunc'd therein, was <quote>MONARCHIA BRITANNICA </quote>
          <pb xml:id="ep000103-003-a"/>and fittely: applying to the aboue mentioned Title of the Citty, the Kings Chamber, and therefore heere placed as in the proper seate of the Empire: for, <ref target="A04637-e100140-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e100140-a" place="margin">Brit. 367. </note>so the glorie and light of our Kingdome M. Camden, speaking of London, saieth, shee is, totius Britanniae Epitome, Britannicíque imperii sedes, Regúmque Angliae Camera, tantum inter omneis eminet, quantum (vt ait ille) inter viburna Cupressus. Shee was a woman richly attir'd in cloth of golde and tissue; a rich mantle; ouer her state twoo Crownes hanging, with pensile shieldes thorow them; the one lim'd with the particular Coate of England, the other of Scotland: on either side also a Crowne, with the like Scutchions, and peculiar Coats of France, &amp; Ireland. In her hand she holdes a Scepter; on her head a fillet of gold, inter-wouen with Palme &amp; Lawrel; her haire bound into foure seuerall points, descending from her Crownes; &amp; and in her lappe a little Globe, inscrib'd vpon <quote>
            <l>ORBIS BRITANNICVS. </l>
            <l>And beneath, the word </l>
            <l>DIVISVS AB ORBE. </l>
          </quote>To shew, that this Empire is a world diuided from the world, and alluding to that of* Clau. <ref target="A04637-e100190-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e100190-a" place="margin">De mallij Theodor. cons. Panegyri. </note>
          <quote>
            <l>— Et nostro diducta Britannia mundo. </l>
            <l>And Virg </l>
            <l>— Et penitus toto diuisos orbe Britannos. <ref target="A04637-e100240-b"/>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e100240-a" place="margin">Eclog. 1. </note>
            </l>
          </quote>The wreathe denotes Victory and Happines. The Scepter &amp; Crowns soueraignty. The Shieldes the precedency of the Countries and their distinctions. At her feete was set <quote>THEOSOPHIA, </quote>
          <pb xml:id="ep000103-003-b"/>or Diuine wisdome, al in white, a blew mantle seeded with Stars, a crowne of Stars on hir head. Hir garments figur'd Truth, Innocence and Cleerenesse. She was alwayes looking vp; in her one hand shee sustained a Doue, in the other a Serpent: <ref target="A04637-e100260-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e100260-a" place="margin">Matth. 10. 16. </note>the last to shew her Subtilty, the first her Simplicity; alluding to that text of Scripture, <ref target="A04637-e100270-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e100270-a" place="margin">Prou. 8. 15. </note>Estote ergo prudentes sicut serpentes, &amp; simplices sicut columbae. Her word, <quote>PER ME REGES REGNANT. </quote>
        </p>
        <p>Intimating, how by her, all Kings do gouerne, and that she is the foundation and strength of kingdomes, to which end, she was here placed, vpon a Cube, at the foote of the Monarchie, as her Base and stay. <ref target="A04637-e100300-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e100300-a" place="margin">Antiqui Genium omnium gignendarum rerum existimarunt Deum: et vrbib. quam hominib. vel caeteris rebus natum. Lil. Gre. Gy. in Synt. deor 15. &amp; Rosin. Antiq. Ro. lib. 2. cap. 14. </note>Directly beneath her stoode <quote>GENIVS VRBIS. </quote>
        </p>
        <p>A person attir'd rich, reuerend, and antique: his haire long and white, crowned with a wreathe of Plane tree, which is saide to be Arbor genialis; his mantle of purple, and buskins of that colour: Hee held in one hand a Goblet, in the other a braunch full of little twigges, to signifie Increase and Indulgence: His word <quote>HIS ARMIS .</quote>pointing to the two that supported him, whereof the one on the right hand, was <quote>BOVLEVTES .</quote>Figuring the Councell of the Citty, <ref target="A04637-e100350-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e100350-a" place="margin">Civica corona fit è fronde querna, quoniam cibus, victusque antiquissimus querceus capisolitus sit. Ros. libr. 10. cap. 27. </note>and was suted in blacke and purple; a wreathe of* Oake vppon his head; sustaining for his ensignes, on his left arme a scarlet roabe, and in his right hand the <pb xml:id="ep000103-004-a"/>
          <ref target="A04637-e100360-b">* </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e100360-a" n="*" place="margin">* vascicull virgarum, intra quas obligata securis erat, sic, vt ferrum in summo fasce extaret, Ros. lib. 7. cap. 3. vbi notandum est, non debere precipitem, &amp; solutam iram esse magistratus. Mora enim allata, &amp; cunctatio, dum sensim virgae solvuntur, identidem consilium mutauit deplectendo. Quando autem vitia quaedam sunt corrigibilia, deplorata alia; castigant virgae, quod revocari valet, immendabile secures praecidunt. Plut. Prob. Rom. 82. </note>Fasces, as tokens of Magistracie, with this inscription; <quote>SERVARE CIVES. </quote>
        </p>
        <quote>The other on the left hand. POLEMIVS </quote>
        <p>The warrelike force of the City, in an antique Coate, or Armour, with a Target and Sword; his helme on, and crowned with Lawrell, implying Strength and Conquest: in his hand he bore the Standard of the Citty, with this word, <quote>EXTINGVERE ET HOSTEIS. </quote>
        </p>
        <p>Expressing by those seuerall Motts, connexed, that with those Armes of Councell and Strength, the Genius was able to extinguish the Kings enemies, and preserue his Citizens, alluding to those verses in Seneca, <ref target="A04637-e100420-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e100420-a" place="margin">Octa: Act: 2 </note>
          <quote>
            <l>Extinguere hostem, maxima est virtus Ducis. </l>
            <l>Servare Cives, maior est patriae, patri. </l>
          </quote>
        </p>
        <p>Vnderneath these, in an Aback thrust out before the rest lay <quote>TAMESIS. </quote>
        </p>
        <p>The Riuer, as running along the side of the City; in a skinne made like flesh, naked, and blew. His mantle of sea-greene or water colour, thinne, and bolne out like a sayle; Bracelets about his wreasts, of willow and sedge, a crowne of sedge and reede vpon his head, mixt with water-lillies; alluding to Virgills description of Tiber; <pb xml:id="ep000103-004-b"/>
          <quote>
            <l>— Deus ipse loci, <ref target="A04637-e100510-b"/>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e100510-a" place="margin">Aen. lib. 8. </note>fluvie Tyberinus amoeno, </l>
            <l>Populeas inter senior se attolere frondes </l>
            <l>Visus. cum tenuis glauco velabat amictu </l>
            <l>Carbasus. &amp; crineis vmbrosa tegebat Arundo. </l>
          </quote>
        </p>
        <p>His beard, and haire long, and ouergrowne. He leanes his arme vpon an earthen pot, out of which, water, with liue Fishes, are seene to runne forth, and play about him. His word, <quote>FLVMINA SENSERVNT IPSA .</quote>A Hemistich of Ouids: <ref target="A04637-e100570-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e100570-a" place="margin">Amor. lib. 3. el. 5. </note>The rest of the verse being, <quote>quid esset amor. </quote>
        </p>
        <p>Affirming, that Riuers themselues, and such inanimate Creatures, haue heeretofore beene made sensible of Passions, and Affections; and that hee, nowe, no lesse pertooke the ioy of his Maiesties gratefull approach to this Citty, than any of those persons, to whome he pointed, which were the daughters of the Genius, and sixe in number: who, in a spreading ascent, vpon seuerall grices, help to beautifie both the sides. The first, <quote>EVPHROSYNE ,</quote>or Gladnes: was suted in greene, a mantle of diuers colors, embroydred with all varietie of floures: on her head a Gyrland of Myrtle, in her right hand a cristall Cruze filld with wine, in the left a Cup of golde: at her feete a Tymbrell, Harpe, and other Instruments, all ensignes of gladnesse, <ref target="A04637-e100610-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e100610-a" place="margin">Hor. car. I. ode 27. </note>
          <quote>
            <l>Natis in vsum laetitiae scyphis, &amp;c. </l>
            <l>And in another place, </l>
            <l>Nunc est bibendum, <ref target="A04637-e100660-b"/>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e100660-a" place="margin">&amp; Ode 37 </note>nunc pede libero </l>
            <l>Pulsanda Tellus, &amp;c. </l>
          </quote>Her word. <ref target="A04637-e100680-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e100680-a" place="margin">Stat. Syl. 4. Epu Domit. </note>
        </p>
        <quote>HAEC AEVI MIHI PRIMA DIES. </quote>
        <pb xml:id="ep000103-005-a"/>
        <p>As if this were the first houre of her life, and the minute wherein she beganne to be; beholding so long coueted, and look'd for a presence. The second. <quote>SEBASIS .</quote>or Veneratio, was varied in an ashe colour'd sute, and darke mantle, a vayle ouer her head of ash-colour: her hands crost before her, and her eyes halfe closde: Her word: <quote>MIHI SEMPER DEVS. <ref target="A04637-e100730-b"/>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e100730-a" place="margin">Virg. Ecl. I. </note>
          </quote>
        </p>
        <p>Implying both her office of reuerence, and the dignity of her obiect, who being as God on earth, should neuer be lesse in her thought: The third: <quote>PROTHYMIA .</quote>or Promptitude, was attir'd in a short tuckt garment of flame-colour, wings at her backe; her hayre bright, &amp; bound vp with ribands; her breast open, virago-like; hir buskins so ribanded: She was crowned with a Chaplet of Trifoly, to expresse readines, and opennesse euery way; in her right hand shee held a squirrell, as being the creature most full of life and quicknesse: in the left a close round Censor, with the perfume sodainely to be vented forth at the sides. Her word: <quote>QVA DATA PORTA. <ref target="A04637-e100770-b"/>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e100770-a" place="margin">Aene 1. </note>
          </quote>
        </p>
        <p>Taken from an other place in Virgill where Eolus at the command of Iuno letts forth the winde; <ref target="A04637-e100790-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e100790-a" place="margin">Aene 1. </note>
          <quote>
            <l>— ac venti velut agmine facto </l>
            <l>Qua data porta ruunt, &amp; terras turbine perflant. </l>
          </quote>
        </p>
        <p>And shew'd that shee was no lesse prepar'd with promptitude, and alacrity, then the windes were, <pb xml:id="ep000103-005-b"/>vpon the least Gate that shall be opened to his high commaund. The fourth <quote>AGRYPNIA .</quote>or Vigilance, in yellow, a sable mantle, seeded with waking eies, and siluer fringe: her Chaplet of Heliotropium, or Turnsole; in her one hand a Lampe, or Cresset, in her other a Bell. The Lampe signified search and sight, the Bell warning. The Heliotropium care; and respecting her obiect. Her word <quote>SPECVLAMVR IN OMNEIS. </quote>
        </p>
        <p>Alluding to that of Ouid, where he describes the office of Argus, <quote>
            <l>— Ipse procul montis sublime cacumen </l>
            <l>Occupat, <ref target="A04637-e100900-b"/>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e100900-a" place="margin">Met. 1. </note>vnde sedens partes speculatur in omneis. </l>
          </quote>and implying the like duety of care and vigilance in her selfe. The fifth <quote>AGAPE .</quote>Or louing Affection, in Crimson fringed with golde, a mantle of flame-colour, her Chaplet of red and white roses; in her hand a flaming heart: The flame expressed zeale, the red and white roses, a mixture of Simplicity with Loue: her robes freshnes and feruency. <ref target="A04637-e100920-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e100920-a" place="margin">De 4. Cons. Honor. Panegyri </note>Her word, <quote>NON SIC EXCVBIAE .</quote>Out of Claudian, in following <quote>
            <l>— Nec circumstantia peila </l>
            <l>— Quàm tutatur amor. </l>
          </quote>Inferring, that though her Sister before had protested watchfulnes, &amp; circumspection, yet no watch <pb xml:id="ep000103-006-a"/>or guard could be so safe to the estate, or person of a Prince, as the loue and naturall affection of his Subiects: which she in the Citties behalfe promised. The sixt, <quote>OMOTHYMIA .</quote>Or Vnanimity in blew, her roabe blew, and buskins. A Chaplet of blew lillies, shewing one trueth and intirenesse of minde. In her lappe lies a sheafe of arrowes bound together, and she her selfe sittes weauing certaine small siluer twists. Her word, <quote>
            <l>FIRMA CONSENSVS FACIT. </l>
            <l>Auxilia humilia firma, <ref target="A04637-e101010-b"/>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e101010-a" place="margin">Pub. Syr. Mi. </note>&amp;c. </l>
          </quote>
        </p>
        <p>Intimating, that euen the smallest and weakest aydes, by consent, are made strong: herselfe personating the vnanimity, or consent of Soule, in all inhabitants of the Citty to his seruice. </p>
        <p>¶ These are all the personages, or liue figures, whereof onely two were Speakers (Genius and Tamesis) the rest were Mutes. Other dumbe complements there were, as the Armes of the Kingdome on the one side, with this Inscription. <quote>
            <l>HIS VIREAS. </l>
            <l>With these maist thou flourish. </l>
          </quote>
        </p>
        <p>On the other side the Armes of the City, with <quote>
            <l>HIS VINCAS. </l>
            <l>With these maist thou conquer. </l>
          </quote>
        </p>
        <p>In the centre, or midst of the Pegme, there was an Aback, or Square, wherein this Elogie was written. <quote>
            <l>Maximus hic Rex est, &amp; lucc serenior ipsa </l>
            <l>Principe quae talem cernit in vrbe Ducem; </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000103-006-b"/>
            <l>Cuius Fortunam superat sic vnica Virtus, </l>
            <l>Vnus vt is reliquos vincit vtrâque viros. </l>
            <l>Praeceptis alii populos, multâque fatigant </l>
            <l>Lege; sed exemplo nos rapit ille suo. </l>
            <l>Cuique frui totâ fas est vxore marito, </l>
            <l>Et sua fas simili pignora nosse patri. </l>
            <l>Ecce vbi pignoribus circumstipata coruscis </l>
            <l>It comes, &amp; tanto vix minor ANNA viro. </l>
            <l>Haud metus est, Regem posthac ne proximus Hares, </l>
            <l>Neu Successorem non amet ille suum. </l>
          </quote>
        </p>
        <p>This, and the whole frame, was couered with a curtaine of silke, painted like a thicke cloude, and at the approach of the K. was instantly to bee drawne. The Allegory being, that those cloudes were gathered vpon the face of the Citty, through their long want of his most wished fight: but now, as at the rising of the Sunne, all mistes were dispersed and fled. When sodainely vpon silence made to the Musikes, a voyce was heard to vtter this verse; <quote>Totus adest oculis, <ref target="A04637-e101270-b"/>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e101270-a" place="margin">Clau. de laud. Stil. lib. 3. </note>aderat qui mentibus olim, </quote>
        </p>
        <p>Signifying that hee now was really obiected to their eyes, who before had beene only, but still, present in their mindes. </p>
        <p>¶ Thus farre the complementall parte of the first; wherein was not only labored the expression of State and Magnificence (as proper to a triumphall Arch) but the very Site, Fabricke, Strength, Policie, Dignitie and Affections of the Cittie were all laide downe to life: The nature, and propertie of these Deuises being, to present alwaies <pb xml:id="ep000103-007-a"/>some one entire body, or figure, consisting of distinct members and eache of those expressing it selfe, in the owne actiue spheare, yet all, with that generall harmony so connexed, and disposed, as no one little parte can be missing to the illustration of the whole: where also is to be noted, that the Symboles vsed, are not, neither ought to be simply Hierogliphickes, Emblemes, or Imprese, but a mixed Character, pertaking somwhat of all, and peculierly apted to these more magnificent Inuentions: wherein the Garments, and Ensignes deliuer the nature of the person, and the Word the present office. Neither was it becomming, or could it stand with the dignity of these shewes (after the most miserable &amp; desperate shift of the Puppits) to require a Truch-man, or (with the ignorant Painter) one to write. This is a Dog; or, This is a Hare: but so to be presented, as vpon the view they might without cloude, or obscurity declare themselves to the sharpe and learned: And for the multitude, no doubt but their grounded iudgements gazed, said it was fine, and were satisfied. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="speeches" xml:id="ep000103-e101320">
        <head>The speeches of Gratulation. </head>
        <sp who="#ep000103-genius" xml:id="ep000103-e101330">
          <speaker>GENIVS. </speaker>
          <l>TIme, Fate, and Fortune have at length conspir'd, </l>
          <l>To giue our Age the day so much desir'd. </l>
          <l>What all the minutes, houres, weekes, months, and yeares, </l>
          <l>That hang in file vpon these siluer haires, </l>
          <l>Could not produce, beneath the <ref target="A04637-e101390-b">a </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e101390-a" n="a" place="margin">a As being the first, free, and naturall gouernement of this Iland, after it came to ciuilitie. </note>Brittane stroke, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000103-007-b"/>
          <l>The Roman, Saxon, Dane, and Norman <ref target="A04637-e101410-b">a </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e101410-a" n="a" place="margin">a In respect they wer all Cōquests &amp; the obedience of the subiect more inforced. </note>yoke, </l>
          <l>This point of Time hath done. Now London reare </l>
          <l>Thy forehead high, and on it striue to weare </l>
          <l>Thy choisest Gems; Teach thy steepe Towres to rise </l>
          <l>Higher with people: Set with sparkling eies </l>
          <l>Thy spacious windowes; and in euery streete, </l>
          <l>Let thronging Ioy, Loue, and Amazement meete. </l>
          <l>Cleaue all the ayre with showtes, and let the cry </l>
          <l>Strike through as long, and vniuersally </l>
          <l>As Thunder; For, thou now art blist to see </l>
          <l>That sight, for which thou didst beginne to bee. </l>
          <l>When <ref target="A04637-e101530-b">b </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e101530-a" n="b" place="margin">b <p>Rather then the Citie shuld want a Founder, we choose to folowe the receiu'd story of Brute, whether fabulous, or true, and not altogether vnwarrāted in Poetrie: since it is a fauor of Antiquity to few cities, to let them know their first Authors. Besides, a learned Poet of our time, in a most elegāt work of his Con. Tam. &amp; ISIS, celebrating London hath this verse of her: </p>
              <p>Aemula maternae tollens sua lumina Troiae. Here is also an antient rite alluded to in the building of Citties, which was to giue them their boundes with a plough, according to Vir. Aen. li. 10. Interea Aeneas vrbem designat Aratro. And Isidore li. 15. cap. 2. Vrbs vocata ab orbe, quod antiquae ciuitates in orbem fiebant; vel ab vrbe parte aratri, quo muri designabantur, vnde est illud. Optauitque locum regno &amp; concludere sulco. </p>
            </note>Brutus plough first gaue thee infant boūds, </l>
          <l>And I, thy GENIVS walk't auspicious rounds </l>
          <l>In euery <ref target="A04637-e101580-b">c </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e101580-a" n="c" place="bottom">c Primigenius sulcus dicitur, qui in condenda noua vrbe, tauro &amp; vacca designationis causa imprimitur; Hitherto respects that of Camd. Brit. 368. speaking of this Cittie, Quicunque autem condiderit, vitali genio, constructam fuisse ipsius fortuna docuit. </note>furrow; Then did I forelooke, </l>
          <l>And saw this day <ref target="A04637-e101600-b">d </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e101600-a" n="d" place="bottom">d For so all happy dayes were. Plin. cap. 40. lib. 7. Nat. Hist. To which Horace alludes, lib. 1. ode. 36. Cressa ne careat pulchra dies nota. And the other Plin. epist. 11. lib. 6. O diem laetum, not and umque mihi candidissimo calculo. With many other in many places. Mart. lib. 8. epi. 45. lib. 9. epi. 53. lib. 10. 38. lib. 11. 37. Stat. lib. 4. Syl. 6. Pers, sat. 2. Catull. epig. 69. &amp;c. </note>mark't white in <ref target="A04637-e101610-b">e </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e101610-a" n="e" place="bottom">e The Parcae, or Fates, Martianus calls them scribas ac librarias superûm; whereof Clotho is saide to be the eldest, signifying in Latine Euocatio. </note>Clotho's booke. </l>
          <l>The seuerall <ref target="A04637-e101630-b">f </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e101630-a" n="f" place="bottom">f Those before mentioned of the Brittane, Romane, Saxon, &amp;c. and to this Register of the Fates allude those verses of Ouid Met. 15— Cernes illic molimine vasto. Exaere, &amp; solido rerum tabularia ferro: Quae neque concussum coeli, neque fulminis Iram, Nec metuunt vllas tuta atque aeternaruinas. Inuenies illic incisa adamante perenni Fata &amp;c.— </note>Circles, both of change and sway, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000103-008-a"/>
          <l>Within this Isle, there also figur'd lay: </l>
          <l>Of which the greatest, perfectest, and last </l>
          <l>Was this, whose present happinesse we taste. </l>
          <l>Why keep you silence Daughters? What dull peace </l>
          <l>Is this inhabites you? Shall Office cease </l>
          <l>Vpon th'aspect of him, to whom you owe </l>
          <l>More then you are, or can be? Shall TIME knowe </l>
          <l>That Article, wherein your flame stoode still, </l>
          <l>And not aspir'd? Now heauen auert an ill </l>
          <l>Of that blacke looke. Ere pause possesse your breasts </l>
          <l>I wish you more of plagues: "Zeale when it rests, </l>
          <l>Leaues to be Zeale. Vp thou tame RIVER, wake; </l>
          <l>And from thy liquid limbes this slumber shake: </l>
          <l>Thou drown'st thy selfe in inofficious sleepe; </l>
          <l>And these thy sluggish waters seeme to creepe, </l>
          <l>Rather than flow. Vp, rise, and swell with pride </l>
          <l>Aboue thy bankes." Now is not euery Tyde. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000103-tamesis" xml:id="ep000103-e101810">
          <speaker>TAMESIS. </speaker>
          <l>TO what vaine end should I contend to show </l>
          <l>My weaker powres, when Seas of pompe o'reflow </l>
          <l>The Citties face: and couer all the shore </l>
          <l>With sands more rich than <ref target="A04637-e101860-b">a </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e101860-a" n="a" place="margin">a A riuer diuiding Spaine and Portugall, and by the consent of Poets stil'd aurifer. </note>Tagus wealthy ore? </l>
          <l>When in the flood of Ioy, that comes with him, </l>
          <l>He drownes the world; yet makes it liue and swimme, </l>
          <l>And spring with gladnesse: Not my fishes heere, </l>
          <l>Though they be dumbe, but doe expresse the cheere </l>
          <l>Of these bright streames. No lesse may <ref target="A04637-e101920-b">b </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e101920-a" n="b" place="margin">b Vnderstanding Euphrosyne, Sebasis, Prothymia, &amp;c </note>These, and I </l>
          <l>Boast our delights, albe't we silent lie. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000103-008-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000103-genius" xml:id="ep000103-e101940">
          <speaker>GENIVS. </speaker>
          <l>INdeede, true Gladnesse doth not alwayes speake: </l>
          <l>Ioy bred, and borne but in the tongue, is weake. </l>
          <l>Yet (lest the feruor of so pure a flame </l>
          <l>As this my Citty beares, might loose the name, </l>
          <l>Without the apt euenting of her heate) </l>
          <l>Know greatest IAMES (and no lesse good, than great.) </l>
          <l>In the behalfe of all my vertuous Sonnes, </l>
          <l>Whereof my <ref target="A04637-e102030-b">a </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e102030-a" n="a" place="margin">a The Lord Maior who for his yeere, hath Senior place of the rest, and for the day was chief Serieant to the King. </note>eldest there, thy pompe forerunnes, </l>
          <l>(A Man without my flattring, or his Pride, </l>
          <l>As worthy, as hee's <ref target="A04637-e102060-b">b </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e102060-a" n="b" place="margin">b Aboue the blessing of his present office, the word had some particular allusion to his name, which is Benet, and hath (no doubt) in time bin the contraction of Benedict. </note>blest to be thy guide) </l>
          <l>In his graue name, and all his Brethrens right, </l>
          <l>(Who thirst to drinke the Nectar of thy sight) </l>
          <l>The Councell, Commoners, and Multitude; </l>
          <l>(Glad, that this day so long deny'd, is viewd) </l>
          <l>I tender thee the heartiest welcome, yet </l>
          <l>That euer King had to his <ref target="A04637-e102130-b">c </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e102130-a" n="c" place="margin">c The Cittie, which title is toucht before. </note>Empires seate: </l>
          <l>Neuer came man, more long'd for, more desir'd: </l>
          <l>And being come, more reuerenc'd, lou'd, admir'd: </l>
          <l>Heare, and record it: In a Prince it is </l>
          <l>No little vertue, to know who are his. </l>
          <l>
            <ref target="A04637-e102190-b">* </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e102190-a" n="*" place="margin">* To the Prince .</note>With like deuotions, doe I stoope t'embrace </l>
          <l>This springing glory of thy <ref target="A04637-e102210-b">d </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e102210-a" n="d" place="margin">d An attribute giuen to great persons, fitly aboue other, Humanity, &amp; in frequent vse with al the Greek Poets, especially Homer. Iliad. <seg xml:lang="unk">{non-Roman} {non-Roman} {non-Roman}</seg>— <seg xml:lang="unk">{non-Roman} {non-Roman} {non-Roman}</seg>. And in the same Booke.— <seg xml:lang="unk">{non-Roman} {non-Roman} {non-Roman}</seg>. </note>Godlike race; </l>
          <l>His Countries Wonder, Hope, Loue, Ioy and Pride: </l>
          <l>How well dooth he become the royall side </l>
          <l>Of this erected, and broade spreading Tree, </l>
          <l>Vnder whose shade, may Brittane euer be. </l>
          <l>And from this branch, may thousand branches more </l>
          <l>Shoote or'e the Maine, and knit with euery shore </l>
          <l>In bonds of Marriage, Kinred, and Increase; </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000103-009-a"/>
          <l>And stile this Land, the <ref target="A04637-e102330-b">a </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e102330-a" n="a" place="margin">a As Lactant. calls Parnassus, Vmbilicum terra. </note>Nauill of their peace. </l>
          <l>This is your Seruants wish, your Citties vow, </l>
          <l>Which still shall propagate it selfe, with you; </l>
          <l>And free from spurres of Hope, that slow mindes moue: </l>
          <l>He seekes no hire, that owes his life to Loue. </l>
          <l>
            <ref target="A04637-e102390-b"/>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e102390-a" place="margin">To the Queene .</note>And heere she comes that is no lesse a part </l>
          <l>In this dayes greatnesse, then in my glad heart. </l>
          <l>Glory of Queenes, and <ref target="A04637-e102420-b">b </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e102420-a" n="b" place="margin">b An emphaticall speach, &amp; well re-enforcing her greatnes; being by this match, more than either hir Brother, Father, &amp;c. </note>Glory of your Name, </l>
          <l>Whose Graces doe as farre out-speake your Fame, </l>
          <l>As Fame doth silence, when her Trumpet rings </l>
          <l>You <ref target="A04637-e102460-b">c </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e102460-a" n="c" place="margin">c Daughter to Frederik secōd kind of Denmarke, &amp; Norway, sister to Christierne the fourth nowe there raigning, &amp; wife to Iames our Soueraigne. </note>Daughter, Sister, Wife of seuerall Kings: </l>
          <l>Besides Alliance, and the stile of Mother, </l>
          <l>In which one Title you drowne all your other. </l>
          <l>Instance, be <ref target="A04637-e102500-b">d </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e102500-a" n="d" place="margin">d The Prince Henry Frederike. </note>that faire shoote, is gone before </l>
          <l>Your eldest Ioy, and top of all your store, </l>
          <l>With those, whose sight to vs is yet deni'd, </l>
          <l>But not our zeale to them, or ought beside </l>
          <l>This Citty can to you: For whose estate </l>
          <l>Shee hopes you will be still good Aduocate </l>
          <l>To her best Lord. So, whilst you mortall are, </l>
          <l>No taste of sower mortalitie once dare </l>
          <l>Approach your house; nor Fortune greete your Grace </l>
          <l>But comming on, and with a forward face. </l>
        </sp>
      </div>
      <div type="part" xml:id="ep000103-e102600">
        <pb xml:id="ep000103-009-b"/>
        <head>THE OTHER AT TEMPLE BARRE. </head>
        <p>CArried the frontispice of a Temple, the Wals of which and Gates were Brasse; the Pillers Siluer, their Capitals and Bases Golde: in the highest point of all was erected a Ianus head, and ouer it written. </p>
        <quote>IANO QVADRIFRONTI SACRVM. </quote>
        <p>Which title of Quadrifrons is said to be giuen him, <ref target="A04637-e102640-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e102640-a" place="margin">Bassus apud Macro. lib. 1. Satur. ca. 9. </note>as he respecteth all Climates, and filles all parts of the world with his Maiestie; which Martiall would seeme to allude vnto in that Hendicasillable, <ref target="A04637-e102650-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e102650-a" place="margin">li. 8. Epi. 2. </note>
          <quote>Et linguâ pariter locutus omni .</quote>Others haue thought it by reason of the foure Elements, which brake out of him, being Chaos: for Ouid is not afraide to make Chaos and Ianus the same, in those verses <quote>
            <l>Me Chaos antiqui (nam sum res prisca) vocabant: <ref target="A04637-e102690-b"/>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e102690-a" place="margin">Fast. lib. I. </note>
            </l>
            <l>Adspice, &amp;c. </l>
          </quote>&amp;c. <quote>
            <pb xml:id="ep000103-010-a"/>PLVTVS .</quote>or Wealth, <ref target="A04637-e102720-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e102720-a" place="margin">So Cephisiodotus hath fained him See Paus. in Boeoti. &amp; Phil. in Imag. contrarie to Aristop. Theogn. Lucian and others, that make him blinde and deformed. </note>a little boy, bare headed, his locks curled, and spangled with golde, of a fresh aspect, his body almost naked, sauing some rich robe cast ouer him; in his armes a heape of gold Ingots to expresse riches, whereof he is the God: Beneath her feete lay <quote>ENYALIVS .</quote>or Mars, Groueling, his armour scattered vpon him in seuerall peeces, and sundrie sortes of weapons broken about him, her word to all was <quote>VNA TRIVMPHIS IN NVMERIS POTIOR. </quote>
          <quote>
            <l>pax optima rerum </l>
            <l>Quas homini nouisse datum est, <ref target="A04637-e102780-b"/>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e102780-a" place="margin">Sil. Ital. </note>pax vna Triumphis Innumeris potior. </l>
          </quote>signifieng that peace alone was better, and more to be coueted then innumerable Tryumphes, besides, vpon the right hand of her, but with some little descent, in a Hemicycle was seated <quote>ESYCHIA .</quote>or Quiet, the first handmaid of peace; A woman of a graue and venerable aspect, attired in black, vpon her head an artificiall nest, out of which appeared Storkes heads to manifest a sweete repose. Her feete were placed vpon a Cube, to shewe stability, <pb xml:id="ep000103-010-b"/>and in her lappe shee held a Perpendicular or leuell, as the ensigne of Euennesse and Rest; on the top of it sate a Halcion or Kings-fisher. She had lying at her feete <quote>TARACHE .</quote>or Tumult, in a garment of diuers, but darke coulers, her haire wilde, and disordered, a fowle and troubled face, about her laye staues, swordes, ropes, chaines, hammers, stones, and such like to expresse Turmoile. The word was <quote>PERAGIT TRANQVILLA POTESTAS. <ref target="A04637-e102820-b"/>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e102820-a" place="margin">De Malii Theo. cons. Panegy. </note>
          </quote>
          <quote>Claud Quod violent a nequit: mandat aque fortius vrget Imperiosa quies .</quote>To shewe the benefits of a calme and facile power, being able to effect in a state that, which no violence can. On the other, side the second hand-maide, was <quote>ELEVTHERIA .</quote>or Libertie, her dressing white, &amp; som-what antique but loose and free; her haire flowing downe her backe, and shoulders: In her right hand shee bare a Club, on her left a Hat, the Characters of freedom, and power: At her feete a Catt was placed, the creature most affecting, and expressing libertie. She trode on <pb xml:id="ep000103-011-a"/>Rauen, as the Augury of ill fortune: &amp; the Soule was <quote>REDEVNT SATVRNIA REGNA .</quote>Out of Virgil, <ref target="A04637-e102860-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e102860-a" place="margin">Eclog. 4. </note>to shewe that nowe those golden times were returned againe, wherein Peace was with vs so aduaunced, Rest receaued, Libertie restored, Safetie assured, and all Blessednesse appearing in euery of these vertues her perticular Triumphe ouer her opposite euill. This is the dumbe argument of the frame, and illustrated with this verse of Virgil, written in the vnder freeze. <ref target="A04637-e102870-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e102870-a" place="margin">Aeneid. lib. 11. </note>
          <quote>
            <l>NVLLA SALVS BELLO </l>
            <l>PACEM TE POSSIMVS OMNES. </l>
          </quote>The speaking parte was performed, as within the Temple where there was erected an Altar, to which at the approach of the K. appeares the Flamen <quote>
            <ref target="A04637-e102920-b">* </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e102920-a" n="*" place="margin">* One of the three Flamines that as some think Numa Pompilius first instituted, but we rather with Varro take him of Romulus institution, whereof there were onely two, Hee, and Dialis: to whom he was next in dignity. He was alwaies created out of the Nobilitie, &amp; did performe the rites to Mars, who was thought the Father of Romulus. </note>MARTIALIS .</quote>And to him. <quote>GENIVS VRBIS .</quote>The Genius we attired before: To the Flamen wee appoint this habit. A long Crimson robe to witnesse his nobility, his typpet and sleeues white as reflecting on purity in his religion, a rich mantle of gold with a traine to expresse the dignity of his function. <pb xml:id="ep000103-011-b"/>Vpon his head a <ref target="A04637-e102940-b">c </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e102940-a" n="c" place="bottom">c Scaliger in coniect. in Varr: saith Totus Pileus, vel potiùs velamenta, Flammcum dicebatur. vnde Flamines dicti. </note>Hat of delicate wooll, whose top ended in a Cone, and was thence called Apex, according to that of Lucan. lib. 1. <quote>Attollensque Apicem generoso vertice Flamen .</quote>This Apex was couered with a <ref target="A04637-e102960-b">d </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e102960-a" n="d" place="bottom">d To this lookes that other coniecture of Varro. lib. 4. de lingua Latina Flamines, quòd licio in Capite velati erant semper, ac caput cinctum habebant filo, Flamines dicti </note>fine net of yearne which they named Apiculum, &amp; was sustained with a <ref target="A04637-e102970-b">e </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e102970-a" n="e" place="bottom">e Which in their attire was called Stroppus, in their wiues Inarculum. </note>bowd twigge of Pomgranat tree, it was also in the hot time of Summer to be bound with Ribands, and throwne behinde them as <ref target="A04637-e102980-b">f </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e102980-a" n="f" place="bottom">f Scal. Ibid: in con. Pone enim regerebant apicem, ne grauis esset summis aestatis caloribus. Amentis enim, quae offendices dicebantur sub mentum adductis, religabant; vt cum vellent, regererent, &amp; pone pendere permitterent. </note>Scaliger teacheth. In his hand hee bore a golden Censor with perfume, and censing about the Altar (hauing first kindled his fier on the toppe) is interrupted by the Genius. </p>
        <q type="speeches">
          <sp who="#ep000103-genius" xml:id="ep000103-e103020">
            <speaker>GENIVS. </speaker>
            <l>STay, what art thou, that in this strange attire, </l>
            <l>Darst kindle stranger, and vnhallowed fire </l>
            <l>Vpon this Altar? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000103-flamin" xml:id="ep000103-e103060">
            <speaker>FL. </speaker>
            <l>Rather what art thou </l>
            <l>That darst so rudely interrupt my vowe? </l>
            <l>My habit speakes my name. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000103-genius" xml:id="ep000103-e103100">
            <speaker>GE. </speaker>
            <l>A Flamin? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000103-flamin" xml:id="ep000103-e103120">
            <speaker>FL. </speaker>
            <l>Yes, </l>
            <l>And <ref target="A04637-e103150-b">a </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e103150-a" n="a" place="margin">a Of Mars, whose rites (as wee haue toucht before) this Flamen did specially celebrate. </note>Martialis calld. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000103-genius" xml:id="ep000103-e103160">
            <speaker>GE. </speaker>
            <l>I so did gesse </l>
            <l>By my short view, but whence didst thou ascend </l>
            <l>Hither? or how? or to what mistick end? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000103-flamin" xml:id="ep000103-e103200">
            <speaker>FL. </speaker>
            <l>The noise, and present tumult of this Day, </l>
            <l>Rowsd me from sleepe, and silence, where I lay </l>
            <l>Obscur'd from light; which when I wakt to see, </l>
            <l>I wondring thought what this great pompe might be. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000103-012-a"/>
            <l>When (looking in my Kalender) I found </l>
            <l>The <ref target="A04637-e103270-b">b </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e103270-a" n="b" place="margin">b With vs the 15. of March, which was the present day of this Triumph; and on which the great feast of Anna Perenna (among the Romans) was yearly and with such solemnitie remembred. Oui. Fast. 3. Idibus est Annae festum geniale Perennae, Haud procul a ripis, &amp;c. </note>Ides of Marche were entred, and I bound </l>
            <l>With these, to celebrate the Geniall feast </l>
            <l>Of <ref target="A04637-e103300-b">c </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e103300-a" n="c" place="bottom">c Who this Anna should be (with the Romanes themselues) hath beene no trifling controuersie. Some haue thought her fabulously the sister of Dido, some a Nimphe of Numicius; some Io; some Themis. Others an olde woman of Bouillae, that fed the seditious multitude, in Monte sacro, with Wafers, and fine Cakes, in time of their penurie: so whom, afterward (in memory of the benefit) their peace being made with the Nobles, they ordaind this feast. Yet, they that haue thought nearest, haue mist all these, and directly imagined her the Moone. And that she was calld Anna, Quia mensibus impleat annum. Ovid. ibid. To which, the vow that they vsd in her Rites, somwhat confirmingly alludes; which was. vt Annare, &amp; Perennare commodè liceret. Maor. Sat. lib. 1. cap. I 2. </note>ANNA stil'd PERENNA, <ref target="A04637-e103310-b">d </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e103310-a" n="d" place="bottom">d So Ouid. ibid. Fast. makes Mars speaking to her, Mense meo coleris, iunxi mea tempora tecum. </note>MARS his guest; </l>
            <l>Who, in this Moneth of his, is yearly call'd </l>
            <l>To banquet at his Altars; and instald; </l>
            <l>
              <ref target="A04637-e103350-b">e </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e103350-a" n="e" place="bottom">e Nuper erat dea facta, &amp;c. ibid. Ouid. </note>A Goddesse with him, since shee filles the Yeare, </l>
            <l>And <ref target="A04637-e103370-b">f </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e103370-a" n="f" place="bottom">f Where is vnderstood the meeting of the Zodiack in March, the month wherein she is celebrated. </note>knits the oblique scarfe that girts the spheare. </l>
            <l>Whilest foure fac't IANVS turnes his <ref target="A04637-e103390-b">g </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e103390-a" n="g" place="bottom">g That face wherewith he beholds the Spring. </note>vernall looke </l>
            <l>Vpon their meeting howers, as if he tooke. </l>
            <l>High pride and pleasure. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000103-genius" xml:id="ep000103-e103420">
            <speaker>GE. </speaker>
            <l>Sure thou stil dost dreame, </l>
            <l>And both thy tongue, and thought rides on the streame </l>
            <l>Of Phantasy: Behold here Hee nor Shee, </l>
            <l>Haue any Altar, Fane, or Deity. </l>
            <l>Stoope; read but this <ref target="A04637-e103480-b">h </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e103480-a" n="h" place="bottom">h Written vpon the Altar, for which wee refer you to the Page. D. 3. </note>inscription: and then veiwe </l>
            <l>To whome the Place is consecrate. Tis trew </l>
            <l>That this is IANVS Temple, and that nowe </l>
            <l>He turnes vpon the Yeare his freshest browe; </l>
            <l>That this is MARS his moneth; and these the Ides, </l>
            <l>Wherein his ANNE was honourd; Both the Tides, </l>
            <l>Titles, and Place, wee knowe: But these dead rites </l>
            <l>Are long since buried, and newe power excites </l>
            <l>More highe and hartie flames. Loe, there is hee, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000103-012-b"/>
            <l>Who brings with him a <ref target="A04637-e103580-b">i </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e103580-a" n="i" place="margin">i The Queene. to answere which in our inscription wee spake to the King MARTE MAIORI. </note>greater ANNE then shee: </l>
            <l>Whose strong and potent vertues haue <ref target="A04637-e103600-b">k </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e103600-a" n="k" place="margin">k The Temple of Ianus we apprehend to be both the house of War, &amp; Peace; of War, when it is open; of Peace when it is shut: And that there, each ouer the other is interchangeably placd, to the vicissitude of Times. </note>defac'd </l>
            <l>Sterne MARS his Statues, and vpon them plac'd </l>
            <l>His, <ref target="A04637-e103630-b">l </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e103630-a" n="l" place="margin">l Which are Peace, Rest, Liberty, Safetie, &amp;c. and were his actiuely, but the worlds passiuely. </note>and the worlds blest blessings: This hath brought </l>
            <l>Sweete Peace to sit in that bright state she ought </l>
            <l>Vnbloodie, or vntroubled; hath forc'd hence </l>
            <l>All tumults, feares, or other darke portents </l>
            <l>That might inuade weake mindes; hath made men see </l>
            <l>Once more the face of welcome Liberty: </l>
            <l>And doth (in all his present actes) restore </l>
            <l>That first pure world, made of the better Ore. </l>
            <l>Now Innocence shall cease to be the spoile </l>
            <l>Of rauenous Greatnesse, or to steepe the soile </l>
            <l>Of raised Pesantrie with teares, and bloud; </l>
            <l>No more shall rich men (for their little good) </l>
            <l>Suspect to be made guiltie; or vile Spies </l>
            <l>Enioye the lust of their so murdring eyes: </l>
            <l>Men shall put off their Yron mindes, and hearts; </l>
            <l>The Time forget his olde malicious artes </l>
            <l>With this new minute; and no print remaine </l>
            <l>Of what was thought the former ages staine. </l>
            <l>Back FLAMIN, with thy superstitious fumes, </l>
            <l>And cense not heere; Thy ignorance presumes </l>
            <l>Too much, in acting any Ethnick rite </l>
            <l>In this translated Temple: Heere no wight, </l>
            <l>To sacrifice, saue my deuotion comes, </l>
            <l>That brings insteed of those thy <ref target="A04637-e103870-b">m </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e103870-a" n="m" place="bottom">m Somewhat a strange Epithite, in our tongue, but proper to the thing; for they were only Masculine Odours, which were offerd to the Altars. Vir. Ecl. 8. Verbenasque adole pingueis, et mascula Tura. And Plin. Nat. Hist. lib. 12. cap. 14. speaking of these, hath Quod ex eo rotunditate guttam pependit, Masculum vocamus, cum alias non fere mas vocetur, vbi non sit femina: religioni tributum ne sexus alter vsurparetur. Masculum aliqui putant a specie testium dictum. See him also, lib. 34. cap. 11. And Arnob. lib. 7. aduers. Gent. Non si mille iupōdera masculi Turis incendas, &amp;c. </note>Masculine gummes. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000103-013-a"/>
            <l>My Citties heart; which shall for euer burne </l>
            <l>Vpon this Altar, and no Time shall turne </l>
            <l>The same to ashes: Heere I fixe it fast, </l>
            <l>Flame bright, flame high, and may it euer last. </l>
            <l>Whilest I, before the figure of thy Peace, </l>
            <l>Still tend the fire; and giue it quick increase </l>
            <l>With praiers, wishes, vowes; whereof be these </l>
            <l>The least, and weakest: that no Age may leese </l>
            <l>The Memory of this so rich a daye; </l>
            <l>But rather, that it henceforth yearely may </l>
            <l>Begin our Spring and with our spring the prime, </l>
            <l>And <ref target="A04637-e104000-b">n </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e104000-a" n="n" place="margin">n According to Romulus his institution, who made March the first Month and consecrated it to his Father, of whome it was called Martius: Varr. Fest. in Frag. Martius mensis initium anni fuit, et in Latio, &amp; post Romam conditam &amp;c. And Ouid. Fast. 3. A te principium Romano dicimus anno: Primus de patrio nomine mensis erit. Vox ratafit; &amp;c. See Macro lib. 1. Sat. cap. 12. and Solin. in Poly. hist. cap. 3 Quòd hoc mense mercedes exoluerint magistris, quas completus annus deberi fecisset, &amp;c. </note>first accompt of Yeares, of Months, <ref target="A04637-e104010-b">o </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e104010-a" n="o" place="margin">o Some, to whom we haue read this, haue taken it for a Tautologie, thinking Time inough express'd before, in Yeares, and Months. For whose ignorant sakes we must confesse to haue taken the better part of this trauale in noting, a thing not vsuall, neither affected of vs, but where there is necessitie, as here, to auoide their dull censures: where in Yeares and Months we alluded to that is obserued in our former note; but by Time we vnderstand the present, &amp; that from this instant, we should begin to reckon, and make this the first, of our Time. Which is also to be helpt by Emphasis. </note>of Time: </l>
            <l>And may these Ides as fortunate appeare </l>
            <l>To thee, as they to <ref target="A04637-e104040-b">p </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e104040-a" n="p" place="margin">p In which he was slaine in the Senate. </note>Caesar fatall were. </l>
            <l>Be all thy Thoughts borne perfect, and thy Hopes </l>
            <l>In their euents still crownd beyond their scopes. </l>
            <l>Let not wide Heauen that secret blessing know </l>
            <l>To giue, which shee on thee will not bestow. </l>
            <l>Blind Fortune be thy slaue; and may her store </l>
            <l>(The lesse thou seek'st it) follow thee the more. </l>
            <l>Much more I would: but see, these brazen Gates </l>
            <l>Make hast to close, as vrged by thy Fates; </l>
            <l>Here ends my Cities office, here it breakes: </l>
            <l>Yet with my tongue, and this pure heart, she speakes </l>
            <l>A short farewell; and lower then thy feete, </l>
            <l>With feruent thankes, thy royall paines doth greete. </l>
            <l>Pardon, if my abruptnesse breed disease; </l>
            <l>He merits not t'offend, that hastes to please. </l>
          </sp>
        </q>
        <pb xml:id="ep000103-013-b"/>
        <p>Ouer the Alter was written this Inscription: </p>
        <quote>
          <p>D. I. O. M. BRITANNI ARVM. IMP. PACIS. VINDICI. MARTE. MAIORI. P. P. F. S. AVGVSTO. NOVO. GENTIVM. CONIVNCTARVM. NVMINI. TVTELARI. D. A. CONSERVATRICI. ANNAE. IPSAE. PERENNAE. DEABVSQVE. VNIVERSIS. OPTATIORI. SVI FORTVNATISSIMI. THALAMI. SOCIAE. ET CONSORTI. PVLCHERIMAE. AVGVSTISSIMAE. ET H. F. P. FILIO. SVO. NOBILISSIMO. OB. ADVENTVM. AD VRBEM. HANC. SVAM. EXPECTATISSIMVM. GRATISSIMVM. CELEBRATISSIMVM. CVIVS. NON. RADII. SED SOLES. POTIVS. FVNESSIMAM. NVPER. AERIS. INTEMPERIEM. SERENARVNT S. P. Q. L. VOTIS. X. VOTIS. XX. ARDENTISSIMIS. L. M. HANC. ARAM. P. </p>
        </quote>
        <pb xml:id="ep000103-014-a"/>
        <p>And vpon the Gate being shut, </p>
        <quote>
          <p>IMP. IACOBVS MAX. CAESAR AVG. P. P. PACE POPVLO BRITANNICO TERRA MARIQVE PARTA IANVM CLVSIT. S. C. </p>
        </quote>
      </div>
      <div type="part" xml:id="ep000103-e104250">
        <p>THus hath both Court-Towne-and Countrey-Reader, our portion of deuise for the Cittie; neither are we ashamed to professe it, being assured well of the difference betweene it and Pageantry. If the Mechanick part yet standing, giue it any distaste in the wrye mouthes of the Time, we pardon them; for their owne ambitious ignorance doth punish them inough. From hence we will turne ouer a new leafe with you, and lead you to the Pegme in the Strand, a worke thought on, begun, and perfected in twelue dayes. </p>
        <pb xml:id="ep000103-014-b"/>
        <p>THe Inuention was a Raine-bow, the Moone, Sunne, and those seauen Starres, which antiquitie hath stil'd the Pleiades, or Vergiliae, aduanced betweene two Magnificent Pyramid's of 70. foote in height, on which were drawne his Maiesties seuerall pedigrees Eng. and Scot. To which body (being framd before) we were to apt our soule. And finding that one of these seauen lights, Electra, is rarely or not at all to be seene, (as Ouid. lib. 4. Fast. affirmeth. <quote>
            <l>Pleiades incipient humeros releuare paternos: </l>
            <l>Quae septem dici, sex tamen esse solent. </l>
          </quote>And by and by after, <quote>
            <l>Siue quòd Electra Troiae spectare ruinas </l>
            <l>Non tulit: aute oculos opposuitque manum. </l>
          </quote>And Festus Auien. <ref target="A04637-e104340-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e104340-a" place="margin">Paraph. in Arat Phaenom. </note>
          <quote>
            <l>Fama vetus septem memor at genitore creatas </l>
            <l>Longaeuo: sex se rutila inter sidera tantùm </l>
            <l>Sustollunt, &amp;c. </l>
          </quote>And beneath <quote>
            <l>— cerni sex solas carmine Mynthes </l>
            <l>Asserit: Electram coelo abscessisse profundo, &amp;c.) </l>
          </quote>We ventred to follow this authoritie; and made her the speaker: presenting her hanging in the ayre, in figure of a Comet; according to Anonymus. Electra non sustinens videre casum pronepotum sugerit; vnde &amp; illam disso lutis crinibus propter luctum ire asserunt, et propter comas quidam Cometen appellant. </p>
        <q type="speech">
          <pb xml:id="ep000103-015-a"/>
          <label>The speach. </label>
          <sp who="#ep000103-electra" xml:id="ep000103-e104450">
            <speaker>Electra. </speaker>
            <l>THe long <ref target="A04637-e104470-b">a </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e104470-a" n="a" place="margin">a Fest. Aui. paraph. Pars ait Idææ deflentem incendia Troiae, et numerosa suae lugentem funerae gentis, Electram tetris moestum dare nubibus orbem. Besides the reference to antiquity, this speach might be vnderstood by Allegorie of the Towne here, that had beene so ruined with sicknesse, &amp;c. </note>Laments, I spent for ruin'd Troy, </l>
            <l>Are dried; and now mine eyes run teares of Ioy. </l>
            <l>No more shall men suppose Electra dead, </l>
            <l>Though from the consort of her sisters fled </l>
            <l>Vnto the <ref target="A04637-e104520-b">b </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e104520-a" n="b" place="margin">b Hyginus. Sed postquam Troia fuit capta, &amp; Progenies cius quae à Dardano fuit euersa, dolore permotam ab his se remouisse, &amp; in circulo qui Arcticus dicitur constitisse, &amp;c. </note>Arctick circle, here to grace, </l>
            <l>And guild this day with her <ref target="A04637-e104540-b">c </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e104540-a" n="c" place="bottom">c Electra signifies Serenity it selfe, and is compounded of <seg xml:lang="unk">{non-Roman} {non-Roman} {non-Roman} </seg>which is the Sunne, and <seg xml:lang="unk">{non-Roman} {non-Roman} {non-Roman} </seg>that signifies serene. She is mentioned to be Anima sphaerae solis, by Proclus. Com. in Hesiod. </note>serenest Face: </l>
            <l>And see, my <ref target="A04637-e104580-b">d </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e104580-a" n="d" place="bottom">d She is also faind to be the Mother of the Rainbow. Nascitur enim Iris ex aqua et serenitate, è refractione radiorum scilicet: Arist. in Meteorol. </note>daughter Iris hasts to throw </l>
            <l>Her Rose at wings, in compasse of a bow, </l>
            <l>About our state, as <ref target="A04637-e104610-b">e </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e104610-a" n="e" place="bottom">e Val. Flac. Argonaut. 1. makes the Rainbow indicum serenitatis. Emicuit reserata dies, coelumque resoluit. Arcus, &amp; in summos redierunt nubila montes. </note>signe of my approche </l>
            <l>Attracting to her seate from <ref target="A04637-e104630-b">f </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e104630-a" n="f" place="bottom">f A name of the Sunne. Stat. The. lib. 1. torquentem cornua Mithran. And Martian. Capel. lib. 3. de nup. Mer. &amp; Phil. Te Serapim Nilus, Memphis veneratur Osirin; Dissona sacra Mithran, &amp;c. </note>Mithras coach, </l>
            <l>A thousand different, and particular hewes, </l>
            <l>Which shee throughout her body doth diffuse. </l>
            <l>The Sunne, as loath to part from this halfe spheare, </l>
            <l>Stands still; and Phoebe labors to appeare </l>
            <l>In all as bright (if not as rich) as hee: </l>
            <l>And, for a note of more serenity, </l>
            <l>My sixe <ref target="A04637-e104710-b">g </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e104710-a" n="g" place="bottom">g Alcyone,. Celaeno, Taygete, Asterope, Merope, Maia. which are also said to bee the soules of the other sphaeres, as Electra of the Sunne. Proclus. ibi. in com. Alcyone Veneris. Celaeno Saturni. Taygete Lunae. Asterop. Iouis. Merope Martis. Maia Mercurij. </note>faire Sisters hether shift their lights; </l>
            <l>To do this hower the vtmost of her Rites. </l>
            <l>Where least the captious, or prophane might doubt, </l>
            <l>How these cleare heauenly bodyes come about </l>
            <l>All to be seene at once; yet neithers light </l>
            <l>Eclips'd, or shadow'd by the others sight: </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000103-015-b"/>
            <l>Let Ignorance know, great King, this Day is thine, </l>
            <l>And doth admit no Night; but all do shine </l>
            <l>As well nocturnall, as diurnall fiers, </l>
            <l>To adde vnto the flame of our desiers. </l>
            <l>Which are (now thou hast closd vp <ref target="A04637-e104820-b">h </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e104820-a" n="h" place="margin">h Alluding backe to that of our Temple. </note>IANVS gates, </l>
            <l>And giu'n so generall peace to all estates) </l>
            <l>That no offensiue mist, or cloudie staine </l>
            <l>May mixe with splendor of thy golden raigne; </l>
            <l>But, as th' ast free'd thy <ref target="A04637-e104870-b">i </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e104870-a" n="i" place="margin">i London. </note>Chamber, from the noyse </l>
            <l>Of Warre and Tumult; thou wilt powre those ioyes </l>
            <l>Vpon <ref target="A04637-e104900-b">k </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e104900-a" n="k" place="margin">k His Citty of Westminster, in whose name, and at whose charge, together with the Duchie of Lancaster this Arch was erected. </note>this Place, which claimes to be <ref target="A04637-e104910-b">l </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e104910-a" n="l" place="bottom">l Since here, they not only sate being Crownd, but also first receiued their Crownes. </note>the Seate </l>
            <l>Of all thy Kingly race: the Cabinet </l>
            <l>To all thy Counsels; and the iudging Chayre </l>
            <l>To this thy speciall Kingdome. Whose so faire </l>
            <l>And wholsome Lawes, in euery Court, shall striue </l>
            <l>By Aequity, and their first Innocence to thriue; </l>
            <l>The base and guiltie bribes of guiltier men </l>
            <l>Shall be throwne back, and Iustice looke, as when </l>
            <l>She lou'd the earth, and feard not to be sold </l>
            <l>For that, <ref target="A04637-e105010-b">m </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e105010-a" n="m" place="bottom">m Hor. Car. lib. 4. Ode 9. Ducentis ad se cuncta pecuniae. </note>which worketh all things to it, Gold. </l>
            <l>The Dam of other euils, Auarice </l>
            <l>Shall here lock downe her Iawes, and that rude vice </l>
            <l>Of ignorant, and pittied Greatnesse, Pride, </l>
            <l>Decline with shame; Ambition now shall hide </l>
            <l>Her face in dust, as dedicate to sleepe, </l>
            <l>That in great Portalls wont her watch to keepe. </l>
            <l>All ills shall flie the light: Thy Court be free </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000103-016-a"/>
            <l>No lesse from Enuie, then from Flatterie; </l>
            <l>All Tumult, Faction, and harsh Discord cease, </l>
            <l>That might perturbe the musique of thy Peace: </l>
            <l>The querulous Nature shall no longer finde </l>
            <l>Roome for his Thoughts: One pure concent of minde </l>
            <l>Shall flowe in euery brest, and not the Ayre, </l>
            <l>Sunne, Moone, or Starres shine more serenely faire. </l>
            <l>This from that lowd, blest Oracle, I sing </l>
            <l>Who here, and first pronounc'd, thee Brittaines King </l>
            <l>Long maist thou liue, and see me thus appeare, </l>
            <l>As omenous <ref target="A04637-e105200-b">n </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e105200-a" n="n" place="margin">n For our more authoritie to induce her thus, See Fest. Auien. paraph. in Arat. speaking of Electra, Nonnumquam Oceani tamen istam surgere ab vndis, In conuexa poli, sed sede carere sororum; Atque os discretum procul edere, detestatam Germanosque, choros sobolis lachrymare ruinas, Diffusamque comas corni, crinisque soluti Monstrari effigie, &amp;c. </note>a Comet, from my Spheare, </l>
            <l>Vnto thy raigne; as that <ref target="A04637-e105220-b">o </ref>
              <note anchored="true" corresp="A04637-e105220-a" n="o" place="bottom">o All Comets were not fatall, some were fortunatly ominous, as this to which we allude; and wherefore we haue Plinies testimonie. Nat. Histo. lib. 2. cap. 25. Cometes in vno totius orbis loco colitur in templo Romae, admodum faustus Diuo Augusto iudicatus ab ipso: qui incipiente eo, apparuit ludis quos faciebat Veneri Genetrici, non multo post obitum patris Caesaris, in Collegio ab eo instituto. Namque his verbis id gaudium prodidit. Iisipsis ludorum meorum diebus, sydus crinitum per septem dies in regione Coeli, quae sub septentrionibus est, conspectum. Id oriebatur circa vndecimam horam dici, clarumque &amp; omnibus terris conspicuum fuit. Eo sydere significari vulgus credidit, Caesaris animam inter Deorum immortalium numina receptam: quo nomine id insigne simulacro capitis eius, quod mox in foro consecrauimus adiectum est. Hec Ille in publicum, interiore gaudio sibi illum natum, seque in conasci inter pretatus est. Et si verum fatemur, salutare id terris fuit. </note>did auspicate </l>
            <l>So lasting glory to Augustus state. </l>
          </sp>
        </q>
        <trailer>The end. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="supplied_by_editor">
        <head>Notes, typically marginal, from the original text</head>
        <div corresp="A04637-e100030" xml:id="ep000103-e100030-n">
          <head>Notes for div A04637_01-e100030</head>
        </div>
        <div corresp="A04637-e101320" xml:id="ep000103-e101320-n">
          <head>Notes for div A04637_01-e101320</head>
        </div>
        <div corresp="A04637-e102600" xml:id="ep000103-e102600-n">
          <head>Notes for div A04637_01-e102600</head>
        </div>
        <div corresp="A04637-e104250" xml:id="ep000103-e104250-n">
          <head>Notes for div A04637_01-e104250</head>
        </div>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
