<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000110" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Hymenaei</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Ben</forename>
            <surname>Jonson</surname>
          </persName>
          <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q193857</idno>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A04654.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="A04654-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull n="TCP source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">Hymenaei: or The solemnities of masque, and barriers magnificently performed on the eleventh, and twelfth nights, from Christmas; at court: to the auspicious celebrating of the marriage-vnion, betweene Robert, Earle of Essex, and the Lady Frances, second daughter to the most noble Earle of Suffolke. By Ben: Ionson.</title>
                <author>Jonson, Ben, 1573?-1637.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>24 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
                <date>2003 January (TCP phase 1)</date>
                <idno type="marc">99844880</idno>
                <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 14774.</idno>
                <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 237(a).</idno>
                <idno type="vid">9729</idno>
                <idno type="DLPS">A04654</idno>
                <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2240854676</idno>
                <availability>
                  <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
                </availability>
              </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
            <biblFull n="printed source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">Hymenaei: or The solemnities of masque, and barriers magnificently performed on the eleventh, and twelfth nights, from Christmas; at court: to the auspicious celebrating of the marriage-vnion, betweene Robert, Earle of Essex, and the Lady Frances, second daughter to the most noble Earle of Suffolke. By Ben: Ionson.</title>
                <title type="alt">Hymenaei</title>
                <title type="alt">Solemnities of masque, and barriers.</title>
                <author>Jonson, Ben, 1573?-1637.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[44] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Printed by Valentine Sims for Thomas Thorp,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication_date">1606.</date>
                <date type="creation_date">1606</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>
                  <p>Partly in verse.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Signatures: A-E4 F2.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>The first leaf is blank.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</p>
                </note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <person xml:id="ep000110-hymen">
            <persName>Hymen</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000110-reason">
            <persName>Reason</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000110-truth">
            <persName>Truth</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000110-opinion">
            <persName>Opinion</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000110-angel">
            <persName>Angel</persName>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1606">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
    <listRelation>
      <relation name="wikidata"
                   active="https://dracor.org/entity/ep000110"
                   passive="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q5956420"/>
    </listRelation>
  </standOff>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000110-e100030">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000110-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000110-001-b"/>
        <p>HYMENAEI: OR The Solemnities of Masque, and Barriers, </p>
        <p>Magnificently performed on the eleventh, and twelfth Nights, from Christmas; </p>
        <p>At Court: </p>
        <p>To the auspicious celebrating of the Marriage-vnion, betweene Robert, Earle of Essex, and the Lady Frances, second Daughter to the most noble Earle of Suffolke. </p>
        <p>By BEN: IONSON. </p>
        <p>Iam veniet Virgo, iam dicetur Hymenaeus. </p>
        <p>AT LONDON Printed by Valentine Sims for Thomas Thorp. 1606. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="text" xml:id="ep000110-e100120">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000110-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000110-002-b"/>
        <head>HYMENAEI. </head>
        <p>IT is a noble and iust advantage, that the things subjected to Vnderstanding have of those which are objected to Sense, that the one sorte are but momentarie, and meerely taking; the other impressing, and lasting: Else the Glory of all these Solemnities had perish'd like a Blaze, and gone out, in the Beholders eyes. So short-liv'd are the Bodies of all Thinges, in comparison of their Soules. And, though Bodies oft-times have the ill lucke to be sensually preferr'd, they find afterwards, the good fortune (when Soules live) to be vtterly forgotten. This it is hath made the most royall Princes, and greatest Persons, (who are commonly the Personaters of these Actions) not onely studious of Riches, and Magnificence in the outward Celebration, or Shew; (which rightly becomes them) but curious after the most high, and hearty Inventions, to furnish the inward parts: (and those grounded vpon Antiquitie, and solide Learnings) which, though their Voyce be taught to sound to present Occasions, their Sense, or dooth, or should alwayes lay holde on more remov'd Mysteries. And, howsoever some may squeamishly cry out, that all Endevor of Learning, and Sharpnesse in these transitory <pb xml:id="ep000110-003-a"/>Devises especially, where it steppes beyond their little, or (let me not wrong 'hem) no Braine at all is superfluous; I am contented, these fastidious Stomachs should leave my full Tables, and enioy at home, their cleane empty Trenchers, fittest for such airy Tasts: where perhaps a few Italian Herbs, pick'd vp, &amp; made into a Sallade, may find sweeter acceptance, than al, the most norishing, and sound Meates of the world. </p>
        <p>For these Mens palates, let not mee answere, O Muses. It is not my fault, if I fill them out Nectar, and they runne to Metheglin. <quote>Vaticana bibant, si delectentur. </quote>
        </p>
        <p>All the curtesie I can doe them, is to cry, againe; <quote>Praetereant, si quid non facit ad stomachum. </quote>
        </p>
        <p>As I wil, from the thought of them, to my better Subject. </p>
        <p>ON the Night of the Masques (which were two, One of Men, the Other of Women) the Scene being drawne, there was first discovered an Altar; vpon which was inscribed, in Letters of Gold. </p>
        <quote>
          <ref target="A04654-e100210-b">a </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e100210-a" n="a" place="margin">a Mystically implying, that both It, the Place, and all the succeeding Ceremonies were sacred to Marriage, or VNION; over which IVNO was praesident: to whom there was the like Altar erected, at Rome, as she was called IVGA IVNO, in the Street, which thence, was named lugarius. See Fest. and, at which Altar, the Rite was to ioyne the maried Paire with bands of silke, in signe of future Concord. </note>I. oni. imae. imae. VNIONI SACR. </quote>
        <p>To this Altar entred five Pages, attir'd in white, <pb xml:id="ep000110-003-b"/>bearing <ref target="A04654-e100230-b">a </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e100230-a" n="a" place="margin">a Those were the Quinque Cerei, which Plutarch in his Quaest. Roman. mentions to be vsed in Nuptialls. </note>five Tapers of Virgine Waxe; Behinde them, One representing a Bridegroome: His <ref target="A04654-e100240-b">b </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e100240-a" n="b" place="margin">b The dressing of the Bridegroome (with the Antients) was chiefly noted in that, quód tonderetur. lu. Sat. 6. lámque à Tonsore magistro Pecteris. And Lucan. li. 2. Where he makes Cato negligent of the Ceremonies in Marriage, sayth, Ille nec horrificam sancto dimovit abore Caesariem. </note>haire short, and bound with party-coloured ribbands, and gold twist: His Garments purple, and white. </p>
        <p>On the other hand, entred HYMEN (the God of Marriage) in a saffron-coloured Robe, his vnder-Vestures white, his Sockes yellow, a yellow Veile of silke on his left arme, his Head crowned with Roses, and <ref target="A04654-e100260-b">c </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e100260-a" n="c" place="margin">c See how he is called out, by Catullus in Nupt. Iul. &amp; Manl. Cinge tempora floribus Suave olentis amaraci &amp;c. </note>Marioram, in his right hand a Torch of <ref target="A04654-e100270-b">d </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e100270-a" n="d" place="margin">d For so I preserve the Reading, there, in Catull. Pineam quate taedam, rather than to change it Spineam; and mooved by the authoritie of Virg. in Ciri, where he sayes, Pronuba nec castos incendet Pinus amores: and Ovid. Fast. lib 2. Expectet puros pinea taeda dies. Though I deny not, there was also Spineataeda, which Plinie calles Nuptiarum facibus auspicatissimam. Nat. Hist. lib. 16. cap 18. and whereof Sextus Pompeius Fest. hath left so particular testimonie. For which, see the following Note. </note>Pine tree. </p>
        <p>After him <ref target="A04654-e100290-b">e </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e100290-a" n="e" place="margin">e This (by the Antients) was called Camillus, quasi Minister (for so that signified in the Hetruriā tong) and was one of the three, which by Sex. Pompei. were said to be Patrimi &amp; Matrimi, Pueri praetestati tres, qui nubentem deducunt: Vnus, qui facem praefert ex spinâ albâ, Duo qui tenent nubentem. To which conferre that of Varr. lib. 6. de lingua Lat. Dicitur in nuptijs Camillus, qui Cumerum fert: as also that of Fest. lib. 3. Cumeram vocabant Antiqui vas quoddam, quod opertum in Nuptijs ferebant, in quo erant nubentis vtensilia, quod &amp; Camillum dicebant: eò quod sacrorum Ministrum <seg xml:lang="unk">{non-Roman} {non-Roman} {non-Roman} </seg>appellabant. </note>a Youth, attired in white, bearing another Light, of white Thorne; vnder his arme, a litle wicker-Flasket, shut: Behind him two Others, in white, the one bearing a Distaffe, the other a Spindle. Betwixt these a Personated Bride, supported, her haire flowing, and loose, sprinckled with grey; on her head a Gyrland of Roses, like a Turret; her Garments white: and, on her back, a Weathers <pb xml:id="ep000110-004-a"/>Fleece hanging downe: Her Zone, or Girdle about her waste of white wooll, fastned with the Herculean Knot. </p>
        <p>In the middst went the <ref target="A04654-e100320-b">a </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e100320-a" n="a" place="margin">a Auspices wer those that hand fasted the maried Couple; that wished them good lucke; that took care for the Dowry: and heard them professe that they came together, for the Cause of Children. Iuven. Sat 10. Veniet cum signatoribus Auspex. And Lucan. lib. 2. Iungunturtaciti, contentique Auspice Bruto. They were also stilld Pronubi, Proxenetae, Paranymphi. </note>Auspices; after them, two that sung, in severall colored silks. Of which, One bore the Water, the Other the Fire: Last of all the <ref target="A04654-e100330-b">b </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e100330-a" n="b" place="margin">b The Custome of Musike at Nuptials, is cleare in all Antiquitie. Ter. Adel. Act. 5. Verum hoc mihi mora est, Tibicina, &amp; Hymenaeum qui cantent. And Claud. in Epithal. Ducant pervigiles carmina Tibiae &amp;c. </note>Musitians, diversly attired, all crowned with Roses; and, with this Song beganne. </p>
        <q type="song">
          <label>SONG. </label>
          <l>BId all profane away; </l>
          <l>None here may stay </l>
          <l>To view our Mysteries, </l>
          <l>But, who themselues have beene, </l>
          <l>Or will, in Time, be seene </l>
          <l>The selfe-same Sacrifice. </l>
          <l>For VNION, Mistris of these Rites, </l>
          <l>Will be observ'd with Eyes, </l>
          <l>As simple as her Nights. </l>
          <lg>
            <head>Chorus. </head>
            <l>Flie then, all profane, away, </l>
            <l>Flie farre off, as hath the Day; </l>
            <l>Night her Cortine doth display, </l>
            <l>And this is HYMENS Holiday. </l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <pb xml:id="ep000110-004-b"/>
        <p>The Song being ended, HYMEN presented him selfe formost; and, after some signe of Admiration, beganne to speake. </p>
        <sp who="#ep000110-hymen" xml:id="ep000110-e100520">
          <speaker>HYMEN. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>WHat more than vsuall Light </l>
            <l>(Throughout the Place extended) </l>
            <l>Makes IVNO'S Fane so bright! </l>
            <l>Is there some greater Deitie descended? </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Orraigne, on earth, those Powers </l>
            <l>So rich, as with their beames </l>
            <l>Grace VNION more than our's; </l>
            <l>And bound her Influence, in their happier streames? </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Tis so: This same is he, </l>
            <l>The King, and Priest of Peace! </l>
            <l>And that his Empresse, she, </l>
            <l>That sits so crowned with her owne increase! </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>O you, whose better Blisses, </l>
            <l>Have proov'd the strict embrace </l>
            <l>Of VNION, with chaste kisses, </l>
            <l>And seene it flowe so in your happy Race; </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>That know, how well it bindes </l>
            <l>The fighting Seedes of Things, </l>
            <l>Winnes Natures, Sexes, Mindes, </l>
            <l>And ev'ry discord in true Musique brings: </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <pb xml:id="ep000110-005-a"/>
            <l>Sit now propitious Aydes, </l>
            <l>To Rites, so duely priz'd; </l>
            <l>And view two Noble Maydes, </l>
            <l>Of different Sexe, to VNION sacrifiz'd. </l>
            <l>In honour of that blest Estate, </l>
            <l>Which all Good Mindes should celebrate. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <p>Here out of a Microcosme, or Globe (figuring Man) with a kind of contentious Musique, issued forth the first Masque, of eight Men, whose Names in order, as they were then Marshalled, by Couples, I have Heraldry enough to set downe. <list>
            <item>1 L. WILLOVGHBY. </item>
            <item>2 LO. WALDEN. </item>
            <item>3 Sir IAMES HAY. </item>
            <item>4 Ear. of MONGOMERY. </item>
            <item>Sir THOMAS HOWARD. </item>
            <item>Sir THOMAS SOMERSET. </item>
            <item>Ear. of ARVNDELL. </item>
            <item>Sir IOHN ASHLY. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>These represented the foure <ref target="A04654-e100960-b">a </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e100960-a" n="a" place="margin">a That they were personated in men, hath (already) come vnder some Gramatical exception. But there is more than Gramar to release it. For, besides that Humores and Affectus are both Masculine in Genere, not one of the Specialls, but in some Language is knowne by a Masculine word: Againe, when their Influences are common to both Sexes, and more generally impetuous in the Male, I see not, why they should not, so, be more properly presented. And, for the Allegory, though here it be very cleare, and such as might well escape a Candle, yet because there are some, must complain of Darknes, that have but thick Eies, I am contented to hold them this Light First, as in Naturall Bodies, so likewise in Mindes, there is no disease, or distemperature, but is caused either by som abounding Humor, or perverse Affection; After the same maner, in Politike Bodies (where Order, Ceremony, State, Reverence, Devotion, are Parts of the Mind) by the diffrence, or praedominant Wil of what we (Metaphorically) call Humors, and Affections, all things are troubled and confusd. These, therefore, were Tropically brought in, before Marriage, as disturbers of that Mysticall Body, and the Rites, which were Soule vnto it; that afterwards, in Marriage, being dutifully tempted by hir Power, they might more fully celebrate the happines of such as live in that sweet Vnion, to the harmonious Laws of Nature, and Reason. </note>Humors, &amp; foure Affections, all gloriously attired, distinguisht only, <pb xml:id="ep000110-005-b"/>by their severall Ensignes, and Colours; And, dauncing out on the Stage, in their returne, at the end of their Daunce, drew all their swordes, offered to encompasse the Altar, and disturbe the Ceremonies. at which HYMEN troubled, spake, </p>
        <sp who="#ep000110-hymen" xml:id="ep000110-e100970">
          <speaker>HYMEN. </speaker>
          <l>SAve, save the Virgins; Keepe your hallow'd Lights </l>
          <l>Vntouch'd: And with their flame defend our Rites. </l>
          <l>The foure vntempred Humors are broke out: </l>
          <l>And, with their wild Affections, goe about </l>
          <l>To ravish all Religion. If there be </l>
          <l>A Power, like REASON, left in that huge Bodie, </l>
          <l>Or little World of Man, from whence these came, </l>
          <l>Looke forth, and with thy bright and <ref target="A04654-e101060-b">a </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e101060-a" n="a" place="margin">a Alluding to that opinion of Pythagoras; who held all Reason, all Knowledge, all Discourse of the Soule to be mere Number. See Plut. de Plac. Phil. </note>numerous flame </l>
          <l>Instruct their Darkenesse, make them know, and see, </l>
          <l>In wronging these, they have rebell'd gainst thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>Hereat, REASON seated in the top of the Globe (as in the braine, or highest parte of Man) figur'd in a venerable Personage, her haire white, and trayling to her waste, crowned with Lights, her Garments blew, and semined with Starres, girded vnto her with a white Bend, fill'd with Arithmeticall Figures, in one hand bearing a Lampe, in the other a bright Sword, descended, and spake. </p>
        <sp who="#ep000110-reason" xml:id="ep000110-e101100">
          <speaker>REASON. </speaker>
          <l>FOrbeare your rude attempt; what Ignorance </l>
          <l>Could yeelde you so profane, as to advance </l>
          <l>One thought in Act, against these Mysteries? </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000110-006-a"/>
          <l>Are VNION'S <ref target="A04654-e101150-b">a </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e101150-a" n="a" place="margin">a <seg xml:lang="unk">{non-Roman} {non-Roman} {non-Roman}</seg>, with the Greekes value the same, that Ceremoniae with the Latines; and imply all sorts of Rites: howsoeuer (abusively) they have beene made particular to Bacchus. See Serv. to that of Vir. Aeneid. 4. qualis commotis excita sacris Thyas. </note>Orgies of so slender price? </l>
          <l>She that makes Soules, with Bodies, mixe in Love, </l>
          <l>Contracts the World in one, and therein IOVE; </l>
          <l>Is <ref target="A04654-e101200-b">b </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e101200-a" n="b" place="margin">b Mac. in som. Scipion. lib. 1. </note>Spring, and End of all Things yet, most strange! </l>
          <l>Her selfe nor suffers Spring, nor End, nor Change. </l>
          <l>No wonder, they were you, that were so bold; </l>
          <l>For none but Humors and Affections would </l>
          <l>Have dar'd so rash a venture. You will say </l>
          <l>It was your Zeale, that gave your powers the sway; </l>
          <l>And vrge the masqued, and disguisd pretence </l>
          <l>Of saving Bloud, and succ'ring Innocence? </l>
          <l>So want of Knowledge, still, begetteth iarres, </l>
          <l>When humorous Earthlings will controle the Starres. </l>
          <l>Informe your selves, with safer Reverence, </l>
          <l>To these mysterious Rites, whose mysticke sense </l>
          <l>REASON (which all things but it selfe) confounds) </l>
          <l>Shall cleare vnto you, from th'authentique grounds. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>At this, the Humors &amp; Affections sheathed their swordes, and retir'd amazed to the sides of the Stage, while HYMEN began to ranke the Persons, and order the Ceremonies: And REASON proceeded to speake. </p>
        <sp who="#ep000110-reason" xml:id="ep000110-e101350">
          <speaker>REASON. </speaker>
          <l>THe Paire, which doe each other side, </l>
          <l>Though (yet) some space doth them divide, </l>
          <l>This happy Night must both make one </l>
          <l>Blest Sacrifice, to VNION. </l>
          <l>Nor is this Altar but a Signe </l>
          <l>Of one more soft, and more divine </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000110-006-b"/>
          <l>The <ref target="A04654-e101430-b">a </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e101430-a" n="a" place="margin">a Properly that, which was made ready for the new-married Bride, and was calld Genialis, à Generandis liberis. Ser. in 6 Aeneid. </note>Geniall Bed, where HYMEN keepes </l>
          <l>The solemne Orgies, voyd of sleepes: </l>
          <l>And wildest CVPID, waking, hovers </l>
          <l>With adoration 'twixt the Lovers. </l>
          <l>The Tead of white, and blooming Thorne, </l>
          <l>In token of increase is borne: </l>
          <l>As <ref target="A04654-e101500-b">b </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e101500-a" n="b" place="margin">b See Ovid. Fast. lib. 6. Sic fatus, spinam, quâ tristes pellere pesset A foribus noxas, haec erat alba, dedit. </note>also, with the omenous Light, </l>
          <l>To fright all Malice from the Night. </l>
          <l>Like are the <ref target="A04654-e101530-b">c </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e101530-a" n="c" place="margin">c Plutarch. in Quaest. Rom. And Var. lib. 4 de ling. Lat. </note>Fire, and Water set; </l>
          <l>That, ev'n as Moysture, mixt with Heate, </l>
          <l>Helpes every Naturall Birth, to life; </l>
          <l>So, for their Race, ioyne Man, and Wife. </l>
          <l>The <ref target="A04654-e101580-b">d </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e101580-a" n="d" place="margin">d Pun. Nat. Hist. li. 21. ca. 8 </note>blushing Veyle shewes shamefastnesse </l>
          <l>Th'ingenuous Virgin should professe </l>
          <l>At meeting with the Man: Her Haire </l>
          <l>That <ref target="A04654-e101620-b">e </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e101620-a" n="e" place="margin">e Pomp. Fest. Briss Hotto. de Rit. Nup. </note>flowes so liberall, and so faire, </l>
          <l>Is shed with grey, to intimate </l>
          <l>She entreth to a Matrons state. </l>
          <l>For which those <ref target="A04654-e101660-b">f </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e101660-a" n="f" place="margin">f Var lib. 6. de ling. Lat. and Fest. in Frag. </note>Vtensills are borne. </l>
          <l>And, that shee should not Labour scorne, </l>
          <l>Her selfe a <ref target="A04654-e101690-b">g </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e101690-a" n="g" place="margin">g Fest. ibid. </note>Snowie Fleece doth weare, </l>
          <l>And these her <ref target="A04654-e101710-b">h </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e101710-a" n="h" place="margin">h Plutarch. in Quaest. Rom. &amp; in Romul. </note>Rocke and Spindle beare, </l>
          <l>To shew, that Nothing, which is good, </l>
          <l>Gives checke vnto the highest blood. </l>
          <l>The <ref target="A04654-e101750-b">i </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e101750-a" n="i" place="margin">i Plin. Nat. Hist. li. 8. ca. 48 </note>Zone of wooll about her waste, </l>
          <l>Which, in contrary Circles cast, </l>
          <l>Doth meete in one <ref target="A04654-e101780-b">k </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e101780-a" n="k" place="margin">k That was Nodus Herculeanus, which the Husband, at night, vntied in signe of good fortune, that hee might be happie in propagation of Issue, as Hercules was, who left seventie Children. See Fest. in voc. Cingul. </note>strong knot, that bindes, </l>
          <l>Tells you, so should all Married Mindes. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000110-007-a"/>
          <l>And lastly, these five Waxen Lights </l>
          <l>Imply Perfection in the Rites; </l>
          <l>For <ref target="A04654-e101830-b">a </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e101830-a" n="a" place="margin">a Plutarch. in Quaest. Rom. </note>Five the speciall Number is, </l>
          <l>Whence halow'd VNION claymes her blisse. </l>
          <l>As being all the Summe, that growes </l>
          <l>From the vnited strengths, of those </l>
          <l>Which <ref target="A04654-e101880-b">b </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e101880-a" n="b" place="margin">b See Mart. Capel. lib. 6. de Nupt. Phil. &amp; Mer. in numero Pentade. </note>Male, and Female Numbers wee </l>
          <l>Do stile, and are First Two, and Three. </l>
          <l>Which, ioyned thus, you cannot sever </l>
          <l>In aequall partes, but One will ever </l>
          <l>Remaine as common; so we see </l>
          <l>The binding-force of Vnitie: </l>
          <l>For which alone, the peace-full Gods </l>
          <l>In Number, alwayes, love the oddes; </l>
          <l>And even partes as much despise, </l>
          <l>Since out of them all Discords rise. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>Here, the vpper part of the Scene, which was all of Cloudes, and made artificially to swell, and ride like the Racke, beganne to open; and, the Ayre clearing, in the toppe thereof was discovered <ref target="A04654-e101990-b">c </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e101990-a" n="c" place="margin">c With the Greekes; IVNO was interpreted to be the Ayre it selfe. And so Macr. de som. Scipio. li. 1. c. 17. calls her. Mar. Cap. surnames her Aeria, of reigning there. </note>IVNO, sitting in a Throne, supported by two beautifull <ref target="A04654-e102000-b">d </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e102000-a" n="d" place="margin">d They were sacred to IVNO, in respect of their colors, and temper so like the Aire. Ovid. de Arte Amand. Laudatas ostendit aves Iunonia pennas And Met. li. 2. Habili Saturnia curru Ingreditur liquidum pavonibus aethera pictis. </note>Peacockes, her attire rich, and like a <ref target="A04654-e102010-b">e </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e102010-a" n="e" place="margin">e Shee was call'd Regina IVNO with the Latines, because she was Soror &amp; Coniux IOVIS, Deorum &amp; hominum Regis. </note>Queene, a <ref target="A04654-e102020-b">f </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e102020-a" n="f" place="margin">f Reade Apul. describing her, in his 10, of the Asse. </note>white Diademe on her head, from whence descended a Veyle, and that bound with <pb xml:id="ep000110-007-b"/>a <ref target="A04654-e102030-b">a </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e102030-a" n="a" place="margin">a After the manner of the antique Bend; the varied colors implying the severall mutations of the Ayre, as Showres, Dewes, Serenitie, Force of winds, clouds Tempest, Snow, Hayle, Lightning, Thunder, all which had their noises signified in hir Timbrell: the faculty of causing these being ascribed to her, by Virg. Aeneid. lib. 4. where he makes her say, His ego nigrantem commista grandine nimbum Desuper infundam, &amp; tonitru Coelum omne ciebo. </note>Fascia of severall color'd silkes, set with all sorts of Iewelles, and raisd in the top with <ref target="A04654-e102040-b">b </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e102040-a" n="b" place="margin">b Lillies were sacred to IVNO, as being made white with her milke, that fell vpon the earth, when IOVE tooke HERCVLES away, whome by stealth he had layd to her Breast: the Rose was also call'd Iunonia. </note>Lillies, and Roses; In her right hand she held a Scepter, in the other a Timbrell, at her golden feete the <ref target="A04654-e102050-b">c </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e102050-a" n="c" place="margin">c So was she figur'd at Argos, as a Stepmother insulting on the spoyles of her two Privigni, BACCHVS, and HERCVLES. </note>Hide of a Lion was placed: Round about her sate the Spirites of the ayre, in severall colours, making Musique, Above her the Region of Fire, with a continuall Motion, was seene to whirle circularly, and IVPITER standing in the Toppe (figuring the Heaven) brandishing his Thunder: Beneath her the Raine-bowe, IRIS, and, on the two sides eight Ladies, attired richly, and alike in the most celestiall colours, who represented her Powers, as she is the <ref target="A04654-e102060-b">d </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e102060-a" n="d" place="margin">d See Virg. Aeneid. lib. 4. IVNONI ante omnes cui vinela iugalia curae: and in another place, Dant signum prima &amp; Tellus, &amp; Pronuba IVNO: And Ovid. in Phill. Epist. IVNONEM-que terris quae praesidet alma Maritis. </note>Governesse of Marriage, and made the second Masque. All which, vpon the discoverie, REASON made narration of. </p>
        <sp who="#ep000110-reason" xml:id="ep000110-e102070">
          <speaker>REASON. </speaker>
          <l>ANd see, where IVNO, whose great Name </l>
          <l>Is VNIO, in the Anagram, </l>
          <l>Displayes her glistering State, and Chaire, </l>
          <l>As she enlightned all the Ayre! </l>
          <l>Harke how the charming Tunes doe beate </l>
          <l>In sacred Concords bout her seate! </l>
          <l>And loe! to grace what these intend, <pb subtype="duplicate" type="blank" xml:id="ep000110-008-a"/>
            <pb subtype="duplicate" type="blank" xml:id="ep000110-008-b"/>
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000110-009-a"/>
          <l>Eight of her Noblest Powers descend, </l>
          <l>Which are <ref target="A04654-e102170-b">a </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e102170-a" n="a" place="margin">a They were all eight call'd by particular Surnames of IVNO, ascribed to her for some peculiar propertie in Marriage, as somwhere after is more fitly declared. </note>enstil'd her Faculties, </l>
          <l>That governe nuptiall Mysteries; </l>
          <l>And weare those Masques before their faces, </l>
          <l>Lest, dazling Mortalls with their graces </l>
          <l>As they approach them, all Mankind </l>
          <l>Should be, like CVPID, stroken blinde. </l>
          <l>These ORDER waytes for, on the ground, </l>
          <l>To keepe, that you should not confound </l>
          <l>Their measur'd steppes, which onely move </l>
          <l>About th' harmonious sphaere of LOVE. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>The names of the eight Ladies, as they were after orderd (to the most conspicuous shew) in their Daunces, by the rule of their statures; were the <list>
            <item>Co. of MONGOMERY. </item>
            <item>Mi. CI. SACKVILE. </item>
            <item>La. DOR. HASTINGS. </item>
            <item>Co. of BEDFORD. </item>
            <item>La. KNOLLES. </item>
            <item>La. BERKLEY. </item>
            <item>La. BLANCH SOMERSET. </item>
            <item>Co. of RVTLAND. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>Their Descent was made in two great Cloudes, that put forth themselves severally, and (with one measure of time) were seene to stoupe, &amp; fall gently downe vpon the Earth. The maner of their Habites, came after some Statues of IVNO, no lesse airie, than glorious. The dressings of their Heades, rare; so likewise of their Feete: and all full of splendor, soveraignety, and riches. Whilst they were descending, this Song was sung at the Altar. </p>
        <pb xml:id="ep000110-009-b"/>
        <q type="song">
          <label>SONG. </label>
          <l>THese, these are they, </l>
          <l>Whom Humor and Affection must obey; </l>
          <l>Who come to decke the geniall Bower, </l>
          <l>And bring, with them, the gratefull Hower </l>
          <l>That crownes such Meetings, and excites </l>
          <l>The married Paire to fresh Delights: </l>
          <l>As Courtings, Kissings, Coyings, Oths, &amp; Vowes, </l>
          <l>Soft Whisperings, Embracements, all the Ioyes, </l>
          <l>And melting Toyes, </l>
          <l>That chaster LOVE allowes. </l>
          <l>CHO. Hast, hast, for HESPERVS his head down bowes. </l>
        </q>
        <p>The Song ended, they daunced forth in Paires, and each Paire with a varied and noble grace; to a rare and full Musique of twelve Lutes: led on by ORDER, the Servant of REASON, who was, there, rather a Person of Ceremony, than Vse. His vnder-Garment was blew, his vpper white, and painted full of Arithmeticall, and Geometricall Figures; his Hayre, and Beard long, a Starre on his forehead, and in his hand a Geometricall Staffe: To whom, after the Daunce, REASON spake. </p>
        <sp who="#ep000110-reason" xml:id="ep000110-e102530">
          <speaker>REASON. </speaker>
          <l>COnvey them, ORDER, to their places, </l>
          <l>And ranke them so, in severall traces, </l>
          <l>As they may set their mixed Powers </l>
          <l>Vnto the Musique of the Howers; </l>
          <l>And THESE, by ioyning with them, know </l>
          <l>In better temper how to flow: </l>
          <l>Whilst I (from their abstracted Names) </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000110-010-a"/>
          <l>Report the vertues of the Dames. </l>
          <l>First <ref target="A04654-e102630-b">a </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e102630-a" n="a" place="margin">a This Surname IVNO receiv'd of the Sabines; from them, the Romanes gave it her: of the Speare, which (in the Sabine tongue) was called Curis, and was that, which they nam'd Hasta Caelibaris, which had stuck in the Body of a slaine Sword-player, and wherewith the Brides Head was drest. whereof Fest. in Voce Celibar. gives these reasons, Vt quemadmodumilla coniuncta fuerit cum corpore Gladiatoris, sic ipsa cum Viro sit; vel quia Matronae IVNONIS Curitis in tutelâ sit, quae ita appellabatur à ferenda hasta: vel quod fortes viros genitur as ominetur; vel quod nuptiali iure imperio viri subijcitur Nubens, quià Hasta summa armorum, &amp; imperij est, &amp;c. To most of which Plutarch in his Quaest. Rom. consents, but addes a better in Romul. That when they divided the Brides haire with the poynt of the Speare, <seg xml:lang="unk">{non-Roman} {non-Roman} {non-Roman}</seg>, it noted their first Nuptialles (with the Sabines) were contracted by force, and as with Enemies. Howsoever, that it was a Custome with them, this of Ovid. Fast. lib. 2. confirmes. Comat Virgineas hasta recurva comas. </note>CVRIS comes to decke the Brides faire Tresse. </l>
          <l>Care of the oyntments <ref target="A04654-e102660-b">b </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e102660-a" n="b" place="margin">b For the Surname of VNXIA, we have Mart. Capel. his Testimony, De Nupt. Phil. &amp; Mercu. libr. 2. quod vnctionibus praeest: As also Servius, libro quarto Aeneid. where they both report it a Fashion with the Romanes, that before the new-married Brides entred the houses of their Husbandes, they adorned the Postes of the Gates with woollen Tawdries, or Fillets, and annoynted them with Oyles, or the fatte of Wolves, and Bores; being superstitiously possest, that such Oyntments had the vertue of expelling Evilles from the Family: and thence were they called Vxores, quasi Vnxores. </note>VNXIA doth professe. </l>
          <l>
            <ref target="A04654-e102680-b">c </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e102680-a" n="c" place="margin">c Shee was named IVGA, propter Iugum, (as Servius sayes) for the yoke which was imposd, in Matrimony, on those that were married, or (with Sex. Pomp Fest.) quòd Iuges sunt eiusdem iugi Pares, vnde &amp; Coniuges. or in respect of the Altar (to which I have declar'd before) sacred to IVNO, in Vico Iugario .</note>IVGA, her office to make One of Twaine: </l>
          <l>
            <ref target="A04654-e102700-b">d </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e102700-a" n="d" place="margin">d As shee was GAMELIA, in sacrificing to her, they tooke away the Gall, and threw it behinde the Altar; intimating, that (after Marriage) there shoulde be knowne, no Bitternesse, nor Hatred betweene the ioyned Couple, which might divide, or seperate them: See Plutarch. Connub. Prae. This Rite I have somewhere following touch'd at. </note>GAMELIA sees that they should so remaine. </l>
          <l>Faire <ref target="A04654-e102720-b">e </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e102720-a" n="e" place="margin">e The Title of ITERDVCA shee had amongst them, quòd ad sponsi aedes, sponsas comitabatur; or was a Protectresse of their journey, Mart. Capel. De Nupt. Philolog. &amp; Mercur. libro secundo. </note>ITERDVCA leades the Bride her way; </l>
          <l>And <ref target="A04654-e102740-b"/>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e102740-a" place="margin">The like of DOMIDVCA, quòd ad optatas domus duceret. Mart. ibid. </note>DOMIDVCA home her steppes doth stay: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000110-010-b"/>
          <l>
            <ref target="A04654-e102760-b">a </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e102760-a" n="a" place="margin">a CINXIA, the same Author gives vnto her, as the Defendresse of Maydes, when they had put off their Girdle, in the Bridall Chamber; To which, Festus. Cinxiae Iunonis nomen sanctum habebatur in Nuptijs, quod initio Coniugij solutio erat Cinguli, quo nova Nupta erat cincta. And Arnobius, a man most learned in their Ceremonies, lib. 3. advers. Gent. saith, Vnctionibus superest Vnxia. Cinguloruus Cinxia replicationi. </note>CINXIA the Maid, quit of her Zone defends; </l>
          <l>
            <ref target="A04654-e102780-b">b </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e102780-a" n="b" place="margin">b TELIA signifies Perfecta, or, as some translate it, Perfectrix; with Iul. Pol. libr. 3. Onomast. <seg xml:lang="unk">{non-Roman} {non-Roman} {non-Roman} </seg>valewes IVNO Praeses Nuptiarum who saith, the Attribute descends of <seg xml:lang="unk">{non-Roman} {non-Roman} {non-Roman}</seg>, which (with the Antients) signified Marriage, and thence, were they called <seg xml:lang="unk">{non-Roman} {non-Roman} {non-Roman}</seg>, that entred into that estate. Servius interprets it the same with GAMELIA, Aeneid. 4. ad verb. Et Iunone secundâ: But it implies much more, as including the faculty to mature, and perfect; See the Greeke Scholiaste on Pind. Nem. in Hym. ad Thyaeum Vliae filium Argi. <seg xml:lang="unk">{non-Roman} {non-Roman} {non-Roman}</seg>: that is, Nuptialls are therefore calld <seg xml:lang="unk">{non-Roman} {non-Roman} {non-Roman} </seg>because they effect Perfection of Life, and doe note that Maturity which should be in Matrimony. For before Nuptialles, shee is called IVNO <seg xml:lang="unk">{non-Roman} {non-Roman} {non-Roman} </seg>that is, Virgo; after Nuptialls, <seg xml:lang="unk">{non-Roman} {non-Roman} {non-Roman}</seg>, which is adulta, or Perfecta. </note>TELIA (for HYMEN) perfects all, and ends. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>By this time, the Ladies were payred with the Men, and the whole Sixteene rank'd foorth, in order, to daunce: &amp; were with this Song provok'd. </p>
        <floatingText>
          <body>
            <div type="song" xml:id="ep000110-e102890">
              <head>SONG. </head>
              <l>NOw, now beginne to set </l>
              <l>Your spirits in active heate; </l>
              <l>And, since your Hands are met, </l>
              <l>Instruct your nimble Feete, </l>
              <l>In motions swift, and meete, </l>
              <l>The happy ground to beate: </l>
              <lg>
                <head>Chorus. </head>
                <l>Whilst all this Roofe doth ring, </l>
                <l>And ech discording String, </l>
                <l>With every varied Voyce, </l>
                <l>In VNION doth reioyce. </l>
              </lg>
            </div>
          </body>
        </floatingText>
        <pb xml:id="ep000110-011-a"/>
        <p>Here, they daunced forth a most neate and curious Measure, full of Subtelty and Device; which was so excellently performed, as it seemed to take away that Spirite from the Invention, which the Invention gave to it: and left it doubtfull, whether the Formes flow'd more perfectly from the Authors braine, or their feete. The Straines were all notably different, some of them formed into Letters, very signifying to the Name of the Bridgroome, and ended in manner of a Chaine, linking hands: To which, this was spoken. </p>
        <sp who="#ep000110-reason" xml:id="ep000110-e103020">
          <speaker>REASON. </speaker>
          <l>SVch was <ref target="A04654-e103040-b">a </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e103040-a" n="a" place="margin">a Mentioned by HOMER, Ilia. 〈◊〉. which many have interpreted diversely: all Allegorically; Pla. in Thaeteto, vnderstands it to be the Sunne, which while he circles the worlde in his course, all thinges are safe, and preserved: Others vary it. Macrob, (to whose interpretation, I am specially affected in my Allusion) considers it thus: in Som. Scip. libr. 1. cap. 14. Ergo cùm ex summo Deo mens, ex mente anima sit; anima vero &amp; condat, &amp; vita compleat omnia quae sequuntur, cunctaque hic vnus fulgor illuminet, &amp; in vniversis appareat, vt in multis speculis, per ordinem positis, vultus vnus; Cumque omnia continuis successionibus se sequantur, degenerantia per ordinem ad imum meandi: invenietur pressius intuenti à summo Deo vsque ad vltimam rerum faecem vna mutuis se vinculis religans, &amp; nusquam interrupta connexio. Et haec est Hemeri Catena aurea, quam pendere de coelo in terras Deum iussisse commemorat. To which strengh and evennesse of connexion, I have not absurdly likened this vniting of Humors, and Affections, by the sacred Powers of Mariage. </note>the Golden Chaine let down from Heaven; </l>
          <l>And not those Linkes more even, </l>
          <l>Then these: so sweetly temper'd, so combin'd </l>
          <l>By VNION, and refin'd. </l>
          <l>Here no Contention, Envie, Griefe, Deceipt, </l>
          <l>Feare, Iealousie have weight; </l>
          <l>But all is Peace, and Love, and Faith, and Blisse: </l>
          <l>What Harmony like this? </l>
          <l>The Gall, behinde the Altar quite is throwne; </l>
          <l>This Sacrifice hath none. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000110-011-b"/>
          <l>Now no Affections rage, nor Humors swell; </l>
          <l>But all composed dwell. </l>
          <l>O IVNO, HYMEN, HYMEN, IVNO! who </l>
          <l>Can merit with you two? </l>
          <l>Without your presence, VENVS can doe nought, </l>
          <l>Save what with shame is bought: </l>
          <l>No Father can himselfe a Parent show, </l>
          <l>Nor any House with prosp'rous Issue grow. </l>
          <l>O then! What Deities will dare </l>
          <l>With HYMEN, or with IVNO to compare? </l>
        </sp>
        <p>The speach being ended, they dissolv'd: and all tooke forth other Persons, (Men, and Women,) to daunce other Measures, Galliards, and Corranto's; the whilst this Song importun'd them to a fit Remembrance of the Time. </p>
        <q type="song">
          <label>SONG. </label>
          <l>Thinke, yet, how Night doth wast, </l>
          <l>How much of Time is past, </l>
          <l>What more then winged hast </l>
          <l>Your selves would take, </l>
          <l>If you were but to tast </l>
          <l>The ioy, the Night doth cast </l>
          <l>(O might it ever last) </l>
          <l>On this bright Virgin, and her happy Make. </l>
        </q>
        <p>Their Daunces yet lasting, they were the second time importun'd, by Speach. </p>
        <pb xml:id="ep000110-012-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000110-reason" xml:id="ep000110-e103370">
          <speaker>REASON. </speaker>
          <l>See, see! the bright <ref target="A04654-e103390-b">a </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e103390-a" n="a" place="margin">a Stella Veneris, or VENVS, which when it goes before the Sunne, is call'd Phosphorus, or Lucifer; when it followes, Hesperus, or Noctifer (as Cat. translates it.) See Cic. 2. de Natu. Deor. Mar. Cap. de Nup. Phi. &amp; Mer. libr. 8. The nature of this starre Pythagoras first found out; and the present office Claud. expresseth in Fescen. Attollens thalamis Idalium iubar dilectus Veneri nascitur Hesperus. </note>Idalian Starre, </l>
          <l>That lighteth Lovers to their Warre, </l>
          <l>Complaines, that you her influence loose; </l>
          <l>While thus the Night-sports you abuse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000110-hymen" xml:id="ep000110-e103430">
          <speaker>HYMEN. </speaker>
          <l>THe longing Bridegroome, <ref target="A04654-e103450-b">b </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e103450-a" n="b" place="margin">b It was a Custome for the Man to stand there, expecting the approach of his Bride. See Hotto. de Rit. Nupt. </note>in the Porch, </l>
          <l>Shewes you againe, the bated Torch; </l>
          <l>And thrice hath IVNO <ref target="A04654-e103480-b">c </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e103480-a" n="c" place="margin">c Alluding to that of Virg. Aeneid. 4. Prima &amp; Tellus, &amp; Pronuba IVNO Dant signum: fulsere ignes, &amp; conscius aether Connubij, &amp;c. </note>mixt her Ayre </l>
          <l>With Fire, to sommon your repaire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000110-reason" xml:id="ep000110-e103500">
          <speaker>REASON. </speaker>
          <l>SEe, now she cleane withdrawes her Light; </l>
          <l>And (as you should) gives place to Night: </l>
          <l>That spreades her broad, and blackest wing </l>
          <l>Vpon the world, and comes to bring </l>
          <l>A <ref target="A04654-e103560-b">d </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e103560-a" n="d" place="margin">d Stat. in Epit. Fulcra, torosque deae, tenerum premit agmen Amorum. And Claud. in Epith. Pennati passim pueri, quo quemque vocavit vmbra, iacent. Both which, prove the Antients faind many Cupids. Reade also Prop. Ele. 29. libr. 2. </note>thousand severall-colour'd Loves, </l>
          <l>Some like Sparrowes, some like Doves, </l>
          <l>That hop about the Nuptiall-Roome, </l>
          <l>And flutt'ring there (against you come) </l>
          <l>Warme the chaste Bowre, which <ref target="A04654-e103610-b">e </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e103610-a" n="e" place="margin">e VENVS is so induced by Stat. Claud. and others, to celebrate Nuptialls. </note>CYPRIA strowes, </l>
          <l>With many a Lilly, many a Rose. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000110-012-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000110-hymen" xml:id="ep000110-e103630">
          <speaker>HYMEN. </speaker>
          <l>HAste therefore, haste, and call, Away: </l>
          <l>The gentle Night is prest to pay </l>
          <l>The vsurie of long Delights, </l>
          <l>She owes to these protracted Rites. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>At this (the whole Scene being drawne againe, and all cover'd with Cloudes, as a Night,) they left off their entermixed Daunces, and return'd to their first Places; where, as they were but begining to move, this Song, the third time, vrg'd them. </p>
        <q type="song">
          <label>SONG. </label>
          <l>O Know to end, as to beginne: </l>
          <l>A Minutes losse, in Love, is sinne. </l>
          <l>These Humors will the Night out weare </l>
          <l>In their owne Pastimes here; </l>
          <l>You doe our Rites much wrong, </l>
          <l>In seeking to Prolong </l>
          <l>These outward Pleasures: </l>
          <l>The Night hath other Treasures </l>
          <l>Then these (though long concea'ld) </l>
          <l>Ere day, to be reveal'd. </l>
          <l>Then, know to end, as to beginne; </l>
          <l>A Minutes losse, in Love, is sinne. </l>
        </q>
        <p>Here they daunc'd their last Daunces, full of excellent delight and change, and, in their latter straine, fell into a faire Orbe, or Circle; REASON standing in the midst, and speaking. </p>
        <pb xml:id="ep000110-013-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000110-reason" xml:id="ep000110-e103850">
          <speaker>REASON. </speaker>
          <l>HEre stay, and let your Sports be crown'd: </l>
          <l>The perfect'st Figure is the Round. </l>
          <l>Nor fell you in it by adventer, </l>
          <l>When REASON was your Guide, and Center. </l>
          <l>This, this that beauteous <ref target="A04654-e103910-b">a </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e103910-a" n="a" place="margin">a VENVS Girdle, mentioned by Homer. Il. 〈◊〉. which was fain'd to be variously wrought with the Needle, and in it woven Love, Desire, Sweetnesse, Soft Parlee, Gracefulnesse, Perswasions, &amp; all the Powers of VENVS. </note>Ceston is </l>
          <l>of Lovers many-coulor'd Blisse. </l>
          <l>Come HYMEN, make an inner Ring, </l>
          <l>And let the Sacrificers sing; </l>
          <l>Cheare vp the faint, and trembling Bride, </l>
          <l>That quakes to touch hir Bridegroom's side: </l>
          <l>Tell her, what IVNO is to IOVE, </l>
          <l>The same shall she be to her Love; </l>
          <l>His Wife: which we doe rather measure </l>
          <l>
            <ref target="A04654-e104010-b">b </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e104010-a" n="b" place="margin">b See the words of Aelius verus. in Spartian. </note>A Name of Dignity, then Pleasure. </l>
          <l>Vp Youths, hold vp your Lights in ayre, </l>
          <l>And shake abroad <ref target="A04654-e104040-b">c </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e104040-a" n="c" place="margin">c So Cat. in Nup. Iul. &amp; Manlij hath it. Viden', vt faces splendid as quatiunt comas? and by and by after, aureas quatium comas. </note>their flaming haire. </l>
          <l>Now move vnited, and, in Gate, </l>
          <l>As you (in paires) doe front the State, </l>
          <l>With gratefull Honors, thanke his Grace </l>
          <l>That hath so glorified the Place: </l>
          <l>And as, in Circle, you depart </l>
          <l>Link'd hand in hand; So, heart in heart, </l>
          <l>May all those Bodies still remaine </l>
          <l>Whom he, (with so much sacred paine) </l>
          <l>No lesse hath bound within his Realmes </l>
          <l>Then they are with the OCEANS streames. </l>
          <l>Long may his VNION find increase </l>
          <l>As hee, to ours, hath deign'd his peace. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000110-013-b"/>
        <p>With this, to a soft straine of Musique, they pac'd once about, in their Ring, every Payre making their Honors, as they came before the State: and then dissolving, went downe in Couples, led on by HYMEN, the Bride, and Auspices following, as to the Nuptiall Bowre. After them, the Musitians with this Song, of which, then, onely one Staffe was sung; but because I made it both in Forme, and Matter to aemulate that kinde of Poeme, which was call'd <ref target="A04654-e104180-b">a </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e104180-a" n="a" place="margin">a It had the name à Thalamo, dictum est autem, <seg xml:lang="unk">{non-Roman} {non-Roman} {non-Roman} </seg>cubiculum Nuptiale primo suo significatu, <seg xml:lang="unk">{non-Roman} {non-Roman} {non-Roman}</seg>, quod est simul genialem vitam agere. Scal. in Poet. </note>Epithalamium, and (by the Auntients) vs'd to be song, when the Bride was led into her Chamber, I have here set it down whole: and doe hartily forgive their ignorance whom it chanceth not to please. Hoping, that Nemo doctus me iubeat Thalassionem verbis dicere non Thalassionis. </p>
        <q type="song">
          <label>EPITHALAMION. </label>
          <l>GLad Time is at his point arriv'd, </l>
          <l>For which Loves hopes were so long-liv'd. </l>
          <l>Lead HYMEN, lead away; </l>
          <l>And let no Obiect stay, </l>
          <l>Nor Banquets, (but sweete kisses) </l>
          <l>The Turtles from their Blisses. </l>
          <l>
            <ref target="A04654-e104310-b">b </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e104310-a" n="b" place="margin">b This Poeme had for the most part Versum intercalarem. or Carmen Amoebaeum; yet that not alwaies one, but oftentimes varied, and sometimes neglected in the same Song, as in ours you shall finde observed .</note>Tis CVPID calls to arme; </l>
          <l>And this his last Alarme. <pb subtype="duplicate" type="blank" xml:id="ep000110-014-a"/>
            <pb subtype="duplicate" type="blank" xml:id="ep000110-014-b"/>
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000110-015-a"/>
          <l>Shrinke not, soft VIRGIN, you will love, </l>
          <l>Anone, what you so feare to prove. </l>
          <l>This is no killing Warre, </l>
          <l>To which you pressed are; </l>
          <l>But faire and gentle strife </l>
          <l>Which Lovers call their Life. </l>
          <l>Tis CVPID cries to Arme; </l>
          <l>And this his last Alarme. </l>
          <l>Helpe Youths, and Virgins, helpe to sing </l>
          <l>The Prize, which HYMEN here doth bring, </l>
          <l>And did so lately <ref target="A04654-e104440-b">a </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e104440-a" n="a" place="margin">a The Bride was alwaies fain'd, to be ravish'd ex Gremio Matris; or (if she were wanting) exproximâ Nccessitudine. because that had succeeded well to Romulus, who, by force gat Wives for him, and his, from the Sabines. See Fest. and that of Catul. Qui rapis teneram ad virum virgine. </note>rap </l>
          <l>From forth the Mothers lap, </l>
          <l>To place her by that side </l>
          <l>Where she must long abide. </l>
          <l>On HYMEN, HYMEN call, </l>
          <l>This Night is HYMEN's all. </l>
          <l>See, HESPERVS is yet in view! </l>
          <l>What Starre can so deserve of you? </l>
          <l>Whose light doth still adorne </l>
          <l>Your Bride, that ere the Morne, </l>
          <l>Shall farre more perfect bee, </l>
          <l>And rise as bright as Hee; </l>
          <l>When <ref target="A04654-e104570-b">b </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e104570-a" n="b" place="margin">b When he is Phosphorus, yet the same Star, as I have noted before. </note>(like to him) her Name </l>
          <l>Is chang'd, but not her Flame. </l>
          <l>Hast, tender Lady, and adventer; </l>
          <l>The covetous House would have you enter, </l>
          <l>That it might wealthy bee, </l>
          <l>And you, her <ref target="A04654-e104630-b">c </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e104630-a" n="c" place="margin">c At the entrance of the Bride, the Custome was to give her the Keyes, to signifie that she was absolute Mistresse of the Place, and the whole Disposition of the Familie at her Care, Fest. </note>Mistresse see: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000110-015-b"/>
          <l>Hast your owne good to meete; </l>
          <l>Aud <ref target="A04654-e104660-b">a </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e104660-a" n="a" place="margin">a This was also an other Rite; that she might not touch the Threshold as she entred, but was lifted over it. Servius saith, because it was sacred to VESTA. Plut. in. Quaest. Rom. remembers divers causes. But that, which I take to come nearest the truth, was only the avoyding of Sorcerous Drugs, vs'd by Witches to be buri'd vnder that Place, to the destroying of Mariage- Amitie, or the Power of Generation. See Alexand. in Genialibu. and Christ. Landus vpon Gatul. </note>lift your golden feete </l>
          <l>Above the Threshold, high, </l>
          <l>With prosperous Augury. </l>
          <l>Now, Youths, let goe your pretty armes; </l>
          <l>The Place within chant's other charmes. </l>
          <l>Whole showers of Roses flow; </l>
          <l>And Violets seeme to grow, </l>
          <l>Strew'd in the Chamber there, </l>
          <l>As VENVS Meade it were. </l>
          <l>On HYMEN, HYMEN call, </l>
          <l>This Night is HYMEN's all. </l>
          <l>Good Matrons, that so well are knowne </l>
          <l>To aged Husbands of your owne, </l>
          <l>Place you our Bride to night; </l>
          <l>And <ref target="A04654-e104810-b">b </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e104810-a" n="b" place="margin">b For this looke Fist. in Voc. Rapi. </note>snatch away the Light: </l>
          <l>That <ref target="A04654-e104830-b">c </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e104830-a" n="c" place="margin">c quo vtroque mors propanqua alterius vltrius captari putatur Fest. ibid. </note>she not hide it dead </l>
          <l>Beneath her Spouse's Bed; </l>
          <l>Nor <ref target="A04654-e104860-b">d </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e104860-a" n="d" place="margin">d quo vtroque mors propinquae alterius vltrius captari putatur Fest. ibid. </note>he reserve the same </l>
          <l>To helpe the funerall Flame. </l>
          <l>So, now you may admit him in; </l>
          <l>The Act he covets, is no Sinne, </l>
          <l>But chast, and holy Love, </l>
          <l>Which HYMEN doth approve: </l>
          <l>Without whose hallowing Fires </l>
          <l>All Aymes are base Desires. </l>
          <l>On HYMEN, HYMEN call, </l>
          <l>This Night is HYMEN's all. </l>
          <l>Now, free from Vulgar Spight, or Noyse, </l>
          <l>May you enioy your mutuall ioyes; </l>
          <l>Now, You no Feare controules, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000110-016-a"/>
          <l>But Lippes may mingle Soules; </l>
          <l>And soft Embraces binde, </l>
          <l>To each, the others Minde: </l>
          <l>Which may no Power vntie, </l>
          <l>Till One, or both must die. </l>
          <l>And, looke, before you yeeld to slumber, </l>
          <l>That your Delights be drawne past number; </l>
          <l>"Ioyes, got with strife, increase. </l>
          <l>Affect no sleepy peace; </l>
          <l>But keepe the Brides faire eyes </l>
          <l>Awake, with her owne Cries, </l>
          <l>Which are but Mayden-feares: </l>
          <l>And Kisses drie such teares. </l>
          <l>Then, Coyne them, twixt your Lippes so sweete, </l>
          <l>And let not Cockles closer meete; </l>
          <l>Nor may your Murmuring Loves </l>
          <l>Be drown'd by <ref target="A04654-e105160-b">a </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e105160-a" n="a" place="margin">a A frequent Surname of VENVS, not of the Place, as CYPRIA; but quòd parere faciat, <seg xml:lang="unk">{non-Roman} {non-Roman} {non-Roman} </seg>Theop. Phurnut. and the Grammarians vpon Homer, See them. </note>CYPRIS Doves: </l>
          <l>Let Ivie not so bind </l>
          <l>As when your Armes are twin'd: </l>
          <l>That you may Both, e're Day, </l>
          <l>Rise perfect every way. </l>
          <l>And, IVNO, whose great Powers protect </l>
          <l>The Marriage-Bed, with good effect </l>
          <l>The Labour of this Night </l>
          <l>Blesse thou, for future Light; </l>
          <l>And, Thou, thy happy charge, </l>
          <l>Glad <ref target="A04654-e105280-b">b </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e105280-a" n="b" place="margin">b Deus Naturae, sive gignendi. And is the same in the Male, as IVNO in the Female. Hence Genialis Lectus, qui nuptijs sternitur, in honorem Genij. Fesi. Genius meus, quia me genuit. </note>GENIVS, enlarge: </l>
          <l>That they may Both, e're Day, </l>
          <l>Rise perfect every way. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000110-016-b"/>
          <l>And <ref target="A04654-e105320-b">a </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e105320-a" n="a" place="margin">a She hath this faculty given her, by all the Antients See Hom. Iliad. θ. Lucret. in prim. Vir. in 2. Georg &amp;c. </note>VENVS, Thou, with timely seede </l>
          <l>(Which may their after-Comforts breede) </l>
          <l>Informe the gentle Wombe; </l>
          <l>Nor, let it prove a Tombe: </l>
          <l>But, e're ten Moones be wasted, </l>
          <l>The Birth, by CYNTHIA hasted. </l>
          <l>So may they Both, e're Day, </l>
          <l>Rise perfect everie Way. </l>
          <l>And, when the Babe to light is showne, </l>
          <l>Let it be, like each Parent, knowne; </l>
          <l>Much of the Fathers Face, </l>
          <l>More of the Mothers Grace: </l>
          <l>And eyther Grand-Sires Spirit, </l>
          <l>And Fame let it inherit. </l>
          <l>That Men may blesse th' Embraces, </l>
          <l>That ioyned two such Races. </l>
          <l>Cease Youths, and Virgins, you have done; </l>
          <l>Shut fast the Dore: And, as They soone </l>
          <l>To their Perfection hast, </l>
          <l>So may their ardors last. </l>
          <l>So eithers strength out-live </l>
          <l>All losse that Age can give: </l>
          <l>And, though full Yeares be tolde, </l>
          <l>Their Formes growe slowly olde. </l>
        </q>
        <p>HItherto extended the first Nights Solemnitie, whose Grace in the Exequution left not where to adde vnto it, with wishing: I meane, (nor doe I court them) in those, that sustain'd the Nobler parts. Such was the exquisit Performance, as (beside the Pompe, Splendour, or what wee may <pb xml:id="ep000110-017-a"/>call Apparrelling of such Presentments) that alone (had all else beene absent) was of power to surprize with Delight, and steale away the Spectators from themselves. Nor was there wanting whatsoever might give to the Furniture, or Complement: eyther in riches, or strangenesse of the Habites, delicacie of Daunces, Magnificence of the Scene, or divine Rapture of Musique. Onely the Envie was, that it lasted not still, or (now it is past) cannot by Imagination, much lesse Description, be recover'd to a part of that Spirit, it had in the gliding by. </p>
        <p>Yet, that I may not vtterly defraud the Reader of his Hope, I am drawne to give it those briefe touches, which may leave behind some shadow of what it was: And first of the Attires. </p>
        <p>That, of the Lords, had parte of it (for the fashion) taken from the Antique Greeke Statue; mixed with some Moderne Additions: which made it both gracefull, and strange. On their Heades they wore Persick Crowns, that were with Scroles of Gold-plate turn'd outward; and wreath'd about with a Carnation and Silver Net-lawne: The one End of which hung carelesly on the left shoulder, the other was trick'd vp before in severall degrees of fouldes, betweene the Plates, and set with rich Iewelles, and great Pearle. Their Bodies were of Carnation cloth of silver, richly wrought, and cut to expresse the Naked, in maner of the Greeke Thorax; girt vnder the Breasts, with a broade Belt of Cloth of Golde, imbrodered, and fastned before <pb xml:id="ep000110-017-b"/>with Iewells: Their Labells were of White Cloth of silver, lac'd, and wrought curiously betweene, sutable to the vpper halfe of their Sleeves; whose nether partes, with their Bases, were of Watchet Cloth of Silver, chev'rond all over with Lace. Their Mantills were of severall colour'd silkes, distinguishing their Qualities, as they were coupled in payres; The first, Skie colour; The second, Pearle colour; The third, Flame colour; The fourth, Tawnie; And these cut in leaves, which were subtilly tack'd vp, and imbrodered with Oo's, and between every ranke of Leaves, a broad silver Lace. They were fastned on the right shoulder, and fell Compasse downe the backe in gratious folds, and were againe tied with a round Knot, to the fastning of their Swords. Vpon their legges they wore Silver Greaves, answering in worke to their Labells; and these were their Accoutrements. </p>
        <p>The Ladies Attire was wholy new, for the Invention, and full of Glory; as having in it the most true impression of a Celestiall Figure: The vpper part of White Cloth of Silver, wrought with IVNOES Birdes and Fruicts; A loose vnder garment, full-gather'd, of Carnation, strip't with Silver, and parted with a Golden Zone; Beneath that, an other flowing Garment, of Watchet Cloth of Silver, lac'd with Gold: Through all which, though they were round, and swelling, there yet appear'd some touch of their delicate Lineaments, preserving the sweetenesse of Proportion, and expressing it selfe beyond expression. The Attire of their Heads, <pb xml:id="ep000110-018-a"/>did answer, if not exceede; their Hayre being carelesly (but yet with more art, then if more affected) bound vnder the circle of a rare, and rich Coronet, adorn'd with all variety, and choyce of Iewells; from the top of which, flow'd a trasparent Veile downe to the ground; whose verge, returning vp, was fastned to eyther side in most sprightly Manner. Their shooes were Azure, and Gold, set with Rubies, and Diamonds; so were all their Garments: and euery part abounding in Ornament. </p>
        <p>No lesse to be admir'd, for the Grace, and Greatnesse, was the whole Machine of the Spectacle, from whence they came: the first part of which was a <seg xml:lang="unk">{non-Roman} {non-Roman} {non-Roman}</seg>, or Globe, filld with Countreys, and those guilded; where the Sea was exprest, heightned with siluer waues. This stoode, or rather hung, (for no Axell was seene to support it) and turning softly, discoverd the first Masque, (as we have before, but too runningly declar'd) which was of the Men, sitting in faire Composition, within a Mine of severall Mettalls: To which, the Lights were so plac'd, as noe one was seene; but seemed, as if onely REASON, with the splendor of her Crowne, illumin'd the whole Grot. </p>
        <p>On the sides of this (which began the other part) were placed two great Statues, fayn'd of Gold, one of Atlas, the other of Hercules, in varied postures, bearing vp the Cloudes, which were of Releue, embossed, and tralucent, as Naturalls: To <pb xml:id="ep000110-018-b"/>these, a Cortine of painted Cloudes ioyned, which reach'd to the vpmost Roofe of the Hall; and sodainely opening, reveal'd the three Regions of Ayre: In the highest of which, sate IVNO, in a glorious Throne of Gold, circled with Comets, and fiery Meteors, engendred in that hot and dry Region; her Feete reaching to the lowest, where was made a Rainebow, and within it, Musitians seated, figuring Ayry Spirits, their habits various, and resembling the seuerall colours, caused in that part of the Ayre by reflexion. The midst was all of darke and condensed Cloudes, as being the proper Place where Rayne, Hayle, and other watry Meteors are made; out of which two concave Clouds, from the rest, thrust forth themselves (in nature of those Nimbi, wherein, by Homer, Virgill, &amp;c. the Gods are fain'd to descend) and these carried the eight Ladies, over the heads of the two <ref target="A04654-e105630-b">a </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e105630-a" n="a" place="margin">a Atlas, and Hercules, the Figures mentioned before. </note>Termes; who (as the Ingine mov'd) seem'd also to bow themselves (by vertue of their shadowes) and discharge their shoulders of their glorious burden: when, having set them on the Earth, both they, and the Cloudes gather'd themselves vp againe, with some rapture of the Beholders. </p>
        <p>But that, which (as above in place, so in the beuty) was most taking in the Spectacle, was the Spheare of Fire; in the top of all, encompassing the Ayre, and imitated with such art, and industry, as the Spectators might discerne the Motion (all the time the Shewes lasted) without any Moover: and, that so swift, as no Eye could distinguish any Colour <pb xml:id="ep000110-019-a"/>of the Light, but might forme to it selfe five hundred severall hewes, out of the tralucent Body of the Ayre, obiected betwixt it, and them. </p>
        <p>And this was crown'd with a statue of IVPITER, the Thunderer. </p>
        <p>The Designe, and Act of all which, together with the Device of their Habits, belongs properly to the Merit, and Reputation of Maister YNYGO IONES; whom I take modest occasion, in this fit place, to remember, lest his owne worth might accuse mee of an ignorant neglect from my silence. </p>
        <p>And here, that no mans Deservings complain of iniustice (though I should have done it timelier, I acknowledge) I doe for honours sake, and the pledge of our Friendship, name Ma. ALPHONSO FERABOSCO, a Man, planted by himselfe, in that divine Spheare; &amp; mastring all the spirits of Musique: To whose iudiciall Care, and as absolute Performance, were committed all those Difficulties both of Song, and otherwise. Wherein, what his Merit made to the Soule of our Invention, would aske to be exprest in Tunes, no lesse ravishing then his. Vertuous friend, take well this abrupt testimonie, and thinke whose it is: It cannot be Flatterie, in me, who never did it to Great ones; and lesse then Love, and Truth it is not, where it is done out of Knowledge. </p>
        <p>The Daunces were both made, and taught by Maister THOMAS GILES; and cannot bee more approv'd, then they did themselves: Nor doe I want the will, but the skill to commend such Subtilties; <pb xml:id="ep000110-019-b"/>of which the Spheare, wherein they were acted, is best able to iudge. </p>
        <p>What was my part, the Faults here, as well as the Vertues must speake. <quote>Mutare dominum nec potest Liber notus. </quote>
        </p>
        <p>ON the next Night, whose Solemnitie was of Barriers, (all mention of the former, being vtterly remo'vd, and taken away) there appeared, at the lower end of the Hall, a Mist made of delicate perfumes; out of which (a Battaile being sounded vnder the Stage) did seeme to breake foorth two Ladies, the one representing TRVTH, the other OPINION: but both so alike attired, as they could by no Note, be distinguish'd. The colour of their Garments were blew, their Socks White; They were crowned with wreathes of Palme, and in their hands, each of them sustain'd a Palm-bough. These, after the Mist was vanished, began to examine each other curiously with their eyes, and approching the State, the one expostulated the other in this manner. </p>
        <sp who="#ep000110-truth" xml:id="ep000110-e105720">
          <speaker>TRVTH. </speaker>
          <l>WHo art thou, thus that imitat'st my Grace, </l>
          <l>In Steppes, in Habite, and resembled Face? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000110-opinion" xml:id="ep000110-e105750">
          <speaker>OPINION. </speaker>
          <l>Grave <ref target="A04654-e105770-b">a </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e105770-a" n="a" place="margin">a Truth is fain'd to be the Daughter SATVRNE; who indeede, with the Auntients was no other than TIME, and so his name alludes, <seg xml:lang="unk">{non-Roman} {non-Roman} {non-Roman}</seg>. Plut. in Quaest To which conferre the Greeke Adage, <seg xml:lang="unk">{non-Roman} {non-Roman} {non-Roman}</seg>. </note>Time, and Industry my Parents are; </l>
          <l>My Name is TRVTH, who through these sounds of War </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000110-020-a"/>
          <l>(Which figure the wise Mindes discursive fight) </l>
          <l>In Mists by Nature wrapt, salute the Light. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000110-truth" xml:id="ep000110-e105830">
          <speaker>TRVTH. </speaker>
          <l>I am that TRVTH, thou some illusive Spright; </l>
          <l>Whome to my likenesse, the blacke Sorceresse Night </l>
          <l>Hath of these drie, and empty fumes created. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000110-opinion" xml:id="ep000110-e105870">
          <speaker>OPINION. </speaker>
          <l>Best Herald of thine owne Birth, well related: </l>
          <l>Put me and mine to proofe of wordes, and facts, </l>
          <l>In any Question this faire Houre exacts. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000110-truth" xml:id="ep000110-e105910">
          <speaker>TRVTH. </speaker>
          <l>I challenge thee, and fit this Time of Love, </l>
          <l>With this Position, which TRVTH comes to prove; </l>
          <l>That the most honor'd state of Man and Wife, </l>
          <l>Doth farre exceede th'insociate Virgin-Life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000110-opinion" xml:id="ep000110-e105960">
          <speaker>OPINION. </speaker>
          <l>I take the adverse part; and she that best </l>
          <l>Defends her side, be TRVTH by all confest. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000110-truth" xml:id="ep000110-e105990">
          <speaker>TRVTH. </speaker>
          <l>It is confirm'd. With what an equall brow </l>
          <l>To TRVTH, <ref target="A04654-e106020-b">a </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e106020-a" n="a" place="margin">a Hippocrat. in a certaine Epistle to Philopoem. describeth her, Mulierem, quae non mala videatur, sed audacior aspectu &amp; concitatior. To which, Caesare Ripa in his Iconolog. alludeth, in these wordes, Faccia, ne bella, ne dispiaceuole, &amp;c. </note>OPINION''s confident! and how, </l>
          <l>Like TRVTH, her Habite shewes to sensuall Eies! </l>
          <l>But whosoe're thou be, in this disguise, </l>
          <l>Cleare TRVTH, anone, shall strippe thee to the heart; </l>
          <l>And shew how mere Phantasticall thou arte. </l>
          <l>Know then, the first Production of Things, </l>
          <l>Required Two; from meere One nothing springs: </l>
          <l>Without that knot, the Theame thou gloriest in, </l>
          <l>(Th'vnprofitable Virgin) had not bin. </l>
          <l>The Golden Tree of Marriage began </l>
          <l>In Paradise, and bore the fruict of Man; </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000110-020-b"/>
          <l>On whose sweete branches Angells sate, and sung, </l>
          <l>And from whose firme roote all Societie sprung. </l>
          <l>LOVE (whose strong Vertue wrapt Heav'ns soule in Earth, </l>
          <l>And made a Woman glory in his Birth </l>
          <l>In Marriage, opens his inflamed Breast; </l>
          <l>And, lest in him Nature should stifled rest, </l>
          <l>His geniall fire about the world he dartes; </l>
          <l>Which Lippes with Lippes combines, and Hearts with Hearts. </l>
          <l>Marriage LOVES Obiect is; at whose bright eies </l>
          <l>He lights his Torches, and call's them his Skies. </l>
          <l>For her, he wings his shoulders; and doth flie </l>
          <l>To her white bosome, as his Sanctuary: </l>
          <l>In which no lustfull Finger can profane him, </l>
          <l>Nor anie Earth, with blacke Eclipses wane him. </l>
          <l>She makes him smile in sorrowes, and doth stand </l>
          <l>Twixt him, and all wants, with her silver hand. </l>
          <l>In her soft Lockes, his tender Feete are tied; </l>
          <l>And in his Fetters he takes worthy pride. </l>
          <l>And as Geometricians have approv'd </l>
          <l>That Lines, and Superficies are not mov'd </l>
          <l>By their owne forces, but doe follow still. </l>
          <l>Their Bodies motions; so the selfe-lov'd Will </l>
          <l>Of Man, or Woman should not rule in them, </l>
          <l>But each with other weare the Anademe. </l>
          <l>Mirrors, thogh deckt with Diamants, are noght worth, </l>
          <l>If the like Formes of Things they set not forth; </l>
          <l>So Men, or Women are worth Nothing, neyther, </l>
          <l>If eithers Eyes and Hearts present not either. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000110-opinion" xml:id="ep000110-e106410">
          <speaker>OPINION. </speaker>
          <l>Vntouch'd Virginity, Laugh out; to see </l>
          <l>Freedome in Fetters plac'd, and vrg'd 'gainst thee. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000110-021-a"/>
          <l>What Griefes lie groaning on the Nuptiall Bed? </l>
          <l>What dull Satietie? In what sheetes of Lead </l>
          <l>Tumble, and tosse the restlesse Married Paire, </l>
          <l>Each, oft, offended with the Others aire? </l>
          <l>From whence springs all-devouring Avarice, </l>
          <l>But from the Cares, which out of Wedlocke rise? </l>
          <l>And, where there is in Lifes best-tempred Fires </l>
          <l>And End, set in it selfe to all desires, </l>
          <l>A setled Quiet, Freedome never checkt, </l>
          <l>How farre are Maried Lives from this effect? </l>
          <l>
            <ref target="A04654-e106550-b">a </ref>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04654-e106550-a" n="a" place="margin">a A narrow Sea, betweene Aulis, a Port of Boeotia, and the Isle Euboea. See Pom. Mela. lib. 2. </note>EVRIPVS, that beares Shippes, in all their pride, </l>
          <l>Gainst roughest Windes, with violence of his Tide, </l>
          <l>And ebbes, and flowes, seven times in every day, </l>
          <l>Toyles not more turbulent, or fierce then they. </l>
          <l>And then, what Rules Husbands praescribe their Wives! </l>
          <l>In their Eyes Circles, they must bound their Lives. </l>
          <l>The Moone, when farthest from the Sunne she shines, </l>
          <l>Is most refulgent; nearest, most declines: </l>
          <l>But your poore Wives farre off must never rome, </l>
          <l>But wast their Beauties, neare their Lords, at home: </l>
          <l>And when their Lords range out, at home must hide </l>
          <l>(Like to beg'd Monopolies) all their Pride. </l>
          <l>When their Lords list to feede a serious Fit </l>
          <l>They must be serious; when to shew their Wit </l>
          <l>In Iests, and Laughter, they must laugh, and iest; </l>
          <l>When they wake, wake; and when they rest, must rest. </l>
          <l>And to their Wives Men give such narrow scopes, </l>
          <l>As if they meant to make them walke on Ropes: </l>
          <l>No Tumblers bide more perill of their Necks </l>
          <l>In all their Tricks; Then Wives in Husbands Checks. </l>
          <l>Where Virgins, in their sweete, and peacefull State </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000110-021-b"/>
          <l>Have all things perfect; spinne their owne free Fate; </l>
          <l>Depend on no prowd Second; are their owne </l>
          <l>Center, and Circle; Now, and alwaies One. </l>
          <l>To whose Example, we doe still heare nam'd </l>
          <l>One God, one Nature, and but one World fram'd, </l>
          <l>One Sunne, one Moone, one Element of Fire, </l>
          <l>So, of the Rest; One King, that doth inspire </l>
          <l>Soule, to all Bodies, in this royall Spheare: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000110-truth" xml:id="ep000110-e106840">
          <speaker>TRVTH. </speaker>
          <l>And where is Mariage more declar'd, then there? </l>
          <l>Is there a Band more strict, then that doth tie </l>
          <l>The Soule, and Body in such vnity? </l>
          <l>Subiects to Soveraignes? doth one Mind display </l>
          <l>In th'ones Obedience, and the others Sway? </l>
          <l>Beleeve it, Mariage suffers no compare, </l>
          <l>When both Estates are valew'd, as they are. </l>
          <l>The Virgin were a strange, and stubborne Thing, </l>
          <l>Would longer stay a Virgin, then to bring </l>
          <l>Her selfe fit vse, and profit in a Make. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000110-opinion" xml:id="ep000110-e106950">
          <speaker>OPINION. </speaker>
          <l>How she doth erre! and the whole Heav'n mistake! </l>
          <l>Looke how a Flower, that close in Closes growes, </l>
          <l>Hid from rude Cattell, bruised with no Ploughes, </l>
          <l>Which th' Ayre doth stroke, Sun strengthen, Showers </l>
          <l>It many Youths, &amp; many Maids desire; (shoot higher, </l>
          <l>The same, when cropt by cruell hand is wither'd, </l>
          <l>No Youths at all, No Maydens have desir'd: </l>
          <l>So a Virgin, while vntouch'd she doth remaine, </l>
          <l>Is deare to hers; but when with Bodyes stayne </l>
          <l>Her chaster Flower is lost, she leaves to appeare </l>
          <l>Or sweete to Yong Men, or to Maydens deare. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000110-022-a"/>
          <l>That Conquest then may crowne me in this Warre, </l>
          <l>Virgins, O Virgins fly from HYMEN farre. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000110-truth" xml:id="ep000110-e107090">
          <speaker>TRVTH. </speaker>
          <l>Virgins, O Virgins, to sweete HYMEN yeeld, </l>
          <l>For as a lone Vine, in a naked Field, </l>
          <l>Never extols her branches, never beares </l>
          <l>Ripe Grapes, but with a headlong heavinesse weares </l>
          <l>Her tender bodie, and her highest sproote </l>
          <l>Is quickly levell'd with hir fading roote; </l>
          <l>By whom no Husband-men, no Youths wil dwell; </l>
          <l>But if, by fortune, she be married well </l>
          <l>To th Elme, her Husband, many Husband-men, </l>
          <l>And many Youths inhabite by her, then: </l>
          <l>So whilst a Virgin doth, vntouch't, abide </l>
          <l>All vnmanur'd, she growes old, with hir pride; </l>
          <l>But when to equall Wedlocke, in fit Time, </l>
          <l>Her Fortune, and Endeuor lets her clime </l>
          <l>Deare to her Loue, and Parents, she is held. </l>
          <l>Virgins, O Virgins, to sweete HYMEN yeeld. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000110-opinion" xml:id="ep000110-e107260">
          <speaker>OPINION. </speaker>
          <l>These are but words; hast thou a Knight will trie </l>
          <l>(By stroke of Armes) the simple Veritie? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000110-truth" xml:id="ep000110-e107290">
          <speaker>TRVTH. </speaker>
          <l>To that high proofe I would haue dared thee. </l>
          <l>Ile strait fetch Champions for the Brides and Mee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000110-opinion" xml:id="ep000110-e107320">
          <speaker>OPINION. </speaker>
          <l>The like will I do for Virginitie. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>HEre, they both descended the Hall, where at the lower end, a March being sounded with Drums and Phifes, there entred (led foorth by <pb xml:id="ep000110-022-b"/>the Earle of Notingham, who was Lord high Constable for that night, and the Earle of Worc'ster, Earle Marshall) sixteene Knights, Armed, with Pikes, and Swords; their Plumes, and Colours, Carnation and White, all richly accoutred, and making their Honors to the State, as they march'd by in Paires, were all rank'd on one side of the Hall. They plac'd, Sixteene others alike accoutred for Riches, and Armes, onely that their Colours were varied to Watchet, and White; were by the same Earles led vp, and passing in like manner, by the State, plac'd on the opposite side. Whose Names (as they were given to me, both in Order, and Orthographie) were these. <list>
            <head>TRVTH. </head>
            <item>Duke of LENNOX. </item>
            <item>Lo. EFFINGHAM. </item>
            <item>Lo. WALDEN, </item>
            <item>Lo. MOVNTEAGLE. </item>
            <item>Sir THO. SOMERSET. </item>
            <item>Sir CHAR HOWARD. </item>
            <item>Sir IOHN GRAY. </item>
            <item>Sir THO MOVNSON. </item>
            <item>Sir IOHN LEIGH. </item>
            <item>Sir ROB. MAVNSELL. </item>
            <item>Sir EDVV. HOWARD. </item>
            <item>Sir HEN GOODYERE. </item>
            <item>Sir ROGER DALISON. </item>
            <item>Sir FRAN. HOWARD. </item>
            <item>Sir LEW. MAVNSELL. </item>
            <item>Mr. GVNTERET. </item>
          </list>
          <list>
            <head>OPINION. </head>
            <item>Earle of SVSSEX. </item>
            <item>Lo. WILLOVGHBY. </item>
            <item>Lo— GERRARD. </item>
            <item>Sir. ROB. CAREY. </item>
            <item>Sir OL. CRVMWEL. </item>
            <item>Sir WIL. HERBERT. </item>
            <item>Sir ROB. DREWRY. </item>
            <item>Sir WI. WOODHOVSE. </item>
            <item>Sir CAREY REYNOLDS. </item>
            <item>Sir RIC. HOVGHTON. </item>
            <item>Sir WIL. CONSTABLE. </item>
            <item>Sir THO. GERRARD, </item>
            <item>Sir ROB. KYLLEGREW. </item>
            <item>Sir THO BADGER. </item>
            <item>Sir THO. DVTTON. </item>
            <item>Mr. DIG BIE. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <pb xml:id="ep000110-023-a"/>
        <p>By this time, the Barre being brought vppe, TRVTH proceeded. </p>
        <sp who="#ep000110-truth" xml:id="ep000110-e107700">
          <speaker>TRVTH. </speaker>
          <l>Now ioyne; and if his varied Triall faile, </l>
          <l>To make my Truth in Wedlocks praise prevaile, </l>
          <l>I will retire, and in more power appeare; </l>
          <l>To cease this strife, and make our Question cleare. </l>
          <l>Whereat OPINION insulting, followed her with this speach. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000110-opinion" xml:id="ep000110-e107760">
          <speaker>OPINION. </speaker>
          <l>I, Doe: it were not safe thou shouldst abide: </l>
          <l>This speakes thy Name, with shame to quit thy side. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>Heere the Champions on both sides addresst themselves for fight, first Single; after Three to Three: and performed it with that alacritie, and vigor, as if MARS himselfe had beene to triumph before VENVS, &amp; invented a new Musique. When, on a sodaine, (the last Six having scarcely ended) a striking Light seem'd to fil all the Hall, and out of it an Angell or Messenger of Glorie appearing. </p>
        <sp who="#ep000110-angel" xml:id="ep000110-e107800">
          <speaker>ANGEL. </speaker>
          <l>PRinces, attend a tale of height, and wonder. </l>
          <l>TRVTH is descended in a second Thunder, </l>
          <l>And now will greete you, with ludiciall state, </l>
          <l>To grace the Nuptiall part in this debate; </l>
          <l>And end with reconciled hands these warres. </l>
          <l>Vpon her head she weares a Crowne of Starres, </l>
          <l>Through which her orient Hayre waves to her wast, </l>
          <l>By which beleeving Mortalls hold her fast, </l>
          <l>And in those golden Chordes are carried even </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000110-023-b"/>
          <l>Till with her breath she blowes them vp to Heaven. </l>
          <l>She weares a Roabe enchas'd with Eagles Eyes, </l>
          <l>To signifie her sight in Mysteries; </l>
          <l>Vpon each shoulder sits a milke white Dove, </l>
          <l>And at her feete doe witty Serpents move: </l>
          <l>Her spacious Armes doe reach from East to West, </l>
          <l>And you may see her Heart shine through her breast. </l>
          <l>Her right hand holds a Sunne with burning Rayes, </l>
          <l>Her left a curious bunch of golden Kayes, </l>
          <l>With which Heav'n Gates she locketh, and displayes. </l>
          <l>A Cristall Mirror hangeth at her brest, </l>
          <l>By which mens Consciences are search'd, and drest: </l>
          <l>On her Coach wheeles Hypocrisie lies rackt; </l>
          <l>And squint-eyd Slander, with Vaine-Glory backt </l>
          <l>Her bright Eyes burne to dust: in which shines Fate. </l>
          <l>An Angel vshers hir triumphant Gate, </l>
          <l>Whilst with her fingers Fannes of Starres she twists, </l>
          <l>And with them beates backe Error, clad in mists. </l>
          <l>Eternall Vnity behind her shines </l>
          <l>That Fire, and Water, Earth, and Ayre combines. </l>
          <l>Her voyce is like a Trumpet lowd, and shrill, </l>
          <l>Which bids all sounds in Earth, and Heav'n be still. </l>
          <l>And see! descended from her Chariot now, </l>
          <l>In this related Pompe she visits you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000110-truth" xml:id="ep000110-e108140">
          <speaker>TRVTH. </speaker>
          <l>Honor to all, that Honor Nuptialls. </l>
          <l>To whose faire Lot, in iustice, now it falls, </l>
          <l>That this my Counterfeit be here disclos'd, </l>
          <l>Who, for Virginity hath her selfe oppos'd. </l>
          <l>Nor, though my Brightnesse doe vndoe her Charmes, </l>
          <l>Let these her Knights thinke, that their equall Armes </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000110-024-a"/>
          <l>Are wrong'd therein; "For Valure wins applause </l>
          <l>" That dares, but to maintaine the weaker Cause. </l>
          <l>And Princes, see, tis meere OPINION, </l>
          <l>That in TRVTH'S forced Robe, for TRVTH hath gone! </l>
          <l>Her gaudy Colours, peec'd, with many Folds, </l>
          <l>Shew what vncertainties she ever holds: </l>
          <l>Vanish Adult'rate TRVTH, and never dare </l>
          <l>With prowd Maydes prayse, to prease where Nuptialls are. </l>
          <l>And Champions, since you see the Truth I held, </l>
          <l>To Sacred HYMEN, reconciled, yeeld: </l>
          <l>Nor, (so to yeeld,) thinke it the least Despight </l>
          <l>"It is a Conquest to submit to Right. </l>
          <l>This Royall Iudge of our Contention </l>
          <l>Will prop, I know, what I have vnder gone; </l>
          <l>To whose right Sacred Highnesse I resigne </l>
          <l>Low, at his feete, this Starry Crowne of mine, </l>
          <l>To shew his Rule, and Iudgement is diuine; </l>
          <l>These Doves to him I consecrate withall, </l>
          <l>To note his Innocence, without spot, or gall; </l>
          <l>These Serpents, for his Wisedome; and these Rayes, </l>
          <l>To shew his piercing Splendor; These bright Keyes, </l>
          <l>Designing Power to ope the ported Skies, </l>
          <l>And speake their Glories to his Subjects Eyes. </l>
          <l>Lastly, this Heart, with which all Hearts be true: </l>
          <l>And TRVTH in him make Treason ever rue. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>With This, they were led forth, hand in hand, reconciled, as in Triumph: and thus the Solemnities ended. </p>
        <quote>Vivite concordes, &amp; nostrum discite munus. </quote>
        <pb xml:id="ep000110-024-b"/>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="supplied_by_editor">
        <head>Notes, typically marginal, from the original text</head>
        <div corresp="A04654-e100120" xml:id="ep000110-e100120-n">
          <head>Notes for div A04654-e100120</head>
        </div>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
