<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000121" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Corona Minervae</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Francis</forename>
            <surname>Kynaston</surname>
          </persName>
          <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q5481650</idno>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A04959.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
        </bibl>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Corona Minervæ. Or A masque presented before Prince Charles His Highnesse, the Duke of Yorke his brother, and the Lady Mary his sister, the 27th of February, at the Colledge of the Museum Minervæ.</title>
            <author>Kinnaston, Francis, Sir, 1587-1642.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>15 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2011 April (TCP phase 2)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99843843</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 15100.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, II, 503.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">8602</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04959</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2240947206</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Corona Minervæ. Or A masque presented before Prince Charles His Highnesse, the Duke of Yorke his brother, and the Lady Mary his sister, the 27th of February, at the Colledge of the Museum Minervæ.</title>
            <title type="alt">Corona Minervæ</title>
            <title type="alt">Masque presented before Prince Charles His Highnesse, the Duke of Yorke his brother, and the Lady Mary his sister, the 27th of February, at the Colledge of the Museum Minervæ.</title>
            <author>Kinnaston, Francis, Sir, 1587-1642.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[28] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed for William Sheares,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date type="publication_date">1635.</date>
            <date type="creation_date">1635</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Anonymous. By Sir Francis Kinnaston.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>In verse.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-C4 D2.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Variant: with an added leaf, "To the reader", inserted after title page.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <person xml:id="ep000121-minerva">
            <persName>Minerva</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000121-time">
            <persName>Time</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000121-spring">
            <persName>Spring</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000121-winter">
            <persName>Winter</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000121-summer">
            <persName>Summer</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000121-autumn">
            <persName>Autumn</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000121-all">
            <persName>All</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000121-chorus">
            <persName>Chorus</persName>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1635">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000121-e100030">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000121-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000121-001-b"/>
        <p>CORONA MINERVAE. OR A MASQVE Presented before Prince CHARLES HIS HIGHNESSE, The Duke of Yorke his Brother, and the Lady Mary his Sister, the 27th of February, at the Colledge of the MVSEUM MINERVAE. </p>
        <p>LONDON, Printed for WILLIAM SHEARES. 1635. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="masque" xml:id="ep000121-e100070">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000121-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000121-002-b"/>
        <head>Corona Minervae. A Masque PRESENTED BEFORE Prince CHARLES his Highnesse, The Duke of YORKE his Brother, And the Lady MARY his Sister, the 27th. of February, at the Colledge of the Museum Minervae. </head>
        <p>A Curtaine being drawne, there is discovered a Frontispice, wheron the Image of Minerva is seene sitting upon a stone, placed betweene two Returnes of a broken Arch, supported by two Brasse statues of Mars, and Mercury, standing in neeches of Corinthian Worke: Vnder, within <pb xml:id="ep000121-003-a"/>a Prospective is seene, a pav'd Gallery invironed on either side and terminated with Dorike Columnes, which flying away, Minerva presents her selfe attired in her proper Habit. </p>
        <p>Over the Entrance in a Square was Written </p>
        <p>
          <quote>Corona Minervae. </quote>
        </p>
        <sp who="#ep000121-minerva" xml:id="ep000121-e100120">
          <speaker>Minerva. </speaker>
          <l>WHat rare unvaliew'd Iewels are here sent, </l>
          <l>As if the Gods themselves striv'd to present </l>
          <l>Minerva with their choicest Gems, &amp; Grace </l>
          <l>Her cabinet, as yet too meane a place </l>
          <l>To hold such Deities, who more adorne </l>
          <l>This presence, than the rosie finger'd Morne </l>
          <l>(Guiding the East for the uprising Sun) </l>
          <l>Doth beautifie his Carre, ready to run </l>
          <l>His daily Circle round. It hath been sayd, </l>
          <l>The Friends and Servants of the Iove-borne Mayd </l>
          <l>Are poore, except those, whom Bellonas hand </l>
          <l>Enrols for Souldiers of Mars warlike band, </l>
          <l>Who sometimes want their pay too: But now see </l>
          <l>A treasure here deposited with mee, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000121-003-b"/>
          <l>Out-valuing all the Riches of the Earth; </l>
          <l>Three Pledges of sweet Peace, whose happy Birth </l>
          <l>Blesseth this present Age, and Crown's it so, </l>
          <l>That former Ages past, could they but know </l>
          <l>How fortunate this is, they all would mourne </l>
          <l>They past so soone, or else would backe returne, </l>
          <l>To see an Age, wherein both Armes and Arts </l>
          <l>Flourish at height, and both share equall parts. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000121-e100350">Time enters here to Minerva in a Party coloured Robe halfe White, halfe Blacke, fringed with Silver, with one wing of a Swan, another of a Batt. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000121-time" xml:id="ep000121-e100360">
          <speaker>Time. </speaker>
          <l>Great Mistrisse of both Armes and Arts, 'tis true, </l>
          <l>Your exploration of their praises due, </l>
          <l>They are the Blessings, which the Ages past </l>
          <l>Fell ignorant, and unworthy-of to taste. </l>
          <l>And I old Time, that of those Ages saw </l>
          <l>The first, and last, till now could never draw </l>
          <l>Ayre, that so pleas'd mee, as in this blest Clime, </l>
          <l>That Crown's with Youth the old-old head of Time. </l>
          <l>All breath's Panchaian here: nay onely this </l>
          <l>Is the cleare Westerne that Favonian is, </l>
          <l>Perpetuall Spring creating. Gods heere </l>
          <l>Your two-fold Discipline, in which you were </l>
          <l>So late distracted by the world's neglect, </l>
          <l>Shall re-assume it's ancient faire respect. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-minerva" xml:id="ep000121-e100510">
          <speaker>Minerva. </speaker>
          <p>Time, you speake comfort to mee. </p>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000121-004-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000121-time" xml:id="ep000121-e100530">
          <speaker>Time. </speaker>
          <l>And no more </l>
          <l>Than my glad Daughter Truth is spreading o're </l>
          <l>This happy Monarchy, whose supreame head </l>
          <l>(In highest Heaven his name is registred) </l>
          <l>By Pow'r and Wisdome, will the use advance </l>
          <l>Of Armes and Arts, above dispight and chance. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-minerva" xml:id="ep000121-e100600">
          <speaker>Minerva. </speaker>
          <p>Time, thou hast made mee happy. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-time" xml:id="ep000121-e100620">
          <speaker>Time. </speaker>
          <l>No, 'tis hee </l>
          <l>That hath felicitated you and mee, </l>
          <l>Who hath already by defensive Armes, </l>
          <l>Beate backe the boasts, that were intended harmes, </l>
          <l>Which Industry is crowned with a peace, </l>
          <l>That daily will bring forth the Arts increase; </l>
          <l>You may observe th' assurance of it here </l>
          <l>In these, who he is pleas'd (to grace your Spheare) </l>
          <l>Should leave their owne; each an illustrious gem, </l>
          <l>Proper to his Imperiall Diadem; </l>
          <l>I could with Ioy and wonder dwell an age </l>
          <l>Vnder their smiles; from an old man, turne Page </l>
          <l>To waite upon their persons: breake my Glasse, </l>
          <l>And pick up sand by sand, ere I would passe </l>
          <l>From their divine aspects; use all delay </l>
          <l>Had not the Fates decreed Time must away. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000121-004-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000121-minerva" xml:id="ep000121-e100790">
          <speaker>Minerva. </speaker>
          <l>But not so fast, good Time, your haste may make </l>
          <l>Their Graces leave me too. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-time" xml:id="ep000121-e100820">
          <speaker>Time. </speaker>
          <l>Ile undertake, </l>
          <l>Sacred Minerva, they will not, but grace </l>
          <l>You and your Arts, whilst there is time and place, </l>
          <l>Yet ere I goe, for I must stay a while </l>
          <l>In this faire presence, and my haste beguile </l>
          <l>With a report of an unlook't for crew, </l>
          <l>Comming to see your Princely guests and you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-minerva" xml:id="ep000121-e100900">
          <speaker>Minerva. </speaker>
          <p>Time, what are they? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-time" xml:id="ep000121-e100920">
          <speaker>Time. </speaker>
          <l>The seasons of the yeare </l>
          <l>Having discover'd the convention here, </l>
          <l>All equally possest with an ambition, </l>
          <l>To see and to be seene without commission </l>
          <l>From me, or from the Moneths, or powerfull Sol, </l>
          <l>That wont is to infranchise, or controle </l>
          <l>Them at his pleasure, now are altogether </l>
          <l>Broke loose, and fill'd with gladnesse, posting hither. </l>
          <l>Cold Winter stretching out his cramp'd up nerves, </l>
          <l>Strives to out-strip the Iolly Spring, who serves </l>
          <l>Sommer the like, and with her nimble feet </l>
          <l>Runs through her heat, till they with Autumne meet; </l>
          <l>At last, they all conjoyn'd come on their way, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000121-005-a"/>
          <l>Like the whole yeere contracted in this day, </l>
          <l>Each season hath a severall present too, </l>
          <l>In which they strive each other to out-do, </l>
          <l>As if by generall warrant from their Fate, </l>
          <l>They all were alwayes to attend this State. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-minerva" xml:id="ep000121-e101110">
          <speaker>Minerva. </speaker>
          <p>'Tis welcome newes. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000121-e101130">A Confusion is here heard of severall voyces of Birds, and Beasts, such as are peculiar to every season. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000121-e101140">Againe here severall noyses and voyces are heard confusedly of Birds and Beasts, as exactly performed to the life, that no man could distinguish them. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000121-e101150">Vpon which, </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000121-time" xml:id="ep000121-e101160">
          <speaker>Time. </speaker>
          <l>Harke, they are all at hand, </l>
          <l>And all their Heraulds, both by ayre and land, </l>
          <l>The Birds and Beasts of every season met, </l>
          <l>In a most singular discord; harke how they set </l>
          <l>Throat against throat; the Wren and Red-brest swel </l>
          <l>To be above the Larke and Philomell. </l>
          <l>The Cuckow with the Howlet strives, and now </l>
          <l>The bleating Lamb joyes 'gainst the lowing Cow, </l>
          <l>All in confusion, and so shall you see, </l>
          <l>Will the contention of the Seasons be, </l>
          <l>Till I be stickler. See they come, stand by. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000121-e101280">Here enter the foure Seasons rushing in, Winter, Spring pulling him backe, Spring, Sommer, Autume, and Winter striving for precedence. </stage>
        <pb xml:id="ep000121-005-b"/>
        <stage xml:id="ep000121-e101290">Springs habit was of greene Taffata, fringed with silver; and figured with flowers, a Chaplet of severall flowers upon her head. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000121-spring" xml:id="ep000121-e101300">
          <speaker>Spring. </speaker>
          <p>Winter, keepe backe, I claime priority. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000121-e101320">Winter in a long Gowne of freeze, his haire and beard all made of Icicles, a Garland of Hollies and Ivie intwin'd upon his head. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000121-winter" xml:id="ep000121-e101330">
          <speaker>Winter. </speaker>
          <l>No wanton Girle, I must have first accesse, </l>
          <l>My age and honour can require no lesse. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000121-e101360">Sommer in a straw coloured Robe of Taffata, with a Garland of Corne-flowers, and blew Bottles upon his head. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000121-summer" xml:id="ep000121-e101370">
          <speaker>Sommer. </speaker>
          <p>I claime it from you both. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000121-e101390">Autumne his garment of Peuke-colour, a pruning knife in his hand, as a Vintiger, a Chaplet of Grapes and Damosens upon his head. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000121-autumn" xml:id="ep000121-e101400">
          <speaker>Autumne. </speaker>
          <l>Why, Summer you? </l>
          <l>The place to Autumne properly is due. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-spring" xml:id="ep000121-e101430">
          <speaker>Spring. </speaker>
          <l>How can that be? Looke into every race, </l>
          <l>Doe you not find, that Youth takes the first place. </l>
          <l>Was not the whole world young before 'twas old? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-winter" xml:id="ep000121-e101470">
          <speaker>Winter. </speaker>
          <l>And what of that, proud girle? thy reason's cold, </l>
          <l>Colder than is my Frost. Did not the Spring </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000121-006-a"/>
          <l>Of the old world rise from an elder thing, </l>
          <l>What else was Chaos? hah? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-spring" xml:id="ep000121-e101520">
          <speaker>Spring. </speaker>
          <p>I mind not that. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-winter" xml:id="ep000121-e101540">
          <speaker>Winter. </speaker>
          <p>Fond Lass, thou mind'st, say'st, do'st, thou know'st not what. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-summer" xml:id="ep000121-e101560">
          <speaker>Sommer. </speaker>
          <l>I doe: for Sommers strength is at full growth, </l>
          <l>Like middle age in man. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-autumn" xml:id="ep000121-e101590">
          <speaker>Antumne. </speaker>
          <l>I would be loath </l>
          <l>To give the knowledge of declining Age </l>
          <l>Which Autumne shadowes, for the Sommers rage. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-winter" xml:id="ep000121-e101630">
          <speaker>Winter. </speaker>
          <l>Y'are all against mee, and yet it doth appeare, </l>
          <l>None is anothers Friend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-spring" xml:id="ep000121-e101660">
          <speaker>Spring. </speaker>
          <l>Yet to the yeare </l>
          <l>Wee all doe gratefull Service, thou do'st none. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-winter" xml:id="ep000121-e101690">
          <speaker>Winter. </speaker>
          <p>I would heare that. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-spring" xml:id="ep000121-e101710">
          <speaker>Spring. </speaker>
          <l>In mee the Spring, 'tis knowne, </l>
          <l>The Grass, the Grain, the Leafe, the Flow'r, the Fruit, </l>
          <l>The Birds that sing, the Beasts, the Fishes mute </l>
          <l>Take their beginnings. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-summer" xml:id="ep000121-e101760">
          <speaker>Sommer. </speaker>
          <l>Make no tedious tale, </l>
          <l>You begin well, I ripe and perfect all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-spring" xml:id="ep000121-e101790">
          <speaker>Spring. </speaker>
          <l>In that you wrong mee Sommer: For you doe </l>
          <l>Out of my hands take Worke and Credit too. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000121-006-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000121-summer" xml:id="ep000121-e101820">
          <speaker>Sommer. </speaker>
          <l>I wrong not you so much as Autumne mee; </l>
          <l>For hee gets all the Crop from me and thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-autumn" xml:id="ep000121-e101850">
          <speaker>Autumne. </speaker>
          <l>But all the store I gather for the yeare, </l>
          <l>Winter devours, or spoyles. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-winter" xml:id="ep000121-e101880">
          <speaker>Winter. </speaker>
          <l>Pray Sirs forbeare, </l>
          <l>You increase all, you ripen all you say, </l>
          <l>You gather all, I spend all, and best may. </l>
          <l>I am the carefull Husband of the Earth, </l>
          <l>That gives her comforts after every Birth, </l>
          <l>In which you weare her out, or bring her low </l>
          <l>Past hope, that from her teeming womb should grow </l>
          <l>Ever more timely Fruits: I kindly then </l>
          <l>(That shee may live and propagate agen) </l>
          <l>Quench her feint thirst with plenteous showrs of rain </l>
          <l>Wherewith I fill her veines, and drowne her paine. </l>
          <l>Then having made her bed as soft below, </l>
          <l>I cover her with Swan downe, you call Snow, </l>
          <l>Which keepes her warme, so lay I her to rest: </l>
          <l>And for her lying-in make many a Feast </l>
          <l>Of her late store, for mortals that doe pray </l>
          <l>To see her blithe againe another day. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-spring" xml:id="ep000121-e102060">
          <speaker>Spring. </speaker>
          <p>Which day would never come, wer't not with mee. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-winter" xml:id="ep000121-e102080">
          <speaker>Winter. </speaker>
          <p>Nor thou with it, did not I set her free. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-summer" xml:id="ep000121-e102100">
          <speaker>Sommer. </speaker>
          <p>This strife will grow unto an endlesse fit. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-autumn" xml:id="ep000121-e102120">
          <speaker>Autumne. </speaker>
          <p>Would wee had Time here to determine it. </p>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000121-007-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000121-time" xml:id="ep000121-e102140">
          <speaker>Time. </speaker>
          <l>Time is at hand, who gives an instant charge </l>
          <l>Distinctly, that each one of you enlarge </l>
          <l>Himselfe by practise, shew what you can doe, </l>
          <l>Before the Presence you aspire unto. </l>
          <l>What Presents, or what Pastimes you have brought </l>
          <l>To please these Glories, whom all you have sought </l>
          <l>T'endeere your service to. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-all" xml:id="ep000121-e102220">
          <speaker>All Foure. </speaker>
          <p>I have the best. </p>
          <stage xml:id="ep000121-e102240">Here every one offered Baskets of fresh Fruits and Flowres. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-time" xml:id="ep000121-e102250">
          <speaker>Time. </speaker>
          <l>Nay one at once, for whilst you all contest </l>
          <l>Each to be first, you but confusion make; </l>
          <l>Let Time then governe you, for order sake: </l>
          <l>Seasons, I promise you both first and last, </l>
          <l>And all shall equally their favours taste. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-all" xml:id="ep000121-e102310">
          <speaker>All foure. </speaker>
          <p>Wee all obey. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-time" xml:id="ep000121-e102330">
          <speaker>Time. </speaker>
          <l>Then thus I order yee, </l>
          <l>Out of your discord to raise harmonie, </l>
          <l>Presents y'have brought I see of fruits, and flowers, </l>
          <l>Leave them with me; whilst from their Caves and Bowers, </l>
          <l>Each season summon forth &amp; here advance </l>
          <l>A paire of his attendance in a dance, </l>
          <l>To move delight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-all" xml:id="ep000121-e102410">
          <speaker>All foure. </speaker>
          <p>Immediately 'tis done. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000121-e102430">Here as Time speaketh, the Seasons go off. First, Spring, then Sommer, Autumne next, and last Winter, and immediately, as they depart, the severall voyces are heard distinctly, and in order according to the words of Time. </stage>
        <pb xml:id="ep000121-007-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000121-time" xml:id="ep000121-e102440">
          <speaker>Time. </speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>First Spring lead you the way, then ev'ry one </l>
            <l>In order follow, let your Heraulds sound </l>
            <l>Each to his season, as the yeare goes round: </l>
            <l>The Spring begins her part already, harke! </l>
            <l>The evening Lambe, and morning early Larke </l>
            <l>Lead her her way, the merry Cuckow too </l>
            <l>Busie in's office; Sommer, now goe you, </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Now marke the Ioy the Fawne &amp; Swallow takes, </l>
            <l>Of which there's more then one a Sommer makes, </l>
            <l>To welcome her; now Autumne take your turne, </l>
            <l>Lest Sommers too long raigne your Harvest burne: </l>
            <l>The Thrush now chaunts her notes at his approach, </l>
            <l>And the glad Bore-pig having scap'd the broach </l>
            <l>At the last Faire, runs wild about to taste </l>
            <l>The scatter'd graine, and the sweet fatting maste. </l>
            <l>Now follow Winter whilst your Robin sings, </l>
            <l>Over the halfe dead earth, to wake the Springs, </l>
            <l>In her cold veines, hearke how the hoarse growne Cow </l>
            <l>Low's for her fodder, and to whit to whow </l>
            <l>Madge Howlet cryes, for cold she 'as in her feet, </l>
            <l>But other musicke now for Dauncers meet. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000121-e102680">Here enter to dance, <ref target="A04959-e102690-b">1 </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04959-e102690-a" n="1" place="margin">1 Emblem of the Spring. </note>a Frog followed by a Fisher-man. To them, <ref target="A04959-e102700-b">2 </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04959-e102700-a" n="2" place="margin">2 Of the Sommer. </note>a Sheepsherer leading a Ram. To them, <ref target="A04959-e102710-b">3 </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04959-e102710-a" n="3" place="margin">3 Of the Autumne. </note>a Drunken Butcher holding a Pig by the taile. <ref target="A04959-e102720-b">4 </ref>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A04959-e102720-a" n="4" place="margin">4 Of Winter. </note>To them a Chimney-sweeper and a Cat. All to severall straines of agreeing musicke. At length all being entred, they joyne in a Dance. The Dance ended. </stage>
        <pb xml:id="ep000121-008-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000121-time" xml:id="ep000121-e102730">
          <speaker>Time. </speaker>
          <l>Creatures be gone, and let your Muses meet </l>
          <l>With fluent numbers, and harmonious sweet </l>
          <l>Voyces, to sing, of all their presents here </l>
          <l>The worth and rarity, and let the neere </l>
          <l>Adjoyning Woods, Rocks, Vallies, Caues, and Hils </l>
          <l>Resound their ecchoing helpes to grace their skils, </l>
          <l>While I their severall presents over-view, </l>
          <l>The Spring brings here all that is rare, and new, </l>
          <l>Of early flowers and fruits, such as to name </l>
          <l>In other seasons might beget a blame, </l>
          <l>For longing Ladies sakes. The Sommer brings </l>
          <l>Gifts no lesse dainty, for her offrings; </l>
          <l>So Autumne, and so Winter, so all beare </l>
          <l>At once, the rarities of all the yeare. </l>
          <l>Yet let not my dull talke attempt to wrong, </l>
          <l>T'anticipate the Subject of their Song, </l>
          <l>But let the woods, rocks, &amp;c. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000121-e102910">Here are sung the severall Songs by severall voices, with Symphanies betwixt, and a Chorus: during which, Time peruseth the severall presents, as he discovers them orderly: All which are exprest in the Song. </stage>
        <floatingText>
          <body>
            <div type="song" xml:id="ep000121-e102940">
              <head>The Seasons Song. </head>
              <sp who="#ep000121-spring" xml:id="ep000121-e102950">
                <speaker>Spring. </speaker>
                <l>Those Flow'rs your Infancie did crowne, </l>
                <l>Spring doth againe to you resigne, </l>
                <l>Which now are yours, no more her owne, </l>
                <l>The Prim-rose, and sweet Eglantine, </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000121-008-b"/>
                <l>The Daisie, Pinck, and Violet blew, </l>
                <l>All which receiv'd their sents from you. </l>
                <l>May Blossomes now shall never fade, </l>
                <l>You have May everlasting made. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp who="#ep000121-chorus" xml:id="ep000121-e103040">
                <speaker>Chorus. </speaker>
                <lg>
                  <l>All hearts rejoyce, which now behold </l>
                  <l>Againe the happy Age of Gold. </l>
                  <l>For Time to us hath brought far more </l>
                  <l>True joyes, then fain'd were heretofore. </l>
                  <l>Three Royall Blossomes to us hee doth bring, </l>
                  <l>Whose lookes and sweetnesse, make eternall Spring. </l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                  <l>May Cherries plasht up to the wall, </l>
                  <l>The Dew-berries, that in valleyes growes, </l>
                  <l>Kept in your lips, shall never fall, </l>
                  <l>The Lady Grasse, and the Muske Rose, </l>
                  <l>Which were your Mantle swathing band </l>
                  <l>You make yet florish freshly, and </l>
                  <l>Sweet Fennell, for Court flatterers fit </l>
                  <l>Lives under you, you above it. </l>
                </lg>
              </sp>
              <sp who="#ep000121-chorus" xml:id="ep000121-e103210">
                <speaker>Chorus. </speaker>
                <l>All hearts rejoyce, &amp;c. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp who="#ep000121-summer" xml:id="ep000121-e103230">
                <speaker>Sommer. </speaker>
                <l>To keepe the Sommers heat away, </l>
                <l>Which Earth from the young Sun receives. </l>
                <l>The Elme, the Siccamore, and Bay </l>
                <l>Still shade you with their lasting Leaves. </l>
                <l>The Lillies, and the Damaske Rose, </l>
                <l>The sheets and bed, when you repose, </l>
                <l>More white, more sweet, more soft have bin </l>
                <l>Since they did touch your whiter skin. </l>
                <pb subtype="duplicate" type="blank" xml:id="ep000121-009-a"/>
                <pb subtype="duplicate" type="blank" xml:id="ep000121-009-b"/>
                <pb xml:id="ep000121-010-a"/>
                <l>To sleepe when your faire eyes incline, </l>
                <l>Hiding from Men their dearest light, </l>
                <l>Let hearts ease, Flow'rs of Iessamine, </l>
                <l>And Rose-marie your couches dight. </l>
                <l>The holy Thistle downe shall fill </l>
                <l>Your Pillowes, Boulsters, and untill </l>
                <l>You rise like Gemini, arme in arme, </l>
                <l>Levander cotten keepe you warme. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp who="#ep000121-chorus" xml:id="ep000121-e103400">
                <speaker>Chorus. </speaker>
                <l>All hearts rejoyce, &amp;c. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp who="#ep000121-autumn" xml:id="ep000121-e103420">
                <speaker>Autumne. </speaker>
                <l>Rising from Beds of Iuly flow'rs </l>
                <l>With Hyacinthus, and Narcissus spred </l>
                <l>Into your lap Autumnus pow'rs, </l>
                <l>The Mul-berries, and Raspis red, </l>
                <l>Pomona in her Basket beares </l>
                <l>Apricocks, and Bon Christian Peares. </l>
                <l>And Bacchus forth his hand will reach </l>
                <l>To pluck the Damson, Fig, and Peach. </l>
                <l>And for digestion, Candian wines </l>
                <l>Will skinke out of his Indian gourd </l>
                <l>Mellecottones, and Nectarines </l>
                <l>Hee brings you from his mellow hoord, </l>
                <l>That you shall wish, while you them taste, </l>
                <l>Autumne and Spring may ever last: </l>
                <l>Or, that, except them two, there were </l>
                <l>No other Seasons of the yeare. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp who="#ep000121-chorus" xml:id="ep000121-e103590">
                <speaker>Chorus. </speaker>
                <l>All hearts rejoyce, &amp;c. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp who="#ep000121-winter" xml:id="ep000121-e103610">
                <speaker>Winter. </speaker>
                <l>Cold Winter brings to crowne your Age </l>
                <l>Many happy yeares are told. </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000121-010-b"/>
                <l>The Mirtle, Savory, and Sage, </l>
                <l>The semper viva, never old, </l>
                <l>To Crowne your high victorious browes </l>
                <l>Greene lawrell Garlands, Arbute boughes </l>
                <l>With Palmes, and Olives, whose increase </l>
                <l>Are emblems of your lasting peace. </l>
                <l>Nor is cold winter yet at all </l>
                <l>Lesse frolicke, then the wanton Spring: </l>
                <l>The Robin red Brest in the Hall </l>
                <l>Picking up crummes at Christmas sing </l>
                <l>When winds blow cold, and wayes be fowle </l>
                <l>In Barnes, and sheepe coats sits the Owle, </l>
                <l>Whose note the husbandman delights </l>
                <l>When as shee hoots in frosty nights. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp who="#ep000121-chorus" xml:id="ep000121-e103780">
                <speaker>Chorus. </speaker>
                <l>All harts, &amp;c. </l>
                <stage xml:id="ep000121-e103800">The Songs being ended. </stage>
              </sp>
            </div>
          </body>
        </floatingText>
        <sp who="#ep000121-minerva" xml:id="ep000121-e103810">
          <speaker>Minerva. </speaker>
          <stage xml:id="ep000121-e103820">Here is discovered the Temple of Minerva supported upon Doricke columnes standing in a grove, before the Temple gate an anticke Greeke Altar whereon was a Crowne placed. </stage>
          <l>SEasons I thanke you, that have all so well </l>
          <l>Striv'd by your loves each others to excell </l>
          <l>In honour of these Princes. Now by you, </l>
          <l>Time, let my service be presented too. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-time" xml:id="ep000121-e103870">
          <speaker>Time. </speaker>
          <l>TIme takes your charge, and swiftly will declare </l>
          <l>What the devotions of Minerva are. </l>
          <l>To you great Prince, and to each blessed Bud </l>
          <l>Of the same Royall Stocke, and link'd in bloud </l>
          <l>With you, Minerva gratefully imparts </l>
          <l>Full knowledge, and true use of Armes, Arts, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000121-011-a"/>
          <l>And that shee, bound unto this gratitude </l>
          <l>I by fames Trumpet will make understood </l>
          <l>Her reason through the World, for thus shee sayes, </l>
          <l>Whereas of old shee was sole patronesse </l>
          <l>Of Armes, and Arts, and former ages through </l>
          <l>Had reverence, and adoration due </l>
          <l>To her divinitie; shee by blind chance </l>
          <l>Hath beene of late, and blinder ignorance </l>
          <l>Rudely oppos'd, opprest, and lastly throwne </l>
          <l>By violence from her proper mansion </l>
          <l>Altars, and Temples, that were dedicate </l>
          <l>To her of old, are now laied ruinate, </l>
          <l>And shee forlorne to give the World a view </l>
          <l>Was all to seeke of house, and patron too, </l>
          <l>Labouring with that distresse, unto this Ile </l>
          <l>More gratious made by the most gratious smile </l>
          <l>Of its most royall Soveraigne, then the day </l>
          <l>In other Lands, by Phoebus brightest ray, </l>
          <l>She bent her course, and here shee was receiv'd </l>
          <l>By the most gratious, bounteous King releiv'd, </l>
          <l>Planted, and raisd to a magnificke State, </l>
          <l>Above the reach of her malignant Fate: </l>
          <l>For which unequall grace, shee can no lesse </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000121-e104170">Here a cupid descending with a light in his hand shewes unto the Prince a Crowne, which is placed on Minerva's Altar, and reserved by her for his highnes. </stage>
          <l>Then yeeld her selfe to be his votaresse, </l>
          <l>Of all her gifts devoting the renowne </l>
          <l>A due addition to his fourefold Crowne. </l>
          <l>In pledge whereof, first branch of that faire stem, </l>
          <l>High Prince, here is a Royall diadem </l>
          <l>Brought from her old, here to her Athens new </l>
          <l>By your propitious Fate reserv'd for you </l>
          <l>Vpon Minerva's Altar, 'tis noe slight </l>
          <l>Or fabulous thing that Time shall now recite; </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000121-011-b"/>
          <l>
            <ref target="A04959-e104280-b"/>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04959-e104280-a" place="margin">Hippocrates divinanatura preditus nonus a Chrisamide Rege, decimus et octavus ab AEsculapio. Vigesimus a looe ex Patre Heraclida, ex matre Paxithea Phaenaretes silia ex familia He aclidarum, quare ex utroque se. mine a Diis ortum habet divinus Hippocrates, ut qui a patre quidem Asclepiades est, a matre Heraclides. didicit artātuma Patre Heraclidatū ab avo Hippocrate &amp; proinde iustissime, in multis terrae locis divinos honores etiam ipse consequutus est, et tisdem donariis cum Hercule et AEscula pioab Atheniensi bus dignus factus est. paetus in epistola ad Regem Regum Magnum Artaxerxem. Heraclidae erant Gigantes, in oratione Thessaliad Athenienses. Hippocrates genere et arte conjunctus est Aesculapio, hic vero Herculis est ex fratre nepos. in Epistola senatus Populique Abderitarum. </note>Tis found in my records 'mongst ancient rules </l>
          <l>That were observed in Minervas Schooles </l>
          <l>That those of Physicke were not held the least </l>
          <l>But rather most Divine of all the rest, </l>
          <l>And that of old Physitians had relation </l>
          <l>Mongst Princes, and the gods, and adoration </l>
          <l>Given to their person, and their memories. </l>
          <l>Then shin'd Minerva's Altar, when her wise </l>
          <l>Athenians there, to adde his renowne, </l>
          <l>Gave Hercules an Aesculapian Crowne: </l>
          <l>And after him, when by the same decree </l>
          <l>Great skil'd Hippocrates upon his knee </l>
          <l>Receiv'd the like, and was sent crowned thence </l>
          <l>Physitians, and Philosophers, high Prince, </l>
          <l>This Crowne still reserves in store </l>
          <l>Great Sir, to adde unto your future fowre. </l>
          <l>To this, as to the rest, y'are Princely heire </l>
          <l>Prince of Physitians borne your titles faire </l>
          <l>And I finde it (Time shall doe noe wrong) </l>
          <l>In rendring truth, though his discourse be long. </l>
          <l>In Florence the first Dukes to crowne the name </l>
          <l>Of Cosmus, who most piously became </l>
          <l>Patron of christian cures successively, </l>
          <l>Were (the Physitians art to dignifie) </l>
          <l>Through many raignes calld Cosmus, latter daies </l>
          <l>Have crow'nd the Medici with flourishing Baies, </l>
          <l>All of them still imploying, that they are </l>
          <l>Patrons of all Physitians regulare: </l>
          <l>And from the illustrious Florence Medici </l>
          <l>You draw a line from France to Britanie </l>
          <l>Twas first the honour of the Florence Crowne </l>
          <l>To take its faire denomination </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000121-012-a"/>
          <l>From physicks Art, and that but rationall </l>
          <l>In France to physicke supernaturall. </l>
          <l>That titles linckt, and both in one brought ore </l>
          <l>Met the miraculous cure was here before </l>
          <l>In the thrice happy England, soe you are </l>
          <l>By vertue of descent apparant heire </l>
          <l>To the Physitians crowne, who both inherit </l>
          <l>Of rationall, and miraculous cures the spirit. </l>
          <l>
            <ref target="A04959-e104690-b"/>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04959-e104690-a" place="margin">That those of physicke. Hippocrates divina natura praeditus est, nonus quidem a Crisamide Rege: &amp;c, Hippocrates is indowed with a Divine Nature the ninth truly by descent from King Crisamides, the eightteenth from Esculapius, the twentith from Iupiter: by his mother Praxithea the daughter of Phaenaretes. he is of the family of the Heraclides, by his father an Asclepiad, so that by both his parents divine Hippocrates hath his off-spring from the gods, &amp; for his Art most iustly hath in many places of the earth obtayned divine honors &amp; with Hercules &amp; Esculapius, hee hath by the Athenians bin made worthy of the same gifts &amp;c: Petus Proconsull in his Epistle to the great King of Kings Artaxerxes. </note>For which, and for the favours done to her </l>
          <l>Minerva must on you this Crowne conferre. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-minerva" xml:id="ep000121-e104710">
          <speaker>Minerva. </speaker>
          <stage xml:id="ep000121-e104720">Here the musicke sounds for the dance of the 4. Nations of England Scotland, France and Ireland. </stage>
          <l>TIme while you strive to shew my gratitude </l>
          <l>I feare you are thought tedious if not rude </l>
          <l>To presse soe farre. But harke this Musicke saies </l>
          <l>Each Nation, that subjectingly obeyes </l>
          <l>Their Majesties, and you are come to show </l>
          <l>With nimble feete the duty, that they owe </l>
          <l>
            <ref target="A04959-e104800-b"/>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04959-e104800-a" place="margin">Visum est, ac decretum senatui &amp; populo Atheniensium ut gratiam condignam Hippocrati pro benefactis referat, ipsum publicè magnis mysteriis initiare quemadmodum Herculem fusum lovis, &amp; Coronare ipsum Corona aurea mille anreorum, et ipsam Coronam quatriis magnis Minerva festis, in Gertamine gymnico per praeconem proclamare. in Decreto Atheni, ensium. Ab initio Dei unde genus nostrum esse gloriamur Aesculapius et Hercules in hominum utilitatem prognatisunt. Et hos proptervirtutem quam exercuerunt, omnes de-rumloco habent Oratio Thèssali ad Athenienses. </note>All in their kinde t'expresse their skill in dance. </l>
          <l>Glad England first, blith Scotland, sprightly France </l>
          <l>And civiliz'd Ireland shall in order trace </l>
          <l>And doe their best to gaine a greater grace. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000121-e104840">Enter the Dancers who having ended their dance Minerva speakes to the Princes. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000121-minerva" xml:id="ep000121-e104850">
          <speaker>Minerva. </speaker>
          <l>NOw Princely ones may't please you to advance </l>
          <l>And your aspects on fresher objects glance </l>
          <l>Of Armes, and Arts. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000121-012-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000121-time" xml:id="ep000121-e104890">
          <speaker>Time. </speaker>
          <l>Pray you be pleas'd to walke </l>
          <l>and pardon Time, old folks are full of talke. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000121-e104920">The Prince, and the rest are here conducted by Minerva, and Time towards the Chamber of Arts, and Armes, by the way Minerva turning to the Prince speakes. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-minerva" xml:id="ep000121-e104930">
          <speaker>Minerva. </speaker>
          <l>GReat Britaines Prince, since that your innate love </l>
          <l>To learning doth soe soone your highnes move </l>
          <l>To view Minerva's mansion, and to be </l>
          <l>Admitted one of hers. Behold, and see </l>
          <l>How I begin (out of a tender care </l>
          <l>Complying with your yeeres) bookes to prepare </l>
          <l>Fit for your studies, now from which by sense </l>
          <l>You may extract the sweetest quintessence </l>
          <l>
            <ref target="A04959-e105030-b"/>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A04959-e105030-a" place="margin">Ego nunc cum mea sobole, oleaeramulis coronotus ad Mineruae aram supplex consisto. Oratio Hippocratis ad aram consistentis Coro. illa aurea in vestro theatro in posita ad sum. ām aemulationēac felicitatem patrem meum evexit: sed et hoc beneficium superastis, dum et patrem et me publicè Cereris et Proserpinae mysteriis ac sacris initiastis. Thessalus in ora●. ad Athenienses. Thessalus filius Hippocratis aurea corona coronatus ab Atheniensibus Theodoret. </note>Had by allusion to each Authours name </l>
          <l>To sweeten learnings roote soe as the same </l>
          <l>To others bitter might prove sweete to you </l>
          <l>Then freely taste, and tasting cast your view </l>
          <l>Vpon each Authours name, whereby you may </l>
          <l>Be more acquainted with them day by day. </l>
          <l>And, as your better part shall shine more cleare </l>
          <l>I'le from themselves still make you better cheare. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000121-e105110">The Princes, and the rest being entred. </stage>
        <pb xml:id="ep000121-013-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000121-time" xml:id="ep000121-e105120">
          <speaker>Time. </speaker>
          <l>HOw now, what mystery is this? </l>
          <l>How dare you use the Prince thus, schoole-mistris? </l>
          <l>Are th'armes, and arts you promis'd to his view </l>
          <l>To be pick't out of bookes? This is a new </l>
          <l>And a course way of entertainment too. </l>
          <l>A banquet had ben fitter. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-minerva" xml:id="ep000121-e105190">
          <speaker>Minerva. </speaker>
          <l>Such is this </l>
          <l>TIme, if you knew but what sweete learning is </l>
          <l>Compos'd in these plaine bookes, your selfe would say </l>
          <l>Both for delight, and health his Highnes may </l>
          <l>Not onely taste, but as his meat devoure them, </l>
          <l>And soe become a Helluo librorum. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-time" xml:id="ep000121-e105260">
          <speaker>Time. </speaker>
          <l>YEt by your learned leave, Minerva, let </l>
          <l>Before his taster here the bookes be set </l>
          <l>What Authour's this? pray let us here begin </l>
          <l>Suetonius saies his out side: but within </l>
          <l>All sweet meats. Oh sweete Suetonius! </l>
          <l>What's his next neighbour? Aulus Gellius, </l>
          <l>All gellies, as I am true Time. What lurkes </l>
          <l>Here in this volume? Tis Frier Bacons workes </l>
          <l>Most sweetely interlarded. And here's Cato </l>
          <l>In bisket cakes, and sugar plates in Plato. </l>
          <l>Erasmus full of preserv'd Raspices, </l>
          <l>Delicate Authors all. Now what are these </l>
          <l>Damesins in Damascenus, and preserv'd </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000121-013-b"/>
          <l>Lemons here in Levinus Lemnius serv'd. </l>
          <l>Aples in Apuleius. All's good cheere. </l>
          <l>But stay Minerva, what good drinke ha'ye here </l>
          <l>To wash it downe? oh here I see are brought </l>
          <l>Nine Amphora's of glasse; in each a draught </l>
          <l>Of severall waters, sent from severall wells </l>
          <l>And fountaines, where the sacred Muses dwelles, </l>
          <l>As their nine names, which are inscrib'd thereon </l>
          <l>Doe plainely show. See first from Helicon </l>
          <l>Clio a cleare immortall liquour sends, </l>
          <l>Vrania Eridanus commends, </l>
          <l>Thalia of Ionian pleasant streames </l>
          <l>A drinke hath sent. The auncient Poets Theames </l>
          <l>Bacchus Minervas botle-man did bring </l>
          <l>This sweetest Nectar from the Thespian spring, </l>
          <l>A present from Erato: this pure cleane </l>
          <l>Fresh water seemes to come from Hippocrene </l>
          <l>Euterpe's gift: and here, and please you, sip ye </l>
          <l>Of the cleare brooke, that runnes from Aganippe, </l>
          <l>Sent by Melpomene, so of the rest, </l>
          <l>Whose liquours come to dignifie the feast, </l>
          <l>So may you eate, and drinke, and carry more </l>
          <l>Of learning hence then Pallas keepes in store. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000121-e105630">The banquet being ended Minerva turning to the Prince speakes for a conclusion thus. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000121-minerva" xml:id="ep000121-e105640">
          <speaker>Minerva. </speaker>
          <l>NOw (royall Prince) with thankes let Pallas say; </l>
          <l>Sh'has by your brightnesse had a glorious day: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000121-014-a"/>
          <l>But you declining your Phoebean light </l>
          <l>Will leave her shrouded in perpetuall night, </l>
          <l>Vnlesse to show y'are pleas'd you leave for grace </l>
          <l>A smile, which may illuminate the place. </l>
          <l>So shall Minerva give a glad adieu </l>
          <l>Withall her Atmes, and Arts to wait on you. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000121-e105730">For the Banquet were provided litle Angels holding Candles to give light unto the Princes: which hung in the aire could no way be discerned. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000121-e105740">The Banquet which Minerva gave was inclosed in Artificiall bookes, so handsomely made that no man could know but that they were very bookes indeed, disposed and placed according to their severall volumnes: betweene which by these nine severall amphoras of Glasse were placed, full of 9 severall sorts of Wines as sent from the 9 Muses. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000121-e105750">The Authors that Minerva shewed the Princes were many, but the first that fell into the Princes hands were these, which follow named: and in the frontispeece of them were found these Verses following. </stage>
        <lg>
          <head>In Suetonius these </head>
          <l>MY title is Suetonius, but within </l>
          <l>A history of sweete meates doth begin, </l>
          <l>Which so may please (Illustrious Prince) your taste </l>
          <l>As your life may all Caesars Acts out last. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <head>Aulus Gellius. </head>
          <l>LEt the lampe wasting student, who delights </l>
          <l>In reading Aulus Gellius Attike nights, </l>
          <l>Make himselfe pale: here for a Courtiers wit </l>
          <l>Is nourishing strong gelly much more fit. </l>
        </lg>
        <pb xml:id="ep000121-014-b"/>
        <lg>
          <head>Frier Bacons workes. </head>
          <l>Frier Bacons workes my inside well may be </l>
          <l>Now Conjur'd into Collops: and yet see </l>
          <l>There is no Puritane but would desire </l>
          <l>Like to the devill to devoure this Frier. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <head>Lucius Florus. </head>
          <l>See Lucius Florus from his history </l>
          <l>Renders you nothing but a Prophecy </l>
          <l>Vpon your flower deluces, which he sayes </l>
          <l>Shall grace your crowne bove all his Emperours bayes. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <head>Levinus Lemnius de occultis naturae miraculis. </head>
          <l>IF for Levinus Lemnius you doe finde </l>
          <l>Dried canded Lemons, or a Citron rinde, </l>
          <l>Heere soone read over: for at once you looke </l>
          <l>On all the hidden secrets of his booke. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <head>Apuleius. </head>
          <l>NOt Apuleius golden Asses story </l>
          <l>(Glory of Princes) here is set before ye: </l>
          <l>But golden apples of the Hesperides </l>
          <l>Are brought your taste, as well as sight to please. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <head>Quintus Curtius. </head>
          <l>MY outside's Quinius Curtius (gratious Princes) </l>
          <l>But see within my leaves are curious Quinces </l>
          <l>This transposition well excused may be: </l>
          <l>Bookes and their titles doe not still agree. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <head>Origen. </head>
          <l>IF (curious reader) you desire to know, </l>
          <l>Why the inside and the title differ so: </l>
          <l>As Origen and Orang, make no doubt, </l>
          <l>The Anagram's within of what's without. </l>
        </lg>
        <pb xml:id="ep000121-015-a"/>
        <lg>
          <head>Damascenus. </head>
          <l>OLd Damascenus sayes you are to young, </l>
          <l>Sweet Prince, to reade or taste of Physicke strong: </l>
          <l>Therefore which better may your palate suite, </l>
          <l>Praescribes you damsens your liege Country fruite. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <head>Erasmus Roterodamus. </head>
          <l>WHen with Erasmus you hereafter meete, </l>
          <l>Youle find him like this Raspis sharpe &amp; sweet </l>
          <l>Sweete like Almond butter, which ne're came </l>
          <l>From any butter box of Roterdame. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <head>Cato. </head>
          <l>CAto from Sugar Cakes not differs farre, </l>
          <l>Since into distickes both divided are. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <head>Plato. </head>
          <l>VOuchsafe of Platoes workes to taste a piece, </l>
          <l>Though not of Greeke, yet full of Ambergreece. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <head>Manuscripti. </head>
          <l>AMongst so many bookes tis not ore slip't, </l>
          <l>That you have here a Manuscript. </l>
          <l>You may well see by what you doe finde in't, </l>
          <l>'Twas done by hand and never yet in Print. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <head>Hermolaus Barbarus. </head>
          <l>OF Hermolaus Barbarus the sence </l>
          <l>Is harmeles; barberies, like Eloquence: </l>
          <l>Which though 'tis sweet, hath tartnes mix't among </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000121-015-b"/>
          <l>Witnesse each wanton witty womans tongue. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <head>Cardanus. </head>
          <l>Cardanus workes these are, as some doe say, </l>
          <l>But it seemes rather that they were his play. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <head>Littleton. </head>
          <l>HEre Littleton is set before your eyes, </l>
          <l>Because law's common, little shall suffice: </l>
          <l>Yet is that little much to be regarded, </l>
          <l>Because an old Coke hath it interlarded. </l>
        </lg>
        <trailer>FINIS </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="supplied_by_editor">
        <head>Notes, typically marginal, from the original text</head>
        <div corresp="A04959-e100070" xml:id="ep000121-e100070-n">
          <head>Notes for div A04959-e100070</head>
        </div>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
