<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The triumphs of integrity A noble solemnity, performed through the city, at the sole cost and charges of the Honorable Fraternity of Drapers, at the confirmation and establishment of their most worthy brother, the Right Honorable, Martin Lumley, in the high office of his Maiesties Lieutenant, Lord Maior and Chancellor of the famous City of London. Taking beginning at his Lordships going, and perfecting it selfe after his returne from receiuing the oath of maioralty at Westminster, on the morrow after Simon and Iudes Day, being the 29. of October. 1623. By Tho. Middleton Gent.</title>
        <author>
<!--Middleton, Thomas-->
          <persName>
            <forename>Thomas</forename>
            <surname>Middleton</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <idno type="dracor" xml:base="https://dracor.org/id/">ep000196</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A07516.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <p>
            This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is available for reuse, according to the terms of
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>
            . The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
          </p>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull>
              <titleStmt>
                <title>The triumphs of integrity A noble solemnity, performed through the city, at the sole cost and charges of the Honorable Fraternity of Drapers, at the confirmation and establishment of their most worthy brother, the Right Honorable, Martin Lumley, in the high office of his Maiesties Lieutenant, Lord Maior and Chancellor of the famous City of London. Taking beginning at his Lordships going, and perfecting it selfe after his returne from receiuing the oath of maioralty at Westminster, on the morrow after Simon and Iudes Day, being the 29. of October. 1623. By Tho. Middleton Gent.</title>
                <author>Middleton, Thomas, d. 1627.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[20] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes, dwelling in Foster-lane,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                <date>1623.</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ C² .</note>
                <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000196-e10">
        <pb xml:id="ep000196-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000196-001-b"/>
        <p>THE TRIVMPHS OF Integrity. </p>
        <p>A Noble Solemnity, performed through the City, at the sole Cost and Charges of the Honorable Fraternity of Drapers, at the Confirmation and Establishment of their most worthy Brother, The Right Honorable, <hi>MARTIN LVMLEY</hi>, in the high Office of his Maiesties Lieutenant, Lord Maior and Chancellor of the famous <hi>City of </hi>London. </p>
        <p>Taking beginning at his Lordships going, and perfecting it selfe after His Returne from receiuing the Oath of Maioralty at Westminster, <hi>on the Morrow after Simon and Iudes </hi>Day, being the 29. of October. 1623. </p>
        <p>By THO. MIDDLETON Gent. </p>
        <figure>
          <head>IN DOMINO CONFIDO </head>
          <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Nicholas Okes</hi>, dwelling in Foster-Lane. 1623. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000196-e190">
        <pb xml:id="ep000196-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000196-002-b"/>
        <head>TO The Honor of him, to whom the Noble Fraternity of Drapers, his Worthy Brothers haue Consecrated their Loues, in costly Triumphs; the Right Honorable, MARTIN LVMLEY, Lord Maior of this Renowned City. </head>
        <l>THy Descent Worthy, (Fortunes Early Grace) </l>
        <l>Sprung of an Antient, and most Generous Race </l>
        <l>Mac'ht with a Vertuous Lady; iustly may </l>
        <l>Challenge the Honor of so Great a Day. </l>
        <closer>
          <signed>
            <hi>Faithfully deuoted to the Worthines of you Both, </hi>The. Middleton. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="solemnity" xml:id="ep000196-e300">
        <pb xml:id="ep000196-003-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000196-003-b"/>
        <head>THE TRIVMPHS OF Integrity, or a Noble Solemnity through the City. </head>
        <p>OF all Solemnities, by which the Happy inauguration of a Subiect is celebrated, I find none that transcends the State and Magnificence of that Pompe prepared to receiue his Maiesties Great Substitute into his Honorable charge, (the City of London,) Dignified by the Title of the Kings Chamber Royall, which that it may now appeare no lesse hightned with Brotherly Affection, Colt, Art, or Inuention, then some other praeceeding Triumphs (by which of late times, the Cities Honor hath beene more faithfully illustrated) this takes it's fit occasion to present it selfe. </p>
        <p>And first to specifie the loue of his Noble Fraternity after his Lordshippes returne from Westminster, hauing receiued some seruice vpon <pb xml:id="ep000196-004-a"/>the water, by a proper and significant Maister-peece of Triumph, called the <hi>Imperiall Canopy</hi>, being the Antient Armes of the Company, an Invention neither old, nor enforst, the same Glorious and Apt Property, accompanied with foure other Triumphall Pegmes, are in their conuenient Stages planted to honor his Lordships progresse through the City; the first for the land, attending his most wished ariuall in Pauls-Church-yard, which beares the inscription of a Mount Royall, on which Mount are plac't certaine Kings and great Commanders, which Antient History produces, that were originally sprung from Shepheards, and humble beginnings; onely the number of Six presented, some with Crownes, some with gilt Laurels, holding in their hands siluer Sheephookes, <hi>viz. Viriat</hi>, a prime Commander of the Portugals, renowned amongst the Historians, especially the Romans, who in battailes of 14 yeares continuance, purchased many great and honorable victories; Arsaces King of the Parthians, who ordained the first Kingdome that euer was amongst them, and in the reuerence of this Kings Name and memory, all others His Successors were called Arsacides after his Name, as the Roman Emperours tooke the Name of Caesar, <pb xml:id="ep000196-004-b"/>for the loue of Great <hi>Caesar Augustus</hi>; Also <hi>Marcus Iulius Lucinus, Bohemiaes Primislaus, </hi>the Emperour Pertinax, the Great Victor Tamburlayne, Conqueror of <hi>Syria, Armenia, Babilon, Mesapotamia, Scythia, Albania, &amp;c. </hi>Many Honorable Worthies more I could produce; By their deserts enobling their meane Originals. But for the better expression of the purpose in Hand, a Speaker lends a voyce to these followings words! </p>
        <lg type="speech">
          <head>The Speech in the Mount Royall. </head>
          <l>THey that with Glory-enflamde hearts; desire </l>
          <l>To see Great Worth deseruingly aspire, </l>
          <l>Let e'm draw neere and fixe a serious Eye, </l>
          <l>On this Tryumphant Mount of Royaltye; </l>
          <l>Here they shall finde faire Vertue and her Name, </l>
          <l>From low-obscure Beginnings raysde to Fame, </l>
          <l>Like Light struck out of Darknes; the meane wombes </l>
          <l>No more Eclipse braue Merit, then rich Toombes </l>
          <l>Make the Soule happy; 'tis the Life, and Dying </l>
          <l>Crownes both with Honors Sacred Satisfying; </l>
          <l>And 'tis the Noblest Splendor vpon Earth, </l>
          <l>For man to adde a Glory to his Birth </l>
          <l>(All his Lifes Race with honor'd Acts commixt) </l>
          <l>Then to be Nobly-borne and there stand fixt; </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000196-015-a"/>
          <l>As if 'twere Competent Vertue for whole Life </l>
          <l>To be Begot a Lord; 'tis vertuous Strife </l>
          <l>That makes the compleate Christian; not high Place, </l>
          <l>As true Submission is the State of Grace, </l>
          <l>" The Path to Blisse, lyes in the humblest Feild, </l>
          <l>" Who euer rise to Heauen that neuer kneeld, </l>
          <l>Although the Roofe hath Supernaturall Height, </l>
          <l>Yet there's no Flesh can thither goe vpright: </l>
          <l>All this is instanc'st onely to commend, </l>
          <l>The low condition whence these Kings descend; </l>
          <l>I spare the <ref target="A07516-e770-b"/>
            <note corresp="A07516-e770-a" place="margin">Dauid. </note>Prince of Prophets in this File, </l>
          <l>And preserue him for a farre Holier Stile, </l>
          <l>Who being King Annoynted, did not scorne </l>
          <l>To be a Shepheard after; these were borne </l>
          <l>Shepheards, and rise to Kings, tooke their ascending </l>
          <l>From the strong hand of Vertue, neuer ending </l>
          <l>Where Shee begins to rayse, vntill shee place </l>
          <l>Her Loue sicke Seruants equall with her Grace; </l>
          <l>And by this Dayes great Honor it appeares </l>
          <l>Sh' as much preuaylde amongst the Reuerend yeares </l>
          <l>Of these Graue Senators, chiefe of the rest </l>
          <l>Her Fauour hath reflected most and best, </l>
          <l>Vpon that Sonne whom wee of Honor call, </l>
          <l>And may 't Successiuely reflect on all. </l>
        </lg>
        <p>From this Mount Royall beautified with the Glory of deseruing Aspirers, descend we to the <pb xml:id="ep000196-005-a"/>Moderne vse of this Antient and Honorable Mistery, and there we shall finde the whole Liuery of this most renowned and famous City, as vpon this Day, and at all Solemne meetings, furnished by it; it clothes the Honorable Senators in their highest and richest Wearings, all Courts of Iustice, Magistrates, and Iudges of the Land. </p>
        <p>By this time his Lordship, and the Worthy Company being gracefully conducted toward the little Conduit in Cheape, there another part of the Triumph waytes his Honors happy approach, being a Chariot Artfully framde, and properly garnished; And on the Conspicuous part thereof is plac'st the Register of all Heroicke Acts and worthy Men, bearing the Title of Sacred Memory, who for the greater Fame of this Honorable Fraternity presents the Neuer-dying Names of many memorable and remarkable Worthies of this Antient Society, such as were the Famous for State and Gouernment, Sir <hi>Henry Fitz-alwin </hi>Knight, who held the Seate of Magistracy in this City twenty foure yeares together, He sits figured vnder the Person of Gouernment: Sir <hi>Iohn Norman</hi>, tho first Lord Maior rowed in Barge to Westminster with siluer Oares at his owne cost and charges; vnder <pb xml:id="ep000196-006-a"/>the person of Honor, the Valiant Sir <hi>Francis Drake</hi>, that rich Ornament to Memory, (who in two yeares and ten moneths space did cast a girdle about the world) vnder the person of Victory, Sir <hi>Simon Eyre</hi>, (who at his owne cost built Leaden Hall, a Granary for the Poore,) vnder the figure of Charity, Sir <hi>Richard Champion</hi>, and Sir <hi>Iohn Milborne</hi>, vnder the person of Munificenee or Bounty, Sir <hi>Richard Hardell</hi>, and Sir <hi>Iohn Poultney</hi>, the one in the seate of Magistracy sixe yeares, the other foure yeares together, vnder the figures of Iustice, and Piety, That Sir Iohn being a Colledge-Founder, in the Parish of St. <hi>Lawrence Poultney</hi>, by Candle-wick streete; <hi>&amp; fic de caeteris</hi>. This Chariot drawne by two pellited Lyons, being the proper Supporters of the Companies Armes, those two vpon the Lyons presenting Power and Honor, the one in a little Streamer or Banneret bearing the Lord Maiors Armes, the other the Companies. </p>
        <lg type="speech">
          <head>The Speech, in the Chariot. </head>
          <l>I Am all Memory, and me thinkes I see </l>
          <l>Into the fardest Time, Act, Quality; </l>
          <l>As cleere as if 'twere now begun agen, </l>
          <l>The Natures, Dispositions, and the Men; </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000196-006-b"/>
          <l>I finde to Godnesse they bent all their powers, </l>
          <l>Which very Name makes blushing Times of ours; </l>
          <l>They heapt vp Vertues, long before they were old, </l>
          <l>This Age fits laughing vpon Heapes of Gold, </l>
          <l>We by great Buildings striue to rayse our Names, </l>
          <l>But they more truely wise built vp their Fames, </l>
          <l>Erected faire Examples, large and hie, </l>
          <l>Patternes for vs to build our Honors by; </l>
          <l>For instance onely Memory relates, </l>
          <l>The Noblest of all City-Magistrates, </l>
          <l>Famous Fitz-alwin, naming him alone, </l>
          <l>I summe vp twenty foure Lord Maiors in one, </l>
          <l>For He by free election and consent </l>
          <l>Fild all those yeares with vertuous Gouerment; </l>
          <l>Custome and Time requiring now but one, </l>
          <l>How ought that yeare to be well dwelt vpon, </l>
          <l>It should appeare an Abstract of that worth, </l>
          <l>Which former Times in many yeares brought forth, </l>
          <l>Through all the life of Man, this is the yeare, </l>
          <l>Which many wish, and neuer can come neare, </l>
          <l>Thinke and giue thanks; to whom this yeare do's come, </l>
          <l>The Greatest Subject's made in Christendome; </l>
          <l>This is the yeare for whom some long preparde, </l>
          <l>And others haue their glorious Fortune sharde, </l>
          <l>But serious in thanksgiuing, 'tis a yeare, </l>
          <l>To which all Vertues like the people heere </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000196-007-a"/>
          <l>Should throng and cleaue together, for the Place </l>
          <l>Is a fit Match for the whole Stocke of Grace; </l>
          <l>And as men gather wealth, 'gainst the Yeare comes, </l>
          <l>So should they gather Goodnesse with their Summes, </l>
          <l>For 'tis not showes, Pompe, nor a House of State </l>
          <l>Curiously deckt, that makes a Magistrate, </l>
          <l>'Tis his faire Noble soule, his Wisedome, Care, </l>
          <l>His vpright Iustnes to the Oath he sware </l>
          <l>Giues him compleate; when such a Man to mee, </l>
          <l>Spreads his Armes open, there my Pallace bee, </l>
          <l>He's both an Honor to the Day so grac'st, </l>
          <l>And to his Brother-hoods loue that sees him plac'st, </l>
          <l>And in his faire Deportment there reuiues, </l>
          <l>The Antient Fame of all his Brothers Liues. </l>
        </lg>
        <p>After this, for the full close of the Fore-noones Triumph, neere St. Lawrence-lane, his Lordship Receiues an Entertainment from an vnparaleld Maister-peece of Art, called the <hi>Cristall Sanctuary</hi>, stilde by the name of the Temple of Integrity, where her Immaculate selfe with all her glorious and Sanctimonious Concomitants sit transparently seene through the Crystall; and more to expresse the Inuention, &amp; the Art of the Engineer, as also for Motion, Variety, and the content of the Spectators, this <hi>Crystall Temple </hi>
          <pb xml:id="ep000196-007-b"/>is made to open in many parts, at fit and conuenient Times, and vppon occasion of the Speech; the Columnes or Pillars of this <hi>Cristall Sanctuary</hi>, are Gold, the Battlements Siluer, the whole Fabrick for the Night Triumph adorned and beautified with many Lights, dispersing their glorious Radiances on all sides thorough the Cristall. </p>
        <lg type="speech">
          <head>The Speech from the Sanctuary. </head>
          <l>HAue you a minde thicke Multitude to see </l>
          <l>A Vertue, neere concernes Magistracy, </l>
          <l>Here on my Temple throw your greedy eyes, </l>
          <l>See me, and learne to know me, then y' are wise; </l>
          <l>Looke, and looke through me, I no fauour craue, </l>
          <l>Nor keepe I hid the Goodnesse you should haue, </l>
          <l>Tis all transparent what I thinke or do, </l>
          <l>And with one looke your Eye may pierce me through, </l>
          <l>There's no disguise, or hypocriticke vaile, </l>
          <l>(Vsde by adulterous Beauty set to sale) </l>
          <l>Spread o're my actions, for respect or feare, </l>
          <l>Onely a Cristall which approues me cleare; </l>
          <l>Would you desire my Name? Integritie, </l>
          <l>One that is ouer what she seemes to be, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000196-008-a"/>
          <l>So manifest, perspicuous, plaine, and cleere </l>
          <l>You may ee'n see my thoughts as they sit here, </l>
          <l>I thinke vpon faire Equity and Truth, </l>
          <l>And there they sit crownde with eternall Youth, </l>
          <l>I fixe my Cogitations vpon Loue, </l>
          <l>Peace, Meeknes, and those thoughts come from aboue, </l>
          <l>The Temple of an vpright Magistrate, </l>
          <l>Is my faire <hi>Sanctuary, Throne</hi>, and State; </l>
          <l>And as I dare Detractions euillest Eye, </l>
          <l>Sore at the sight of Goodnesse, to espie </l>
          <l>Into my wayes and actions, which lie ope </l>
          <l>To euery censure, arm'd with a strong Hope: </l>
          <l>So of Your part ought nothing to be done, </l>
          <l>But what the enuious Eie might looke vpon: </l>
          <l>As Thou art Eminent, so must thy Acts </l>
          <l>Be all Tralucent, and leaue worthy Tracts </l>
          <l>For future times to finde, thy very Brest </l>
          <l>Transparent, like this Place wherein I rest: </l>
          <l>Vaine doubtings; al thy Daies haue bin so cleare </l>
          <l>Neuer came Nobler Hope to fill a yeare. </l>
        </lg>
        <p>At the close of this Speech, this <hi>Cristall Temple </hi>of Integritie with all her caelestiall Concomitants, and the other parts of Triumph take leaue of his Lordship for that time, and rest from <pb xml:id="ep000196-008-b"/>seruice til the great Feast be ended, after which the whole Body of the Triumph attends vpon his Honor, both toward St. Paules, and homeward, his Lordship accompanied with the Graue and Honorable Senators of the City; amongst whom the two worthy Consulls, his Lordships Graue-Assistants for the yeare, the worshipfull and Generous, Mr. <hi>Raph Freeman</hi>, and Mr. <hi>Thomas Moulson</hi>, Sheriffes and Aldermen, ought not to passe of my respect vnremembred; whose Bounty and Noblenesse will prooue best their owne Expressers. </p>
        <p>Neere the entrance of woodstreete, that part of Triumph being planted to which the concluding Speech hath chiefly reference, and the rest, about the Crosse, I thought fit in this place to giue this it's full Illustration; It being an Inuention both glorious and proper to the Company, bearing the name of the thrice <hi>Royall Canopie </hi>of State, being the honored Armes of this Fraternity, the three Imperiall Crownes cast into the Forme and Bignesse of a Triumphall Pageant, with Cloude and Sun-beames, those Beames by Enginous Art made often to mount and spred like a Golden and Glorious Canopy ouer the Deified persons that are plac'st vnder it, <pb xml:id="ep000196-009-a"/>which are eight in number, figuring the eight Beatitudes, To improoue with conceite, <foreign xml:lang="lat">Beati Pacifici</foreign>, being the Kings word or Motto, is set in faire great Letters, neare the vppermost of the three Crownes; and as in all great Edifices or Buildings, the Kings Armes is especially remembred, as a Honor to the Building and Builder in the Frontispice: so is it comely and requisite in these matters of Triumph framed for the Inauguration of his great Substitute, the Lord Maior of London, that some remembrance of Honour should reflect vpon his Maiesty, by whose peacefull Gouernment vnder Heauen we enjoy the Solemnity! </p>
        <lg type="speech">
          <head>The speech, hauing Reference to this Imperiall Canopy, being the Drapers Armes. </head>
          <l>THe Blessednesse, Peace, Honor, and Renowne, </l>
          <l>This Kingdome do's enioy vnder the Crowne, </l>
          <l>Worne by that Royall Peace-maker, our King, </l>
          <l>(So oft preserude from Dangers menacing) </l>
          <l>Makes this Armes, (glorious in it selfe) outgoe </l>
          <l>All that Antiquity could euer showe, </l>
          <l>And thy Fraternity hath striude t' appeare </l>
          <l>In all their course, worthy the Armes they beare, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000196-009-b"/>
          <l>Thrice haue They Crown'd their Goodnes this one Day </l>
          <l>With Loue, with Care, with Cost; by which they may </l>
          <l>By their Deserts most iustly these Armes claime, </l>
          <l>Got once by Worth, now Trebly held by Fame: </l>
          <l>Shall I bring Honor to a larger Feild, </l>
          <l>And show what Royall Businesse these Armes yeild? </l>
          <l>First the three Crownes affords a Diuine scope, </l>
          <l>Set for the Graces, <hi>Charity, Faith</hi>, and Hope; </l>
          <l>Which Three the onely safe Combiners be, </l>
          <l>Of Kingdomes, Crownes, and euery Company; </l>
          <l>Likewise with iust propriety they may stand </l>
          <l>For those three Kingdomes swaide by the meek Hand </l>
          <l>Of Blest <hi>Iames; England, Scotland, Ireland, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>The Cloud that swells beneath e'm, may imply </l>
          <l>Some Enuious Mist cast forth by Heresie, </l>
          <l>Which through his happy Raigne, and Heauens blest will; </l>
          <l>The sun-beames of the Gospell strikes through still; </l>
          <l>More to assure it to Succeeding Men, </l>
          <l>We haue the Crowne of Brittaines Hope agen, </l>
          <l>(Illustrious Charles our Prince,) which all will say, </l>
          <l>Addes the chiefe Ioy and Honor to this Day: </l>
          <l>And as three Crownes, three Fruites of Brotherhood </l>
          <l>By which all Loues Worth may be vnderstood, </l>
          <l>So threefold Honor makes the Royall Sute </l>
          <l>In the King, Prince, and the Kings Substitute: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000196-010-a"/>
          <l>By th' eight Beatitudes, Yee vnderstand </l>
          <l>The Fulnesse of all Blessings to this Land, </l>
          <l>More chiefly to this City, whose safe Peace </l>
          <l>Good Angels guard, and Goodmens prayers encrease: </l>
          <l>May all succeeding-Honor'd Brothers bee, </l>
          <l>With as much Loue brought Home, as Thine brings Thee. </l>
        </lg>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="appreciation" xml:id="ep000196-e2850">
        <p>FOr all the Proper Adornments of Arte and Workmanship in so short a Time, so gracefully setting forth the Bodie of so Magnificent a Triumph, the prayse comes as a iust due to the Exquisit Deseruings of Mr. <hi>Garret Crismas</hi>, whose faithfull performances still take the vpper hand of his promises. </p>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
      <div type="supplied_by_editor">
        <head>Notes, typically marginal, from the original text</head>
        <div corresp="A07516-e300" xml:id="ep000196-e300-n">
          <head>Notes for div A07516-e300</head>
        </div>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
