<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000198" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Triumphs of Truth; The Entertainment on Michaelmas Day 1613</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Thomas</forename>
            <surname>Middleton</surname>
          </persName>
          <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q344865</idno>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A07518.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
        </bibl>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The triumphs of truth. A solemnity vnparalleled for cost, art, and magnificence, at the confirmation and establishment of that worthy and true nobly-minded gentleman, Sir Thomas Middleton, knight, in the honorable office of his Maiesties lieuetenant, the lord maior of the thrice famous citty of London. Taking beginning at his Lord-ships going, and proceeding after his returne from receiuing the oath of maioralty at Westminster, on the morrow next after Simon and Iudes day, October 29. 1613. All the showes, pageants, chariots; morning, noone, and night-triumphes. Directed, written, and redeem'd into forme, from the ignorance of some former times, and their common writer, by Thomas Middleton.</title>
            <author>Middleton, Thomas, d. 1627.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>16 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2005 December (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99855091</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 17903.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, 311.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">20563</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07518</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2240870498</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The triumphs of truth. A solemnity vnparalleled for cost, art, and magnificence, at the confirmation and establishment of that worthy and true nobly-minded gentleman, Sir Thomas Middleton, knight, in the honorable office of his Maiesties lieuetenant, the lord maior of the thrice famous citty of London. Taking beginning at his Lord-ships going, and proceeding after his returne from receiuing the oath of maioralty at Westminster, on the morrow next after Simon and Iudes day, October 29. 1613. All the showes, pageants, chariots; morning, noone, and night-triumphes. Directed, written, and redeem'd into forme, from the ignorance of some former times, and their common writer, by Thomas Middleton.</title>
            <title type="alt">Triumphes of truth.</title>
            <title type="alt">Song with the note.</title>
            <author>Middleton, Thomas, d. 1627.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[32] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes dwelling at the signe of the Hand, neere Holbourne-Bridge,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date type="publication_date">1613.</date>
            <date type="creation_date">1613</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Running title reads: The triumphes of truth.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Appended, with caption title: The song with the note.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-D4.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <person xml:id="ep000198-missing">
            <persName>Missing</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000198-london">
            <persName>London</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000198-angel">
            <persName>Angel</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000198-zeal">
            <persName>Zeal</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000198-error">
            <persName>Error</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000198-truth">
            <persName>Truth</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000198-king">
            <persName>King</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000198-queen">
            <persName>Queen</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000198-perfect_love">
            <persName>Perfect Love</persName>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1613">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000198-e100030">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000198-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000198-001-b"/>
        <p>The Triumphs of Truth. </p>
        <p>A Solemnity vnparalleld for Cost, Art, and Magnificence, at the Confirmation and Establishment of that Worthy and true Nobly. Minded Gentleman, Sir THOMAS MIDDLETON, Knight, in the Honorable Office of his Maiesties Lieuetenant, the Lord Maior of the thrice Famous Citty of LONDON. </p>
        <p>Taking Beginning 〈◊〉 his Lord-ships going and proceeding 〈…〉 e from receiuing the Oath of Ma 〈…〉 Westminster, on the Morrow of 〈…〉 and Iudes day, 〈◊〉 19 1613. </p>
        <p>All the Showes, Pa Pageants, Chariots; Morning, Noone, and Night-Triumphes. </p>
        <p>Directed, written, underdeem'd into Forme from the Ignorance of some former times and their Common Writer. </p>
        <p>By Thomas Middleton. </p>
        <p>LONDON. Printed by N 〈…〉 dwelling at the signe of the Hand, o 〈…〉 Holborne-Bridge. 1613. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000198-e100110">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000198-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000198-002-b"/>
        <head>TO THE GREAT EXPectation of Vertue and Goodnesse, and most worthy of all those Costs and Honors, which the Noble Fellowship and Society and Grocers, and generall Loue of the whole City, in full heap'd bounties bestow vpon him, the truly. Generous and Iuditious, Sir Thomas Middleton, Knight, Lord Maior of the Honorable Citty of London. </head>
        <p>AS often as we shall fixe our thoughts vpon the Almighty Prouidence, soften they returne to our capacities laden with Admiration, either from the Diuine workes of his Mercy, or those incomprehensible of his Iustice: but here to instance onely his Omnipotent Mercy, it being the Health and Preseruation of all his workes: and first not onely in raising, but also in preseruing your L. from many great and insident dangers, especially <pb xml:id="ep000198-003-a"/>in forraine Countries in the time of your Youth and Trauels: and now with Safety, Loue and Triumph, to establish You in this yeares Honor: crowning the Perfection of your Daies, &amp; the Grauity of your Life, with Power, Respect &amp; Reuerence. Next, in that my selfe (though vnworthy) being of one Name with your Lordship, notwithstanding all Oppositions of Malice, Ignorance and Enuy, should thus happily liue, protected by part of that Mercy (as if one Fate did prosperously cleaue to one Name) now to do Seruice to your Fame and Worthinesse, and my Pen, onely to be employd in these Bounteous and Honorable Tryumphs, being but shadowes to those Eternall Glories that stand ready for Deseruers, to which I commend the Deserts of your Iustice, remaining euer </p>
        <closer>
          <signed>To your Lordship, in the best of my obseruance, Thomas Middleton. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="triumph" xml:id="ep000198-e100160">
        <pb xml:id="ep000198-003-b"/>
        <head>THE TRYVMPHS Of Truth. </head>
        <p>SEarch all Chronicles, Histories, Records, in what language or letter soeuer; let the inquisitiue man waste the deere Treasures of his Time and Eye-sight, he shall conclude his life only in this certainty, that there is no subiect vpon earth receiued into the place of his gouernement with the like State &amp; Magnificence as is the Lord Maior of the Citty of London. This being then infallible (like the Mistresse of our Triumphs) and not to be denied of any, how carefull ought those Gentlemen to be, to whose discretion and Iudgement the weight and charge of such a businesse is entirely referred and committed by the whole Society, to haue all things correspondent to that Generous and Noble freenesse of cost and liberality, the streames of Art, to aequall those of Bounty; a Knowledge that may take the true height of such an Honorable Solemnity; the miserable want of both which in the impudent common Writer, hath often forc'd from me much pitty and sorrow; and it would heartily grieue any vnderstanding spirit to behold many times so glorious a fire in <pb xml:id="ep000198-004-a"/>bounty and goodnesse offering to match in selfe with freezing Art, sitting in darknesse, with the candle out, looking like the picture of Blacke Monday. </p>
        <p>But to speake truth, which many beside my selfe can affirme vpon knowledge, a care that hath beene seldome equal'd, and not easily imitated, hath been faithfully showne in the whole course of this businesse, both by the Wardens and Committies, men of much vnderstanding, industry, and carefulnesse, little weighing the greatnesse of expence, so the cost might purchase perfection, so feruent hath beene their desire to excell in that (which is a learned and vertuous Ambition) and so vnfainedly pure the loues and affections of the whole Company to his Lordship; If any shall imagine that I set fairer colours vpon their Deserts, then they vpon themselues, let them but reade and conceiue, and their owne vnderstandings will light them to the acknowledgement of their errors. First, they may here behold loue and bounty opening with the morning, earlier then some of former yeares, ready at the first appearing of his Lordship, to giue his eare a taste of the dayes succeeding glory, and thus the forme of it presents it selfe. </p>
        <p>At Soper-lane end a Senate-house erected, vpon which Musitians sit playing; and more a quicken time, a sweet voyce married to these words: </p>
        <sp who="#ep000198-missing" xml:id="ep000198-e100200">
          <lg type="song">
            <head>THE SONG. </head>
            <l>Mother of many honorable Sounes, </l>
            <l>Thinke not the Glasse too slowly runnes </l>
            <l>That in Times hand is set, </l>
            <l>Because thy worthy Sonne appeares not yet: </l>
            <l>Lady be pleas'd, the hower growes on, </l>
            <l>Thy ioy will be compleate anon; </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000198-004-b"/>
            <l>Thou shalt behold </l>
            <l>The man enrold </l>
            <l>In Honours bookes, whom Vertue raises, </l>
            <l>Loue-circled round, </l>
            <l>His triumphs crownd </l>
            <l>With all good wishes, prayers, and praises. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <p>After this sweet aire hath liberally spent it selfe, at the first appearing of the Lord Maior from Guild-hall in the morning, a Trumpet plac'd vpon that Scaffold, sounds forth his welcome; then after a straine or two of Musicke, a Graue Foeminine Shape presents it selfe, from behinde a silke curtaine, representing London, attired like a reuerend Mother, a long white haire naturally flowing on either side of her: on her head a modell of Steeples and Turrets, her habite Crimson silke, neere to the Honourable garment of the Citty: her left hand holding a Key of gold, who after a comely grace, equally mixt with Comfort and Reuerence, sends from her lips this Motherly salutation. </p>
        <sp who="#ep000198-london" xml:id="ep000198-e100350">
          <speaker>The speech of London. </speaker>
          <l>Honour and Ioy salute thee, I am raisd </l>
          <l>In comfort and in loue to see thee, glad </l>
          <l>And happy in thy blessings, nor esteeme </l>
          <l>My words the lesse, cause I a woman speake, </l>
          <l>A womans counsell is not alwayes weake. </l>
          <l>I am thy Mother, at that name I know </l>
          <l>Thy heart do's reuerence to me, as becomes </l>
          <l>A Sonne of Honour, in whose soule burnes cleere </l>
          <l>The sacred lights of diuine feare and knowledge, </l>
          <l>I know, that at this instant, all the workes </l>
          <l>Of Motherly loue in me, showne to thy Youth </l>
          <l>When it was soft and helplesse, are sum'd vp </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000198-005-a"/>
          <l>In thy most gratefull minde, thou well remembrest </l>
          <l>All my deere paines and care, with what affection </l>
          <l>I cherish thee in my bosome, watchfull still </l>
          <l>Ouer thy wayes, </l>
          <l>Set wholesome and Religious Lawes before </l>
          <l>The foot-steps of thy youth, show'd Thee the way </l>
          <l>That lead thee to the Glory of this Day. </l>
          <l>To which (with teares of the most fruitfull ioy </l>
          <l>that euer Mother shed) I welcome Thee. </l>
          <l>Oh I could be content to take my part </l>
          <l>Out of Felicity onely in weeping, </l>
          <l>Thy Presence and this Day is so deere to me. </l>
          <l>Looke on my age (my Honorable Sonne) </l>
          <l>And then begin to thinke vpon thy Office: </l>
          <l>See how on each side of mee hang the cares </l>
          <l>Which I bestowd on Thee, in siluer haires. </l>
          <l>And now the Faith, the Loue, the zealous Fires </l>
          <l>With which I cheer'd thy Youth, my Age requires, </l>
          <l>The duty of a Mother I haue showne, </l>
          <l>Through all the Rites of pure affection, </l>
          <l>In Care, in Gouernment, in Wealth, in Honour, </l>
          <l>Brought Thee to what thou art, throw'st all from mee, </l>
          <l>Then what thou shouldst be I expect from Thee. </l>
          <l>Now to Thy Charge, Thy Gouernment, Thy Cares, </l>
          <l>Thy Mother in her age submits her yeares. </l>
          <l>And though (to my abundant griefe I speake it, </l>
          <l>Which now ore-flowes my ioy) some Sonnes I haue </l>
          <l>Thanklesse, vnkind, and disobedient, </l>
          <l>Rewarding all my Bounties with Neglect, </l>
          <l>And will of purpose wilfully retire </l>
          <l>Themselues, from doing grace and seruice to me, </l>
          <l>When they haue got all they can, or hope for, from me, </l>
          <l>The thankfulnesse in which Thy Life doth moue, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000198-005-b"/>
          <l>Did euer promise fairer fruits of Loue, </l>
          <l>And now they show themselues, yet they haue all </l>
          <l>My blessing with them, so the world shall see </l>
          <l>'Tis their vnkindnesse, no defect in me; </l>
          <l>But go Thou forward (my thrice Honor'd Sonne) </l>
          <l>In waies of goodnesse, Glory is best wonne </l>
          <l>When Merit brings it home, disdaine all Titles </l>
          <l>Purchas'd with Coine, of Honor take Thou hold, </l>
          <l>By thy Desert let others buy't with Gold; </l>
          <l>Fixe thy most serious Thought vpon the Weight </l>
          <l>Thou goest to vndergo, 'tis the iust Gouernment </l>
          <l>Of this Fam'd Citty, (Mee) whom Nations call </l>
          <l>Their brightest Eye, then with great care &amp; feare </l>
          <l>Ought I to be ore-seene to be kept cleare. </l>
          <l>Spots in deformed Faces are scarce Noted, </l>
          <l>Faire cheekes are stain'd if ner'e so little blotted. </l>
          <l>See'st thou this Key of Gold? it showes thy charge, </l>
          <l>This place is the Kings Chamber, all pollution, </l>
          <l>Sinne and Vncleannesse must be lock't out here, </l>
          <l>And be kept sweet, with Sanctity, Faith &amp; Feare, </l>
          <l>I see Grace take effect, Heauens Ioy vpon her, </l>
          <l>'Tis rare, when Vertue opes the Gate to Honor, </l>
          <l>My blessing be vpon thee, Sonne, and Lord, </l>
          <l>And on my Sonnes all, that obey my word. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>Then making her Honour, as before, the Waites of the Citty there in seruice, his Lordship and the Worthy Company, are lead forward toward the water side, where you shall finde the Riuer deck't in the richest glory to receiue him; vpon whose Christall Bosome stands fiue Islands art-fully garnished with all manner of Indian Fruite-Trees, Drugges, Spiceries; and the like, the middle Island with a faire Castle especially beautified. </p>
        <pb xml:id="ep000198-006-a"/>
        <p>But making haste to returne to the Citty againe, where Triumph waites in more Splendor and Magnificence, the first then that attends to receiue his Lordship off the water at Bainards Castle, is Truths Angell on Horse-backe, his Raiment of white Silke powdred with Starres of Gold: on his head a Crowne of Gold, a Trumpeter before him on Horse-backe, and Zeale the Champion of Truth, in a Garment of Flame-coloured Silke, with a bright haire on his head, from which shoot Fire-beames, following close after him, mounted alike, his Right hand holding a flaming Scourge, intimating thereby that as hee is the manifester of Truth, he is likewise the chastizer of Ignorance and Error. </p>
        <sp who="#ep000198-angel" xml:id="ep000198-e101070">
          <speaker>The Salutation of the Angell. </speaker>
          <l>I haue within mine Eye my blessed Charge, </l>
          <l>Haile Friend of Truth, Safety and Iay attnds thee; </l>
          <l>I am Truths Angell, by my Mistresse sent </l>
          <l>To guard and guid thee, when thou took'st thy Oath </l>
          <l>I stood on thy Right hand, though to thy eye </l>
          <l>In visible forme I did not then appeare, </l>
          <l>Aske but thy Soule t'will tell thee I stood neere; </l>
          <l>And 'twas a Time to take care of Thee then </l>
          <l>At such a Marriage before Heauen and Men, </l>
          <l>(Thy Faith being wed to Honor) close behinde thee </l>
          <l>Stood Errors Minister, that still sought to blinde thee, </l>
          <l>And wrap his subtill mists about thy Oath, </l>
          <l>To hide it from the nakednesse of Troth, </l>
          <l>Which is Truths purest glory, but my light </l>
          <l>Still as it shone, Expeld her blackest spite; </l>
          <l>His Mists fled by, yet all I could deuise, </l>
          <l>Could hardly keepe them from some Peoples eyes, </l>
          <l>But thine they flew from, thy Care's but begun </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000198-006-b"/>
          <l>Wake on, the Victory is not halfe yet wun, </l>
          <l>Thou wilt be still assaulted, thou shalt meete </l>
          <l>With many dangers, that in voyce seeme sweet, </l>
          <l>And waies most pleasant to a worldlings eye, </l>
          <l>My Mistresse ha's but One, but that leads hye </l>
          <l>To yo'n triumphant Citty follow mee, </l>
          <l>Keepe thou to Truth, Eternitie keepes to thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000198-zeal" xml:id="ep000198-e101330">
          <speaker>ZEALE. </speaker>
          <l>On boldly Man of Honor, thou shalt win, </l>
          <l>I am Truths Champion, Zeale, the Scourge of Sin. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>The Trumpet then sounding, the Angell and Zeale ranke themselues iust before his Lordship, &amp; conduct him to Pauls-chaine, where in the South-yard Error in a Chariot with his infernall Ministers attends to assault him, his Garment of Ash-colour Silke, his head rowld in a cloud, ouer which stands, an Owle, a Moale on one shoulder, a Bat on the other, all Symboles of blinde Ignorance and Darknesse, Mists hanging at his Eyes: close before him rides Enuy his Champion, eating of a humane heart, mounted on a Rhenoceros, attired in Red Silke, sutable to the bloudinesse of her manners her left Pap bare, where a Snake fastens, her Armes halfe Naked, holding in her right hand a Dart tincted in bloud. </p>
        <sp who="#ep000198-error" xml:id="ep000198-e101370">
          <speaker>The greeting of Error. </speaker>
          <l>Art come? O Welcome my triumphant Lord, </l>
          <l>My Glories Sweet-heart! how many millions </l>
          <l>Of happy wishes hath my loue told out </l>
          <l>For this desired minute, I was dead </l>
          <l>Till I enioyd the Presence, I saw nothing, </l>
          <l>A Blindnesse thicker then Idolatry, </l>
          <l>Cloue to my Eye-bals, now I am all of Light, </l>
          <l>Of Fire, of Ioy, Pleasure runs nimbly through mee, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000198-007-a"/>
          <l>Lets ioyne together both in State and Triumph, </l>
          <l>And down with beggarly and friendlesse Vertue, </l>
          <l>That hath so long impouerish't this faire Citty, </l>
          <l>My Beasts shall trample on her naked breast, </l>
          <l>Vnder my Chariot-wheeles her Bones lye prest, </l>
          <l>She ner'e shall rise againe, great Power this day, </l>
          <l>Is giuen into thy hand, make vse on't Lord, </l>
          <l>And let thy Will and Appetite sway the Sword, </l>
          <l>Downe with them all now, whom thy heart enuies, </l>
          <l>Let not thy Conscience come into thine Eyes </l>
          <l>This twelue-month, if thou lou'st reuenge or gaine, </l>
          <l>Ile teach thee to cast mists, to blinde the plaine </l>
          <l>And simple eye of Man, he shall not know't, </l>
          <l>Nor see thy Wrath when 'tis vpon his throte, </l>
          <l>All shall be carried with such Art and Wit, </l>
          <l>That what thy Lust Acts, shal bee counted fit, </l>
          <l>Then for Attendants that may best obserue thee, </l>
          <l>Il'e picke out Seriants of my band to serue thee, </l>
          <l>Heres Gluttony and Sloth, two pretious Slaues, </l>
          <l>Wil tell thee more then a whole heard of Knaues, </l>
          <l>The worth of euery Office to a Haire, </l>
          <l>And who bids most, and bow the Markets are, </l>
          <l>Let them alone to smell, and for a need, </l>
          <l>They'l bring thee in Bribes for Measure and light Bread, </l>
          <l>Keepe thy eye winking, and thy hand wide ope, </l>
          <l>Then thou shalt know what Wealth is, and the scope </l>
          <l>Of rich Authority, Ho tis sweete and deere, </l>
          <l>Make vse of Time then, thou'st but one poore Yeare, </l>
          <l>And that will quickly slide, then be not nice, </l>
          <l>Both Power and Profite cleaues to my Aduice, </l>
          <l>And what's he lockes his Eare from those sweet Charmes, </l>
          <l>Or runs not to meet Gaine with wide-stretch't Armes, </l>
          <l>There is a poore thin thred-bare thing, cal'd Truth, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000198-007-b"/>
          <l>I giue thee warning of her, if shee speake </l>
          <l>Stop both thine eares close, most Professions breake </l>
          <l>That euer delt with her, an Vnlucky thing, </l>
          <l>Shee's almost sworne to nothing, I can bring </l>
          <l>A thousand of our Parish, besides Queanes, </l>
          <l>That nere knew what Truth meant, nor euer meanes. </l>
          <l>Some I could cull out here, e'en in this Throng, </l>
          <l>If I would show my Children, and how strong </l>
          <l>I were in faction; 'lasse poore simple Stray, </l>
          <l>Shee's all her life time finding out one way: </l>
          <l>Shee 'as but one foolish way, streight on, right forward, </l>
          <l>And yet she makes a toyle on't, and goes on </l>
          <l>With Care and Feare forfooth, when I can run </l>
          <l>Ouer a hundred with delight and pleasure, </l>
          <l>Backe-waies, and by-waies, and fetch in my Treasure </l>
          <l>After the wishes of my heart, by shifts, </l>
          <l>Deceits, and slightes, and Ile giue thee those giftes; </l>
          <l>Ile show thee all my corners yet vntold, </l>
          <l>The very nookes where Beldams hide their gold, </l>
          <l>In hollow wals and chimneies, where the Sun </l>
          <l>Neuer yet shone, nor Truth came euer neere, </l>
          <l>This of thy Life Ile make the golden yeare: Follow me then. </l>
          <l>Enuy. Learne now to scorne thy Inferiours, those must loue thee, </l>
          <l>And wish to eate their Hearts, that sit aboue thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>Zeale stird vp with Diuine Indignation, at the Impudence of these Hel-hounds, both forces their retirement, and makes way for the Chariot wherein Truth his Mistresse sits, in a close garment of white Sattin, which makes her appeare thin and naked, figuring thereby her simplicity and neerenesse of heart to those that embrace her; a roabe of white silke cast ouer it, fil'd with the eies of Eagles, shewing her deep <pb xml:id="ep000198-008-a"/>insight, and height of wisedome, ouer her thrice sanctified head a milke-white Doue, and on each shoulder one, the sacred Emblemes of Purity, Meekenesse, and Innocency, vnder her Feete, Serpents, in that she treads downe all Subtelty and Fraud, her Fore-head empal'd with a Diadem of Stars, the Witnesse of her Eternall descent; on her Breast a pure round Cristall, showing the brightnesse of her thoughts and actions; a Sun in her Right-hand, then which, nothing is truer, a fan fild all with Starres in her left, with which she parts Darkenesse, and strikes away the vapours of Ignorance; if you hearken to Zeale her Champion after his holy anger is past against Error, and his crue, hee will giue it you in better tearmes, or at least more smoothly and pleasingly. </p>
        <sp who="#ep000198-zeal" xml:id="ep000198-e102040">
          <speaker>The speech of Zeale. </speaker>
          <l>Bold Furies, backe, or with this scourge of Fire </l>
          <l>Whence sparkles out Religious chast-desire </l>
          <l>Ile whip you downe to darkenesse; this a place </l>
          <l>Worthy my Mistresse, her Aeternall Grace </l>
          <l>Be the full obiect to feast all these eies </l>
          <l>But Thine the first, hee that feeds here is wise; </l>
          <l>Nor by the naked plainenesse of her weeds </l>
          <l>Iudge thou her worth, no burnisht glosse Truth needs; </l>
          <l>That Crowne of Starres showes her descent from heauen; </l>
          <l>That Roabe of white fild all with Eagles eies, </l>
          <l>Her piercing sight through hidden mysteries; </l>
          <l>Those milke-white Doues her spotlesse Innocence; </l>
          <l>Those Serpents at her feete her victory showes </l>
          <l>Ouer deceite and guile, her rankest foes, </l>
          <l>And by that Cristall Mirrour at her Brest, </l>
          <l>The cleerenesse of her Conscience is exprest; </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000198-008-b"/>
          <l>And showing that her deeds all darkenesse shun, </l>
          <l>Her Right-hand holds Truths Symbole, the bright Sunne; </l>
          <l>A Fan of Starres shee in the other twists, </l>
          <l>With which shee chaceth away Errors mists: </l>
          <l>And now shee makes to thee, her so euen Grace, </l>
          <l>For to her Rich and Poore looke with one Face. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000198-truth" xml:id="ep000198-e102270">
          <speaker>The Words of Truth. </speaker>
          <l>Man raysd by Faith and Loue, vpon whose Head </l>
          <l>Honour sits fresh, let not thy Heart be led </l>
          <l>In ignorant waies of insolence and pride </l>
          <l>From Her, that to this day hath bene thy guide; </l>
          <l>I neuer showed thee yet more Paths then one, </l>
          <l>And thou hast found sufficient That alone </l>
          <l>To bring Thee hether, then go forward still, </l>
          <l>And hauing most power, first subiect thy Will, </l>
          <l>Giue the first Fruits of Iustice to thy Selfe, </l>
          <l>Then dost thou wisely Gouerne, though that Elfe </l>
          <l>Of Sin and Darkenesse still opposing mee, </l>
          <l>Counsels thy Appetite to Master Thee. </l>
          <l>But call to minde what brought thee to this Day, </l>
          <l>Was Falshood, Cruelty, or Reuenge the way? </l>
          <l>Thy lust or pleasures? peoples curse or hate? </l>
          <l>These were no waies could raise Thee to this State </l>
          <l>The ignorant must acknowledge, if then from Mee, </l>
          <l>Which no Ill dare deny, or Sin controule, </l>
          <l>Forsake mee not, that can aduance thy soule: </l>
          <l>I see a blessed yeelding in thy Eye, </l>
          <l>Thou'rt mine, leade on, thy Name shall neuer dye. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>These words ended, they all set forward, this Chariot of Truth and her coelestiall hand-maids the Graces &amp; Vertues, taking place next before his Lord ship, Zeale and the Angell before that, the Chariot of Error following <pb xml:id="ep000198-009-a"/>as neere as it can get, all passing on, till they come into Pauls Church-yard, where stand ready the fiue Ilands, those dumbe Glories that I spake of before vpon the water, vpon the heighth of these fiue Ilands sit fiue persons representing the fiue Sences, Visus, Auditus, Tactus, Gustus, Olfactus, (or) Seeing, Hearing, Touching, Tasting, Smelling; at their feete their proper Emblemes, Aquila, Ceruus, Araneus, Simia, Canis, an Eagle, a Hart, a Spider, an Ape, a Dogge. </p>
        <p>No sooner can your eyes take leaue of these, but they may suddenly espy a strange Ship making toward, and that which may raise greater astonishment, it hauing neither Saylor nor Pilot, onely vpon a white silke streamer these two words set in letters of Gold, Veritate Gubernor, I am Steer'd by Truth; the Persons that are contained within this little Vessell are onely foure; a King of the Moores, his Queene, and two Attendants of their owne colour, the rest of their followers, people the Castle that stands in the middle Iland, of which company two or three on the top appeares to sight, this King seeming much astonied at the many eies of such a multitude, vtters his thoughts in these words. </p>
        <sp who="#ep000198-king" xml:id="ep000198-e102510">
          <speaker>The Speech of that King. </speaker>
          <l>I see amazement set vpon the faces </l>
          <l>Of these white people, wondrings, and strange gazes, </l>
          <l>Is it at mee? do's my Complexion draw </l>
          <l>So many Christian Eyes, that neuer saw </l>
          <l>A King so blacke before? no, now I see </l>
          <l>Their entire obiect, the're all meant to thee </l>
          <l>(Graue Citty Gouernour) my Queene and I </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000198-009-b"/>
          <l>Well honor'd with the Glances that by, </l>
          <l>I must confesse many wilde thoughts may rise, </l>
          <l>Opinions, Common murmurs, and fixt Eyes </l>
          <l>At my so strange arriuall, in a Land </l>
          <l>Where true Religion and her Temple stand: </l>
          <l>I being a Moor, ethen in Opinions lightnesse </l>
          <l>As far from Sanctity as my Face from whitenesse; </l>
          <l>But I forgiue the Iudgings of th'Vnwise, </l>
          <l>Whose Censures euer quicken in their Eyes, </l>
          <l>Onely begot of outward forme and show, </l>
          <l>And I thinke meete to let such Censurers Know, </l>
          <l>How euer Darkenesse dwels vpon my Face, </l>
          <l>Truth in my soule sets vp the Light of Grace; </l>
          <l>And though in daies of Error I did runne </l>
          <l>To giue all Adoration to the Sunne, </l>
          <l>The Moone &amp; Stars; nay Creatures base and poore, </l>
          <l>Now onely their Creator I adore: </l>
          <l>My Queene and People all, at one time wun, </l>
          <l>By the Religious Conuersation </l>
          <l>Of English Merchants, Factors, Trauailers, </l>
          <l>Whose Truth did with our Spirits hold Commerse </l>
          <l>As their affaires with vs, following their path </l>
          <l>Wee all were brought to the true Christian Faith: </l>
          <l>Such benefite in good Example dwels, </l>
          <l>It oft hath power to conuert Infidels; </l>
          <l>Nor could our Desires rest, till wee were led </l>
          <l>Vnto this place, where those good Spirits were bred; </l>
          <l>And see how we arriu'd, in Blessed Time, </l>
          <l>To do that Mistresse Seruice, in the Prime </l>
          <l>Of these her Spotlesse Triumphs, and t'attend </l>
          <l>That Honorable Man, her Late sworne Frend. </l>
          <l>If any wonder at the safe Arriue </l>
          <l>Of this small Vessell, which all Wethers driue </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000198-010-a"/>
          <l>According to their Rages, where appeares </l>
          <l>Nor Marriner nor Pylot (arm'd 'gainst feares) </l>
          <l>Know this came hether from mans guidance free, </l>
          <l>Onely by Truth Steer'd; as our Soules must bee; </l>
          <l>And see where one of her faire Temples stands, </l>
          <l>Do Reuerence, Moores, bow low, and Kisse your hands, </l>
          <l>Behold our Queene. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000198-queen" xml:id="ep000198-e102990">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>Her Goodnesses are such </l>
          <l>Wee cannot Honour Her, and Her House too much. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>All in the Shippe and those in the Castle bowing their bodies to the Temple of Saint Paul, but Error smiling betwixt Scorne and Anger to see such a deuout humility take hold of that complexion, breakes into these, </p>
        <sp who="#ep000198-error" xml:id="ep000198-e103030">
          <speaker>Error. </speaker>
          <l>What, haue my Sweete-fac'st Deuils forsooke me too, </l>
          <l>Nay, then my charmes will haue enough to doo? </l>
        </sp>
        <p>But Time, sitting by the Frame of Truth his Daughters Chariot, attir'd agree-able to his Condition, with his Hower-glasse, Wings, and Sithe, Knowing best himselfe when it is fittest to speake, goes forward in this manner: </p>
        <sp who="#ep000198-missing" xml:id="ep000198-e103070">
          <l>This Time hath brought t'effect, for on thy Day </l>
          <l>Nothing but Truth and Vertue shall display: </l>
          <l>Their Virgin Ensignes, Infidelity, </l>
          <l>Barbarisme and Guile shall in deepe Darkenesse lye. </l>
          <l>O I could euer stand still thus, and gaze, </l>
          <l>Neuer turne Glasse agen; wish no more daies </l>
          <l>So this might euer last, pitty the Light </l>
          <l>Of this rich Glory must be casde in Night; </l>
          <l>But Time must on, I go, 'tis so decreed, </l>
          <l>To blesse my Daughter Truth, and all her seed </l>
          <l>With Ioyes Immortal, Triumphs neuer ending: </l>
          <l>And as her Hand lifts mee, to thy Ascending </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000198-010-b"/>
          <l>May it be alwaies ready (worthy Sonne) </l>
          <l>To hasten which, my Howers shall quickly run, </l>
          <l>Seest thou you place, <ref target="A07518-e103230-b"/>
            <note anchored="true" corresp="A07518-e103230-a" place="margin">Saint Pauls Crosse. </note>thether Ile weekely bring thee, </l>
          <l>Where Truths coelestiall Harmony Thou shalt heare, </l>
          <l>To which I charge Thee bend a serious Eare: </l>
          <l>Leade on, Times swift Attendants. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>Then the fiue Ilands passe along into Cheape-side, the Ship next after them; the Chariot of Truth still before his Lord-ship, and that of Prror still chac'st before it, where their Eies meete with another more subtile Obiect, planting it selfe close by the little Conduite, which may beare this Character, the True Forme and Fashion of a Mount Triumphant, but the Beauty and Glory thereof ouer-spred with a thicke Sulphurous Darkenesse, it being a Fog or Mist raisde from Error, enuiously to blemish that Place which beares the Title of Londons Triumphant Mount (the chiefe Grace and Luster of the whole Triumph) at the foure corners sit foure Monsters Errors Disciples, on whom hangs part of the Mist for their cloathing, holding in their hands little thicke Clubbes, coloured like their Garments; the Names of these foure Monsters, Barbarisme, Ignorance, Impudence, Falshood, who at the neere approaching of Truths Chariot, are seene a little to tremble, whilst her Deity giues life to these words. </p>
        <sp who="#ep000198-truth" xml:id="ep000198-e103280">
          <speaker>Truth. </speaker>
          <l>What's here? the Mist of Error? dare his Spight </l>
          <l>Staine this Triumphant Mount? where our delight </l>
          <l>Hath bene Diuinely fixt so many Ages, </l>
          <l>Dare darkenesse now breathe forth her Insolent Rages, </l>
          <l>And hang in poysnous Vapours o're the Place </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000198-011-a"/>
          <l>From whence wee receiu'd Loue and return'd Grace? </l>
          <l>I see if Truth a while but turne her Eies, </l>
          <l>Thicke are the Mists that o're faire Citties rise: </l>
          <l>Wee did expect to receiue welcome here, </l>
          <l>From no deform'd Shapes but Diuine and Cleere, </l>
          <l>In steed of Monsters that this place attends; </l>
          <l>To meete with Goodnesse and her Glorious Frends, </l>
          <l>Nor can they so forget mee to bee far, </l>
          <l>I Know there stands no other enuious Bar: </l>
          <l>But that foule Cloude to Darken this Bright Day, </l>
          <l>Which with this Fanne of Starres Ile Chace away. </l>
          <l>Vanish Infectious Fog that I may see </l>
          <l>This Citties Grace, that takes her Light from Mee. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>At this her powerfull command, the Vanish, giue Way, Cloude suddenly rises, and changes into a bright spredding Canopy, stucke thicke with Starres, and beames of Gold, shooting forth round about it, the Mount appearing then most rich in Beauty and Glory, the foure Monsters falling flat at the Foote of the Hill; that graue Foeminine Shape, figuring London, sitting in greatest Honour; next aboue her in the most eminent place, sits Religion, the Modell of a faire Temple on her Head, and a burning Lampe in her Hand, the proper Emblemes of her Sanctity, Watchfulnesse, and Zeale; on her right Hand sits Liberality, her head circled with a Wreath of Gold, in her hand a Cornucopia, or Horne of Abundance, out of which rusheth a seeming Floud of Gold, but no way flowing to Prodigality; for as the Sea is gouern'd by the Moone, so is that wealthy Riuer by her Eie, (for Bounty must bee led by Iudgement) and hence is Art-fully deriued the onely difference betweene Prodigality and Bounty, the one deales her Giftes with open eyes, the <pb xml:id="ep000198-011-b"/>other blind-fold; on her left side sits Perfect Loue, his proper Seate being neerest the Heart, wearing vpon his Head a wreath of white and red Roses mingled together, the Antient Witnesse of Peace, Loue and Vnion, wherein consists the Happinesse of this Land, his Right hand holding a Sphaere, where in a Circle of Gold, is contained all the 12 Companies Armes; and therefore cal'd the Spaere of true Brother-hood, or Annulus Amoris, the Ring of Loue: vpon his left hand stand two Billing Turtles, expressing thereby the happy Condition of mutuall Loue and Society: on either side of this Mount are displaid the Charitable and Religious workes of London (especially the worthy Company of Grocers) in giuing maintenance to Schollers, Souldiers, Widdowes, Orphans, and the like, where are plac'd one of each number: &amp; on the two Heights sit Knowledge &amp; Modesty; Knowledge wearing a Crowne of Starres, in her Hand a Perspectiue Glasse, betokening both her High Iudgement, and Deepe In-sight, the Brow of Modestie circled with a Wreath all of red Roses, expressing her Bashfulnesse and Blushings, in her hand a Crimson Baner, fild with Siluer Stars, figuring the white Purity of her Shamfastnesse, her cheeks not red with Shame or Guilt, but with Virgin-Feare, and Honor. At the Backe of this Triumphant Mount, Chastity, Fame, Simplicity, Meeknesse, haue their Seats, Chastity wearing on her Head a Garland of white Roses, in her Hand a white Silke Banner, fild with Starres of Gold, expressing the aeternity of her vn-spotted Purenesse: Fame next vnder her, on her a Head a Crowne of Siluer, and a Siluer Trumpet in her hand, showing both her Brightnesse and Shrilnesse: Simplicity with a Milke-white Doue vpon her Head, and <pb xml:id="ep000198-012-a"/>Meekenesse with a Garland of mingled Flowers, in her hand a white Silke Banner with a red Crosse, a Lambe at her Feet, by which both their Conditions are sufficiently exprest; The Mount thus made glorious by the Power of Truth, and the Mist expeld, London thus speakes. </p>
        <sp who="#ep000198-london" xml:id="ep000198-e103480">
          <speaker>London. </speaker>
          <l>Thicke Scales of Darknesse in a Moments space </l>
          <l>Are fell from both mine Eyes, I see the Face </l>
          <l>Of all my Friends about me (now) most cleerely, </l>
          <l>Religions Sisters, whom I Honour deerely; </l>
          <l>Oh I behold the worke, it comes from Thee </l>
          <l>Illustrious Patronesse, thou that mad'st me see </l>
          <l>In Dayes of blindest Ignorance, when this Light </l>
          <l>Was ee'n extinguisht, Thou Redeem'st my sight; </l>
          <l>Then to Thy Charge (with Reuerence) I commend </l>
          <l>That worthy Son of mine, thy vertuous Friend, </l>
          <l>Whom on my Loue and Blessing I require, </l>
          <l>To obserue Thee Faithfully, and his Desire </l>
          <l>To imitate Thy will, and there lye bounded, </l>
          <l>For Power's a Dangerous Sea, which must be sounded </l>
          <l>With Truth and Iustice, or Man soone runs on </l>
          <l>'Gainst Rockes and Shelues to Dissolution; </l>
          <l>Then that thou maist the Difference euer know, </l>
          <l>Twixt Truth and Error, a few words shall show; </l>
          <l>The many Wayes that to blind Error slide </l>
          <l>Are in the entrance broad, Hell-mouth is wide, </l>
          <l>But when Man enters farre, he findes it then </l>
          <l>Close, Darke and Streight, for Hell returnes no Men; </l>
          <l>But the One sacred Way which Truth directs, </l>
          <l>Onely at Entrance Mans Affection Checks, </l>
          <l>And is there strict alone, to which place throngs </l>
          <l>All Worlds Afflictions, Calumnies and wrongs. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000198-012-b"/>
          <l>But hauing past those, then thou find'st a way </l>
          <l>In bredth, whole Heauen, in length, aeternall Day, </l>
          <l>Then following Truth, she brings Thee to that way; </l>
          <l>But first obserue what workes she here requires, </l>
          <l>Religion, Knowledge, Sanctity, Chast Desires, </l>
          <l>Then Charity, which Bounty must expresse, </l>
          <l>To Schollers, Souldiers, Widdowes, Fatherlesse; </l>
          <l>These haue beene still my Workes, they must be thine, </l>
          <l>Honour and Action must together shine, </l>
          <l>Or the best part's Eclipst, behold but this, </l>
          <l>Thy very Crest showes Bounty, here 'tis put, </l>
          <l>Thou giu'st the open Hand, keepe it not shut; </l>
          <l>But to the Needie, or Deseruing Spirit, </l>
          <l>Let it spred wide, and Heauen enrowles that Merit; </l>
          <l>Do these, and proue my Hopefull Worthy Sonne, </l>
          <l>Yet nothing's spoke, but needfully must bee done. </l>
          <l>And so lead forward. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>At which Words the whole Triumph moues in his richest glory toward the Crosse in Cheape, at which place Error full of Wrath and Mallice to see his Mist so chaced away, falles into this Fury. </p>
        <sp who="#ep000198-error" xml:id="ep000198-e103930">
          <speaker>Error. </speaker>
          <l>Heart of all the Fiends in Hell! </l>
          <l>Could her Beggarly Power expell </l>
          <l>Such a Thicke and Poisonous Mist </l>
          <l>Which set Enuies Snakes to twist; </l>
          <l>Vp Monsters, was her Feeble Frowne </l>
          <l>Of Force to strike my Officers downe? </l>
          <l>Barbarisme, Impudence, Lies, Ignorance, </l>
          <l>All your Hell-bred Heads aduance, </l>
          <l>And once againe with Rotten Darknesse shroud </l>
          <l>This Mount Triumphant, drop downe sulphurous Cloud. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000198-013-a"/>
        <p>At which the Mist falles againe, and hangs ouer all the Beauty of the Mount, not a Person of Glory seene, onely the foure Monsters gather courage againe, and take their Seates, aduancing their Clubs aboue their Heads, which no sooner perceiu'd, but Truth in her Chariot making neere to the place, willing still to rescue her Friends and Seruants, from the Powers of Ignorance and Darknesse, makes vse of these Words, </p>
        <sp who="#ep000198-truth" xml:id="ep000198-e104050">
          <speaker>Truth. </speaker>
          <l>Dare yet the workes of Vglinesse appeare </l>
          <l>Gainst this Dayes Brightnesse, and see Vs so neere? </l>
          <l>How bold is Sinne and Hell, that yet it dare </l>
          <l>Rise against Vs? but know (Perditions Heire) </l>
          <l>T'is Idle to contend against our Power, </l>
          <l>Vanish againe Fowle Mist from Honors Bower. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>Then the Cloud dispersing it selfe againe, and all the Mount appearing Glorious, it passeth so on to the Standard, about which place, by Elaborate action from Error it falles againe, and goes so darkned, till it comes to S. Laurence lane end, where by the former words by Truth vtter'd, being againe chac'd away, London thus gratefully requites her Goodnesse. </p>
        <sp who="#ep000198-london" xml:id="ep000198-e104130">
          <speaker>London. </speaker>
          <l>Aeternities bright Sister, by whose Light, </l>
          <l>Errors infectious Workes still flye my Sight. </l>
          <l>Receiue thy Seruants Thankes; Now perfect Loue </l>
          <l>Whose Right hand holds a Sphaere, wherein doe moue </l>
          <l>Twelue blest Societies, whose belou'd encrease, </l>
          <l>Stiles it the Ring of Brother-hood, Faith and Peace, </l>
          <l>From thy Harmonious Lips let them all taste, </l>
          <l>The Golden Counsell that makes Health long last. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>Perfect Loue then standing vp, holding in his right <pb xml:id="ep000198-013-b"/>hand a Sphaere, on the other, two Billing Turtles, giues these words. </p>
        <sp who="#ep000198-perfect_love" xml:id="ep000198-e104230">
          <speaker>Perfect Loue. </speaker>
          <l>First then I banish from this Feast of Ioy, </l>
          <l>All Excesse, Epicurisme, both which destroy </l>
          <l>The Healths of Soule and Body, no such Guest </l>
          <l>Ought to be welcome to this Reuerend Feast </l>
          <l>Where Truth is Mistresse, who's admitted here, </l>
          <l>Must come for Vertues loue more then for Cheere, </l>
          <l>These two white Turtles may example giue </l>
          <l>How Perfect Ioy and Brother-hood should liue, </l>
          <l>And they from whom Graue Order is expected, </l>
          <l>Of rude Excesse must neuer bee detected; </l>
          <l>This is the Councell which that Lady calles </l>
          <l>Golden Aduice, for by it no man falles </l>
          <l>Hee that desires Dayes healthfull, sound and blest, </l>
          <l>Let moderate Iudgement serue him at his Feast, </l>
          <l>And so lead on, may Perfect Brother-hood shine, </l>
          <l>Still in Sphaere, and Honor still in thine. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>This Speech so ended, his Lordship and the Companies passe on to Guild-hall; and at their Returning backe, these Triumphs attend to bring his Lordship toward Saint Pauls Church, there to performe those yearely Ceremoniall Rites, which Antient and Graue Order hath determined, Error by the way still busie and in Action to drawe Darknesse often vpon that Mount of Triumph, which by Truth is as often disperst: then all returning homewards full of Beauty and Brightnesse, this Mount and the Chariot of Truth, both plac'd neere to the Entrance of his Lordships Gate, neere Leaden-hall; London, the Lady of that Mount; first giues vtterance to these words, </p>
        <pb xml:id="ep000198-014-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000198-london" xml:id="ep000198-e104410">
          <speaker>London. </speaker>
          <l>Before the Day sprang from the Mornings Wombe </l>
          <l>I rose, my Care was earlier then the Light, </l>
          <l>Nor would it rest till I now brought Thee Home, </l>
          <l>Marrying to one Ioy both thy Day and Night; </l>
          <l>Nor can we call this Night, if our Eyes count </l>
          <l>The Glorious beames that dance about this Mount, </l>
          <l>Sure did not Custome guide'em, Men would say </l>
          <l>Two Noones were seene together in one day, </l>
          <l>The Splendor is so piercing, Triumph seemes </l>
          <l>As if it sparkled, and to Mens esteemes </l>
          <l>Threw forth his Thankes, wrapt vp in Golden Flames, </l>
          <l>As if hee would giue Light to reade their Names </l>
          <l>That were at Cost this Day to make him shine, </l>
          <l>And be as free in Thankes, as they in Coine, </l>
          <l>But see Time checkes me, and his Sithe stands ready </l>
          <l>To cut all off, no State on Earth is steady, </l>
          <l>Therefore Graue Sonne the Time that is to come, </l>
          <l>Bestow on Truth, and so Thour't welcome Home. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>Time standing vp in Truths Chariot, seeming to make an offer with his Sithe to cut off the Glories of the Day, growing neere now to the Season of Rest and Sleepe, his Daughter Truth thus meekely stayes his Hand. </p>
        <sp who="#ep000198-truth" xml:id="ep000198-e104610">
          <speaker>Truth. </speaker>
          <l>Father desist a while till I send forth </l>
          <l>A few Words to our Friend, that Man of Worth: </l>
          <l>The Power that Heauen, Loue, and the Cities choyce, </l>
          <l>Haue all confer'd on Thee with Mutuall voyce, </l>
          <l>As it is Great, Reuerend, and Honorable, </l>
          <l>Meet it with equall Goodnesse, striue t'excell </l>
          <l>Thy former Selfe, as thy Command exceeds </l>
          <l>Thy last-yeares State, so let new Acts, old Deeds; </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000198-014-b"/>
          <l>And as great men in Riches and in Birth </l>
          <l>(Heightning their Blouds, and ioyning Earth to Earth,) </l>
          <l>Bestow their best houres and most serious cares </l>
          <l>In chusing out fit Matches for their Heires: </l>
          <l>So neuer giue Thou ouer day or howre </l>
          <l>Till with a Vertue thou hast matcht this Power: </l>
          <l>For what is Greatnesse if not ioyn'd with Grace? </l>
          <l>Like one of High-bloud that hath married Base. </l>
          <l>Who seekes Authority with an Ignorant Eye, </l>
          <l>Is like a man seekes out his Enemy: </l>
          <l>For where before his Follies were not spred </l>
          <l>Or his corruptions, then theire cleerely read </l>
          <l>Ee'n by the eyes of all men; 'tis so pure </l>
          <l>A Cristall of it selfe, it will endure </l>
          <l>No poyson of Oppression, Bribes, Hir'd Law, </l>
          <l>But 'twill appeare soone in some cracke or flaw, </l>
          <l>How e're men sooth their hopes with Popular breath, </l>
          <l>If not in Life, she'ile finde that crack in Death: </l>
          <l>I was not made to fawne or stroake fin smooth </l>
          <l>Bee wise and heare me then that cannot sooth: </l>
          <l>I haue set Thee High now, bee so in Example, </l>
          <l>Made thee a Pinacle in Honors Temple, </l>
          <l>Fixing ten thousand Eyes vpon thy Brow </l>
          <l>There is no hiding of thy Actions now, </l>
          <l>They must abide the Light, and imitate Mee, </l>
          <l>Or bee throwne downe to Fire where Errors bee. </l>
          <l>Nor onely with these words thy eare I feede, </l>
          <l>But giue those part that shall in Time succeed, </l>
          <l>To thee in present, and to them to come </l>
          <l>That Truth may bring you all with Honour home </l>
          <l>To these your Gates, and to those, after these </l>
          <l>Of which your owne good Actions Keepe the Keyes; </l>
          <l>Then as the Loues of thy Society </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000198-015-a"/>
          <l>Hath flowde in Bounties on this Day and Thee, </l>
          <l>Counting all Cost too little for true Art, </l>
          <l>Doubling rewards there where they found Desert, </l>
          <l>In Thankefulnesse, Iustice, and Vertuous care </l>
          <l>Perfect their hopes, those thy Requitals are; </l>
          <l>With Fatherly Respect embrace'em all, </l>
          <l>Faith in thy Heart, and Plenty in thy Hall, </l>
          <l>Loue in thy Walkes, but Iustice in thy State, </l>
          <l>Zeale in thy Chamber, Bounty at thy Gate: </l>
          <l>And so to Thee and these a Blessed Night, </l>
          <l>To thee Faire Citty, Peace, my Grace and Light. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000198-e105140">Trumpets sounding Triumphantly, </stage>
        <p>Zeale, the Champion of Truth on Horse-backe, his head circled with strange Fires, appeares to his Mistresse, and thus speakes: </p>
        <sp who="#ep000198-missing" xml:id="ep000198-e105160">
          <l>See yonder, Lady, Errors Chariot stands, </l>
          <l>Brauing the Power of your incenst commands, </l>
          <l>Emboldned by the priuiledge of Night </l>
          <l>And her blacke Faction, yet to crowne his Spight </l>
          <l>Which Ile confound, I burne in Diuine wrath. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000198-truth" xml:id="ep000198-e105220">
          <speaker>Truth. </speaker>
          <l>Strike then, I giue thee leaue to shoote it forth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000198-zeal" xml:id="ep000198-e105240">
          <speaker>Zeale. </speaker>
          <l>Then here's to the destruction of that Seate, </l>
          <l>There's nothing seene of Thee but Fire shall eate. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>At which, a Flame shootes from the Head of Zeale, which fastening vpon that Cariot of Error sets it on Fire, and all the Beasts that are ioynde to it. </p>
        <p>The Fire-worke being made by Maister Humphrey Nichols, a Man excellent in his Art: and the <pb xml:id="ep000198-015-b"/>whole Worke and Body of the Triumph, with all the proper Beauties of the Workemanship most Artfully and Faithfully performed by Iohn Grinkin: and those furnished with Apparrell and Porters by Anthony Monday, Gentleman. </p>
        <p>This proud Seate of Error lying now onely glowing in Imbers, (being a Figure or Type of his Lord-ships Iustice on all wicked offenders in the Time of his Gouernement,) I now conclude, holding it a more learned Discretion to cease of my selfe, then to haue Time cut mee off rudely, and now let him strike at his pleasure. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="supplied_by_editor">
        <head>Notes, typically marginal, from the original text</head>
        <div corresp="A07518-e100160" xml:id="ep000198-e100160-n">
          <head>Notes for div A07518-e100160</head>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="illustration" xml:id="ep000198-e105310">
        <p>
          <figure>
            <head>TAM ROBVR· TAM ROBOR. IN-COLIS ARBOR IOVIS. 1610. ❀ </head>
            <p>NO </p>
            <p>♃ </p>
            <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="song" xml:id="ep000198-e105370">
        <pb xml:id="ep000198-016-a"/>
        <head>The Song with the Note. </head>
        <p>
          <gap n="16-a-0070" reason="music"/>MOther of many honorable Sonnes, thinke not <gap n="16-a-0160" reason="music"/>thy glasse too slowly runs, That in Times hand is <gap n="16-a-0280" reason="music"/>set, because thy worthy Sonne appeares not yet, <gap n="16-a-0390" reason="music"/>Lady be pleasd the houre growes on, thy ioys will be <gap n="16-a-0520" reason="music"/>compleat anon, thou shalt behold, the man in-rold, <gap n="16-a-0640" reason="music"/>in honors-booke whome vertue raises, loue circled, <pb xml:id="ep000198-016-b"/>
          <gap n="16-b-0010" reason="music"/>round, his tryumphes crownd, withall good wishes, <gap n="16-b-0120" reason="music"/>prayers and praises. </p>
        <l>What greater comfort to a Mothers heart, </l>
        <l>Then to behold her sonnes Desert: </l>
        <l>Goe hand in hand with loue, </l>
        <l>Respect and Honor (Blessings from aboue) </l>
        <l>It is of power all greefes to kill, </l>
        <l>And with a floud of ioy to fill. </l>
        <l>Thy Aged Eyes, </l>
        <l>To see him rise, </l>
        <l>With Glory dect, where Expectation. </l>
        <l>Grace, Truth, and Fame, </l>
        <l>Met in his Name, </l>
        <l>Attends his Honors Confirmation. </l>
        <div n="bassus" type="part" xml:id="ep000198-e105590">
          <head>BASSVS. </head>
          <p>
            <gap n="16-b-1000" reason="music"/>
          </p>
        </div>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
