<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000193" xml:lang="eng">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     The triumphs of health and prosperity A noble solemnity performed through the city, at the sole cost and charges of the Honorable Fraternity of Drapers, at the inauguration of their most worthy brother, the Right Honorable, Cuthbert Hacket, Lord Major of the famous city of London. By Tho. Middleton Gent.
    </title>
    <author>
     <!--Middleton, Thomas-->
     <persName>
      <forename>
       Thomas
      </forename>
      <surname>
       Middleton
      </surname>
     </persName>
    </author>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher xml:id="dracor">
     DraCor
    </publisher>
    <idno type="URL">
     https://dracor.org/
    </idno>
    <availability>
     <licence>
      <ab>
       CC0 1.0
      </ab>
      <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
       Licence
      </ref>
     </licence>
    </availability>
    <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl type="digitalSource">
     <name>
      EarlyPrint Project
     </name>
     <idno type="URL">
      https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A07512.xml
     </idno>
     <availability>
      <p>
       This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is available for reuse, according to the terms of
       <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
        Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
       </ref>
       . The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
      </p>
     </availability>
     <bibl type="originalSource">
      <biblFull>
       <titleStmt>
        <title>
         The triumphs of health and prosperity A noble solemnity performed through the city, at the sole cost and charges of the Honorable Fraternity of Drapers, at the inauguration of their most worthy brother, the Right Honorable, Cuthbert Hacket, Lord Major of the famous city of London. By Tho. Middleton Gent.
        </title>
        <author>
         Middleton, Thomas, d. 1627.
        </author>
       </titleStmt>
       <extent>
        [16] p.
       </extent>
       <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>
         By Nicholas Okes, dwelling in Foster-lane,
        </publisher>
        <pubPlace>
         Imprinted at London :
        </pubPlace>
        <date>
         MDCXXVI. [1626]
        </date>
       </publicationStmt>
       <notesStmt>
        <note>
         Partly in verse.
        </note>
        <note>
         Signatures: A-B&#8308;.
        </note>
        <note>
         Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
        </note>
       </notesStmt>
      </biblFull>
     </bibl>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
   <profileDesc>
    <particDesc>
     <listPerson>
     </listPerson>
    </particDesc>
   </profileDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <standOff>
  <listEvent>
   <event type="written" when="">
    <desc/>
   </event>
  </listEvent>
 </standOff>
 <text>
  <front>
   <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000193-e10">
    <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000193-001-a"/>
    <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000193-001-b"/>
    <head>
     TO THE HONOR OF HIM, to whom the Noble Fraternity of Drapers, his Worthy Brothers haue Consecrated their loues in Magnificent Tryumphs, the Right Honorable CUTHBERT HACKEY Lord Major of the City of LONDON.
    </head>
    <lg>
     <l>
      THE Cities choyce, thy Companies free loue,
     </l>
     <l>
      This Dayes vnlookt for Tryumph, all three proue,
     </l>
     <l>
      The Happinesse of thy life to be most great;
     </l>
     <l>
      Adde to these, Justice, and thou art Compleate.
     </l>
    </lg>
    <closer>
     <signed>
      At your Lordships Command, Thomas Middleton.
     </signed>
    </closer>
    <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000193-002-a"/>
    <gap extent="1" reason="duplicate" unit="pages"/>
    <pb xml:id="ep000193-002-b"/>
    <gap extent="1" reason="duplicate" unit="pages"/>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <div type="text" xml:id="ep000193-e160">
    <pb xml:id="ep000193-003-a"/>
    <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000193-003-b"/>
    <head>
     The Triumphes of Health and Prosperity.
    </head>
    <p>
     IF you should search all Chronicles, Histories, Records, in what Language or Letter soeuer; if the Inquisitiue Man should waste the deere Treasure of his Time and Ey-sight, He shall conclude his life onely with this certainety, that there is no Subiect vpon earth receiued into the place of his Gouernement with the like State and Magnificence, as is his Maiesties great Substitute into his Honorable charge the Citty of London, bearing the Inscription of the
     <hi>
      Chamber Royall
     </hi>
     : which that it may now appeare to the world no lesse illustrated with brotherly Affection then former Tryumphall times haue beene partakers of, this takes delight
     <pb xml:id="ep000193-004-a"/>
     to present it selfe.
    </p>
    <p>
     And first to enter the worthy loue of his honorable Society, for his Lordships returne from Westminster, hauing receiued some seruice by water, by the Triumphant
     <hi>
      Chariot of Honor
     </hi>
     , the first that attends his Lordships most wished Arriuall, beares the Title of the
     <hi>
      Beautifull Hill
     </hi>
     , or
     <hi>
      Fragrant Garden
     </hi>
     , with flowry bankes, neere to which, Lambes and Sheepe are a grazing, this platforme so cast into a Hill, is adorned and garnisht with all variety of Odoriferous flowers, on the top Archt with an Artificial and curious
     <hi>
      Raine bow
     </hi>
     , which both shewes the Antiquity of colours, the diuersity and Noblenesse, and how much the more glorious and highly to be esteem'd, they being presented in that blessed Couenant of Mercy, the
     <hi>
      Bow in the Clouds
     </hi>
     , the worke it selfe incompast with all various fruites, and beares the name of the most pleasant garden of England (the Noble City of London) the flowers intimating the sweete odors of their Vertue and Goodnesses, and the fruites of their workes of Iustice and Charity, which haue bene both Honorable Brothers, and bounteous benefactors of this antient Fraternity, who are presented in &#12296;&#9674;&#12297; deuice following, vnder the types and figures of their Vertues in their life
     <pb xml:id="ep000193-004-b"/>
     time, which made them famous then, and memorable for euer, and since we are yet amongst the woolly Creatures that graze on the Beautie of this beautifull platforme, come we to the moderne vse of this Noble mystery of Antient Drapery, and we shall find the whole Liuery of this renowned and famous City furnished by it, it clothes the honorable Senators in their highest and chiefest wearing, all Courts of Iustice, Magistrates and Iudges of the Land. But for the better expression of the purpose in hand, a Speaker giues life to these following words.
    </p>
    <lg>
     <head>
      The Speech in the Hill where the
      <hi>
       Raine-bow appeares
      </hi>
      .
     </head>
     <l>
      A Cloude of griefe hath showrde vpon the face
     </l>
     <l>
      Of this sad City, and vsurpt the place
     </l>
     <l>
      Of Ioy and Cheerfulnesse, wearing the forme,
     </l>
     <l>
      Of a long blacke Ecclipse in a rough storme,
     </l>
     <l>
      With flowers of Teares this garden was oreflowne,
     </l>
     <l>
      Till mercy was like the blest Rain-bow showne.
     </l>
     <l>
      Behold what figure now the City beares,
     </l>
     <l>
      Like Iems vnvalued, her best joyes she weares;
     </l>
     <l>
      Glad as a faithfull Hand-mayde to obay,
     </l>
     <l>
      And waite vpon the Honour of this Day;
     </l>
     <pb xml:id="ep000193-005-a"/>
     <l>
      Fixt in the Kings great Substitute, Delight,
     </l>
     <l>
      Triumph, and Pompe had almost lost their right:
     </l>
     <l>
      The Garden springs agen, the Violet Beds,
     </l>
     <l>
      The lofty Flowers beare vp their fragrant heads;
     </l>
     <l>
      Fruit ouer-lade their Trees, Barnes cracke with store,
     </l>
     <l>
      And yet how much the Heavens wept before:
     </l>
     <l>
      Threatning a second mourning, who so dull,
     </l>
     <l>
      But must acknowledge Mercie was at full.
     </l>
     <l>
      In these two mighty blessings; what's requir'd?
     </l>
     <l>
      That which in conscience ought to be desir'd;
     </l>
     <l>
      Care and Vprightnesse in the Magistrates place,
     </l>
     <l>
      And in all men Obedience, Truth and Grace.
     </l>
    </lg>
    <p>
     After this awaites his Lordships approach, a Maister-peece of Triumph, called the
     <hi>
      Sanctuary of Prosperity
     </hi>
     , on the Top Arch of which hangs the
     <hi>
      Golden Fleece
     </hi>
     , which raises the worthy memory of that most famous and renowned Brother of this Company, Sir
     <hi>
      Francis Drake
     </hi>
     , who in two yeares and ten moneths did incompasse the whole world, deseruing an eminent remembrance in this Sanctuary, who neuer returned to his Countrey without the
     <hi>
      Golden Fleece
     </hi>
     of Honour and Victory. The foure faire Corinthian Columnes or Pillars, imply the foure principall Vertues,
     <hi>
      Wisedome, Iustice, Fortitude, Temperance,
     </hi>
     the especiall vpholders of Kingdomes, Cities
     <pb xml:id="ep000193-005-b"/>
     and Honorable Societies.
    </p>
    <lg>
     <head>
      The Speech in the Sanctuary vpon the Fleece.
     </head>
     <l>
      <hi>
       IF Iason
      </hi>
      with the noble hopes of Greece,
     </l>
     <l>
      Who did from Colchis fetch the Golden Fleece,
     </l>
     <l>
      Deserue a Story of immortall fame,
     </l>
     <l>
      That both the Asiaes celebrate his name,
     </l>
     <l>
      What Honor, Celebration and Renowne,
     </l>
     <l>
      In Vertues right, ought justly to be showne,
     </l>
     <l>
      To the faire memory of Sir
      <hi>
       Francis Drake
      </hi>
      ;
     </l>
     <l>
      Englands true Iason, who did boldly make
     </l>
     <l>
      So many rare Adventures, which were held
     </l>
     <l>
      For worth, vnmatcht, danger, vnparaleld,
     </l>
     <l>
      Neuer returning to his Countries Eye,
     </l>
     <l>
      Without the Golden Fleece of Victory.
     </l>
     <l>
      The World's a Sea, and euery Magistrate
     </l>
     <l>
      Takes a yeares Voyage, when he takes this state,
     </l>
     <l>
      Nor on these Seas, are there lesse dangers found,
     </l>
     <l>
      Then those, on which the bold Adventurer's bound:
     </l>
     <l>
      For Rockes, gulfes, quicke sands, here is &#12296;&#9674;&#12297; spite,
     </l>
     <l>
      Enuy, Detraction of all Noble Right&#9642;
     </l>
     <l>
      Vessels of Honor, those doe threaten more,
     </l>
     <l>
      Then any Ruine betweene Sea and Shore.
     </l>
     <pb xml:id="ep000193-006-a"/>
     <l>
      Sayle then by th'Compasse of a Vertuous name,
     </l>
     <l>
      And spite of Spite's, thou bringst the Fleece of fame.
     </l>
    </lg>
    <p>
     Passing from this, and more to encourage the Noble endeauours of the Magistrate, his Lordship and the worthy Company, is gracefully Conducted toward the Chariot of Honor, on the most Eminent seate thereof is Gouernement Illustrated, it being the proper Vertue by which we rayse the noble memory of Sir
     <hi>
      Henry Fitz&#9642; Alwin
     </hi>
     , who held the Seate of Magistracy in this City twenty foure yeares together, a most renowned Brother of this Company: In like manner, the Worthy Sir
     <hi>
      Iohn Norman
     </hi>
     first rowed in Barge to Westminster with silver Oares, vnder the person of Munificence: Sir
     <hi>
      Simon Eyre
     </hi>
     that built Leaden Hall, a Granary for the poore, vnder the Type of Piety,
     <foreign xml:lang="lat">
      Et sic de caeteris
     </foreign>
     . This Chariot drawne by two Golden pellited Lyons, beeing the proper Supporters of the Companies Armes, those two that haue their Seates vpon the Lyons, presenting Power and Honor, the one in a little Streamer or Banneret, bearing the armes of the present Lord Major; the other the late, the truely Generous and Worthy, Sir
     <hi>
      Allen Cotton
     </hi>
     Knight, a bounteous
     <pb xml:id="ep000193-006-b"/>
     and a Noble House-keeper, one that hath spent the yeare of his Magistracy, to the great Honour of the City, and by the sweetnesse of his Disposition, and the vprightnesse of his Iustice and Government, hath rays'd vp a fayre lasting Memory to himselfe and his Posterity for euer; at whose happy Inauguration, though Tryumph was not then in season, (Deaths Pageants being onely advanc'st vppon the shoulders of men,) His Noble deservings were not thereby any way ecllipsed.
    </p>
    <p>
     <foreign xml:lang="lat">
      Est Uirtus sibi Marmor, et Integritate Triumphat.
     </foreign>
    </p>
    <lg>
     <head>
      The Speech of Gouernement.
     </head>
     <l>
      With just propriety dos this City stand,
     </l>
     <l>
      As fixt by fate, ith' middle of the Land,
     </l>
     <l>
      It ha's as in the body the Heartes place,
     </l>
     <l>
      Fit for her workes of Piety and Grace:
     </l>
     <l>
      The Head her Soueraigne, vnto whom she sends
     </l>
     <l>
      All duties that just seruice comprehends;
     </l>
     <l>
      The Eyes may be compar'd (at wisedomes rate)
     </l>
     <l>
      To the illustrious Councellors of State,
     </l>
     <l>
      Set in that Orbe of Royalty, to giue light
     </l>
     <l>
      To noble actions, Starres of truth and right:
     </l>
     <l>
      The Lips, the Reuerend Cleargy, Iudges, all
     </l>
     <l>
      That pronounce Lawes Diuine, or Temporall;
     </l>
     <pb xml:id="ep000193-007-a"/>
     <gap extent="1" reason="duplicate" unit="pages"/>
     <pb xml:id="ep000193-007-b"/>
     <gap extent="1" reason="duplicate" unit="pages"/>
     <pb xml:id="ep000193-008-a"/>
     <l>
      The Armes to the defensiue part of men,
     </l>
     <l>
      So I descend vnto the Heart agen:
     </l>
     <l>
      The place where now you are, witnesse the loue,
     </l>
     <l>
      True Brother-hoods cost and Tryumph, all which moue
     </l>
     <l>
      In this most graue Solemnity, and in this
     </l>
     <l>
      The Cities generall loue abstracted is:
     </l>
     <l>
      And as the Heart in it's meridian seate,
     </l>
     <l>
      Is stil&#9642; d the Fountayne of the bodies heate:
     </l>
     <l>
      The first thing receiues life, the last that dyes,
     </l>
     <l>
      Those properties experience well applies
     </l>
     <l>
      To this most loyall City, that hath beene
     </l>
     <l>
      In former ages as in these times seene;
     </l>
     <l>
      The Fountayne of Affection, Duty, Zeale,
     </l>
     <l>
      And taught all Cities through the Common weale,
     </l>
     <l>
      The first that receiues quickning life and spirit,
     </l>
     <l>
      From the Kings grace, which stil she striues to inherit
     </l>
     <l>
      And like the Heart will be the last that dyes,
     </l>
     <l>
      In any duty toward good supplies:
     </l>
     <l>
      What can expresse affections nobler fruite,
     </l>
     <l>
      Both to the King, and You, his Substitute.
     </l>
    </lg>
    <p>
     At the close of this Speech, this Chariot of Honor, and Sanctuary of Prosperity, with all her gracefull Concomitants, and the two other parts of Tryumph, take leaue of his Lordship for that time, and rest from service till the great Feast at
     <pb xml:id="ep000193-008-b"/>
     <hi>
      Guild hall
     </hi>
     be ended, after which the whole Fabricke of the Triumph attends vpon his Honour, both toward Saint Paules and homeward, his Lordship accompanied with the graue and Honourable Senators of the City, amongst whom the two worthy Shrieffes, his Lordships Graue Assistants for the yeare, the Worshipfull and gen&#233;rous Maister
     <hi>
      Richard Fen
     </hi>
     , and Master
     <hi>
      Edward Brumfield
     </hi>
     ought not to passe of my respect vnremembred, whose bounty and Noblenesse for the yeare, will no doubt, giue the best expression to their owne Worthinesse. Betweene the Crosse and the entrance of Woodstreet, that part of Tryumph being planted, being the
     <hi>
      Fragrant Garden of England
     </hi>
     , with the Raine-Bow to which the concluding Speech hath chiefly reference, there takes its farwell of his&#772;Lordship, accompanied with the
     <hi>
      Fountayne &#12296;&#9674;&#12297; Vertue
     </hi>
     , being the fourth part of the Tryumph.
    </p>
    <lg>
     <head>
      The last Speech.
     </head>
     <l>
      MErcies faire Object, the Caelestiall Bow,
     </l>
     <l>
      As in the morning it began to show,
     </l>
     <l>
      It closes vp this great Tryumphall day,
     </l>
     <l>
      And by example showes the Yeare, the Way,
     </l>
     <pb xml:id="ep000193-009-a"/>
     <l>
      Which if Power worthily, and rightly spend,
     </l>
     <l>
      It must with Mercy both begin and end;
     </l>
     <l>
      It is a yeare that crownes the life of man,
     </l>
     <l>
      Brings him to Peace with Honor and what can
     </l>
     <l>
      Be more desir'd, 'tis vertues harvest time,
     </l>
     <l>
      When Grauity and Iudgements in their prime,
     </l>
     <l>
      To speake more happily, 'tis a time giuen
     </l>
     <l>
      To treasure vp good Actions fit for Heauen,
     </l>
     <l>
      To a Brother hood of Honor thou art fixt
     </l>
     <l>
      That has stood long faire in just Vertues eye;
     </l>
     <l>
      For within twelue yeares space, thou art the Sixt,
     </l>
     <l>
      That has bin Lord Major of this Company:
     </l>
     <l>
      This is no vsuall grace, being now the last,
     </l>
     <l>
      Close the Worke Nobly vp, that what is past,
     </l>
     <l>
      And knowne to be good in the former Fiue:
     </l>
     <l>
      May in thy present Care be kept aliue;
     </l>
     <l>
      Then is thy Brotherhood for their Loue and Cost,
     </l>
     <l>
      Requited amply; but thy owne Soule most.
     </l>
     <l>
      Health and a happy Peace fill all thy dayes,
     </l>
     <l>
      When thy Yeare ends, may then begin thy prayse.
     </l>
    </lg>
    <pb xml:id="ep000193-009-b"/>
    <p>
     <hi>
      FOR the Fabricke or Structure of the whole Tryumph, in so short a time, so gracefully performed, the Commendation of that, the Industry of Maister
      <hi>
       Garret Chrismas
      </hi>
      may justly Challenge, a man not onely excellent in his Arte, but faithfull in his Vndertakings.
     </hi>
    </p>
    <trailer>
     FINIS.
    </trailer>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
