<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000195" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The triumphs of honor and vertue A noble solemnitie, performed through the City, at the sole cost and charges of the honorable Fraternitie of Grocers, at the confirmation and establishment of their most worthy brother, the Right Honorable Peter Proby, in the high office of his Maiesties Lieutenant, Lord Maior and Chancellor of the famous City of London. Taking beginning at his Lordships going, and perfecting it selfe after his returne from receiuing the oath of maioralty at Westminster, on the morrow after Simon and Iudes Day, being the 29. of October, 1622. By Tho. Middleton Gent.</title>
        <author>
<!--Middleton, Thomas-->
          <persName>
            <forename>Thomas</forename>
            <surname>Middleton</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A07515.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <p>
            This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is available for reuse, according to the terms of
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>
            . The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
          </p>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull>
              <titleStmt>
                <title>The triumphs of honor and vertue A noble solemnitie, performed through the City, at the sole cost and charges of the honorable Fraternitie of Grocers, at the confirmation and establishment of their most worthy brother, the Right Honorable Peter Proby, in the high office of his Maiesties Lieutenant, Lord Maior and Chancellor of the famous City of London. Taking beginning at his Lordships going, and perfecting it selfe after his returne from receiuing the oath of maioralty at Westminster, on the morrow after Simon and Iudes Day, being the 29. of October, 1622. By Tho. Middleton Gent.</title>
                <author>Middleton, Thomas, d. 1627.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[20] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                <date>1622.</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>Mostly in verse.</note>
                <note>Signatures: A&#178; B-C&#8308;.</note>
                <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
      <profileDesc>
        <particDesc>
          <listPerson/>
        </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000195-e10">
        <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000195-001-a"/>
        <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000195-001-b"/>
        <p>THE TRIVMPHS OF Honor and Vertue. </p>
        <p>A Noble Solemnitie, performed through the <hi>City, at the sole Cost and Charges of the Honorable </hi>Fraternitie of Grocers, at the Confirmation and Establishment of their most worthy Brother, the Right Honorable PETER PROBY, <hi>in the high Office of his Maiestus </hi>Lieutenant, Lord Maior and Chancellor <hi>of the famous City of </hi>London. </p>
        <p>Taking beginning at his Lordships going, and perfecting <hi>it selfe after His returne from receiuing the Oath of Maioralty </hi>at Westminster, on the Morrow after Simon and Iudes Day, being the 29. of October, 1622. </p>
        <p>By THO. MIDDLETON Gent. </p>
        <p>LONDON. Printed by NICHOLAS OKES. 1622. </p>
        <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000195-002-a"/>
        <gap extent="1" reason="duplicate" unit="pages"/>
        <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000195-002-b"/>
        <gap extent="1" reason="duplicate" unit="pages"/>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000195-e250">
        <pb xml:id="ep000195-003-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000195-003-b"/>
        <head>TO The Honor of him, to whom the Noble Fraternitie of Grocers, his Worthy Brothers, haue Dedicated their Loues, in costly Triumphs; the Right Honorable, PETER PROBY, Lord Maur of this Renowned City. </head>
        <l>TO be His Seruant, that hath seru'd </l>
        <l>Two Royall Princes, and deseru'd </l>
        <l>So Worthily of Both; the Same </l>
        <l>Call not Seruice, rather Fame. </l>
        <closer>
          <signed>At your Lordships Command: Tho. Middleton. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="triumph" xml:id="ep000195-e340">
        <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000195-004-a"/>
        <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000195-004-b"/>
        <head>THE TRIVMPHS OF Honor and Vertue. </head>
        <p>IF forreine Nations haue beene strucke with Admiration at the Forme, State, and Splendor of some yeerly Triumphs, wherein Arte hath beene but faintly imitated: There is faire hope that things where Inuention flourishes, cleere Art and her gracefull Proprieties, should receiue fauor and encouragement from the content of the Spectator, which next to the seruice of his Honor and honorable Societie, is the principall reward it lookes for; then not despairing of that common fauour, this takes delight to present it selfe. </p>
        <p>And first, to beginne with the worthy loue of his Noble Fraternity, after his Honors returne from Westminster, hauing receiued some seruice vpon the Water, by the conduct of two Artfull <pb xml:id="ep000195-005-a"/>Triumphs. Viz. The <hi>Throne of Vertue</hi>, and the <hi>Continent of Jndia</hi>; which also by Land attends his Lordships most wished arriuall, accompanied with the whole body of the Triumph, which neere vpon the time of his Honors approch are decently and distinctly placed; the first, bearing the Title of the <hi>Continent of India</hi>: A triumph replenished with all manner of Spice-plants, and trees bearing Odour, attends his Honors arriuall in Paules Church-yard; A blacke Personage representing India, call'd for her odours and riches, the Queene of Merchandize, challinging the most eminent Seate, aduanceth her selfe vpon a bed of Spices, attended by Indians in Antique habits: <hi>Commerce, Aduenture </hi>and Traffique, three habited like Merchants, presenting to her view a bright Figure, bearing the inscription of Knowledge, a Sunne appearing aboue the trees in brightest splendor and glory: The blacke Queene before mentioned, lending a voyce to these following words: </p>
        <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000195-e490">
          <head>The Speech. </head>
          <l>YOu that haue eyes of Iudgement, and discerue </l>
          <l>Things that the best of Man and Life concerne, </l>
          <l>Draw neere, this blacke is but my natiue dye, </l>
          <l>But view me with an Intellectuall eye, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000195-005-b"/>
          <l>As Wise men shoote their beames forth, you'le then find </l>
          <l>A change in the complexion of the mind; </l>
          <l>I'me beauteous in my blacknesse, O yee Sonnes </l>
          <l>Of Fame and Honor, through my best part runnes </l>
          <l>A Spring of liuing Waters, cleere and true, </l>
          <l>Found first by Knowledge, which came first by you, </l>
          <l>By you, and your examples, blest Commerce, </l>
          <l>That by Exchange settles such happinesse, </l>
          <l>Of Gummes and fragrant Spices, I confesse </l>
          <l>My Climate Heauen do's with aboundance blesse, </l>
          <l>And those you haue from me, but what are they </l>
          <l>Compar'd with Odours whose sent ne're decay, </l>
          <l>And those I haue from you, plants of your youth, </l>
          <l>The Sauour of eternall life sweet Truth, </l>
          <l>Exceeding all the odoriferous sent, </l>
          <l>That from the beds of Spices euer went: </l>
          <l>I that command, (being prosp'rously possest) </l>
          <l>The Riches and the Sweetnesse of the East, </l>
          <l>To that fam'd Mountaine Taurus spreading forth </l>
          <l>My balmy Arme, whose height do's kisse the North, </l>
          <l>And in the Sea Eoum laue this hand, </l>
          <l>Account my blessings not in those to stand, </l>
          <l>Though they be large and fruitfull, but confesse </l>
          <l>All wealth cons; ists in Christian holynesse, </l>
          <l>To such caelestiall knowledge I was led; </l>
          <l>By English Merchants first enlightened, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000195-006-a"/>
          <l>Jn Honor of whose memory, onely Three </l>
          <l>I instance here, all of this ' Brotherhood free, </l>
          <l>To whose Fames the great Honor of this howre </l>
          <l>Aptly belongs, but to that Man of Power </l>
          <l>The first and chiefest, to whose worth so cleere, </l>
          <l>Iustice hath giuen her Sword vp for a yeere: </l>
          <l>And as yo'n Sunne his perfect splendor showes, </l>
          <l>Cheering the Plants; and no Cloudes interpose </l>
          <l>His Radiant Comforts; so no Earthy part </l>
          <l>Which makes Eclipses in a Rulers hart </l>
          <l>(As in that glorious Planet) must come nye </l>
          <l>The Sunne of Iustice, all such mysts must flye; </l>
          <l>You're in an Orbe of Brightnesse plac'd and fixt, </l>
          <l>And with no soyle must Honor be commixt. </l>
          <l>So to your worthy Progresse Zeale commends </l>
          <l>Your Lordship, with your Graue and Noble friends. </l>
          <p>The Speech being ended, to adde a little more help to the fainter Apprehensions, the three Merchants plac'd in the Continent, haue reference to the Lord Maior and Sheriffes, all Three being this yeer Brothers of this Ancient and Honorable Society, which triple or three fold Honor hapned to this Worthy Company in the yeere 1577. Sir <hi>Thomas Ramsey </hi>being then Lord Maior, and Master <hi>Nicholas Backhouse </hi>and Master <hi>Francis Bowyer</hi>, Sheriffes; hauing cohereuce with this yeeres Honor, <pb xml:id="ep000195-006-b"/>matcht and paralell'd with these Three their as worthy Successors, the right Honorable, <hi>Peter Proby</hi>, and the generous and Nobly affected, Master <hi>Iohn Hodges</hi>, and Sir <hi>Humphrey Handford </hi>Sheriffes and Aldermen. </p>
          <p>By this time his Lordship being gracefully conducted toward the <hi>Chariot of Fame</hi>, which awaits his Honors approach neare the little Conduit in <hi>Cheape; Antiquitie </hi>a graue and reuerend Personage, with a golden Register-booke in his hand, giues life to these words: </p>
        </div>
        <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000195-e1150">
          <head>The Speech. </head>
          <l>OBiects of Yeeres and Reuerence greete mine eye, </l>
          <l>A Sight most pleasing to Antiquitie; </l>
          <l>I neuer could vnclaspe this Booke of Fame </l>
          <l>Where Worthies dwell by a distinguisht Name, </l>
          <l>At a more comely season; I shall tell </l>
          <l>Things sprung from Truth, neere kin to Miracle; </l>
          <l>With that of later dayes I first begin, </l>
          <l>So backe into the deeper Times agen: </l>
          <l>I onely touch Thy memory (which I know </l>
          <l>In thankefulnesse can neuer be found slowe) </l>
          <l>With Heauens miraculous Mercy, to Thy Health </l>
          <l>After so long a Sicknesse, all the wealth </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000195-007-a"/>
          <l>Which thou with an vnusuring hand hast got </l>
          <l>Which is not the least wonder worthy note, </l>
          <l>(Truth makes me speake things frely) cannot be </l>
          <l>A greater worke then thy recouerie, </l>
          <l>Nine Brethren-Senators thy Seniors all </l>
          <l>Whose times had beene before thee, Death did call </l>
          <l>To their eternall Peace, from this degree </l>
          <l>Leauing their earthly Honor now to thee, </l>
          <l>Thinke and be thankefull still, this seemes the more </l>
          <l>Another obseruation kept in store, </l>
          <l>For seuenteene Senators since thy time were chose </l>
          <l>And to this minute not one dead of those. </l>
          <l>Those are not vsuall notes, nor here it endes, </l>
          <l>The Court and City two most Noble Friends, </l>
          <l>Haue made exchange a late, I reade, from hence </l>
          <l>There ha's gone some most worthy Citizens </l>
          <l>Vp to the Courts aduance; in lieu of that </l>
          <l>You haue a Courtier now your Magistrate, </l>
          <l>A Seruant to Elizabeth the blest, </l>
          <l>Since to K. Iames that raignes with Salomons brest. </l>
          <l>Kept the Records for both, from the Queene tooke </l>
          <l>Charge of three hundred Horse, three thousand Foote, </l>
          <l>Foure Attributes cleaues to this Man of Men, </l>
          <l>A Scholler, Souldier, Courtier, Citizen, </l>
          <l>These are no vsuall touches, to conclude </l>
          <l>(Like to his life with blessings so endude) </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000195-007-b"/>
          <l>Ha's chose his Brotherhood, men of that Fame </l>
          <l>For Bounty, Amity and honored Name </l>
          <l>The City bounds transcend not in their place, </l>
          <l>And their word makes e'm prosper, <hi>God grant grace</hi>. </l>
          <l>Honor they neuer wanted, when was't seene </l>
          <l>But they had Senators to their Bretheren </l>
          <l>Nay, one record here to make ioy more glad, </l>
          <l>I finde seuenteene that were in Scarlet clad </l>
          <l>All at one time of this Fraternitie, </l>
          <l>Now fiue, for this houres honor brings forth three, </l>
          <l>Fame triple will make triple vertue striue </l>
          <l>At whose triumphant Throne you next ariue. </l>
          <p>For farther Illustration there are contained in Antiquities golden Legend, the Names of many Worthies of ancient Time, by whom this Noble Fraternity ha's receiued much honor, such as were the worthy and famous Sir <hi>Andrew Bockerell</hi>, who was Lord Maior of this City, the sixteenth yeere of King Henry the third, and continued in the Magistracie seuen yeeres together, also the Noble <hi>Allen de la Zouch</hi>, who for his good gouernement in the time of his Maioralty, was by King Henry the third, created both a Baron of this Realme, and Lord chiefe Iustice of England. Also that famous Worthy, Sir <hi>Thomas Knowles</hi>, twice Lord Maior of this honorable City, which said Sir Thomas <pb xml:id="ep000195-008-a"/>beganne at his owne charge that famous building of Guild-Hall in London, and other memorable workes both in the City and in his owne Company, Reedifying also Saint Anthonies Church; with many others that are faire Ornaments to Memory. Viz. Sir <hi>William Seuenock</hi>, sir <hi>Robert Chichsley</hi>, sir <hi>Stephen Browne</hi>, sir <hi>Henry Keble</hi>, sir <hi>William Laxton, &amp;c.</hi> Who by those Vertues that they were most addicted vnto in their life-time, are Illustrated by persons of Brightnesse in the <hi>Throne of Vertue</hi>, the next part of Triumph that presents it selfe: next beneath Antiquitie, sits Authoritie, plac'd between Wisedome and Innocence, holding a naked Sword, a Serpent woond about the Blade thereof, two Doues standing vpon the crosse Barre of the Hilt, and two hands meeting at the Pummel, intimating Mercy and Iustice, accompanied with Magistracie, who holdes in his hand a Key of gold, signifying both the Key of Knowledge and of Confidence, the City Magistrate taking into his trust the Custodie of the Kings Chamber, the proper Title of the City; and which Key of gold also stands in his Lordships Crest, viz. an Estridge holding a Key of gold in his Mouth, his Necke circled with a golden Crowne. </p>
          <pb xml:id="ep000195-008-b"/>
          <p>His Lordship by this time arriuing at the <hi>Throne of Vertue</hi>, plac'd neere Saint Laurence-Lane end, Receiues this greeting from her Deitie. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000195-e2060">
          <head>The Speech. </head>
          <l>I See great Power approach; here makes a Stand, </l>
          <l>Would it with Vertue ought? for some Command </l>
          <l>Seemes so compleate in Selfe-Opinions Eye, </l>
          <l>It will scarce looke on me, but passes by; </l>
          <l>As if the Essence of my Deitie </l>
          <l>Were rais'd by Power, and not Power rais'd by me; </l>
          <l>But let such Rulers know that so command </l>
          <l>They build the Empire of their Hopes on Sand&#9642; </l>
          <l>Still This remaines, with Eye vpon me fixt </l>
          <l>As if he sought to haue His splendors mixt </l>
          <l>With these of mine, which makes Authoritie meeke, </l>
          <l>And I'me so ficke of Loue to those that seeke </l>
          <l>I cannot choose but yeeld; nor do's it wrong </l>
          <l>Great Power to come to Vertue to be strong, </l>
          <l>Being but a Woman, mercifull and milde, </l>
          <l>Therein is Heauen with greater glory stilde </l>
          <l>That makes weake things, as Clemencie, and Right, </l>
          <l>Sway Power, which would else rule all by Might: </l>
          <l>It maybe said you did but late passe by </l>
          <l>Some part of Triumph that spake Vertuously, </l>
          <l>And one such Speech suffices; 'tis not so </l>
          <l>In taking of your office, there you goe </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000195-009-a"/>
          <l>From Court to Court, before You be confirm'd </l>
          <l>In this high place, which Praetorship is term'd; </l>
          <l>From Vertue, if to Vertue you resort, </l>
          <l>It is but the same course you haue in Court </l>
          <l>In setling of your Honor; which should bee </l>
          <l>Redoubled rather, that I hope to see: </l>
          <l>So Power and Vertue when they fill one Seate, </l>
          <l>The City's blest, the Magistrate compleate. </l>
          <p>At the close of the Speech, this <hi>Throne of Vertue </hi>with all her Caelestiall Concomitants, and the other parts of the Triumph, take leaue of his Lordship for that time, and till after the Feast at Guild-Hall rests from Seruice; but the Feast ended, the whole state of the Triumph attends vpon his Lordship, both to Saint Paules and homeward; and in Soper-Lane two parts of the Triumph stand ready planted; viz. the <hi>Throne of Vertue</hi>, and the <hi>Globe of Honor</hi>, which Globe suddenly opening and flying into eight Cants or distinct parts, discouers in a twinckling, eight bright Personages most gloriously deckt, representing (as it were) the <hi>Inward Man</hi>, the Intentions of a Vertuous and Worthy Brest, by the Graces of the Minde and Soule, such as <hi>Cleere Conscience, Diuine Speculation, Peace </hi>of <hi>Heart, Integritie, Watchfulnesse, AEqualitie, Prouidence; Impartialitie, </hi>each exprest by Its proper <pb xml:id="ep000195-009-b"/>Illustration. And because Mans perfection can receiue no constant Attribute in this Life, the Cloude of Frailty, euer and anon shadowing and darkening our brightest Intentions, makes good the Morality of those Cants or Parts, when they fall and close into the full round of a Globe againe, showing, that as the Brightest Day ha's his ouer-castings; so the best men in this life haue their Imperfections; and worldly Mists oftentimes interpose the cleerest Cogitations, and yet that but for a season, turning in the end like the mounting of this Engine, to their euerlasting Brightnesse, conuerting it selfe to a Canopie of Starres: at the foure corners below are plac'd the foure Cardinall Vertues, <hi>Wisedome, Iustice, Fortitude </hi>and Temperance, by each of them fixt a little Streamer or Banner, in which are displayed, the Armes of this Honorable City, the Lord Maiors, the Grocers, and the Noble East-India Companies: The out-parts of the Globe shewing the Worlds Type, in Countries, Seas and Shipping, whereon is depicted or drawne Ships that haue bene fortunate to this Kingdome, by their happy and successefull Voyages; as also that prosperous Plantation in the Colonie of Virginia, and the Bermudaes, with all good wishes to the Gouernors, Traders and Aduenturers vnto those Christianly Reformed Islands. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000195-e2650">
          <pb xml:id="ep000195-010-a"/>
          <head>The Speech at Night, presented by Honor, A Personage mounted on the top of this Vnparalel'd Master-piece of Inuention and Art, the Globe or Orbe of Honor. </head>
          <head type="sub">Honor. </head>
          <l>BY Vertue you came last, and who brings home </l>
          <l>True Honor, must by Vertue alwayes come, </l>
          <l>The right Path you haue tooke then, still proceede, </l>
          <l>For t'is Continuance crownes each worthy Deeds: </l>
          <l>Behold this <hi>Globe of Honor</hi>; euery Part </l>
          <l>It is compos'd of, to a Noble Hart </l>
          <l>Applyes Instruction; when t'is clos'd and round </l>
          <l>It represents the World, and all that's found </l>
          <l>Within the labouring Circle of Mans Dayes, </l>
          <l>Aduentures, Dangers, Cares, and steepie Wayes; </l>
          <l>Which when a Wise-man thinkes on, strait he mounts </l>
          <l>To Heauenly Cogitations, and accounts </l>
          <l>The vexing Spirite of Care and Labour vaine: </l>
          <l>Lifting himselfe to his full height againe: </l>
          <l>And as this Engine do's in eight Parts rise </l>
          <l>Discouering eight Bright Figures, so the Wise </l>
          <l>From this Lifes slumber rowz'd, (which Time deludes,) </l>
          <l>Opens his Heart to eight Beatitudes: </l>
          <l>And as I (Honor) ouertopping All, </l>
          <l>Here fixe my Foote on this Orbicular Ball, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000195-010-b"/>
          <l>Ouer the World expressing my Command </l>
          <l>As I in this Contemptuous Posture stand: </l>
          <l>So euery good and vnderstanding Spirit </l>
          <l>Makes but Vse onely of this Life, t'inherit </l>
          <l>An euerlasting Liuing; making Frends </l>
          <l>Of Mammons Heapes, got by vnrighteous Ends, </l>
          <l>Which happy Thou standst free from, the more white </l>
          <l>Sits Honor on thee, and the Cost more bright </l>
          <l>Thy Noble Brotherhood this Day bestowes; </l>
          <l>Expence is grac'd when Substance follow Showes, </l>
          <l>Now to no higher Pitch of Praise I'le come, </l>
          <l>Loue brought thee forth, and Honor brings thee home. </l>
          <p>FOr the body of the whole Triumph, with all the proper Graces and Ornaments of Art and Workemanship, the Reputation of those, rightly appertaine to the deserts of Master <hi>Garret Crismas</hi>, an Exquisite Master in his Art, and a Performer aboue his Promises. </p>
        </div>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
