<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000186" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Honorable Entertainments</title>
        <author>
<!--Middleton, Thomas-->
          <persName>
            <forename>Thomas</forename>
            <surname>Middleton</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A07502.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="A07502-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull n="TCP source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">Honorable entertainments compos'de for the seruice of this noble cittie. Some of which were fashion'd for the entertainment of the Lords of his Maiesties most Honorable Priuie Councell, vpon the occasion of their late royall employment. Inuented by Thomas Middlevon [sic].</title>
                <author>Middleton, Thomas, d. 1627.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>29 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
                <date>2005 December (TCP phase 1)</date>
                <idno type="marc">99845625</idno>
                <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 17886.</idno>
                <idno type="stc">Greg, II, 369-78.</idno>
                <idno type="vid">10535</idno>
                <idno type="DLPS">A07502</idno>
                <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2240893593</idno>
                <availability>
                  <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
                </availability>
              </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
            <biblFull n="printed source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">Honorable entertainments compos'de for the seruice of this noble cittie. Some of which were fashion'd for the entertainment of the Lords of his Maiesties most Honorable Priuie Councell, vpon the occasion of their late royall employment. Inuented by Thomas Middlevon [sic].</title>
                <author>Middleton, Thomas, d. 1627.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[60] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>By G[eorge] E[ld],</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication_date">1621.</date>
                <date type="creation_date">1621</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>
                  <p>In verse.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Printer's name from STC.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Signatures: A2 B-D E4.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>The last leaf is blank.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
                </note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <person xml:id="ep000186-levity">
            <persName>Levity</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000186-spring">
            <persName>Spring</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000186-temperance">
            <persName>Temperance</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000186-summer">
            <persName>Summer</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000186-winter">
            <persName>Winter</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000186-autumn">
            <persName>Autumn</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000186-all">
            <persName>All</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000186-flora">
            <persName>Flora</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000186-hyacinth">
            <persName>Hyacinth</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000186-unassigned">
            <persName>Unassigned</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000186-both">
            <persName>Both</persName>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1621">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000186-e100030">
        <pb xml:id="ep000186-001-a"/>
        <p>HONORABLE ENTERTAINMENTS, Compos'de for the Seruice of this Noble Cittie. SOME OF WHICH WERE fashion'd for the Entertainment of the Lords of his Maiesties most Honorable Priuie Councell, vpon the Occasion of their late Royall Employment. </p>
        <p>Inuented by Thomas Middleton. </p>
        <p>Imprinted at London by G. E. 1621. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000186-e100070">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000186-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000186-002-b"/>
        <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE </head>
        <p>Sir Francis Ihones, Knight, L. Maior of the Citty of London; the Right Worshipfull, Sir Iohn Garrard, Sir Thomas Bennet, Sir Thomas Lowe, Sir Thomas Middleton, Sir Iohn Iolles, Sir Iohn Leman, Sir George Bolles, Sir William Cokayne, Knights and Aldermen; The truely Generous and Noble, Heneage Finch Esquire, Master Recorder; Master Edward Barkham, Master Alexander Prescot, Master Peter Probye, Master Martin Lumley, Master William Goare, Master Iohn Goare, Master Allen Cotton, Master Cuthbert Hacket, Master William Halliday, Master Robert Iohnson, Master Richard Herne, Master Hugh Hamersley, Master Richard Deane, Master Iames Cambell, Aldermen. </p>
        <p>Sheriffes and Aldermen. <list>
            <item>Master Edward Allen. </item>
            <item>Master Robert Ducye. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>All Brethren-Senators, Presidents of religious, and worthy Actions, Carefull Assistants in the State of so vnmatch'd a Gouernment; And a'l of them being his Worthy and Horable Patrons. </p>
        <closer>T. M. Wisheth the Fulnes of that Honor, whose Obiect is Vertue, and Goodnesse. </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000186-e100150">
        <lg>
          <l>THose Things that haue tooke Ioy (at seuerall Feasts) </l>
          <l>To giue you Entertainment, as the Guests </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000186-003-a"/>
          <l>They held most truely Worthy, become now </l>
          <l>Poore Suiters to be entertaynde by you, </l>
          <l>So were they from the first; their Suite is then, </l>
          <l>Once seruing you, to be receiude agen, </l>
          <l>And You, to aequall Iustice are so true, </l>
          <l>You alwaies cherish that, which honors You. </l>
        </lg>
        <closer>
          <signed>Euer obedient in his Studies, to the Seruice of so compleate a Goodnes. Tho. Middleton. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div n="1" type="entertainment" xml:id="ep000186-e100280">
        <pb xml:id="ep000186-003-b"/>
        <head>HONOVRABLE ENTERTAINMENTS. </head>
        <p>On Monday and Tuesday in Easter weeke, 1620. the first Entertainment, at the house of the right worthy, Sr. William Cokaine then L. Mayor: Which on the Saturday following was fashioned into seruice for the Lords of his Maiesties most Hoble. Priuy Councell; vpon which day, that noble Marriage was celebrated betwixt the Right Hoble. Charles L. Howard Baron of Essingham, and Mary, eldest Daughter of the said St. William Cokaine, then L. Mayor of London, and L. Generall of the Military forces. </p>
        <stage xml:id="ep000186-e100300">One habited like a Gentleman Sewer, bearing in his hand an Artificiall Cocke, conducted by the City Musicke, toward the high Table, a Song giuing notice of his Entrance. </stage>
        <lg>
          <head>
            <pb xml:id="ep000186-004-a"/>SONG. </head>
          <l>ROome, roome, make roome, </l>
          <l>You Friends to Fame, </l>
          <l>Officers of worth and Name, </l>
          <l>Make roome, make roome, </l>
          <l>Behold the Bird of State doth come, </l>
          <l>Make roome, </l>
          <l>Cleere the place, </l>
          <l>O doe it all the grace; </l>
          <l>It is the King of Birds, whose chaunting, </l>
          <l>And early morning Crowing, </l>
          <l>So quicke and strongly flowing, </l>
          <l>Doe's make the King of Beasts lye panting; </l>
          <l>How worthy then to be brought in with Honour, </l>
          <l>That daunts the proudest in that humble manner. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <head>
            <pb xml:id="ep000186-004-b"/>The Speech. </head>
          <l>TWo powers at strife about conceiued wrong, </l>
          <l>To whom this Bird should properly belong, </l>
          <l>Were reconcil'd by Harmony: First, the Sunne </l>
          <l>Cald it his Bird, cause still when day begun </l>
          <l>To ope her modest Eye, this Creature then, </l>
          <l>Proclaimes his glory to the world agen; </l>
          <l>Minerua next, Goddesse of Armes and Art, </l>
          <l>Claymd it for hers (not without iust desert) </l>
          <l>He, like the Morning being the Muses friend, </l>
          <l>And then for courage, 'tis his life, his end; </l>
          <l>Without wrong then those properties related, </l>
          <l>To both, hee may be iustly consecrated: </l>
          <l>But, Worthy Lord, how properly to you, </l>
          <l>Whose place pertakes of both; it is so true </l>
          <l>An Emblem of your worth, charge, power, &amp; state, </l>
          <l>None, Noblier can expresse a Magistrate; </l>
          <l>For all that is in this Bird, Quality, </l>
          <l>Is in you Vertue, Iustice, Industry, </l>
          <l>What do's his early morning note imply? </l>
          <l>But in you, early care and vigilancie; </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000186-005-a"/>
          <l>A Duty that begets Duty to you, </l>
          <l>So Vertue still payes, and receiues her due: </l>
          <l>What do's the striking of his wings import, </l>
          <l>Ere to his Neighbour hee his sounds retort? </l>
          <l>But the deere labours and incessant paines </l>
          <l>Of a iust Magistrate, that e'en constraines </l>
          <l>His Nerues, to giue more Vertue to his word, </l>
          <l>And beate in sense into the most absurd: </l>
          <l>The Sharpest is the easiest to apply, </l>
          <l>For his quicke Spurre, Lawes sword doth signifie; </l>
          <l>The execution of your Charge and Place, </l>
          <l>To cut off all crimes that are bold and base: </l>
          <l>" Vertues should be with kind embraces, heap'd, </l>
          <l>" But with a Sword, Sins haruest must be reap'd. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <head>To the Aldermen. </head>
          <l>My reuerence next to you, to you, that are </l>
          <l>The Fathers of this Citty; by whose care, </l>
          <l>Wisedome &amp; watchfulnes, the good cause thriues, </l>
          <l>You that are Lights and Presidents in Liues, </l>
          <l>Noble Examples, Honours t'age and Time, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000186-005-b"/>
          <l>This is the Top which your good cares must climbe, </l>
          <l>" A ceaslesse labour Vertue hath impos'd, </l>
          <l>" Vpon all those, whom Honour hath enclos'd; </l>
          <l>And such are you, selected from the rest, </l>
          <l>Works then that are most choice become you best; </l>
          <l>Place before all your Actions and Intents, </l>
          <l>The rare gifts of that Bird, this but presents: </l>
          <l>Behold the very shape and Figure, now, </l>
          <l>Serues for a Noble Welcome, turnd into </l>
          <l>A Cup of Bounty, and t'adorne the Feast, </l>
          <l>Loaden with loue comes to each worthy Guest; </l>
          <l>And but obserue the manner, there's in that, </l>
          <l>Freenesse exprest, humility, yet State; </l>
          <l>First you take off his head, to tast his heart, </l>
          <l>Which showes at this time power is laid apart, </l>
          <l>And bounty fils the place; then he goes round; </l>
          <l>To shew a Welcome of an equall Sound, </l>
          <l>To euery one a free one, through the Boord, </l>
          <l>So plaine hee speakes the goodnesse of his Lord, </l>
          <l>Take then respectfull Notice through the Hall, </l>
          <l>That heere the noble Health begins to All. </l>
        </lg>
        <stage xml:id="ep000186-e101080">
          <pb xml:id="ep000186-006-a"/>The Cock-cup then deliuered by this Gentle man Sewer to the L. Mayor, hee beginning the Health, a second Song thus honouring it. </stage>
        <lg>
          <head>2. SONG. </head>
          <l>THe Health's begun, </l>
          <l>In the Bird of the Sun, </l>
          <l>pledge it round pledge it round, </l>
          <l>With hearty welcome it comes crownd, </l>
          <l>O pledge it round: </l>
          <l>The Ceremonies due </l>
          <l>Forget not as they were begun to you, </l>
          <l>When you are dranke to, y'are by duty led, </l>
          <l>First to kisse your hand, then take off the head, </l>
          <l>You cannot misse it then, </l>
          <l>To put it on and kisse it agen; </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <pb xml:id="ep000186-006-b"/>
          <l>The next to whom the Health doth flow, </l>
          <l>It taught to honour your Pledge so, </l>
          <l>So round, round, round, round, let it goe, </l>
          <l>As aboue, so below; </l>
          <l>For Bounty did intend it alwayes so. </l>
        </lg>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="entertainment" xml:id="ep000186-e101270">
        <pb xml:id="ep000186-007-a"/>
        <head>The second Entertainment. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000186-e101280">At Bun-hill, on the Shooting day; Another habited like an Archer did thus greet the L. Mayor and Aldermen after they were placed in their Tent. </stage>
        <lg>
          <l>WHy this is nobly done, to come to grace </l>
          <l>A Sport, so wel becomes the Time &amp; Place, </l>
          <l>Old Time made much on't, &amp; it thought no praise </l>
          <l>Too deere for't, nor no honour in those dayes, </l>
          <l>Not only Kings ordaind Lawes to defend it, </l>
          <l>But shinde the first Examples to commend it, </l>
          <l>In their owne Persons honord it so farre, </l>
          <l>A Land of Peace show'd like a field of Warre; </l>
          <l>But chiefly Henry, (Memories Fame) the Eight, </l>
          <l>And the Sixt Edward; gaue it worth and weight, </l>
          <l>By Act and fauour, (not without desert) </l>
          <l>It being the comliest and the Manliest Art, </l>
          <l>And whereas meaner Crafts took their first forme </l>
          <l>From humble Things, as Twisting from a worme, </l>
          <l>And Weauing from the Spiders limber frame; </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000186-007-b"/>
          <l>Musicke and Archery from Apollo came: </l>
          <l>He cals himself great Maister of this Sport, </l>
          <l>In whose bright name faire Wisedome keepes her Court: </l>
          <l>Well may this Instrument be first in Fame, </l>
          <l>Aboue all others that haue got a Name, </l>
          <l>In war or peace; when Heauen it selfe doth show, </l>
          <l>" The Couenant of Mercy, by a Bow: </l>
          <l>And as each Creature, nay, each sencelesse Thing, </l>
          <l>Is made a Glasse to see Heauens goodnesse in; </l>
          <l>So though this be a meere delight, a Game, </l>
          <l>Iustice may see heere somthing she may claime, </l>
          <l>(Without wrong done to State) and cal't her own, </l>
          <l>Since the greatst power is oft through weakenesse known. </l>
          <l>What are Reproofs? with them I first begin, </l>
          <l>But Arrowes shot against the Brest of Sin; </l>
          <l>Who hits Vice home, &amp; cleaues a wrong in twaine, </l>
          <l>So that it neuer comes to close againe, </l>
          <l>Shewes not he noble Archery? Ile pray euer, </l>
          <l>He may be followed, mended he can neuer: </l>
          <l>And as a cunning Bowman markes his ground, </l>
          <l>And from light things (which being tost vp) is found </l>
          <l>Where the winde sits (for his aduantage best) </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000186-008-a"/>
          <l>Before he let his Arrow passe his Brest; </l>
          <l>So the graue Magistrate, discreetly wise, </l>
          <l>Makes vse of light occasions that arise, </l>
          <l>To lead him on to weightier, windes a Cause, </l>
          <l>From things but weakly told, much substance draws </l>
          <l>And will the state of Truth exactly trye, </l>
          <l>Before he let the Shaft of Iudgement flie: </l>
          <l>Then in this Art, there's Vertue still exprest, </l>
          <l>For euery man desires heere to be Best, </l>
          <l>Their Ayme is still Perfection, to outreach, </l>
          <l>And goe beyond each other; which do's teach </l>
          <l>A Noble Strife in our more serious Deeds, </l>
          <l>Assuring Glory to him best exceeds: </l>
          <l>And where some sports seek corners for their shame </l>
          <l>Day-light and open Place, commends this Game; </l>
          <l>Much like an Honest Cause, it appeares Bold </l>
          <l>In publicke Court, for all Eyes to behold; </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <head>To the Archers. </head>
          <l>On then, Apolloes Scholers, You ne're found </l>
          <l>Nobler Spectators compast in this Ground; </l>
          <l>To whom I wish (worthy their Vertuous Wayes) </l>
          <l>Peace to their Hearts, long Health, &amp; Blessed daies. </l>
        </lg>
        <div type="part" xml:id="ep000186-e101890">
          <pb xml:id="ep000186-008-b"/>
          <head>Vpon the renewing of that worthy and laudable Custome of Uisiting the Springs and Conduite Heads, for the Sweetnesse and Health of the City. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000186-e101900">A Uisitation long discontinued. A Water-Nimph, seeming to rize out of the Ground by the Conduit Head, neare the Banquetting-House, thus greets the Honourable Assembly. </stage>
          <lg>
            <l>HAh? let me cleare mine Eyes, me thinks I see </l>
            <l>Comforts approach, as if They came to me; </l>
            <l>I am not vsde to e'm; I ha beene long without, </l>
            <l>How comes the Vertue of the Times about? </l>
            <l>Ha's Ancient Custome yet a Friend? of Weight? </l>
            <l>So many? rare I Goodnesse is wak't alate </l>
            <l>Out of her long Sleepe sure; that ha's laine still </l>
            <l>Many a deere Day, charm'd with Neglect and Will, </l>
            <l>I thought I'de beene forsaken, quite forsooke, </l>
            <l>For none these 7. yeares, ha's bestow'd a Looke </l>
            <l>Vpon my watry Habitation here; </l>
            <l>I meane, of Power, that ought to see Me cleere, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000186-009-a"/>
            <l>For yon'd faire Cities health, which Sweetnes blesse </l>
            <l>And Vertue in full Strength, euer possesse; </l>
            <l>Well fare thy Visitation, Noble Lord, </l>
            <l>And this most Graue Assembly; that accord </l>
            <l>In wayes of Charity and Care with Thee; </l>
            <l>Ioyes visit You, as Your Loues visit Me: </l>
            <l>The Water stands so full now in mine Eyes </l>
            <l>I cannot chuse but weepe; but the Teares rise </l>
            <l>From Gladnesse, not from Sorrow, for that's lost </l>
            <l>Now I see you, Vnkindnesse yet ha's cost </l>
            <l>Many a deere Drop, since I beheld the Face </l>
            <l>Of the last Magistrate, in Power and Place; </l>
            <l>I h'a done good Seruice; t'is no boasting part </l>
            <l>In one forgot, to speake her owne desert: </l>
            <l>I grant my kind and louing Sisters both </l>
            <l>Chadwell and Amwell, haue exprest no Sloth </l>
            <l>In their Pipe-Pilgrimage, but fairely proou'd </l>
            <l>Most excellent Seruants, hous'de, and welbelou'd; </l>
            <l>And haue, when hard Necessity requires, </l>
            <l>Giuen happy Quench to many mercilesse Fires; </l>
            <l>Therefore am I neglected? An old Friend? </l>
            <l>The Head? that to the Heart a'th City send </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000186-009-b"/>
            <l>My best and cleerest Seruice, take Delight </l>
            <l>To be at hand, make your Dames Pure and White; </l>
            <l>Who for their ciuill Neatnesse, are proclaim'd </l>
            <l>Mirrours of women, through all Kingdoms fam'd; </l>
            <l>Can I be so forgot? and daily heare </l>
            <l>The noise of Water-bearers din your care? </l>
            <l>Those are my Almes folkes, trotting in a Ring, </l>
            <l>And liue vpon the bounty of my Spring, </l>
            <l>Yet like dull wormes that haue no sence at all, </l>
            <l>Lick vp the Dewes, ne're look from whence they fal, </l>
            <l>The head's not minded, whence the goodnes flows: </l>
            <l>So with the worlds condition right it goes; </l>
            <l>" Blessings are swallowed with a greedy loue, </l>
            <l>" But Thanks flye slowly to yon'd place Aboue, </l>
            <l>From whence the Euerliuing Waters spring, </l>
            <l>Which to your soules eternall comforts bring: </l>
            <l>The Dewes of Heauen fal on you, prosperous Fates </l>
            <l>Like fruitfull Riuers, flow into your States. </l>
          </lg>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="ep000186-e102440">
          <pb xml:id="ep000186-010-a"/>
          <head>Vpon discontinuance, and to excite them to practise. A Speech intended for the generall Training, being appointed for the Tuesday next ensuing the Visitation of the Springs, but vppon some occasion, the Day deferred. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000186-e102450">Pallas on Horsebacke, on her Helmet the figure of a Cocke, her proper Crest, thus should haue greeted the L. Generall the L. Mayor Sir William Cokaine, at his entrance into the Field, the worthy Colonels, the right Generous Mr: Alderman Hamersley, President of the Noble Councell of Warre, for the Martiall Garden; the Captaines, &amp;c. </stage>
          <lg>
            <l>WHy here's my wish, the Ioy I liue vpon, </l>
            <l>Wisedome and Valour when both meet in one, </l>
            <l>Now tis a Field of Honor, Fames true Sphere, </l>
            <l>Me thinks I could eternally dwell here; </l>
            <l>Why here's perfection, tis a place for me, </l>
            <l>Pallas delights in such community; </l>
            <l>This Bird of Courage, (Enemy to Feare) </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000186-010-b"/>
            <l>Whose Figure on my Helmet now I weare, </l>
            <l>And haue done euer from my Birth in Heauen </l>
            <l>Is consecrate to Me, as to Thee giuen, </l>
            <l>Our Crest's alike, and fits both warre and peace, </l>
            <l>The Vertues are, Valour and Watchfulnesse, </l>
            <l>And both shine cleare now in thy present State, </l>
            <l>Field-Generall, and City-Magistrate: </l>
            <l>As I from Arts and Armes deriue my name; </l>
            <l>So thou suppliest two Offices, with Fame: </l>
            <l>Why here the Ancient Romane Honor dwels, </l>
            <l>A Praetor, Generall; Senators, Colonels; </l>
            <l>Captaines, graue Citizens; so richly inspir'd, </l>
            <l>They can assist in Councell, if requir'd, </l>
            <l>And set Court-Causes in as fayre a Forme, </l>
            <l>As they doe Men, here, without Rage or Storme: </l>
            <l>Lieuetenants, Ensigners, Seriants of Bands, </l>
            <l>Of worthy Citizens the Army stands, </l>
            <l>Each in his place deseruing faire respect; </l>
            <l>I can complaine of nothing but Neglect, </l>
            <l>That such a noble Cities Arm'd Defence </l>
            <l>Should be so seldome seene; I could dispence </l>
            <l>With great occasions, but alasse, whole yeares </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000186-011-a"/>
            <l>To put off exercise, giues cause of feares; </l>
            <l>" In getting wealth all care should not be set, </l>
            <l>" But some, in the defending what you get: </l>
            <l>There's fewe but haue their prouidence so pure, </l>
            <l>(Blest with a faire estate) to make it sure, </l>
            <l>By strength of writings, and in good mens hands </l>
            <l>Putting their Coyne, secur'd by Lifes and Lands, </l>
            <l>This is the common Fort to which all flye, </l>
            <l>Euery man labours for Security; </l>
            <l>But what's all this? (I speake in Truths behalfe) </l>
            <l>If neither Men, City, nor Deeds be safe </l>
            <l>Where's now Security of State? that day, </l>
            <l>When life stands doubtfull of her house of clay; </l>
            <l>A ruine, which neglect of glorious Armes </l>
            <l>H'as brought on many a Kingdome, rockt with charmes </l>
            <l>Of lazy dulnesse, by vnpractis'd men </l>
            <l>Fit for no seruice; I resolue you then; </l>
            <l>This is Security, if you'le rightly know, </l>
            <l>And do's Secure that Word which you call so: </l>
            <l>Let not a small pecuniary Expence </l>
            <l>(Which is but drossie dotage) keepe you hence, </l>
            <l>You lose all that you saue, after that manner, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000186-011-b"/>
            <l>What i'st to rise in riches, fall in honour? </l>
            <l>Nay to your Safeties to commit selfe-treason, </l>
            <l>Which euery thing prouides for, blest with reason, </l>
            <l>Let this graue Lord's Example, (in its Prime) </l>
            <l>Who perfects all his Actions with his Time, </l>
            <l>Makes euen with the Years, to his faire Fame, </l>
            <l>Giues His Accounts vp with a Glorious Name </l>
            <l>In Field and Court, moue all men to discharge </l>
            <l>Their manly Offices and paines at large; </l>
            <l>Let euery Yeare (at least) once in his Round, </l>
            <l>See you like Sonnes of Honour tread this Ground; </l>
            <l>And Heauen that both giues, &amp; secures iust welth, </l>
            <l>The City blesse with Safety, You with Health. </l>
          </lg>
          <pb xml:id="ep000186-012-a"/>
          <stage xml:id="ep000186-e103110">At the House of Sir William Cokaine; Upon Simon and Iudes day following, being the last great Feast of the Magistrates Yeare, and the expiration of his Pretorship. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000186-e103120">One attir'd like a Mourner, enters after a made Dish like a Herse, stuck with sable Bannerets, Drums and Trumpets expressing a mournfull Seruice. </stage>
          <lg>
            <head>
              <pb xml:id="ep000186-012-b"/>The Speech. </head>
            <l>IMagine now, each apprehensiue Guest </l>
            <l>The Yeare departed; this his Funerall Feast, </l>
            <l>I, a chiefe Mourner, this a sad Pageant, here, </l>
            <l>Set with the Orphans Sigh, the Widowes Teare, </l>
            <l>All seeme to mourne, as lockt from their reliefes, </l>
            <l>Till the New Sun of Iustice dry their griefes; </l>
            <l>And as there is no Glorious thing that ends, </l>
            <l>But leaues a Fame behind it, that commends </l>
            <l>Or disapproues the Progresse of his Acts: </l>
            <l>So in this Epitaph, sad Truth contracts </l>
            <l>A spacious Story, which spread forth at large, </l>
            <l>Might instruct All, built vp for Power &amp; Charge </l>
          </lg>
          <list>
            <pb xml:id="ep000186-013-a"/>
            <head>The Last Will and Testament of 162. finishing for the City. </head>
            <item>Inprimis, I Annus 620. do bequeath to my Succcessor 21. all my good wishes, paines, labours and reformations, to bee nobly perfected by his endeuours and diligence. </item>
            <item>Item, I make Iustice my Executor, and Wisedome my Ouerseer, which is, that Honorable Court which neuer failed yet to see Iustice performed. </item>
            <item>Item, I giue and bequeath to all the Officers, for Legacies; Truth, Temperance, Example of Humility and Gentlenesse. </item>
            <item>Lastly, I bequeath to the whole Body of the beloued Commonalty, three inestimable Iewels, Loue, Mecknesse and Loyaltie; which are alwaies the forerunners of a blessed prosperity; which heauen grant they may euerlasting enioy. </item>
          </list>
          <lg>
            <head>
              <pb xml:id="ep000186-013-b"/>The Epitaph. </head>
            <l>HEre ends a Yeare that neuer mispent day, </l>
            <l>Throgh Fames celestial Signes made his own way, </l>
            <l>By discrete iudgement all his time still led, </l>
            <l>Which is the onely Signe gouernes the Head, </l>
            <l>Mercy to wants, and Bounty to Desert, </l>
            <l>The speciall Signe that rules the noble Heart, </l>
            <l>A Yeare of goodnesse, and a Yeare of right, </l>
            <l>In which the honest cause sued with delight. </l>
            <l>A Yeare wherein nothing that's good, was dull, </l>
            <l>Began at Moones Encrease, and ends at Full; </l>
            <l>Full cup, full welcome: adding the Suns gift, </l>
            <l>Who nearer his declining, the more swift </l>
            <l>In his illustrious course, more bright, more cleere, </l>
            <l>Such is the glorious setting of this Yeare, </l>
            <l>His beamy substance shines e'ne through his shroud </l>
            <l>As the faire Sun shoots splendor through his cloud; </l>
            <l>May euery Yeare succeeding this, still haue </l>
            <l>No worse an Epitaph to decke his Graue, </l>
            <l>And so my last farewell (this Teare for me) </l>
            <l>Wishing that many may conclude like Thee. </l>
          </lg>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="ep000186-e103520">
          <pb xml:id="ep000186-014-a"/>
          <head>At the House of the Right Honorable Sir Francis Ihones. </head>
          <p>The property, to which this Speech especially hath Respect, was a deuice like a made Dish, expressing Two naked Armes breaking through a Cloud, supporting a wreath of Lawrell, being part of the Haberdashers Armes. </p>
          <p>The First Entertainement, at his first Great Feast praeparde to giue Welcome to his Owne Noble Fraternitie, the Company of Haberdashers. </p>
          <lg>
            <head>
              <pb xml:id="ep000186-014-b"/>The Speech presented by a seruant to Comus, the great Sir of Feasts. </head>
            <l>FRee Loue, full welcome, bounty fayre, &amp; cleere, </l>
            <l>E'en as it flowes from Heauen, inhabit here, </l>
            <l>And with your Liberall Vertues blesse the yeare, </l>
            <l>Make this thy Pallace thou smooth youth of Feasts, </l>
            <l>Comus! and put Ioy into all the Guests, </l>
            <l>That they may truely taste in fewest words, </l>
            <l>Th' Abundant welcome yon'd Kind Lord affords, </l>
            <l>Especially to You, aboue the rest, </l>
            <l>Of all most worthy to be First and Best; </l>
            <l>You challenge two Respects, in Brotherhood, one, </l>
            <l>Which had desert enough came it alone, </l>
            <l>Without a second Vertue, but to adde </l>
            <l>Vnto Your Worthinesse, Your Loue was clad </l>
            <l>With Honor, Cost, and Care, and how applide, </l>
            <l>The late triumphant Day best testified, </l>
            <l>Stands in no need of my applause and praise, </l>
            <l>Your Worth can of it selfe, it selfe best raise; </l>
            <l>So much for Noble Action in your Right, </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <pb xml:id="ep000186-015-a"/>
            <l>Which I presume his goodnesse will require: </l>
            <l>Now for Himselfe, (not far to wade or swim) </l>
            <l>I borrow of your Honours to fit him, </l>
            <l>Which both preserues me in my first bounds still, </l>
            <l>And may agree best with his Loue and Will: </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000186-e103800">Here the Property is presented. </stage>
          <lg>
            <l>Behold in this rare Symbole of Renowne, </l>
            <l>The Embleme of all Iustice, and the Crowne </l>
            <l>The faire reward for't, euer fresh and greene; </l>
            <l>Which imitates those Ioyes Eye hath not seene; </l>
            <l>These Armes, that for their nakednesse resemble </l>
            <l>E'en Truth it selfe, no couering, to dissemble, </l>
            <l>Nor shift for Bribe, but open, plaine, and bare, </l>
            <l>Shows, Men of Power should keep their conscience </l>
            <l>And were their Acts transparent, without vaile (faire </l>
            <l>Disguize or Vizard, and such neuer faile; </l>
            <l>Obserue this more, tis not one Arme alone </l>
            <l>That beares this Laurell, but two ioyn'd in one, </l>
            <l>Mercy and Iustice, the two Props of State, </l>
            <l>They must be both fixt in the Magistrate; </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000186-015-b"/>
            <l>If wanting either, subiect to much harme, </l>
            <l>For he that ha's but one, ha's but one Arme; </l>
            <l>Iudge then the Imperfection; marke agen, </l>
            <l>They breake both through a Cloud; which instructs Men </l>
            <l>How they should place their Reuerence and their Loue, </l>
            <l>Seeing all lawfull power, comes from Aboue; </l>
            <l>And as the Laurell (which is now your due) </l>
            <l>Bring due to Honour, therefore most to you, </l>
            <l>Feares no iniurious Weather the Yeare brings, </l>
            <l>But spite of Storms looks euer greene and springs, </l>
            <l>Apolloes Tree, which Lightnings neuer blast, </l>
            <l>So (Honor'd Lord) should burning Malice cast, </l>
            <l>Her pitchy Fires at your Triumphant State; </l>
            <l>You are Apolloes Tree, a (Magistrate,) </l>
            <l>Which no foule Gust of Enuy can offend, </l>
            <l>Nor may it euer to your Lordships End, </l>
            <l>Health and a Noble Courage blesse your Dayes; </l>
            <l>To this your worthy Brotherhood, fame and praise </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="ep000186-e104140">
            <pb xml:id="ep000186-016-a"/>Leuity, a person attired sutable to her condition, from a Window, vnexpectedly thus greets the Assembly in the midst of the Feast. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000186-e104150">At the house of the Right Honorable Sir Francis Ihones L. Mayor, For the Celebration of the Ioyfull Feast of Christmas last. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000186-levity" xml:id="ep000186-e104160">
            <speaker>Leu. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>WHy well said, thus should Christmas be </l>
              <l>Lightsome, Iocond, blithe and free, </l>
              <l>Now it lookes like Bounties Pallace, </l>
              <l>Where euery Cup ha's his full Ballace, </l>
              <l>Drowne Cares with Iuice that Grapes haue bled, </l>
              <l>And make Times cheeke looke fresh and red, </l>
              <l>Let nothing now but Healths goe round, </l>
              <l>And no sooner off, but crown'd </l>
              <l>With sparkling Liquors, bounding vp, </l>
              <l>Quicke in Pallet, as in Cup: </l>
              <l>To be heauy, to be dull, </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000186-016-b"/>
              <l>Is a fault so pittifull, </l>
              <l>We bar it from the course of Reason, </l>
              <l>Care must not peep abroad this Season, </l>
              <l>Nor a sad looke dare appeare </l>
              <l>Within ten Mile of Christmas cheere; </l>
              <l>Sighes are banisht ten leagues farder, </l>
              <l>Either Cellar, Hall or Larder; </l>
              <l>To be Iouiall then and blithe </l>
              <l>Is truely to pay (Christmas) Tithe, </l>
              <l>And where free Mirth is and impartiall, </l>
              <l>Christmas there h'as made me Marshiall. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000186-e104400">
            <pb xml:id="ep000186-017-a"/>Seuerity, from an opposite window, as vnexpectedly reproues her. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000186-spring" xml:id="ep000186-e104410">
            <speaker>Seu. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Why how now? know you where you are? rude thing; </l>
              <l>Bold and vnmanner'd Licence, dare you bring </l>
              <l>Your free Speech hither, before me begin? </l>
              <l>Who let this Skittish thing of Lightnesse in? </l>
              <l>Some call the Porter hither, yet stay, stay, </l>
              <l>I'ue power in words to chase this toy away; </l>
              <l>I wonder that the Musique suffers thee </l>
              <l>To come into their roome? </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-levity" xml:id="ep000186-e104510">
            <speaker>Leu. </speaker>
            <p>Why Nicety? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-spring" xml:id="ep000186-e104530">
            <speaker>Seu. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Beleeue me honest Me( what e're you be) </l>
              <l>She's able to spoyle all your Harmony, </l>
              <l>Corrupt your ayres with Lightnesse. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-levity" xml:id="ep000186-e104580">
            <speaker>Leu. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Oh fie, fie, </l>
              <l>How ill you blaze my Coate, Seuerity? </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-spring" xml:id="ep000186-e104620">
            <speaker>Seu. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Is this a place for you? can Lightnesse here </l>
              <l>Vnder the Hazard of her Shame appeare? </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000186-017-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000186-levity" xml:id="ep000186-e104660">
            <speaker>Leu. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Why thou dull lumpish Thing, void of all fashion, </l>
              <l>Mirths poyson, Enemy to Recreation, </l>
              <l>Thou Melancholly wretch, so fil'd with spite </l>
              <l>Thou eat'st thy heart, when others take delight, </l>
              <l>I must be merry, tis my nature— </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-spring" xml:id="ep000186-e104730">
            <speaker>Seu. </speaker>
            <p>Foole. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-levity" xml:id="ep000186-e104750">
            <speaker>Leu. </speaker>
            <p>Dull dogbolt. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-spring" xml:id="ep000186-e104770">
            <speaker>Seu. </speaker>
            <p>Skit. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000186-e104790">Enter below, Temperance. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000186-temperance" xml:id="ep000186-e104800">
            <speaker>Temp. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>What? this a Scolding Schoole, </l>
              <l>How now? so hie got? and so lowd withall? </l>
              <l>Whose doing was't plac'st you two there to braule? </l>
              <l>Pray marke the Assembly, looke vppon e'm well, </l>
              <l>Thinke where you are, and let that rude thought quell </l>
              <l>Your vnbeseeming difference, tis not heere </l>
              <l>As at a Pit, here's Reuerence, Worth, and Feare. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-levity" xml:id="ep000186-e104890">
            <speaker>Leu. </speaker>
            <p>She sayes this place and season suites not me. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-temperance" xml:id="ep000186-e104910">
            <speaker>Temp. </speaker>
            <p>She sayes but right in that, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-spring" xml:id="ep000186-e104930">
            <speaker>Seu. </speaker>
            <p>O Leuity, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-temperance" xml:id="ep000186-e104950">
            <speaker>Temp. </speaker>
            <p>No, nor you neither, </p>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000186-018-a"/>
          <sp who="#ep000186-levity" xml:id="ep000186-e104970">
            <speaker>Leu. </speaker>
            <p>You may be gon too, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-temperance" xml:id="ep000186-e104990">
            <speaker>Temp. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Y'are Both Extreames, therefore no place for you, </l>
              <l>Lightnes becomes not, nor Seuerity, </l>
              <l>It must me betweene both, and I am Shee, </l>
              <l>Too Light, is bad, and too Seuere as Vilde, </l>
              <l>But both well temperd, makes the mixture milde, </l>
              <l>As I stand now betweene you, so it makes </l>
              <l>A perfect Vertue vp, when it pertakes </l>
              <l>Of each, and comes no neerer then I doo, </l>
              <l>And Vertue made, We haue no neede of you, </l>
              <l>Vanish, be gon. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-spring" xml:id="ep000186-e105110">
            <speaker>Seu. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>I giue glace willingly </l>
              <l>To You, but not to Her. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000186-e105150">They giue place. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000186-levity" xml:id="ep000186-e105160">
            <speaker>Leu. </speaker>
            <p>Nor I to Thee, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-temperance" xml:id="ep000186-e105180">
            <speaker>Tem. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>So, Thus things should haue their becomming grace, </l>
              <l>For Temperance fits the Reuerence of this place: </l>
              <l>Graue Senators, in goodnes still encreast! </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000186-018-b"/>
              <l>Long may you Liue to celebrate this Feast, </l>
              <l>This blessed Season of true Ioy compilde </l>
              <l>In which faire Heauen and Man were reconcilde: </l>
              <l>Musique? thou modest Seruant to this place, </l>
              <l>Raise chast Delight, to doe this Season grace. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <floatingText>
            <body>
              <div type="song" xml:id="ep000186-e105300">
                <pb xml:id="ep000186-019-a"/>
                <head>A Song? </head>
                <stage xml:id="ep000186-e105310">Answered at seuerall places, </stage>
                <lg>
                  <l>Eccho! Eccho! by thy loue once to Narcissus, </l>
                  <l>I now coniure thee not to misse vs, </l>
                  <l>But make thy Sound </l>
                  <l>Vppon the Woods rebound </l>
                  <l>And Mountains— Ecch: And mountaines, </l>
                  <l>And to thy neighbouring Sisters cal,— Sisters cal, </l>
                  <l>Log'd in Caue or hollow Wall </l>
                  <l>And those resounding neere faire Fountaines </l>
                  <l>Ecch: Neere faire Fountaines, </l>
                  <l>Let e'm call to one another— To one another </l>
                  <l>— one another— </l>
                  <l>And one Sister rayse vp tother </l>
                  <l>Ecch.— vp tother— </l>
                  <l>Let it goe from me to you— From me to you </l>
                  <l>— Mee— To you, </l>
                  <l>From you to them, be iust and true </l>
                  <l>— Iust and True </l>
                  <pb xml:id="ep000186-019-b"/>
                  <l>Neuer cease your Voyces Flight, </l>
                  <l>Till you raise vp chast Delight </l>
                  <l>—— Vp chast Delight, </l>
                  <l>Delight— Who calls me from my Caue </l>
                  <l>Twas I— Twas I, Twas I; </l>
                  <l>This is no Time in silence now to lye </l>
                  <l>Delight— Who I? </l>
                  <l>O I; </l>
                  <l>This is a Season of all Ioy compilde, </l>
                  <l>In which faire Heauen and Man were reconcilde </l>
                  <l>Ecch— Heauen and Man were reconcilde, </l>
                  <l>each-reconciled, </l>
                  <l>Behold how many a worthy Guest </l>
                  <l>Are met to celebrate this Feast. </l>
                  <l>Delight— I see it plaine, O blame me then, </l>
                  <l>I ne're will showe such Sloth agen; </l>
                  <l>For whose delight am I now raisde? </l>
                  <l>Oh for the Citties! </l>
                  <l>Delight— How? for the Citties? </l>
                  <l>Ecch— For the Citties: </l>
                  <l>Del. To faile a Mistris so renown'd it were a thousand pitties, </l>
                  <pb xml:id="ep000186-020-a"/>
                  <l>Ecch— Thousand pitties. </l>
                  <l>Those are her Honor'd Sonnes you now behold, </l>
                  <l>Del. Heauen blesse them all, with Graces manifold. </l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                  <head>To the Musique. </head>
                  <l>Temp. So! </l>
                  <l>Tis thankfully accepted, y'haue exprest, </l>
                  <l>Your seruice well and fully to this Feast: </l>
                  <l>Adorn'd and honor'd in each happy part, </l>
                  <l>With those most reuerend Patrons to Desert: </l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                  <head>The Close! </head>
                  <l>Ioy neuer faile your meetings, good successe </l>
                  <l>All your Endeuours, and your Fortunes blesse, </l>
                  <l>Gladnes of heart dwell euer in your Brests, </l>
                  <l>And Peace of faire Workes bring you glorious Rests. </l>
                </lg>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="ep000186-e105850">
          <pb xml:id="ep000186-020-b"/>
          <head>The Inuention. </head>
          <p>At the House of the Right Honorable SIR Francis Ihones, L. Maior. For the solemne feast of Easter last, vpon the Times of that blessed and laudable Custome of Celebrating the memory of Pious workes in this Cittie, at Saint Mary Spittle. </p>
          <stage xml:id="ep000186-e105870">The foure Seasons of the Yeare, Spring, Summer, Autumne and Winter, In a Song into foure parts diuided, Call vp Flora, the Goddesse of the Spring, who in a Bower, deckt with Artificiall Flowers, appeares vpon the Musicall Inuocation. </stage>
          <floatingText>
            <body>
              <div type="song" xml:id="ep000186-e105900">
                <pb xml:id="ep000186-021-a"/>
                <head>The Song! at seuerall Windowes. </head>
                <sp who="#ep000186-spring" xml:id="ep000186-e105910">
                  <speaker>Spring </speaker>
                  <lg>
                    <l>FLora, Flora! </l>
                    <l>We call thee heere, </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-summer" xml:id="ep000186-e105950">
                  <speaker>Sum. </speaker>
                  <lg>
                    <l>We call thee heere, </l>
                    <l>From forth thy fragrant Bower, </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-spring" xml:id="ep000186-e105990">
                  <speaker>Spri. </speaker>
                  <lg>
                    <l>Thou Queene of euery laughing Flower, </l>
                    <l>Appeare! </l>
                    <l>Appeare to vs, </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-summer" xml:id="ep000186-e106040">
                  <speaker>Sum. </speaker>
                  <lg>
                    <l>To vs appeare: </l>
                    <l>Thou Banquet of the Yeare, </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-spring" xml:id="ep000186-e106080">
                  <speaker>Spri. </speaker>
                  <lg>
                    <l>Or if a Name may be more sweet, more deere. </l>
                    <l>Harke, Summer harke, </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-summer" xml:id="ep000186-e106120">
                  <speaker>Sum. </speaker>
                  <lg>
                    <l>Marke, Autumne, marke, </l>
                    <l>How coughing Winter mournes to see </l>
                    <l>This smiling Houre, </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-winter" xml:id="ep000186-e106170">
                  <speaker>Win. </speaker>
                  <lg>
                    <l>Would it were nipt for me, </l>
                    <l>But soft I feele no such decay </l>
                    <l>But I may liue to kisse faire May, </l>
                    <l>And in the Morne and Euening howers, </l>
                    <l>Leaue my cold sweats vpon the Flowers. </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <pb xml:id="ep000186-021-b"/>
                <sp who="#ep000186-spring" xml:id="ep000186-e106240">
                  <speaker>Spri. </speaker>
                  <p>Alasse poore Mumps, at thy weake power We laugh, </p>
                </sp>
                <stage xml:id="ep000186-e106260">The Sun will rise and take thy cold Kisse off. And now behold. </stage>
                <sp who="#ep000186-winter" xml:id="ep000186-e106270">
                  <speaker>Win. </speaker>
                  <p>— Oh— Oh— O— </p>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-autumn" xml:id="ep000186-e106290">
                  <speaker>Autum. </speaker>
                  <lg>
                    <l>he's strucke cold </l>
                    <l>At Floraes first appearing, </l>
                    <l>Looke, in a Sound, </l>
                    <l>Will drop to'th ground. </l>
                    <l>Helpe, helpe, helpe, he wants your cheering. </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-winter" xml:id="ep000186-e106360">
                  <speaker>Win. </speaker>
                  <lg>
                    <l>Oh I confesse </l>
                    <l>Feild Emperesse, </l>
                    <l>The Beauty of thy power amazes, </l>
                    <l>I am content to ioyne </l>
                    <l>With those three Friends of thine, </l>
                    <l>And helpe to chant thy prayses; </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-all" xml:id="ep000186-e106440">
                  <speaker>All. </speaker>
                  <lg>
                    <l>Now all the Seasons of the Yeare agree </l>
                    <l>To giue, (Faire Flora) the prime place to Thee. </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <stage xml:id="ep000186-e106480">
                  <pb xml:id="ep000186-022-a"/>Flora, rising in her Bower, calls forth two of her Seruants. </stage>
                <sp who="#ep000186-flora" xml:id="ep000186-e106490">
                  <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
                  <lg>
                    <l>Where's Hyacinth! the Boy Appollo loude, </l>
                    <l>And turnde into a Flower? </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-hyacinth" xml:id="ep000186-e106530">
                  <speaker>Hy. </speaker>
                  <p>Here, Queene of sweetnes. </p>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-flora" xml:id="ep000186-e106550">
                  <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
                  <lg>
                    <l>Adonis! thou that for thy beauteous chastity, </l>
                    <l>Wert turnde into the chastest of all Flowers, </l>
                    <l>(The closse-infolded Rose) blowen into Blushes </l>
                    <l>It is so mayden-modest, </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-unassigned" xml:id="ep000186-e106610">
                  <speaker>Ad. </speaker>
                  <lg>
                    <l>What's thy pleasure </l>
                    <l>Faire Empresse of sweete Odours, </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-flora" xml:id="ep000186-e106650">
                  <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
                  <lg>
                    <l>Willing Seruants! </l>
                    <l>I haue Employment for you both, and speedy, </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-unassigned" xml:id="ep000186-e106690">
                  <speaker>Beth. </speaker>
                  <p>We waite with much Ioy to receiue the charge on't; </p>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-flora" xml:id="ep000186-e106710">
                  <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
                  <lg>
                    <l>Hast, to the two Assisting Magistrates, </l>
                    <l>Those worthy Citty Consulls, </l>
                    <l>Beare our sweete wishes to e'm, and speake Ioy </l>
                    <l>From vs, to both their Feasts, </l>
                    <l>And to that part of their Graue-worthy Guesse </l>
                    <pb xml:id="ep000186-022-b"/>
                    <l>Which here we misse to day, though here be those </l>
                    <l>Whom we ought more especially to Honor, </l>
                    <l>Say though we cannot there our selfe appeare, </l>
                    <l>Because we owe our greater seruice here, </l>
                    <l>Yet that they shal not faile of all their due, </l>
                    <l>We send the wishes of our Heart by you. </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-hyacinth" xml:id="ep000186-e106840">
                  <speaker>Hy. </speaker>
                  <p>Which shall be faithfully tendred, </p>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-flora" xml:id="ep000186-e106860">
                  <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
                  <lg>
                    <l>Tis presum'd; </l>
                    <l>But to this faire Assembly present now </l>
                    <l>I, and these yeelding Sweets all their heads bow </l>
                    <l>In honour of this Feast, of the Day, chiefe, </l>
                    <l>Made solemne by the workes of your Reliefe, </l>
                    <l>Your Cares, your Charities, the holy Vse </l>
                    <l>Of pious exercise; all which infuse </l>
                    <l>Blessings into your Fortunes, you abound </l>
                    <l>In temporall things, cause blessed fruits are found </l>
                    <l>Vpon the Stocks you graft on, marke the Encrease; </l>
                    <l>You plant poore Orphans in a ground of Peace, </l>
                    <l>And carefully prouide, when fruit time comes, </l>
                    <l>You gather Heauens Ioyes for't, in infinite Summer; </l>
                    <l>This day you view'd the Garden of those Deeds, </l>
                    <l>That blesse the Founders; and all those succeeds </l>
                    <pb xml:id="ep000186-023-a"/>
                    <l>In Zeale and Imitation; you saw there, </l>
                    <l>Vertues true Paradise, drest with your Care; </l>
                    <l>(Your most religious Care) and those Blew Sets, </l>
                    <l>They are the Cities Bancke of Violets </l>
                    <l>That smels most sweet to Heauen; neuer cease then </l>
                    <l>You worthy Praesidents for Times and Men, </l>
                    <l>Till Charitie spring, (by your Examples giuen) </l>
                    <l>As thick on Earth, as Rewards stand in Heauen; </l>
                    <l>If there were sloth or faintnes tow'ard good works; </l>
                    <l>(As blest be Heauen there is not) Time instructs, </l>
                    <l>The Season of the Yeare, for as the Ground, </l>
                    <l>The heauiest and dul'st Creature can be found, </l>
                    <l>Yet now begins both in her Meades and Bowers </l>
                    <l>To offer vp her Sacrifice, in Flowers, </l>
                    <l>How much more ought that Earth with a Soule blest, </l>
                    <l>Which is of euery of you here possest, </l>
                    <l>To spring forth Workes of Piety and Loue, </l>
                    <l>To gratifie those Dewes fall from Aboue; </l>
                    <l>And as the humblest Flower that euer grew, </l>
                    <l>Ha's not his Sent alone, but Vertue too, </l>
                    <l>Good for Mans griefes; so tis not Mans full Fame </l>
                    <l>To haue a Christian Sauour, or a Name, </l>
                    <pb xml:id="ep000186-023-b"/>
                    <l>An empty voice of Charity and Reliefe, </l>
                    <l>He must apply Ease to his Brothers griefe; </l>
                    <l>“ Faith is the Sent and Odour of the Flower, </l>
                    <l>"But Work's the Vertue, that makes good the power; </l>
                    <l>Tis like the Tincture of those Roabes you weare, </l>
                    <l>In which cleare Vesture you to me appeare </l>
                    <l>Like Borders of faire Roses; and worne hie </l>
                    <l>Vpon the Cities forehead; that rich Dye </l>
                    <l>As it is reuerend, honourable, graue, </l>
                    <l>So it is pretious, wholesome; which doth craue </l>
                    <l>A double Vertue at the Wearers hands, </l>
                    <l>Iustice and Mercy; by which goodnesse stands: </l>
                    <l>Thus Honour still claimes Vertue for his Due, </l>
                    <l>And may both euer lay iust claime to you: </l>
                    <l>What? the foure Seasons of the Yeare struck dumbe? </l>
                    <l>I lookt for a kind Welcome, now Im'e come. </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
          <floatingText>
            <body>
              <div type="song" xml:id="ep000186-e107430">
                <head>2. Song, by the foure Seasons! called the Song of Flowers. </head>
                <sp who="#ep000186-spring" xml:id="ep000186-e107440">
                  <speaker>Spr. </speaker>
                  <lg>
                    <l>WElcome, O welcome, Queene of sweetnes </l>
                    <l>welcome, in the noblest manner, </l>
                    <pb xml:id="ep000186-024-a"/>
                    <l>With all thy Flowers, thy sweete breath't Maides of Honour; </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-summer" xml:id="ep000186-e107490">
                  <speaker>Sum. </speaker>
                  <p>Flower gentle! I begin with Thee, </p>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-autumn" xml:id="ep000186-e107510">
                  <speaker>Aut. </speaker>
                  <p>Fayre Flower of Chrystall! that's for me, </p>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-spring" xml:id="ep000186-e107530">
                  <speaker>Spr. </speaker>
                  <p>Apples of Loue! there sweetnesse dwels; </p>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-winter" xml:id="ep000186-e107550">
                  <speaker>Win. </speaker>
                  <p>Puh, giue me Canterbury Bels; </p>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-spring" xml:id="ep000186-e107570">
                  <speaker>Spr. </speaker>
                  <p>Faire double-Gold cups, griefes expelling, </p>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-summer" xml:id="ep000186-e107590">
                  <speaker>Sum. </speaker>
                  <p>Agnus Castus, all excelling, </p>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-autumn" xml:id="ep000186-e107610">
                  <speaker>Aut. </speaker>
                  <p>Venus Bath! the loueliest pride of Iune, </p>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-winter" xml:id="ep000186-e107630">
                  <speaker>Win. </speaker>
                  <p>Giue me that Flower, cald, Go to bed at noone, </p>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-spring" xml:id="ep000186-e107650">
                  <speaker>Spr. </speaker>
                  <p>Blessed Thistle, fam'd for good, </p>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-summer" xml:id="ep000186-e107670">
                  <speaker>Sum. </speaker>
                  <p>Shepheards Pouch, for stanching blood, </p>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-autumn" xml:id="ep000186-e107690">
                  <speaker>Aut. </speaker>
                  <p>Faire yallow Knight-wort, for a foule relapse, </p>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-winter" xml:id="ep000186-e107710">
                  <speaker>Win. </speaker>
                  <p>And Ladies Mantle, good for Maydens Paps, </p>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-spring" xml:id="ep000186-e107730">
                  <speaker>Spr. </speaker>
                  <lg>
                    <l>Tuft Hyacinth! that crownes the Bower, </l>
                    <l>Cald of some, the Virgins Flower; </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-winter" xml:id="ep000186-e107770">
                  <speaker>Win. </speaker>
                  <lg>
                    <l>Take that for me, more good I feele </l>
                    <l>In Ruffling Robin, and Larkes Heele. </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-spring" xml:id="ep000186-e107810">
                  <speaker>Spr. </speaker>
                  <lg>
                    <l>There is a Sweete, Vnnamed yet, </l>
                    <l>The root is white, the Marke of pure Delight, </l>
                    <pb xml:id="ep000186-024-b"/>
                    <l>Bearing his Flowers faire and hie, </l>
                    <l>The colour like a purple Dye: </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-winter" xml:id="ep000186-e107870">
                  <speaker>Win. </speaker>
                  <p>What is the name tis blest withall? </p>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-spring" xml:id="ep000186-e107890">
                  <speaker>Spr. </speaker>
                  <p>Liue-long! it so the Shepheards call; </p>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-winter" xml:id="ep000186-e107910">
                  <speaker>Win. </speaker>
                  <lg>
                    <l>Liue-long? tis Vertues promis'd Due </l>
                    <l>And may it Long remaine with You </l>
                    <l>Honor'd Patrons, </l>
                    <l>Vertuous Matrons, </l>
                    <l>Whose Lifes and Acts this City graces, </l>
                    <l>Daily striuing, </l>
                    <l>And reuiuing </l>
                    <l>Workes worthy your renowne and places. </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <sp who="#ep000186-flora" xml:id="ep000186-e108010">
                  <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
                  <lg>
                    <l>So ya're confirm'd; from your harmonious Closes </l>
                    <l>May Sweetnesse drop, as Hony-Dew from Roses, </l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage xml:id="ep000186-e108050">Then turning, to the Lord Mayor and Aldermen. </stage>
                  <lg>
                    <l>A blessed Health possesse you, and a long, </l>
                    <l>That in this latter Spring of your graue yeares, </l>
                    <pb xml:id="ep000186-025-a"/>
                    <l>You may be greene in Vertues, and grow strong </l>
                    <l>In works of Grace, which soules to Heauen endeers; </l>
                    <l>your good Cares, here, Iustice, and well spent houres </l>
                    <l>Crowne you hereafter with eternall Flowers. </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
          <stage xml:id="ep000186-e108130">Hyacinth, and Adonis, sent forth by Flora, to the 2. other Feasts, thus sets off their Employments. </stage>
          <lg>
            <l>THe goddesse Flora, Empresse of the Spring, </l>
            <l>Chusing (this Feast) her Flowry Soiourning, </l>
            <l>Vnder the Roofe of the chiefe Magistrate, </l>
            <l>Whose power layes iust claime to the greatest state, </l>
            <l>Hath sent me forth, not meanest in her Grace, </l>
            <l>To breath forth her sweet wishes to this place; </l>
            <l>First to the Master of this bounteous Feast, </l>
            <l>To speake her ioy; next, to each worthy Guest; </l>
            <l>And though she cannot now her Selfe appeare, </l>
            <l>Because she owes her greater Seruice there, </l>
            <l>Yer her Hearts Loue to euery one I bring, </l>
            <l>To whom sh'as sent a Present of the Spring. </l>
            <l>Then fals into the former speech of Flora, making </l>
            <l>Use of her diuine instructions. </l>
          </lg>
          <pb xml:id="ep000186-025-b"/>
          <p>Here followes the worthy and Noble Entertainments of the Lords of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuy Councell; at the Houses of the Lord Mayor, and Sheriffes. </p>
          <p>The first Entertainment vpon Thursday in Easter weeke beeing the fift of Aprill, 1621. And vpon the sixeteenth of the same Month those Persons of Honor receiued their second Noble welcome, in a free and Generous Entertainment, at the house of the Right Worshipfull, Mr. Sheriffe Allen; Flora the Person vsed before, thus prepared for them. </p>
          <p>Flo. </p>
          <lg>
            <l>AM I so happy to be blest agen? </l>
            <l>With These! the choice of many thousand </l>
            <l>For Royall Trust selected, and a Care </l>
            <l>That makes you Sacred; may the world compare men, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000186-026-a"/>
            <l>A Confidence with yours? from so compleate </l>
            <l>And excellent a Master? Or so great </l>
            <l>And free a Loue can any Nation showe </l>
            <l>In Subiect to the Soueraigne, then doth flow </l>
            <l>From this most thankfull Citty? Waues of Loue </l>
            <l>Ee'n ouerwhelme each other, as they moue, </l>
            <l>All striuing to be first, they runne in one </l>
            <l>To'th Oceans Brest! (the Kings Affection.) </l>
            <l>And you of Honor! that doe oft appeare </l>
            <l>In presence of a Maiesty so cleere, </l>
            <l>So mighty in Heauens blessings, be so kind </l>
            <l>To grace with Words what He shall euer find, </l>
            <l>And tis a glorious Truth, and well beseemes </l>
            <l>Places and Persons of your faire Esteemes, </l>
            <l>Not all the Kingdomes of the Earth, containe </l>
            <l>A Citty freer to her Soueraigne, </l>
            <l>More faithfull, and more carefull; obserue here </l>
            <l>His Highnes excellent Tryall; Loue and Feare </l>
            <l>Make vp a Subiects duty, to his King, </l>
            <l>As Iustice and sweete Mercy makes vp Him; </l>
            <l>So two fold Uertue two-fold Dutie, cheeres, </l>
            <l>He knew their lones, now came &amp; toucht their fears </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000186-026-b"/>
            <l>To try their Temper, (O blest Heauen) he found </l>
            <l>It was the Feare he lookt for, had it's ground </l>
            <l>Vpon Religion, Reuerence, sweete Respect, </l>
            <l>Loue lookt not Louelier, nor Diuinelier deckt, </l>
            <l>Each reprehensiue word He did impart </l>
            <l>Flewe, and cleaude fast to their obedient Heart, </l>
            <l>Twas fire within their bosome, 'could not rest, </l>
            <l>Till in some serious manner, they'de exprest </l>
            <l>Their duteous Care, with all speede put in Act </l>
            <l>Their Soueraignes sacred pleasure, to coact </l>
            <l>Where manners failde, and force, as with a Pill </l>
            <l>From Humours rude, the Venom of the Ill; </l>
            <l>“ A Kings owne Admonition, against Crimes, </l>
            <l>“ Is Phisicke to the Body of the Times. </l>
            <l>And herein did He Imitate the Highest, </l>
            <l>(To whom it best becomes Him to be nighest) </l>
            <l>To chasten, where he loues, it is the Seale </l>
            <l>Of the Almighties fauour, He doth deale </l>
            <l>So with his Chosen, doe not languish then, </l>
            <l>Thou Prince of Citties, cause the King of Men </l>
            <l>Diuinely did reprooue thee, Know, tis Loue, </l>
            <l>Thou art his Chosen Cittie, and wilt prooue </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000186-027-a"/>
            <l>(As thou hast euer beene) faithfull and free, </l>
            <l>The Chamber of his sweete Security: </l>
            <l>Then in a Health of loy your Hearts expresse, </l>
            <l>Whilst I breath welcome to those Noble Guesse. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <head>The Song of welcome, after which Flora thus Closes the Entertainment. </head>
            <l>A Trust of Honor, and a Noble Care </l>
            <l>Still to discharge that Trust, Keepe your Fames faire, </l>
            <l>You haue proceeded carefully; goe on, </l>
            <l>And a full Praise Crowne your Progression. </l>
          </lg>
          <p>The last Entertainment full as Noble and worthy as the former, vpon the Saturday ensuing, being the 21. of the same Moneth, at the House of the equally Generous and bounteous, the Right Worshipfull, Master Sheriffe Ducy. </p>
          <pb xml:id="ep000186-027-b"/>
          <stage xml:id="ep000186-e108910">Flora, this the third time, in her Bower, beginning to speake, interrupted, by her two Seruants, Hyacinth and Adonis. </stage>
          <sp who="#ep000186-flora" xml:id="ep000186-e108920">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>GOod Heauen </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-hyacinth" xml:id="ep000186-e108940">
            <speaker>Hy. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Fye, this is vsurpation meerely, </l>
              <l>Speake thrice together? there's no right in this: </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-flora" xml:id="ep000186-e108980">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>What's that? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-unassigned" xml:id="ep000186-e109000">
            <speaker>Ado. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>I haue the iuster cause to take exceptions, </l>
              <l>This is the place I seru'd in, lately seru'd in, </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000186-028-a"/>
              <l>And by her own appointment, my wrong's greatest. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-flora" xml:id="ep000186-e109050">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>Here's a strange sudden boldnesse a' both sides a' me, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-hyacinth" xml:id="ep000186-e109070">
            <speaker>Hy. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Was't not sufficient grace for you to speake </l>
              <l>At the chiefe Magistrates house, there, where that Bower </l>
              <l>Was first erected, but to shift your seate </l>
              <l>From place to place, pull downe, and then set vp, </l>
              <l>I wonder how she scapes Informers, trust me. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-unassigned" xml:id="ep000186-e109140">
            <speaker>Ad. </speaker>
            <p>Beleeue me so doe I, sh'as fauour showne her. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-flora" xml:id="ep000186-e109160">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <p>So, this becomes you well, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-hyacinth" xml:id="ep000186-e109180">
            <speaker>Hy. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>There's right in all things, </l>
              <l>We might haue kept our places as we held e'm, </l>
              <l>There's little Conscience in your dealing, thus, </l>
              <l>You might haue left the Lower Bookes for vs, </l>
              <l>For our poore seruice. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-flora" xml:id="ep000186-e109250">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Thus I answere you, </l>
              <l>Taking my President from the iust care </l>
              <l>Of those cleare Lights of Honour, shining faire </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000186-028-b"/>
              <l>To their Workes End; you see before your Eyes </l>
              <l>The Trust that was committed to their wise </l>
              <l>And discreet Powers (for his Highnesse Vse) </l>
              <l>They put not off to others, with excuse </l>
              <l>Of wearinesse, or paines; as they begun, </l>
              <l>In their owne Noble Persons see all done: </l>
              <l>So, by their sweet Example, I that am </l>
              <l>Your Queene and Mistris, and may rightly blame, </l>
              <l>And taxe the boldnesse of your ruder blood, </l>
              <l>I doe not thinke, or hold my selfe too good </l>
              <l>In mine owne Person, to commend their Cares </l>
              <l>That haue so iustly seru'd their King, in Theirs, </l>
              <l>Now you pull in your Heads. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-both" xml:id="ep000186-e109430">
            <speaker>Both. </speaker>
            <p>Pardon sweet Queene. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000186-flora" xml:id="ep000186-e109450">
            <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Yet why should Anger in my brow be seene </l>
              <l>They came but to shew duty to the Time, </l>
              <l>Contention to doe Seruice was their Crime, </l>
              <l>That's no ill looking fault; but 'tis still knowne, </l>
              <l>“They that giue Honour, loue to doe't alone, </l>
              <l>It brookes no Partnership:— To giue this last </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000186-029-a"/>
              <l>Duty her Due, as others before past, </l>
              <l>Though it came now from men of meaner Rancke, </l>
              <l>Where welth was ne're known to oreflow the bank </l>
              <l>Like Spring-Tides of the Rich, that swell more hie, </l>
              <l>Yet tak't for Truth, it comes as cheerefully, </l>
              <l>All smiling Giuers; and well may it come </l>
              <l>With smooth and louing Faces, the small Summe </l>
              <l>That they returne, is thousand times repaide </l>
              <l>In Peace and Safety, besides Soueraigne Ayde </l>
              <l>For each Hearts Grieuance, (to its full content) </l>
              <l>By this high Synode of the Parliament; </l>
              <l>Before whose faire, cleare, and Unbribed Eyes, </l>
              <l>(When it appeares) Corruption sincks and dies, </l>
              <l>Secure Oppression once, comes trembling thither </l>
              <l>(Stead of her hard heart knoks her knees together </l>
              <l>This Benefite is purchas'd, this Reward </l>
              <l>To which all Coyne is drosse to be compar'de: </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <lg>
            <l>But, the faire Workes concluded, on all parts, </l>
            <l>Your Care, which I place first of all deserts, </l>
            <l>And it becomes it, t'as beene nobly Iust, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000186-029-b"/>
            <l>You haue discharg'd with Honor your hie Trust: </l>
            <l>The Cities Loue, I must remember next, </l>
            <l>And faithfull Duty, both deuoutly mixt; </l>
            <l>And (as the State of Court sets last, the Best,) </l>
            <l>His boundlesse Goodnesse, not to be exprest, </l>
            <l>That is your King and Master, Blessings fall </l>
            <l>Vpon His Actions; Honor, on you All. </l>
          </lg>
          <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back></back>
  </text>
</TEI>
