<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000644" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The island princess, or, The generous Portuguese made into an opera, as it is performed at the Theatre Royal / all the musical entertainments and the greatest part of the play new, and written by Mr. Motteux.</title>
        <title>Island princess. Libretto</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Peter</forename>
            <surname>Motteux</surname>
          </persName>
          <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q3382857</idno>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A51499.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <p>
            This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is available for reuse, according to the terms of
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>
            . The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
          </p>
          </availability>
        </bibl>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>The island princess, or, The generous Portuguese made into an opera, as it is performed at the Theatre Royal / all the musical entertainments and the greatest part of the play new, and written by Mr. Motteux.</title>
            <title>Island princess. Libretto</title>
            <author>Motteux, Peter Anthony, 1660-1718.</author>
            <author>Purcell, Daniel, 1660?-1717.</author>
            <author>Fletcher, John, 1579-1625. Island princess.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[9], 47, [1] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed for Richard Wellington ... and sold by Bernard Lintott ...,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1699.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>Adaptation of: The island princess / John Fletcher.</note>
            <note>Without the music (chiefly by Daniel Purcell).</note>
            <note>Advertisements: p. [1] at end.</note>
            <note>Reproduction of original in Folger Library.</note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc/>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="print" when="1699">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000644-e10">
        <pb xml:id="ep000644-001-a"/>
        <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000644-001-b"/>
        <p>THE Island Princess, OR THE Generous Portuguese. Made into an OPERA. As it is performed at the THEATRE ROYAL. </p>
        <p>All the Musical Entertainments and the greatest Part of the Play new, and written by Mr. Motteux. </p>
        <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Richard Wellington</hi>, at the Lute in St. Paul's Church-Yard; and Sold by <hi>Bernard Lintott</hi>, at the Cross-Keys in St. Martins-Lane, next <hi>Long Acre</hi>. 1699. </p>
        <p>A Treatise of Education, especially of Young Gentlemen, by <hi>Obodiah Walker</hi>, D. D. </p>
        <p>Where Gentlemen may pick Novels at 6 s. the Dozen. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000644-e170">
        <pb xml:id="ep000644-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000644-002-b"/>
        <head>To the Honorable POPHAM CONWAY, Esq </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>SIR, </salute>
        </opener>
        <p>A Poetical Dedication is one of those Accidents, I had almost said Diseases, which few persons of extraordinary Merit and Fortune can escape, especially in this Town: soon or late it fixes on the most Conspicuous, and too often defaces the Beauties which it touches. The Apologies that usher in most addresses of this nature, sufficiently show, that they are thought a trouble even by those who presume to make them. It may well then seem strange, that I should own this, and at the same time dare to approach in that very manner a Person for whom I would express the greatest Respect. Yet, Sir, these Considerations, instead of deterring me from the attempt, are perhaps the chief Inducements that embolden me to make it: For You are of too generous and obliging a Temper, and too great a Favourer of the Muses in general, and more particularly of Dramatic Performances, not to be expos'd to the danger of having some of them forc'd upon You, by way of Dedication, beyond a possibility of escaping such a Compliment. Therefore, Sir, I flatter my self with the thoughts of having a better Pretence to do You that civil Violence, than many others, who perhaps wou'd not use You so gently, but wou'd rudely invade Your Character, and put You to more pain than my tender Respect will suffer me to do. For 'tis but too common with some Authors in a manner to dissect their Patrons, and read tedious Lectures over every individual <pb xml:id="ep000644-003-a"/>Qualification. Now, Sir, I am not inclin'd to run into such a Fault: My Zeal may indeed make me afraid of saying too little, but my concern for the satisfaction of the Person to whom I write, makes me still more fearful of being thought guilty of saying too much; if yet too much can ever be said of such merit as seems above the reach of Flattery; Praise is a Tribute due to Vertue and acceptable even to the highest Powers: We offer up our Incense, and they shower down their Blessings. But a vulgar and unskilful hand sometimes prophanes the Rites it would perform, and no common Expressions can illustrate uncommon Desert. Shou'd I say, that where-ever You appear, You captivate the hearts of one Sex, and raise the Envy and Admiration of the other, 'twou'd be but what is universally own'd, tho' no more than what has been said to many: And shou'd I wave Your outward Graces to speak of those Nobler Accomplishments of Your mind that only wait Occasions to signalize Your Life by a Genius peculiar to Your illustrious Family, I could do little more than enumerate the Endowments of the living Ornaments and springing hopes of their Country. For, tho' most men have discernment enough to admire, very few have Capacity to commend. In an extraordinary Subject, I wou'd say something new and worthy of it; but, in so beaten a path as Panegyric, 'tis next to impossible to make Discoveries; and little more than to give a new turn to old Thoughts is what can be done, even by Masters of Wit and Oratory. Thus, Sir, I please my self with the hopes of being the more excusable in not aiming at that Theme; since, after all, the greatest Artists might be reduc'd to speak like the rest of the World that would do Justice to Your <pb xml:id="ep000644-003-b"/>Character. Besides, some shining Truths, as well as Merit set off to advantage, are like those sparkling Diamonds which so much exceed the common magnitude, that they are sometimes suspected of not being what really they are. So blind some People are, not to consider, that a noble Soul looks most like her self in a graceful habitation. Certainly, Sir, had Yours been to have chosen her Dwelling, she cou'd not have pitch'd on one more worthy such a Guest. A transient sight of such Perfections may create Envy, but even that Envy must Convert it self to Esteem and Love upon a nearer view: For that Discretion, that Prudence which secures You from the dangerous Attacks of insinuating Designers, when joyn'd with Your sweetness of Temper, and other Qualifications, must blunt the Darts of the most repining Malice. The Judgment that attends Your kind disposition to oblige, never hinders it from becoming a diffusive Good, and only heightens the Favours You bestow, by Your Modesty in concealing them. Fortune is more oblig'd to You, than You to her. She has been thought one of those noble Prodigals who had rather be lavish of their Gifts than just in the payment of their debts; but we must cease to accuse her of Blindness, when we see how deservedly she has heap'd her Favours on You. May You live to possess 'em long, and those richer Blessings, those native and acquir'd Treasures that so singularly set 'em off; and may You ever believe me to be, what I am ambitious of appearing, </p>
        <closer>
          <salute>SIR, </salute>
          <signed>Your most humble and Most obedient Servant, <hi>Peter Motteux</hi>. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="to_the_reader" xml:id="ep000644-e290">
        <pb xml:id="ep000644-004-a"/>
        <head>To the Reader. </head>
        <p>THO' Mr. Fletcher's Island Princess was frequently Acted of old, and Revived twelve years ago, with some alterations, the Judicious seem satisfy'd, that it wou'd hardly have been relish'd now on the Stage. As I found it not unfit to be made what we here call an Opera, I undertook to revise it, but not as I wou'd have done, had I design'd a correct Play. Let this at once satisfie the Modern Critics, and the Zealous Admirers of Old Plays; for I neither intended to make it regular, nor to keep in all that I lik'd in the Original, but only what I thought fit for my Purpose▪ and the success has answer'd my intent, far beyond Expectation. However, I am not willing to attribute it to my self, but chiefly to the Excellency of the Musical Part. What Mr. <hi>Daniel Purcel </hi>has set is so fine, that as he seems inspir'd with his Brother's wonderful Genius, it cannot but be equally admir'd. The Notes of the Interlude set by Mr. Clarke have air and humour that crown 'em with Applause: And the Dialogue and Enthusiastic Song, which Mr. Leveridge set, are too particularly lik'd not to engage me to thank him for gracing my words with his Composition, as much as for his celebrated singing; Nor must I omit Mr. Pate's admirable Performance, which, with Mr. Leveridge's, gives life to the whole Entertainment. </p>
        <p>I should now say something in answer to two late Books in which the Discourse about the Lawfulness and Vnlawfulness of the Stage, printed before <hi>Beauty in Distress </hi>is examin'd: but I am too much engag'd in other matters to do my Friend and my self that Justice at present. Yet if the doubting Gentleman will be pleas'd to meet the Booksellers and Me, they and I can convince him or any Friend of his that the Discourse was really English'd and sent me by the person mentioned in the Title. </p>
        <p>The Dialogue in the 4th Act, should have been sung in the first Entertainment, which, as well as the last, is not very proper for that place, nor wou'd I have let 'em appear thus but for Reasons as improper to be mention'd here. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="prologue" xml:id="ep000644-e430">
        <head>PROLOGUE </head>
        <byline>
          <hi>Spoken by Mr. </hi>Powell. </byline>
        <sp xml:id="ep000644-e470">
          <l>PRologues, some say, are useless, grave or gay: </l>
          <l>The first but clog, the last ne're save a Play. </l>
          <l>Yet, since for hum'rous Prologues most you long, </l>
          <l>Before this Play we'll have a Ballad sung. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000644-004-b"/>
          <l>This is our Play-wright's Thoughts: But we who know </l>
          <l>The just Respect to mighty Names you show, </l>
          <l>Think fit t' acquaint you, that, 'tis humbly own'd, </l>
          <l>He rais'd his Structure on fam'd Fletcher's Ground. </l>
          <l>This known, we hope we've little now to dread; </l>
          <l>You'll spare the Living, lest you wrong the Dead. </l>
          <l>Perhaps too, when you know we wave our Pay, </l>
          <l>At our own Cost t' adorn these Scenes to day, </l>
          <l>In Pity to the Play'rs, you'll kindly use the Play. </l>
          <l>Left by our Rulers for our selves to strive </l>
          <l>When our faint hopes could scarce be kept alive, </l>
          <l>Tho' by Misfortunes drain'd, we by your Smiles revive. </l>
          <l>Your gen'rous Pity wou'd not let us fall, </l>
          <l>And, in Return, we freely venture all. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e670">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000644-e680">
          <hi>Enter Mr. </hi>Leveridge, <hi>who sings the following words</hi>. </stage>
        <lg n="1">
          <head>1. </head>
          <l>YOu've been with dull Prologues here banter'd so long, </l>
          <l>They signifie nothing, or less than a Song. </l>
          <l>To Sing you a Ballad this time we thought fit; </l>
          <l>For sound has oft nick'd you, when Sense cou'd not hit. </l>
          <l>Then Ladies be kind, </l>
          <l>And Gentlemen mind! <list>
              <item>Wit-Carpers, </item>
              <item>Mobb'd Sinners, </item>
              <item>Play-Sharpers, </item>
              <item>In Pinners, </item>
              <item>Loud Bullies, </item>
              <item>Kept-Toppers, </item>
              <item>Tame Cullies, </item>
              <item>Bench-Hoppers, </item>
              <item>Sowre Grumblers, </item>
              <item>High-Fliers, </item>
              <item>Wench-Bumblers, </item>
              <item>Pit-Plyers, </item>
              <item>Give Ear, ev'ry Man! </item>
              <item>Be still, if you can! </item>
            </list>
          </l>
          <l>You're always in Mischief for leading the Van. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg n="2">
          <head>2. </head>
          <l>Ye Side-box Gallants, whom the Vulgar call Beaux, </l>
          <l>Admirers of— Self, and nice Judges of— Cloaths, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000644-005-a"/>
          <l>Who, now the War's over, cross boldly the Main, </l>
          <l>Yet ne're were at Sieges, unless at Compiegne. </l>
          <l>Spare all, on the Stage, </l>
          <l>Love in every Age. <list>
              <item>Young Tattles, </item>
              <item>Young Graces </item>
              <item>Wild Rattles, </item>
              <item>Black Faces, </item>
              <item>Fan-Tearers, </item>
              <item>Some faded, </item>
              <item>Mask-Fleerers, </item>
              <item>Some jaded, </item>
              <item>Old Coasters, </item>
              <item>Old Mothers, </item>
              <item>Love Boasters, </item>
              <item>And Others, </item>
              <item>Who set up for Truth! </item>
              <item>Who've yet a Colts-Tooth, </item>
            </list>
          </l>
          <l>See us act that in Winter, you'd all act in youth, </l>
        </lg>
        <lg n="3">
          <head>3. </head>
          <l>Ye Gallery haunters, who Love to Lie Snug, </l>
          <l>And munch Apples or Cakes while some Neighbour you hug </l>
          <l>Ye loftier Genteels, who above us all sit, </l>
          <l>And look down with contempt on the Mob in the Pit! </l>
          <l>Here's what you like best, </l>
          <l>Jig, Song, and the rest. <list>
              <item>Free Laughers, </item>
              <item>Sly Spouses </item>
              <item>Close Gaffers, </item>
              <item>With Blowzes, </item>
              <item>Dry Joakers, </item>
              <item>Grave Horners, </item>
              <item>Old Soakers, </item>
              <item>In Corners, </item>
              <item>KindCousins </item>
              <item>Kind No-Wits, </item>
              <item>By Dozens, </item>
              <item>Save-Poets, </item>
              <item>Your Custom don't break! </item>
              <item>Clap till your hands ake; </item>
            </list>
          </l>
          <l>And though the Wits damn us, we'll say the Whims take. </l>
        </lg>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="ep000644-e1440">
        <head>Dramatis Personae. </head>
        <list>
          <item>
            <label>Armusia, A Noble Portuguese, </label>Mr. Powell. </item>
          <item>
            <label>Ruidias, General of the Portuguese in the Spice Islands. </label>Mr. Mills. </item>
          <item>
            <label>Piniero, A Portuguese Officer, his Friend. </label>Mr. Thomas. </item>
          <item>
            <label>King Of Tidore. </label>Mr. Evans. </item>
          <item>
            <label>The Governor, or Tyrant of the Island of Ternate. </label>Mr. Johnson. </item>
          <item>
            <label>King Of Bakam. </label>Mr. Bullock. </item>
          <item>
            <label>Prince Of Syana </label>Mr. Kent. </item>
          <item>
            <label>Quisara, The King of Tidore's Sister. </label>Mrs. Rogers. </item>
          <item>
            <label>Panura, One of her Women. </label>Mrs. Wilkins. </item>
        </list>
        <p>Bramins, Portuguese, Officers, Citizens, Guards and Attendants. </p>
        <p>SCENE the Spice-Islands. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="play" xml:id="ep000644-e1930">
        <pb n="1" xml:id="ep000644-005-b"/>
        <head>The Island Princess. </head>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="ep000644-e1950">
          <head>ACT I. </head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000644-e1970">
            <head>SCENE I. The Entrance to the Temple in the Palace. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e1990">Enter Armusia, Emanuel, Sosa, <hi>and two other </hi>Portuguese Gentlemen. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e2030">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>WE're now in those delicious Eastern Climes </l>
              <l>Where ev'ry Wind diffuses balmy sweets. </l>
              <l>The Treasure of the Sun dwells here; each Tree, </l>
              <l>As if it envy'd the Old Paradice, </l>
              <l>Strives to bring forth Immortal Fruit. The Spices, </l>
              <l>Renewing Nature, can preserve her Beauties </l>
              <l>Untainted in the Grave. The very Rivers as we float along </l>
              <l>Throw up their Pearls. The Earth, still cloth'd in Flow'rs, </l>
              <l>Teems with the Birth of Gemms, and dazzling Riches: </l>
              <l>Nothing that bears a Life but brings a Treasure. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e2150">
              <speaker>Em. </speaker>
              <l>To wander, with us, Sir, you left betimes </l>
              <l>Your Country, tho' the darling of its Court. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e2190">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>We Portuguese with ease now journey thro' the Globe. </l>
              <l>New worlds disclose their Beauties and their Prides to our embraces. </l>
              <l>And we the first of Nations find these wonders. </l>
              <l>But of 'em all, this Island boasts the greatest; </l>
              <l>A Princess whom all Nature's Blessings grace. </l>
              <l>The very Sun, I think, respects her Charms; </l>
              <l>Nor dares affect 'em with the common gloom. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e2290">
              <speaker>Em. </speaker>
              <l>So lately Landed, and already struck! Beware, Armusia! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e2330">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Your Councel comes too late— Let's find the General, </l>
              <l>Our Countryman, Ruidias— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e2380">
              <speaker>So. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis rumour'd, Sir, he loves her. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e2410">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Ha!— Yet I must on, in spight of Reason's Laws, </l>
              <l>He meanly loves, whom fancied distance awes; </l>
              <l>Like a bright Star, she's fix'd and shines on high, </l>
              <l>But Love has wings, and to her Orb I'll fly. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e2470">
              <pb n="2" xml:id="ep000644-006-a"/>Enter Piniero, Christophero. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e2490">
              <speaker>Chri. </speaker>
              <l>You're early here, Piniero. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e2530">
              <speaker>Pini. </speaker>
              <l>Not so early, Sir. </l>
              <l>But I've already seen our Watch reliev'd. </l>
              <l>And bid our Guards be careful of their Charge. </l>
              <l>The Fort is all our strength in these Spice Islands. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e2590">
              <speaker>Chri. </speaker>
              <l>And sure our common safety </l>
              <l>Requires strict watch upon our Treach'rous Neighbours. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e2630">
              <speaker>Pini. </speaker>
              <l>Their late attempt is yet too fresh among us, </l>
              <l>In which against the Laws of Arms and Nations </l>
              <l>The Governor of Ternate seiz'd by stealth </l>
              <l>This Island's Monarch, our confederate King, </l>
              <l>While for Diversion coasting in his Barge. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e2710">
              <speaker>Chri. </speaker>
              <l>His Royal Sister, the admir'd Quisara, </l>
              <l>Has shew'd a noble mind, and tender'st Love </l>
              <l>To her unhappy Brother and the nobler </l>
              <l>Because his Fall wou'd raise her to a Throne. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e2780">
              <speaker>Pini. </speaker>
              <l>Such Charms and Virtue with just admiration </l>
              <l>Have robb'd the Neighbouring Courts, and fill'd her </l>
              <l>Palace with Royal Suiters— </l>
              <l>Our General is in among 'em too, and has the start, 'tis thought. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e2840">
              <speaker>Chri. </speaker>
              <l>But have you seen Armusia, </l>
              <l>The handsome Portuguese arriv'd here lately? </l>
              <l>I fear he'll spoil his game, Piniero. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e2920">
              <speaker>Pini. </speaker>
              <l>A Man of noble Promise, </l>
              <l>Without Reserv'dness Grave, and doubtless Valiant, </l>
              <l>For he that dares come hither dares fight any where. </l>
              <l>But hold— </l>
              <l>We're in the Palace of the Island, </l>
              <l>Not our own Fort. D'ye mark these Preparations? </l>
              <l>Those doors lead to the Temple, where the Princess </l>
              <l>Has summon'd all her Lovers to assemble; </l>
              <l>But to what Purpose we are yet to learn. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e3030">
              <speaker>Chri. </speaker>
              <l>But who are chief? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e3060">
              <speaker>Pini. </speaker>
              <l>That swelling vanity, the King of Bakam. </l>
              <l>The next Syana's Prince; but, what's the greatest wonder, </l>
              <l>The haughty Governor, our Enemy, </l>
              <l>He that surprized the King, to gain the Sister, </l>
              <l>Is under formal Hostages arriv'd.— </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e3150">Enter Armusia, <hi>and his Companions</hi>. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e3180">
              <speaker>Pini. </speaker>
              <l>You're welcome, to Tidore, Sir! </l>
              <pb n="3" xml:id="ep000644-006-b"/>
              <l>Know there is nothing in our power to serve you, </l>
              <l>But you may freely challenge. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e3240">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, we thank you, and rest your Servants. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e3270">
              <speaker>Chri. </speaker>
              <l>Brave Armusia, you never saw this Court before— </l>
              <l>But hark, the Signal's given, and see the Pageants enter. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e3320">
              <hi>Enter the King of </hi>Bakam, Syana, <hi>and Governour with their respective Attendants. </hi>
            </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e3350">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>These sure are Islanders. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e3380">
              <speaker>Pini. </speaker>
              <l>And Princes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e3410">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>What may he be that bears so proud a Port? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e3440">
              <speaker>Pini. </speaker>
              <l>The King of Bakam, Sir, a mere Barbarian— </l>
              <l>This is Syana's Prince— and that the Governour </l>
              <l>Who seiz'd the King, and keeps him Prisoner.— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e3510">
              <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
              <l>Away, ye Trifles; </l>
              <l>Am I in Competition with such Toys! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e3550">
              <speaker>Sy. </speaker>
              <l>You speak loud, Sir. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e3580">
              <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
              <l>Young man, I will speak louder. </l>
              <l>Can any man but I deserve her favour? </l>
              <l>Ye petty Princes! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e3630">
              <speaker>Sy. </speaker>
              <l>Thou proud vain Thing, whom Nature— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e3660">
              <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
              <l>I contemn Thee, and that Fort-keeping Fellow. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e3690">
              <speaker>Go. </speaker>
              <l>Ha! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e3720">
              <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
              <l>Keep thy Rank, Thing, with thy own petty Peers— </l>
              <l>Call out the Princess? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e3760">
              <speaker>Go. </speaker>
              <l>Dost thou know me, Bladder? </l>
              <l>Art thou acquainted with my Nature? </l>
              <l>What can'st thou merit? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e3810">
              <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
              <l>Merit! I'm above it. </l>
              <l>Honour's my Servant, Fortune is my Slave. </l>
              <l>I slight ye, Insects: had not the vain People </l>
              <l>Bestowed some Titles on ye, I shou'd forget your Names. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e3870">
              <speaker>Sy. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, talk less, that men may think you can do more. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e3900">
              <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
              <l>Why, I can talk and do. </l>
              <l>I tell you, only I deserve the Princess, </l>
              <l>And make good, only I, if you dare, you, </l>
              <l>Or you, Syana's Prince.— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e3970">
              <speaker>Sy. </speaker>
              <l>Here lies my Proof. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e4000">
              <speaker>Go. </speaker>
              <l>I'll be short with you. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e4030">
              <hi>The Temple opens, an Altar is discovered, and Priests near it. Enter </hi>Ruidias, Quisara <hi>in state, with her Attendants. </hi>
            </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e4060">
              <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
              <l>For shame forbear, ye Princes; rule your angers: </l>
              <l>You violate the Freedom of this Place, </l>
              <pb n="4" xml:id="ep000644-007-a"/>
              <l>The State and Royalty— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e4110">
              <speaker>Go. </speaker>
              <l>He's well content I see, so I have done. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e4140">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>You wrong me, and my Court, contentious Princes. </l>
              <l>Comes your Love drest in violence to seek us? </l>
              <l>Is't fit our Palace, and this Sacred Place </l>
              <l>Shou'd be polluted with your bloody Rage? </l>
              <l>He that loves me, loves my Commands; be temperate, </l>
              <l>Or be no more what you profess, my Servants. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e4220">
              <speaker>Omn. </speaker>
              <l>We are calm as Peace. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e4250">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>What Command she carries, </l>
              <l>And what a sparkling Majesty flies from her! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e4290">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Since you're for Action, I shall find you danger: </l>
              <l>But not this way: 'Tis not this mean Contention </l>
              <l>Among your selves, nor Courtship to my Face </l>
              <l>Who best can Love, or who can flatter most </l>
              <l>Shall guide my choice; he that will hope my Favour </l>
              <l>Must win me with his merit. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e4370">
              <speaker>Omn. </speaker>
              <l>Propose the way. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e4400">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>First I shall call our Gods to witness what I promise. </l>
              <l>Now give me hearing. 'Tis well known to you, </l>
              <l>The King my Brother is Pris'ner to this Man. </l>
              <l>Were I Ambitious there I'd let him die; </l>
              <l>And wear his Crown; but greatness cannot tempt me </l>
              <l>To forget Nature, and a King's Distress. </l>
              <l>Therefore the Man that wou'd be known my Lover </l>
              <l>Must first redeem my Brother, or seek another Mistress. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e4500">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Divine Creature! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e4530">
              <speaker>Chri. </speaker>
              <l>A dang'rous task; how they stand gazing all! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e4560">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>I grant ye, this will be no easie work, </l>
              <l>But the Reward is certain— Ruidias cold! </l>
              <l>Perhaps you doubt me, Princes. </l>
              <l>He that shall free the King, shall be my Husband. </l>
              <l>By that most bright and Sacred Shrine, I swear, </l>
              <l>Before these Holy Men I here proclaim it. </l>
              <l>No stirring yet? </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e4660">
              <hi>Looks on </hi>Ruidias. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e4680">
              <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
              <l>If, Madam, to attempt this Royal Rescue </l>
              <l>Thro' all forms of Danger </l>
              <l>Might crown your hope, I had not lost this Minute; </l>
              <l>But here, where Conduct must keep Pace with Courage, </l>
              <l>The starting fiery Will is rein'd with Torment </l>
              <l>To Judgment's flower march. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e4760">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Take your own Method. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e4790">
              <pb n="5" xml:id="ep000644-007-b"/>
              <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
              <l>Madam, believe him here. I'll raise an Army, </l>
              <l>Shall bring him to you, Island, Fort and all, </l>
              <l>And fix it here. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e4840">
              <speaker>Sy. </speaker>
              <l>What may be, Madam, </l>
              <l>And what my Pow'r can promise, I engage. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e4880">
              <speaker>Go. </speaker>
              <l>Ha; Ha! </l>
              <l>Madam, their Pow'r and Arts are all too weak, </l>
              <l>'Tis only in my Will to give your Wishes. </l>
              <l>I seiz'd your Brother to secure you mine. </l>
              <l>Then thus the Treaty's finisht! Take your Prisoner, </l>
              <l>And make me yours, close Prisoner to these Arms: </l>
              <l>Say but the word, your Brother shall be render'd quick as your wishes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e4970">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Know, base Ravisher, </l>
              <l>I hate both you, your Country, and your Love. </l>
              <l>Heav'n knows how dear I prize his Liberty; </l>
              <l>But e're I wou'd so basely buy his Freedom, </l>
              <l>I'd study to forget he was my Brother. </l>
              <l>By Force you took him; he that wou'd possess me, </l>
              <l>Must fetch him back by Force, or ne're succeed. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e5060">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Noble Spirit! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e5090">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>Be Wise, and use me better. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e5120">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>I say by Force, and suddenly— so return, Sir; </l>
              <l>And glad we have kept Faith for your safe Passage. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e5160">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>How's this? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e5190">
              <speaker>Pini. </speaker>
              <l>Your hopes are great, good Governor. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e5220">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>Am I then made a Property? </l>
              <l>I'll check this Pride. This neglect of me </l>
              <l>Shall cost your Brother dear. </l>
              <l>For, as till now I've us'd him like a King, </l>
              <l>He now shall in a Dungeon fetter'd lye, </l>
              <l>Darkness and lingring Death for his Companions. </l>
              <l>And let me see who dares attempt his Rescue. </l>
              <l>Farewell: And when you find him thus, lament your scorn. </l>
              <l>Nay, I shall make you kneel to take my Offer. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e5330">Exit Governour▪ </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e5340">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Provoking Insolence! he dares you, Princes. </l>
              <l>Your Honour now's concern'd. Haste, joyn your Powers; </l>
              <l>When Majesty's thus wrong'd all Princes shou'd revenge. </l>
              <l>Oh that I were a Man to lead you on, </l>
              <l>To free a King, and punish that Barbarian, </l>
              <l>That Tyrant, who by treach'rous Force wou'd gain </l>
              <l>What ev'n submissive Truth can scarce obtain. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e5430">Exit Quisara <hi>with her Train</hi>, Bak. and Sya. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e5470">
              <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
              <l>We must resolve and speedily. Walk with me Gentlemen. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e5500">Eexit Rui. Christ. and Pin. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e5530">
              <pb n="6" xml:id="ep000644-008-a"/>Manent <hi>Armusia, Emanuel</hi>, and Sosa. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e5560">
              <speaker>Em. </speaker>
              <l>Now, Sir, you stand as you were charm'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e5590">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>O Sosa, O Emanuel! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e5640">
              <speaker>So. </speaker>
              <l>What now? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e5670">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>This Captive King! What an Action </l>
              <l>Would this be to put forwards, Friends! What glory </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e5710">
              <speaker>Em. </speaker>
              <l>And what an everlasting Wealth to crown it! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e5740">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>To step into't while they are thinking. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e5770">
              <speaker>So. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, 'tis impossible; The Fort's impregnable. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e5800">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>No more, dissuade me not, for I will rule in this. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e5830">
              <speaker>So. </speaker>
              <l>If it must be— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e5860">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Stay not for second Thoughts— Oh! She's an Angel! </l>
              <l>At least we can attempt; our very Fate </l>
              <l>Will sometimes be the Theme of her Discourse, </l>
              <l>And I would dye ten thousand thousand Deaths </l>
              <l>To have her talk of me— </l>
              <l>Love, Love with all his Fires has shot himself </l>
              <l>Into my Soul, and urges on to dare. </l>
              <l>Shou'd we succeed, how vast is the Reward! </l>
              <l>Come on, my Friends!— For such a Prize 'tis wise to hazard all; </l>
              <l>Blest if we Live, and Glorious tho' we Fall. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e5980">Exeunt. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e5990">The End of the First Act. </stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="ep000644-e6000">
          <pb n="7" xml:id="ep000644-008-b"/>
          <head>ACT II. </head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000644-e6020">
            <head>SCENE I. A Vault under the Castle. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e6040">Armusia, Sosa, Emanuel, <hi>and two more in Disguise, some of 'em with lighted Matches. </hi>
            </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e6060">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>OUR prosperous Passage was a lucky Omen, </l>
              <l>The Sea and Wind strove which should most befriend us. </l>
              <l>Where lies our Boat? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e6110">
              <speaker>So. </speaker>
              <l>Safe lodg'd within the Reeds behind the Enemies Castle. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e6140">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>These Merchant's Habits too have done us service: </l>
              <l>Unquestion'd thus I've travel'd thro the Town, </l>
              <l>View'd all the Tyrant's Magazines; got knowledge </l>
              <l>Ev'n of the Prison, </l>
              <l>Where the King's dungeon'd, and the Power that guards it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e6210">
              <speaker>So. </speaker>
              <l>You attempt strong Work. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e6240">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Courage is strong; besides a Monarch's Fate's in't; </l>
              <l>Yet lose or win, there's no retiring now. </l>
              <l>Thus far our Game holds fair, as Merchants we </l>
              <l>Have hir'd this Vault, and stow'd those Mattled Wares, </l>
              <l>That soon will blow it up. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e6310">
              <speaker>Em. </speaker>
              <l>The Trains are laid, Sir. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e6340">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Come nearer then, </l>
              <l>That no false Ear may reach us; o're this Vault </l>
              <l>The Castle stands, where the proud Governor </l>
              <l>Has stor'd his Arms and Treasure, next to that </l>
              <l>The Prison where the injur'd King is kept. </l>
              <l>The Fire I've brought shall break out into Flames </l>
              <l>That all the Island shall stand wond'ring at. </l>
              <l>When the Town's full of Fright, and all employ'd </l>
              <l>To quench the Flames, then fly we to the Prison, </l>
              <l>And push for the King's Rescue. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e6460">
              <speaker>So. </speaker>
              <l>Fortune speed us! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e6490">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Let us be worthy of it by our Courage, </l>
              <l>And so take leave, but keep still within sight, </l>
              <l>Till the Flames rise, then meet to do or dye. </l>
              <l>Fail not, dear Fire, and Powder, hold your Nature; </l>
              <pb n="8" xml:id="ep000644-009-a"/>
              <l>By useful Mischiefs nobly triumph here! </l>
              <l>Redeem a King, and serve a matchless Fair, </l>
              <l>Assist my Love, and make one happy Pair. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e6580">Exeunt severally. </stage>
          </div>
          <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000644-e6590">
            <head>Scene the Town of Ternate. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e6620">Enter Governour and one of his Captains. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e6630">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>No, Captain, for those Troops, we need 'em not, </l>
              <l>The Town is strong enough to stand their Furies. </l>
              <l>D'you think they dare attempt to free the King? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e6680">
              <speaker>Cap. </speaker>
              <l>Perhaps by Treaty, </l>
              <l>But sure by Force they will not prove so forward. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e6720">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>Well, wou'd I had the Princess, I must have her, </l>
              <l>In spight of all her scorn.— Hark! what's that? </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e6760">A noise is heard like the springing of a Mine. </stage>
              <l>That Noise there, it went with a violence. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e6780">
              <speaker>Cap. </speaker>
              <l>Some Wall, belike, Sir, is fallen suddenly. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e6810">
              <speaker>Within. </speaker>
              <l>Fire, Fire! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e6840">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>I hear another Tune, 'tis loud and dreadful. </l>
              <l>Look up into the Town, how bright the Air shews! </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e6880">Exit Cap. </stage>
              <l>Upon my Life some sudden Fire— The Bell too. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e6900">The Bell rings. </stage>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e6910">Enter 1. Citizen. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e6940">
              <speaker>1 Cit. </speaker>
              <l>Fire, Fire! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e6980">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>Where? Where? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e7010">
              <speaker>1 Cit. </speaker>
              <l>Suddenly taken in a Merchant's Vault, Sir, </l>
              <l>It blazes fearfully! help! help, good People. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e7060">Re-enter Captain. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e7070">
              <speaker>Cap. </speaker>
              <l>Your Magazine's a fire, Sir, help, help, suddenly, </l>
              <l>All will be lost. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e7110">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>Raise all the Garrison. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e7140">Enter other Citizens. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e7150">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>The Flames increase! help, help dear Citizens. </l>
              <l>Freedom and Wealth to him that helps! </l>
              <l>Fling Wine, fling any Thing, I'll see it recompens'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e7200">Exeunt omnes. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e7210">Enter 2 <hi>d Citizen</hi>. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e7240">
              <speaker>2. </speaker>
              <l>Fire, Fire! What, my Brats hanging still about me! get you gone, you young Bastards, go, go and plunder! </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e7270">
              <pb n="9" xml:id="ep000644-009-b"/>Enter 3 <hi>d Citizen drunk</hi>. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e7300">
              <speaker>3. </speaker>
              <l>I heard 'em cry Fire, I wish I knew where 'tis, I'm deadly cold. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e7330">
              <speaker>2. </speaker>
              <l>Oh Neighbour, run, save your Goods, your House is a Fire. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e7360">
              <speaker>3. </speaker>
              <l>I don't care, I've got the Key in my Pocket. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000644-e7390">
            <head>SCENE changes to a Prison, and a prospect of Fire. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e7410">Enter Armusia <hi>and his Company breaking open a Door. </hi>
            </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e7440">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>So, thou art open, keep the Way clear behind still, </l>
              <l>Now for the place where the King lies. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e7480">
              <speaker>Em. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis here, Sir. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e7510">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Force open the Door; quick, while the Guards are scatter'd. </l>
              <l>All's in disorder— The Fire rages on— </l>
              <l>Oh 'tis a glorious blaze— Ha! a miserable object! </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e7560">The King is discover'd. </stage>
              <l>Yet by his manly Face he shows a King. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e7580">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Why stare ye on me? </l>
              <l>You cannot put on Faces to fright me: </l>
              <l>In death, I'm still a King. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e7630">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Quick, break the Chain! </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e7660">They take off his Chains and put a Sword into his hand. </stage>
              <l>Oh Barb'rous Wretches thus to use a Prince. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e7680">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>What does this mean? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e7710">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, we are Friends, and come to set you free! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e7740">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Heaven! thou art gracious. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e7770">Enter Guard. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e7780">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Ha! the Guard! Charge 'em! </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e7810">They fight two Parties of Guards who at last fly. </stage>
              <l>They fly! the day is ours! the King is free. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e7830">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Thou gen'rous stranger, what art thou! Some Angel sure. </l>
              <l>Oh! if thou art a man, let me embrace thee? </l>
              <l>Command my Pow'r, my Life. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e7880">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Your Love, no more, Sir. </l>
              <l>But now let's hence! haste to the Boat, </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e7920">They go with the King. </stage>
              <l>Then to Tidore, there, there is my Reward. </l>
              <pb n="10" xml:id="ep000644-010-a"/>
              <l>Such a Reward! Oh the thoughts on't transport me. </l>
              <l>Possess'd of that, I shall think India poor. </l>
              <l>There is no Wealth but she: She's Crowns, and Scepters, </l>
              <l>Health, Freedom, Life, the Empire of the Globe; </l>
              <l>Nay, more, she's— she's the Woman I adore, </l>
              <l>And with Armusia that outweighs the World. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e8030">Exeunt. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e8040">Enter several Townsmen. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e8050">
              <speaker>1. </speaker>
              <l>What, is the Fire out, or past the worst yet? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e8080">
              <speaker>2. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis out, Neighbour, but whether past the worst or no, I know not. I never so bestirr'd my self since I was a Man. I have been burnt at both ends like a Squib. I liv'd two long hours in the Fire. The Flame at last got down into my Throat, and broke out again I don't know where. I fry'd like a burnt Marrow-Bone.▪— If they had not clap'd in a dozen Buckets on this goodly Tenement of mine, I had flam'd up like any Tavern Brush, and been one of the seven Stars by this Time. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e8110">
              <speaker>3. </speaker>
              <l>Well, of all the seven Elements, ware fire, say I. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e8140">
              <speaker>2. </speaker>
              <l>Seven Elements, quoke he! why, you talk as if the Fire had scar'd you out of your seven Sences! I tell ye there are but four Elements: Water and Malt are two of 'em; and Fire and Brimstone, the other. They've past thro' me a little too lately, I thank 'em. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e8170">
              <speaker>3. </speaker>
              <l>Hold, I say, there's a fifth Element, right Brandy. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e8200">
              <speaker>2. </speaker>
              <l>Thou art drunk? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e8230">
              <speaker>3. </speaker>
              <l>Right then, now I'm in my Element. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e8260">
              <speaker>1. </speaker>
              <l>Ay, Neighbour, if ev'ry Man had wrought as you did. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e8290">
              <speaker>2. </speaker>
              <l>Why, I stole nothing, you slandring Cuckold you. That Son of a Batchelor is always back-biting a man to his face. I'd have you to know, I scorn your words. 'Tis well known I get my living at my Finger's ends, and that too I get out of the Fire, as a man may say. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e8320">
              <speaker>3. </speaker>
              <l>How many Rogues were there pretending to help remove Goods, and ran away with 'em. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e8350">
              <speaker>2. </speaker>
              <l>Ay, those unconscionable Rogues! I hate 'em. I hate a Thief. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e8380">
              <speaker>1. </speaker>
              <l>But is there not a deal of damage done? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e8410">
              <speaker>2. </speaker>
              <l>Only some six score houses burnt, that's all, Neighbour— Come let's go home, and fright our Wives, for we look like Devils! away! yonder comes our Governor, a worse Plague than the Fire, he has beams enough yet standing to hang us all. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e8440">Exeunt. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e8450">
              <pb n="11" xml:id="ep000644-010-b"/>
              <hi>Re-enter Governor</hi>. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e8470">
              <speaker>Go. </speaker>
              <l>Fool'd with a Fire! Oh I cou'd tear my Limbs. </l>
              <l>The King is scap'd, fled, past Recovery, </l>
              <l>All, all my hopes of Love and Greatness lost. </l>
              <l>Shall I give over then? No, Spight, Ambition, </l>
              <l>Revenge, and fiercer Love forbid it. Rather, </l>
              <l>I'll venture all, and, in disguise, unknown, </l>
              <l>Crown my Foe's Fortune, or retrieve my own. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e8560">Exit. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e8570">
              <hi>The Scene changes to the King's Palace in </hi>Tidore, <hi>thro' which is discovered a Fleet of Ships of War. Enter </hi>Ruidias. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e8600">
              <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
              <l>Love bids me dare, but reason bids delay. </l>
              <l>Our strength is now too small for such a Siege. </l>
              <l>Yet I must on, the Princess Fires my Soul, </l>
              <l>And though she seems to favour my addresses </l>
              <l>Unless I free the King I must despair. </l>
              <l>Well then, I'll die, or do't— We'll now embark— </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e8680">Shouts at a distance. </stage>
              <l>What means that Shout? </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e8700">Enter Piniero. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e8720">
              <speaker>Pini. </speaker>
              <l>Where are you, Sir? Oh you're undone, prevented. </l>
              <l>The King's releas'd, he's coming in his Barge, </l>
              <l>That met him nigh the Port. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e8770">
              <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
              <l>Impossible! who should redeem him? </l>
              <l>The Princes are all here. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e8810">
              <speaker>Pini. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis done, Sir. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e8840">
              <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
              <l>It cannot be! Done! who dares do it? </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e8870">Shout again. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e8880">Enter Quisara, Panura, <hi>and other Attendants</hi>. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e8910">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Can it be possible! The King returning! </l>
              <l>Freed by a Stranger! Oh my Fatal Vow! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e8950">
              <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
              <l>Grief strikes me dumb! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e8980">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>I thought none but Ruidias cou'd have freed him. </l>
              <l>Is there another like him in the World? </l>
              <l>But Oh! Surprise and Grief betray me, and I lose </l>
              <l>The Sister's gladness in the Lover's sorrow. </l>
              <l>Oh Brother! cou'd I have thought I shou'd have shed a Tear </l>
              <pb n="12" xml:id="ep000644-011-a"/>
              <l>For your Return, unless it were for Joy! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e9070">
              <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
              <l>Oh Princess! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e9100">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>The general Joy comes on, </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e9130">Shout again. </stage>
              <l>And I must meet it, but oh with what comfort? </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e9150">
              <hi>Enter King attended with a numerous Train, Trumpets, Kettledrums and Music. </hi>Armusia, Sofa, Emanuel <hi>with him</hi>, Bakam, and Syana <hi>on each side with their Attendants and Guards. </hi>
            </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e9200">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Rise my Sister! </l>
              <l>I am not welcome yet, till you embrace me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e9240">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>My Royal Brother! Oh I'm lost in Pleasure, </l>
              <l>To see you safe again. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e9280">
              <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, I rejoyce to see you here restor'd, </l>
              <l>But must repine, that 'twas not by my means: </l>
              <l>'Twas a brave Deed, I envy him that did it: </l>
              <l>Yet had it mist, my project had not fail'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e9340">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>I thank you, noble Sir, I know you love me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e9370">
              <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
              <l>I have an Army, Sir, </l>
              <l>That wou'd have scour'd your Tyrant and his Country. </l>
              <l>I'm sorry you're releas'd, and wish you in your Dungeon again, </l>
              <l>That I might bring you hither at my Armies Head. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e9430">
              <speaker>Sya. </speaker>
              <l>I have done nothing, Sir, and therefore think it </l>
              <l>Convenient to say little of what my Love design'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e9470">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>I like your Modesty— My generous Friends, </l>
              <l>I thank you all; I know it griev'd ye </l>
              <l>To hear my Misery: But this Man, Princes, </l>
              <l>I must thank heartily indeed. </l>
              <l>This wondrous Man, even from the Grave of Sorrow, </l>
              <l>Has rais'd me up to Freedom, Life, and Empire. </l>
              <l>Oh Sister, if there may be thanks for this, </l>
              <l>Or any thing near Recompense, invent it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e9570">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>You are too Noble Sir, there is Reward, </l>
              <l>Reward above my Action too, by Millions; </l>
              <l>A Recompense, so Rich, so Great, so Glorious </l>
              <l>I durst not dream it mine, but that 'twas promis'd </l>
              <l>Before the Face of Heaven. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e9640">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>O speak it, speak it, bless me with the Knowledge. </l>
              <l>Make me a happy man, </l>
              <l>For still methinks I am a Prisoner, </l>
              <l>And feel no Liberty, till that is found. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e9700">
              <pb n="13" xml:id="ep000644-011-b"/>
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>It is— (But first to Heav'n and you I bend; </l>
              <l>If either can forgive the high Demand) </l>
              <l>It is your Sister, Royal Sir, She's mine. </l>
              <l>I claim her, by her own Word, and her Honour: </l>
              <l>It was her open Promise to the Man </l>
              <l>That durst redeem you— Beauty set me on, </l>
              <l>And Fortune crowns my hopes, if She receive me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e9790">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Receive you, Sir— Why, Sister! ha! turn from him? </l>
              <l>Stand as you knew not me, nor what he has ventur'd? </l>
              <l>My dearest Sister! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e9840">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>O Sir, your Pardon, </l>
              <l>There is a blushing Modesty </l>
              <l>That holds her back; Virgins are nice to Love; </l>
              <l>I wou'd not have her forc'd; give her fair liberty: </l>
              <l>Ladies of her soft Nature, if compell'd, </l>
              <l>Turn into Fears, and fly ev'n their own Wishes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e9920">
              <speaker>King </speaker>
              <l>Look on him, Princess, is there such another? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e9950">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, I confess, </l>
              <l>My Word is pass'd, and he by that has purchas'd; </l>
              <l>But yet be pleas'd to give me Time to be </l>
              <l>Acquainted with his Merit: we are Strangers, </l>
              <l>And Love, like Pow'r, must pass thro Ceremonies, </l>
              <l>E're it can fix in Virgin's hearts. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e10030">
              <speaker>King </speaker>
              <l>Be speedy. </l>
              <l>You will respect your Word: I know you will: </l>
              <l>I'll be your Pledge, my Hero: Come, my Sister, </l>
              <l>Let's see what Welcome you can give a Prisoner, </l>
              <l>And what kind Looks a Friend— </l>
              <l>Thus in my Arms once more. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e10110">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>You make me blush, Sir. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e10140">
              <speaker>King </speaker>
              <l>Let this Day see our whole Court crown'd with Pleasure. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e10170">An Entertainment of Music and Dancing. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e10180">
              <hi>Several Shepherds advance and express their Joy. The Words were fitted to the Music, which is charmingly compos'd by Mr. </hi>Daniel Purcel▪ Whatever is mark'd thus (") is left out in the singing. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e10200">
              <speaker>Mr. <hi>Leveridge. Shepherd</hi>. </speaker>
              <l>This glorious Day, let Pleasures flow; </l>
              <l>Now Love and Hymen jar no more: </l>
              <l>Ye Sports, appear, let Sorrow cease below; </l>
              <l>Hither repair, the Golden Age restore: </l>
              <l>Let Mortals share the Blessings of the Skies. </l>
              <l>See Jove for ever cease to rove, </l>
              <l>And own, tho' Nuptial Fewds arise, </l>
              <l>No Joys can Vye with Lawful Love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e10320">
              <pb n="14" xml:id="ep000644-012-a"/>
              <speaker>Mr. <hi>Freeman. A Shepherd</hi>. </speaker>
              <l>Happy he who wisely chose </l>
              <l>To taste of Love without his Woes. </l>
              <l>" Happy She whose Charms improve </l>
              <l>" The soft Delights of Harmless Love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e10390">
              <speaker>CHORUS. </speaker>
              <l>Change may raise a wanton Fire, </l>
              <l>But Truth can best improve Desire, </l>
              <l>And Kindles, never to expire. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e10440">
              <speaker>M. Pate and Mr. <hi>Leveridge. Two Shepherds</hi>. </speaker>
              <l>Cease, ye Rovers, cease to Range </l>
              <l>Pleasure revels least in Change. </l>
              <l>Wandring still, and still uneasy, </l>
              <l>Nought can fix ye, nought can please ye; </l>
              <l>While True Love, like Heav'nly Joys, </l>
              <l>Never dies, and never cloys. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e10540">
              <speaker>A Shepherdess. </speaker>
              <l>" From drooping Minds let Sorrow fly, </l>
              <l>" Joy must reign, and Anguish die. </l>
              <l>" Souls who grieve for Coy Denying, </l>
              <l>" Hearts now raging, Wretches dying, </l>
              <l>" Know, that Lovers who pursue, </l>
              <l>" Soon or late the Fair subdue. </l>
              <l>" Blame your Fear when you despair, </l>
              <l>" Not the wishing dying Fair. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e10640">
              <speaker>Mr. Magnus's Boy. <hi>A Shepherd</hi>. </speaker>
              <l>All the Pleasures, Hymen brings </l>
              <l>Lawful Sweets, and chast Desires, </l>
              <l>All the Pleasures Hymen brings, </l>
              <l>Flow from ever-living Springs, </l>
              <l>And never-dying Fires. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e10730">
              <speaker>Mis <hi>Lindsey. A Shepherdess</hi>. </speaker>
              <l>The Jolly Swains </l>
              <l>That were roving o're the Plains </l>
              <l>From all Regions hither fly, </l>
              <l>To claim kind Hymen's gentle Tye. </l>
              <l>With their wanton Motions courting </l>
              <l>Some lovely Maid </l>
              <l>Whose Eyes persuade </l>
              <l>To soft Delights, and am'rous Sporting. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e10840">Enter Swains and Shepherdesses, who dance, </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e10850">
              <speaker>Grand CHORUS. </speaker>
              <l>Love's Flame divinely burns: </l>
              <l>The Golden Age returns. </l>
              <l>
                <hi>Jove, Juno</hi>, and Cupid, and Hymen agree, </l>
              <l>All Hearts thus are bless'd, and less happy when free. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e10940">
              <pb n="15" xml:id="ep000644-012-b"/>
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Lead on! Sister, your hand to my Deliverer. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e10970">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Oh let me first approach it with a Kiss, </l>
              <l>Thus trembling with Extremity of Bliss. </l>
              <l>Wisely, bright Princess, you allay the Joy, </l>
              <l>Still slowly Bless, and leasurely Destroy. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e11030">Exeunt omnes. </stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="ep000644-e11040">
          <head>ACT. III. The Palace. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e11060">Armusa, Sosa, Emanuel. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e11070">
            <speaker>Em. </speaker>
            <l>SIR, why so sad amidst so much good Fortune? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e11100">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>I want what Beggars are allow'd, Content. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e11130">
            <speaker>So. </speaker>
            <l>Does then the King neglect you? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e11160">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>No, he is grateful ev'n to meer profuseness, </l>
            <l>But Oh his Sister, that disdainful Fair, </l>
            <l>That shou'd a little smile upon my service, </l>
            <l>And foster my Deserts, with care avoids me, </l>
            <l>Spight of her solemn Promise. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e11230">
            <speaker>Em. </speaker>
            <l>And you go sighing up and down for this? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e11260">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>What would you have me do? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e11290">
            <speaker>Em. </speaker>
            <l>Do what a Man that knows the Sex wou'd do </l>
            <l>In such a Case, go to her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e11330">
            <speaker>So. </speaker>
            <l>That's the way. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e11360">
            <speaker>Em. </speaker>
            <l>And talk as if you fought for her, boldly. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e11390">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>I shall do something; but with more Respect. </l>
            <l>Pray leave me to my Thoughts, and in an hour command me. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e11430">Ex. Sosa, Emanuel. </stage>
            <l>What shall I do to move her Soul to Pity! </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e11460">Enter Panura. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e11480">
            <l>Ha! This Woman waits on her— Lower I cannot fall, </l>
            <l>I'll try my Fate— Madam, May I presume— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e11510">
            <speaker>Pan. </speaker>
            <l>'Tis the brave stranger! a handsome Gentleman! </l>
            <pb n="16" xml:id="ep000644-013-a"/>
            <l>How happy will she be in such a Husband! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e11550">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>You wait on the Princess; </l>
            <l>With one kind Office you may bind a Gentleman </l>
            <l>Hereafter to be yours. Such beauteous Faces </l>
            <l>Shou'd have courteous minds. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e11610">
            <speaker>Pan. </speaker>
            <l>Tell me your Business, Sir. </l>
            <l>Yet if it be to her, I think your self </l>
            <l>Wou'd do much better, I know your Interest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e11660">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>I want assurance, </l>
            <l>And am yet but a Stranger— I wou'd speak with her●punc. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e11700">
            <speaker>Pan. </speaker>
            <l>She's now alone. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e11730">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>Pray wear this, and believe my meaning civil— </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e11760">Gives her a Jewel. </stage>
            <l>I wou'd speak to her in private. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e11780">
            <speaker>Pan. </speaker>
            <l>You shall, Sir. </l>
            <l>Be pleased to go with me; </l>
            <l>My Chamber's next to her's. But pray be secret. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e11830">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>As Death. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e11860">Exeunt. </stage>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="ep000644-e11870">
            <head>SCENE II. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e11890">
              <hi>Enter King, Governor like an old </hi>Bramin, or Indian Monk. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e11920">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>So far and truly you've discover'd to me </l>
              <l>The former Currents of my Life and Fortunes </l>
              <l>That I acknowledge you most Wise and Holy, </l>
              <l>And credit your Predictions. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e11980">
              <speaker>Go. </speaker>
              <l>I have liv'd long sequester'd from the World </l>
              <l>To find out Knowledge, which I've now attain'd to. </l>
              <l>Many a Mystic Vision have I seen </l>
              <l>Wherein the good and evils of these Islands </l>
              <l>Were lively shadow'd. Many a Charge I've had too, </l>
              <l>Still as the Time grew ripe, to reveal these, </l>
              <l>And now I speak. </l>
              <l>Beware these Portuguese! </l>
              <l>The Cause is now the Gods: hear and believe▪ King! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e12100">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>I do, but know I've found 'em gentle, faithful, </l>
              <l>And am oblig'd to 'em for my Deliverance. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e12140">
              <speaker>Go. </speaker>
              <l>O Son, the Aims of Men are to be look'd at </l>
              <l>Above their present actions: </l>
              <l>These Men came hither, as my vision tells me, </l>
              <l>Almost starv'd, and Shipwrackt, begg'd leave to Trade, </l>
              <l>Grew rich, then suck'd the Fat, </l>
              <l>And Freedom of this Isle, taught her to tremble, </l>
              <l>Witness the Fort they've clapt here on the Neck </l>
              <l>Of your Tidore. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e12250">
              <pb n="17" xml:id="ep000644-013-b"/>
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>They have so, indeed, Father. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e12280">
              <speaker>Go. </speaker>
              <l>Take heed! your late delivery is only </l>
              <l>A fair fac'd Prologue to future mischief. </l>
              <l>Mark but the end of your Restorer! </l>
              <l>Your Sister is his due. What's she? your Heir, Sir. </l>
              <l>And what's he akin then to the Kingdom? </l>
              <l>But Heirs are not ambitious— who thou suffers? </l>
              <l>What reverence shall our Gods have? And what Justice </l>
              <l>The miserable People? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e12380">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>You've well advis'd me. </l>
              <l>And I will seriously consider, Father. </l>
              <l>In the mean time you shall have fair access </l>
              <l>To my Sister, dispose her to your Purpose, </l>
              <l>And let me still know how the Gods determine. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e12450">Exit King. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e12460">
              <speaker>Go. </speaker>
              <l>So, thanks to this false Beard, and falser Cant, </l>
              <l>I've hopes to ruin thee, and my bold Rival. </l>
              <l>The Bramins shall foment the Pious mischief; </l>
              <l>And when each Party's weaken'd, I'll unmask, </l>
              <l>Strike in between, and get the Princess and the Crown. </l>
              <l>Revive my hopes! Revive!— Mankind to fool, </l>
              <l>Still the great Maxim is; divide and rule. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e12560">Exit. </stage>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="ep000644-e12570">
            <head>SCENE III, The Princesses Apartment. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e12590">Enter Quisara, Panura, <hi>and Page</hi>. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e12620">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Sing me a Song, then leave me— and if Ruidias </l>
              <l>Sould come and beg admittance, introduce him. </l>
              <l>But stay— Will Vertue warrant this admission? </l>
              <l>Surely, for once it may, in such an Exigence— </l>
              <l>We must consult about this Turn of Fortune. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e12700">Qui. <hi>seats her self on a Couch</hi>. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e12720">A SONG; by the Page. Set by Mr. Purcel. </stage>
            <l>Lovely Charmer, dearest Creature, </l>
            <l>Kind Invader of my heart, </l>
            <l>Grac'd with ev'ry gift of Nature, </l>
            <l>Rais'd with ev'ry grace of Art! </l>
            <l>Oh! cou'd I but make thee love me, </l>
            <l>As thy Charms my heart have mov'd, </l>
            <l>None cou'd e're be blest above me, </l>
            <l>None cou'd e're be more belov'd. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e12820">Exit Pan. and Page. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e12850">Enter Armusia. </stage>
            <l>Shield me, ye Powers! What's here! </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e12880">She sees him. </stage>
            <l>Sure 'tis the Phantasm of the Man I dread, </l>
            <l>Form'd by my Fears! Who are you? </l>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e12910">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>The fondest and most wretched of your slaves. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e12940">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Who waits there? Rude Intruder, leave me. </l>
              <pb n="18" xml:id="ep000644-014-a"/>
              <l>What means this Treachery? Who let you in? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e12980">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>What cou'd keep out the Love that brought me hither. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e13010">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>This is an Insolence unparalell'd, </l>
              <l>Nor shall my Brother's Love protect this boldness. </l>
              <l>I'm mistress of my self, and will not be </l>
              <l>Thus visited, spight of your boasted Service. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e13070">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Bright Vertue— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e13100">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Stand off, I read dishonour in your Eyes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e13130">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>By all that Beauty they are Innocent. </l>
              <l>Pray tremble not, you have no Cause, Fair Princess. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e13170">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>So base a violation of my Privacy! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e13200">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>If vertuous Love may claim a pitying glance, </l>
              <l>Look on me, and believe me! Is this violence? </l>
              <l>Far be it from my heart to fright your quiet, </l>
              <l>And heaviest curse falls on him that intends it; </l>
              <l>If you mistrust me still, take this and sheath it here. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e13270">He offers her his Dagger. </stage>
              <l>'Twill give a Wound less cruel than your doubts. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e13290">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Why this Intrusion then? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e13320">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>With trembling aw to urge my Love and Service. </l>
              <l>But hopes remove, the nearer I approach you, </l>
              <l>And I even dread to claim what you have promised. </l>
              <l>So much more easie was the task proposed </l>
              <l>Than to demand the Recompence. Oh Princess! </l>
              <l>When greatness check'd the Fire your Beauty kindled, </l>
              <l>Your promise fann'd it to a Flame. I dar'd, </l>
              <l>But 'twas you quicken'd hope: Then kill it not; </l>
              <l>My flame is grown too mighty to be quench'd; </l>
              <l>Yet Oh, 'tis pure, 'tis free from selfish dross. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e13440">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>May I believe? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e13470">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Wrong not your Charms that claim no less a duty. </l>
              <l>Believe me all devoted to your Will. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e13510">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Oh, Love! Why must I be ungrateful to such merit. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e13540">aside. </stage>
              <l>Shall I exact a Proof of your Obedience? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e13560">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Command a thousand, till I've tir'd your doubts </l>
              <l>Set any task, Mortality may dare. </l>
              <l>Point out new dangers, bid me Face Destruction. </l>
              <l>Command me any thing— but not to Love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e13620">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Then hear me! Cease for ever to expect </l>
              <l>The Recompence you ask'd, and leave me now. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e13660">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>What have I promis'd? </l>
              <l>Is this my doom, and is there no redress? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e13700">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>But one, which you must to my pity owe, </l>
              <l>For I must blush to tell your Cure— I love— </l>
              <l>My heart was all dispos'd before you claim'd it. </l>
              <l>Fancy had got the start of your deserts, </l>
              <l>Which yet I prize so high, that for your Ease </l>
              <pb n="19" xml:id="ep000644-014-b"/>
              <l>I force my modesty on this Confession, </l>
              <l>To disengage your hopes, nor let the man </l>
              <l>That has so highly serv'd, depend on fruitless air. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e13800">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Oh, Madam!— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e13830">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Replies are vain: Obey! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e13860">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Wretched Armusia. Doubly wretched now; </l>
              <l>What wilt thou do? Can'st thou resign thy Princess? </l>
              <l>Resign her to a Rival? Tamely yield </l>
              <l>Thy beauteous Prize, and starve thy self to let </l>
              <l>Another Riot. Oh this Racks my Soul! </l>
              <l>Grief, Jealous Rage, Despair, and Envy tear it. </l>
              <l>Bid me with naked Brest go storm a Breach, </l>
              <l>When thro' the dreadful gap a thousand Deaths, </l>
              <l>Rush down in Fires and Rocks and Iron hail. </l>
              <l>But change th' ungrateful task. 'Tis death to hope, </l>
              <l>And hope's the Life of Love; 'tis torment in extream, </l>
              <l>Wheels, Daggers, dying Pangs, and lingring Fires. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e14010">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Hard fate! Why must I use him thus? But Oh! </l>
              <l>I must be cruel to my self or him, </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e14050">Aside. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e14060">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Still dumb, relentless Fair? Well, I'll content you, </l>
              <l>And keep my Promise, tho' I lose my Life. </l>
              <l>Despair will make that easie, Joy attend you, </l>
              <l>While I withdraw to die; It should be at your Feet, </l>
              <l>But I will not Prophane this Place, nor cost </l>
              <l>Your heart a sigh, Farewel! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e14140">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Stay, gen'rous Stranger: your despair alarms me, </l>
              <l>Oh, promise me to live. </l>
              <l>See, see the Pity which I pay your anguish: </l>
              <l>My grateful Soul suffers no less than yours; </l>
              <l>For 'tis a pain to be so much oblig'd </l>
              <l>And Bankrupt in Returns. It kills my Joy, </l>
              <l>I'm angry with my self, and torn in two. </l>
              <l>I wou'd recall my heart, but Oh! I cannot. Fear, Duty, </l>
              <l>Honour, Shame, Pity, Gratitude and Love distract me, </l>
              <l>War in my Brest, my Head, my Soul, and strain the strings of Life. </l>
              <l>Oh leave, leave me, my Confusion is such, </l>
              <l>I dread to say too little or too much. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e14280">going. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e14290">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Oh stay; </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e14320">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>I cannot; must not. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e14350">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Must I then leave you thus? Oh! if I must, </l>
              <l>First see th' affliction of my Soul, see now a separation </l>
              <l>More cruel more a death </l>
              <l>Than that between the Body and the Soul: </l>
              <l>They part to meet again, to be more bless'd; </l>
              <l>But I to be divorc'd from Joy for ever. </l>
              <l>Let me be mad, ye Powers, or let me die! </l>
              <l>Oh Heavens! Oh Princess, Judge what I endure, </l>
              <l>When Death or Madness must bestow the Cure. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e14460">going. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e14470">
              <pb n="20" xml:id="ep000644-015-a"/>Enter Ruidias, Armusia, <hi>is going off. They justle one another at the Door accicidentally. </hi>
            </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e14500">
              <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
              <l>Ha! who is this? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e14530">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Who art thou? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e14560">
              <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
              <l>My Rival with the Princess! and so private. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e14590">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Ha! 'Tis Ruidias, </l>
              <l>My happy Rival, </l>
              <l>But hold out, Patience, yet! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e14650">
              <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
              <l>Is there not door enough, you take such elbow room. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e14680">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>What I take I'll carry. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e14710">
              <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
              <l>Confusion▪ Know proud man, I love the Princess; she harkens to my suit, </l>
              <l>And tho in Portugal you claim precedence, </l>
              <l>I'll have it here; here I command the Fort, </l>
              <l>And that commands the Town. Be wise, desist, </l>
              <l>Or with my Sword— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e14790">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>You wou'd not use it here? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e14820">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Oh hold!— Ruidias, you I may command, </l>
              <l>Forbear, and as you prize my Love, respect him. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e14870">
              <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
              <l>Is then his Life so dear to you? I'm lost. </l>
              <l>Had I your leave to wait on you, and for this? </l>
              <l>Oh I've not Patience. Must I be outdone? </l>
              <l>Out brav'd, out rival'd? Must that Stranger get </l>
              <l>At once the start in Glory and in Love, </l>
              <l>And tread me like a name in sand, to nothing? </l>
              <l>Death, and Hell! shall I bear it? tamely bear it? </l>
              <l>No, e're I do, I'll give or take a Life. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e14970">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Brave stranger, by your Love I charge you, </l>
              <l>Retire, and entertain no thoughts of Vengeance. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e15010">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>O my Patience! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e15040">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis with you still: Oh do not chide it from you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e15070">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Weak flesh rebels, but you and Vertue Conquer. </l>
              <l>I go, but judge, Oh judge! ye tender hearts, </l>
              <l>What Pangs, what Racks the wretched Lover tear </l>
              <l>Who to his Rival leaves the darling fair. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e15130">Exit Armusia. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e15150">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Great soul, I am asham'd I cannot love him yet. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e15180">aside. </stage>
              <l>Now, you, whose Jealous Rage is so presumptuous, </l>
              <l>Know, I resent it and your disrespect. </l>
              <l>Your Love stands yet upon my Courtesie: </l>
              <l>'Tis true, I've suffer'd you to tell your Passion, </l>
              <l>But I ne're promis'd you a kind return; </l>
              <l>And if you dare abuse your privilege— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e15250">
              <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
              <l>Armusia here, and stealing out, when I </l>
              <l>Had hopes to be in private entertain'd! </l>
              <l>What Lover cou'd have tamely born the sight? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e15310">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Know what I am? how durst you doubt my honour? </l>
              <l>I never taught you to dispose my Freedom; </l>
              <pb n="21" xml:id="ep000644-015-b"/>
              <l>And had I promis'd you my heart, 'twere a less Crime </l>
              <l>In me to change than in you to suspect me; </l>
              <l>The first's but frailty, but the last ill Nature. </l>
              <l>Is this your Faith? True Love is more respectful. </l>
              <l>Armusia wou'd not pass so rash a Censure; </l>
              <l>And I shou'd punish thee; I'll strive to do't. </l>
              <l>'Tis still the Lot of groundless Jealousie </l>
              <l>To bring on what it fears. </l>
              <l>Vows, Duty, Gratitude concur to exclude thee, </l>
              <l>Yet should I slight thee, should I chuse thy Rival </l>
              <l>Blame most thy self, and learn how dang'rous 'tis </l>
              <l>To let a Woman, spight of Wisdom's Laws, </l>
              <l>See that you're Jealous, tho' without a Cause. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e15490">Exit. Qui. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e15510">
              <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
              <l>She's gone! what shall I do? Oh that Armusia </l>
              <l>Hangs betwixt hopes and me, and threats my Ruin: </l>
              <l>He has her vows, fresh Services, the King, </l>
              <l>And a vast stock of merit on his side: </l>
              <l>I have but naked Love, and wav'ring too, I fear. </l>
              <l>The Sword then in my hand, I now must try </l>
              <l>To fix my Fortune, and o'recome, or die: </l>
              <l>When Conquest can't by formal means be got, </l>
              <l>A brave Despair may cut the Gordian knot. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="ep000644-e15630">
          <head>ACT IV. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e15650">
            <hi>The Scene draws and discovers </hi>Armusia <hi>lying on a bank in a Grove of Orange-Trees. </hi>Emanuel <hi>by him</hi>. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e15690">This Dialogue is sung to him by a Clown and his Wife. Set by <hi>Mr. Leveridge</hi>, and Sung by him and <hi>Mr. Pate</hi>. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e15720">
            <speaker>Wife. </speaker>
            <l>HOld, John, e're you leave me, i'troth I will know </l>
            <l>Whither so smugg'd up thus early you go? </l>
            <l>With clean Hands and Face, </l>
            <l>Your best Band with a Lace, </l>
            <l>Your Sunday Reparel when you shou'd go Plough, </l>
            <l>So trim none wou'd think you a married Man now. </l>
            <l>Hold, John, e're you leave me, itroth I will know </l>
            <l>Whither so smugg'd up thus early you go? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e15840">
            <speaker>Man. </speaker>
            <l>Go, Joan, I wo'n't tell you: To lead a sweet Life </l>
            <l>I've learnt of my Betters to steal from my Wife. </l>
            <l>Mayhaps with my Neighbour I'll dust it away, </l>
            <l>Mayhaps play at Put, or some other such Play. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e15910">
            <speaker>Wife. </speaker>
            <l>I guess at what game you'd be playing to day. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e15940">
            <pb n="22" xml:id="ep000644-016-a"/>
            <speaker>Man. </speaker>
            <l>Don't plague me. The Devil's in Women I think. </l>
            <l>Go, Joan, I tell thee I'm going to drink? </l>
            <l>Come, prithee, don't think that I've got no more Grace: </l>
            <l>Nay go, or I'll gi' thee a Dowse in the Face. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e16010">
            <speaker>Wife. </speaker>
            <l>I'll find then some body to strike in your Place. </l>
            <l>Why should you deny me? I never did you. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e16050">Weeping. </stage>
            <l>Because I an't new, you won't give me my due, </l>
            <l>But Troth if you wo'not, another shall do. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e16080">
            <speaker>Man. </speaker>
            <l>If thus you e're do, </l>
            <l>Oh! how I'll belabour your Booby and you. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e16120">Threatning. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e16130">
            <speaker>Wife. </speaker>
            <l>If thus you e're do, </l>
            <l>Oh how I'll belabour your Trollop and You. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e16170">
            <speaker>Both. </speaker>
            <l>Oh how I'll belabour <list>
                <item>your Booby and you </item>
                <item>your Trollop and you, and you. </item>
              </list>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e16230">
            <speaker>Wife. </speaker>
            <l>Well, John, do not go, </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e16270">Wheadling and crying. </stage>
            <l>And I wo'not do so, </l>
            <l>Do not go, my dear Johny, </l>
            <l>My Precious, my Hony. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e16320">She kisses him. </stage>
            <l>Oh pray do not go, </l>
            <l>And I wo'not do so. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e16350">
            <speaker>Man. </speaker>
            <l>Adsooks by that Buss I'm inveigled to stay, </l>
            <l>Come, Joan, come and spoil me from going astray. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e16400">CHORUS. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e16410">
            <speaker>Wife. </speaker>
            <l>
              <hi>Come give your best Band.</hi>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e16450">
            <speaker>Man. </speaker>
            <l>
              <hi>Here take my best Band.</hi>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e16490">
            <speaker>Both. </speaker>
            <l>
              <hi>Now, give me thy Hand. </hi>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e16530">
            <speaker>Man. </speaker>
            <l>
              <hi>Thus 'tis with you Women</hi>. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e16570">
            <speaker>Wife. </speaker>
            <l>Thus 'tis with you Men. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e16600">
            <speaker>Both. </speaker>
            <l>Whene're you fall out 'tis to fall in again. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e16630">Ex. Clown with his Wife. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e16640">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>In vain with Mirth you wou'd beguile my Cares. </l>
            <l>Alas! I'm dead to Joy, and but a walking Trouble, </l>
            <l>Insensible to all but Love and Grief, </l>
            <l>To all but Grief, for Grief and Love are one. </l>
            <l>Why wou'd my Rival kill me? If he hates me </l>
            <l>Sure he shou'd bid me live!— Let's range the Grove </l>
            <l>Perhaps I soon shall meet him, or my Princess. </l>
            <l>Both can deal Death; yet I, like other Wretches, </l>
            <l>Tho! that's my only Ease, must struggle with my Fate. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e16750">Exeunt. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e16760">
            <hi>Enter Governour and </hi>Quisara. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e16780">
            <speaker>Go. </speaker>
            <l>I wou'd talk further with you from the Gods. </l>
            <l>You are a Princess of that Excellence— </l>
            <l>Nay do not blush, I do not flatter you. </l>
            <l>The Gods bestow'd this on you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e16840">
            <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
            <l>I own their Bounty. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e16870">
            <speaker>Go. </speaker>
            <l>Apply it then to their Use, to their Honour, </l>
            <l>To ruine or convert those Misbelievers </l>
            <pb n="23" xml:id="ep000644-016-b"/>
            <l>Those Portuguese; Invite 'em to our Temples— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e16920">
            <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
            <l>Father we may sit yonder, and be still more private. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e16950">Exit. Qui. and Go. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e16960">Enter Ruidias and Piniero. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e16990">
            <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
            <l>What, did Armusia then return the Challenge </l>
            <l>You carried him? Will he not meet me? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e17040">
            <speaker>Pin. </speaker>
            <l>He calmly told me, that he disapproves </l>
            <l>All formal Duels, yet that with a Sword </l>
            <l>He ev'ry Day is walking in this Grove. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e17090">
            <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
            <l>Then let us strive to find him out— But see he comes. </l>
            <l>Now Love, Revenge, and Fortune guide my Arm. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e17130">Enter Armusia, with Emanuel. </stage>
            <l>Draw, Armusia! </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e17180">Rui. and Pin. draw. </stage>
            <l>Dye or resign the Princess. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e17220">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>I will do neither. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e17250">Armusia, and Emanuel draw. </stage>
            <l>But hold, why must our Friends now share our Danger? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e17290">
            <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
            <l>Stand still, I charge ye, as you honour me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e17320">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>And, good Emanuel, hold— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e17360">
            <speaker>Pin. </speaker>
            <l>'Tis well you spoke— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e17390">
            <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
            <l>Fight home, I will not spare you, </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e17420">They fight with Sword and Dagger. </stage>
            <l>Nor do I look for mercy. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e17440">Enter Quisara, and Governor. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e17470">
            <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
            <l>Ha! fighting! hold! Oh hold, rash Men! Oh part 'em! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e17500">
            <speaker>Go. </speaker>
            <l>Let 'em alone, let 'em kill one another. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e17530">
            <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
            <l>Ruidias, hold. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e17570">
            <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
            <l>Unless he dyes, I'm hopeless. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e17600">
            <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
            <l>If e're you lov'd, I charge ye cease! Oh! Father. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e17630">
            <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
            <l>My Love were small, shou'd I desist. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e17660">
            <speaker>Go. </speaker>
            <l>Oh let both fall, kind Fortune. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e17690">Ruidias falls. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e17700">
            <speaker>Pin. </speaker>
            <l>Ruidias down! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e17740">
            <speaker>Em. </speaker>
            <l>Stand still, or my Sword's in— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e17770">
            <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
            <l>Oh hold Armusia. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e17810">
            <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
            <l>I can expect no Mercy. Why do you not kill me then? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e17840">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>A Boy might do as much at this Advantage. </l>
            <l>Will you not ask your Life? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e17880">
            <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
            <l>'Tis not worth asking. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e17910">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>Nor is it worth my taking in this Posture. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e17940">
            <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
            <l>Spare him Armusia, spare him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e17980">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>My Love is all Obedience. Rise, Sir, and take your Sword again </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e18010">
            <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
            <l>Not against him that spar'd me! Oh curst Fortune. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e18040">
            <speaker>Go. </speaker>
            <l>What have you done? 'Twere better they had all perish'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e18070">
            <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
            <l>Father, be pacify'd; I'm working for the best— </l>
            <l>This Jealous Rage and Disobedience cure me— </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e18110">Aside. </stage>
            <l>Armusia, meet me in the Neighbouring Temple. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e18140">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>Madam, I shall— </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e18170">Exit Quis. Gov. </stage>
            <l>Come brave Ruidias, let us now be Friends; </l>
            <l>Believe your Honor safe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e18230">
            <pb n="24" xml:id="ep000644-017-a"/>
            <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
            <l>Oh you have beat me both ways, and so nobly </l>
            <l>That I must ever love the hand that did it. </l>
            <l>But Oh the Princess. Both cannot possess her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e18280">
            <speaker>Pin. </speaker>
            <l>You cannot, Sir, unless She break her Vow. </l>
            <l>Come leave these Toys; and wed your Mistress, Fame. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e18320">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>Oh Sir, you ask too too much of a Lover. </l>
            <l>Ev'n I my self had rather leave the world, than quit so fair a Prize. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e18360">
            <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
            <l>And you alone deserve her. Yet, Armusia, </l>
            <l>I cannot yet resign her, tho' I must. </l>
            <l>The heat of Love remains, tho' the Soul hope is fled. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e18420">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>Yet let's be Friends. Why shou'd we hate each other </l>
            <l>For Sympathy in Love? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e18460">
            <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
            <l>Too gen'rous Man, I cannot call you Rival, </l>
            <l>Let me embrace you; Let all hatred end. </l>
            <l>Oh thus I'm blest— What e're the Fates intend, </l>
            <l>I cannot lose, possest of such a Friend. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e18520">Exeunt. </stage>
          <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000644-e18530">
            <head>SCENE the Temple. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e18550">Enter Governor still Disguis'd and Bramin. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e18560">
              <speaker>Go. </speaker>
              <l>I need not now repeat what we've to dread </l>
              <l>From these bold mis-believing Portuguese. </l>
              <l>Therefore to ruine them, all means are just. </l>
              <l>Thus I've decoy'd to Princess the invite </l>
              <l>Her promis'd Husband hither, where no doubt </l>
              <l>He will Blaspheme our Gods. </l>
              <l>The King will in Disguise hear their Discourse. </l>
              <l>You know your Time t'appear and back my words. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e18660">
              <speaker>Bra. </speaker>
              <l>You need not doubt us in so good a Cause </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e18690">
              <hi>Exeunt Enter </hi>Armusia and Quisara, meeting. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e18730">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>See, Madam, at your Feet your faithful Slave </l>
              <l>Who studies new humility to please you, </l>
              <l>And takes a kind of Joy in his afflictions, because they come from you. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e18780">
              <hi>Kneels to </hi>Quisara. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e18800">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Oh rise, Sir, I did not invite you hither </l>
              <l>Thus to prophane our Altars, but to ask </l>
              <l>A better Proof of Love than so misplac'd a Worship; </l>
              <l>A Proof which, since I've sworn, since you persist, </l>
              <l>Must make me yours, at least my grateful Duty. </l>
              <l>Few Brides, alas! at first have more to give. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e18880">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Oh name it, Madam, what wou'd I not do, </l>
              <l>Tho' but to gain you thus: Love, greedy Love, </l>
              <l>That still unsatisfy'd, still murm'ring Passion </l>
              <l>Will pine, but since 'tis often but Esteem </l>
              <l>And gratitude improv'd, 'twill shoot at last </l>
              <l>Forc'd by a Zeal like mine. Oh then command me. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e18960">
              <pb n="25" xml:id="ep000644-017-b"/>
              <hi>Enter King and Governour both disguis'd. </hi>
            </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e18980">
              <speaker>Go. </speaker>
              <l>Now harken, Sir, and as he treats our Gods </l>
              <l>So use him, or expect severest Judgments. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19020">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Change your Religion, and adore our Gods. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19050">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Ha! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19080">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Renounce-your Faith. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19110">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Heav'n forbid! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19140">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Offer as we do? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19170">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>To Wood and Stone, vile Beasts, and cursed Devils? </l>
              <l>Is this the Proof you ask? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19210">
              <speaker>Go. </speaker>
              <l>O Blasphemy! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19240">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Peace. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19270">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>I'll reason with you. Are not our Gods as great as yours? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19300">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>They are senceless, wretched, and the worst of Creatures, </l>
              <l>Unfit to help themselves, much less mankind. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19340">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>The Sun and Moon we worship, they are heavenly. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19370">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>But I the Maker of that Sun and Moon </l>
              <l>Who gave 'em Motion, Influence, and Light. </l>
              <l>Excuse me, Princess, if my Zeal for Truth </l>
              <l>Extort a gen'rous Freedom of my Tongue. </l>
              <l>You shou'd have said, Instruct the King and me. </l>
              <l>In that blest Doctrine that guides Souls to Heaven. </l>
              <l>Oh may you follow that, destroy your Idols, </l>
              <l>Beat down their Altars, ruine their false Temples— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19470">
              <speaker>Go. </speaker>
              <l>Oh horror! My Prophecy was true. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19500">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>I'm sorry I came hither— I've heard too much. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e19530">Exit King and Governour. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19540">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Thus far in Charity I was oblig'd </l>
              <l>To rectifie the Errors of your Thought, </l>
              <l>Nor can the Blame be mine to want success. </l>
              <l>'Twas by these Gods that I was sworn to wed you </l>
              <l>These upon blaspheme: You have renounc'd their Power </l>
              <l>And thereby free me from all obligation. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19620">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>You are too just to make this slight Evasion. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19650">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>You shall both find me just, sincere and plain </l>
              <l>Therefore resolve to quit your Faith or me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19690">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>My Life is yours, but my Religion Heavens </l>
              <l>And I no more can change it than my Love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19730">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>You hear your Task. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19760">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Princess, cease t'injoyn what heav'n forbids. </l>
              <l>Name any Task that Honour may not blush </l>
              <l>To execute, Toyls, Dangers, Death it self, </l>
              <l>But do not, do not tempt me to be bad. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19820">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Obey, and instantly; or from this hour </l>
              <l>No Recantation shall prevail. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19860">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Call you this Charity? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19890">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Nay then— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e19920">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>You must not go. </l>
              <l>What have I done, to merit this hard Sentence? </l>
              <l>To have my very Soul rack'd, forc'd to quit </l>
              <l>My Heav'n above, or Paradice on Earth! </l>
              <pb n="26" xml:id="ep000644-018-a"/>
              <l>How well I love, how much I prize your Charms </l>
              <l>My Life must show, but Honour, Conscience, Heaven </l>
              <l>I never must forego. Must I then lose You or my self? </l>
              <l>Can You persist? Must I be torn from you? I must— </l>
              <l>Yet once more let me gaze— O now I cannot go. </l>
              <l>Dreadful Strife! Cruel Struggle. </l>
              <l>I must not look, nor leave her! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e20050">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Farewel. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e20080">Going, he holds her. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e20090">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Stay, stay, dear Mischief!— But what am I doing? </l>
              <l>Ha!— Now I dread my Thoughts— assist, ye Pow'rs! </l>
              <l>Awake my Soul! Oh look no more my Eyes. </l>
              <l>Hush! Treacherous Love! </l>
              <l>Since Heart or Soul must perish on this Sea </l>
              <l>Sink thou, my Heart, to save the immortal Treasure. </l>
              <l>Quit thy rich Claim, tho' while I so resign, </l>
              <l>No Martyrdom sure ever equal'd mine. </l>
              <l>Away, away! Oh! If I look I dye, </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e20200">He looks on her, then turns from her suddenly. </stage>
              <l>There's no way left, to conquer, but to flye. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e20220">Going. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e20230">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Heroic Soul! Stay! This confirms me yours. </l>
              <l>In quitting, you have gain'd me. I resolv'd </l>
              <l>To make the utmost Tryal of your Faith, </l>
              <l>And in your Faith of you. I've long in private </l>
              <l>Weigh'd your Belief. I find by you 'tis Heavenly: </l>
              <l>You've prov'd the practice; and 'twas a blest Vision </l>
              <l>Bespoke my Change, no fickleness of Mind. </l>
              <l>Whom shou'd I love indeed but him I've sworn to wed, </l>
              <l>Who freed my Brother, and retreives my Soul! </l>
              <l>Heav'n, Reason, Duty, Gratitude, and Love decree it, </l>
              <l>Your Faith and you for ever, now are mine. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e20360">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Amazement! Ravishment! am I awake! </l>
              <l>And are you mine! I will, I must believe it. </l>
              <l>Oh happy Change! O unexpected Bliss. </l>
              <l>Look down, ye Sacred Choirs, and share my Joys, </l>
              <l>While thus I pay my Thanks. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e20430">Kneels and kisses her hand. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e20440">Enter King, Governour and Guards. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e20450">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Nay, start not, take my Confirmation too. </l>
              <l>I promis'd you to let Quisara's Hand </l>
              <l>Be joyn'd with yours, and here I ratifie it. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e20510">The King joyns their Hands. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e20520">
              <speaker>Go. </speaker>
              <l>Ha! Did I plot for this! </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e20550">Aside. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e20560">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Thought is drown'd in Joy. How shall I speak my Thanks! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e20590">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Hold, as the Gods have seen me just to you, </l>
              <l>To their own Altars they must see me just. </l>
              <l>Guards, seize your Prisoner— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e20640">
              <speaker>Go. </speaker>
              <l>That's well retriev'd! Be sure you bind him fast. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e20670">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Is this your gratitude? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e20700">
              <pb n="27" xml:id="ep000644-018-b"/>
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Bind your Restorer, Sir? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e20730">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Oh Sister, with Reluctance I'm severe. </l>
              <l>Had he offended me, I had forgiven, </l>
              <l>But to our Gods the injury is done, </l>
              <l>Blasphem'd, Revil'd: Yet still he may be yours, </l>
              <l>He must appease our Gods by humble Worship, </l>
              <l>Or fall a Sacrifice where he blasphem'd 'em; </l>
              <l>And sure to save his Life, and gain you, he'll submit. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e20820">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>To serve my Princess, to secure my Joys </l>
              <l>I'd rush thro' Seas, thro' Fires, I'd smile at danger, </l>
              <l>I wou'd do any thing, but injure Heaven, </l>
              <l>And to serve Idols were the greatest wrong. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e20880">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>What means my Friend? sure you'll not lose your self, </l>
              <l>Oh quick, recant, submit, appease our Gods </l>
              <l>And those more angry Men that awe me, and the People. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e20930">
              <speaker>Go. </speaker>
              <l>He instantly must own our Gods or die. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e20960">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>What, use my breath t' abjure the Pow'r that gave it, </l>
              <l>Renounce, th' Almighty Being! Worship Hell! </l>
              <l>No more; bring me to Torments, Racks, and Fires; </l>
              <l>I'll offer there my self: But when I quit my Faith, </l>
              <l>And grow unworthy thus of her and mercy, </l>
              <l>Let me dread ev'ry Curse that guilt deserves, </l>
              <l>Want, Shame, Diseases, and what's worse, her hate, </l>
              <l>Despair on Earth, and worse Despair below. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e21060">
              <speaker>Go. </speaker>
              <l>Mildness but hardens him. Our Bramins here demand him. </l>
              <l>This Temple has its Prison; there they best </l>
              <l>Will work the wish'd-for Change. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e21120">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>You're wise and holy: </l>
              <l>Act for the best, but still respect my Friend. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e21160">
              <speaker>Go. </speaker>
              <l>Fear not. Death's no misusage of a Rival. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e21190">Aside. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e21200">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Oh, Sir, do not resign him to his Foes. </l>
              <l>Rather exert your Pow'r. O save him, save your Friend. </l>
              <l>I know he'll ne're abjure his Faith. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e21250">
              <speaker>Go. </speaker>
              <l>Then he must die. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e21280">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>He shall not die! Oh! Sir, why turn you from me? </l>
              <l>See, on her knees your Sister begs his Life; </l>
              <l>With tears she begs it, save the Man that freed you, </l>
              <l>Him I must wed, and wed by your command. </l>
              <l>Must I bring on his death? O spare him! Father, holy men, </l>
              <l>Joyn, joyn with me: True Piety is mild. </l>
              <l>Oh whither wou'd you lead him! stay! stay! Take me too. </l>
              <l>I'll not out live his Loss. No, I'll now save his Life, </l>
              <l>Or lose my own. Our Love and Faith are one: </l>
              <l>Our Fates must be the same. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e21400">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>How's this, Quisara! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e21440">
              <speaker>Bra. </speaker>
              <l>She raves. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e21470">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>No, thou false Man, like him I serve a Pow'r </l>
              <pb n="28" xml:id="ep000644-019-a"/>
              <l>That gives me strength to scorn your cursed Idols. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e21510">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Ha! own his Faith. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e21540">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>I do, I do! Oh spare him! spare your Sister! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e21570">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>O fatal found. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e21600">
              <speaker>Go. </speaker>
              <l>Take him away, he hardens her in Error: </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e21630">Exit Arm. guarded. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e21660">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Oh Princess! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e21690">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>O Sir, will you then let him go? call, call him back! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e21720">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>O Sister! have a care, lose not your self; he will recant. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e21750">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Oh never, Sir; ev'n I wou'd not to save him. </l>
              <l>Then save us both. Nay, do not, do not fly me. </l>
              <l>My hopes are all in you. Oh! hear me, hear me! </l>
              <l>Let not blind Zeal prevail! save your own honour, </l>
              <l>Can you resign us to be Butcher'd, mangled, </l>
              <l>Our Limbs torn, and abandon'd to vile wretches? </l>
              <l>Your dearest Friend, your Sister! sure you cannot! </l>
              <l>Our hearts are near akin, and mine wou'd bleed </l>
              <l>To see you thus distress'd. Thus I bore your affliction. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e21860">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Oh I shall lose the Monarch in the Friend. </l>
              <l>Rise, rise, Quisara. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e21910">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Oh Sir! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e21940">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Sister! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e21970">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Brother! Friend! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e22000">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Let Crowns be lost, and let me save my Sister and my Friend. </l>
              <l>Thus in my arms, thus let me ever guard 'em. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e22040">
              <speaker>Go. </speaker>
              <l>Ha! all goes ill. Run, Call the Bramins hither. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e22080">
                <hi>To the </hi>Bramin. </stage>
              <l>Hope not to save 'em, tho' you lose your Crown. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e22110">Exit Bra <hi>and re-enter presently with the Choir. </hi>
              </stage>
              <l>No, King, the Gods can punish them and you. </l>
              <l>Nay, if you pause, I've Judgments to denounce </l>
              <l>From angry Heaven. The Sacred Choir attends; </l>
              <l>Leave her to us, we'll only fright and preach her from her Errors— </l>
              <l>Or put it past your Power to save her or my Rival. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e22190">Aside. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e22200">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Oh, King, do you then yield me up! Hold, wretches; </l>
              <l>Touch not my hand. I'll freely go to Dungeons, </l>
              <l>Nay, death it self, for such a Noble Cause: </l>
              <l>Tho' Earth forsakes us, heaven will mend our Fates. </l>
              <l>And pour severest Vengeance on your heads. </l>
              <l>Yes, cruel men, then tremble, fear its anger, </l>
              <l>Dread, dread its fierce Revenge! our blood will claim it. </l>
              <l>But hold! we ought to love our very Foes. </l>
              <l>Then Bless these Men: thou power of mercy, spare e'm. </l>
              <l>May they like me their Idol Gods despise, </l>
              <l>And dare to fall, more gloriously to rise. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e22330">Exit Qui. <hi>with Guards and </hi>Bramins. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e22360">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>I fear you'll not prevail. Oh urge not then </l>
              <l>The Vengeance of the Gods too far: for if you do— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e22400">
              <speaker>Bra. </speaker>
              <l>To clear your doubts we'll move the angry Powers </l>
              <l>By solemn Incantation. </l>
            </sp>
            <floatingText>
              <body>
                <div type="incantation" xml:id="ep000644-e22470">
                  <pb n="29" xml:id="ep000644-019-b"/>
                  <head>An Incantation set by Mr. D. and Purcell. </head>
                  <l>" HEar thou by whom the rattling Thunder's hurl'd! </l>
                  <l>" Hear, Parent Sun, bright Eye, and Monarch of the World. </l>
                  <sp xml:id="ep000644-e22530">
                    <speaker>Mr. <hi>Bowen. A Bramin</hi>. </speaker>
                    <l>Hear, gentle Moon, pale Queen of Night, </l>
                    <l>And ye refulgent Orbs of Light, </l>
                    <l>Great Court of Heaven so ample and so high, </l>
                    <l>And all ye swarming Commons of the Sky. </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp xml:id="ep000644-e22600">
                    <speaker>CHORUS. </speaker>
                    <l>
                      <hi>O Skies! O Sea! O Earth! on all Your Pow'rs call </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                      <hi>E're the Blasphemers fall</hi>, </l>
                    <l>
                      <hi>Oh hear our solemn call</hi>. </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp xml:id="ep000644-e22680">
                    <speaker>Mr. <hi>Freeman. Another Bramin</hi>. </speaker>
                    <l>Hear, ye friendly earthly Powers, </l>
                    <l>Gods of kindly Fruits and Flowers, </l>
                    <l>Who, unseen, delight to trip </l>
                    <l>Where Birds flutter, hop, and skip, </l>
                    <l>Where there warble, chirp and coo, </l>
                    <l>Where in Whispers Zephirs woo, </l>
                    <l>Where poor Eccho sweetly grieves, </l>
                    <l>And remurmurs thro' the Leaves. </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp xml:id="ep000644-e22790">
                    <speaker>Mr. <hi>Pate. Another Bramin</hi>. </speaker>
                    <lg>
                      <l>Rouse, ye Gods of the main! </l>
                      <l>Take Vengeance on those who your Altars prophane. </l>
                      <l>Hush no more the loud Storms! Command them to blow, </l>
                      <l>Till foaming with Rage the Waves roar as they flow, </l>
                      <l>" While they heave and they swell, </l>
                      <l>" Toss the Slaves to the Skies, and then plunge 'em to hell. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg>
                      <l>Infernal Pow'rs, grim sullen sprights </l>
                      <l>Who fill our Souls with dire affrights! </l>
                      <l>By all the dismal yell, </l>
                      <l>And horrors of your hell, </l>
                      <l>Your dreadful Pleasure tell. </l>
                      <pb n="30" xml:id="ep000644-020-a"/>
                      <l>End with the Verse, <hi>Hear ye Gods of the main, </hi>&amp;c. </l>
                    </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp xml:id="ep000644-e22970">
                    <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
                    <l>The Gods are Sullen, and displeased. But see </l>
                    <l>The Ancient Seer, who oft declares their will. </l>
                    <l>Advance, wise Bramin, while by Pow'r of sound, </l>
                    <l>We Prompt some God, by Thee to ' inform a Doubting Monrach. </l>
                  </sp>
                </div>
              </body>
            </floatingText>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e23040">An Old Bramin, comes forwards and Sings, The Enthusiastic SONG. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e23070">
              <hi>Set, Sung, and Acted, by </hi>Mr. Leveridge. </stage>
            <lg>
              <lg>
                <l>OH Cease, cease, urge no more the God to swell my Breast! </l>
                <l>The Mansion dreads the greater Guest. </l>
                <l>But lo! he comes! I shake! I feel, I feel his Sway, </l>
                <l>And now he hurries me along. </l>
                <l>Then, Crouds, believe, and, Kings, obey, </l>
                <l>'Tis Heav'n inspires the Song. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Haste! To the Gods due Vengeance give. </l>
                <l>Hark! From their Seats they cry, </l>
                <l>Who lets Blasphemers live, </l>
                <l>Shall by Blasphemers die. </l>
                <l>Haste, haste, due Vengeance give. </l>
                <l>" Let the Sound </l>
                <l>" Eccho all around. </l>
                <l>Haste, haste, due Vengeance give. </l>
                <l>Beware! Ten thousand, thousand threatning Ills I see! </l>
                <l>Invasions! Wars! Plagues! Ruin! Endless Woes! </l>
                <l>Ah wretched Isle, I weep for Thee, </l>
                <l>Save, save thy self, Resign the God's Blaspheming Foes. </l>
                <l>Now, now the Thunder roars. </l>
                <l>The Earth now groans and quakes. </l>
                <l>The rising Main a Deluge pours. </l>
                <l>The World's Foundation shakes. </l>
                <l>Hell gapes? The Fiends appear! </l>
                <l>Oh hold, ye angry Pow'rs, relent, or we dispair. </l>
                <l>See, we fulfill </l>
                <l>On your Foes your dreadful Will. </l>
                <l>See the Throng </l>
                <l>Hoot 'em, as they're dragg'd along. </l>
                <pb n="31" xml:id="ep000644-020-b"/>
                <l>Now they tear 'em, now they dye; </l>
                <l>All applaud, and shout for Joy. </l>
                <l>Peace returns, all Nature smiles, </l>
                <l>Happy Days now bless our Isles, </l>
                <l>Now we laugh with Plenty crown'd, </l>
                <l>Merry Sports and Love go round.— </l>
              </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>" The Vision's o'er!— The God deserts my Brest. </l>
              <l>" Hush! gently bear me hence to Rest. </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e23490">He is led off. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e23500">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>Now, Sir, you've heard the Gods confirm their Doom. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e23530">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>They yet may Change. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e23560">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>It must be quickly then. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e23590">
              <speaker>King </speaker>
              <l>I'll try to win 'em.— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e23620">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>Leave us to do that. </l>
              <l>We dare not trust your Nature with the Parly. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e23660">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Delay awhile. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e23690">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>Take heed! Dread, dread the Gods; if you defer their Doom. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e23720">
              <speaker>King </speaker>
              <l>Am I a King, and must they dye! my Sister, my Restorer! </l>
              <l>Oh Death is in the Thought! First let it reach me. </l>
              <l>Let Vengeance rage, and sweep me from the World,— </l>
              <l>But Oh this will not save 'em. I must yield. </l>
              <l>But judge my Grief, all great, all gen'rous Hearts! </l>
              <l>Why do we boast of Pow'r? A Crown's a Pageant; </l>
              <l>Kings are but glorious Slaves, controll'd by Odds, </l>
              <l>The Priests, the People, and the greater Gods. </l>
              <l>When These are touch'd, 'tis They the Scepter Weild, </l>
              <l>And Kings, those petty Substitutes, must yield. </l>
              <l>Empire's a stinted Grant, a Taste of Pow'r, </l>
              <l>And we but Rule to feel Restraint the more. </l>
              <l>Gods, do us right: 'Tis Just we be withstood </l>
              <l>When doing Ill, but not when doing Good. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e23880">Exeunt. </stage>
          </div>
          <trailer>The End of the Fourth ACT. </trailer>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="ep000644-e23900">
          <pb n="32" xml:id="ep000644-021-a"/>
          <head>ACT V. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e23920">The Curtain slowly rises to mournful Musick, and discovers a Prison, Quisara lying on the Floor, all in White, reading by the Light of a Lamp; her Women in Black, some, Standing, others Kneeling by her, and Weeping: The Bell Tolls sometime before she speaks. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e23940">
            <speaker>Quisara. </speaker>
            <l>HOW blest is Piety! It cheers my Soul, </l>
            <l>Ev'n here, where I'm preparing for my Fate, </l>
            <l>Of all but you forsaken!— Do not Weep; </l>
            <l>You break my Peace of Mind,— Nay, then I beg, </l>
            <l>I must not now Command, retire a while— </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e24010">Ex. Women. </stage>
            <l>Grief is Infectious,— Now I think on them, </l>
            <l>On my Distress, and poor Armusia, Doom'd </l>
            <l>For me to fall, I Weep,— </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e24060">The Bell tolls again. </stage>
            <l>Hark! The Bell tolls again! Our fatal Hour is come. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e24080">Enter Armusia <hi>in Chains</hi>. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e24110">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>Oh my rack'd Soul! How shall I stand this Sight, </l>
            <l>The strongest Tryal they cou'd put me to! Oh! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e24150">
            <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
            <l>Ha! Whence that Groan? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e24180">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>Oh Princess! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e24210">
            <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
            <l>Oh Armusia! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e24250">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>How shall I dare t'approach that Suff'ring Vertue! </l>
            <l>And yet I must. Thus then, now let me crawl, </l>
            <l>And in this Agony breathe out a Soul </l>
            <l>Rack'd with unutterable Love and Woe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e24310">
            <speaker>Qui </speaker>
            <l>Oh 'tis too much, thou best, thou only Lover, </l>
            <l>Thou Lover of my Soul. I only greive for thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e24350">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>And shall I not Grieve for you, betray'd for me to Death? </l>
            <l>Not Grieve to see you here! Oh! Hopes of Heav'n, </l>
            <l>'Tis only you ●n buoy▪ up sinking Vertue, </l>
            <l>When such a Tryal comes. Let Pagan Fiends </l>
            <l>On Racks Distend me, Burn me, Tear my Limbs, </l>
            <l>I'd Smile, so you be safe. They cannot hurt me; </l>
            <l>But when they Pain you, then my Heart they'll Tear. </l>
            <l>Oh! at the Thought I shake, I bleed, I rave, and I dispair. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e24450">
            <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
            <l>I Glory in my Fate; then calm thy mind, </l>
            <l>Dear Man; I've only Tears to pay thy Worth, </l>
            <pb n="33" xml:id="ep000644-021-b"/>
            <l>But we shall meet in Heav'n at better Nuptials, </l>
            <l>There no bad Men shall interrupt our Joys. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e24510">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>Oh now you've rais'd my Soul from one Extream to t'other. </l>
            <l>I dare Rejoyce ev'n here. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e24550">Enter Officer. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e24560">
            <speaker>Officer. </speaker>
            <l>I'm bid to tell you, You must now attend </l>
            <l>T'appease our Gods, or Dye. 'Tis the last Summons. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e24600">
            <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
            <l>We come. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e24630">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>To Dye. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e24660">
            <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
            <l>To Triumph. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e24690">
            <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
            <l>Yes, my Bride. </l>
            <l>But, sure I first may claim a Chaste Endearment </l>
            <l>Due to a Bridegroom, and a Dying Friend. </l>
            <l>Yes, blushing Saint, and thus I seize the Blessing,— </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e24750">Kisses her. </stage>
            <l>My Soul is on the Wing to mix with Thine; </l>
            <l>Another Kiss, and they'd for ever joyn. </l>
            <l>Oh! since below we taste such Sweets in Love, </l>
            <l>How great, how vast must be our Joys above! </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e24800">Exeunt. </stage>
          <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000644-e24810">
            <head>SCENE. The Temple. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e24840">Enter King, Bramin, and Governour. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e24850">
              <speaker>King </speaker>
              <l>OH! yet delay your Pious Cruelty. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e24880">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>It makes me Weep to urge their Punishment, </l>
              <l>But ev'n your Crown's at stake, if 'tis deferr'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e24920">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>They come. I dread the Sight, yet still must try to win 'em. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e24950">Solemn Musick <hi>Enter a Procession of Barwins, as to the Sacrifice. </hi>Armusia and Quisara <hi>Wreath'd and Bound. Guards and Attendants. </hi>
            </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e24990">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>I force my self to see you thus, to save you. </l>
              <l>Sister, Armusia, Oh, once more I beg,— </l>
              <l>Save, save your Lives. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e25050">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Name not these Toys, when Heav'n's concern'd; For that, Sir, </l>
              <l>I cou'd forego ev'n her, and yet what's Life without her? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e25090">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>And I shou'd hate him, cou'd he love me more. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e25120">
              <speaker>Bra. </speaker>
              <l>Oh quick worship our Gods. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e25150">
              <pb n="34" xml:id="ep000644-022-a"/>
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>Oh Princess.— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e25180">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>No more. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e25210">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Away, deluding Men. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e25240">
              <speaker>Bra. </speaker>
              <l>Your Life,— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e25270">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Take it, Bramin. </l>
              <l>And all the Misery that shall attend it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e25320">
              <speaker>Bra. </speaker>
              <l>Make the Fires ready. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e25350">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Heav'n gives us Strength to dread 'em not. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e25380">
              <speaker>King </speaker>
              <l>Yet, Stay. </l>
              <l>What shall I do to save you, Stubborn Pair? </l>
              <l>Look on me, like the Criminal I beg, </l>
              <l>And Majesty is fled from me, to you. </l>
              <l>Why will you Kill me? Or, what's worse than Death, </l>
              <l>Afflict me thus? Oh you've no Pangs to dread </l>
              <l>More painful than I suffer. O submit— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e25470">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Save your mistaken Pity for your self, Sir. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e25500">
              <speaker>Bra. </speaker>
              <l>They must Dye instantly, they'll pervert all else. </l>
              <l>You see all's ready, Sir, then pray retire, </l>
              <l>Or we must Strike before your Eyes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e25550">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis hard, ye injur'd Powers! Must I permit you Justice? </l>
              <l>Oh Sister— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e25590">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Come, Grieve not, Sir! you wound my tender Soul. </l>
              <l>Farewel. And may our Deaths instruct you how to Live. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e25630">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Amazing Love, and Fortitude, and Zeal! </l>
              <l>And shall I let you Dye! </l>
              <l>Such Vertue, sure, deserves a better Fate. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e25680">Enter Messenger. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e25690">Guns let off at a distance. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e25700">
              <speaker>Mes. </speaker>
              <l>Arm, Sir! Seek for Defence. The Portuguese </l>
              <l>Fire from their Fort and Ships upon the Town. </l>
              <l>Gen'ral Ruidias sent t'inform us now </l>
              <l>He'll Beat it down, unless Armusia be set Free. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e25790">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Hah! Dares he do't? Must In-mates too Controul us? </l>
              <l>Ev'n in this Case I must Resent th'Insult; </l>
              <l>And, were I Rash, I wou'd Revenge it here. </l>
              <l>However, bear 'em back to Prison, Guards: </l>
              <l>And you demand a Parley. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e25860">Ex. All, except Governour. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e25870">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>Curst Event! Had now my Rival Fall'n, </l>
              <l>I'd yet found means to save her. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e25910">Exeunt. </stage>
          </div>
          <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000644-e25920">
            <pb n="35" xml:id="ep000644-022-b"/>
            <head>SCENE. The Town. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e25950">Enter several Townsmen. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e25960">
              <speaker>1 </speaker>
              <l>BLess us, what Thundering's here, what Fire-spitting. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e25990">
              <speaker>2 </speaker>
              <l>And how the Guns take the side of a House here, and the side of a House there, and mend them up again with another Ward. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26020">
              <speaker>3. </speaker>
              <l>I had the Roof of my House taken off with a Chain Shot, and in the twinkling of an Eye another clap't in the place on't. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26050">
              <speaker>2. </speaker>
              <l>That's a Gun I'll Swear. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26080">
              <speaker>1. </speaker>
              <l>You think he Lyes now, I ha' seen a Steeple taken off with a Chain Shot, and another put in the place on't, with Twenty Men Ringing the Bells. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26110">
              <speaker>3. </speaker>
              <l>Pish, what's that! I saw an Old Man's Head set upon a Young Man's Shoulders.— </l>
              <l>But, Woe be to the Potters, I saw a Hand-Granado in one of their Shops, just now, and the Pots, Pans, Pipkins, and Glasses, at Fisticuffs with it, at such a rate, you'd ha' Sworn, a whole Troop of Devils had been at Foot-Ball there. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26150">
              <speaker>1. </speaker>
              <l>For my part, I'm afraid we shall all find ourselves Knock'd o'th Head to Morrow Morning, as soon as we are awake. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26180">
              <speaker>Omnes. </speaker>
              <l>Like enough. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26210">
              <speaker>1. </speaker>
              <l>They've rid me of as good a Wife as a Man wou'd desire to part withall. I met a Hand with a Letter in't just now in post haste, and by and by Whiz comes the Leg after it, as if the Hand had forgot half it's Errand. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26240">
              <speaker>3. </speaker>
              <l>Ay. I saw the very Man that had lost these Goods, come Hopping upon his t'other Leg that was left, to raise a Hue and Cry after the Bullet that had Robb'd him of half himself. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26270">
              <speaker>2. </speaker>
              <l>Why, d'ye think there's any Law for these Cannon Bullets then? 1. Law! No. Prethee run to a Granado when it comes Piping Hot out of a Mortar-piece, and tell't you'll take the Law of him.— I do but think what Lane a Chain-shot wou'd make in the Law, and how like an Ass a Judge wou'd sit on the Bench with his Head shot off. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26300">
              <speaker>3. </speaker>
              <l>I must confess, to have one's Head shot off, wou'd put any man out of Countenance. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26330">
              <speaker>1. </speaker>
              <l>A Friend of mine lost his Head just now, a very Honest Fellow, a Taylor, and 'twas no sooner off, but a Lawyer's Head that no body own'd, dropt out of the Clouds, and settled upon honest Stiche's Shoulders; the Fellow's Ruin'd by't— for he never spoke a True Word since. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26370">
              <speaker>2. </speaker>
              <l>What shall we do? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26400">
              <speaker>1. </speaker>
              <l>Let's to the King in a Body, all and one, and desire him to Compound with the Foe for such Lambs as we want most in our Callings.— Let me see, Thou art a Fencer, thou shalt give thy Legs to secure thy Arms. Thou'rt a Dancer, thou shalt giue thy Head to secure thy Heels. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26430">
              <pb n="36" xml:id="ep000644-023-a"/>
              <speaker>3. </speaker>
              <l>Thou'rt a Cuckold, thou shalt give thy Horns to secure thy Head. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26460">
              <speaker>2. </speaker>
              <l>Lets about it instantly, and go to the King. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26490">
              <speaker>1. </speaker>
              <l>Aye, so he is not where the Bullets fly. If he be, I must desire his Majesty to come to me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26520">
              <speaker>Omn. </speaker>
              <l>Agreed, agreed. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e26550">A Gun is let off the first Townsman drops. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26560">
              <speaker>3. </speaker>
              <l>What's the matter, now.— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26590">
              <speaker>1. </speaker>
              <l>Oh I am Slain, let me be carried off quickly, before I come to my self, for I cannot indure to be Shot to Death, as I am a living Man. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e26620">Carried off. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e26630">Exeunt. </stage>
          </div>
          <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000644-e26640">
            <head>SCENE. A Field or broad place near the Fort. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e26670">
              <hi>Enter on one side King, Gov. Guards, &amp;c. </hi>Ruidias <hi>and the </hi>Portuguese. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26700">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>How dare you offer to prescribe us Laws </l>
              <l>Proud Portuguese, and thus abuse the Liberty </l>
              <l>My Predecessors gave you to fix here? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26760">
              <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
              <l>Thrice in my Prince's Name I sent to claim Armusia, </l>
              <l>And Thrice you by your Priests sent word you scorn'd the Summons. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26810">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>That was my work. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e26840">Aside. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26850">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Ha! Did they dare do this? Abuse my Name? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26880">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>Nay, then I must be quick. Despair assist me. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e26910">Aside </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e26920">Exit Gov. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26930">
              <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
              <l>Once more I claim him as my Prince's Subject. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e26960">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Our Priests too claim him from our injur'd Gods, </l>
              <l>He's Doom'd by them to Dye, nay, ev'n his Bride my Sister. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27000">
              <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
              <l>Curs'd are the Mouthes that doom'd 'em! Quickly save 'em. </l>
              <l>I'll hearken to no Terms till they're deliver'd: </l>
              <l>Ev'n you should pray me to do you that Justice, </l>
              <l>I'll pay the Debt of Honour, which I owe him, </l>
              <l>Do you the like, Sir, nor be still Deluded. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27070">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>But, Oh the Priests, the People! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27100">
              <speaker>Mes. </speaker>
              <l>The People, Sir, beg they may both be spar'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27130">
              <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
              <l>Then leave me, Sir, to take 'em from their Foes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27160">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>I can no longer what I wish oppose. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e27190">Exeunt </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e27200">
              <pb n="37" xml:id="ep000644-023-b"/>
              <hi>The Scene draws and discovers the Prison. The Governour dragging </hi>Quisara <hi>by the hair with a Dagger at her Brest. </hi>
            </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27230">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Help, help! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27260">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>Be dumb, or this shall make you so— be kind; </l>
              <l>I'm not the old Drone you think. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27300">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>O why d'you drag me thus? hold. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27330">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>I come not here to talk. I ev'n want Time </l>
              <l>To seek out my curst Rival, and with This— </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e27370">Enter Armusia <hi>in Chains</hi>. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27400">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Ha! Villan! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27430">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>Art thou here? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27460">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Oh save your self and me, run, call for help. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27490">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>Hold, if thou stir'st, I strike. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27520">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Oh Misery, oh horror! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27550">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>Stay, I'll ease thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27580">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Help, Murther, help. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e27610">Enter Ruidias <hi>and ali the </hi>Portuguese. The King with Guards. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27660">
              <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
              <l>Ha! Monster! Seize him— how! The Treach'rous Governor! </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e27690">Ruidias <hi>seizes the </hi>Gov. <hi>by his false Beard and Hair, which come off, and discover him. </hi>
            </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27720">
              <speaker>King </speaker>
              <l>What do I see! my cruel Enemy! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27750">
              <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
              <l>Art thou a Prophet? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27780">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>Curst Fortune! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27810">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Blest deliverance! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27840">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Surprising Change! </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e27870">
              <hi>They unbind </hi>Armusia. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27890">
              <speaker>King </speaker>
              <l>How have I been abus'd! ye gen'rous Souls, </l>
              <l>You've half perswaded me t'embrace your Faith. </l>
              <l>You're free. Be happy now. Haste to the Pallace, </l>
              <l>Let Sports and Mirth Revive; Feasts, Revels, Masques. </l>
              <l>Guards take that Fiend, and e're we punish him, </l>
              <l>Let the Croud see their Prophet. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e27970">
              <speaker>Gov. </speaker>
              <l>Confusion! Thirst of Revenge, and Frantic Love undo me. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e28000">Exit King, Gov. Guards <hi>and the </hi>Portuguese, <hi>all but </hi>Rui. and Arm. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e28050">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>How shall I thank you, Sir? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e28080">
              <speaker>Rui. </speaker>
              <l>I've scarce yet paid my debt, Sir. </l>
              <l>Thank your own Virtue and my Death to hopes, </l>
              <l>Dispair has murther'd Love. I still withstood your Right, </l>
              <l>While Honour gave me leave. No more; let's to the King. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e28140">Exit Ruidias. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e28160">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>O Princess still I doubt I dream, </l>
              <l>I dare not yet trust Fortune. </l>
              <pb n="38" xml:id="ep000644-024-a"/>
              <l>Still as I reach my hand She draws back her's, </l>
              <l>And snatches from me her deriding Favours. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e28220">
              <speaker>Qui. </speaker>
              <l>Oh, trust my heart, brave Man, that tells me now we're blest. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e28250">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>I must be so, 'twere now a Sin to doubt it. </l>
              <l>Yes, Pleasure comes too strong not to be real. </l>
              <l>I want a Name to call this Blessing by. </l>
              <l>Oh Fortune, like her Sex, is wisely coy, </l>
              <l>And deals us Sorrow but to raise our Joy. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e28320">Exeunt. </stage>
          </div>
          <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000644-e28330">
            <head>The SCENE changes to a Palace. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e28360">Enter King. Courtiers, Ruid. Pin. Portuguese, Guards, &amp;c. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e28390">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Come all, and share my Joys, Peace Reigns, the People pleased, </l>
              <l>I've punish'd my worst Foe, and sav'd the best of Friends. </l>
              <l>Let Music now resound. Begin the Sports </l>
              <l>To entertain our Court, while I and They, </l>
              <l>Too full of our new Joys to relish others, </l>
              <l>Look back with pleasing Horror on past dangers. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e28470">Enter Armusia and Quisara. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e28500">
              <speaker>Arm. </speaker>
              <l>Oh! Sir! accept my silent gratitude, words were not made to speak a Joy like mine. </l>
              <l>I cannot speak my Thanks. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e28540">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Rise, you're excus'd from words, </l>
              <l>You must have time to calm the stormy Bliss. </l>
              <l>Then leave awhile this bright Assembly here </l>
              <l>To Mirth and soft delights. </l>
              <l>We'll ease with Talk our Pangs of Joy within. </l>
              <l>Now spight of Subtle Foes all Danger's past, </l>
              <l>And Heav'n on Vertue showrs Rewards at last. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e28630">[Exeunt. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e28640">
              <hi>The End of the last </hi>ACT. </stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="song" xml:id="ep000644-e28660">
          <pb n="39" xml:id="ep000644-024-b"/>
          <head>The Four Seasons or Love in every Age. A Musical Interlude. Set to Music by Mr. <hi>Jeremy Clarke</hi>. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e28720">This Entertainment is perform'd at the End of the last Act, but was design'd for another Season, and another Occasion: And what is mark'd thus (") is omitted. </stage>
          <p>THe Overture is a Symphony, lofty, yet gay: At the latter part, it changes to a flat adagio; to which mournful Movement </p>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e28740">
            <speaker>Mr. Leveridge. </speaker>
            <l>
              <hi>The Genius of the Stage appears in a melancholic Posture, with attendants. </hi>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e28790">
            <speaker>Genius. </speaker>
            <l>" Mourn, drooping Seat of Pleasures, mourn. </l>
            <l>" Mourn what all others bless, the Summer's warm Return. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e28830">
            <speaker>Chorus. </speaker>
            <l>" <hi>Mourn, drooping Seat of Pleasures, mourn</hi>! </l>
            <l>" Thy darling Guests, thy fair, thy best Supports, </l>
            <l>" For rival Fields forsake our lovely Sports: </l>
            <l>" We grieve alone, while Birds and Shepherds Sing. </l>
            <l>" Alas, we bear a Winter in the Spring. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e28910">
            <speaker>Chorus. </speaker>
            <l>" Mourn, drooping Seat of Pleasures, Mourn! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e28940">
            <speaker>Mr. Freeman. </speaker>
            <l>
              <hi>While a gay March is perform'd </hi>Apollo appears. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e29000">
            <speaker>Apollo. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Rouse, rouse, ye tuneful Sons of Art! </l>
              <l>The Soul of Numbers and of Days, </l>
              <l>Infusing Life in ev'ry Part, </l>
              <l>Appears, your fainting hopes to raise. </l>
              <l>" Advance in Crouds, soft Pleasures, sprightly Joys, </l>
              <l>" Tune ev'ry Lyre, raise ev'ry voice. </l>
              <l>" Advance, soft Pleasures, sprightly Joys. </l>
              <l>" While your <ref target="A51499-e29110-b">* </ref>
                <note corresp="A51499-e29110-a" n="*" place="margin">* Mr. <hi>Henry Purcel</hi>. </note>Amphion plai'd, and Sung, </l>
              <l>" Your Thebes in decent Order sprung. </l>
              <l>" Let harmony be thus employ'd, </l>
              <l>" To raise what Discord has destroy'd; </l>
              <l>" And Musick, that ev'n Trees can move, </l>
              <l>" Shall draw the Fair from ev'ry Grove. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Revive, ev'ry Pleasure, and die, ev'ry Care! </l>
              <l>Ye Ages of Life, and ye Seasons appear! </l>
              <l>Show now, that, as Love in all Ages can warm, </l>
              <l>So Harmony here in all Seasons can charm. </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e29250">The Chorus repeat from </stage>
            <l>Revive, ev'ry Pleasure, and die ev'ry Care! &amp;c. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e29280">
            <pb n="40" xml:id="ep000644-025-a"/>
            <hi>While the Chorus repeat that verse, the Scene changes, and discovers the four Seasons, on four several Stages. The Genius and some of his Attendants withdraw. </hi>
          </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e29300">
            <speaker>Miss Campion. </speaker>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e29330">Enter a Girl of Thirteen or Fourteen years old. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e29340">
            <speaker>Girl. </speaker>
            <l>Must I a Girl for ever be! </l>
            <l>Will n'er my Mother marry me! </l>
            <l>They tell me I'm Pretty, </l>
            <l>They tell me I'm Witty: </l>
            <l>But when I would Marry, </l>
            <l>She cry's, I must tarry, </l>
            <l>Must I a Girl for ever be! </l>
            <l>Will ne're my Mother marry me! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e29440">
            <speaker>Mr. <hi>Magnes's Boy</hi>. </speaker>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e29470">Enter a Youth. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e29480">
            <speaker>Youth. </speaker>
            <l>Oh! Miss! The Spring is come again, </l>
            <l>The pretty Birds sing, bill, and cooe: </l>
            <l>All dance in Couples on the Green: </l>
            <l>'Tis time we shou'd be doing too. </l>
            <l>My Dear, let's marry; then will you and I, </l>
            <l>As Man and Wife togetherly. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e29560">
            <speaker>Girl. </speaker>
            <l>Peace, naughty Thing! I heard one say </l>
            <l>That Marriage is no Children's Play. </l>
            <l>Think you to have me for a Song? </l>
            <l>Besides, they tell me I'm too young: </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e29620">
            <speaker>Boy </speaker>
            <l>No, now to wed betimes is common: </l>
            <l>When e're you marry, you're a Woman. </l>
            <l>Come, I must have you, quickly too, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e29670">
            <speaker>Girl. </speaker>
            <l>Fy, why d'you make so much ado? </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e29700">he kisses her. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e29710">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <l>Fy, I'm asham'd! Fy, what d'you do? </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e29740">Both repeat their last Line together. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e29750">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <l>Be quiet, or I'll call my Mother. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e29780">
            <speaker>Girl. </speaker>
            <l>Nay, prethee, let me take another. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e29810">Both repeat their last Line together. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e29820">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <l>Another Kiss, and then— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e29850">
            <speaker>Girl. </speaker>
            <l>What then? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e29880">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <l>Another, and another. </l>
            <l>Come, never fear, you'll quickly know, </l>
            <l>Tho I am little, soon I'll grow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e29930">
            <speaker>Girl. </speaker>
            <l>Oh, no, no, no. Oh, no, no, no. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000644-e29960">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <l>Oh let us go. You'll find it so. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000644-e29990">They repeat their last Line together for a Chorus. </stage>
          <div type="dance" xml:id="ep000644-e30000">
            <pb n="41" xml:id="ep000644-025-b"/>
            <head>The Dance of Spring here. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e30020">Enter two young Lasses with Baskets of Flowers, and Nosegays in their hands. They Dance. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e30030">Enter to them two young Sparks, the Lasses, dancing, offer 'em Nosegays, curtisying, and smiling. The Sparks make love to 'em. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e30040">
              <speaker>Mrs. Lindsey. </speaker>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e30070">Enter a Country Lass with a Rake, as at Hay-making. </stage>
              <lg n="1">
                <head>1. </head>
                <l>" Oh Why thus alone must I pass the long day! </l>
                <l>" Were a Gentleman by, 'twere sweet to make hay, </l>
                <l>" And on the Grass coupled to jig it away. </l>
                <l>" I'll then go sell all, ev'n my Rake and my Pail, </l>
                <l>" To buy a high Topping, and hugeous long Tail. </l>
                <l>" Your Powder'd wild Bores will then all come to woo, </l>
                <l>" i'll learn how to flaunt it, and quickly come to, </l>
                <l>" And serve a Town Husband, as other Wives do. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg n="2">
                <head>2. </head>
                <l>" I hate a dull Clown who knows hardly what's what, </l>
                <l>" Who shrugging and grinning stands twirling his Hat, </l>
                <l>" Nor dares tell a Body what he wou'd be at. </l>
                <l>" With smoke and worse-Liquor he sots and he Feasts, </l>
                <l>" And instead of his Mistress he fondles his Beasts. </l>
                <l>" With his hands in his Pockets he whistling goes by, </l>
                <l>" Or by me on a Hay-cock he snoring does lie, </l>
                <l>" When the Booby much better himself might employ. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e30280">
              <speaker>Mr. Leveridge. </speaker>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e30310">Enter a Town-spark. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e30320">
              <speaker>Gent. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis sultry Weather, Pretty Maid, </l>
              <l>Come, let's retire to yonder shade. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e30360">She stands bashfully hiding her face. </stage>
              <l>Pray, why so shy? Why thus d'ye stand? </l>
              <l>Sure 'Tis no Crime to touch your hand. </l>
              <l>Oh let me take a civil kiss! </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e30400">She Curtsies when he kisses her. </stage>
              <l>What harm is there in doing this? </l>
              <l>Fy, why d'ye cover thus your Brest? </l>
              <pb n="42" xml:id="ep000644-026-a"/>
              <l>One Favour more, and then I'm blest. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e30440">She bashfully puts him off </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e30450">
              <speaker>Lass. </speaker>
              <l>Oh pray, Sir. </l>
              <l>Nay, nay, Sir. </l>
              <l>Oh fie, Sir. </l>
              <l>Oh why, Sir. </l>
              <l>Why do you </l>
              <l>Now pull me thus to you? </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e30530">Aside. </stage>
              <l>Oh what shall I say! </l>
              <l>When a Gentleman suiters 'tis hard to say nay— </l>
              <l>I'm e'en out of Breath; Oh, dear! what d'ye do? </l>
              <l>Good La! Is it thus that you Gentlefolks woo! </l>
              <l>Good, Sir, do not hold me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e30590">
              <speaker>Gent. </speaker>
              <l>Good Lass, do not fly. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e30620">
              <speaker>Lass. </speaker>
              <l>What good can I do you? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e30650">
              <speaker>Gent. </speaker>
              <l>Come yonder, we'll try. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e30680">
              <speaker>Lass. </speaker>
              <l>No, no; I can't find in my heart to comply. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e30710">
              <hi>Enter an </hi>African <hi>Lady, with Slaves who dance with Timbrels. A </hi>Negro <hi>Lord makes Love to her</hi>. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e30750">
              <speaker>Mr. Pate. </speaker>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e30780">Enter a Lusty Strapping Middle-ag'd Widow all in Mourning. She weeps and blubbers. </stage>
              <l>Oh my poor Husband! For ever he's gone! </l>
              <l>Alas! I'm undone. </l>
              <l>I sigh, and I moan. </l>
              <l>Must I these cold Nights lie alone! </l>
              <l>Alas! I'm undone— </l>
              <l>I did what I list: </l>
              <l>We kist, and we kist: </l>
              <l>But his Health soon he mist, </l>
              <l>And thro Business and Care he ceas'd to be gay; </l>
              <l>And at last, poor Soul! he dwindled away, </l>
              <l>We wrangled </l>
              <l>And jangled </l>
              <l>When in an ill mood, </l>
              <l>Yet often like Pigeons we bill'd and we coo'd. </l>
              <l>'Tis done. </l>
              <l>Oh! he's gone </l>
              <l>Alack, and alack </l>
              <l>I must now for ever do Penance in Black. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e30970">
              <pb n="43" xml:id="ep000644-026-b"/>
              <speaker>Mr. Leveridge. </speaker>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e31000">Enter a Drunken Officer, Reeling, he hickhups. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e31010">
              <speaker>Offi. </speaker>
              <l>Why, Widow, why Widow! What makes thee so sad? </l>
              <l>Art thou mad? </l>
              <l>If one Husband is gone, there are more to be had. </l>
              <l>Come, I'll be thy Hony!— Leave keeping a Pother, </l>
              <l>One Man like one Nail serves to drive out another. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e31080">
              <speaker>Wi. </speaker>
              <l>How! Talk so to me! What, think you I'd Wed? </l>
              <l>'Tis scarce a Month yet since my poor Hony's dead. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e31120">
              <speaker>Offi. </speaker>
              <l>A Month! 'Tis an Age. You're mad to delay. </l>
              <l>Most Widows now chuse e're the Funeral Day. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e31160">
              <speaker>Wi. </speaker>
              <l>Not I: I'll ne're do't. Fy, what would People say? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e31190">
              <speaker>Offi. </speaker>
              <l>They'll say, you're a Woman. Come, away with this Fan! </l>
              <l>See! See!— here's a Shape!— here's a Grace,— here's a Leg! here's a Man, </l>
              <l>I'll get thee with Twins, till a hundred and ten. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e31240">
              <speaker>Wi. </speaker>
              <l>You lie,— go, you'll talk at another rate then. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e31270">She pats him in a smiling way. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e31280">
              <speaker>Offi. </speaker>
              <l>Then try me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e31310">
              <speaker>Wi. </speaker>
              <l>Leave fooling. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e31340">
              <speaker>Offi. </speaker>
              <l>I'll do't by this Kiss. </l>
              <l>By this, this, and this! </l>
              <l>I'll be hang'd if I miss. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e31390">
              <speaker>Wi. </speaker>
              <l>Oh should I do this! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e31420">
              <speaker>Offi. </speaker>
              <l>Twill ease you of Pain. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e31450">
              <speaker>Wi. </speaker>
              <l>Go, you're a sad Man! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e31480">
              <speaker>Offi. </speaker>
              <l>I'll kill thee with Kindness. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e31510">
              <speaker>Wi. </speaker>
              <l>Ay, do if you can. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e31540">A French Country-woman with Grapes and other Fruits comes in, in Wooden Shoes, a French Vintage-maker makes Love to her in a Dance. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e31550">
              <pb n="44" xml:id="ep000644-027-a"/>
              <speaker>Mr. Crossfield. Mrs. Lindsey. Miss Campion. The Boy. </speaker>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e31600">While four of five Bars are perform'd by a Thorough Base, enter an Old Gentleman, in an Old-fashion'd Dress, following a Young Lass, or Girl, and pushing a Youth from her. An Old Woman, in an Old-fashion'd Dress, comes and Thrusts him away from the Young Couple, The Old Woman sings like one without Teeth. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e31610">
              <speaker>Old Wom. </speaker>
              <l>Hold good Mr. Fumble, Fy! What do your mean, </l>
              <l>To court my my Grand Daughter? She's scarce yet fifteen. </l>
              <l>And you H'usi'fe; why stay you? go get you to School. </l>
              <l>Your Baby go dandle, </l>
              <l>I'll handle </l>
              <l>This doating old Tool. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e31700">
              <speaker>Old Man. </speaker>
              <l>Hold, hold! </l>
              <l>Do not scold. </l>
              <l>With my Grandson go cooe. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e31750">He points to the Youth </stage>
              <l>You love him I know. </l>
              <l>Together go cooe! </l>
              <l>" Good Lad, prethee do. </l>
              <l>" Tho he's somewhat bashful, he'll quickly come to. </l>
              <l>I'm not yet so old, </l>
              <l>I long to be at her, to have and to hold. </l>
              <l>I'll wed thee, </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e31830">To the Girl. </stage>
              <l>I'll bed thee, </l>
              <l>I'll rouse thee, </l>
              <l>I'll touze thee, </l>
              <l>I'll give thee what's better and sweeter than Gold. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e31880">
              <speaker>Girl. </speaker>
              <l>No, no, you're too old. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e31910">
              <speaker>Old Man. </speaker>
              <l>Dear Girl, why so shy? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e31940">
              <speaker>Girl. </speaker>
              <l>Old Man why so bold? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e31970">
              <speaker>Old Wom. </speaker>
              <l>Good Lad, how d'you do? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e32000">
              <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
              <l>Ne're the better for You </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e32030">
              <speaker>Old. Wom. </speaker>
              <l>Hold! Boy! I am brisk yet. </l>
              <l>And gayly can frisk it </l>
              <l>I've yet three good Teeth, and a Stump. </l>
              <l>And see I can caper and jump; </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e32090">Jumps to the Boy. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e32100">
              <speaker>Old Man </speaker>
              <l>Why thus do you shun her? What makes you so bold? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e32130">
              <pb n="45" xml:id="ep000644-027-b"/>
              <speaker>Old Wom. </speaker>
              <l>Why thus do you shun him? What makes you so bold? </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e32160">To the Girl. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e32170">
              <speaker>Boy and Girl. </speaker>
              <l>Indeed you're too old. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e32200">
              <speaker>Old Man. </speaker>
              <l>I find 'tis in vain! </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e32230">To the Old Woman. </stage>
              <l>Come, no longer let's strain. </l>
              <l>Let the Young take the Young, Let the Old take the Old. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e32260">The Old Man goes and takes the Old Wom. by the hand, and she him, hugging one another. </stage>
              <l>We'll hug our selves warm, now the Weather is cold. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000644-e32280">All the four repeat the last two Lines as a Chorus. Enter a Dutch-woman with a Stove warming her self, her Cloaths lin'd with Furs. An Old Miser makes Love to her in a Dance. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000644-e32290">
              <speaker>Enter Cupid, who sings. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Come all, come all— <stage xml:id="ep000644-e32340">Enter the Ages and Seasons. </stage>
                </l>
                <l>" Let soft Desires your Heart engage, </l>
                <l>" 'Tis sweet to Love in ev'ry Age. </l>
                <l>" Ev'ry Season, ev'ry Creature, </l>
                <l>" Yeilds to Love, and courts his Joys. </l>
                <l>" None are Truer, none are Sweeter </l>
                <l>" When Discretion guides the Choice. </l>
                <l>" Cupid <hi>with the Four Ages and the Four Seasons, mingle in a Dance while the following Grand Chorus is sung. Grand Chorus of all the Voices and Instruments. </hi>
                </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Hail, Soul of Desire! </l>
                <l>Hail, Guide of the Year! </l>
                <l>All Ages you fire. </l>
                <l>All Seasons you cheer. </l>
                <l>Thus ever conspire, </l>
                <l>And reign ev'ry where. </l>
                <l>" Love blooms in our Spring. <stage xml:id="ep000644-e32520">The four Parts of Music answerable to the four Ages of Life and Seasons of the Year, sing each the Line that's suitable to them. </stage>
                </l>
                <l>" In our Summer it grows. </l>
                <l>" In our Autumn 'tis ripe. </l>
                <l>" In our Winter it glows. </l>
              </lg>
              <stage xml:id="ep000644-e32590">Then all together. </stage>
              <lg>
                <l>Hail, God of Desire! </l>
                <l>Hail, God of the Year! </l>
                <l>All Ages you fire. </l>
                <l>All Seasons you cheer. </l>
                <l>Thus ever conspire, </l>
                <l>And reign ev'ry where </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="epilogue" xml:id="ep000644-e32690">
        <pb n="46" xml:id="ep000644-028-a"/>
        <head>THE EPILOGUE. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000644-e32710">Enter Mr. Penkethman thrust forwards. </stage>
        <l>HOld, pray don't thrust me on— hold! I'm asham'd. </l>
        <l>Well, if I speak, the Op'ra will be damn'd. </l>
        <l>D'you think by me to get an act of Grace, </l>
        <l>And gain the Ladies with my Charming Face? </l>
        <l>No, I'm too Modest, and dread coming on, </l>
        <l>As a poor Poet dreads a hiss or dun. </l>
        <l>I doubt, no Epilogue will please the Town, </l>
        <l>Loose Jests and Smut are damnably cry'd down. </l>
        <l>Had <hi>Joe Haines </hi>sung one, h'has a way so winning, </l>
        <l>'T might pass perhaps, like fine Italian Singing. </l>
        <l>Then my best way is humbly thus to fall. </l>
        <stage xml:id="ep000644-e32870">Knock. </stage>
        <l>Good People, pray, our Op'ra do not mawl! </l>
        <l>With rueful Phiz I beg it of you all. </l>
        <l>Dear Friends above, for me do your Endeavour, </l>
        <l>Stand by me still: Now, now's the time, or never. </l>
        <l>Sure I at least the gentle Masks shall please, </l>
        <l>They can't deny a Man upon his Knees. </l>
        <l>To please the Beaux, I'll study new Grimaces, </l>
        <l>For they're bely'd, or they love ugly Faces. </l>
        <l>Their own, I mean, in their dear Looking-Glasses. </l>
        <l>To please you, Criticks, who fit here uneasy, </l>
        <l>I'll study— Nothing— for nothing e're cou'd please ye. </l>
        <stage xml:id="ep000644-e33000">Mrs. Rogers advances. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000644-e33020">
          <speaker>Mrs. Ro. </speaker>
          <l>Hold, Sir, methinks you better words might use. </l>
          <l>We should beg Favour, and Defects excuse. </l>
          <l>Pray let me try that less presuming Way, </l>
          <l>And humbly beg Indulgence, for the Play. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000644-e33090">
          <speaker>Mr. Penk. </speaker>
          <l>With all my heart, and so I'll sneak away. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000644-e33130">Exit. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000644-e33140">
          <speaker>Mrs. Rog. </speaker>
          <l>In altering Plays, there's an ungrateful Curse: </l>
          <l>Some still will say they're alter'd for the worse. </l>
          <pb n="47" xml:id="ep000644-028-b"/>
          <l>If ours be so, sure 'tis a Plot on us; </l>
          <l>For he that did it writes for t'other house: </l>
          <l>Perhaps he does so now two several ways; </l>
          <l>Those write for Them who bring us wretched Plays. </l>
          <l>If with his Stuff he meant our house to break, </l>
          <l>To disappoint him, kind Sirs, let it take. </l>
          <l>Let this Play live; then we stand bravely fixt, </l>
          <l>But let none come his third day, nor the sixth. </l>
          <l>To you, bright Beauties, all our Joys we owe, </l>
          <l>You're the kind Stars from whom our Blessings flow. </l>
          <l>Cheer'd by your Beams we boast a second Life, </l>
          <l>And Pleasure's doubled by a gen'rous Strife. </l>
          <l>To prop us now, new Favours on us show'r, </l>
          <l>And still be great in Mercy, as in Pow'r▪ </l>
        </sp>
      </div>
      <div type="publishers_advertisement" xml:id="ep000644-e33330">
        <pb xml:id="ep000644-029-a"/>
        <head>A Catalogue of Novells Printed for <hi>Richard Wellington </hi>at the Lute in St. Paul's Church-yard. </head>
        <list>
          <item>THe Drudge or Jealous Extravagant. </item>
          <item>Princess of Cleves. </item>
          <item>Nicerc●●s. A Novell. </item>
          <item>Agiatis Queen of Sparta. </item>
          <item>
            <hi>Mock Clelia</hi>. </item>
          <item>Revengeful Mistress. </item>
          <item>The Dutchess of <hi>Mazarines Memoirs </hi>written by her self. </item>
          <item>Pallace Royal, or the Amours of the French King. </item>
          <item>
            <hi>Cardinal Mazarines </hi>Letters. </item>
          <item>Count <hi>de Soisions</hi>. </item>
          <item>Chast Seraglio. </item>
          <item>Count <hi>de Amboise</hi>. </item>
          <item>
            <hi>Don Henrick</hi>. </item>
          <item>Court Secret. </item>
          <item>Fatal Beauty, or <hi>Agnes de Castro</hi>. </item>
          <item>Art of Making Love. </item>
          <item>Alcander. </item>
          <item>Neapolitan, or the Defender of his Mistress. </item>
          <item>Amours of Count Teckley. </item>
          <item>Don Sebastian. </item>
          <item>Rival Princess. </item>
          <item>Character of Love. </item>
          <item>Unhappy Lovers, or the Timmerous Fair one. </item>
          <item>Clytie. A Novel. </item>
          <item>Humours and Conversation of the Town. </item>
          <item>Rival Mother. A Novel. </item>
          <item>Casimir King of Poland. </item>
          <item>The Lovers Secretary. </item>
          <item>The Nuns Letters to a Cavileer. </item>
          <item>
            <foreign xml:lang="lat">Religio Laici</foreign>, in a Letter to Mr: Dryden. </item>
          <item>Intreagues and Gallantries of Christina Queen of Sweden. </item>
          <item>Gallant Ladies. A Novell. </item>
          <item>Princess of Fez. </item>
          <item>Count Gabalis. </item>
          <item>Homais Queen of Tunis. </item>
          <item>Life of the Duke of Guise. </item>
          <item>Unfortunate Hero. </item>
          <item>Irish Princess. </item>
          <item>Bassa of Buda. </item>
          <item>Amorous Abbess. </item>
          <item>Lisarda, or the Travels of Love, and Jealousy. </item>
          <item>Duke of Alancon and Queen Elizabeth. </item>
          <item>Amours of the Queen of Polonia. </item>
          <item>Hattigi King of Tameran. </item>
          <item>Pilgrim. </item>
          <item>Scanderbegg. </item>
          <item>Revived Fugitive. </item>
          <item>Lord Rochester's Familiar Letters, in 2 Voll. </item>
          <item>A Treatise of Education but especially of Young Gentlemen, by <hi>Obadiah Walker</hi>. </item>
          <item>The History of Polybius the Megalopilitan containing an Account of the Transactions of the whole World but principally of the Roman People during the 1 <hi>st. Punick </hi>War, Translated by Sir <hi>Henry Sheers </hi>and Mr. Dryden in 3 Vollums, the 3 d. never before Printed. </item>
          <item>Mrs. Behn's Novells in one Voll. </item>
          <item>Incognita, or Love and Duty Reconciled, by Mr. Congreve. </item>
        </list>
        <p>Where you may be also furnish'd with all sorts of Plays. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="supplied_by_editor">
        <head>Notes, typically marginal, from the original text</head>
        <div corresp="A51499-e1930" xml:id="ep000644-e1930-n">
          <head>Notes for div A51499-e1930</head>
        </div>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
