<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Triumphs of Reunited Britannia</title>
        <author>
<!--Munday, Anthony-->
          <persName>
            <forename>Anthony</forename>
            <surname>Munday</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <idno type="dracor" xml:base="https://dracor.org/id/">ep000209</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A07907.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="A07907-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull n="TCP source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">The triumphes of re-vnited Britania. Performed at the cost and charges of the Right Worship: Company of the Merchant-Tayulors, in honor of Sir Leonard Holliday kni: to solemnize his entrance as Lorde Mayor of the Citty of London, on Tuesday the 29. of October. 1605. Deuised and written by A. Mundy, cittizen and draper of London.</title>
                <author>Munday, Anthony, 1553-1633.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>12 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
                <date>2007 October (TCP phase 1)</date>
                <idno type="marc">99848241</idno>
                <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 18279.</idno>
                <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 218.</idno>
                <idno type="vid">13321</idno>
                <idno type="DLPS">A07907</idno>
                <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2240931592</idno>
                <availability>
                  <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
                </availability>
              </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
            <biblFull n="printed source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">The triumphes of re-vnited Britania. Performed at the cost and charges of the Right Worship: Company of the Merchant-Tayulors, in honor of Sir Leonard Holliday kni: to solemnize his entrance as Lorde Mayor of the Citty of London, on Tuesday the 29. of October. 1605. Deuised and written by A. Mundy, cittizen and draper of London.</title>
                <title type="alt">Triumphes of re-united Britania</title>
                <title type="alt">Triumphes of re-united Britania.</title>
                <author>Munday, Anthony, 1553-1633.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[24] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>By W. Jaggard,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication_date">[1605]</date>
                <date type="creation_date">1605</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>
                  <p>Mostly in verse.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Publictaion date from STC.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Signatures: A-C4.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</p>
                </note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
      <profileDesc>
        <particDesc>
          <listPerson>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-master">
              <persName>Master</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-mate">
              <persName>Mate</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-boy">
              <persName>Boy</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-britannia">
              <persName>Britannia</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-brute">
              <persName>Brute</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-loegria">
              <persName>Loegria</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-cambria">
              <persName>Cambria</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-albania">
              <persName>Albania</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-locrine">
              <persName>Locrine</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-camber">
              <persName>Camber</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-albanact">
              <persName>Albanact</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-troya_nova">
              <persName>Troya Nova</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-thamesis">
              <persName>Thamesis</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-savarne">
              <persName>Savarne</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-humber">
              <persName>Humber</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-pheme">
              <persName>Pheme</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-unassigned">
              <persName>Unassigned</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-eros">
              <persName>Eros</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-eleutheriotes">
              <persName>Eleutheriotes</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-sophrosyne">
              <persName>Sophrosyne</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-agnites">
              <persName>Agnites</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-hypomone">
              <persName>Hypomone</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-epimeleia">
              <persName>Epimeleia</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-neptune">
              <persName>Neptune</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000209-amphitrita">
              <persName>Amphitrita</persName>
            </person>
          </listPerson>
        </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1605">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000209-e100030">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000209-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000209-001-b"/>
        <p>THE TRIVMPHES of re-vnited BRITANIA. </p>
        <p>Performed at the cost and charges of the Right Worship: Company of the Merchant-Taylors, in honor of Sir Leonard Holliday kni: to solemnize his entrance as Lorde Mayor of the Citty of London, on Tuesday the 29. of October. 1605. </p>
        <p>Deuised and Written by A. Mundy, Cittizen and Draper of London. </p>
        <p>Printed at London by W. Jaggard. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="text" xml:id="ep000209-e100090">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000209-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000209-002-b"/>
        <head>The triumphes of re-vnited Brytannia. </head>
        <p>BEcause our present conceit, reacheth vnto the antiquitie of Brytaine, which (in many mindes) hath carried as many and variable opinions: I thought it not vnnecessary, (being thereto earnestly solicited) to speake somewhat concerning the estate of this our Countrey, euen from the very first originall, vntil her honourable attaining the name of Brytannia, and then lastlye how she became to be called England. Most Writers do agree, that after the Deluge, <ref target="A07907-e100110-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A07907-e100110-a" place="margin">A viterb. in coment. super 4 lib. Beros. de auti.. </note>Noah was the sole Monarch of all the World, and that hee deuided the dominion of the whole earth to his three sonnes: all Europe with the Isles therto belonging (wherein this our Isle of Brytaine was one among the rest) fell to the lot and possession of Iaphet his third sonne. Samothes the sixt sonne of Iaphet, <ref target="A07907-e100120-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A07907-e100120-a" place="margin">Wolfangus Lazius. </note>called by Moses Mesech, by others Dys, had for his portion the whole contrey lying between the Ryner of Rhene and the Pyrenian mountains, where he founded his kingdome of Celtica <ref target="A07907-e100130-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A07907-e100130-a" place="margin">I Bale cent. 1 </note>ouer his people called <pb xml:id="ep000209-003-a"/>Celtae, which name, by the opinion of Bale our Countrey man, was indifferent to them of Gallia, and vs of this Isle of Britaine. This Samothes being the first King ouer these people, of him came lineally these kings following: Magus, Sarron, Bruis and Bardus, all ruling seuerally ouer the Celts and Brytons, who were not then so called, but Samotheans, after the name of Samothes. Of Bardus, whoe, according to Berosus, was very famous for inuenting of Musicke and Duties, came an order of philosophicall Poets or Heralds, called Bardi, after his owne name, whose excellent qualities were of such power, as they coulde enforce armies of Enemies ready to fight fierce battell, to stand at a gaze, and forbeare their cruell intent, vntil these Bardes lefte singing, and went out of the battel: According to Lucane. lib. 1. <quote>
            <l>Vos quoque qui fortes animas belloque peremptas, </l>
            <l>Laudius in longum vates dimittitis aeuum, </l>
            <l>Plurima securi fudistis carmina Bardi. </l>
          </quote>Many of these Bards lined among the Britans, <ref target="A07907-e100180-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A07907-e100180-a" place="margin">I. Bale script. Brit cent. 2 I Prise. defens hist. Brit. Ca Caius de ant Cant lib. 1 John Leland filla. ant. dict. </note>before the birth of Christ, as Plenidius and Oronius. Since then, Thalestine, the two Merlins, Melkin, Elaskirion and others. Among the Welshmen nowe of late daies, Dauid Die, Iollo Gough, Dauid ap-Williams, and diuers others remayning yet amongest them, and called in their owne language Bardhes. </p>
        <p>Thus continued the name of Samothes the space of 310. <ref target="A07907-e100200-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A07907-e100200-a" place="margin">Neptune for his many ships called king or god of the Seas, and in regard of his great skil in Nauigation. </note>yeares, ti'l Neptune put his son Albion the Gyant in possession of this land, who subduing the Samotheans, called this Iland Albion after his owne name. Concerning the comming hither of Danaus <pb xml:id="ep000209-003-b"/>50. daughters, and that one of them shoulde be called Albina, and so the land to bee named by her: First, not any one of them was so named, neither do I thinke the storie so authentical, but doe hold Albions name for the truest. </p>
        <p>The Country thus peopled with Giantes, and continuing after the name of Albion for 600. years: Brute, (being directed by a vision in his sleepe, to finde out a country scituated in the West) with the remaines of his Troyan folowers, arriued and Landed at the hauen now called Totnes, the yeare of the world, 2850. after the destruction of Troy, 66. before the building of Rome 368. and 1116. before Christs natiuity. He, searching the land ouer from side to side, found it to be very fertile, and inhabited by vnciuil, monstrous huge men of stature, tearmed Grants, whom he with his bolde and resolued companions slew and destroyed. One of them named Goemagot or Gogmagog, exceeding the rest in strength and courag, Brute caused Corineus, one of his confederates, to wrastle with the said Goemagot at a place beside Douer, where the Grant hapned to break a tib in the side of Corineus, which so sharply incensed him, that redoubling his power to win the victory, he threw him headlong downe from off one of the Rocks, which place was after called Gogmagogs leape The Gyant being thus dispatched, in reward of this honourable piece of seruice, Brute gaue vnto Corineus a part of his lande, which according to his name, was, and yet is vnto this day, caled Cornwall. </p>
        <pb xml:id="ep000209-004-a"/>
        <p>Brute thus hauing the whole Land in his owne quiet possession, began to build a citty, neer to the side of the Riuer Thamesis, in the second yeare of his raign, which he named Troynouant, or as Humfrey Lhoyd saith, <ref target="A07907-e100230-b"/>
          <note anchored="true" corresp="A07907-e100230-a" place="margin">Gal. Mon. </note>Troinewith; which is, newe Troy: in remembrance of that famous citty Troy, whence hee and his people (for the greater part) were descended. Now beganne he to alter the name of the Iland, and according to his owne name, called it Brytaine, and caused all the inhabitantes to bee named Brytons, for a perpetuall memory, that he was the first bringer of them into this land. In this time he had by his wife faire Innogen, daughter to King Pandrasus king of the Greeks, three worthy sonnes, the first named Locrine, the second Camber, and the third Albanact, to which three (not long before his death) he deuided his whole kingdome in seuerall partitions, giuing to Locrine all that part which we know best by the name of England, then tearmed by him Loegria or Logres. To Camber he limitted the Countrey of Wales, called Cambria after his name, and deuided from Loegria by the riuer of Sauerne. To Albanact his third sonne, he appointed al the North part of the Ile, lying beyond the Riuer of Humber, then called Albania, now Scotland; and to that Riuer then Albania did reach. But since that time, the limits of Loegria were enlarged, first by the prowesse of the Romanes, then by our owne conquests, that the Twede on the one side, and the Solue on the other, were taken for the principal <pb xml:id="ep000209-004-b"/>boundes betweene vs and Scotland. </p>
        <p>After Brute, I finde not any other alteration of our Countryes name, vntill the raign of King Ecbert, who about the yeare of Grace 800. and the first of his raigne, gaue foorth an especiall Edict, dated at Winchester: that it shoulde be named Angles Land, or Angellandt, for which (in our time) we do pronounce it England. Nor can Hengyst the Saxon be the Father of this latter name, for Ecbert, because his ancestors descended from the Angles, one of the sixe Nations that came with the Saxons into Britaine, (for they were not all of one, but of diuers Countries, viz. Angles, Saxons, Germains, Switzers, Norwegians, Iutes, otherwise tearmed Iutons, Vites, Gothes, or Getes and Vandales, and all comprehended vnder the name of Saxons, beca because of Hengist the Saxon and his company, that first arriued here before any of the other) and thereto hauing now the Monarchy and preheminence, in manner of this whole Island, called the same after the name of the country, from whence he deriued his originall. So that neither Hengist, nor anye Qu. named Angla, or deriuation ab Angulo, is to be allowed before this sounde and sure authoritye. Thus much briefely concerning the names of our Countrey, now come wee to discourse the whole frame and body of our deuise, in this solemne triumph of re-vnited Brytannia. </p>
        <div type="part" xml:id="ep000209-e100250">
          <pb xml:id="ep000209-005-a"/>
          <head>The Shippe called the Royall EXCHANGE. </head>
          <sp who="#ep000209-master" xml:id="ep000209-e100260">
            <speaker>Maister. </speaker>
            <l>All hayle faire London, to behold thy Towers, </l>
            <l>After our voyage long and dangerous: </l>
            <l>Is Seamens comfort, thankes vnto those powers. </l>
            <l>That in all perils haue preserued vs. </l>
            <l>Our Royall Exchange hath made a rich returne, </l>
            <l>Laden with Spices, Silkes, and Indico, </l>
            <l>Our wines that for our absence long did mourne, </l>
            <l>Now find release from all their former woe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000209-mate" xml:id="ep000209-e100350">
            <speaker>Mate. </speaker>
            <l>Maister good newes, our Owner, as I heare, </l>
            <l>Is this day sworne in Londons Maioralty: </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000209-boy" xml:id="ep000209-e100380">
            <speaker>Boy. </speaker>
            <l>Maister tis true, for, see what troupes appeare, </l>
            <l>Of Cittizens, to beare him company. </l>
            <l>Harke how the Drums and Trumpets cheerely sound, </l>
            <l>To solemnize the triumph of this day, </l>
            <l>Shall we do nothing, but be idle found, </l>
            <l>On such a generall mirthfull Holyday? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000209-master" xml:id="ep000209-e100450">
            <speaker>Maister. </speaker>
            <l>Take of our Pepper, of our Cloues and Mace, </l>
            <l>And liberally bestow them round about, </l>
            <l>Tis our ships luggage, and in such a case, </l>
            <l>I know our Owner meanes to beare vs out. </l>
            <l>Then, in his honor: And that company, </l>
            <l>Whose loue and bounty this day doth declare, </l>
            <l>Hurle Boy, hurle Mate. And Gunner, see you ply </l>
            <l>Your Ordinance, and of fireworkes make no spare, </l>
            <l>To adde the very vttermost we may, </l>
            <l>To make this vp a cheerefull Holi-day. </l>
          </sp>
          <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="ep000209-e100570">
          <pb xml:id="ep000209-005-b"/>
          <head>The Lyon, and the Camell. </head>
          <p>ON the Lyon and Camell, we doe figuratiuely personate Neptune and his Queene Amphitrita, who first seated their sonne Albion in this land. And in them we figure Poetically, that as they then triumphed in their sonnes happy fortune, so now they cannot chuse but do the like, seeing what happy successe hath thereon ensued, to renowne this Countrey from time to time. And as times haue altred former harshe inciuilities, bringing the state to more perfect shape of Maiestie, so (as occasion serues) do they likewise laye their borrowed formes aside, and speak according to the nature of the present busines in hand, without any imputation of grosnesse or error, considering the lawes of Poesie grants such allowance and libertye. Corineus and Goemagot, appearing in the shape and proportion of huge Giants, for the more grace &amp; beauty of the show, we place as guides to Britaniaes mount, and being fetterd vnto it in chaines of golde, they seeme (as it were) to drawe the whole frame, shewing much enuy and contention, whoe shall exceed most in duty and seruice. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="ep000209-e100590">
          <head>The Pageant. </head>
          <p>ON a Mount triangular, as the Island of Britayne it selfe is described to bee, we seate in the Supreame place, vnder the shape <pb xml:id="ep000209-006-a"/>of a fayre and beautifull Nymph, Britania hir selfe accosted with Brutes deuided kingdoms, in the like female representations, Loegria, Cambria, and Albania. Brytania speaking to Brute her Conqueror, (who is seated somwhat lower, in the habite of an aduenturous warlike Troyan) tels him, that she had still continued her name of Albion, but for his conquest of her virgine honour, which since it was by heauen so appointed, she reckons it to be the very best of her fortunes. Brute shewes her, what height of happinesse she hath attained vnto by his victorie, being before a vast Wildernes, inhabited by Giantes, and a meere den of Monsters: Goemagot and his barbarous brood, being quite subdued, his ciuill followers, first taught her modest manners, and the meanes how to raigne as an Imperial lady, building his Troya noua by the riuer Thamesis, and beautifieng his land with other Citties beside. But then the three Virgin kingdomes seeme to reproue him, for his ouermuch fond loue to his sons, and deuiding her (who was one sole Monarchy) into three seueral estates, the hurt and inconuenience whereon ensuing, each one of them modestly deliuered vnto him. He staies their further progres in reproofe, by his and their now present reuyued condition, beeing raised againe by the powerfull vertue of Poesie (after such length of time) to behold Britaniaes former Felicity againe, and that the same Albania, where Humber slew his son Albanact, had bred a second Brute, by the blessed mariage of Margaret, eldest daughter to king Henrie <pb xml:id="ep000209-006-b"/>the seauenth, to Iames the fourth king of Scotland, of whom our second Brute (Royall king Iames) is truely and rightfully descended: by whose happye comming to the Crowne, England, Wales, &amp; Scotland, by the first Brute seuered and diuided, is in our second Brute re-united, and made one happy Britania again: Peace and quietnesse bringing that to passe, which warre nor any other meanes could attaine vnto. For ioy of which sacred Vnion and combination, Locrine, Camber, and Albanact, figured there also in their antique estates, deliuer vp theyr Crownes and Scepters, applauding the day of this long-wisht coniunction, and Troya-noua (now London) incites fair Thamesis, and the riuers that bounded the seuered kingdoms, (personated in faire and beautifull Nymphs) to sing Paeans and songs of tryumph, in honor of our second Brute, Royall King Iames. Thamesis, as Queene of all Britaines riuers, begins the triumphal course of solemne reioysing. Next her, Sauerne, that took her name of Sabrina, begotten by Locrine on faire Elstrid, and both mother and daughter were drowned in that riuer, by Guendolenaes command, the wife to Locrine, dooth the like. Lastly, Humber, whose name was deriued from Humber king of the Scythians, who being pursued by Locrine and Camber, in reuenge of theyr Brothers death, was inforced to leap into that Ryuer, and there drowned himselfe, of whom I finde these verses written. <quote>
              <l>Dum fugit obstat ei flumen submergitur illic, </l>
              <l>Deque suo tribuit nomine aquae. </l>
            </quote>
            <pb xml:id="ep000209-007-a"/>What further may be required, to expresse Britaniaes triumph more perfectly to the life, with al the other personages her seruants and attendantes, is more at large let downe in the seuerall speeches, which I haue hereto annexed as most meet &amp; conuenient. </p>
          <div type="subpart" xml:id="ep000209-e100640">
            <head>The speeches deliuered by the seuerall children, according to their degrees of seating in the PAGEANT. </head>
            <sp who="#ep000209-britannia" xml:id="ep000209-e100650">
              <speaker>Britannia. </speaker>
              <l>I that sometime was termed Albion, </l>
              <l>After the name of Neptunes valiant Sonne: </l>
              <l>Albion the Gyant, and so had still held on, </l>
              <l>But that my conquest, first by thee begun, </l>
              <l>Hath in fames Chronicle such honor woon, </l>
              <l>That thy first setting from Albania, <ref target="A07907-e100720-b"/>
                <note anchored="true" corresp="A07907-e100720-a" place="margin">Albania in Greece. </note>
              </l>
              <l>Crownd me thy virgin Queene Britania. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000209-brute" xml:id="ep000209-e100740">
              <speaker>BRVTE. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Wherein, recount thy height of happinesse, </l>
                <l>Thou that before my honord victorie, </l>
                <l>Wert as a base and oregrowne wildernes, </l>
                <l>Peopled With men of inciuility, </l>
                <l>Huge and stearne Gyants, keeping company </l>
                <l>With sauage monsters, thus was Albion then, </l>
                <l>Till I first furnisht thee with ciuill men. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Goentagot, and all his barbarous brood, </l>
                <l>(When he was foyld by Corineus hand,) </l>
                <l>Were quite subdued, and not one withstood </l>
                <l>My quiet prograce ouer all thy land, </l>
                <l>But, as sole Conqueror, I did commaund: </l>
                <l>And then from Albion did I change thy name, </l>
                <l>To Brutes Britania, still to hold the same. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <pb xml:id="ep000209-007-b"/>
                <l>Then built I my New Troy, in memorie </l>
                <l>Of whence I came, by Thanesis faire side, </l>
                <l>And nature giuing me posterity, </l>
                <l>Three worthy sonnes, not long before I died, </l>
                <l>My kingdome to them three I did deuide. </l>
                <l>And as in three parts I had set it downe, </l>
                <l>Each namde his seat, and each did weare a Crowne. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000209-loegria" xml:id="ep000209-e100990">
              <speaker>LOEGRIA. </speaker>
              <l>But she whom thou hadst made one Monarchy </l>
              <l>To be so seuerd, to thy sonnes might shew </l>
              <l>Some signe of loue, to her small courtesie, </l>
              <l>When three possesse what one did solie owe, </l>
              <l>It makes more waies to harme then many know. </l>
              <l>And so proou'd that deuision of the land, </l>
              <l>It brought in warie that hellish fierbrand. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000209-cambria" xml:id="ep000209-e101070">
              <speaker>CAMBRIA. </speaker>
              <l>The king of Hunnes entred Albania, </l>
              <l>Slew Albanact thy Sonne, and there bare sway, </l>
              <l>Till Locrine rose with valiant Cambria, </l>
              <l>And to reuendge their Brothers death made way, </l>
              <l>Which instantly they did without delay, </l>
              <l>And made that Riuer beare the proud kings name, </l>
              <l>That thus intruded, drownd him in the same. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000209-albania" xml:id="ep000209-e101150">
              <speaker>ALBANIA. </speaker>
              <l>Faire Elstrid taken in that fatall fight, </l>
              <l>And Locrines loue to her, wrong to his wife, </l>
              <l>Duke Corineus daughter, deare delight, </l>
              <l>That reft both her and Locrine of his life, </l>
              <l>Opened a gap to much more dismall strife, </l>
              <l>Of all which heauy haps there had bin none, </l>
              <l>Had Brute left me one gouernor alone. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000209-brute" xml:id="ep000209-e101230">
              <speaker>BRVTE. </speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>See, after so long slumbring in our toombes </l>
                <l>Such multitudes of yeares, rich poesie </l>
                <l>That does reuiue vs to fill vp these roomes </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000209-008-a"/>
                <l>And tell our former ages Historie, </l>
                <l>(The better to record Brutes memorie,) </l>
                <l>Turnes now our accents to another key, </l>
                <l>To tell olde Britaines new borne happy day. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>That seperation of her sinewed strength, </l>
                <l>Weeping so many hundred yeeres of woes </l>
                <l>Whereto that learned Barde dated long length </l>
                <l>Before those vlcerd wounds againe could close, <ref target="A07907-e101370-b"/>
                  <note anchored="true" corresp="A07907-e101370-a" place="margin">Merlyn, who propheted herof long agoe. </note>
                </l>
                <l>And reach vnto their former first dispose. </l>
                <l>Hath run his course thorough times sandie glasse, </l>
                <l>And brought the former happines that was. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Albania, Scotland, where my sonne was slaine </l>
                <l>And where my follies wretchednes began, </l>
                <l>Hath bred another Brute, that giues againe </l>
                <l>to Britaine her first name, he is the man </l>
                <l>On whose faire birth our elder wits did scan, </l>
                <l>Which Prophet-like seuenth Henry did forsee, </l>
                <l>Of whose faire childe comes Britaines vnitie. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>And what fierce war by no meanes could effect, </l>
                <l>To re-vnite those sundred lands in one, </l>
                <l>The hand of heauen did peacefully elect </l>
                <l>By mildest grace, to seat on Britaines throne </l>
                <l>This second Brute, then whom there else was none. </l>
                <l>Wales, England, Scotland, seuerd first by me: </l>
                <l>To knit againe in blessed vnity. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>For this Britannia tides in triumph thus, </l>
                <l>For this these Sister-kingdomes now shake hands, </l>
                <l>Brutes Troy, (now London) lookes most amorous </l>
                <l>And stands on tiptoe, telling forraine lands, </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000209-008-b"/>
                <l>So long as Seas beare ships, or shores haue sands: </l>
                <l>So long shall we in true deuotion pray, </l>
                <l>And praise high heauen for that most happy day. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000209-locrine" xml:id="ep000209-e101650">
              <speaker>LOCRINE. </speaker>
              <l>England, that first was cald Loegria, </l>
              <l>After my name, when I commanded heere: </l>
              <l>Giues backe hir due vnto Britannia, </l>
              <l>And doth her true borne sonne in right prefer, </l>
              <l>Before deuided rule, irreguler. </l>
              <l>Wishing my brethren in like sort resigne, </l>
              <l>A sacred vnion once more to combine. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000209-camber" xml:id="ep000209-e101730">
              <speaker>CAMBER. </speaker>
              <l>I yeelded long ago, and dyd in heart, </l>
              <l>Allow Britanniaes first created name, </l>
              <l>My true borne Brutes haue euer tooke her part </l>
              <l>And to their last houre will maintaine the same. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000209-albanact" xml:id="ep000209-e101780">
              <speaker>ALBANACT. </speaker>
              <l>It is no meruaile though you gladly yeeld, </l>
              <l>When the all-ruling power doth so commaund, </l>
              <l>I bring that Monarch now into the field, </l>
              <l>With peace and plenty in his sacred hand, </l>
              <l>To make Britannia one vnited land: </l>
              <l>And when I brought him, after times will say </l>
              <l>It was Britanniaes happy Holi-day. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000209-009-a"/>
            <sp who="#ep000209-troya_nova" xml:id="ep000209-e101860">
              <speaker>Troya Nova. </speaker>
              <l>Then you faire Swans in Thamesis that swim, </l>
              <l>And you chose o●se Nimphes that do delight to plaie </l>
              <l>On Humber and faire Sauerne, welcome him </l>
              <l>In Canz Canzons, Iigges and many a Roun-delay </l>
              <l>that from the North brought you this blessed day. </l>
              <l>And in one tuneful, harmonie lets sing, </l>
              <l>Welcome King Iames, welcome bright Britaines King. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000209-thamesis" xml:id="ep000209-e101940">
              <speaker>Thamesis. </speaker>
              <l>I that am Queene of all Britanniaes streames, </l>
              <l>The Oceans darling and endeard delight, </l>
              <l>that want on daily with the Sunnes guilt beames </l>
              <l>and ore my bosome suffer daie and night, </l>
              <l>Faire flotes of ships to saile in goodlie sight: </l>
              <l>Vnto my second Brute shall homelie sing, </l>
              <l>Welcome King Iames, welcome great Britaines King. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000209-savarne" xml:id="ep000209-e102020">
              <speaker>Savarne. </speaker>
              <l>Faire Elstrids and Sabrinaes fatall graue, </l>
              <l>(Whereby the name of Sauerne fell to me:) </l>
              <l>When Locrines Quendoline in anger gaue, </l>
              <l>My wombe to be their dismall tragedie, </l>
              <l>Whereof my Nymphes (as yet) talke mournfullie, </l>
              <l>Vnto my second Brute do likewise sing, </l>
              <l>Welcome King Iames, welcome great Britaines King. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000209-humber" xml:id="ep000209-e102100">
              <speaker>HVMBER. </speaker>
              <l>Proud Scithians Humber that slew Albanact, </l>
              <l>Whose brethren forest him to a shamefull flight, </l>
              <l>When in my watrie armes his lite I wrackt, </l>
              <l>I tooke his name, and kept it as my right, </l>
              <l>For which my Nymphes still dauncing in delight, </l>
              <l>With me these Peans and sweet Canzoni sing, </l>
              <l>Welcome King Iames, our second Brute and king. </l>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="ep000209-e102190">
          <pb xml:id="ep000209-009-b"/>
          <head>The Chariot. </head>
          <sp who="#ep000209-pheme" xml:id="ep000209-e102200">
            <speaker>Pheme </speaker>
            <stage xml:id="ep000209-e102210">Riding before it. </stage>
            <lg>
              <l>FAME that attends on Britaines Monarchy, </l>
              <l>Thus revnited to one state againe, </l>
              <l>Vshers this Chariot of true dignity, </l>
              <l>Wherein seauen kings that did in England raigne, </l>
              <l>These Royall vertues in their shields containe, </l>
              <l>Expressing what great grace each Maiesty, </l>
              <l>Gaue to the Marchant-Taylors Company </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>When they were first a Guilde, and bare the stile </l>
              <l>Of Taylors, and of Armorers beside </l>
              <l>Of the Linnen armorie: for no little while </l>
              <l>Were they so knowne, and daily did prouide, </l>
              <l>Those coats of armes that quaild our foe-mens pride </l>
              <l>When Englands bent-Bow, and the gray-goos wing </l>
              <l>Our many victories abroad did sing. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>From this employment for the States defence, </l>
              <l>Their ancient tytle first vnto them came, </l>
              <l>and then their following care and dilligence, </l>
              <l>Squarde them the way to order well and frame, </l>
              <l>all meanes to keepe their Guilde in honest fame. </l>
              <l>Now gratious vertues vnto you I leaue, </l>
              <l>What further fortunes Time did them bequeath. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000209-unassigned" xml:id="ep000209-e102460">
            <speaker>Tapesnotes. </speaker>
            <l>EDward the third, whose Noble name I beare, </l>
            <l>Hearing the Loue and royall amity, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000209-010-a"/>
            <l>That good report gaue of them euery where, </l>
            <l>Preseruing peace and kinde socitie, </l>
            <l>In his first yeare vnto this Companie, </l>
            <l>He gaue this Charter to confirme their Guilde: </l>
            <l>And they inioyd it, as his Highnesse wilde. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000209-eros" xml:id="ep000209-e102540">
            <speaker>EROS. </speaker>
            <l>To build this body on a stronger frame, </l>
            <l>Richard the second gaue authoritie, </l>
            <l>A Mayster and foure keepers they should name, </l>
            <l>and full elect to sway their mysterie, </l>
            <l>Granting them power to haue a Lyuerie, </l>
            <l>and hold a Feast on saint Iohn Baptist day, </l>
            <l>Yearelie for euer, as they do and may. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000209-eleutheriotes" xml:id="ep000209-e102620">
            <speaker>Eleutheriotes. </speaker>
            <l>To fortifie a worke so well begun, </l>
            <l>Henrie the fourth did liberally create: </l>
            <l>(Beside the former fauours to them doone,) </l>
            <l>Their Guilde a Brother-hood incorporate, </l>
            <l>And thought it no disgrace to his high state, </l>
            <l>To weare the Clothing of the Companie, </l>
            <l>A most Maiestike royall courtesie. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000209-sophrosyne" xml:id="ep000209-e102700">
            <speaker>Sophrosyne. </speaker>
            <l>Henry the fift my war-like Lord maintainde </l>
            <l>His fathers loue to this socyetie, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000209-agnites" xml:id="ep000209-e102730">
            <speaker>AGNITES. </speaker>
            <l>Of my sixt Henry they as freely gainde, </l>
            <l>all former graunts in self-same qualitie, </l>
            <l>He wore their clothing, milde and graciously: </l>
            <l>For Princes loose no part of dignity, </l>
            <l>In beeing affable, it addes to Maiesty. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000209-010-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000209-hypomone" xml:id="ep000209-e102790">
            <speaker>Hypomone. </speaker>
            <l>Thus long a Mayster and foure keepers stood. </l>
            <l>Till my fourth Edward changde the keepers name </l>
            <l>To Wardens: for the strength of Brother-hood, </l>
            <l>And thus at first Mayster and Wardens came. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000209-epimeleia" xml:id="ep000209-e102840">
            <speaker>Epimeleia. </speaker>
            <l>And for they traded, as no men did more, </l>
            <l>With forren Realmes, by clothes and Merchandize, </l>
            <l>Returning hither other Countries store, </l>
            <l>Of what might best be our commodities, </l>
            <l>Henry the seuenth a gracious king, and wise, </l>
            <l>To Merchant-Taylors did exchange their name: </l>
            <l>Since when, with credite they haue kept the same. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000209-pheme" xml:id="ep000209-e102920">
            <speaker>PHEME. </speaker>
            <l>But sacred Lady, deigne me so much grace, </l>
            <l>As tell me, why that seat is vnsupplied, </l>
            <l>Being the most eminent and chiefest place, </l>
            <l>With State, with Crowne and Scepter dignified? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000209-epimeleia" xml:id="ep000209-e102970">
            <speaker>Epimeleia. </speaker>
            <l>Haue our discourses (Pheme) let thee know, </l>
            <l>That seauen Kings haue borne free brethrens name, </l>
            <l>Of this Societie, and may not time bestow </l>
            <l>an eight, when Heauen shall so appoint the same? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000209-pheme" xml:id="ep000209-e103020">
            <speaker>PHEME. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>I finde recorded in my Register, </l>
              <l>Seauen Kings haue honord this Society: </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000209-011-a"/>
              <l>Fourteene great Dukes did willingly prefer, </l>
              <l>Their loue and kindnesse to this Company, </l>
              <l>Threescore eight Lords declarde like amitie, </l>
              <l>tearming themselues all brethren of this band, </l>
              <l>The verie worthiest Lordes in all the Land. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Three Dukes, three Earles, foure Lords of Noble name </l>
              <l>all in one yeare did ioyne in Brother-hood: </l>
            </lg>
            <p>IN the yeare 1390. Edward Duke of Yorke. Thomas, Duke of Glocester. Henry Duke of Hereford and Earle of Darby, who afterward was K. Henry the fourth. Edward, Earle of Rutlande. Thomas Earle of Warwick. Iohn Holland, Earle of Huntingdon. Iohn, Lord Rose. Rafe Lord Nevill. Thomas L. Furniuall. Reignald, Lord Gray of Rithin. </p>
            <lg>
              <l>I finde beside great Lords from France there came </l>
              <l>To hold like league, and do them any good: </l>
            </lg>
            <p>Gaylard, Lord Danuers. Barard, Lord Delamote, Barard, Lord Montferrant, &amp;c. </p>
            <lg>
              <l>Yet no imbasing to their heigth in bloud: </l>
              <l>For they accounted honor then most hie, </l>
              <l>When it was held vp by communitie. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Of Bishops, Knights and Deanes, to those before, </l>
              <l>(Not spoke in vaunt, or any spirit of pride) </l>
              <l>My Records could affoord as many more, </l>
              <l>All Brethren, Marchant-Taylors signified </l>
              <l>That liu'de in loue with them, and when they dide </l>
              <l>Left me their names, to aftertimes to tell, </l>
              <l>Thus then they did, and thought it good and well. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000209-011-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000209-neptune" xml:id="ep000209-e103310">
            <speaker>Neptune on the Lyon. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>MY borrowed name of Neptune now I leaue, </l>
              <l>the like doth Amphitrita my faire Queene, </l>
              <l>And worthy Lord, grant fauour to receiue </l>
              <l>What in these mysteries we seeme to meane, </l>
              <l>Britanniaes glorie hath beene heard and seene, </l>
              <l>Reuiu'de from her old Chaos of distresse, </l>
              <l>and now vnited in firme happinesse. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Blest be that second Brute Iames our dread king, </l>
              <l>that set this wreath of Vnion on her head, </l>
              <l>Whose verie name did heauenlie comfort bring, </l>
              <l>When in despaire our hopes lay drooping dead, </l>
              <l>When comfort from most harts was gon and fled, </l>
              <l>Immediatlie the trumpets toong did say, </l>
              <l>God saue king Iames: Oh twas a happie daie. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000209-amphitrita" xml:id="ep000209-e103480">
            <speaker>Amphitrita. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>OVr latest Phaenix whose dead cinders shine, </l>
              <l>In Angels spheres, she, like a mother milde, </l>
              <l>yeelding to Nature, did her right resigne </l>
              <l>To times true heyre, her God-son, and lou'de childe, </l>
              <l>When giddy expectation was beguilde: </l>
              <l>And Scotland yeelded out of Teudors race, </l>
              <l>a true borne bud, to sit in Teudors place. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Which seat to him and his, heauen euer blesse, </l>
              <l>that we nere want a Rose of Teudors tree, </l>
              <l>to maintaine Britaines future happinesse, </l>
              <l>to the worldes end in true tranquilitie. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000209-012-a"/>
          <sp who="#ep000209-neptune" xml:id="ep000209-e103620">
            <speaker>Neptune. </speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Sir Leonard Holiday, now vnto thee, </l>
              <l>My loue in some meane measure let me shew, </l>
              <l>Since heauen hath cald thee to this dignity, </l>
              <l>Which (then my selfe) farre better thou doest est know, </l>
              <l>I make no doubt thou wilt thy time bestow, </l>
              <l>A fits s so great a Subiects place as this, </l>
              <l>To gouerne iustlie, and amend each misse. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Bethink thee how on that high Holyday, </l>
              <l>Which beares Gods Champion, th'Arch-angels name, </l>
              <l>When conquering Sathan in a glorious fray, </l>
              <l>Michaell Hels-monster nobly ouercame, </l>
              <l>And now a sacred Saboath being the same, </l>
              <l>A free and full election on all parts, </l>
              <l>Made choise of thee, both with their hands and harts. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Albeit this day is vsuall euery yeare, </l>
              <l>For new election of a Magistrate, </l>
              <l>Yet, now to me some instance doth appeare, </l>
              <l>Worth note, which to my selfe I thus relate, </l>
              <l>Holyday, cald on Holyday to state, </l>
              <l>Requiers methinks a yeare of Holydayes, </l>
              <l>To be disposd in good and vertuous wayes. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>For I account tis a Lords Holyday, </l>
              <l>When Iustice shines in perfect Maiesty, </l>
              <l>When as the poor can to the rich man say, </l>
              <l>The Maiestrate hath giuen vs equity, </l>
              <l>And lent no eare to partiality, </l>
              <l>When sinne is punisht, lewdnes beares no sway: </l>
              <l>All that day long, each day is Holyday. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000209-012-b"/>
              <l>When good prouision for the poore is made, </l>
              <l>Sloth set to labour, vice curbd euery where, </l>
              <l>When through the Citty euery honest trade, </l>
              <l>Stands not of might or insolence in feare, </l>
              <l>But Iustice in their goodnesse does them beare: </l>
              <l>then, as before, in safety I may saie: </l>
              <l>All that yeare long, each daie is Holliday. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Now in behalfe of that Societie, </l>
              <l>Whereof thou bear'st a louing brothers name, </l>
              <l>What hath bin doon this day to dignifie, </l>
              <l>they pray thee kindly to accept the same, </l>
              <l>More circumstance I shall not need to frame: </l>
              <l>But from the Marchant-Taylors this I say, </l>
              <l>They wish all good to Leonard Holliday. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="supplied_by_editor">
        <head>Notes, typically marginal, from the original text</head>
        <div corresp="A07907-e100090" xml:id="ep000209-e100090-n">
          <head>Notes for div A07907-e100090</head>
        </div>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
