<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Preface to Seneca's Ten Tragedies</title>
        <author>
<!--Newton, Thomas-->
          <persName>
            <forename>Thomas</forename>
            <surname>Newton</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <idno type="dracor" xml:base="https://dracor.org/id/">ep000246</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A11909_00.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="A11909-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull n="TCP source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">Seneca his tenne tragedies, translated into Englysh.</title>
                <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus, ca. 4 B.C.-65 A.D.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>225 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
                <date>2007 October (TCP phase 1)</date>
                <idno type="marc">99852323</idno>
                <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 22221.</idno>
                <idno type="stc">Greg, III, p. 1105-6.</idno>
                <idno type="vid">17639</idno>
                <idno type="DLPS">A11909</idno>
                <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2248540344</idno>
                <availability>
                  <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
                </availability>
              </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
            <biblFull n="printed source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">Seneca his tenne tragedies, translated into Englysh.</title>
                <title type="alt">Tragedies. English</title>
                <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus, ca. 4 B.C.-65 A.D.</author>
                <author>Heywood, Jasper, 1535-1598,</author>
                <author>Neville, Alexander, 1544-1614,</author>
                <author>Studley, John, 1545?-1590?,</author>
                <author>T. N. d. 1617,</author>
                <author>Newton, Thomas, 1542?-1607.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[4], 65, 64-217, [1] leaves.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>In Fleetstreete neere vnto Saincte Dunstans church by Thomas Marsh,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication_date">1581.</date>
                <date type="creation_date">1581</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>
                  <p>Editor's dedication signed: Thomas Newton.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>In verse.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>A reprinting of the following translations previously published separately: "Hercules furens", "Thyestes", and "Troas" by Jasper Heywood; "¦edipus" by Alexander Neville (a revised version); "Medea" and "Agamemnon" by John Studley; and "Octavia" (not by Seneca) by Thomas Nuce. Prints for the first time "Hippolytus" and "Hercules Oetæus" translated by Studley, and "Thebais" translated by Thomas Newton.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A"; the last leaf is blank.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
                </note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1581">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A11909-e100030">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="A11909-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="A11909-001-b"/>
        <p>SENECA HIS TENNE TRAGEDIES, TRANSLATED INTO Englysh. </p>
        <p>Mercurij nutrices, horae. </p>
        <p>IMPRINTED AT LONDON IN Fleetstreete neere vnto Saincte Dunstans church by Thomas Marsh. 1581 </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="A11909-e100070">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="A11909-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="A11909-002-b"/>
        <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPEVL, SIR THOMAS HENNEAGE KNIGHT, TREASVRER OF HER MAIESTIES CHAMBER: Thomas Newton wisheth all abundaunce of Felicitie, and Spirituall benedictions in Christe.⁂ </head>
        <p>YOV may think Sir, some want of discretion in mee, for thus boldly presuminge to thrust into your handes these Tragedies of SENECA. From whych boldnesse, the very Conscience of myne own vnworthynes, might easely haue dissuaded mee, had not certayne learned Gentlemen of good credite and worship thereunto persuaded &amp; animated mee. Assuring mee (where of I thought my selfe afore assured) that your Worship (such is your loue to learning, &amp; the generosity of your Heroicall mynde) would daygne not onely to dispence with my temerity, but also take in worth my affectionate simplicity. And yet (all this notwithstandinge) well durst I not haue geuen the aduenture to approch your presence, vpon trust of any singularity, that in this Booke hath vnskilfully dropped out of myne owne penne, but that I hoped the perfection of others artificiall workmanship, that haue trauayled herein aswell as my selfe should somewhat couer my nakednèsse 〈◊〉 pùrchase my pardon. And hard were <pb xml:id="A11909-003-a"/>the dealing, if in payment of a good round gubbe of Gold of full wayght and poyse, one poore peece somewhat clypped and lighter then his fellowes may not be foysted in among the rest, and passe in pay for currant coigne. Theirs I know to be deliuered with singuler dexterity: myne, I confesse to be an vnflidge nestling, vnhable to flye: an vnnatural abortion, and an vnperfect Embryon: neyther throughlye laboured at Aristophanes and Cleanthes candle, neither yet exactly waighed in Critolaus his precise ballance. Yet this dare I saye, I haue deliuered myne Authors meaning with as much perspicuity, as so meane a Scholler, out of so meane a stoare, in so smal a time, and vpon so short a warning was well able to performe. And whereas it is by some squeymish Areopagites surmyzed, that the readinge of these Tragedies, being enterlarded with many Phrases and sentences, literally tending (at the first sight) some time to the prayse of Ambition, sometyme to the mayntenaunce of cruelty, now and then to the approbation of incontinencie, and here and there to the ratification of tyranny, can not be digested without great daunger of infection: to omit all other reasons, if it might please than with no forestalled iudgment, to mark and consider the circumstaunces, why, where, &amp; by what maner of persons such sentences are pronounced, they cannot in any equity otherwise choose, but find good cause ynough to leade them to a more fauourable and milde resolution. For it may not at any hand be thought and deemed the direct meaning of SÈNECA himselfe, whose whole wrytinges (penned with a peerelesse sublimity and loftinesse of Style, are so farre from còuntenauncing Vice, that I doubt whether there bee any amonge all the Catalogue of Heathen wryters, that with more grauity <pb xml:id="A11909-003-b"/>of Philosophicall sentences, more waightynes of sappy words, or greater authority of sound matter beateth down sinne, loose lyfe, dissolute dealinge, and vnbrydled sensuality: or that more sensibly, pithily, and bytingly layeth downe the guerdon of filthy lust, cloaked dissimulation &amp; odious treachery: which is the dryft, wherunto he leueleth the whole yssue of ech one of his Tragedies. Howsoeuer &amp; whatsoeuer it be, your Worships curteous acceptaunce shal easily counterpoyse any of our imperfections. Vnto whose learned Censure, wee humbly submit these the exercises of our blusshing Muses. The Lord God in mercy long preserue you in health and dignity with daily encrease of many his gracious gyfts, already rychly abounding in you: to the propagation, and aduauncement of his truth (whereof yee are a zealous Professor, to the honoure of her Maiestye, to whom you are a most loyall seruitour, and to the generall benefite of your Countrey, whereof you are a rare and most worthy Ornament. </p>
        <closer>
          <dateline>From Butley in Chesshyre <date>the 24. of Aprill. 1581. </date>
          </dateline>
          <signed>Your Worshippes most humble, Thomas Newton. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="table" xml:id="A11909-e100130">
        <pb xml:id="A11909-004-a"/>
        <head>THE NAMES OF THE TRAGEDIES OF SENECA, AND by whom each of them was translated. </head>
        <list>
          <item>1 Hercules Furens, </item>
          <item>2 Thyestes, </item>
          <item>6 Troas, <list>
              <item>By Iasper Heywood. </item>
              <item>1560. </item>
            </list>
          </item>
          <item>5 Oedipus, <list>
              <item>By Alex Neuile. </item>
            </list>
          </item>
          <item>4 Hippolytus, </item>
          <item>7 Medea, </item>
          <item>8 Agamemnon, </item>
          <item>10 Hercules Oetaeus <list>
              <item>By Iohn Studley. </item>
            </list>
          </item>
          <item>9 Octauia, <list>
              <item>By T. Nuce. </item>
            </list>
          </item>
          <item>3 Thebais. <list>
              <item>By Thomas Newton. </item>
            </list>
          </item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-digit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber. A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a keyword in context.</p>
        <note target="A11909-002-b-1730">
          <label>A11909_00-002-b-1730</label>
          <sic>vnski●fully</sic>
          <seg>any singularity , that in this Booke hath</seg>
          <corr>vnskilfully</corr>
          <seg>dropped out of myne owne penne , but that</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A11909-003-a-0970">
          <label>A11909_00-003-a-0970</label>
          <sic>ballaūce</sic>
          <seg>exactly waighed in Critolaus his precise</seg>
          <corr>ballance</corr>
          <seg>. Yet this dare I saye , I haue deliuered</seg>
        </note>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
