<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000801" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Clyomon and Clamydes</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>George</forename>
            <surname>Peele</surname>
          </persName>
          <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q704626</idno>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A69121.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="A69121-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull n="TCP source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">The historie of the tvvo valiant knights, Syr Clyomon Knight of the Golden Sheeld, sonne to the King of Denmarke: and Clamydes the white Knight, sonne to the King of Suauia As it hath bene sundry times acted by her Maiesties Players.</title>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
                <date>2008 September (TCP phase 1)</date>
                <idno type="marc">AUA7872</idno>
                <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 5450a</idno>
                <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 157</idno>
                <idno type="vid">10869</idno>
                <idno type="DLPS">A69121</idno>
                <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2264197379</idno>
                <availability>
                  <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
                </availability>
              </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
            <biblFull n="printed source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">The historie of the tvvo valiant knights, Syr Clyomon Knight of the Golden Sheeld, sonne to the King of Denmarke: and Clamydes the white Knight, sonne to the King of Suauia As it hath bene sundry times acted by her Maiesties Players.</title>
                <title type="alt">Historie of the two valiant knights, Syr Clyomon Knight of the Golden Sheeld, sonne to the King of Denmarke: and Clamydes the white Knight, sonne to the King of Suavia</title>
                <title type="alt">Historie of Clyomon Knight of the golden Sheeld.</title>
                <title type="alt">Sir Clyomon and Sir Clamydes.</title>
                <title type="alt">Historie of the two valiant knights, Syr Clyomon Knight of the Golden Sheeld, sonne to the King of Denmarke: and Clamydes the white Knight, sonne to the King of Suavia.</title>
                <author>Peele, George, 1556-1596,</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[68] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Printed by Thomas Creede,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication_date">1599.</date>
                <date type="creation_date">1599</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>
                  <p>Erroneously attributed to George Peele.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>In verse.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Signatures: A-HÛp4Ûs IÛp2Ûs .</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A"; the last leaf is blank.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Running title reads: The historie of Clyomon Knight of the golden Sheeld.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Identified as STC 19538 on UMI microfilm reel 348.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Reproductions of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Appears at reel 348 ± and reel 1022 #5 (same copy filmed twice).</p>
                </note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-clamydes">
            <persName>Clamydes</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-juliana">
            <persName>Juliana</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-clyomon">
            <persName>Clyomon</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-shift">
            <persName>Shift</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-king">
            <persName>King</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-1">
            <persName>1</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-2">
            <persName>2</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-all">
            <persName>All</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-alexander">
            <persName>Alexander</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-omnes">
            <persName>Omnes</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-bryan">
            <persName>Bryan</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-boatswain">
            <persName>Boatswain</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-neronis">
            <persName>Neronis</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-ambo">
            <persName>Ambo</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-thrasellus">
            <persName>Thrasellus</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-knight">
            <persName>Knight</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-corin">
            <persName>Corin</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-coryn">
            <persName>Coryn</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-provi">
            <persName>Provi</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-mustantius">
            <persName>Mustantius</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-queen">
            <persName>Queen</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-page">
            <persName>Page</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-unassigned">
            <persName>Unassigned</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-both">
            <persName>Both</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-lord">
            <persName>Lord</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000801-knowledge">
            <persName>Knowledge</persName>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1599">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
    <listRelation>
      <relation name="wikidata"
                   active="https://dracor.org/entity/ep000801"
                   passive="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q7526354"/>
    </listRelation>
  </standOff>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000801-e100030">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000801-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-001-b"/>
        <p>THE HISTORIE OF the two valiant Knights, Syr Clyomon Knight of the Golden Sheeld, sonne to the King of Denmarke: </p>
        <p>And Clamydes the white Knight, sonne to the King of Suauia. </p>
        <p>As it hath bene sundry times Acted by her Maiesties Players. </p>
        <p>
          <figure>
            <p>VIRESSIT VVLNERE VERITAS </p>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <p>LONDON Printed by Thomas Creede. 1599. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="prologue" xml:id="ep000801-e100110">
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-002-a"/>
        <head>The Prologue. </head>
        <l>AS lately lifting vp the leaues of worthy writers workes, </l>
        <l>Wherein the Noble acts and deeds of many hidden lurks, </l>
        <l>Our Author he hath found the Glasse of glory shining bright, </l>
        <l>Wherein their liues are to be seene, which honour did delight, </l>
        <l>To be a Lanthorne vnto those which dayly do desire, </l>
        <l>Apollos Garland by desert, in time for to aspire, </l>
        <l>Wherein the froward chances oft, of Fortune you shall see, </l>
        <l>Wherein the chearefull countenance, of good successes bee: </l>
        <l>Wherein true Louers findeth ioy, with hugie heapes of care, </l>
        <l>Wherein as well as famous facts ignomius placed are: </l>
        <l>Wherein the iust reward of both, is manifestly showne, </l>
        <l>That vertue from the roote of vice, might openly be knowne. </l>
        <l>And doubting nought right Courteous all, in your accustomed woont </l>
        <l>And gentle eares, our Author he, is prest to bide the brunt </l>
        <l>Of bablers tongues, to whom he thinks, as frustrate all his toile, </l>
        <l>As peereles taste to filthy Swine, which in the mire doth moile. </l>
        <l>Well, what he hath done for your delight, he gaue not me in charge, </l>
        <l>The Actors come, who shall expresse the same to you at large. </l>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="text" xml:id="ep000801-e100310">
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-002-b"/>
        <head>THE HISTORIE OF Sir Clyomon Knight of the golden Sheeld, son to the King of Denmark: And Clamydes the white Knight, sonne to the King of Swauia. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e100320">Enter Clamydes. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e100330">
          <speaker>CLamy. </speaker>
          <l>As to the wearie wandring wights, whom waltring waues enuirō, </l>
          <l>No greater ioy of ioyes may be, then when from out the Ocean </l>
          <l>They may behold the Altitude of Billowes to abate, </l>
          <l>For to obserue the Longitude of Seas in former rate. </l>
          <l>And hauing then the latitude of Sea-roome for to passe, </l>
          <l>Their ioy is greater through the griefe, then erst before it was. </l>
          <l>So likewise I Clamydes, Prince of Swauia Noble soyle, </l>
          <l>Bringing my Barke to Denmarke here, to bide the bitter broyle: </l>
          <l>And beating blowes of Billowes high, while raging stormes did last, </l>
          <l>My griefes was greater then might be, but tempests ouerpast, </l>
          <l>Such gentle calmes ensued hath, as makes my ioyes more </l>
          <l>Through terror of the former feare, then erst it was before. </l>
          <l>So that I sit in safetie, as Sea-man vnder shrowdes, </l>
          <l>When he perceiues the stormes be past, through vanquishing of Clowdes. </l>
          <l>For why, the doubtfull care that draue me off, in daunger to preuaile, </l>
          <l>Is dasht through bearing lesser braine, and keeping vnder saile: </l>
          <l>So that I haue through trauell long, at last possest the place </l>
          <l>Whereas my Barke in harbour safe, doth pleasures great embrace: </l>
          <l>And hath such license limited, as heart can seeme to aske, </l>
          <l>To go and come, of custome free, or any other taske. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-003-a"/>
          <l>I meane by Iuliana she, that blaze of bewties breeding, </l>
          <l>And for her noble gifts of grace, all other dames exceeding: </l>
          <l>Shee hath from bondage set me free, and freed, yet still bound </l>
          <l>To her, aboue all other Dames that liues vpon the ground: </l>
          <l>For had not she bene mercifull, my ship had rusht on Rocks, </l>
          <l>And so decayed amids the stormes, through force of clubbish knocks: </l>
          <l>But when she saw the daunger great, where subiect I did stand, </l>
          <l>In bringing of my silly Barke, full fraught from out my land, </l>
          <l>She like a meeke and modest Dame, what should I else say more? </l>
          <l>Did me permit with full consent, to land vpon her shore: </l>
          <l>Vpon true promise that I would, here faithfull still remaine, </l>
          <l>And that performe which she had vowed, for those that should obtaine </l>
          <l>Her princely person to possesse, which thing to know I stay, </l>
          <l>And then aduenturously for her, to passe vpon my way. </l>
          <l>Loe where she comes, ah peereles Dame, my Iuliana deare. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e100690">Enter Iuliana with a white Sheeld. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-juliana" xml:id="ep000801-e100700">
          <speaker>Iuliana. </speaker>
          <l>My Clamydes, of troth Sir Prince, to make you stay thus here, </l>
          <l>I profer too much iniurie, thats doubtlesse on my part, </l>
          <l>But let it no occasion giue, to breede within your hart </l>
          <l>Mistrust that I should forge or faine, with you my Loue in ought. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e100750">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>No Lady, touching you, in me doth lodge no such a thought, </l>
          <l>But thankes for your great curtesie that would so friendly heere </l>
          <l>In mids of miserie receiue, a forraine straunger meere: </l>
          <l>But Lady say, what is your will, that it I may perstand? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-juliana" xml:id="ep000801-e100800">
          <speaker>Iulia. </speaker>
          <l>Sir Prince, vpon a vow, who spowseth me, must needsly take in hand </l>
          <l>The flying Serpent for to sley, which in the Forrest is, </l>
          <l>That of strange maruels beareth name, which Serpent doth not mis </l>
          <l>By dayly vse from euery coast, that is adyacent there, </l>
          <l>To fetch a Virgin maide or wife, or else some Lady faire, </l>
          <l>To feed his hungrie panch withall, if case he can them take, </l>
          <l>His nature loe it onely is, of women spoyle to make: </l>
          <l>Which thing no doubt, did daunt me much, and made me vow indeed, </l>
          <l>Who should espouse me for his wife, should bring to me his head: </l>
          <l>Whereto my father willingly, did giue his like consent, </l>
          <l>Lo Sir Clamydes, now you know what is my whole intent: </l>
          <l>And if you will as I haue said, for me this trauell take, </l>
          <l>That I am yours, with heart and mind, your full account do make. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-003-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e100940">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>Ah Lady, if case these trauels should surmount, the trauels whereby came </l>
          <l>Vnto the worthies of the world, such noble brute and fame, </l>
          <l>Yea though the dangers should surpasse stout Hercules his toyle, </l>
          <l>Who fearing nought the dogged feend, sterne Serbarus did foyle. </l>
          <l>Take here my hand, if life and limbe the liuing Gods do lend, </l>
          <l>To purchase thee, the dearest drop of bloud my heart shall spend. </l>
          <l>And therefore Lady lincke with me, thy loyall heart for aye, </l>
          <l>For I am thine til fates vntwine, of vital life the stay: </l>
          <l>Protesting here if Gods assist, the Serpent for to kil. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-juliana" xml:id="ep000801-e101040">
          <speaker>Iuli. </speaker>
          <l>Then shalt thou of all women win, the heart and great good wil, </l>
          <l>And me possesse for spowsed wife, who in election am </l>
          <l>To haue the Crowne of Denmarke here, as heire vnto the same. </l>
          <l>For why, no children hath my fire besides mee, but one other, </l>
          <l>And he indeed is heire before, for that he is my brother. </l>
          <l>And Clyomon so hight his name, but where he doth remaine, </l>
          <l>Vnto my Parents is vnknowne, for once he did obtaine </l>
          <l>Their good wills for to go abroad, a while to spend his daies, </l>
          <l>In purchasing through actiue deeds, both honour, laud and praise, </l>
          <l>Whereby he might deserue to haue the order of a Knight, </l>
          <l>But this omitting vnto thee, Clamydes here I plight </l>
          <l>My faith and troth, if what is said by me thou dost performe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e101170">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>If not, be sure O Lady with my life, I neuer will returne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-juliana" xml:id="ep000801-e101190">
          <speaker>Iuli. </speaker>
          <l>Then as thou seemest in thine attire, a Virgins Knight to be, </l>
          <l>Take thou this Sheeld likewise of white, and beare thy name by me, </l>
          <l>The white Knight of the Siluer Sheeld, to eleuate thy praise. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e101230">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>O Lady as your pleasure is, I shall at all assayes </l>
          <l>Endeuour my good will to win, if Mars do send me might, </l>
          <l>Such honour as your grace with ioy, shall welcome home your Knight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-juliana" xml:id="ep000801-e101270">
          <speaker>Iuli. </speaker>
          <l>Then farewell my deare Clamydes, the gods direct thy way, </l>
          <l>And graunt that with the Serpents head, behold thy face I may. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e101300">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e101310">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>You shall not need to doubt thereof, O faithfull Dame so true, </l>
          <l>And humbly kissing here thy hand, I bid thy Grace adue. </l>
          <l>Ah happie time and blisfull day, wherein by fate I find </l>
          <l>Such friendly fauours as is foode, to feede both heart and mind: </l>
          <l>To Suauia soile I swiftly will prepare my foot-steps right, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-004-a"/>
          <l>There of my father to receiue the order of a Knight: </l>
          <l>And afterwards addresse my selfe in hope of honours Crowne, </l>
          <l>Both Tyger fell and Monster fierce, by dint for to driue downe. </l>
          <l>The flying Serpent soone shall feele, how boldly I dare vaunt me, </l>
          <l>And if that Hydras head she had, yet dread should neuer daunt me. </l>
          <l>If murdering Minataure, a man might count this ougly beast, </l>
          <l>Yet for to win a Lady such, I do account it least </l>
          <l>Of trauels toyle to take in hand, and therefore farewell care, </l>
          <l>For hope of honour sends me forth, mongst warlike wights to share. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e101460">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e101470">Enter Sir Clyomon Knight of the golden Sheeld, sonne to the King of Denmarke, with subtill Shift the Vice, booted. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e101480">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Come on good fellow follow me, that I may vnderstand </l>
          <l>Of whence thou art, thus trauelling here in a forraine land: </l>
          <l>Come why dost thou not leaue loytering there, and follow after me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e101520">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Ah I am in ant shall please you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e101540">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>In, why where art thou in? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e101560">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Faith in a dirtie Ditch with a woman, so beraide, as it's pittie to see. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e101580">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Wel, I see thou art a merrie companion, I shall like better of thy company: </l>
          <l>But I pray thee come away. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e101610">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>If I get out one of my legs as fast as I may </l>
          <l>Ha lo, A my buttocke, the very foundation thereof doth breake, </l>
          <l>Ha lo, once againe, I am as fast, as though I had frozen here a weeke. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e101650">Here let him slip vnto the Stage backwards, as though he had puld his leg out of the mire, one boote off, and rise vp to run in againe. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e101660">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Why how now, whither runst thou, art thou foolish in thy minde </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e101680">
          <speaker>Shi. </speaker>
          <l>But to fetch one of my legs ant shall please, that I haue left in the mire behind. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e101700">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>One of thy legs, why looke man, both thy legs thou hast, </l>
          <l>It is but one of thy bootes thou hast lost, thy labour thou doest wast. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e101730">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>But one of my bootes, Iesu, I had such a wrench with the fall, </l>
          <l>That I assure, I did thinke one of my legs had gone withall. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e101760">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Well let that passe, and tell me what thou art, and what is thy name? </l>
          <l>And from whence thou cam'st, and whither thy iourney thou doest frame, </l>
          <l>That I haue met thee by the way, thus trauelling in this sort? </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-004-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e101800">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>What you haue requested, ant shall please, I am able to report, </l>
          <l>What I am by my nature each wight shall perceiue </l>
          <l>That frequenteth my company, by the learning I haue. </l>
          <l>I am the sonne of Appollo, and from his high seate I came, </l>
          <l>But whither I go, it skils not, for knowledge is my name: </l>
          <l>And who so hath knowledge, what needs he to care </l>
          <l>Which way the wind blowe, his way to prepare. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e101880">
          <speaker>Cly. </speaker>
          <l>And art thou knowledge, of troth I am glad that I haue met with thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e101900">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>I am knowledge, and haue as good skill in a woman as any man whatsoeuer he bee. </l>
          <l>For this I am certaine of let me but lie with her all night, </l>
          <l>And Ile tell you in the morning, whither she is maide, wife, or spright: </l>
          <l>And as for other matters, speaking of languishes, or any other thing, </l>
          <l>I am able to serue ant shall please, ant were great Alexander the King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e101960">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Of troth, then for thy excellencie, I will thee gladly entertaine, </l>
          <l>If in case that with me thou wilt promise to remaine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e101990">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Nay ant shall please ye, I am like to a woman, say nay and take it, </l>
          <l>When a gentleman profers entertainment, I were a foole to forsake it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e102020">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Well knowledge, then sith thou art content my seruant to bee, </l>
          <l>And endued with noble qualities, thy personage I see, </l>
          <l>Thou hauing perfect knowledge, how thy selfe to behaue: </l>
          <l>I will send thee of mine arrant, but haste thither I craue: </l>
          <l>For here I will stay thy comming againe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e102080">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Declare your pleasure sir, and whither I shall go, and then the case is plaine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e102100">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Nay of no great importance, but being here in Suania </l>
          <l>And neare vnto the Court, I would haue thee to take thy way </l>
          <l>Thither with all speede, because I would heare </l>
          <l>If any shewes or triumphs be towards, else would I not come there, </l>
          <l>For onely vpon feates of armes, is all my delight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e102160">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>If I had knowne so much before, serue that serue will, I would haue seru'd no martiall Knight. </l>
          <l>Well sir, to accomplish your will, to the court I will by, </l>
          <l>And what newes is there stirring, bring word by and by. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e102200">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e102210">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Do so good knowledge, and here in place thy comming I will stay: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-005-a"/>
          <l>For nothing doth delight me more then to heare of martiall play, </l>
          <l>Can foode vnto the hungrie corps, because of greater ioy, </l>
          <l>Then for the haughtie heart to heare, which doth it selfe imploy, </l>
          <l>Through martiall excercises much to winne the brute of Fame, </l>
          <l>Where mates do meete which there vnto their fancies seemes to frames: </l>
          <l>Can musicke more the pensiue heart or daunted mind delight, </l>
          <l>Can comfort more the carefull corps and ouer palled spright, </l>
          <l>Reioyce then sound of Trumpet doth each warlike wight allure, </l>
          <l>And Drum and Fyfe vnto the fight doth noble hearts procure, </l>
          <l>To see in sunder shiuered, the Lance that leades the way, </l>
          <l>And worthy knights vnbeauered, in field amidst the fray, </l>
          <l>To heare the ratling Cannons roare, and Hyles on Helmets ring, </l>
          <l>To see the souldiers swarme on heapes, where valiant hearts doth bring </l>
          <l>The cowardly crew into the case of carefull Captiues band, </l>
          <l>Where auncients braue displayed be, and wonne by force of hand. </l>
          <l>What wight would not as well delight as this to heare and see, </l>
          <l>Betake himselfe in like affaires a fellow mate to bee, </l>
          <l>With Clyomon to Denmarke King the onely sonne and heire. </l>
          <l>Who of the Golden Sheeld as now, the knightly name doth beare </l>
          <l>In euery land since that I foyld the worthy Knight of Fame, </l>
          <l>Sir Samuel before the King, and Prince of martiall game. </l>
          <l>Alexander cald the Great, which when he did behold, </l>
          <l>He gaue to me in recompence, this Shield of glittering Gold: </l>
          <l>Requesting for to know my name, the which shall not be showen </l>
          <l>To any Kight, vnlesse by force he make it to be knowen. </l>
          <l>For so I vowed to Denmarke King, my fathers grace when I </l>
          <l>First got his leaue, that I abroad my force and strength might try. </l>
          <l>And so I haue my selfe behau'd, in Citie, Towne and field, </l>
          <l>That neuer yet did fall reproach, to the Knight of the Golden Shield. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e102520">Enter Subtill Shift, running. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e102530">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Gods ames, where are you, where are you? and you bee a man come away. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e102550">
          <speaker>Clya. </speaker>
          <l>Why what is the matter knowledge to tell thy arrand stay. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e102570">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Stay, what talke you of staying, why then all the sight will be past, </l>
          <l>Clamides the Kings sonne shall be dubd Knight in all hast. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e102600">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Ah knowledge, then come indeed, and good pastime thou shalt see, </l>
          <l>For I will take the honour from him, that dubbed I may bee. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-005-b"/>
          <l>Vpon a couragious stomacke, come let vs haste thither. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e102640">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e102650">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Leade you the way and ile follow, weele be both made knights togither, </l>
          <l>Ah sirrah, is my maister so lustie, or dares he be so bold? </l>
          <l>It is no maruell then, if he beare a Sheeld of Gold. </l>
          <l>But by your patience if he continue in this businesse, farewell maister than, </l>
          <l>For I promise you, I entend not very long to be his man: </l>
          <l>Although vnder the tytle of knowledge my name I do faine, </l>
          <l>Subtill Shift I am called, that is most plaine. </l>
          <l>And as it is my name, so it is my nature also, </l>
          <l>To play the shifting knaue wheresoeuer I go. </l>
          <l>Well, after him I will, but soft now, if my maister chance to be lost </l>
          <l>And any man examine me, in telling his name I am as wise as a post. </l>
          <l>What a villaine was I, that ere he went, could not aske it? </l>
          <l>Well, its no great matter, I am but halfe bound, I may serue whom I will yet. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e102790">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e102800">Enter the Ring of Suauis with the Herauld before him: Clamydes, three Lords. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e102810">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Come Clamides thou our sonne, thy Fathers talke attend, </l>
          <l>Since thou art prest thy youthfull dayes in prowesse for to spend: </l>
          <l>And doest of vs the order aske, of knighthood for to haue, </l>
          <l>We know thy deeds deserues the same, and that which thou doest craue </l>
          <l>Thou shalt possesse: but first my sonne, know thou thy fathers charge, </l>
          <l>And what to knighthood doth belong, thine honour to enlarge: </l>
          <l>Vnto what end a knight is made, that likewise thou maiste know, </l>
          <l>And beare the same in mind also, that honour thine may flow </l>
          <l>Amongst the worthies of the world, to thy immortall fame: </l>
          <l>Know thou therefore Clamydes deare, to haue a knightly name </l>
          <l>Is first aboue all other things his God for to adore, </l>
          <l>In truth according to the lawes prescribde to him before. </l>
          <l>Secondly, that he be true vnto his Lord and king. </l>
          <l>Thirdly, that he keepe his faith and troth in euery thing. </l>
          <l>And then before all other things that else we can commend, </l>
          <l>That he be alwaies ready prest, his countrey to defend: </l>
          <l>The Widow poore, and fatherlesse, or Innocent bearing blame, </l>
          <l>To see their cause redressed right, a faithfull knight must frame: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-006-a"/>
          <l>In truth he alwaies must be <seg type="tba">tried, this is the totall charge,</seg>
          </l>
          <l>That will receiue a knightly name, his honour to enlarge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e103020">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>O Father this your gracious counsell giuen to me your onely sonne, </l>
        </sp>
        <l>Shall not be in obliuion cast <seg type="tba">, till vitall race</seg>be runne: </l>
        <l>What way dooth winne Dame Honours Crowne, those pathes any steppes shall trace </l>
        <l>And those that to reproach doth leade, which seeketh to deface </l>
        <l>True Honour in her Regall seate, I shall detest for aye, </l>
        <l>And be as vtter enemie, to them both night and day: </l>
        <l>By flying force of flickring fame, your grace shall vnderstand▪ </l>
        <l>Of my behauiour noble syre, in euery forraine land. </l>
        <l>And if you heare by true report <seg type="tba">, I venture in the Barge</seg>
        </l>
        <l>Of wilfulnesse contrary this, your graces noble charge: </l>
        <l>Let ignomie to my reproach in steed of Lady fame. </l>
        <l>Sound through the earth and Azure Skies the strained blast of shame. </l>
        <l>Whereby within Obliuions Tombe, my deeds shall be detained, </l>
        <l>Where otherwise of memorie <seg type="tba">, the mind</seg>I might haue gained. </l>
        <l>So that the den of darksomenesse shall euer be my chest, </l>
        <l>Where worthy deeds prefers each wight, with honour to be blest. </l>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e103190">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Well <seg type="tba">Clamydes then kneele downe, according as is</seg>right, </l>
        </sp>
        <l>That here thou mayst receiue of me the order of a Knight. </l>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e103220">Here let <seg type="tba">him kneele downe, Cloymon with subtill Shift watching in place,</seg>and as the King doth go about to lay the <seg type="tba">Mace of his head, let</seg>Clyomon take the <seg type="tba">blowe, and so passe away presently</seg>. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e103230">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Now prepare your selfe, or <seg type="tba">ile be either a Knight or a knaue.</seg>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e103250">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Content thy selfe knowledge, for i●● quickly him deceiue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e103270">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>The Noble orders of a Knight, <seg type="tba">Clamydes vnto thee</seg>
          </l>
          <l>We giue through due <seg type="tba">desert, wherefore see</seg>that thou bee, </l>
          <l>Both Valiant, Wise, and Hardie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e103310">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Away now <seg type="tba">quickly, least we</seg>be take ●ardie. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e103330">Exeunt. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e103340">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Ah stout attempt of <seg type="tba">Barron bold, that hath from this</seg>my sonne, </l>
          <l>The Knight-hood <seg type="tba">him, his</seg>
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-006-b"/>
          <l>Ah Clamydes how art thou be rest of honour here? </l>
          <l>Was like presumption euer seene, that one a straunger meere, </l>
          <l>Should come in presence of a Prince, and tempt as he hath done, </l>
          <l>To take the Knight-hood thus away, from him who is his sonne? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e103410">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Ah father, how am I perplext, till I reuenged be, </l>
          <l>Vpon the wretch which here hath tane, the honour thus from me? </l>
          <l>Was euer any one deceiu'd of Knight hood so before? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e103450">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Well Clamydes, my Lords returne, stay till we do know more. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e103470">Enter Shift brought in by the two Lords, who pursued Clyomon. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-1" xml:id="ep000801-e103480">
          <speaker>1. Lord. </speaker>
          <l>O King the knight is fled and gone, pursute preuaileth nought, </l>
          <l>But here his slaue we taken haue, to tell why this he wrought. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e103510">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Ah cruell grudge that greeues my ghost, shall he escape me so! </l>
          <l>Shall he with honour from my sonne, without disturbance go? </l>
          <l>Ah Catiffe thou, declare his name, and why he ventred here: </l>
          <l>Or death shall be thy guerdon sure, by all the Gods I sweare. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e103560">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Ah ant shall please you, I know neither 〈…〉 country nor name. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-2" xml:id="ep000801-e103580">
          <speaker>2. Lo. </speaker>
          <l>What, what sir, are not you his seruants will you denie the same▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e103600">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Nay then you are a dissembling knaue, I know very well. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e103620">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Ant shall please your Grace, euen the very troth I shall tell, </l>
          <l>I should haue bene his seruant when we met together; </l>
          <l>Which was not full three houres before we came hither. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e103660">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Well what is his name, and of what countrey declare? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e103680">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>That cannot I tell an t shall please you, you neuer saw seruant to such care: </l>
          <l>To know his Maisters name, neither in Towne nor Field, </l>
          <l>And what he was he would tell, but the Knight of the Golden Sheeld. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e103720">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Well Clamides marke my charge, what I to thee shall say, </l>
          <l>Prepare thy selfe for to pursue that Traytor on his way: </l>
          <l>Which hath thine honour reft from thee, and either by force of hand </l>
          <l>Or loue, his name and natiue soyle, see that thou vnderstand, </l>
          <l>That I may know for what intent, he bare this grudge to thee, </l>
          <l>Else see thou neuer doest returne againe to visit mee: </l>
          <l>For this imports him for to be, of valiant heart and mind: </l>
          <l>And therefore do pursue thy foe, vntill thou doest him find. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-007-a"/>
          <l>To know his name and what he is, or as I said before, </l>
          <l>Do neuer view thy father I, in presence any more. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e103830">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Well father, sith it is your charge, and precept giuen to mee, </l>
          <l>And more for mine owne honours sake, I franckly do agree </l>
          <l>To vndertake the enterprise, his name to vnderstand, </l>
          <l>Or neuer else to shew my face againe in Swauia land. </l>
          <l>Wherefore I humbly do desire, the order to receiue, </l>
          <l>Of Knighthood, which my sole desire hath euer bene to haue: </l>
          <l>It is the name and meane, whereby true honour is atchiued: </l>
          <l>Let me not then O father deare, thereof be now depriued. </l>
          <l>Sith that mine honour cowardly was stolne by Caitiffe he, </l>
          <l>And not by dinted dastards deed, O father lost by me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e103940">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Well Clamydes, then kneele downe, here in our Nobles sight, </l>
          <l>We giue to thee that art our sonne, the order of a Knight: </l>
          <l>But as thou wilt our fauour winne, accomplish my desire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e103980">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Else neuer to your royall Court, O father ile retire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e104000">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Well, then adieu Clamides deare, the Gods thine ayder be: </l>
          <l>But come my Lords, to haue his hire, that Caitiffe bring with me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e104030">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Alas not shall please you, I am knowledge, and no euill did pretend, </l>
          <l>Set me at libertie, it was the knight that did offend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e104060">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>O father, sith that he is knowledge, I beseech your grace set him free, </l>
          <l>For in these affaires, he shall waite and tend on mee: </l>
          <l>If he will protest, to be true to me euer. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e104100">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Ah Noble Clamydes, heere's my hand, ile deceiue you neuer. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e104120">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Wel then father, I beseech your Grace grant that I may haue him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e104140">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Well Clamydes, I am content, sith thou my sonne doest craue him. </l>
          <l>Receiue him therefore at my hands. My Lords come lets depart. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-all" xml:id="ep000801-e104170">
          <speaker>All. </speaker>
          <l>We ready are to waite on you O King, with willing hart. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e104190">Exeunt. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e104200">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Well knowledge, do prepare thy selfe, for here I do protest, </l>
          <l>My fathers precepts to fulfill, no day nor night to rest </l>
          <l>From toylsome trauell, till I haue reuengd my cause aright, </l>
          <l>On him who of the golden Sheeld, now beareth name of knight: </l>
          <l>Who of mine honour hath me robd, in such a cowardly sort, </l>
          <l>As for to be of noble heart, it doth him not import. </l>
          <l>But knowledge, to me thy seruice stall thou must with loyall hart professe. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-007-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e104280">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Vse me that all other villains may take ensample by me, if I digresse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e104300">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Well then come follow speedily, that him pursue we may. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e104320">(Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e104330">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Keepe you before ant shall please you, for I mind not to stay. </l>
          <l>Ah sirrah Shift, thou wast driuen to thy shifts now indeed, </l>
          <l>I dreamd bfore, that vntowardly I should speed: </l>
          <l>And yet it is better lucke then I looked to haue: </l>
          <l>But as the prouerbe saith, good fortune euer hapneth to the veryest knaue. </l>
          <l>And yet I could not escape with my maister, do what I can, </l>
          <l>Well by this bargaine he hath lost his new Seruing-man, </l>
          <l>But if Clamydes ouertake him now, what buffets will there be, </l>
          <l>Vnlesse it be foure miles off the fray, there will be no standing for me. </l>
          <l>Well after him I will, but howsoeuer my maister speed, </l>
          <l>To shift for my selfe I am fully decreed. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e104450">(Exit. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e104460">Enter King Alexander the Great, as valiantly set forth as may be, and as many souldiers as can. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-alexander" xml:id="ep000801-e104470">
          <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
          <l>After many inuincible victories, and conquests great atchiued, </l>
          <l>I Alexander with sound of Fame, in safetie am arriued </l>
          <l>Vpon my borders long wished for, of Macedonia soile, </l>
          <l>And all the world subiect haue, through force of warlike toile, </l>
          <l>O Mars I lawd thy sacred name, and for this safe returne, </l>
          <l>To Pallas Temple will I wend, and sacrifices burne </l>
          <l>To thee, Bellona and the rest, that warlike wights do guide, </l>
          <l>Who for King Alexander did, such good successe prouide. </l>
          <l>Who bowes not now vnto my becke, my force who doth not feare? </l>
          <l>Who doth not of my conquests great, throughout the world heare? </l>
          <l>What King as to his soueraigne Lord, doth now not bow his knee? </l>
          <l>What Prince doth raigne vpon the earth, which yeelds not vnto mee </l>
          <l>Due homage for his Regall Mace? What countrey is at libertie? </l>
          <l>What Dukedome, Iland or Prouince else, to me now are not tributarie? </l>
          <l>What Fort of Force, or Castle strong, haue I not battered downe? </l>
          <l>What Prince is he, that now by me, his Princely seate and Crowne </l>
          <l>Doth not acknowledge for to hold, not one the world throughout, </l>
          <l>But of King Alexanders power they all do stand in doubt? </l>
          <l>They feare as Fowles that houering flie, from out the Fawcons way, </l>
          <l>As Lambe the Lyon, so my power, the stowtest do obey. </l>
          <l>In field who hath not felt my force, where battering blowes abound? </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-008-a"/>
          <l>King or Keysar, who hath not fixt his knees to me on ground, </l>
          <l>And yet Alexander, what art th●● thou art a mortall wight, </l>
          <l>For all that ever thou hast got or wonne by force in fight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-1" xml:id="ep000801-e104720">
          <speaker>I. Lo. </speaker>
          <l>Acknowledging thy state ô King, to be at thou hast said, </l>
          <l>The Gods no doubt as they haue bene, will be thy sheeld and aid </l>
          <l>In all attempts thou takst in hand, 〈◊〉 no glorie vaine </l>
          <l>Thou seekest, but acknowledging thy victories and gaine, </l>
          <l>Through the prouidence of sacred Gods to happen vnto thee, </l>
          <l>For vaine is trust, that in himselfe, man doth repose we see: </l>
          <l>And therefore least these victories which thou ô King hast got, </l>
          <l>Should blind thine eyes with arrogancie thy, noble fame to blot, </l>
          <l>Let that victorious Prince his words, of Macedon thy fire, </l>
          <l>To acknowledge still thy state O King, thy noble heart inspire, </l>
          <l>Who after all his victories, triumphantly obtained, </l>
          <l>Least that the great felicitie of that which she had gained, </l>
          <l>Should cause him to forget himselfe, <seg type="tba">a child he</seg>did prouide, </l>
          <l>Which came vnto his chamber doore, and euery morning cryde </l>
          <l>Philip, thou art a mortall man, this practise of thy sire, </l>
          <l>A midst all these thy victories, thy seruant doth desire. </l>
          <l>O Alexander that <seg type="tba">thou wilt, them</seg>print within thy mind, </l>
          <l>And then no doubt as father did, thou solace sweete shall find. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-alexander" xml:id="ep000801-e104910">
          <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
          <l>My Lords, your counsell doubtlesse I esteeme, and with great thanks againe, </l>
          <l>I do require <seg type="tba">your courtesie, reiecting</seg>this is plaine, </l>
          <l>All <seg type="tba">vaine glory from my heart</seg>: and since the Gods diuine, </l>
          <l>To vs <seg type="tba">aboue all others Kings,</seg>this fortune doeth assigne, </l>
          <l>To haue in our subiection the world for most part, </l>
          <l>We will at this <seg type="tba">one houre returne</seg>, with feruent zeale of hart, </l>
          <l>In <seg type="tba">Pallas temple to the</seg>gods, such sacrifices make, </l>
          <l>Of thankfulnesse for our successe, as they in part shall take </l>
          <l>The same, <seg type="tba">a gratulation, sufficient</seg>from vs sent: </l>
          <l>Come <seg type="tba">therefore let vs homewards march</seg>, to accomplish our intent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-omnes" xml:id="ep000801-e105020">
          <speaker>Omnes. </speaker>
          <l>We <seg type="tba">readie are most famous</seg>King, to follow thee with victorie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-alexander" xml:id="ep000801-e105040">
          <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
          <l>
            <seg type="tba">Then sound your</seg>Drums and Trumpets both, that we may march triumphantly. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e105060">Exeunt. </stage>
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-008-b"/>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e105070">Enter Sir Clyomon, Knight of G. S. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e105080">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Now Clyomon a knight thou art, though some perhaps may say, </l>
          <l>Thou cowardly camst to Clamydes, and stole his right away: </l>
          <l>No, no, it was no cowardly part, to come in presence of a king, </l>
          <l>And in the face of all his Court, to do so worthy a thing. </l>
          <l>Amidst the mates that martiall be, and sterne knights of his hall, </l>
          <l>To take the knighthood from their Prince, euen mauger of them all. </l>
          <l>It giues a guerdon of goodwill, to make my glory glance, </l>
          <l>When warlike wights shall heare thereof, my fame they will aduance: </l>
          <l>And where I was pretended late, to Denmarke king my sire, </l>
          <l>His royall grace to see, homeward to retire, </l>
          <l>Now is my purpose altered by brute of late report. </l>
          <l>And where fame resteth to be had, thither Clyomon will resort: </l>
          <l>For as I vnderstand by fame, that worthy Prince of might, </l>
          <l>The conqueror of conquerors, who Alexander hight, </l>
          <l>Returning is to Macedon, from many a bloudie broyle, </l>
          <l>And there to keepe his royall Court, now after wearie toyle, </l>
          <l>Which makes the mind of Clyomon, with ioyes to be clad, </l>
          <l>For there I know of martiall mates, is company to be had. </l>
          <l>Adiu therefore, both Denmarke king and Suania Prince beside, </l>
          <l>To Alexanders Court I will, the Gods my iourney guide. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e105290">Enter Clamydes and Shift. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e105300">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Come knowledge here he is, nay stay thou cowardly knight, </l>
          <l>That like a dastard camst, to steale away my right. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e105330">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>What, what, you raile sir princkocks Prince, me coward for to call. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e105350">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Ant shall please you he is a coward, he would haue hyrde me, </l>
          <l>Amidst your fathers hall. </l>
          <l>To haue done it for him, being himselfe in such stay </l>
          <l>That scarcely he durst, before your presence appeare. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e105400">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Why how now knowledge, what forsake thy maister so soone? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e105420">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Nay maister was, but not maister is, with you I haue done. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e105440">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Well for what intent canst thou, my honour to steale away? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e105460">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>That I tooke ought from thee, I vtterly denay. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e105480">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Didst not thou take the honour, which my father to me gaue? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e105500">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Of that thou hadst not, I could thee not depraue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e105520">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Didst not thou take away my knighthood from me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e105540">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>No, for I had it before it was giuen vnto thee: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-009-a"/>
          <l>And hauing it before thee, what Argument canst thou make, </l>
          <l>That euer from thee the same I did take? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e105580">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Thats true, he receiu'd the blow before at you it came, </l>
          <l>And therefore he tooke it not from you, because you had not the same. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e105610">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Well, what hight thy name, let me that vnderstand, </l>
          <l>And wherefore thou trauailedst here in my fathers land </l>
          <l>So boldly to attempt in his Court such a thing? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e105650">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>The bolder the attempt is, more fame it doth bring: </l>
          <l>But what my name is desirest thou to know? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e105680">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Nay he hath stolen sheepe I thinke, for he is ashamd his name for to show. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e105700">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>What thy name is, I would gladly perstand: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e105720">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Nay that shall neuer none know, vnlesse by force of hand </l>
          <l>He vanquish me in fight, such a vow haue I made, </l>
          <l>And therefore to combat with me, thy selfe do perswade, </l>
          <l>If thou wilt know my name. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e105770">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Well, I accord to the same. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e105790">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Nay then God be with you, if you be at that poynt I am gone. </l>
          <l>If you be of the fighters disposition, ile leaue you alone. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e105820">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Why stay knowledge, although I fight, thou shalt not be molested. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e105840">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Ant shall please you, this feare hath made me beray my selfe, with a Proynstone that was not digested. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e105860">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Well Clamydes stay thy selfe, and marke my sayings here: </l>
          <l>And do not thinke I speake this same, for that thy force I feare, </l>
          <l>But that more honour may redound, vnto the victors part, </l>
          <l>Wilt thou here giue thy hand to me, withouten fraud of hart </l>
          <l>Vpon the faith which to a knight doth rightly appertaine, </l>
          <l>And by the loyaltie of a knight, ile sweare to thee againe, </l>
          <l>For to obserue my promise iust, which is if thou agree, </l>
          <l>The fifteenth day next following, to meete Sir Prince with mee, </l>
          <l>Before King Alexanders grace, in Macedonia soyle, </l>
          <l>Who all the world subiect hath, through force of warlike toyle: </l>
          <l>For hee is chiefe of chiualrie, and king of Martiall mates, </l>
          <l>And to his royall Court thou knowest, repaire all estates. </l>
          <l>Giue me thy hand vpon thy faith, of promise not to faile. </l>
          <l>And here is mine to thee againe, if Fortunes froward gaile, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-009-b"/>
          <l>Resist me not, the day forespoke to meete sir Prince with thee, </l>
          <l>Before that king to try our strengths, say if thou doest agree, </l>
          <l>For tryple honour will it be, to him that gets the victorie, </l>
          <l>Before so worthy a Prince as hee, and Nobles all so publikely, </l>
          <l>Where otherwise if in this place we should attempt the same, </l>
          <l>Of the honour that were got thereby, but small would be the fame. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e106070">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Well Sir knight, here is my hand, ile meete in place forespoke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e106090">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>And by the loyaltie of a knight, ile not my words reuoke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e106110">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Till then adieu; ile keepe my day. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e106130">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e106140">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>And I, if fates do not gainsay. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e106160">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>What is he gone, and did take no leaue of me? </l>
          <l>Iesu so vnmannerly a Gentleman did any man see, </l>
          <l>But now my Lord which way will you trauell declare? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e106200">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Sith I haue fifteene dayes respit my selfe to prepare, </l>
          <l>My Ladies charge for to fulfill, behold I do entend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e106230">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Your Lady ant shall please you, why who is your Lady, may a man be so bold as aske and not offend? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e106250">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Iuliana daughter to the King of Denmarke loe is she, </l>
          <l>Whose knight I am, and from her hands this shield was giuen to me, </l>
          <l>In signe and token of good will, whose noble grace to gaine, </l>
          <l>I haue protested in her cause for to omit no paine </l>
          <l>Nor trauaile, till I haue subdued the flying Serpents force, </l>
          <l>Which in the Forrest of Maruels is, who taketh no remorse </l>
          <l>Of women kind, but doth deuoure all such as are a stray, </l>
          <l>So that no one dares go abroad, nor wander forth the way. </l>
          <l>And sith I haue yet fifteene dayes, my selfe for to prepare, </l>
          <l>To meete the Knight of the Golden Shield, my heart is voyd of care. </l>
          <l>I will vnto the Forrest wend, sith it is in my way, </l>
          <l>And for my Iulianas sake, that cruell Serpent slay. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e106380">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>What are you a mad man, will you wilfully be slaine? </l>
          <l>If you go into that Forrest, you will neuer come out againe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e106410">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Why so knowledge, dost thou thinke the Serpent I feare? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e106430">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>No, but do you not know of Bryan sance foy, the champion dwels there </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e106450">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>A cowardly knight knowledge is he, and dares fight with no man. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-010-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e106470">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Ah a noble match, couple him and me togither than: </l>
          <l>Yea, but although he dares not fight, and Enchanter he is, </l>
          <l>And whosoeuer comes in that Forrest, to enchant he doth not mis. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e106510">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Tush, tush, I feare him not knowledge, and therefore come away. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e106530">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e106540">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Well seeing you are so wilfull, go you before ile not stay. </l>
          <l>Ah sirrah, now I know all my maisters mind, the which I did not before, </l>
          <l>He aduentureth for a Lady, well I say no more: </l>
          <l>But to escape the enchantments of Bryan Sance foy, </l>
          <l>Thats Bryan without faith, I haue deuisde a noble toy: </l>
          <l>For he and I am both of one consanguinitie, </l>
          <l>The veryest cowardly villaine that euer was borne, thats of a certaintie. </l>
          <l>Ile fight with no man, no more will Bryan, thats plaine: </l>
          <l>But by his enchantments, he putteth many to great paine. </l>
          <l>And in a Forrest of strange maruels doth he keepe, </l>
          <l>Altogither by enchantments to bring men a sleepe, </l>
          <l>Till he haue wrought his will of them, to Bryan straight will I, </l>
          <l>And of my maisters comming to the Forrest informe him priuily, </l>
          <l>So shall I win his fauour, and subtill Shift in the end, </l>
          <l>Thou shalt escape his enchantment, for he will be thy frend: </l>
          <l>Well vnknowne to my maister, for mine owne safegard this will I do, </l>
          <l>And now like a subtill shifting knaue, after him ile go. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e106720">Exit: </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e106730">Enter Bryan sance foy. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e106740">
          <speaker>Bry. </speaker>
          <l>Of Brian sance foi who hath not heard? not for his valiant acts, </l>
          <l>But well I know throughout the world, doth ring his cowardly facts. </l>
          <l>What tho I pray all are not borne to be God Mars his men, </l>
          <l>To toy with daintie dames in courts, should be no copesmates then. </l>
          <l>If all were giuen to chiualrie, then Venus might go weepe, </l>
          <l>For any Court in Venerie, that she were like to keepe. </l>
          <l>But shall I frame then mine excuse, by seruing Venus she, </l>
          <l>When I am knowne throughout the world, faint hearted for to be? </l>
          <l>No, no, alas, it will not serue, for many a knight in loue, </l>
          <l>Most valiant hearts no doubt they haue, and knightly prowesse proue, </l>
          <l>To get their Ladies loyall hearts, but I in Ʋenus yoke, </l>
          <l>Am forst for want of valiancie, my freedome to prouoke: </l>
          <l>Bearing the name and port of knight, enchantments for to vse, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-010-b"/>
          <l>Wherewith full many a worthy wight, most cowardly I abuse: </l>
          <l>As witnesseth the number now, which in my Castle lye, </l>
          <l>Who if they were at libertie, in armes I durst not try. </l>
          <l>The feeblest there though he vnarmd, so is my courage danted, </l>
          <l>When as I see the glittering armes, whereby each Knight is vanted. </l>
          <l>But how I vanquish these same Knights, is wonderfull to see, </l>
          <l>And Knights that ventured for her loue, whom I do loue they bee. </l>
          <l>Thats Iuliana, daughter to the King of Denmarks grace, </l>
          <l>Whose beautie is the cause that I do haunt or keepe this place. </l>
          <l>For that no wight may her possesse, vnlesse by vow decreed, </l>
          <l>He bring and do present to her the flying Serpents head. </l>
          <l>Which many hath attempt to do, but none yet could him slay, </l>
          <l>Ne afterward hence backe againe, for me could passe away: </l>
          <l>For that through my inchantments lo, which heere this forrest keepe, </l>
          <l>So soone as I did looke on them, they straight were in a sleepe. </l>
          <l>Then presently I them vnarmd, and to my Castle brought, </l>
          <l>And there in prison they do lye, not knowing what was wrought. </l>
          <l>Lo thus I range the woods to see who doth the Serpent slay, </l>
          <l>That by inchantment I may take the head from him away: </l>
          <l>And it present vnto the Dame, as though I were her Knight, </l>
          <l>Well heere comes one, ile shrowd my selfe, for sure I will not fight. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e107090">Enter Subtill Shift. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e107100">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Gogs bloud where might I meete with that cowardly knaue Bryan sance foy? </l>
          <l>I could tell him such a tale now as would make his hart leape for ioy. </l>
          <l>Well yonder I haue espied one, whatsoeuer he be. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e107140">
          <speaker>Bryan. </speaker>
          <l>Nay gogs bloud ile be gone, he shall not fight with me, </l>
          <l>But by inchantment ile be euen with him by and by. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e107170">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>A ant shall please you, ile fight with no man, neuer come so nye. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e107190">
          <speaker>Bryan. </speaker>
          <l>Why what art thou declare? whither doost thou run? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e107210">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Euen the cowardly cowardlyest villaine ant shall please you that liues vnder the sun. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e107230">
          <speaker>Bryan. </speaker>
          <l>What of my fraternitie, doest thou not know Bryan sance foy? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e107250">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>What maister Bryan, Iesu how my hart doth leape for ioy </l>
          <l>That I haue met with you, who euer had better lucke? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e107280">
          <speaker>Bryan. </speaker>
          <l>But touch me not. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e107300">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Wherefore? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e107320">
          <speaker>Bryan. </speaker>
          <l>A lest you inchant me into the likenesse of a bucke. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-011-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e107340">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Tush, tush, I warrant thee, but what art thou declare? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e107360">
          <speaker>Bryan. </speaker>
          <l>Knowledge and it shall please you, who hither doth repaire To tell you good newes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e107380">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Good newes? what are they knowledge expresse? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e107400">
          <speaker>Bryan. </speaker>
          <l>A Knight hath slaine the flying Serpent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e107420">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Tush it is not so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e107440">
          <speaker>Bryan. </speaker>
          <l>It is most true that I do confesse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e107460">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Ah what hight his name Knowledge? let me that vnderstand. </l>
          <l>Clamydes the White Knight, sonne to the King of Swauia land, </l>
          <l>Who for Iuliana, daughter to the King of Denmarks grace, </l>
          <l>Did take the attempt in hand, now you know the whole case. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e107510">
          <speaker>Bryan. </speaker>
          <l>Ah happy newes of gladsomnesse vnto my danted mind, </l>
          <l>Now for to winne my Ladyes loue, good fortune is assignd: </l>
          <l>For though she be Clamydes, right wonne worthely indeed, </l>
          <l>Yet will I sure possesse that Dame, by giuing of the head. </l>
          <l>But Knowledge where about declare, doeth that Clamydes rest? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e107570">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Euen hard by in the Forrest heere where he slew the beast </l>
          <l>I left him, and to seeke you did hye: </l>
          <l>But let vs go furder into the woods, you shall meete him by and by. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e107610">
          <speaker>Bryan. </speaker>
          <l>Well Knowledge for thy paines take this as some reward, </l>
          <l>And if thou wilt abide with me, be sure ile thee regard </l>
          <l>Aboue all others of my men, besides ile giue to thee </l>
          <l>A thing, that from inchantments aye, preserued shalt thou be. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e107660">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Then here is my hand, ile be your seruant euer: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e107680">
          <speaker>Bryan. </speaker>
          <l>And seeing thou art a coward as well as I, ile forsake thee neuer. </l>
          <l>But come let vs go Clamydes to meete. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e107710">Exeunt. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e107720">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Keepe on your way and ile follow, I trust if he meete him, heele take him to his feete. </l>
          <l>Gogs bloud was euer seene such a iolt-headed villaine as he, </l>
          <l>To be so afraid of such a faint-hart knaue as I am to see? </l>
          <l>Of the fraternitie quoth you? burlady its a notable brood: </l>
          <l>Well Shift these chinks doeth thy hart some good: </l>
          <l>And ile close with Bryan till I haue gotten the thing </l>
          <l>That he hath promised me, and then ile be with him to bring. </l>
          <l>Well, such shifting knaues as I am, the ambodexter must play, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-011-b"/>
          <l>And for commoditie serue euery man, whatsoeuer the world say, </l>
          <l>Well after Bryan I will, and close with him awhile, </l>
          <l>But as well as Clamydes, in the end ile him begile. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e107840">Enter Clamydes, with the head vpon his sword. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e107850">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Ah happy day my deadly foe submitted hath to death, </l>
          <l>Lo heere the hand, lo heere the sword that stopt the vitall breath: </l>
          <l>Lo heere the head that shall possesse my Iulianas deare, </l>
          <l>The Knight of the golden Sheeld his force, what neede I now to feare: </l>
          <l>Since I by force subdued haue this Serpent fierce of might, </l>
          <l>Who vanquisht hath as I haue heard, full many a worthie Knight. </l>
          <l>Which for to winne my Ladyes loue, their liues haue venterd heere, </l>
          <l>Besides that cowardly Bryan which the faithlesse shield doth beare: </l>
          <l>A number keepes as I haue heard, as captiues in his hold, </l>
          <l>Whome he hath by inchantment got, and not through courage bold. </l>
          <l>Shall such defamed dastards, dard by Knights, thus beare their name? </l>
          <l>Shall such as are without all faith, liue to impaire our fame? </l>
          <l>Shall valiant harts by cowardly charme, be kept in captiues thrall? </l>
          <l>Shall Knights liue subiect to a wretch which hath no hart at all? </l>
          <l>Nay first Clamydes claime to thee fell Atrapos his stroke, </l>
          <l>Ere thou doest see such worthy Knights to beare the heauie yoke, </l>
          <l>Of cowardly Bryan without faith, his charmes let daunt not thee, </l>
          <l>And for his force thou needst not feare, the Gods thy shield will be. </l>
          <l>Well, to meete the Knight of the golden Shield, yet ten daies space I haue, </l>
          <l>And to set free these worthy Knights, but rest a while I craue. </l>
          <l>Heere in this place neere to this fort, for that I weary am </l>
          <l>With trauell, since from killing of the Serpent late I came: </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e108080">Heere let him sit downe and rest himselfe. </stage>
          <l>Lo heere a while I mind to rest, and Bryan then subdue, </l>
          <l>And then to Alexanders court, to keepe my promise true. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e108110">Enter Bryan sance foy, and Shift. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e108120">
          <speaker>Bryan. </speaker>
          <l>Come Knowledge, for here he lyes layd weary on the ground: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e108140">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Nay, ile not come in his sight, if you would giue me a thousand pound. </l>
          <l>For he is the terriblest Knight of any you haue heard spoke, </l>
          <l>Heele beate a hundreth such as you and I am downe at one stroke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e108180">
          <speaker>Bryan. </speaker>
          <l>Tush, feare thou naught at al, I haue charmed him, and he is fast asleepe, </l>
          <l>Lying neere vnto the Castle here which I do keepe. </l>
          <l>And ten dayes in this sleepe I haue charm'd him to remaine, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-012-a"/>
          <l>Before nature shall ouercome it, that he might wake againe. </l>
          <l>In the meane season, lo behold the Serpents head ile take away, </l>
          <l>His shield and his apparell, this done, then will I conuay </l>
          <l>His body into prison, with other his companions to lye, </l>
          <l>Whose strengths, ah knowledge, I durst neuer attempt to try. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e108270">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Ah handle him softly, or else you wil cause him to awake: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e108290">
          <speaker>Bryan. </speaker>
          <l>Tush, tush, not if all the noyse in the world I were able to make, </l>
          <l>Till ten dayes be expired, the charme will not leaue him, </l>
          <l>And then I am sure he will maruell who did thus deceiue him: </l>
          <l>So now he is stripped, stay thou here for a season, </l>
          <l>And ile go fetch two of my seruants to cary him into prison. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e108350">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e108360">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Well do so maister Bryan, and for your comming ile stay, </l>
          <l>Gogs bloud what a villaine am I my maister to betray. </l>
          <l>Nay sure ile awake him if it be possible ere they carry him to iayle: </l>
          <l>Maister, what maister, awake man, what maister, ah it will not preuaile. </l>
          <l>Am not I worthie to be hangd, was euer seene such a deceitfull knaue? </l>
          <l>What villany was in me, when vnto Bryan vnderstanding I gaue </l>
          <l>Of my maisters being in this forrest, but much I muse indeed </l>
          <l>What he meanes to do with my maisters apparell, his shield and the head? </l>
          <l>Well, seeing it is through my villany, my maister is at this drift, </l>
          <l>Yet when he is in prison, Shift shall not be voide of a shift </l>
          <l>To get him away, but if it euer come to his eare </l>
          <l>That I was the occasion of it, heele hang me thats cleare. </l>
          <l>Well heere comes Bryan, ile cloke with him if I may, </l>
          <l>To haue the keeping of my maister in prison night and day. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e108510">Enter Bryan sance foy, two seruants. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e108520">
          <speaker>Bryan. </speaker>
          <l>Come sirs take vp this body, and cary it into the appointed place, </l>
          <l>And there let it lye, for as yet he shall sleepe ten dayes space. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e108550">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>How say you maister Bryan, shall I of him haue the gard? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e108570">
          <speaker>Bryan. </speaker>
          <l>By my troth policie, thy good will to reward </l>
          <l>In hope of thy iust seruice, content I agree </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e108600">Cary him out. </stage>
          <l>For to resigne the keeping of this same Knight vnto thee. </l>
          <l>But giue me thy hand that thou wilt deceiue me neuer: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e108630">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Heres my hand, charme, inchant, make a spider catcher of me, if I be false to you euer. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-012-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e108650">
          <speaker>Bryan. </speaker>
          <l>Well then come follow after me, and the gard of him thou shal haue. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e108670">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e108680">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>A thousand thanks I giue you, this is all the promotion I craue: </l>
          <l>Ah sirrah, little knowes Bryan, that Clamydes my maister is, </l>
          <l>But to set him free from prison I entend not to mis: </l>
          <l>Yet still in my mind, I can do no other but muse, </l>
          <l>What practise with my maisters apparell and shell he will vse: </l>
          <l>Well, seeing I haue played the craftie knaue with the one, ile play it with the other: </l>
          <l>Subtill Shift for aduantage, will deceiue his owne brother. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e108760">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e108770">Here let them make a noyse as though they were Marriners. And after Clyomon Knight of G. S. come in with one. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e108780">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Ah set me to shore sirs, in what countrey so euer we bee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e108800">
          <speaker>Shiftmai. </speaker>
          <l>Well hayle out the Cockboate, seeing so sicke we do him see, </l>
          <l>Strike sayle, cast Ankers, till we haue rigd our Ship againe, </l>
          <l>For neuer were we in such stormes before, thats plaine. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e108840">Enter Clyomon, Boateswaine. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e108850">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Ah Boateswaine, gramercies for thy setting me to shore. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-boatswain" xml:id="ep000801-e108870">
          <speaker>Boatswaine. </speaker>
          <l>Truly Gentlemen we were neuer in the like tempests before. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e108890">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>What countrey is this wherein now we be? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-boatswain" xml:id="ep000801-e108910">
          <speaker>Boates. </speaker>
          <l>Sure the Ile of strange Marshes, as our maister told to me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e108930">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>How far is it from Macedonia, canst thou declare? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-boatswain" xml:id="ep000801-e108950">
          <speaker>Boates. </speaker>
          <l>More then twentie dayes sayling, and if the weather were faire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e108970">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Ah cruell hap of Fortunes spite, which signed this luck to me: </l>
          <l>What Pallace Boateswaine is this same, canst thou declare, we see? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-boatswain" xml:id="ep000801-e109000">
          <speaker>Boates. </speaker>
          <l>There King Patranius keepes his Court, so farre as I do gesse, </l>
          <l>And by this traine of Ladyes heere, I sure can iudge no lesse. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e109030">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e109040">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Well Boateswaine, theres for thy paines, and here vpon the shore </l>
          <l>Ile lie to rest my wearie bones, of thee I craue no more. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e109070">Enter Neronis daughter to Patranius, King of the strange Marshes, two Lords, two Ladies. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e109080">
          <speaker>Neronis. </speaker>
          <l>My Lords, come will it please you walk abroad to take the pleasant ayre? </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-013-a"/>
          <l>According to our wonted vse, in fields both fresh and faire, </l>
          <l>My Ladies here I know right well, will not gainsay the same. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-1" xml:id="ep000801-e109120">
          <speaker>1. Lord. </speaker>
          <l>Nor we sure for to pleasure you, Neronis noble Dame. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e109140">
          <speaker>Nero, </speaker>
          <l>Yes yes, men they loue intreatie much, before they will be wonne, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-2" xml:id="ep000801-e109160">
          <speaker>2. Lo. </speaker>
          <l>No Princes that hath womens natures beene, since first the world begunne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e109180">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>So you say. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-1" xml:id="ep000801-e109200">
          <speaker>1. Lo. </speaker>
          <l>We boldly may, </l>
          <l>Vnder correction of your grace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e109230">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Well, will it please you forth to trace, </l>
          <l>That when we haue of fragrant fields, the dulcet fumes obtained, </l>
          <l>We may vnto the Sea side go, whereas is to be gained, </l>
          <l>More straunger sights among Neptunes waues, in seeing Ships to saile, </l>
          <l>Which passe here by my fathers shore, with merrie westerne gaile. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-1" xml:id="ep000801-e109290">
          <speaker>1. Lo. </speaker>
          <l>We shall your highnesse leade the way to fields erst spoke before. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e109310">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Do so, and as we do returne weele come hard by the shore. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e109330">Exeunt. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e109340">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>What greater griefe can grow to gripe, the heart of greeued wight, </l>
          <l>Then thus to see fell Fortune she, to hold his state in spight. </l>
          <l>Ah cruell chance, ah lucklesse lot, to me poore wretch assign'd, </l>
          <l>Was euer seene such contraries, by fraudulent Goddesse blind. </l>
          <l>To any one saue onely I, imparted for to be, </l>
          <l>To animate the mind of any man, did euer Fortune she </l>
          <l>Showe forth her selfe so cruell bent, as thus to keepe me backe, </l>
          <l>From pointed place by weather driuen, my sorrowes more to sacke, </l>
          <l>Ah fatall hap, herein alas, what furder shall I say? </l>
          <l>Since I am forced for to breake, mine oath and pointed day. </l>
          <l>Before King Alexanders grace, Clamydes will be there: </l>
          <l>And I through Fortunes cruell spight, opprest with sicknesse here: </l>
          <l>For now within two dayes it is that we should meete togither, </l>
          <l>Woe worth the wind and raging stormes, alas that brought me hither. </l>
          <l>Now will Clamides me accuse, a faithlesse knight to be, </l>
          <l>And eke report, that cowardlinesse did dant the heart of me. </l>
          <l>The worthy praise that I haue wonne, through fame shall be defaced, </l>
          <l>The name of the Knight of the Golden Sheeld, alas shall be defaced: </l>
          <l>Before that noble Prince of might, whereas Clamydes he </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-013-b"/>
          <l>Will showe himselfe in Combat wise, for to exclaime on me, </l>
          <l>For breaking of my poynted day, and Clyomon to thy greefe, </l>
          <l>Now art thou in a countrey strange, cleane voyd of all releefe: </l>
          <l>Opprest with sicknesse through the rage of stormie blasts and cold, </l>
          <l>Ah death come with thy direfull Mace, for longer to vnfold </l>
          <l>My sorrowes here it booteth not yet Clyomon do stay, </l>
          <l>The Ladies loe, comes towards thee, that walkt the other way. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e109610">Enter Neronis, two Lords, two Ladies. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e109620">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Come faire dames, sith that we haue in fragrant fields obtained, </l>
          <l>Of dulcet flowers the pleasant smell, and that these knights disdained </l>
          <l>Not to beare vs company, our walke more large to make, </l>
          <l>Here by the sea of surging waues, our home returne weele make. </l>
          <l>My Lords therefore do keepe your way. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-1" xml:id="ep000801-e109680">
          <speaker>1. Lo. </speaker>
          <l>As it please your grace, we shall obey, </l>
          <l>But behold Madame, what wofull wight, here in our way before, </l>
          <l>As seemeth very sicke to me, doth lie vpon the shore. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e109720">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>My Lords, lets know the cause of greefe, whereof he is oppressed: </l>
          <l>That if he be a knight, it may by some meanes be redressed. </l>
          <l>Faire sir well met, why lie you here? what is your cause of griefe? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e109760">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>O Lady, sicknesse by the Sea, hath me opprest in briefe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e109780">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Of truth my Lords, his countenance bewrayes him for to bee, </l>
          <l>In health, of valiant heart and mind, and eke of hye degree. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-2" xml:id="ep000801-e109810">
          <speaker>2. Lo. </speaker>
          <l>It doth no lesse then so import, O Princes as you say. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e109830">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Of whence are you? or whats your name? you wander forth this way. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e109850">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Of small valure O Lady faire, alas my name it is, </l>
          <l>And for not telling of the same, hath brought me vnto this. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e109880">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Why, for what cause sir Knight, shuld you not expresse your name? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e109900">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Because O Lady I haue vowed, contrary to the same. </l>
          <l>But where I trauell Lady faire, in Citie, Towne or field, </l>
          <l>I am called, and do beare by name, the knight of the Golden Shield. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e109940">
          <speaker>Ne. </speaker>
          <l>Are you that knight of the Golden sheeld, of whom such fame doth go? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e109960">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>I am that selfe same knight faire dame, as here my Sheeld doth sho. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e109980">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Ah worthy then of helpe indeed, my Lords assist I pray, </l>
          <l>And to my lodging in the court, see that you him conuey, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-014-a"/>
          <l>For certainly within my minde, his state is much deplored, </l>
          <l>But do dispaire in nought sir knight, for you shall be restored, </l>
          <l>If Phisicke may your greefe redresse, for I Neronis loe, </l>
          <l>Daughter to Patranius king, for that which fame doth shoe, </l>
          <l>Vpon your acts, will be your friend, as after you shall proue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-1" xml:id="ep000801-e110060">
          <speaker>1. Lo. </speaker>
          <l>In doing so, you shall haue need of mightie loue aboue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e110080">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>O Princes, if I euer be to health restord againe, </l>
          <l>Your faithfull seruant day and night, I vow here to remaine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e110110">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Well my Lords, come after me, do bring him I require: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-ambo" xml:id="ep000801-e110130">
          <speaker>Ambo. </speaker>
          <l>We shall O Princes willingly accomplish your desire. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e110150">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e110160">Enter Bryan sance foy, hauing Clamydes his apparell on his Sheeld, and the Serpents head. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e110170">
          <speaker>Bry. </speaker>
          <l>Ah sirrah, now is the ten dayes full expired, wherein Clamydes he, </l>
          <l>Shall wake out of his charmed sleepe, as shortly you shall see: </l>
          <l>But here I haue what I desired, his Sheeld, his coat and head, </l>
          <l>To Denmarke will I straight prepare, and there present with speed, </l>
          <l>The same to Iulianas grace, as in Clamydes name, </l>
          <l>Whereby I am assur'd I shall enioy that noble Dame. </l>
          <l>For why Clamydes he is safe, for euer being free, </l>
          <l>And vnto knowledge is he left, here garded for to bee: </l>
          <l>But no man knowes of my pretents, ne whither I am gone, </l>
          <l>For secretly from Castle I, haue stolne this night alone </l>
          <l>In this order as you see, in the attire of a noble knight, </l>
          <l>But yet poore Bryan, still thy heart holds courage in despight. </l>
          <l>Well, yet the old prouerbe to disproue, I purpose to begin, </l>
          <l>Which alwayes sayth, that cowardly hearts, faire Ladies neuer win. </l>
          <l>Shall I not Iulianas win, and who hath a cowardlyer hart, </l>
          <l>Yet for to brag and boast it out, ile will none take my part. </l>
          <l>For I can sooke both grim and fierce, as though I were of might, </l>
          <l>And yet three Frogs out of a bush, my heart did so affright, </l>
          <l>That I fell dead almost therewith, well cowardly as I am, </l>
          <l>Farewell, Forrest for now I will in knight Clamydes name, </l>
          <l>To Denmarke to present this head, to Iuliana bright, </l>
          <l>Who shall cowardly dastard wed, in steed of a worthy knight. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e110400">Exit. </stage>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-014-b"/>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e110410">Enter Shift with sword and target. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e110420">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Be your leaue I came vp so early this morning that I cannot see my way, </l>
          <l>I am sure its scarce yet in the breake of the day. </l>
          <l>But you muse I am sure wherefore these weapons I bring, </l>
          <l>Well, listen vnto my tale, and you shall know euery thing. </l>
          <l>Because I played the shifting knaue, to saue my selfe from harme, </l>
          <l>And by my procurement, my maister was brought in this charme. </l>
          <l>The ten dayes are exspir'd, and this morning he shall awake, </l>
          <l>And now like a craftie knaue, to the prison my way will I take, </l>
          <l>With these same weapons, as though I would fight to set him free, </l>
          <l>Which will giue occasion that he shall mistrust, there was no deceit in mee. </l>
          <l>And hauing the charge of him, here vnder Bryan sance foy, </l>
          <l>Ile open the prison doores, and make as though I did imploy </l>
          <l>To do it by force, through good will, and onely for his sake, </l>
          <l>Then shall Clamydes being at liberty, the weapons of me take, </l>
          <l>And set vpon Bryan and all his men, now that they are a sleepe, </l>
          <l>And so be reuenged, for that he did him keepe </l>
          <l>By charme in this order, so shall they both deceiued be, </l>
          <l>And yet vpon neither part mistrust towards me. </l>
          <l>Well, neere to the prison ile draw, to see if he be awake, </l>
          <l>Harke, harke, this same is he, that his lamentation doth make. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e110630">
          <speaker>Clamydes in prison. </speaker>
          <l>Ah fatall hap, where am I wretch, in what distressed cace, </l>
          <l>Be reft of Tyro, head and sheeld, not knowing in what place </l>
          <l>My body is, ah heauenly gods, was ere such strangenes seene: </l>
          <l>What do I dreame? or am I still within the forrest greene? </l>
          <l>Dreame? no, no, alas I dreame not I, my senses all do faile, </l>
          <l>The strangenes of this cruell hap, doth make my hart to quaile. </l>
          <l>Clamydes ah by fortune she, what froward luck and fate </l>
          <l>Most cruelly assigned is, vnto thy noble state. </l>
          <l>Where should I be, or in what place hath desteny assignd </l>
          <l>My sely corps for want of foode and comfort to be pind. </l>
          <l>Ah farewell hope of purchasing my lady, since is lost, </l>
          <l>The Serpents head whereby I should possesse that iewell most. </l>
          <l>Ah farewell hope of honour eke, now shall I breake my day </l>
          <l>Before king Alexanders grace, whereon my faith doth stay. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-015-a"/>
          <l>And shall I be found a faithlesse Knight, fye on fell fortune she, </l>
          <l>Which hath her wheele of froward chance, thus whirled back on me. </l>
          <l>Ah farewell King of Swauia land, ah farewell Denmarke dame, </l>
          <l>Farewell thou Knight of the golden Sheeld, to thee shall rest all fame. </l>
          <l>To me this direfull desteny, to thee I know renowne, </l>
          <l>To me the blast of ignomy, to thee dame honours crowne. </l>
          <l>Ah hatefull hap, what shall I say, I see the gods hath signed </l>
          <l>Through cruelty my carefull corps, in prison to be pined. </l>
          <l>And nought alas amates me so, but that I know not where I am, </l>
          <l>Nor how into this dolefull place my wofull body came. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e110880">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Alas good Clamydes, in what an admiration is he, </l>
          <l>Not knowing in what place his body should be. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e110910">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Who nameth poore Clamydes there? reply to him againe, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e110930">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Ant shall please you I am your seruant Knowledge, which in a thousand woes for you remaine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e110950">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Ah Knowledge where am I declare and be briefe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e110970">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Where are you? faith euen in the Castle of that false theefe </l>
          <l>Bryan sance foy, against whome to fight and set you free, </l>
          <l>Looke out at the windowe, behold I haue brought tooles with mee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e111010">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Ah Knowledge, then cowardly that caitife did me charme. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e111030">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Yea, or else he could neuer haue done you any harme, </l>
          <l>But be of good cheere, for such a shift I haue made, </l>
          <l>That the keyes of the prison I haue got, your selfe perswade: </l>
          <l>Wherewith this morning I am come to set you free, </l>
          <l>And as they lye in their beds, you may murder Bryan and his men, and set all other at libertie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e111090">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Ah Knowledge, this hath me bound to be thy friend for euer: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e111110">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>A true seruant you may see will deceiue his maister neuer. </l>
          <l>So the doores are open, now come and follow after me. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e111140">Enter out. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e111150">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Ah heauens, in what case my selfe do I see: </l>
          <l>But speake Knowledge, canst thou tell how long haue I bene heere? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e111180">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>These ten dayes full, and sleeping still, this sentence is most cleere. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e111200">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Alas, then this same is the day the which appointed was </l>
          <l>By the Knight of the golden Sheeld to me, that combat ours should passe </l>
          <l>Before king Alexanders grace, and there I know he is, </l>
          <l>Ah cruell Fortune why shouldst thou thus wrest my chance amis: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-015-b"/>
          <l>Knowing I do but honour seeke, and thou doest me defame, </l>
          <l>In that contrary mine exspect, thou all things seekes to frame. </l>
          <l>The faith and loyaltie of a knight thou causest me to breake, </l>
          <l>Ah hatefull dame, why shouldst thou thus thy fury on me wreake, </l>
          <l>Now will king Alexander iudge the thing in me to bee, </l>
          <l>The which since first I armes could beare, no wight did euer see. </l>
          <l>But knowledge giue from thee to me, those weapons that I may </l>
          <l>Vpon that Bryan be reueng'd, which cowardly did betray </l>
          <l>Me of my things, and heere from thrall all other knights set free, </l>
          <l>Whome he by charme did bring in bale, as erst he did by mee. </l>
          <l>Come, into his lodging will I go, and challenge him and his. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e111360">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e111370">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Do so, and to follow I will not mis. </l>
          <l>Ah sirra, here was a shift according to my nature and condition, </l>
          <l>And a thousand shifts more I haue, to put my selfe out of suspition. </l>
          <l>But it doth me good to thinke how that cowardly knaue Bryan sance foy </l>
          <l>Shall be taken in the snare, my hart doth euen leape for ioy. </l>
          <l>Harke, harke, my maister is amongst them, but let him shift as he can, </l>
          <l>For not to deale with a dog, he shall haue help of his man. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e111450">Exeunt. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e111460">Enter after a little fight within, Clamydes three Knights. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e111470">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Come, come sir Knights, for so vnfortunate was neuer none as I, </l>
          <l>That I should ioy that is my ioy, the heauens themselues deny. </l>
          <l>That cowardly wretch that kept you here, and did me so deceiue, </l>
          <l>Is fled away and hath the Sheeld, the which my Lady gaue </l>
          <l>To me in token of her loue, the Serpents head like case, </l>
          <l>For which this mine aduenture was, to winne her noble grace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-1" xml:id="ep000801-e111540">
          <speaker>1 Knight. </speaker>
          <l>And sure that same th'occasion was, why we aduentred hether. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e111560">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Well, sith I haue you deliuered, when as you please together </l>
          <l>Each one into his natiue soile his iourney do prepare, </l>
          <l>For though that I haue broke my day as erst I did declare, </l>
          <l>Through this most cowardly catifes charmes, in meeting of the Knight, </l>
          <l>Which of the golden Sheeld beares name, to know else what he hight: </l>
          <l>I will to Alexanders court, and if that thence he be, </l>
          <l>Yet will I seeke to finde him out, least he impute to me </l>
          <l>Some cause of cowardlinesse to be, and therefore sir Knights depart, </l>
          <l>As to my selfe I wish to you with feruent zeale of hart: </l>
          <l>Yet if that any one of you do meete this Knight by way </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-016-a"/>
          <l>What was the cause of this my let, let him perstand I pray. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-omnes" xml:id="ep000801-e111680">
          <speaker>Omnes. </speaker>
          <l>We shall not misse ô noble Knight, to accomplish this your will. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e111700">Exeunt. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e111710">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Well then adue fit Knights each one, the gods protect you still. </l>
          <l>What knowledge ho, where art thou man? come forth that hence we may. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e111740">
          <speaker>Shift within. </speaker>
          <l>Where am I? faith breaking open of chests here within, for ile haue the spoile of all away. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e111760">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Tush, tush, I pray thee come that hence we may, no riches thou shalt lacke. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e111780">Shift with a bag as it were full of gold on his backe. </stage>
          <l>I come now with as much money as I am able to carry of my backe. </l>
          <l>A there was neuer poore asse so loden, but how now, that cowardly Bryan haue you slaine? </l>
          <l>And your Sheeld, the Serpents head, and coate, haue you againe? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e111820">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Ah no knowledge, the knights that here were captiues kept, they are by me at libertie, </l>
          <l>But that false Bryan this same night, is fled away for certaintie. </l>
          <l>And hath all things he tooke from me, conuayed where none doth know. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e111860">
          <speaker>Shift, </speaker>
          <l>O the bones of me, how will you then do for the Serpents head to Iuliana to show? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e111880">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>I haue no other hope alas, but onely that her grace </l>
          <l>Will credit giue vnto my words, when as I shew my cace </l>
          <l>How they were lost, but first ere I vnto that dame returne, </l>
          <l>He seeke the knight of the golden Sheeld, whereas he doth soiourne, </l>
          <l>To accomplish what my father wild, and therefore come away. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e111940">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e111950">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Well, keepe on before, for I mind not to stay. </l>
          <l>A fura, the craftiest knaue, the better lucke, thats plaine, </l>
          <l>I haue such a deale of substance here, where Bryans men are slaine, </l>
          <l>That is passeth. O that I had while for to stay, </l>
          <l>I could lode a hundreth cuts full of kitching stuffe away. </l>
          <l>Well, its not best to cary too long behinde, left my maister ouer-go, </l>
          <l>And then some knaue knowing of my money, a peece of cosonage sho. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e112030">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e112040">Enter Neronis. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e112050">
          <speaker>Neronis. </speaker>
          <l>How cast that tree but withered be </l>
          <l>That wanteth sap to moist the roote? </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-016-b"/>
          <l>How can that Vine but waste and pine, </l>
          <l>Whose plants are troden vnder foote? </l>
          <l>How can that spray but soone decay, </l>
          <l>That is with wild weeds ouergrowne? </l>
          <l>How can that wight in ought delight </l>
          <l>Which showes, and hath no good will showne? </l>
          <l>Or else how can that heart alasse, </l>
          <l>But die by whom each ioy doth passe? </l>
          <l>Neronis, ah I am the Tree, which wanteth sap to moyst the roote. </l>
          <l>Neronis, ah I am the vine, whose Plants are troden vnder foote. </l>
          <l>I am the spray which doth decay, and is with wild weeds ouergrowne, </l>
          <l>I am the wight without delight, which shows, and hath no good wil showne. </l>
          <l>Mine is the heart by whom alas, each pleasant ioy doth passe, </l>
          <l>Mine is the heart which vades away, as doth the flower or grasse. </l>
          <l>In wanting sap to moyst the roote, is ioyes that made me glad, </l>
          <l>And plants being troden vnder foote, is pleasures that was had. </l>
          <l>I am the spray which doth decay, whom cares haue ouergrowne, </l>
          <l>But stay Neronis, thou saist thou showest, and hath no good will showne: </l>
          <l>Why so I do, how can I tell, Neronis force no crueltie </l>
          <l>Thou seest thy knight endued is, with all good gifts of courtesie: </l>
          <l>And doth Neronis loue indeed, to whom loue doth she yeeld, </l>
          <l>Euen to that noble brute of fame, the knight of the golden Sheeld. </l>
          <l>Ah wofull Dame, thou knowest not thou, of what degree he is, </l>
          <l>Of noble bloud his gesters showe, I am assured of this. </l>
          <l>Why belike he is some runnagate that will not show his name, </l>
          <l>Ah why should I this allegate, he is of noble fame. </l>
          <l>Why dost thou not expresse thy loue, to him Neronis then? </l>
          <l>Because shamefastnesse and womanhood, bids vs not seeke to men. </l>
          <l>Ah carefull Dame loe thus I stand, as twere one in a trance, </l>
          <l>And lacketh boldnesse for to speake, which should my words aduance. </l>
          <l>The knight of the Golden Sheeld it is, to whom a thrall I am, </l>
          <l>Whom I to health restored haue, since that to court he cam. </l>
          <l>And now he is prest to passe againe, vpon his wearie way, </l>
          <l>Vnto the Court of Alexander, yet hath he broke his day, </l>
          <l>As he to me the whole exprest, ah sight that doth me greeue, </l>
          <l>Loe where he comes to passe away, of me to take his leaue. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-017-a"/>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e112440">Enter Clyomon. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e112450">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Who hath more cause to praise the Gods, then I whose state deplored? </l>
          <l>Through phisicke and Neronis helpe, to health am now restored: </l>
          <l>Whose feruent thrall I am become, yet vrgent causes dooth </l>
          <l>Constraine me for to keepe it close, and not to put in proofe </l>
          <l>What I might do to winne her loue, as first my oath and vow, </l>
          <l>In keeping of my name vnknowne, which she will not allow, </l>
          <l>If I should seeme to breake my minde, being a Princes borne, </l>
          <l>To yeeld her loue to one vnknowne, I know sheele thinke it scorne? </l>
          <l>Besides here longer in this Court, alas I may not stay, </l>
          <l>Although that with Clamydes he, I haue not kept my day: </l>
          <l>Least this he should suppose in me, for cowardlinesse of hart, </l>
          <l>To seeke him out elsewhere, I will from out this Land depart. </l>
          <l>Yet though vnto Neronis she, I may not shew my mind, </l>
          <l>A faithfull heart when I am gone, with her I leaue behind. </l>
          <l>Whose bountiousnesse I here haue felt, but since I may not stay, </l>
          <l>I will to take my leaue of her, before I passe away. </l>
          <l>Loe where she walkes, O Princesse well met, why are you here so sad? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e112630">
          <speaker>Ne. </speaker>
          <l>Good cause I haue, since pleasures passe, the which shuld make me glad. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e112650">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>What you should meane, O Princesse deare, hereby I do not know. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e112670">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Then listen to my talke a while, Sir Knight and I will show. </l>
          <l>If case you will reaunswere me, my question to obsolue, </l>
          <l>The which propound within my mind, doth oftentimes reuolue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e112710">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>I will O Princes answere you as aptly as I may. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e112730">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Well then Sir Knight, apply your cares, and listen what I say: </l>
          <l>A ship that stormes had tossed long, amidst the mounting waues, </l>
          <l>Where harbour none was to be had, fell Fortune so depraues: </l>
          <l>Through ill successe that ship of hope, that Ancors hold doth faile, </l>
          <l>Yet at the last shees driuen to land, with broken Mast and saile: </l>
          <l>And through the force of furious wind, and Billowes bounsing blowes, </l>
          <l>She is a simple shipwracke made, in euery point God knowes. </l>
          <l>Now this same ship by chance being found, the finders take such paine, </l>
          <l>That fit to saile vpon the Seas, they rig her vp againe. </l>
          <l>And where she was through storms sore shakt, they make her whole &amp; sound </l>
          <l>Now answere me directly here, vpon this my propound. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-017-b"/>
          <l>If this same ship thus rent and torne, being brought in former rate, </l>
          <l>Should not supply the finders true to profit his estate </l>
          <l>In what she might. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e112880">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Herein a right, </l>
          <l>I will O Princesse as I may, directly answere you. </l>
          <l>This ship thus found, I put the case it hath an owner now, </l>
          <l>Which owner shall sufficiently content the finders charge: </l>
          <l>And haue againe to serue his vse, his ship, his boate or barge. </l>
          <l>The ship then cannot serue the turne of finders, this is plaine, </l>
          <l>If case the owner do content, or pay him for his paine: </l>
          <l>But otherwise if none lay claime, nor seeme that ship to stay, </l>
          <l>Then is it requisit it should, the finders paines repay: </l>
          <l>For such endeuour as it is to serue for his behoofe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e112990">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>What owner truly that it hath, I haue no certaine proofe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e113010">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Then can I not define thereof, but thus I wish it were, </l>
          <l>That you would me accept to be, that ship O Lady faire: </l>
          <l>And you the finder, then it should be needlesse for to mooue, </l>
          <l>If I the ship, of dutie ought to serue at your behooue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e113060">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Thou art the ship O worthy Knight, so shiuered found by mee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e113080">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>And owner haue I none deare dame, I yeeld me whole to thee: </l>
          <l>For as this ship I must confesse, that was a shipwrack made, </l>
          <l>Thou hast restored me vnto health, whom sicknesse causd to vade, </l>
          <l>For which I yeeld O Princesse deare, at pleasure thine to be, </l>
          <l>If your grace, O noble Dame, will so accept of me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e113140">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>If case I will, what haue you showne? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e113160">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Because I am to you vnknowne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e113180">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Your fame importeth what you be. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e113200">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>You may your pleasure say of me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e113220">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>What I haue said due proofe do showe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e113240">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Well Lady deare, to thee I owe </l>
          <l>More seruice then of dutie I am able to professe, </l>
          <l>For that thou didst preserue my life amidst my deepe distresse: </l>
          <l>But at this time I may not stay, O Lady here with thee, </l>
          <l>Thou knowest the cause, but this I vow within three score dayes to bee, </l>
          <l>If destinie restraine me not, at Court with thee againe, </l>
          <l>Protesting whilest that life doth last, thine faithfull to remaine. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-018-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e113320">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>And is there then no remedie, but needs you will depart? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e113340">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>No Princesse for a certaintie, but here I leaue my hart, </l>
          <l>In gage with thee till my returne, which as I said shall be: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e113370">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Well, sith no perswasion may preuaile, this Iewell take of me, </l>
          <l>And keepe it alwayes for my sake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e113400">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Of it a deare account ile make, yet let vs part deare Dame with ioy, </l>
          <l>And to do the same I will my selfe imploy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e113430">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Well now adieu till thy returne, the Gods thy iourney guide. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e113450">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e113460">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>And happily in absence mine, for thee deare Dame prouide: </l>
          <l>Ah Clyomon let dolours die, driue daunts from out thy mind, </l>
          <l>Since in the sight of Fortune now, such fauour, thou dost find, </l>
          <l>As for to haue the loue of her whom thou didst sooner judge. </l>
          <l>Would haue denied thy loyaltie, and gainst thy good will grudge, </l>
          <l>But that I may here keepe my day, you sacred Gods prouide, </l>
          <l>Most happie fate vnto my state, and thus my iourney guide: </l>
          <l>The which I tempt to take in hand Clamydes for to meete: </l>
          <l>That the whole cause of my first let, to him I may repeate. </l>
          <l>So shall I seeme for to excuse my selfe in way of right, </l>
          <l>And not be counted of my foe, a false periured Knight. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e113580">Exit. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e113590">Enter Thrasellus King of Norway two Lords. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-thrasellus" xml:id="ep000801-e113600">
          <speaker>Thra. </speaker>
          <l>Where deepe desire hath taken roote, my Lords alas you see, </l>
          <l>How that perswasion booteth not, if contrarie it be </l>
          <l>Vnto the first expected hope, where fancie hath take place, </l>
          <l>And vaine it is for to withdraw, by counsell in that case: </l>
          <l>The mind who with affection is, to one onely thing affected, </l>
          <l>The which may not till dint of death, from them be sure reiected: </l>
          <l>You know my Lords through fame, what force of loue hath taken place, </l>
          <l>Within my breast as touching now Neronis noble grace, </l>
          <l>Daughter to Patranius King, who doth the Scepter sway: </l>
          <l>And in the Ile of Marshes eke, beare rule now at this day. </l>
          <l>Through loue of daughter his, nay sorrowes daily grow, </l>
          <l>And daily do loues do me daunt, for that alas I show </l>
          <l>Such Friendship whereas favour none, is to be found againe: </l>
          <l>And yet from o●● my carefull mind, nought may her loue restraine. </l>
          <l>I sent to craue her of the king he answered me with nay: </l>
          <l>But shall I not prouide by force to fetch her thence away? </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-018-b"/>
          <l>Yes, yes, my Lords, and therefore let your aydes be prest with mine, </l>
          <l>For I will sure Neronis haue, or else my dayes ile pine. </l>
          <l>For King Patranius and his power, I hold of small account, </l>
          <l>To winne his daughter to my spouse, amids his men ile mount. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-1" xml:id="ep000801-e113810">
          <speaker>1 Lord. </speaker>
          <l>Most worthy Prince, this rash attempt, I hold not for the best, </l>
          <l>For sure Patranius power is great, and not to be supprest. </l>
          <l>For why, the ile enuirond is, with sea on euery side, </l>
          <l>And landing place lo is there none, whereas you may haue tide </l>
          <l>To set your men from ship to shore, but by one onely way, </l>
          <l>And in that place a garison great, he keepeth at this day. </l>
          <l>So that if you should bring your power, your trauell were in vaine, </l>
          <l>That is not certainly the way, Neronis for to gaine. </l>
          <l>But this your grace may do indeed, and so I count it best, </l>
          <l>To be in all points with a Ship, most like a Merchant prest: </l>
          <l>And saile with such as you thinke best, all drest in Merchants guise, </l>
          <l>And for to get her to your Ship, some secret meane deuise, </l>
          <l>By shewing of strange Merchandies, or other such like thing, </l>
          <l>Lo this is best aduise I can, Thrassellus Lord and King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-2" xml:id="ep000801-e113960">
          <speaker>2 Lord. </speaker>
          <l>And certainly as you haue sayd, my Lord it is the way, </l>
          <l>Wherefore ô King, do prosecute the same without delay. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-thrasellus" xml:id="ep000801-e113990">
          <speaker>Thrasell. </speaker>
          <l>Of truth my Lords this your aduise doth for our purpose frame, </l>
          <l>Come therefore let vs hence depart, to put in vre the same </l>
          <l>With present speed, for Merchant-wise my selfe will thither saile: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-1" xml:id="ep000801-e114030">
          <speaker>1 Lord. </speaker>
          <l>This is the way if any be, of purpose to preuaile. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e114050">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e114060">Enter Clyomon with a Knight, signifying one of those that Clamyde, had deliuered. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e114070">
          <speaker>Clyomon. </speaker>
          <l>Sir Knight, of truth this fortune was most luckely assignd, </l>
          <l>That we should meete in trauell thus, for thereby to my mind </l>
          <l>You haue a castle of comfort brought, in that you haue me told, </l>
          <l>Clamydes our appointed day, no more then I did hold. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-knight" xml:id="ep000801-e114120">
          <speaker>Knight. </speaker>
          <l>No certis sir he kept not day, the cause I haue expressed, </l>
          <l>Through that inchanter Bryans charmes, he came full sore distressed: </l>
          <l>Yet fortune fauored so his state, that through his help all wee </l>
          <l>Which captiues were through cowardly craft, from bondage were set free: </l>
          <l>And at our parting willed vs, if any with you met, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-019-a"/>
          <l>We should informe you with the truth what was his onely let. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e114190">
          <speaker>Clyomon. </speaker>
          <l>Well, know you where he abideth now, sir Knight I craue of curtesie? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-knight" xml:id="ep000801-e114210">
          <speaker>Knight. </speaker>
          <l>No questionlesse I know not I, to say it of a certaintie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e114230">
          <speaker>Clyomon. </speaker>
          <l>Well then adue sir Knight with thanks, I let you on your way: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-knight" xml:id="ep000801-e114250">
          <speaker>Knight. </speaker>
          <l>Vnto the gods I you commit, nought else I haue to say. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e114270">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e114280">
          <speaker>Clyomon. </speaker>
          <l>A sirra, now the hugie heapes of cares that lodged in my mind </l>
          <l>Is skaled from their nestling place, and pleasures passage find. </l>
          <l>For that as well as Clyomon, Clamydes broke his day, </l>
          <l>Vpon which newes my passage now in seeking him ile stay: </l>
          <l>And to Neronis back againe, my ioyfull iourney make, </l>
          <l>Least that she should in absence mine, some cause of sorrow take. </l>
          <l>And now all dumps of deadly dole, that danted knightly brest, </l>
          <l>A due, since salue of solace sweete, hath sorrowes all supprest. </l>
          <l>For that Clamydes cannot brag, nor me accuse in ought, </l>
          <l>Vnto the gods of destenies, that thus our fates hath brought </l>
          <l>In equall ballance to be wayed, due praises shall I send, </l>
          <l>That thus to way each cause aright, their eyes to earth did bend. </l>
          <l>Well, to keepe my day with Lady now, I mind not to be slack, </l>
          <l>Wherefore vnto Patranius court, ile dresse my iourney back. </l>
          <l>But stay, me thinks I Rumor heare throughout this land to ring, </l>
          <l>I will attend his talke, to know what tidings he doth bring. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e114450">Enter Rumor running. </stage>
          <l>Ye rowling Clowdes giue Rumor roome, both ayre and earth below, </l>
          <l>By sea and land, that euery eare may vnderstand and know, </l>
          <l>What wofull hap is chaunced now within the ile of late, </l>
          <l>Which of strange Marshes beareth name, vnto the noblest state. </l>
          <l>Neronis daughter to the King, by the King of Norway he, </l>
          <l>Within a ship of Marchandise, conuayed away is she. </l>
          <l>The King with sorow for her sake, hath to death resignd, </l>
          <l>And hauing left his Queene with child, to guide the realme behind. </l>
          <l>Mustantius brother to the King, from her the Crowne would take, </l>
          <l>But till she be deliuered, the Lords did order make, </l>
          <l>That they before King Alexander, thither comming should appeale, </l>
          <l>And he by whom they hold the Crowne, therein should rightly deale </l>
          <l>For either part, lo this to tell, I Rumor haue in charge, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-019-b"/>
          <l>And through all lands I do pretend, to publish it at large. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e114600">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e114610">
          <speaker>Clyomon. </speaker>
          <l>Ah wofull Rumor raunging thus, what tidings do I heare, </l>
          <l>Hath that false King of Norway stolne my loue and Lady deare? </l>
          <l>Ah hart, ah hand, ah head and mind, and euery sence beside, </l>
          <l>To serue your maisters turne in need, do euery one prouide. </l>
          <l>For till that I reuenged be vpon that wretched king, </l>
          <l>And haue againe my Lady deare, and her from Norway bring, </l>
          <l>I vow this body takes no rest, ah fortune fickle dame, </l>
          <l>That canst make glad and so soone sad, a Knight of worthie fame. </l>
          <l>But what should I delay the time, now that my deare is gone? </l>
          <l>Auaileth ought to ease my griefe, to make this pensiue mone? </l>
          <l>No, no, wherefore come courage to my hart, and happie hands prepare, </l>
          <l>For of that wretched King I will wreake all my sorow and care. </l>
          <l>And mauger all the might he may, be able for to make, </l>
          <l>By force of armes my lady I, from him and his will take. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e114760">Exit. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e114770">Enter Clamydes and Shift, with his bag of money still. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e114780">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Come knowledge, thou art much to blame, thus for to lode thy self </l>
          <l>To make thee on thy way diseased, with carying of that pelfe. </l>
          <l>But now take courage vnto thee, for to that ile I will, </l>
          <l>Which of strange Marshes called is, for fame declareth still </l>
          <l>The Knight of the golden Sheeld is there, and in the court abideth, </l>
          <l>Thither will I him to meete, whatsoeuer me betideth: </l>
          <l>And know his name, as thou canst tell my father charged me, </l>
          <l>Or else no more his princely court nor person for to see. </l>
          <l>Come therefore, that vnto that ile we may our iourney take, </l>
          <l>And afterwards hauing met with him, our viage for to make </l>
          <l>To Denmarke to my Lady there, to shew her all my cace, </l>
          <l>And then to Swauia if her I haue, vnto my fathers grace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e114910">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Nay but ant shall please you, are you sure the Knight of the golden Sheeld in the ile of strange Marshes is? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e114930">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>I was informed credibly, I warrant thee we shall not mis. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e114950">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e114960">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Then keepe on your way, ile follow as fast as I can, </l>
          <l>Faith he euen meanes to make a martris of poore Shift his man. </l>
          <l>And I am so tied to this bag of gold I got at Bryan sance foyes, </l>
          <l>That I tell you where this is, there all my ioy is: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-020-a"/>
          <l>But I am so weary, sometimes with ryding, sometimes with running, </l>
          <l>And other times going a foote: </l>
          <l>That when I came to my lodging at night, to bring me a woman it is no boore. </l>
          <l>And such care I take for this pelfe least I should it lose, </l>
          <l>That where I come, that it is gold, for my life I dare not disclose. </l>
          <l>Well after my maister I must, heeres nothing stil but running and ryding: </l>
          <l>But ile giue him the slip sure, if I once come where I may haue quiet biding. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e115080">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e115090">Enter Neronis in the Forrest, in mans apparell. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e115100">
          <speaker>Ne. </speaker>
          <l>As Hare the Hound, as Lambe the Wolfe, as foule the Fawcons dint, </l>
          <l>So do I flie from tyrant he, whose heart more hard then flint </l>
          <l>Hath sackt on me such hugie heapes of seaceles sorrowes here, </l>
          <l>That sure it is intollerable, the torments that I beare: </l>
          <l>Neronis, ah who knoweth thee, a Princes to be borne, </l>
          <l>Since fatall Gods so frowardly, thy fortune doth adorne: </l>
          <l>Neronis, ah who knoweth her, in painfull Pages show? </l>
          <l>But no good Lady wil me blame, which of my case doth know: </l>
          <l>But rather when they heare the truth, wherefore I am disguised, </l>
          <l>Thaile say it is an honest shift, the which I haue deuised: </l>
          <l>Since I haue giuen my faith and troth to such a brute of fame, </l>
          <l>As is the knight of the Golden Shield, and tyrants seekes to frame </l>
          <l>Their engins to detract our vowes, as the king of Norway hath, </l>
          <l>Who of all Princes liuing now, I finde deuoyd of faith: </l>
          <l>For like a wolfe in lambes skin clad, he commeth with his aide, </l>
          <l>All Marchant like to fathers Court, and ginneth to perswade </l>
          <l>That he had precious iewels bought, which in his ship did lye, </l>
          <l>Whereof he wild me take my choyce, if case I would them buy: </l>
          <l>Then I mistrusting no deceit, with handmaids one or two </l>
          <l>With this deceitfull Marchant then vnto the ship did go. </l>
          <l>No sooner were we vnder hatch, but vp they hoyst their saile, </l>
          <l>And hauing then to serue their turne, a mery Westerne gaile: </l>
          <l>We were lasht out from the hauen, lo a dosen leagues and more, </l>
          <l>When still I thought the Barke had bene, at anker by the shore: </l>
          <l>But being brought by Norway here, not long in Court I was, </l>
          <l>But that to get from thence away, I brought this feate to passe: </l>
          <l>For making semblance vnto him as though I did him loue, </l>
          <l>He gaue me libertie, or ought that seru'd for my behoue: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-020-b"/>
          <l>And hauing libertie, I wrought by such a secret slight, </l>
          <l>That in this tyre like to a page, I scapt away by night. </l>
          <l>But ah I feare that by pursute, he wil me ouertake, </l>
          <l>Well here entreth one, to whom some sure for seruice I wil make. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e115430">Enter Corin a Shepheard. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-corin" xml:id="ep000801-e115440">
          <speaker>Cor. </speaker>
          <l>Gos bone turne in that sheep there and you be good fellowes, </l>
          <l>Iesu how cham beraide, </l>
          <l>Chaue a cur here, an a were my vellow, cha must him conswade, </l>
          <l>And yet an cha should kisse, looke you of the arse, cha must run my selfe, an Ihil, </l>
          <l>An cha should entreat him with my cap in my hand, ha wad stand stil. </l>
          <l>But tis a world to zee what mery liues we shepheards lead, </l>
          <l>Why where Gentlemen and we get once a thorne bush ouer our head, </l>
          <l>We may sleep with our vaces against the zone, an were hogs </l>
          <l>Bath our selues, stretch out our legs ant were a cennell of dogs: </l>
          <l>And then at night when maides come to milkin, the games begin, </l>
          <l>But I may zay to you my nabor, Hogs maid had a clap, wel let them laugh that win. </l>
          <l>Chaue but one daughter, but chould not vor vorty pence she were zo sped, </l>
          <l>Cha may zay to you, she lookes euery night to go to bed: </l>
          <l>But tis no matter, the whores be so whiskish when thare vnder a bush, </l>
          <l>That thare neuer satisfied, til their bellies be flush. </l>
          <l>Well cha must abroad about my flocks, least the fengeance wolues catch a lambe: </l>
          <l>Vor by my cursen zoule, thale steale an cha stand by, there not a verd of the dam. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e115620">
          <speaker>Ne. </speaker>
          <l>Wel to scape the pursute of the king, of this same shepheard here, </l>
          <l>Suspition wholly to auoyd, for seruice ile enquire: </l>
          <l>Wel met good father, for your vse, a seruant do you lacke? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-corin" xml:id="ep000801-e115660">
          <speaker>Cor. </speaker>
          <l>What you wil not flout an old man you courtnold Iacke? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e115680">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>No truly father I flout you not, what I aske I would haue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-corin" xml:id="ep000801-e115700">
          <speaker>Co. </speaker>
          <l>Gos bones they leest, serue a shepheard an be zo braue? </l>
          <l>You courtnoll crackropes, wod be hangd, you do nothing now and then </l>
          <l>But come vp and downe the country, thus to flout poore men. </l>
          <l>Go too goodman boy, chaue no zeruis vor no zuch flouting Iacks as you be </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e115750">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Father I thinke as I speake, vpon my faith and troth beleeue me </l>
          <l>I wil willingly serue you, if in case you wil take me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-corin" xml:id="ep000801-e115780">
          <speaker>Cor. </speaker>
          <l>Doest not inocke? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e115800">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>No truly father. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-corin" xml:id="ep000801-e115820">
          <speaker>Cor. </speaker>
          <l>Then come with me, by gos bones Ihil neuer vorsake thee. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-021-a"/>
          <l>Whow bones of my zoule, tho wilt the brauest shepherds boy in our town, </l>
          <l>Thous go to church in this coate, beuore Madge a sonday in her gray gown. </l>
          <l>Good lord how our church-wardens wil looke vpon thee, bones of god zeest, </l>
          <l>There will be more looking at thee, then our sir Iohn the parish preest. </l>
          <l>Why euery body wil aske whose boy thart, an cha cantel the this by the way, </l>
          <l>Thou shalt haue al the varest wenches of our town in the veelds vor to play. </l>
          <l>Theres nabour Nychols daughter, a iolly smug whore with vat checkes, </l>
          <l>And nabour Hodges maide, meddle not with her, she hath eaten set leekes. </l>
          <l>But theres Frumptons wench in the freese scake, it will do thee good to see </l>
          <l>What canuosing is at the milking time, betweene her and mee. </l>
          <l>And those wenches will loue thee bonnomablely in euery place, </l>
          <l>But do not vall in with them in any kind of cace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e115960">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Tush, you shall not neede to feare me, I can be mery with measure as well as they: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-coryn" xml:id="ep000801-e115980">
          <speaker>Coryn. </speaker>
          <l>Wel then come follow after me, and home Ihil leade thee the way. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e116000">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Alas poore simple Shepheard, by this Princes may see, </l>
          <l>That like man, like talke, in euery degree. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e116030">Exeunt. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e116040">Enter Thrasellus King of Norway, and two Lords. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-thrasellus" xml:id="ep000801-e116050">
          <speaker>Thras. </speaker>
          <l>My Lords pursue her speedely, she cannot far be gone, </l>
          <l>And lo himselfe to seeke her out, your King he will be one. </l>
          <l>Ah fraudulent dame, how hath she glozd, from me to get away? </l>
          <l>With sugred words how hath she fed, my senses night and day? </l>
          <l>Professing loue with outward showes, and inwardly her hart </l>
          <l>To practise such a deepe deceit, whereby she might depart </l>
          <l>From out my court so sodainly, when I did wholy iudge </l>
          <l>She loued me most entirely, and not against me grudge. </l>
          <l>She made such signes by outward showes, I blame not wit and policie, </l>
          <l>But here I may exclaime and say, fye, fye, on womens subtiltie. </l>
          <l>Well well my Lords, no time delay, pursue her with all speed, </l>
          <l>And I this forest will seeke out my selfe, as is decreed, </l>
          <l>With aide of such as are behind, and will come vnto mee: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-ambo" xml:id="ep000801-e116190">
          <speaker>Ambo. </speaker>
          <l>We shal not slake what here in charge to vs is giuen by thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e116210">Exeunt. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-thrasellus" xml:id="ep000801-e116220">
          <speaker>Thras. </speaker>
          <l>Ah subtill Neronis, how hast thou me vexed? </l>
          <l>Through thy crafty dealings how am I perplexed? </l>
          <l>Did euer any winne a dame, and lose her in such sort? </l>
          <l>The maladies are maruellous, the which I do support </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-021-b"/>
          <l>Through her deceit, but forth I will my company to meete, </l>
          <l>If euer she be caught againe, I will her so intreate, </l>
          <l>That others all shall warning take, by such a subtill dame, </l>
          <l>How that a Prince for to delude, such ingins they do frame. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e116310">Enter Clyomon Knight of the golden Sheeld. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e116320">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Nay Traytour stay, and take with thee that mortall blow or stroke </l>
          <l>The which shall cause thy wretched corps this life for to reuoke. </l>
          <l>It ioyeth me at the hart that I haue met thee in this place. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-thrasellus" xml:id="ep000801-e116360">
          <speaker>Thras. </speaker>
          <l>What varlet darest thou be so bold, with words in such a cace, </l>
          <l>For to vpbraide thy Lord and King? what art thou soone declare? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e116390">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord and King, I thee defie, and in despite I dare </l>
          <l>Thee for to say thou art no Prince, for thou a Traytour art, </l>
          <l>And what reward is due therefore, to thee I shall impart. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-thrasellus" xml:id="ep000801-e116430">
          <speaker>Thras. </speaker>
          <l>Thou braggest all too boldly still, what hight thy name expresse? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e116450">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>What hight my name thou shalt not know, ne will I it confesse: </l>
          <l>But for that thou my Lady stolest from fathers court away, </l>
          <l>Ile sure reuenge that trayterous fact vpon thy flesh this day. </l>
          <l>Since I haue met so luckely with thee here all alone, </l>
          <l>Although as I do vnderstand, from thee she now is gone, </l>
          <l>Yet therefore do defend thy selfe, for here I thee assaile, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-thrasellus" xml:id="ep000801-e116520">
          <speaker>Thras. </speaker>
          <l>Alas poore boy, thinkest thou against me to preuaile? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e116540">Here let them fight, the King fall down dead. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-thrasellus" xml:id="ep000801-e116550">
          <speaker>Thras. </speaker>
          <l>Ah heauens, Thrasellus he is slaine, ye Gods his ghost receiue, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e116570">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Now hast thou iustice for thy fact, as thy desert doeth craue: </l>
          <l>But ah alas poore Clyomon, though thou thy foe hast slaine, </l>
          <l>Such greeuous wounds thou hast receiu'd, as doth increase thy paine. </l>
          <l>Vnles I haue some speedy help, my life must needly wast, </l>
          <l>And then as well as traytour false, my corps of death shall tast. </l>
          <l>Ah my Neronis where art thou? ah where art thou become? </l>
          <l>For thy sweete sake thy Knight shall here receiue his vitall doome. </l>
          <l>Lo here all gorde in bloud thy faithfull Knight doth lye, </l>
          <l>For thee, ah faithfull dame, thy Knight for lack of help shall dye. </l>
          <l>For thee, ah here thy Clyomon, his mortall stroke hath tane, </l>
          <l>For thee, ah these same hands of his, the Norway King hath slaine. </l>
          <l>Ah bleeding wounds from longer talke my foltring tong doth stay, </l>
          <l>And if I haue not speedy help, my life doth wast away. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-022-a"/>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e116710">Enter father Coryn the Shepheard, and his dog. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-coryn" xml:id="ep000801-e116720">
          <speaker>Coryn. </speaker>
          <l>A plage on thee for a cur, A ha, driuen me sheepe aboue from the flocke: </l>
          <l>A theefe, art not asham'd? ile beate thee like a stocke: </l>
          <l>And cha beene azeeking here, aboue voure miles and more: </l>
          <l>But Ihill tell you what, chaue the brauest lad of Iack the courtnoll, that euer was zeene beuore. </l>
          <l>A, the whorcop is plagely well lou'd in our towne, </l>
          <l>An you had zeene go to Church beuore Madge my wife in her holy day gowne, </l>
          <l>You would haue blest your zelues t'aue seene it, she went euen cheke by ioule </l>
          <l>With our head controms wife, brother to my nabour Nycholl, </l>
          <l>You know ha dwels by maister Iustice, ouer the water on the other side of the hill, </l>
          <l>Cham zure you know it, betweene my nabour Filchers varme house, and the wind-mill. </l>
          <l>But an you did zee how Ione Ienkin, and Gilian Giffrey loues my boy Iacke, </l>
          <l>Why it is maruelation to see, Ione did so bast Gillians backe, </l>
          <l>That by Gos bones I laught till cha bepist my zelfe, when cha zaw it, </l>
          <l>All the maides in towne valls out for my boy, but and the yongmen know it </l>
          <l>Thale be zo ielisom ouer them, that cham in doubt </l>
          <l>Ich shall not keepe Iack my boy till seuen yeares go about. </l>
          <l>Well, cham nere the neere vor my shepe, chaue sought it this voure mile, </l>
          <l>But chill home, and send Iack foorth to zeeke it another while. </l>
          <l>But bones of God man stay, Iesu whather wilt? wha what meanst lye heere? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e116920">
          <speaker>Clyomon. </speaker>
          <l>Ah good father help me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-coryn" xml:id="ep000801-e116940">
          <speaker>Coryn. </speaker>
          <l>Nay who there, by your leaue, Ihill not come neere. </l>
          <l>What another? bones of me, he is either kild or dead? </l>
          <l>Nay varewell vorty pence, yeare a knaue, gos death a doth bleede. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e116980">
          <speaker>Clyomon. </speaker>
          <l>I bleede indeede father, so grieuous my wounds bee, </l>
          <l>That if I haue not speedie help, long life is not in mee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-coryn" xml:id="ep000801-e117010">
          <speaker>Coryn. </speaker>
          <l>Why what art thou? or how chanst thou camst in this cace? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e117030">
          <speaker>Clyomon. </speaker>
          <l>Ah father, that dead corps which thou seest there in place, </l>
          <l>He was a Knight, and mine enemy, whome here I haue slaine, </l>
          <l>And I a Gentleman, whom he hath wounded with maruellous paine. </l>
          <l>Now thou knowest the truth, good father shew some curtesie </l>
          <l>To stop my bleeding wounds, that I may finde some remedie, </l>
          <l>My life to preserue, if possible I may? </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-022-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000801-coryn" xml:id="ep000801-e117100">
          <speaker>Coryn. </speaker>
          <l>Well he are you gentleman, chould haue you know this by the way, </l>
          <l>Cham but vather Coryn the sheepheard, cham no surringer I, </l>
          <l>But Ihill do what cha can vor you, cha were loth to see you die. </l>
          <l>Loe how zay you by this, haue cha done you any ease? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e117150">
          <speaker>Clya. </speaker>
          <l>Father thy willingnesse of a certaintie, doth me much please: </l>
          <l>But good father lend me thy helping hand once againe. </l>
          <l>To burie this same Knight whom here I haue slaine, </l>
          <l>Although he was to me a most deadly enemie, </l>
          <l>Yet to leaue his body vnburied, were great crueltie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-coryn" xml:id="ep000801-e117210">
          <speaker>Coryn. </speaker>
          <l>Bones of God man, our Priest dwells too farre away. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e117230">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Well, then for want of a Priest, the Priests part I will play: </l>
          <l>Therefore father, helpe me to lay his body aright: </l>
          <l>For I will bestow a herse of him, because he was a Knight: </l>
          <l>If thou wilt go to a Cottage hereby, and fetch such things as I lacke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-coryn" xml:id="ep000801-e117280">
          <speaker>Coryn. </speaker>
          <l>That chill Gentleman, and by and by returne backe. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e117300">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e117310">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>But Clyomon pluck vp thy heart, with courage once againe, </l>
          <l>And I will set ouer his dead Coarse in signe of victorie, </l>
          <l>My Golden Sheeld and Sword, but with the poynt hanging downe, </l>
          <l>As one conquered and lost his renowne. </l>
          <l>Writing likewise thereupon, that all passengers may see, </l>
          <l>That the false King of Norway, here lieth slaine by me. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e117380">Enter Coryn with a Hearse. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-corin" xml:id="ep000801-e117390">
          <speaker>Co. </speaker>
          <l>Lo Gentleman, cha brought zuch things, as are requisit for the zame: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e117410">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Then good father helpe me, the Hearse for to frame. </l>
          <l>Chat chall Gentleman, in the best order that cha may: </l>
          <l>O that our Parish Preest were here, that you might heare him say, </l>
          <l>Vor by gos bones, an there be any noyse in the Church, in the midst of his prayers heele sweare. </l>
          <l>A he loues hunting a life, would to God you were acquainted with him a while, </l>
          <l>And as vor a woman, well Ihill zay nothing, but cha knowe whom hee did beguile. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e117480">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Well father Coryn let that passe, wee haue nothing to do withall, </l>
          <l>And now that this is done, come reward thy paine I shall. </l>
          <l>There is part of a recompence, thy good will to requite. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-023-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000801-coryn" xml:id="ep000801-e117520">
          <speaker>Coryn. </speaker>
          <l>By my troth cha thank you, cham bound to pray vor you day and night. </l>
          <l>And now Ihil euen home, &amp; send Iack my boy this sheep to seek out: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e117550">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Tell me father ere thou goest, didst thou not see a Lady wandring here about? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-corin" xml:id="ep000801-e117570">
          <speaker>Cor. </speaker>
          <l>A Lady, no good vaith gentleman, cha zaw none cha tel you plane: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e117590">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Wel then farewell father, gramercies for thy paine. </l>
          <l>Ah Neronis where thou art, or where thou doest abide, </l>
          <l>Thy Clyomon to seeke thee out shall rest no time nor tide: </l>
          <l>Thy foe here lieth slaine on ground, and liuing is thy frend, </l>
          <l>Whose trauel til he see thy face, shall neuer haue an end. </l>
          <l>My Ensigne here I leaue behind, these verses writ shall yeeld </l>
          <l>A true report of traytor slaine, by the knight of the golden sheeld. </l>
          <l>And as vnknowne to any wight, to trauell I betake, </l>
          <l>Vntil I may her find, whose sight my hart may ioyfull make. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e117690">Exit. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e117700">Enter Shift very braue. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e117710">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Iesu what a gazing do you make at me, to see me in a gowne? </l>
          <l>Do you not know after trauell, men being in Court or in Towne, </l>
          <l>And specially such as is of any reputation, they must vse this guise, </l>
          <l>Which signifieth a foole to be sage, graue, and of counsell wise. </l>
          <l>But where are we thinke you now, that Shift is so braue? </l>
          <l>Not running to seeke the knight of the golden sheeld, an other office I haue: </l>
          <l>For comming here to the court, of strange Marshes so named, </l>
          <l>Where King Alexander in his owne person lies, that Prince mightily famed </l>
          <l>Betweene Mustantius brother to the late king deceased </l>
          <l>And the Queene, through King Alexander, a strife was appeased: </l>
          <l>But how or which way I thinke you do not know, </l>
          <l>Well then giue eare to my tale, and the truth I wil show: </l>
          <l>The old King being dead, through sorrow for Neronis, </l>
          <l>Whom we do heare, Louer to the Knight of the Golden Sheeld is. </l>
          <l>The Queene being with child, the scepter asked to sway, </l>
          <l>But Mustantius the Kings brother, he did it denay. </l>
          <l>Whereof great contention grew, amongst the Nobles on either side, </l>
          <l>But being by them agreed the iudgement to abide </l>
          <l>Of King Alexander the great, who then was comming hither, </l>
          <l>At his arriuall to the Court, they all were cald togither. </l>
          <l>The matter being heard, this sentence was giuen, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-023-b"/>
          <l>That either partie should haue a Champion to combat them betweene: </l>
          <l>That which Champion were ouercome, the other should sway, </l>
          <l>And to be foughten after that time, the sixteene day. </l>
          <l>Now my maister Clamydes comming hither, for Mustantius wil he bee, </l>
          <l>But vpon the Queenes side, to venter none can we see: </l>
          <l>And yet she maketh proclamation through euery land: </l>
          <l>To giue great gift; to any that will take the combat in hand. </l>
          <l>Well within ten daies is the time, and king Alexander hee </l>
          <l>Staieth till the day appointed, the triall to see: </l>
          <l>And if none came at the day for the Queene to fight, </l>
          <l>Then without trauel to my maister, Mustantius hath his right. </l>
          <l>But to see all things in a readines, against thappointed day: </l>
          <l>Like a shifting knaue for aduantage, to Court Ile take my way. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e118060">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e118070">Enter Neronis like a Sheepheards boy. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e118080">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>The painfull pathes, the wearie wayes, the trauels and ill fare, </l>
          <l>That simple feete, to Princes seeme, in practise verie rare, </l>
          <l>As I poore Dame, whose pensiue heart, no pleasure can delight, </l>
          <l>Since that my state so cruelly, fell Fortune holds in spight. </l>
          <l>Ah poore Neronis in thy hand, is this a seemely showe, </l>
          <l>Who shouldst in Court thy Lute supplie, where pleasures erst did flowe? </l>
          <l>Is this an instrument for thee to guide a sheepheards flocke? </l>
          <l>That art a Princes by thy birth, and borne of noble stocke. </l>
          <l>May mind from mourning more refraine, to thinke on former state? </l>
          <l>May heart from sighing eke abstaine, to see this simple rate? </l>
          <l>May eyes from downe distilling teares, when thus a loue I am, </l>
          <l>Resistance make, but must they not, through ceaselesse sorrowes frame </l>
          <l>A Riuer of bedewed drops, for to distill my face? </l>
          <l>Ah heauens when you are reuengd inough, then looke vpon my cace: </l>
          <l>For till I heare some newes alas vpon my louing Knight, </l>
          <l>I dare not leaue this loathsome life, for feare of greater spight: </l>
          <l>And now as did my maister will, as sheepe that is a stray </l>
          <l>I must go seeke her out againe, by wild and wearie way. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-024-a"/>
          <l>Ah wofull sight; what is alas, with these mine eyes beheld, </l>
          <l>That to my louing Knight belongd, I view the Golden Sheeld: </l>
          <l>Ah heauens, this Herse doth signifie my, Knight is slaine, </l>
          <l>Ah death no longer do delay, but rid the liues of twaine: </l>
          <l>Heart, hand, and eueri sence prepare, vnto the Hearse, draw nie: </l>
          <l>And thereupon submit your selues, disdaine not for to die </l>
          <l>With him that was your mistresse ioy, her life and death like case, </l>
          <l>And well I know in seeking me, he did his end embrace. </l>
          <l>That cruell wretch that Norway King this cursed deed hath dunne, </l>
          <l>But now to cut that lingering threed, that Lachis long hath spunne, </l>
          <l>The sword of this my louing knight, behold I here do take, </l>
          <l>Of this my wofull corps alas, a finall end to make: </l>
          <l>Yet ere I strike that deadly stroke that shall my life depraue, </l>
          <l>Ye muses ayd me to the Gods, for mercie first to craue. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e118410">Sing heere. </stage>
          <l>Well now you heauens receiue my ghost, my corps I leaue behind, </l>
          <l>To be inclosd with his in earth, by those that shall it find. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e118440">Descend Prouidence. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-provi" xml:id="ep000801-e118450">
          <speaker>Proui. </speaker>
          <l>Stay, stay thy stroke, thou wofull Dame, what wilt thou thus dispaire? </l>
          <l>Behold to let this wilfull fact, I Prouidence prepaire </l>
          <l>To thee, from seate of mightie loue, looke hereupon againe, </l>
          <l>Reade, that if case thou canst it reade, and see if he be slaine </l>
          <l>Whom thou doest loue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e118510">
          <speaker>Nere. </speaker>
          <l>Ah heauens aboue. </l>
          <l>All land and praise and ho honour due to you I here do render, </l>
          <l>That would vouchsafe your handmaid here, in wofull state to tender: </l>
          <l>But by these same Verses do I find, my faithfull knight doth liue, </l>
          <l>Whose hand vnto my deadly foe, the mortall stroke did giue: </l>
          <l>Whose cursed carkasse loe it is, which here on ground doth lie, </l>
          <l>Ah honour due for this I yeeld, to mightie Ioue on hie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-provi" xml:id="ep000801-e118590">
          <speaker>Proui. </speaker>
          <l>Well, let desparation die in thee, I may not here remaine, </l>
          <l>But be assured, that thou shalt ere long thy knight attaine. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e118620">Ascend. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e118630">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>And for their prouidence diuine, the Gods aboue ile praise, </l>
          <l>And shew their works so wonderfull, vnto their laud alwaies. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-024-b"/>
          <l>Well, sith that the gods by prouidence hath signed vnto mee </l>
          <l>Such comfort sweete in my distresse, my Knight againe to see, </l>
          <l>Farewell all feeding Shepherds flocks, vnseemly for my state, </l>
          <l>To seeke my loue I will set forth, in hope of friendly fate. </l>
          <l>But first to Shepherds house I will, my pages tyre to take, </l>
          <l>And afterwards depart from thence, my iourney for to make. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e118720">Exit. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e118730">Enter Sir Clyomon. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e118740">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Long haue I sought but all in vaine, for neither far nor neare </l>
          <l>Of my Neronis wofull dame, by no meanes can I heare. </l>
          <l>Did euer fortune violate two louers in such sort? </l>
          <l>The griefes ah are intollerable, the which I do support </l>
          <l>For want of her, but hope somewhat reuiues my pensiue hart, </l>
          <l>And doth to me some sodaine cause of comfort now impart </l>
          <l>Through newes I heare, as I abroad in weary trauell went, </l>
          <l>How that the Queene her mother hath her proclamations sent </l>
          <l>Through euery land, to get a Knight to combat on her side, </l>
          <l>Against Mustantius, Duke and Lord, to haue a matter tride: </l>
          <l>And now the day is very nigh, as I do vnderstand, </l>
          <l>In hope to meete my Lady there I will into that land: </l>
          <l>And for her mother vndertake the combat for to trye, </l>
          <l>Yea though the other Hector were, I would him not denye </l>
          <l>What soeuer he be, but ere I go, a golden Sheeld ile haue, </l>
          <l>Although vnknowne, I will come in, as doth my Knighthood craue: </l>
          <l>But couered will I keepe my Sheeld, because ile not be knowne, </l>
          <l>If case my Lady be in place, till I haue prowesse showne. </l>
          <l>Well, to haue my Sheeld in readinesse, I will no time delay, </l>
          <l>And then to combat for the Queene, I straight will take my way. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e118950">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e118960">Enter Neronis like the Page. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e118970">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Ah weary paces that I walke, with steps vnsteady still, </l>
          <l>Of all the gripes of grislie griefes, Neronis hath her fill. </l>
          <l>And yet amids these miseries, which were my first mishaps, </l>
          <l>By brute I heare such newes alas, as more and more inwraps </l>
          <l>My wretched corps with thousand woes, more then I may support, </l>
          <l>So that I am to be compard vnto the scaled fort, </l>
          <l>Which doth so long as men and might, and sustenance preuaile, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-025-a"/>
          <l>Giue to the enemies repulse, that commeth to assailes </l>
          <l>But when assistance gins to faile, and strength of foes increase, </l>
          <l>They forced are through battering blowes, the same for to release. </l>
          <l>So likewise I so long as hope, my comfort did remaine, </l>
          <l>The griefly greefes that me assaild, I did repulse againe: </l>
          <l>But now that hope begins to faile, and greefes anew do rise, </l>
          <l>I must of force yeeld vp the Forte, I can no way deuise </l>
          <l>To keepe the same, the Forte I meane, it is the wearie corse, </l>
          <l>Which sorrowes daily do assaile, and siege without remorse: </l>
          <l>And now to make my griefes the more, report alas hath told, </l>
          <l>How that my fathers aged bones, is shrined vp in mold, </l>
          <l>Since Norway king did me betray, and that my mother shee, </l>
          <l>Through Duke Mustantius, vncle mine, in great distresse to bee: </l>
          <l>For swaying of the Septer there, what should I herein say? </l>
          <l>Now that I cannot find my knight, I would at combat day </l>
          <l>Be gladly there, if case I could with some good maister meete, </l>
          <l>That as his Page in these affaires, would seeme me to intreate: </l>
          <l>And in good time, here commeth one, he seemes a knight to be, </l>
          <l>Ile profer seruice, if in case, he will accept of me. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e119240">Enter Clyomon with his Sheeld couered, strangely disguised. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e119250">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Well, now as one vnknowne, I will go combat for the Queene: </l>
          <l>Who can bewray me, since my Sheeld is not for to be seene? </l>
          <l>But stay, who do I here espie? of truth a proper Boy, </l>
          <l>If case he do a maister lacke, he shall sustaine no noy: </l>
          <l>For why in these affaires, he may stand me in passing steed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e119310">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Well, I see to passe vpon my way, this Gentlemans decreed, </l>
          <l>To him I will submit my selfe, in seruice for to be, </l>
          <l>If case he can his fancie frame, to like so well on me. </l>
          <l>Well met sir knight vpon your way. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e119360">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>My Boy gramercies, but to me say, </l>
          <l>Into what countrey is thy iourney dight? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e119390">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Towards the strange Marshe, of truth Sir Knight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e119410">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>And thither am I going, high Ioue be my guide. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e119430">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Would Gods I were worthy to be your Page by your side. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e119450">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>My Page my boy, why what is thy name? that let me heare. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e119470">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Sir Knight, by name I am called Cur Daceer. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-025-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e119490">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Cur Daceer, what heart of Steele, now certis my boy: </l>
          <l>I am a Gentleman, and do entertaine thee with ioy: </l>
          <l>And to the strange Marshes am I going, the Queene to defend, </l>
          <l>Come therefore, for without more saying, with me thou shalt wend. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e119540">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e119550">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>As diligent to do my dutie as any in this land: </l>
          <l>Ah Fortune, how fauourablie my friend doth she stand: </l>
          <l>For thus no man knowing mine estate nor degree, </l>
          <l>May I passe safely, a Page as you see. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e119600">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e119610">Enter Bryan sance foy with the Head. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e119620">
          <speaker>Bry. </speaker>
          <l>Euen as the Owle that hides her head, in hollow tree till night, </l>
          <l>And dares not while sir Phoebus shines, attempt abroad in flight: </l>
          <l>So likewise I as Buzzard bold, while chearefull day is seene, </l>
          <l>Am forst with Owle to hide my selfe, amongst the Iuie greene: </l>
          <l>And dares not with the seelie Snaile, from cabbin show my head, </l>
          <l>Till Vesper I behold aloft, in skies begin to spread: </l>
          <l>And then as Owle that flies abroad when other fowles do rest, </l>
          <l>I creepe out of my drowsie denne, when summons hath supprest </l>
          <l>The head of euerie valiant heart, loe thus I shrowd the day, </l>
          <l>And trauell as the Owle by night vpon my wished way: </l>
          <l>The which hath made more tedious my iourney, by halfe part, </l>
          <l>But blame not Bryan, blame alas, his cowardly catiffes hart: </l>
          <l>Which dares not showe it selfe by day, for feare of worthy wights, </l>
          <l>For none can trauell openly, to escape the venturous Knights, </l>
          <l>Vnlesse he haue a noble mind, and eke a valiant hart, </l>
          <l>The which I will not brag vpon, I assure you for my part: </l>
          <l>For if the courage were in me, the which in other is, </l>
          <l>I doubtles had inioyed the wight whom I do loue ere this. </l>
          <l>Well, I haue not long to trauell now, to Denmarke I draw nie, </l>
          <l>Bearing knight Clamydes name, yet Bryan sance foy am I. </l>
          <l>But though I do vsurpe his name, his sheeld or ensigne here, </l>
          <l>Yet can I not vsurpe his heart, still Bryans heart I beare: </l>
          <l>Well, I force not that, he is safe inough, and Bryan as I am, </l>
          <l>I will vnto the Court, whereas I shall enioy that dame. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e119870">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-026-a"/>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e119880">Enter Shift like a Waffler. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e119890">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Rowme there for a reckning, see I beseech you if thale stand out of the way, </l>
          <l>Iesu, Iesu, why do you not know that this is the day </l>
          <l>That the combat must passe for Mustantius and the Queene? </l>
          <l>But to fight vpon her side as yet no Champion is seene. </l>
          <l>And Duke Mustantius he smiles in his sleeue, because he doth see </l>
          <l>That neither for loue nor rewards, any one her Champion will be. </l>
          <l>Ant were not but that my maister the other Champion is, </l>
          <l>To fight for the Queene my selfe, I surely would not mis. </l>
          <l>Alas good Lady, she and her child is like to lose all the land, </l>
          <l>Because none will come in, in her defence for to stand. </l>
          <l>For where she was in election, if any Champion had come </l>
          <l>To rule till she was deliuered, and haue the Princes roome: </l>
          <l>Now shall Duke Mustantius be sure the Scepter to sway, </l>
          <l>If that none do come in to fight in her cause this day. </l>
          <l>And King Alexander all this while hath he stayed the triall to see, </l>
          <l>Well here they come, roome there for the King, heres such thrusting of women as it grieueth mee. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e120060">Enter King Alexander, the Queene, Mustantius, two Lords, and Clamydes like a Champion. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-mustantius" xml:id="ep000801-e120070">
          <speaker>Mustan. </speaker>
          <l>O Alexander lo behold, before thy royall grace </l>
          <l>My Champion here at pointed day I do present in place. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-alexander" xml:id="ep000801-e120100">
          <speaker>Alexand. </speaker>
          <l>Well sir Duke in your defence is he content to be? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e120120">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Yea worthy Prince, not fearing who incounter shall with me: </l>
          <l>Although he were with Hercules of equall power and might, </l>
          <l>Yet in the cause of this same Duke, I challenge him the fight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-alexander" xml:id="ep000801-e120160">
          <speaker>Alexa. </speaker>
          <l>I like your courage well sir Knight: what shal we call your name? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e120180">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Clamydes, sonne to the Swauian King, O Prince so hight the same. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-alexander" xml:id="ep000801-e120200">
          <speaker>Alexa. </speaker>
          <l>Now certainely I am right glad Clamydes for to see, </l>
          <l>Such valiant courage to remaine within the mind of thee. </l>
          <l>Well Lady, according to the order tane herein, what do you say, </l>
          <l>Haue you your Champion in like case, now ready at the day? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-queen" xml:id="ep000801-e120250">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>No sure ô King no Champion I, haue for to ayde my cause, </l>
          <l>Vnlesse twill please your noble grace on further day to pause. </l>
          <l>For I haue sent throughout this Ile, and euery forraine land, </l>
          <l>But none as yet hath proffered, to take the same in hand. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-026-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000801-alexander" xml:id="ep000801-e120300">
          <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
          <l>No, I am more sorie certainly, your chance to see so ill, </l>
          <l>But day deferred cannot be, vnlesse Mustantius will, </l>
          <l>For that his Champion readie here, in place he doth present, </l>
          <l>And who so missed at this day, should loose by full consent </l>
          <l>Of either part, the tytle right, and sway of regall Mace, </l>
          <l>To this was your consentment giuen, as well as his in place, </l>
          <l>And therefore without his assent, we cannot referre the day? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e120380">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Ant shall please your grace, herein trie Mustantius what he will say. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-alexander" xml:id="ep000801-e120400">
          <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
          <l>How say you Mustantius, are you content the day to deferre? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-mustantius" xml:id="ep000801-e120420">
          <speaker>Mustan. </speaker>
          <l>Your Grace will not will me I trust, for then from law you erre: </l>
          <l>And hauing not her Champion here, according to decree, </l>
          <l>There resteth nought for her to loose, the Crowne belongs to mee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e120460">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Nay ant shall please your grace, rather then she shall it lose, </l>
          <l>I my selfe will be her Champion for halfe a doozen blowes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-mustantius" xml:id="ep000801-e120490">
          <speaker>Mustan. </speaker>
          <l>Wilt thou? then by full congo to the Challenger there stands. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e120510">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Nay soft, of sufferance commeth ease, though I cannot rule my tongue, ile rule my hands. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-mustantius" xml:id="ep000801-e120530">
          <speaker>Mustan. </speaker>
          <l>Well noble Alexander, sith that she wants her Champion as you see, </l>
          <l>By greement of your royall grace, the Crowne belongs to mee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-alexander" xml:id="ep000801-e120560">
          <speaker>Alex. </speaker>
          <l>Nay Mustantius, she shall haue law, wherefore to sound begin, </l>
          <l>To see if that in three houres space no Champion will come in. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e120590">Sound here once. </stage>
          <l>Of truth Madam I sorie am, none will thy cause maintaine, </l>
          <l>Well, according to the law of Armes, yet Trumpet sound againe. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e120620">Sound second time. </stage>
          <l>What, and is there none will take in hand, to Combat for the Queene? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e120640">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Faith I thinke it must be I must do the deed, for none yet is seene. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-queen" xml:id="ep000801-e120660">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>O King let pittie pleade for me, here in your gracious sight, </l>
          <l>And for so slender cause as this depriue me not of right: </l>
          <l>Consider once I had to spowse a Prince of worthy fame, </l>
          <l>Though now blind Fortune spurne at me, her spight I needs must blame, </l>
          <l>And though I am bereft O King, both of my child and mate, </l>
          <l>Your Grace some greement may procure, consider of my state, </l>
          <l>And suffer not a Widow Queene with wrong oppressed so, </l>
          <l>But pitie the young Infants case, wherewith O King I go: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-027-a"/>
          <l>And though I suffer wrong, let that find fauour in your sight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e120760">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Why Lady I respect you both, and sure would if I might </l>
          <l>Entreate Mustantius there unto, some such good order frame, </l>
          <l>Your strife should cease, and yet each one well pleased with the same. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-queen" xml:id="ep000801-e120800">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>I know your grace may him perswade, as reason wils no lesse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e120820">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Well, Sir Mustantius, then your mind to me in breefe expresse, </l>
          <l>Will you vnto such order stand here limited by me, </l>
          <l>Without deferring longer time, say on if you agree? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-mustantius" xml:id="ep000801-e120860">
          <speaker>Mustan. </speaker>
          <l>In hope your grace my state will way, I giue my glad consent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e120880">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>And for to end all discord say, Madame, are you content? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-queen" xml:id="ep000801-e120900">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>Yea noble King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e120920">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Well then before my nobles all, giue eare vnto the King, </l>
          <l>For swaying of the sword and Mace all discord to beate downe, </l>
          <l>The child when it is borne, we elect to weare the Crowne. </l>
          <l>And till that time Mustantius, you of lands and liuing heere, </l>
          <l>Like equall part in euerie point, with this the Queene shall share: </l>
          <l>But to the child when it is borne, if Gods grant it to liue, </l>
          <l>The kingdome whole in euery part, as tytle we do giue. </l>
          <l>But yet Mustantius, we will yeeld this recompence to you, </l>
          <l>You shall receiue fiue thousand Crownes for yearely pension due, </l>
          <l>To maintaine your estate, while you here liue and do remaine, </l>
          <l>And after let the whole belong vnto the Crowne againe. </l>
          <l>Now say your minds if you agree? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-page" xml:id="ep000801-e121050">
          <speaker>Page. </speaker>
          <l>I would the like choise were put to me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-mustantius" xml:id="ep000801-e121070">
          <speaker>Must. </speaker>
          <l>I for my part O Noble King therewith am well content: </l>
          <l>Well better halfe then nought at all, I likewise giue consent. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e121100">Enter Clyomon, as to Combat. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e121110">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Renowned King and most of fame, before thy royall grace, </l>
          <l>The Queene to aid, I do present my person here in place. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-mustantius" xml:id="ep000801-e121140">
          <speaker>Mustan. </speaker>
          <l>You come too late in faith Sir knight, the houre and time is past. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e121160">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Your houre I am not to respect, I entered with the blast. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-unassigned" xml:id="ep000801-e121180">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>What Princox is it you, are come to combat for the Queene? </l>
          <l>Good Fortune now, I hope ere long your courage shall be seene. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e121210">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>And sure I count my hap as good, to meete with you Sir knight, </l>
          <l>Come according to your promise made, prepare your selfe to fight. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-027-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e121240">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>I knew you well inough sir, although your sheeld were hid from mee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e121260">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Now you shall feele me as well as know me, if hand and hart agree. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e121280">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Stay, stay Sir knights, I charge you not in combat to proceed, </l>
          <l>For why the quarell ended is, and the parties are agreed: </l>
          <l>And therefore we discharge you both, the combat to refraine: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-page" xml:id="ep000801-e121320">
          <speaker>Page. </speaker>
          <l>The heauens therefore O noble King, thy happie sheeld remaine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e121340">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>O King although we be dischargd for this contention now, </l>
          <l>Betwixt vs twaine there resteth yet a combat made by vow: </l>
          <l>Which should be fought before your Grace: and since we here be met, </l>
          <l>To iudge twixt vs for victorie, let me your Grace entreat. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e121390">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>For what occasion is your strifes sir knights, first let me know? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e121410">
          <speaker>Clamid. </speaker>
          <l>The trueth thereof renowned king thy seruant he shall show: </l>
          <l>What time O king, as I should take of Suauia king my sier, </l>
          <l>The noble orders of a Knight, which long I did desier: </l>
          <l>This knight a straunger comes to court, and at that present day, </l>
          <l>In cowardly wise he comes by stealth, and takes from me away </l>
          <l>The honour that I should haue had, for which my father he, </l>
          <l>Did of his blessing giue in charge, O noble king to me, </l>
          <l>That I should know his name, that thus bereaued me of my right </l>
          <l>The which he will not shew, vnles he be subdued in fight: </l>
          <l>Whereto we either plighted faith, that I should know his name, </l>
          <l>If that before thy Grace O King, my force in fight could frame, </l>
          <l>To vanquish him, now hauing met thus happily togither, </l>
          <l>Though they are greed, our combat rest, decreed ere we came hither. </l>
          <l>Are you that knight that did subdue Sir Samuel in field, </l>
          <l>For which you had in recompence of vs, that Golden Sheeld? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e121570">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>I am that knight renowned Prince, whose name is yet vnknowne, </l>
          <l>And since I foyld Sir Samuel, some prowesse I haue showne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-queen" xml:id="ep000801-e121600">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>Then as I gesse, you are that Knight by that same sheeld you bear </l>
          <l>Which sometime was restored to health within our Pallace here? </l>
          <l>By Neronis our daughter she betrayed by Norway king. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e121640">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>I am that knight indeed O Queene, whom she to health did bring, </l>
          <l>Whose seruant euer I am bound wheresoeuer that she be, </l>
          <l>Whose enemie O Queene is slaine pursuing her, by me. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-028-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000801-queen" xml:id="ep000801-e121680">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>Know you not where she abides, Sir knight to vs declare? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e121700">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>No certis would to Gods I did, she should not liue in care, </l>
          <l>But escaped from the Norway king, I am assur'd she is. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-queen" xml:id="ep000801-e121730">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>Well her absence was her fathers death, which turnd to bale my (blis. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e121750">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>And till I find her out againe, my toile no end shall haue </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-queen" xml:id="ep000801-e121770">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>Alas he is nigh inough to her, small toile the space doth craue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e121790">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Well Sir knights, since that you haue declar'd before me here, </l>
          <l>The cause of this the grudge which you to each other beare: </l>
          <l>I wish you both a while to pawse, and to my words attend, </l>
          <l>If Reason rest with you, be sure Knights, this quarell I will end, </l>
          <l>Without the sheading any bloud betwixt you here in sight: </l>
          <l>Clamydes, wey you are nobly borne, and will you then sir Knight, </l>
          <l>Go hazard life so desperately: I charge you both refraine, </l>
          <l>Since for so smal a cause, the strife doth grow betwixt you twaine: </l>
          <l>And let him know your name sir knight, and so your malice end: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e121890">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>I haue vowed to the contrary, which vowe I must defend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e121910">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Well though so it be that you haue vowed, your name shall not be knowne: </l>
          <l>Yet not detracting this your vow, your countrey may be showne, </l>
          <l>And of what stocke by birth you bee: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e121950">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>But Lady he is dashed now I see. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e121970">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Indeed this hath astond me much, I cannot but confesse, </l>
          <l>My country and my birth, my state, which plainly wil expresse </l>
          <l>My name, for that vnto them all my state is not knowne, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e122010">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Sir knight, of our demand from you againe, what answere shall be showne, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e122030">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Of Denmarke noble Prince I am, and son vnto the king: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e122050">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Why then sir Cliomon hight your name, as rare report doth ring? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e122070">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>It doth indeed so hight my name, O Prince of high renowne, </l>
          <l>I am the Prince of Denmarkes sonne, and heire vnto the Crowne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e122100">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>And are you son to Denmarke king? then do imbrace your frend, </l>
          <l>Within whose heart here towards you, all malice makes an end: </l>
          <l>Who with your sister linked is, in loue with loyall hart: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e122140">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>And for her sake, and for thine owne, like friendship I impart. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e122160">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Well sir knights, since friendship rests, where rancor did remaine, </l>
          <l>And that you are such friends become, I certaine am right faine, </l>
          <l>In hope you wil continue stil, you shall to Court repaire, </l>
          <l>And remaine if that you please awhile, to rest you there </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-028-b"/>
          <l>Till time you haue decreed which way your iourney you will frame: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-both" xml:id="ep000801-e122220">
          <speaker>Both. </speaker>
          <l>We yeeld you thanks, beseeching Ioue still to augment your fame. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e122240">Exeunt. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e122250">
          <speaker>Clamydes. </speaker>
          <l>Well, come my Clyomon let vs passe, and as we iourne by way, </l>
          <l>My most misfortunes vnto thee I wholly will bewray </l>
          <l>What hapned in my last affaires, and for thy sisters sake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e122290">
          <speaker>Clyomon. </speaker>
          <l>Well then Coeur d'acer come and waite, your iourney you shall take, </l>
          <l>And seeing thou art prepared, and hast all things in readinesse, </l>
          <l>Hast thee before to Denmarke with speedinesse, </l>
          <l>And tell the King and the Queene that Clyomon their sonne </l>
          <l>In health and happie state to their court doth returne, </l>
          <l>But in no wise to Iuliana say any thing of mee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-unassigned" xml:id="ep000801-e122360">
          <speaker>Curdaser. </speaker>
          <l>I will not shew one word amisse contrary your decree. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e122380">
          <speaker>Clamydes. </speaker>
          <l>Well then my Clyomon, to take our leaue to court let vs repare: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e122400">
          <speaker>Clyomon. </speaker>
          <l>As your friend and companyon Clamydes euery where. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e122420">Exit. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e122430">
          <speaker>Neronis. </speaker>
          <l>Oh heauens! is this my louing knight whom I haue serud so long? </l>
          <l>Now haue I tride his faithfull hart, oh so my ioyes doth throng, </l>
          <l>To thinke how fortune fauoreth me, Nerones now be glad, </l>
          <l>And praise the gods, thy iourney now, such good successe hath had. </l>
          <l>To Denmarke will I hast with ioy my message to declare, </l>
          <l>And tell the King how that his sonne doth homeward now repaire. </l>
          <l>And more to make my ioyes abound, fortune could neuer frame </l>
          <l>A finer meane to serue my turne, then this, for by the same </l>
          <l>I may vnto the Queene declare my state in secret wise, </l>
          <l>As by the way I will recount how best I can deuise. </l>
          <l>Now pack Nerones like a page, hast hence lest thou be spide, </l>
          <l>And tell thy maisters message there, the gods my iourney guide. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e122560">Exit. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e122570">Enter King of Denmarke, the Queene, Iuliana, two Lords. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e122580">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Come Lady Queene, and daughter eke, my Iuliana deare, </l>
          <l>We muse that of your Knight as yet no newes againe you heare, </l>
          <l>Which did aduenture for your loue the Serpent to subdue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-juliana" xml:id="ep000801-e122620">
          <speaker>Iulia. </speaker>
          <l>O father, the sending of that worthy knight my woful hart doth rue, </l>
          <l>For that alas the furious force of his outragious might, </l>
          <l>As I haue heard subdued hath full many a worthy knight. </l>
          <l>And this last night O father past, my mind was troubled sore, </l>
          <l>Me thought in dreame I saw a Knight not knowne to me before, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-029-a"/>
          <l>Which did present to me the head of that same monster slaine, </l>
          <l>But my Clamydes still in voyce me thought I heard complaine, </l>
          <l>As one bereft of all his ioy, now what this dreame doth signifie, </l>
          <l>My simple skill will not suffice the truth thereof to specifie. </l>
          <l>But sore I feare to contraries, the exspect thereof will hap, </l>
          <l>Which will in huge calamities my wofull corps bewrap: </l>
          <l>For sending of so worthy a Prince, as was Clamydes he, </l>
          <l>To sup his dire destruction there, for wretched loue of me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-queen" xml:id="ep000801-e122760">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>Tush daughter these but fancies be, which run within your mind: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e122780">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Let them for to suppresse your ioyes, no place of harbour find. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-lord" xml:id="ep000801-e122800">
          <speaker>Lord. </speaker>
          <l>O Princes let no dollors dant, behold your Knight in place: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-juliana" xml:id="ep000801-e122820">
          <speaker>Iulia. </speaker>
          <l>Ah happie sight, do I behold my knight Clamydes face? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e122840">Enter Bryan Sance foy with the head on his sword. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e122850">
          <speaker>Bryan. </speaker>
          <l>Wel, I haue at last through trauell long, atchiued my iourneys end, </l>
          <l>Though Bryan, yet Clamydes name, I stoutly must defend. </l>
          <l>Ah happie sight, the King and Queene with daughter in like case </l>
          <l>I do behold, to them I will present my selfe in place: </l>
          <l>The mightie Gods renowmed King, thy princely state maintaine: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e122910">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Sir Clamydes, most welcome sure you are to court againe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e122930">
          <speaker>Bryan. </speaker>
          <l>O Princes lo my promise here performed thou maist see, </l>
          <l>The Serpents head by me subdude I do present to thee, </l>
          <l>Before thy fathers royall grace: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-juliana" xml:id="ep000801-e122970">
          <speaker>Iulia. </speaker>
          <l>My Clamydes do embrace. </l>
          <l>Thy Iuliana, whose hart thou hast till vitall race be runne: </l>
          <l>Sith for her sake so venturously this deed by thee was done. </l>
          <l>Ah welcome home my faithfull Knight: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e123020">
          <speaker>Bryan. </speaker>
          <l>Gramerces noble Lady bright. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e123040">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Well Iuliana in our court your louer cause to stay, </l>
          <l>For all our Nobles we will send, against your nuptiall day. </l>
          <l>Go cary him to take his rest: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-juliana" xml:id="ep000801-e123080">
          <speaker>Iulian. </speaker>
          <l>I shall obey your graces hest. </l>
          <l>Come my Clamydes go with me, in court your rest to take: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e123110">
          <speaker>Bryan. </speaker>
          <l>I thanke you Lady, now I see accompt of me you make. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e123130">Exeunt. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e123140">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Well my Queene, sith daughter ours hath chosen such a make, </l>
          <l>The terrour of whose valiant hart may cause our foes to quake, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-029-b"/>
          <l>Come let vs presently depart, and as we did decree, </l>
          <l>For all our nobles will we send, their nuptialls for to see. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-queen" xml:id="ep000801-e123190">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>As pleaseth thee, thy Lady Queene O king is well agreed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-lord" xml:id="ep000801-e123210">
          <speaker>Lo. </speaker>
          <l>May it please your graces to arest, for loe with posting speed </l>
          <l>A messenger doth enter place: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e123240">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Then will we stay to know the case. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e123260">Enter Neronis. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e123270">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>The mightie powers renowned Prince preserue your state for ay, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e123290">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Messenger thou art welcome, what hast thou to say? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e123310">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Sir Clyomon your noble sonne, knight of the golden Sheeld, </l>
          <l>Who for his valiant victories in Towne and eke in field </l>
          <l>Is famed through the world, to your court doth now returne, </l>
          <l>And hath sent me before to Court, your grace for to enforme. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e123360">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Ah messenger declare, is this of truth the which that thou hast told? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e123380">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>It is most true O Noble king, you may thereof be bold. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e123400">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Ah ioy of ioyes surpassing all, what ioy is this to me? </l>
          <l>My Clyomon in Court to haue, the nuptiall for to see, </l>
          <l>Of Iuliana sister his, oh so I ioy in mind. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-queen" xml:id="ep000801-e123440">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>My boy where is thy maister speake, what is he far behind: </l>
          <l>Declare with speed, for these my eyes do long his face to view: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e123470">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Oh Queene this day he will be here, tis truth I tell to you. </l>
          <l>But noble Queene let pardon here my bold attempt excuse, </l>
          <l>And for to heare a simple boy in secret not refuse. </l>
          <l>Who hath strange tidings from your sonne to tell vnto your grace. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e123520">Exit. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-lord" xml:id="ep000801-e123530">
          <speaker>Lord. </speaker>
          <l>Behold my Lord where as I gesse, some strangers enter place: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e123550">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>I hope my Clyomon be not far, Oh ioy, I see his face. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e123570">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Come Knowledge, come forward, why art thou alwaies slacke? </l>
          <l>Get you to Court, brush vp our apparell, vntrusse your packe: </l>
          <l>Go seeke out my Page, bid him come to me with all speed you can: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e123610">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Go seek out, fetch, bring here, gogs ounds, what am I, a dog or a man▪ </l>
          <l>I were better be a hangman, and liue so like a drudge: </l>
          <l>Since your new man came to you, I must packe, I must trudge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e123650">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>How stands thou knaue? why gets thou not away? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-shift" xml:id="ep000801-e123670">
          <speaker>Shift. </speaker>
          <l>Now, now sir, you are so hastie now, I know not what to say. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e123690">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>O noble Prince, the Gods aboue preserue thy royall grace: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e123710">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>How ioyfull is my heart deare sonne, to view againe thy face? </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-030-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e123730">
          <speaker>Clyomon. </speaker>
          <l>And I as ioyfull in the view of parents happie plight, </l>
          <l>Whome sacred gods long time maintaine in honor day and night. </l>
          <l>But this my friend O father deere, euen as my selfe intreate, </l>
          <l>Whose noblenes when time shall serue to you he shall repeate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e123780">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>If case my sonne he be thy friend, with hart I thee imbrace: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e123800">
          <speaker>Clyomon. </speaker>
          <l>With loyall hart in humble wise, I thanke your noble grace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e123820">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>My Clyomon declare my sonne in thine aduentures late, </l>
          <l>What hath bin wrought by fortune most to aduance thy noble state? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e123850">
          <speaker>Clyomon. </speaker>
          <l>O father, the greatest ioy of all the ioyes which was to one assignd </l>
          <l>Since first I left your noble court by cruell fortune blind, </l>
          <l>Is now bereft from me away, through her accursed fate, </l>
          <l>So that I rather finde she doth enuy my noble state, </l>
          <l>Then seeke for to aduance the same, so that I boldly may </l>
          <l>Expresse she neuer gaue so much, but more she tooke away. </l>
          <l>And that which I haue lost by her, and her accursed ire, </l>
          <l>From trauell will I neuer cease, vntill I may aspire </l>
          <l>Vnto the view thereof oh King, wherein is all my ioy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e123950">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Why how hath fortune wrought to thee this care and great anoy? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e123970">
          <speaker>Clyomon. </speaker>
          <l>O father vnto me the heauenly powers assignd a noble dame, </l>
          <l>With whome to liue in happy life, my hart did wholie frame. </l>
          <l>But not long did that glasing starre, giue light vnto mine eyes, </l>
          <l>But this fell fortune gins to frowne, which euery state despise, </l>
          <l>And takes away through cancred haue that happy light from me, </l>
          <l>In which I fixed had my hope, a blessed state to see: </l>
          <l>And daughter to the King she was, which of strange Marshes hight, </l>
          <l>Bearing brute each where, to be dame Bewties darling bright: </l>
          <l>Right heire vnto dame Vertues grace, dame Natures patterne true, </l>
          <l>Dame Prudence scholler for her wit, dame Venus for her hue. </l>
          <l>Diana for her daintie life, Susanna being sad, </l>
          <l>Sage Saba for her sobernesse, mild Marpha being glad. </l>
          <l>And if I should reentre make, amongst the Muses nine, </l>
          <l>My Lady lackt no kind of art, which man may well define </l>
          <l>Amongst those daintie dames to be, then let all iudge that heare, </l>
          <l>If that my cause it be not iust, for which this pensiue cheare </l>
          <l>Fell fortune forceth me to make. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e124150">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Yet Clyomon good counsell take. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-030-b"/>
          <l>Let not the losse of the Lady thine so pinch thy hart with griefe, </l>
          <l>That nothing may vnto thy mind giue comfort or reliefe: </l>
          <l>What man there Ladies are enow, although that she be gone, </l>
          <l>Then leaue to waile the want of her, cease off to make this mone. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e124210">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>No father, neuer seeme for to perswade, for as is said before, </l>
          <l>What trauell I haue had for her, it shall be tryple more, </l>
          <l>Vntill I meete with her againe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e124250">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Well Clyomon, a while refraine, </l>
          <l>And let me here my woes recount before your fathers grace, </l>
          <l>But let me craue, your sister may be sent for into place. </l>
          <l>O King vouchsafe I may demaund a simple bound, </l>
          <l>Although a straunger, yet I hope such fauour may be found, </l>
          <l>The thing is this, that you will send for Iuliana hither, </l>
          <l>Your daughter faire, that we may talke a word or twaine togither. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e124330">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>For what, let me know sir knight, do you her fight desire? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e124350">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>The cause pretends no harme my Liege, why he doth this require. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e124370">
          <speaker>Ki. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord go bid our daughter come and speake with me straight way. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-lord" xml:id="ep000801-e124390">
          <speaker>Lo. </speaker>
          <l>I shall my Liege in euerie point, your mind herein obey. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000801-e124410">Exit. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e124420">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Oh father this is Clamydes, and sonne to Swauia King. </l>
          <l>Who for my sister ventured life, the serpents head to bring: </l>
          <l>With whom I met in trauell mine, but more whad did befall, </l>
          <l>To worke his woe when as she comes, your grace shall know it all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e124470">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>My sonne you are deceiued much, I you assure in this, </l>
          <l>The person whom you tearme him for, in court alreadie is. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e124500">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>No father I am not deceiued, this is Clamydes sure. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e124520">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Well my sonne do cease a while such talke to put in vre: </l>
          <l>For loe thy sister entereth place, which soone the doubt shall end. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e124550">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Then for to shew my name to her, I surely do pretend, </l>
          <l>My Iuliana noble Dame, Clamydes do embrace, </l>
          <l>Who many a bitter brunt hath bode, since that he saw thy face. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e124590">Enter Iuliana. </stage>
          <l>Auant dissembling wretch, what credit canst thou yeeld? </l>
          <l>Wher's the serpents head thou brought, where is my glittering Sheeld? </l>
          <l>Tush, tush sir knight, you counterfet, you would Clamydes be, </l>
          <l>But want of these bewraies you quite, and shewes you are not he, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e124640">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>O Princes do not me disdaine, I certaine am your knight: </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-031-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000801-juliana" xml:id="ep000801-e124660">
          <speaker>Iulia. </speaker>
          <l>What art thou franticke foolish man? auaunt from out my sight. </l>
          <l>If thou art he, then shew my sheeld, and bring the Serpents head: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e124690">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>O Princesse heare me shew my case, by Fortune fell decreed. </l>
          <l>I am your Knight and when I had subdued the monster fell, </l>
          <l>Through wearie fight and trauell great as Knowledge here can tell: </l>
          <l>I laid me downe to rest a space within the Forrest, where </l>
          <l>One Bryan than Sance foy hight, who with cowardly vsage there, </l>
          <l>By chaunting charme, brought me a sleepe, then did he take from me </l>
          <l>The Serpents head, my coate and sheeld, the which you gaue to me: </l>
          <l>And left me in his prison loe still sleeping as I was. </l>
          <l>Loe Lady thus I lost those things the which to me you gaue, </l>
          <l>But certainly I am your Knight, and he who did depraue </l>
          <l>The flying Serpent of his life according as you willed, </l>
          <l>That who so wonne your loue by him, the same should be fulfilled. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-juliana" xml:id="ep000801-e124820">
          <speaker>Iuli. </speaker>
          <l>Alas poore knight, how simplie haue you framed this excuse? </l>
          <l>The name of such a noble knight to vsurpe and eke abuse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e124850">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>No sister you are deceiued, this is Clamydes sure: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-juliana" xml:id="ep000801-e124870">
          <speaker>Iulia. </speaker>
          <l>No brother, then you are deceiued, such tales to put in vre: </l>
          <l>For my Clamydes is in Court, who did present to me, </l>
          <l>In white attire the Serpents head and Sheeld, as yet to see. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e124910">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>That shall I quickly vnderstand, O king permit I may </l>
          <l>Haue conference a while with him, whom as your grace doth say, </l>
          <l>Presents Clamydes, for to be before your royall grace: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-juliana" xml:id="ep000801-e124950">
          <speaker>Iuli. </speaker>
          <l>Behold no whit agast to shew himselfe, where he doth enter place. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e124970">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>Ah traytor, art thou he that doth my name and state abuse? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-juliana" xml:id="ep000801-e124990">
          <speaker>Iuli. </speaker>
          <l>Sir knight you are too bold in presence here, such talke against him for to vse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e125010">
          <speaker>Bry. </speaker>
          <l>Wherefore doest thou vpbraid me thus, thou varlet do declare? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e125030">
          <speaker>Clio. </speaker>
          <l>No varlet he, to call him so, sit knight you are too blame: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e125050">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Wouldst thou perstand for what intent such talk I here do frame? </l>
          <l>Because I know thou doest vsurpe my state and noble name. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e125080">
          <speaker>Bry. </speaker>
          <l>Who art thou, or whats thy name? can swere quickly make: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e125100">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>I am Clamydes, whose name to beare, thou here doest vndertake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e125120">
          <speaker>Bry. </speaker>
          <l>Art thou Clamydes? vaunt thou false vsurper of my state, </l>
          <l>Auoyd this place, or death shall be thy most accursed fate. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-031-b"/>
          <l>How darest thou enterprise to take my name thus vnto thee? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e125160">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Nay rather, how darest thou attempt to vsurpe the name of me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-juliana" xml:id="ep000801-e125180">
          <speaker>Iulia. </speaker>
          <l>You lie Sir Knight, he doth not so, gainst him you haue it done. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e125200">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Sister you are deceiued, my frind here is Clamydes Prince, the King of Suauias sonne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-juliana" xml:id="ep000801-e125220">
          <speaker>Iulia. </speaker>
          <l>Nay Brother, neither you nor he can me deceiue herein. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e125240">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>O King bowe downe thy princely eares, and listen what I say, </l>
          <l>To proue my selfe the wight I am before your royall grace, </l>
          <l>And to disproue this faithlesse Knight which here I find in place, </l>
          <l>For to vsurpe my name so much, the combat will I trie: </l>
          <l>For before I will mine honour loose, I rather chuse to die. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e125300">
          <speaker>Ki. </speaker>
          <l>I like well your determined mind, but how say you sir knight? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e125320">
          <speaker>Bryan. </speaker>
          <l>Nay by his ounds ile gage my gowne he dares not fight: </l>
          <l>By gogs bloud I shall be slaine now, if the Combat I denie, </l>
          <l>And not for the eares of my head with him I dare trie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e125360">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Sir knight why do you not reanswere make in triall of your name? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e125380">
          <speaker>Bry. </speaker>
          <l>I will O King, if case he dare in combat trie the same. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e125400">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Well then go to prepare yourselues, each one his weapons take: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-juliana" xml:id="ep000801-e125420">
          <speaker>Iulia. </speaker>
          <l>Good father let it not be so, restraine them for my sake. </l>
          <l>I may not here behold my Knight in daunger for to be, </l>
          <l>With such a one who doth vsurpe his name to purchase me: </l>
          <l>I speake not this for that I feare his force or strength in fight, </l>
          <l>But that I will not haue him deale with such a desperate wight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e125480">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Nay sure, there is no better way then that which is decreed, </l>
          <l>And therefore for to end their strife the combat shall proceed: </l>
          <l>Sir knights prepare your selues, the truth thereof to trie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e125520">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>I readie am, no cowardly heart shall cause me to denie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e125540">
          <speaker>Bry. </speaker>
          <l>Nay ile neuer stand the triall of it, my heart to fight doth faint: </l>
          <l>Therefore ile take me to my legs, seeing my honour I must attaint. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e125570">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Why whither runs Clamydes? Sir knight seeme to stay him: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e125590">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Nay it is Clamydes O King that doth fray him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e125610">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Nay come sir come, for the combat we will trie: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e125630">
          <speaker>Bry. </speaker>
          <l>Ah no my heart is done, to be Clamydes I denie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e125650">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Why how now Clamydes, how chance you do the combat here thus shunne? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e125670">
          <speaker>Bry. </speaker>
          <l>Oh King grant pardon vnto me, the thing I haue begunne </l>
          <l>I must denie, for I am not Clamides, this is plaine: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-032-a"/>
          <l>Though greatly to my shame, I must my words reuoke againe: </l>
          <l>I am no other then the knight, whome they Sance Foy call, </l>
          <l>This is Clamydes, the feare of whom, my danted mind doth pall. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-juliana" xml:id="ep000801-e125730">
          <speaker>Iulian. </speaker>
          <l>Is this Clamydes? ah worthy Knight, then do forgiue thy deere, </l>
          <l>And welcome eke ten thousand times vnto thy Lady heere. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e125760">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>Ah my Iuliana bright, whats past I do forgiue, </l>
          <l>For well I see thou constant art, and whilst that I do liue, </l>
          <l>For this, my firmed faith in thee for euer ile repose. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-juliana" xml:id="ep000801-e125800">
          <speaker>Iulian. </speaker>
          <l>O father now I do deny that wretch, and do amongst my foes </l>
          <l>Recount him for this treason wrought. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e125830">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Well Knowledge, take him vnto thee, and for the small regard </l>
          <l>The which he had to valiant Knights, this shalbe his reward, </l>
          <l>Sith he by charmes, his crueltie in cowardly manner wrought, </l>
          <l>On Knights, who as Clamydes did, the crowne of honour fought, </l>
          <l>And trayterously did them betray, in prison for to keepe, </l>
          <l>The fruits of such like crueltie, himselfe by vs shall reape: </l>
          <l>By due desert therefore I charge to prison him conuay, </l>
          <l>There for to lye perpetually vnto his dying day. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-bryan" xml:id="ep000801-e125920">
          <speaker>Bryan. </speaker>
          <l>Oh King be mercifull, and shew some fauour in this case: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e125940">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Nay, neuer thinke that at my hands thou shalt finde any grace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e125960">
          <speaker>Clamydes, </speaker>
          <l>ah most welcome thou, our daughter to enioy, </l>
          <l>The heauens be praisd that this hath wrought, to foile all future noy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e125990">
          <speaker>Clamydes. </speaker>
          <l>I thanke your Grace, that you thus so well esteeme of me. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e126010">Enter Knowledge. </stage>
          <l>What is all things finished, and euery man eased? </l>
          <l>Is the pageant packed vp, and all parties pleased? </l>
          <l>Hath each Lord his Lady, and each Lady her loue? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e126050">
          <speaker>Clyomon. </speaker>
          <l>Why Knowledge, what meanst thou those motions to moue? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-knowledge" xml:id="ep000801-e126070">
          <speaker>Knowledge. </speaker>
          <l>You were best stay a while, and then you shall know, </l>
          <l>For the Queene her selfe comes, the motion to show. </l>
          <l>You sent me if you remember, to seeke out your page, </l>
          <l>But I cannot find him, I went whisling &amp; calling through the court in such a rage: </l>
          <l>At the last very scacely in at a chamber I did pry, </l>
          <l>Where the Queene with other Ladyes very busy I did spy: </l>
          <l>Decking vp a strange Lady very gallant and gay, </l>
          <l>To bring her here in presence, as in court I heard say. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e126160">
          <speaker>Clyomon. </speaker>
          <l>A strange Lady Knowledge of whence is she canst thou tell me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-knowledge" xml:id="ep000801-e126180">
          <speaker>Knowledge. </speaker>
          <l>Not I ant shall please you, but anon you shall see. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000801-032-b"/>
          <l>For lo where the Lady with your mother doth come: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e126210">
          <speaker>Clyomon. </speaker>
          <l>Then straightway my duty to her grace shalbe done. </l>
          <l>The mighty Gods preserue your state, O Queene, and mother deare, </l>
          <l>Hoping your blessing I haue had, though absent many a yeare. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000801-e126250">Enter Queene. </stage>
          <l>My Clyomon, thy sight my son doth make thy aged mother glad, </l>
          <l>Whose absence long and many a yeare, hath made thy pensiue parents sad. </l>
          <l>And more to let thee know my sonne, that I do loue and tender thee, </l>
          <l>I haue here for thy welcome home, a present which ile giue to thee. </l>
          <l>This Lady though she be vnknowne, refuse her not, for sure her state </l>
          <l>Deserues a Princes sonne to wed, and therefore take her for thy more. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e126320">
          <speaker>Clyomon. </speaker>
          <l>O noble Queene and mother deere, I thanke you for your great good will, </l>
          <l>But I am otherwise bestowd, and sure I must my oath fulfill. </l>
          <l>And so I mind if gods to fore on such decree I meane to pause, </l>
          <l>For sure I must of force deny, my noble father knowes the cause. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e126370">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Indeed my Queene this much he told, he lou'd a Lady since he went, </l>
          <l>Who hath his hart and euer shall, and none but her to loue he'is bent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e126400">
          <speaker>Clyomon. </speaker>
          <l>So did I say, and so I wil, no beawties blaze, no glistering wight, </l>
          <l>Can cause me to forget her loue, to whom my faith I first did plight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e126430">
          <speaker>Nerones. </speaker>
          <l>Why are you so straight lac't sir Knight, to cast a Lady off so coy? </l>
          <l>Turne once againe and looke on me, perhaps my sight may bring you ioy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e126460">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Bring ioy to me? alas which way? no Ladies looks can make me glad: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e126480">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Then were my recompence but small, to quit my paine for you I had. </l>
          <l>Wherefore sir knight do wey my words, set not so light the loue I show, </l>
          <l>But when you haue bethought your selfe, you wil recant and turne I know. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-queen" xml:id="ep000801-e126520">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>My Clyomon refuse her not, she is and must thy Lady be: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e126540">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>If otherwise my mind be bent, I trust your grace will pardon me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e126560">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Wel then I see tis time to speake, sir knight let me one question craue, </l>
          <l>Say on your mind. Where is that Lady now become, to whom your plighted faith you gaue? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e126590">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Nay if I could absolue that doubt, then were my mind at ease: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e126610">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Were you not brought to health by her, when you came sick once of the seas? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e126630">
          <speaker>Cly. </speaker>
          <l>Yea sure I must confesse a truth, she did restore my health to me, </l>
          <l>For which good deed I rest her owne, in hope one day her face to see. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e126660">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>But did you not promise her to returne, to see her at a certaine day, </l>
          <l>And ere you came that to performe, the Norway King stole her away? </l>
          <l>And so your Lady there you lost: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e126700">
          <speaker>Clyomon. </speaker>
          <l>All this I graunt, but to his cost. </l>
          <l>For stealing her against her will, this hand of mine bereft his life. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-033-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e126730">
          <speaker>Ne. </speaker>
          <l>Now sure sir knight you serud him wel, to reach him know an other mās wife: </l>
          <l>But yet once more sir Knight replie, the truth I craue to vnderstand, </l>
          <l>In Forrest once, who gaue you drink, whereas you stood with sword in hand, </l>
          <l>Fearing least some had you pursude for slaying of your enemie? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e126780">
          <speaker>Cly. </speaker>
          <l>That did a sillie shepheards boy, which there I tooke my Page to be. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e126800">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>And what is of that Page become, remains he with you, yea or no? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e126820">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>I sent him hither ere I came, because the King and Queene should know, </l>
          <l>That I in health returned was, but since, I neuer saw him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e126850">
          <speaker>Ne. </speaker>
          <l>And sure he stands not far from hence, though now you do not know him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e126870">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Not far from hence, where might he be? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e126890">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>Of troth Sir Knight, my selfe am he: </l>
          <l>I bought your message the King, as here the Queene can testifie: </l>
          <l>I gaue you drinke in Forrest sure, when you with drought were like to die. </l>
          <l>I found you once vpon the shore full sicke, when as you came from seas, </l>
          <l>I bought you home to fathers Court, I sought al means your mind to pleas, </l>
          <l>And I it was that all this while haue waighted like a Page on thee: </l>
          <l>Still hoping for to <seg type="tba">spie a time wherein I</seg>might discouer mee. </l>
          <l>And so by hap at last I did, I thanke your mothers noble grace: </l>
          <l>She entertained me courteously, when I had told her all my case. </l>
          <l>And now let this suffice my deare, I am Neronis whom you see, </l>
          <l>Who <seg type="tba">many a wearie step hath</seg>gone, before and since I met with thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e127010">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>
            <seg type="tba">O sudden ioyes, O heauenly</seg>sight, O words more worth then gold, </l>
          <l>Neronis, O my <seg type="tba">deare welcome, my</seg>armes I here vnfold, </l>
          <l>To clasp thy comely corps withall, twice welcome to thy knight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e127050">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>And I enioyfull am no doubt, my Clyomon of thy happie sight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clyomon" xml:id="ep000801-e127070">
          <speaker>Clyo. </speaker>
          <l>Clamydes my assured friend, lo how Dame Fortune fauoureth mee, </l>
          <l>This is Neronis my deare loue, whose face so long I wisht to see. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-clamydes" xml:id="ep000801-e127100">
          <speaker>Clamy. </speaker>
          <l>My Clyomon, I am as glad as you your selfe to see this day: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e127120">
          <speaker>Ki. </speaker>
          <l>Well daughter though a stranger yet, welcome to Court as I may say. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-queen" xml:id="ep000801-e127140">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>And Lady as welcome vnto me, as if thou wert mine onely child. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-neronis" xml:id="ep000801-e127160">
          <speaker>Nero. </speaker>
          <l>For this your gracious curtesie, I thanke you noble Princes mild. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-unassigned" xml:id="ep000801-e127180">
          <speaker>Iu. </speaker>
          <l>Though strange and vnacquainted yet, do make account you welcome are, </l>
          <l>Your nuptiall day as well as mine, I know my father will prepare. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-king" xml:id="ep000801-e127210">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Yes we are prest your nuptiall day with daughter ours to see, </l>
          <l>As well as Clyomons our sonne, with this his Lady faire: </l>
          <l>Come therefore to our Court, that we the same may soone prepare. </l>
          <l>For we are prest throughout our land, for all our Peeres to send: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000801-omnes" xml:id="ep000801-e127260">
          <speaker>Omnes. </speaker>
          <l>Thy pleasure most renowned King, thy seruants shall attend. </l>
        </sp>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
        <pb xml:id="ep000801-033-b"/>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back></back>
  </text>
</TEI>
