<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000683" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Alphonso, King of Naples a tragedy, as it is acted at the Theatre Royal by Their Majesties servants / written by George Powell.</title>
        <author>
<!--Powell, George-->
          <persName>
            <forename>George</forename>
            <surname>Powell</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A55539.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <p>
            This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is available for reuse, according to the terms of
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>
            . The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
          </p>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull>
              <titleStmt>
                <title>Alphonso, King of Naples a tragedy, as it is acted at the Theatre Royal by Their Majesties servants / written by George Powell.</title>
                <author>Powell, George, 1658?-1714.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[9], 47, [2] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Printed for Abel Roper, and Thomas Bever,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                <date>1691.</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000683-e10">
        <pb xml:id="ep000683-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000683-001-b"/>
        <p>Alphonso KING OF NAPLES, A TRAGEDY. As it is Acted at the Theatre Royal, By Their Majesties Servants. </p>
        <p>Written by <hi>GEORGE POWELL</hi>. </p>
        <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Abel Roper</hi>, at the Mitre; and <hi>Thomas Bever</hi>, at the Hand and Star near Temple-Bar, 1691. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000683-e130">
        <pb xml:id="ep000683-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000683-002-b"/>
        <head>To Her GRACE THE DUTCHESS OF ORMOND, &amp;c. </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>MADAM, </salute>
        </opener>
        <p>WHere the Porticoes of Palaces stand like those of Temples, and the Great and the Fair leave their Accesses unbarr'd, Exalted Honour in that condescending Goodness, is so far from lessening its Grandeur, that it rather heightens its State; when True Magnificence must certainly consist in the Numbers of wondring Eyes around it, and Crowds of bending Knees before it. This Argument, which I hope I have not mistaken, is my best Warrant for this Confidence. </p>
        <p>I confess, indeed, in my Approach to Your Grace, I ought to consider how I find your Court fill'd with Quality, whilst that Nobler Train throngs up Your Presence, that my poor Intrusion is a little too presumptuous. This truly I ought to consider, did I not at the same time reflect, that on the very Scaffolds at <pb xml:id="ep000683-003-a"/>Coronations, there are some remoter Benches, (or to speak in my own Province) some Upper Gallery Seats, even for poorer Homagers; the Voice of Adoration, and Echoes of Triumph being not only loudest but sweetest, where all Tongues unite in the Choire; whilst the lowest Humility may make up as hearty, though not so gay, a part of the Ceremony. </p>
        <p>From that Distant Bench, I beseech Your Grace to believe, that this Addressing Paper is handed down over the Heads of Honour to Your Grace's Feet. 'Tis true, I have dared to dedicate this Trifle to Your Grace, and in it publish that piece of Boldness to the World, which how far they may forgive me, I am not so much concerned, provided Your own Descending Mercy vouchsafe my Pardon. </p>
        <p>And thus enter'd under Your Grace's glittering Roof, my dazled Veneration presents me so large and so hallow'd a prospect, the concentring Worth of Two Illustrious Families, that in a long long Line from their Renown'd Originals, number their fair devolving Honours by Centuries. The Great Ormond, and Your bright Self, a fair last Branch of the Royal Plantagenets, so Noble an Union, in that successive Roll of Fame, bring up the splendid Reer to so distant a Front, Your Remoter Leading Ancestors, as requires a Travel into Annals for a full Survey; so ample Your Hereditary Glories, that 'tis a Voyage but to coast 'em. </p>
        <p>But whither am I rapt! I am wandring into so spacious a Field, a speculation so far above me, that the Theme is too sacred for the trembling Pen of so poor a Mushroom Scribler to venture at, Your Graces Herald, and Your Panegyrist, being both an Attempt beyond my humble Talent. Besides, there's Object <pb xml:id="ep000683-003-b"/>enough for my Adoration in a nearer View of Your Grace's radiant Vertues; an Influence so powerful, Greatness so prideless, Wit so elevated, Piety so exemplary; and to crown all these, Your Nuptial Glory, a Conjugal Affection, so inimitable, that a ministring Cornelia might be proud to hold up Your Train; And all these lodged in so Beautiful a Personage, so sacred the Divinity, and so bright the Shrine. The prospect, I say, of these sublime Perfections intirely takes up my humble Devotion; without looking back into Urns and Monuments, Records and Chronicles, for their Glorious Derivation. But my Contemplation of those Adorable Vertues is not alone sufficient; give me leave to Congratulate their Felicities too, the attending smiles of Providence, Vertues divine Rewarder; when, as an earnest-blessing, the Great Ormond, under the Victorious Royal Standard, has made his first Entry into a Grove of Lawrels, by hewing out the possession of his recover'd Patrimony, by a Sword and an Arm, worthy the Inheriting Son of so Heroick a Father. The Continuance of whose Fortunate Successes, the rich, fair Harvest of a Field of Honour abroad, and Your Grace's no less Trophies, the Pride and Ornament of a Court at home, (a fair divided Triumph between You) shall ever be the Prayers of, </p>
        <closer>
          <salute>Madam, </salute>
          <signed>Your Grace's Most Obedient and most devoted Servant, George Powell. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="prologue" xml:id="ep000683-e300">
        <pb xml:id="ep000683-004-a"/>
        <head>THE PROLOGUE. </head>
        <byline>Spoken by M r Powell; As it was Written by Mr. <hi>Iohn Haynes</hi>. </byline>
        <l>PRepar'd to dam ' my Play, methinks you sit </l>
        <l>As if you'd all took Physick in the Pit. </l>
        <l>'Tis hard you won't allow in any Case </l>
        <l>To a Young Player either Wit or Grace. </l>
        <l>You use us like lewd Women of the Town, </l>
        <l>(With Punk and Poet you deal much at one) </l>
        <l>First You enjoy us, then you kick us down. </l>
        <l>" But there's a mighty diff'rence in our Cases; </l>
        <l>" You dam ' new Plays, but cry up all new Faces. </l>
        <l>" And us, poor Devils, you cheaply do mis▪ use; </l>
        <l>" A clipp'd Half-Crown you think pays our abuse. </l>
        <l>" But with your Miss 'tis quite another thing, </l>
        <l>" The Bag of Honey's sweet; but 'ware the Sting. </l>
        <l>" In Wit too, nought but currant Gold will pass, </l>
        <l>" In Love, a Heart of steel, a Face of brass▪ </l>
        <l>Yet have I known, for love of such a Iilt, </l>
        <l>A doughty Hero physick first, then Tilt. </l>
        <l>Since then— </l>
        <l>I hope to find no Favour in your Eyes, </l>
        <l>Who all new Plays before they're heard despise. </l>
        <l>From you to the Fair Sex I now appeal, </l>
        <l>To whom you dare not but be proud to kneel. </l>
        <pb xml:id="ep000683-004-b"/>
        <l>Bright Ladies then, whose Rays throughout the Pit, </l>
        <l>Do influence all around with Love and Wit, </l>
        <l>" Oh tune their Iudgments e'er my Fate be known, </l>
        <l>" 'Tis in your Power to make my Case their own: </l>
        <l>For with their FOIBLES did not you dispence, </l>
        <l>Which of 'em to your Smiles cou'd plead pretence, </l>
        <l>For Dress and Fortune make your Man of Sence. </l>
        <l>Since then 'tis Fancy gives gay Nonsence Charms, </l>
        <l>Which the Fair Sex of Iudgment oft disarms; </l>
        <l>Let Fancy too, that rules the Wise, the Brave, </l>
        <l>That makes a Captive free, a Prince a slave, </l>
        <l>The Lawyer honest, th' Honest Man a Knave; </l>
        <l>That gives Content to Cuckolds, Wealth to th' Poor, </l>
        <l>To Courtiers Friendship, true Love to a Whore; </l>
        <l>That makes your Vizard Mask appear a Queen, </l>
        <l>Who hides her Face on purpose to be seen, </l>
        <l>And Apes of Quality, fond Misses think </l>
        <l>The Spark's in Love that prais'd 'em in his drink; </l>
        <l>Fancying their Beauty 'tis that so prevails, </l>
        <l>When we all know the Charm lies in their T—ls. </l>
        <l>Let Fancy then, that leads the World astray, </l>
        <l>Triumph o'er Wit to night, and save my Play, </l>
        <l>And then I'll laugh at Wits on my <hi>Third Day </hi>
        </l>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="ep000683-e870">
        <pb xml:id="ep000683-005-a"/>
        <head>Dramatis Personae. </head>
        <list>
          <label>ALphonso, <hi>King of </hi>Naples. </label>
          <item>Mr. Bowman. </item>
          <label>Ferdinand, <hi>Prince of </hi>Thessaly, in <hi>Love with </hi>Urania. </label>
          <item>Mr. Powell. </item>
          <label>Cesario, <hi>General of </hi>Naples, <hi>privately Contracted to </hi>Urania. </label>
          <item>Mr. Mountfort. </item>
          <label>Tachmas, <hi>His Brother, banisht from </hi>Naples, <hi>and lives disguised in the Habit of a Hermit </hi>
          </label>
          <item>Mr. Hodgson. </item>
          <label>Vincentio, Commander </label>
          <item>Mr. Bridges. </item>
          <label>Sigismond, Commander </label>
          <item>Mr. Cibber. </item>
          <label>Oswell, <hi>Creature to </hi>Ferdinand. </label>
          <item>Mr. Freeman. </item>
          <label>Fabio, <hi>an Impudent, Impertinent Courtier</hi>. </label>
          <item>Mr. Bowen. </item>
          <label>Attendant. </label>
          <item>Mr. Kirkham. </item>
        </list>
        <list>
          <head>WOMEN. </head>
          <label>Urania, <hi>Princess of </hi>Naples. </label>
          <item>Mrs. Bracegirdle. </item>
          <label>Ardelia, <hi>her Confident</hi>. </label>
          <item>Mrs. Richardson. </item>
        </list>
        <p>Scene NAPLES. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="ep000683-e1270">
        <pb n="1" xml:id="ep000683-005-b"/>
        <head>ACT I. SCENE I. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e1290">Urania discover'd melancholy, Ardelia standing by her. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e1320">
          <speaker>Ardel. </speaker>
          <p>DEar Madam, do not wear this clouded Brow, Those lively Looks that us'd to cheer the Court, Are now grown Strangers to you. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e1350">
          <speaker>Urania. </speaker>
          <l>Prithee Peace. </l>
          <l>Can I look pleasant in Cesario's Absence? </l>
          <l>As well the Sun, wrapt in a dark Eclipse, </l>
          <l>May appear beautiful to th' frighted World. </l>
          <l>Oh when, Cesario, when wilt thou return, </l>
          <l>To free me from thy hated Rival's Suit! </l>
          <l>This Ferdinand, Disturber of my Peace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e1470">
          <speaker>Ardel. </speaker>
          <l>Madam, you need not thus disturb your self. </l>
          <l>He takes all humble ways to gain your Heart: </l>
          <l>Your Father too seems not to force your Love, </l>
          <l>And if Cesario comes with Conquest home, </l>
          <l>The King's Consent perhaps may make you his. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e1550">
          <speaker>Urenia. </speaker>
          <p>What Musick's that? </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e1580">Soft Musick within▪ </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e1590">
          <speaker>Ardel. </speaker>
          <p>'Tis with Prince Ferdinand. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e1630">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>Musick from Ferdinand! </l>
          <l>The Groans of tortur'd Ghosts were Airs more pleasing. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e1680">
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e1690">SONG within. </stage>
          <lg type="song">
            <lg n="1">
              <head>I. </head>
              <l>WHen Silvia is kind, and Love plays in her Eyes, </l>
              <l>I think 'tis no Morning till Silvia does rise; </l>
              <l>Of Silvia the Hills and the Valleys all ring, </l>
              <l>Her Beauty's the Subject each Shepherd does sing: </l>
              <l>But, if she proves cruel, how little will move </l>
              <l>Those Charms which inspir'd us with Raptures of Love? </l>
              <l>Thy Rigour, dear Sylvia, will shorten thy Reign, </l>
              <l>And make our bright Goddess a Mortal again. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
              <head>II. </head>
              <l>
                <stage xml:id="ep000683-e1880">Here enters Ferdinand, who stands gazing on Urania. </stage>Love heightens our Ioys; he's the Ease of our Care; </l>
              <l>Inspires the Valiant, and crowns all the Fair: </l>
              <pb n="2" xml:id="ep000683-006-a"/>
              <l>Oh seize his soft Wings then before 'tis too late, </l>
              <l>Or Cruelty quickly will hasten thy Fate. </l>
              <l>'Tis Kindness, dear Silvia, 'tis Kindness alone, </l>
              <l>Will add to thy Lovers, and strengthen thy Throne: </l>
              <l>In Love as in Empire, Tyrannical Sway </l>
              <l>Will make Loyal Subjects forget to obey. </l>
            </lg>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e1990">
          <speaker>Urania. </speaker>
          <l>Now, now begins my Horrour: </l>
          <l>The fatal Bell, shou'd it proclaim my Death, </l>
          <l>Were Sphere-like Musick to this Night-Crow's Voice. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e2040">
          <speaker>Ferdinand. </speaker>
          <l>Still, my Urania, still that angry Brow, </l>
          <l>Dearer than Life, but Oh, more cold than Death! </l>
          <l>Thou fair Insensible, still deaf to all. </l>
          <l>My Sighs, my Vows, my Prayers, Prayers that move Gods, </l>
          <l>And melt down Blessings even from Heav'n, are Eloquence </l>
          <l>Too weak to touch the more adored Urania. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e2140">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>Oh Ferdinand, why do you still pursue </l>
          <l>Your hopeless Suit, how oft have I deny'd you? </l>
          <l>Nay, when Denials, those rough Arguments, </l>
          <l>Have been but unsuccessful Orators, </l>
          <l>What soft Intreaties have I gently murmur'd, </l>
          <l>To lull that Passion which but only wakes </l>
          <l>To rack your Quiet, and to ruine mine! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e2240">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <p>Too cruel Fair! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e2270">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>I know, great Prince, you are the Man design'd, </l>
          <l>By my most Royal Father, for my Husband; </l>
          <l>But wou'd you wed my Person without Love? </l>
          <l>There are a Thousand Beauties wou'd affect you; </l>
          <l>Beauties, whose Charms do far exceed Urania's, </l>
          <l>And would be happy in so brave a Prince. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e2360">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>Why do you treat me thus like cruel Judges, </l>
          <l>Who speak them fairest whom they mean shou'd die? </l>
          <l>What Charms can ever equal bright Urania's? </l>
          <l>Or who (indeed) is worthy to possess 'em? </l>
          <l>Were I the Glorious Monarch of the Skies, </l>
          <l>By Heav'n, I'd place my Thunder in thy Hand; </l>
          <l>Make Nature and her Laws owne thy Command; </l>
          <l>Mount thee aloft on my proud Eagle's Wings; </l>
          <l>Whilst all my lesser Gods, like Captive Kings, </l>
          <l>And fawning Courtiers, fill'd thy shining Train; </l>
          <l>Thou o'er thy Iove so Absolute shou'dst Reign: </l>
          <l>To kiss thy Feet my Heavens should Homage pay: </l>
          <l>And crowding Stars make a new Milky Way. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e2530">
          <pb n="3" xml:id="ep000683-006-b"/>
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>Forbear this Language I with Horrour hear: </l>
          <l>Alas, I've made a strict and solemn Vow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e2570">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <p>A Vow! to what? to whom? Ah speak! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e2600">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>To one who merits all that I can give. </l>
          <l>To one that long has kept my Heart a Pris'ner: </l>
          <l>With whom I've vow'd it shall remain for ever; </l>
          <l>Make me not perjur'd, keep your Kindness in, </l>
          <l>For Love and I must never meet agen. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e2670">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>What murd'ring Sounds are these! and must this happy, </l>
          <l>Blest, Cursed Rival have more Pow'r than I? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e2710">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>Pardon me, Sir, when I am bound to say, </l>
          <l>And die to prove it true: </l>
          <l>Not all the Sun sees must alter me; </l>
          <l>Not Empires buy my Love, nor Tortures force it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e2770">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>I feel an Ice, creeping through all my Veins, </l>
          <l>That more than killing Winter-blast, that chills </l>
          <l>My crusting Blood, and turns me into Marble. </l>
          <l>Speak, speak, Urania, whilst I've sence to hear; </l>
          <l>Who is this curst Invader of my Right? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e2850">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>'Tis you that are the Invader of his Right; </l>
          <l>For e'er I thought or heard of Ferdinand, </l>
          <l>I'd treasur'd up my Soul in dear Cesario. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e2920">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>Cesario, ha, is he my happy Rival? </l>
          <l>Can you then stoop so low to love a Subject, </l>
          <l>And slight the proffer'd Greatness of a Crown? </l>
          <l>Yet, yet, Urania, call up Noble Thoughts; </l>
          <l>Think of a Crown. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e3010">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>A Crown, a Glittering Trifle, </l>
          <l>On which a Love like mine looks down with Scorn, </l>
          <l>And thinks it greater Pleasure in a Cottage; </l>
          <l>An humble Shepherdess with my Cesario, </l>
          <l>Than Reign the Empress of the Gawdy East </l>
          <l>In any others Arms. You have my Answer; </l>
          <l>And if my Father will not give Consent, </l>
          <l>The Coals the Roman Portia did devour, </l>
          <l>Are not blown out, Steel holds its Temper still: </l>
          <l>Nay there are Thousand ways to let our Life, </l>
          <l>And I dare die for him. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e3160">Exit Uran. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e3180">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>Did my Stars owe me this! Oh I could curse 'em! </l>
          <l>And from my tortured Heart exhale those Vapours, </l>
          <l>Those Sulphur-Fumes from the black Hell within me, </l>
          <pb n="4" xml:id="ep000683-007-a"/>
          <l>With Execration that should blast the Day, </l>
          <l>And darken all the World. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e3250">Enter Oswell. </stage>
          <l>Who's there? my Oswell? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e3290">
          <speaker>Oswell. </speaker>
          <l>Ever your Creature, Sir, but much concern'd </l>
          <l>To find this Alteration in your Looks. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e3330">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>Thou wouldst not wonder, didst thou know the Cause▪ </l>
          <l>The bright Urania, she whose spreading Fame </l>
          <l>Drew me from Thessaly to view that Beauty </l>
          <l>So much admired by every neighb'ring Prince: </l>
          <l>Whom when I saw I scarce could think her mortal. </l>
          <l>Something so all Divine shot from those Eyes, </l>
          <l>That I had not the Power to stand before 'em. </l>
          <l>Our Fathers both consented to the Match; </l>
          <l>But she, that cruel Fair, is still impenetrable; </l>
          <l>Minds not my Passion, slights my proffer'd Glory, </l>
          <l>Dotes on a Subject, one below my Birth▪ </l>
          <l>Flies, with Disdain, from the true Flame I bring, </l>
          <l>To light her humble Taper at a Gloe-worm. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e3500">
          <speaker>Osw. </speaker>
          <l>'Tis very strange the great Prince Ferdinand, </l>
          <l>With all his prosperous Fortunes cannot thaw her. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e3550">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>The fatal Cause of all her Scorn's too plain▪ </l>
          <l>This fair infatuated Charmer </l>
          <l>Dotes on Cesario, on her Father's General, </l>
          <l>Whose threatning Power stands like a flaming Sword, </l>
          <l>To stop my Entrance into Paradise; </l>
          <l>He's now imploy'd 'gainst the Sicilian King, </l>
          <l>And whilst he conquers, Ferdinand is lost. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e3670">
          <speaker>Osw. </speaker>
          <l>I rather think you should with Joy receive him, </l>
          <l>Who comes a Conqu'ror from her Father's Enemy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e3710">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>If he comes home with Victory, the King </l>
          <l>And his wise State must give him Thanks, the People </l>
          <l>Giddily run to meet the Conquerour, </l>
          <l>And owe their Lives and Safeties to his Triumph. </l>
          <l>But where am I? what Peace brings it to me? </l>
          <l>What Blessing is't to hear the popular Voice▪ </l>
          <l>The echoing Crowd, with all their barbarous Throats, </l>
          <l>Shoot their wild Joys to Heaven, and I in Torment? </l>
          <l>Certain to lose my Hopes in fair Urania. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e3830">
          <speaker>Osw. </speaker>
          <l>There may be ways at home to remove him, </l>
          <pb n="5" xml:id="ep000683-007-b"/>
          <l>And place you in your Wishes; but, my Lord▪ </l>
          <l>Whatever Spight you owe his prosp'rous Love, </l>
          <l>'Tis hard to envy him his Sword's Success. </l>
          <l>For should that fail, a Kingdom might be lost. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e3900">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>A Kingdom! Death! were the whole World at stake, </l>
          <l>How light the balanc'd Universe would weigh </l>
          <l>With the Possession of the fair Urania! </l>
          <l>Such Beauty, and such Charms,— I shall run mad, </l>
          <l>And my Desires, by opposition, grow more violent, </l>
          <l>And without vent will burst me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e3990">
          <speaker>Osw. </speaker>
          <l>Who could have thought a Masculine Soul, like yours, </l>
          <l>Should sink beneath a Shock so feeble, </l>
          <l>Shall this poor Diminutive thing, this little Rival, </l>
          <l>Whom with your Breath you may blow out o'th' World, </l>
          <l>Raise such a storm within you? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e4060">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>No, he sha'not. </l>
          <l>I've found my self again, and will be calm: </l>
          <l>No, thou too pityless Urania, spight </l>
          <l>Of all my lowring Fate, my unkind Planets, </l>
          <l>And those fair, cruel Eyes, my angry Stars, </l>
          <l>I will not lose my hold. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e4150">Enter Fabio. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e4170">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <p>How now, what News with you? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e4200">
          <speaker>Fabio. </speaker>
          <p>An't please your Grace, an humble Creature of yours, proud o'th' least Occasion, to express how faithfully my Heart is fixt to serve you. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e4230">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <p>What's your Business? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e4260">
          <speaker>Fab. </speaker>
          <l>I have Business of some Consequence; </l>
          <l>I had not been so bold else to disturb your Princely Conference, </l>
          <l>For I durst never assume that impudent Garb, </l>
          <l>That other Courtiers are known by; </l>
          <l>My Devotion has been still t'appear </l>
          <l>In modest Services. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e4340">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <p>Well, Sir, to'th Point </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e4370">
          <speaker>Fab. </speaker>
          <l>It were a Point of deep Neglect, to keep </l>
          <l>Your Grace in Expectation, yet Delays </l>
          <l>Make Joys the sweeter; Arrows that fly compass </l>
          <l>Arrive with as much Happiness to the Mark, </l>
          <l>As those that are shot point-blank. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e4440">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>This Courtier loves to hear himself talk; </l>
          <l>Be not so impertinent, we know your Care. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e4480">
          <pb n="6" xml:id="ep000683-008-a"/>
          <speaker>Fab. </speaker>
          <l>And Cost, my Lord, I hope: </l>
          <l>For they that hold Intelligence abroad </l>
          <l>To benefit their Countrey, must not make </l>
          <l>Idols of their Estates, and 'tis a Happiness </l>
          <l>To sell their Fortunes for their Prince's Smiles; </l>
          <l>Which I am confident you will vouchsafe, </l>
          <l>When you have heard my News. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e4570">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <p>Would you'd vouchsafe to let me hear it. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e4600">
          <speaker>Fab. </speaker>
          <l>Vouchsafe, my Lord, alas, </l>
          <l>You may command my Tongue, my Hands, my Feet, </l>
          <l>My Head, I should account that Limb superfluous, </l>
          <l>That would not be cut off to do you Service. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e4660">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <p>I do command thee Silence; dost hear? Silence. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e4690">
          <speaker>Fab. </speaker>
          <l>Silence, my Good Lord, is a Vertue I know; </l>
          <l>But where the Tongue has something to deliver, </l>
          <l>That may delight my Prince's Ear, and so forth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e4740">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <p>'s Death, Dog! Torment me not, but tell your News! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e4770">
          <speaker>Fab. </speaker>
          <p>My News, my good Lord, concerns the General. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e4800">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <p>What of him? Is he kill'd? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e4830">
          <speaker>Fab. </speaker>
          <l>The Stars forbid! he is return'd, my Lord, </l>
          <l>Triumphant, Brave and Glorious. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e4870">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>Be dumb. </l>
          <l>Another Syllable I'll have thy Tongue out. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e4910">
          <speaker>Fab. </speaker>
          <p>My Tongue, my Lord. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e4940">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>Thy Tongue, my buzzing Flesh-fly. </l>
          <l>Was all your Circumstance for this? Begone. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e4980">
          <speaker>Fab. </speaker>
          <l>It would be a Piece of Rudeness, my Lord, </l>
          <l>Unpardonable not to obey a Prince; </l>
          <l>For your Grace is sensible, That to we Courtiers </l>
          <l>The Tongue is so very useful a Member— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e5040">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <p>Slave, </p>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e5070">Ex. Fab. bowing. </stage>
          <p>Am I become a Jesting-stock for Fools? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e5100">
          <speaker>Oswell. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord, you are too open-breasted, </l>
          <l>To let this Fellow see into your Heart; </l>
          <l>Wise men disguise their Councels till things are ripe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e5150">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>The News has rent my Soul. </l>
          <l>I feel new Armies in my Breast, Swords, Javelins, </l>
          <l>All a whole Field of clashing War within me; </l>
          <l>But ha, the King! the Subtilty of Serpents </l>
          <l>Inspire me now, and something below Man, </l>
          <l>Spight, Malice, Woman's Malice enter here. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e5230">
          <pb n="7" xml:id="ep000683-008-b"/>Enter the King. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e5250">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Oh Ferdinand! I am all Joy: </l>
          <l>Cesario, beloved Cesario, is return'd with Conquest, </l>
          <l>And Sicily no more dares be our Foe; </l>
          <l>Cesario's Sword cuts with so keen an Edge, </l>
          <l>And drives that formidable Fame before him, </l>
          <l>His very Name alone, without an Army, </l>
          <l>Is more than half the Conquerour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e5390">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>His Name alone, my Lord, though he have conquer'd; </l>
          <l>We must consider, Sir, your Soldiers Courage: </l>
          <l>Their Valour stands the Basis of his Pyramid: </l>
          <l>Their Sweat and Blood that Crown'd him: but alas! </l>
          <l>All the whole Trophies of a conquer'd Field, </l>
          <l>Wreath only Garlands for the Leaders Brow; </l>
          <l>The General's still the mighty Man, he wears </l>
          <l>The Conqu'ring Bays, whose Wounds soever pay for't; </l>
          <l>Whilst the poor Soldier, like the Slave i'th' Mine, </l>
          <l>Bears the least part of the rich Oar he digs for. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e5510">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <p>How, Ferdinand? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e5550">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <p>Nay, Sir, I do not envy him. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e5580">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>You envy him, indeed, I hope you do not, </l>
          <l>Since 'twas for me he fought, and for his Country. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e5620">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>Right, 'twas for you he fought, and 'tis the Cause </l>
          <l>That often prospers, which, without his Valour, </l>
          <l>Had stood its own Defender, for there waits </l>
          <l>A Guardian-Angel on a Righteous Cause, </l>
          <l>And when that arms, Heaven battels on its side. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e5690">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>In all this ill-timed Rhetorick, methinks </l>
          <l>You speak as if you envy'd his Success, </l>
          <l>And wear a Face of Sorrow for his Fortune. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e5740">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <p>Who, I, my gracious Lord? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e5770">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Yes you, my Lord; </l>
          <l>Speak, tell me, does he not deserve all Honours </l>
          <l>That I can give, or he has Power to ask. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e5820">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <p>Indeed I think he does not. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e5850">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <p>Ha! what's that? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e5880">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>Pardon me, Royal Sir, and hear me Speak </l>
          <l>If Subjects spend their Blood in their Kings Cause, </l>
          <l>Forbid it Heaven they should not be rewarded: </l>
          <l>But how, or what Rewards must they expect? </l>
          <pb n="8" xml:id="ep000683-009-a"/>
          <l>Wou'd you, in Recompence of this his Conquest, </l>
          <l>Give him your Crown? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e5960">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <p>No, Sir, nor wou'd he ask it. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e5990">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <p>How know you that! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e6020">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>I know him to be Loyal; </l>
          <l>Know that he wears a Sword which only fights </l>
          <l>For his King's Honour, and his Country's Safety, </l>
          <l>Whilst his clear Soul runs purer than to suck </l>
          <l>A Poyson from that cankered Weed, Ambition. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e6090">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>I think otherwise, </l>
          <l>And, wou'd you give me leave, can prove it to you. </l>
          <l>You know not, Sir, how high his Fancy soars, </l>
          <l>Or to what Pitch his towring Pride wou'd reach; </l>
          <l>For he that aims to be his Monarch's Son, </l>
          <l>Would never rest till he had gain'd his Crown. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e6170">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord, this Riddle wants an OEdipus, </l>
          <l>For 'tis beyond my Fathom to expound it. </l>
          <l>But were Cesario Guilty of such Baseness, </l>
          <l>I would esteem him as my greatest Foe, </l>
          <l>And drive him from my Bosom as Infectious; </l>
          <l>As a Crown'd Head I owe my self that Justice. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e6270">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>Then I dare boldly speak; you know, my Liege, </l>
          <l>By a King's Sacred Promise you are bound, </l>
          <l>To make Urania mine. Would it not be a stain </l>
          <l>Upon your Royal Name, to have a Subject, </l>
          <l>Spight of his great Master's Vow, </l>
          <l>By treacherous Ways, to gain his Daughter's Love, </l>
          <l>And make himself, by stealth, your Kingdoms Heir? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e6370">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <p>Who is it dares do that? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e6400">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>That dares Cesario: </l>
          <l>By Heaven, Urania own'd a Love for him; </l>
          <l>Own'd it to me, who wooed by your Permission; </l>
          <l>And if you meet his Conquests with this Triumph, </l>
          <l>'Twill make your Subjects think he does deserve her: </l>
          <l>The Army then will pay him, not you, Homage, </l>
          <l>And every Voice sound nought but proud Cesario. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e6520">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <p>Can this be true? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e6550">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>Your Daughter will confess it; </l>
          <l>And if you mount his airy Thoughts too high, </l>
          <l>He himself will not blush to ask her of you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e6600">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <p>By Heaven, I will prevent that Insolence. </p>
          <pb n="9" xml:id="ep000683-009-b"/>
          <p>Have I been prodigal in's Praise for this? </p>
          <p>Yes, he shall be received. Who waits? </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e6650">Enter <hi>Fabio▪ </hi>
        </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e6670">
          <speaker>Fabio. </speaker>
          <p>My Lord! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e6700">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <p>Speak, is Cesario with the Army near? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e6740">
          <speaker>Fab. </speaker>
          <p>My Lord, as I'm inform'd, and commonly </p>
          <p>My Information's good, he does not want </p>
          <p>A full Days March, and will be here to night. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e6790">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Give Order that no Man go forth to meet him, </l>
          <l>Until our Pleasure's further known. Command </l>
          <l>The Governour place a Guard about the Gates; </l>
          <l>Let no Man's Face appear upon your Life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e6850">
          <speaker>Fab. </speaker>
          <p>Why, does your Majesty think I will fail </p>
          <p>In the Performance of your Orders? No! </p>
          <p>When I do that, may I— </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e6900">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Begone, I say, and fool some other time. <stage xml:id="ep000683-e6930">Exit Fab. </stage>
          </l>
          <l>Who wou'd repose in Man, whose vast Ambition, </l>
          <l>Wou'd strive to mount above the Rebel-Giants </l>
          <l>Cesario, I will quell thy haughty Pride, </l>
          <l>Who durst attempt the Daughter of thy King; </l>
          <l>Yet she too owns a fault that equals thine. </l>
          <l>Degenerate Princess, can such Low-born Passion </l>
          <l>Stir this course Ferment in thy Royal Blood! </l>
          <l>Run thy rich Veins no purer, Folly, Frailty, Frenzy! </l>
          <l>Oh Woman! Woman, to thy share they fall; </l>
          <l>Thou sweep'st the Heap, and hast engross'd 'em all. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e7060">Exeunt. </stage>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="ep000683-e7070">
        <head>ACT II. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e7090">Enter <hi>Cesario, Vincentio, Sigismond </hi>and Soldiers. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e7120">
          <speaker>Cesario. </speaker>
          <p>COmmand a Halt. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e7150">
          <speaker>1 Soldier. </speaker>
          <p>Halt. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e7180">
          <speaker>2 Soldier. </speaker>
          <p>Halt. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e7210">
          <speaker>3 Soldier. </speaker>
          <p>Halt. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e7240">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <p>The King sure had Intelligence. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e7270">
          <pb n="10" xml:id="ep000683-010-a"/>
          <speaker>Vincentio. </speaker>
          <p>Most certain. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e7300">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>'Tis strange! </l>
          <l>Is it not possible we have mistook the Place, </l>
          <l>Transported with our Victory? </l>
          <l>Speak, Gentlemen, is't so, or do we dream? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e7360">
          <speaker>Vincent. </speaker>
          <l>Those Walls </l>
          <l>Are certainly the same, and that the City, </l>
          <l>Peopled when we set out, and full of Prayers. </l>
          <l>For our Success. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e7420">
          <speaker>Sigism. </speaker>
          <l>It may be they reserve </l>
          <l>Their welcome till we march into the City. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e7460">
          <speaker>Vincent. </speaker>
          <p>Nay, they may have some Conceit. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e7490">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>A general Silence, like Night, dwells round about us, </l>
          <l>And no sign that Men inhabit here. </l>
          <l>Have we won abroad to lose our selves at home? </l>
          <l>Or, what is worse, </l>
          <l>Has, whilst we went, some Monster landed here, </l>
          <l>Made the Place desolate, devoured the Natives, </l>
          <l>And made 'em creep into their Mother Earth? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e7580">
          <speaker>Sigism. </speaker>
          <p>Not one Salute for our Return, such cold reception? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e7610">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>Sure they don't take us for their Enemies. </l>
          <l>Captain, enquire the Cause; let none else move: </l>
          <l>Yet stay; sure it must be some strange Mortality, </l>
          <l>And yet that cannot be. Have we brought home </l>
          <l>Their Safeties, purchas'd through so many Horrours, </l>
          <l>And is this all the payment for our Conquest, </l>
          <l>To shut the Gates upon us? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e7700">
          <speaker>Vincent. </speaker>
          <l>Force 'em open; </l>
          <l>' sDeath! let us shake their Walls about their Ears, </l>
          <l>They are asleep sure. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e7750">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>Such another Rashness </l>
          <l>Forfeits thy Head; Go to; Be temperate: </l>
          <l>As I grudge none the Merit of their Valour, </l>
          <l>I must hear none so bold. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e7810">
          <speaker>Vincent. </speaker>
          <p>I've done, Sir. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e7840">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>Subjects are bound to fight for Princes, </l>
          <l>They not ty'd to the Reward of every Service; </l>
          <l>I look upon thee now dy'd o'er in Blood, </l>
          <l>And have forgot thy Errour, give no breath </l>
          <l>To such a Thought hereafter; Honour pays </l>
          <l>Double where Kings neglect, and he </l>
          <l>Indeed is valiant, that forgets to be rewarded </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e7930">
          <pb n="11" xml:id="ep000683-010-b"/>
          <speaker>Sigism. </speaker>
          <p>This is cold Comfort for a Knapsack-Man. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e7960">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>And yet 'tis strange the King shou'd thus neglect us; </l>
          <l>This is cheap Entertainment for a Conquerour, </l>
          <l>Is't not Vincentio? Misery of Soldiers! </l>
          <l>When they have sweat Blood for their Countries Honour, </l>
          <l>They lie at others Mercy! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e8040">
          <speaker>Vincent. </speaker>
          <p>They have slept since, and dreamt not of our Sufferings. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e8070">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>There's something would fain mutiny within me. </l>
          <l>Strangle these Snakes betimes, Cesario. </l>
          <l>So fold up your Ensigns, throw off all the Pride </l>
          <l>That may express a Triumph; we'll march on, </l>
          <l>As we had over-bought our Victory. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e8150">
          <speaker>Vincent. </speaker>
          <l>The Gates are open now, and we discover, </l>
          <l>A Woman, by her Habit, coming this Way. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e8190">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>Alone! more strange and fatal! </l>
          <l>It may be, 'tis my Genius come to give </l>
          <l>A Melancholy Warning of my Death, </l>
          <l>As Brutus had from his: I'll stand my Destiny: </l>
          <l>Yet bearing the Resemblance of a Woman, </l>
          <l>It will less terrifie. Who should this be? </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e8280">Enter Urania veil'd. </stage>
          <l>Lady, </l>
          <l>Who e'er you are, there's something in that Cloud, </l>
          <l>That mournful Cloud! which speaks some wondrous Sadness; </l>
          <l>Would I'd the Power to dispossess your Sorrow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e8340">
          <speaker>Urania. </speaker>
          <p>My dear Cesario! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e8380">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>My beloved Urania! </l>
          <l>I'm now rewarded, had Cesario taken </l>
          <l>Into his Body, Wounds not to be number'd, </l>
          <l>This Kiss had cur'd 'em all; or but one Drop </l>
          <l>Of this rich Balsom; for I know thy Tears </l>
          <l>Are shed for Joy to see Cesario safe. </l>
          <l>The King, with all the Glories of his Province, </l>
          <l>Cannot do greater Honour to his General; </l>
          <l>For I've a greater Empire in thy Love, </l>
          <l>Than Fame or Victory has ever boasted. </l>
          <l>My Life! My Soul! Uranio! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e8550">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>Call again that Temper which has made Cesario Honour'd, </l>
          <l>And if my Tears (which carry something more </l>
          <l>Then Joy to welcome home my most loved Lord) </l>
          <pb n="12" xml:id="ep000683-011-a"/>
          <l>Affect you with no Sadness, (which I wish not) </l>
          <l>View well my Looks, which I have not put on </l>
          <l>To counterfeit a Grief, and they will tell you, </l>
          <l>There is necessity for you to know, </l>
          <l>Somewhat to check the Current of your Triumph. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e8660">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>I was too careless, </l>
          <l>Of thy sad Looks, my Joy to see thy Face </l>
          <l>Made me distinguish nothing else; proceed, </l>
          <l>And punish my too prodigal Embraces; </l>
          <l>It is not fit I be in one Thought blest, </l>
          <l>And thou in such a Livery. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e8740">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>When you say, </l>
          <l>You've strength enough to entertain the Knowledge </l>
          <l>Of such an Injury. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e8790">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>If it only point at me, </l>
          <l>Speak it at once, I am collected, </l>
          <l>And dare all Shafts that level at this Head: </l>
          <l>If it concern thy self, let it not flow too fast, </l>
          <l>But rather let my Ears receive it </l>
          <l>By such Degrees as may not kill too soon, </l>
          <l>But leave me some Life only to revenge it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e8880">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <p>The King, (although my Father, I must speak) </p>
          <p>The King, for whom you shed your Blood abroad, </p>
          <p>Has ill-rewarded you at home. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e8930">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <p>Speak, how? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e8960">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>Since your departure, here arriv'd a Prince, </l>
          <l>From Thessaly, permitted by my Father, </l>
          <l>To make his Court to me, which I resisted; </l>
          <l>His Personal Visits, Messages, rich Presents, </l>
          <l>Left me not quiet to enjoy my self; </l>
          <l>I told him I had given my Faith already, </l>
          <l>Contracted yours: Impatient of my Answers, </l>
          <l>He urg'd his Greatness, vow'd he would possess me; </l>
          <l>Yet I resisted still, and still am free, </l>
          <l>Preserv'd, and welcome home, my dearest Lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e9090">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <p>Is't possible? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e9120">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>This is but half the Story; </l>
          <l>By his Command none dare salute your Victory▪ </l>
          <l>Or pour their glad Hearts forth at your Return: </l>
          <l>Nay more; Unless I yield to wed the Prince </l>
          <pb n="13" xml:id="ep000683-011-b"/>
          <l>And you your self too grant your free Consent, </l>
          <l>Has vow'd your everlasting Banishment: </l>
          <l>And in it murders me, for when you're gone, </l>
          <l>I cannot, will not, must not, dare not live. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e9220">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>Yes, live Urania, tho' you live my Rival's▪ </l>
          <l>Let not the Icy arms of Death infold thee. </l>
          <l>Better thy Sex beside were all extinguisht, </l>
          <l>And thou the only God-like Woman left </l>
          <l>T'adorn the World. Vincentio, dost hear this? </l>
          <l>We must ask pardon that we have been valiant, </l>
          <l>Repent our Duties, and that Victory </l>
          <l>We bought so dear. We shou'd have dy'd abroad, </l>
          <l>And then perhaps, been talkt of, in the Crowd </l>
          <l>Of honest men, for giving up those Lives, </l>
          <l>Which, for our service, they may now take from us. </l>
          <l>We are not yet i'th' Snare, and have the power </l>
          <l>To stifle their designs. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e9390">
          <speaker>Vincent. </speaker>
          <p>The Soldiers hearts are yours. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e9420">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>No, no, Vincentio, let 'em be the King's. </l>
          <l>If such as they forget their Office, we </l>
          <l>Must keep our Thoughts unstain'd: I'll to the King, </l>
          <l>But without any Train. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e9490">
          <speaker>Sigis. </speaker>
          <p>In this you do not consult your Safety. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e9520">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>Safety is a Lecture </l>
          <l>To be read to Children. But for me, I carry </l>
          <l>My own Security within. The King I know </l>
          <l>Is gracious, tho' at present </l>
          <l>His Passion reigns too strongly in his Breast. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e9590">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>Hear me, Cesario, e'er you see the King. </l>
          <l>Hear me, or poor Urania's lost for ever. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e9650">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <p>What says my Love? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e9680">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <p>Swear then to grant my Suit, </p>
          <p>And I will name the means to make us happy. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e9720">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <p>Oh speak! </p>
          <p>And bless my Ears with the dear Sound: </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e9760">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>Command your Soldiers first to greater distance. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e9790">Cesar. <hi>waves his hand, the Soldiers fall back. </hi>
          </stage>
          <l>You see Cesario, how our Hopes are crost: </l>
          <l>And if you love, as you have often swore, </l>
          <l>You will not stop at any thing to gain me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e9850">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>Propose a Means that may not blot my Fame, </l>
          <pb n="14" xml:id="ep000683-012-a"/>
          <l>Nor make me Traytor to my Sovereign: </l>
          <l>Not all the Dangers that can threaten Man, </l>
          <l>Shall barr Cesario from Urania's Arms. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e9930">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>Were it not better in some distant Clime, </l>
          <l>To live, and love, and peaceably possess </l>
          <l>The small Remainder of our Lives to come? </l>
          <l>What, though we quit all glittering Pomp and Greatness; </l>
          <l>The busie, noisy Flatteries of Court; </l>
          <l>We shall enjoy Content, in that alone </l>
          <l>Is Greatness, Power, Wealth, Honour all summ'd up. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e10020">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>I cannot guess thy Meaning; </l>
          <l>Instruct me plainer what you'd have me do. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e10060">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>Since then the King will ne'er let me be thine, </l>
          <l>Let's in the dead of Night retire from Court, </l>
          <l>And to th' Arcadian Plains direct our Steps; </l>
          <l>There amongst Nymphs and Shepherds we may live, </l>
          <l>And quite forget that we were ever great. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e10140">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>My Soul, my more than Life! now thou art too kind; </l>
          <l>But can my dear Urania, born a Princess, </l>
          <l>Nurs'd up in all the Tenderness of Power; </l>
          <l>The Pride, the Pomp and Glory of a Court; </l>
          <l>From her Arch'd Roofs, and Golden Towers, descend </l>
          <l>To homely Weeds, and humble Cottages, </l>
          <l>And all for worthless me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e10240">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>For thee, my Love! </l>
          <l>Thou Lord of all my Joys! Cells, Caves, and Desarts, </l>
          <l>Are Palaces with thee, Oh my Cesario! </l>
          <l>There there where True Love reigns is only Empire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e10310">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <p>Thou Angel-kind, and more than Angel fair! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e10340">
          <speaker>Sigism. </speaker>
          <p>My Lord, the King comes this way. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e10370">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>Now, Cesario, thou hast thy Choice, Love or Ambition; </l>
          <l>Either to challenge bravely, or resign me poorly: </l>
          <l>But yet, might I instruct you in your Choice, </l>
          <l>Since rather than wed Ferdinand, this hand </l>
          <l>Should give me Death; yet Oh▪ If I must die, </l>
          <l>Let me expire in Pleasure, not in Torment, </l>
          <l>If thou disclaimst me, slighted and despised, </l>
          <l>In that distracted Thought I shall die wretched; </l>
          <l>But if my dearest Lord will Nobly own me, </l>
          <l>Charm'd with that Bliss▪ then I can breath out Life </l>
          <l>Like Saints in Martyrdome; not one weak Nerve, </l>
          <pb n="15" xml:id="ep000683-012-b"/>
          <l>Or shivering sigh shall of the Dart complain, </l>
          <l>But the great cause shall sweeten all the pain. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e10540">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <l>Guide me you Gods in this Unhappy Labyrinth. <stage xml:id="ep000683-e10570">Enter <hi>King, Ferdinand, Oswell, Fabio, </hi>&amp;c. Cesa. kneels. </stage>
          </l>
          <l>Most Royal Sir, Alas, you too much honour </l>
          <l>The poor Cesario; who at your Feet </l>
          <l>Lays all his Lawrels, the fair Grove, </l>
          <l>That your kind Sun has warm'd and cherisht. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e10650">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Did I not give you a strict Charge, that none </l>
          <l>〈◊〉 pass the Gates? Tell me how she came hither? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e10690">To Fab. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e10710">
          <speaker>Fab. </speaker>
          <l>Indeed, an't please your Majesty, you did </l>
          <l>Give Order that no Man shou'd, but she said </l>
          <l>She was a Woman, and I askt no farther. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e10760">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Hence you Buffoon. </l>
          <l>Cesario, rise. I shall not flatter you▪ </l>
          <l>Nor indeed have I any Grace for him, </l>
          <l>Who durst attempt to steal my Kingdoms Heir. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e10830">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <l>Thus prostrate to the Earth, I sue for Pardon, </l>
          <l>That my ambitious Passion soars so high. </l>
          <l>But oh, there's Irresistless Force in Love; </l>
          <l>The Gods have felt it, then can Man withstand it. </l>
          <l>Such is my Fate, nay kill me, 'tis the same; </l>
          <l>For though I know 'tis Death to ask the Gift, </l>
          <l>Yet on my Knees I beg the fair Urania. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e10930">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>What says the Traytor! off, thy Breath will blast me, </l>
          <l>I see it, like a Mist, infect the Air. </l>
          <l>Good Gods! was ever Insolence like this! </l>
          <l>But sure I dream, this cannot be Cesario. </l>
          <l>Vincentio, Souldiers speak, is this your General? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e11020">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>Yes, yes, Great Sir. This is that Valiant Man, </l>
          <l>That fought for Loyalty, and not Ambition. </l>
          <l>Now you may see for what he drew his Sword, </l>
          <l>'Twas for Urania that he fought and Conquer'd; </l>
          <l>'Tis she, 'tis she, that must be his reward: </l>
          <l>O Sir, deny him not, make him your Son, </l>
          <l>Mould that course humble Clay t' Imperial Honour: </l>
          <l>And mix it with the Royal Blood of Naples. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e11140">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <l>This humble Clay! what saist thou haughty Lord! </l>
          <l>By Heaven that Tongue, did not the King protect it, </l>
          <pb n="16" xml:id="ep000683-013-a"/>
          <l>Had better challenge Iove, and all his Thunder, </l>
          <l>Thou titled Vanity! thou Courtier, made for peace, </l>
          <l>How much my Merits, for the fair Urania, </l>
          <l>Exceed thy poor Pretences; thou all Feather, </l>
          <l>Too tender for the very Wind to ruffle: </l>
          <l>When Wars loud Trumpet, in a Field of Death, </l>
          <l>Call'd me to wounds, and dy'd me o'er in Blood, </l>
          <l>Thou slepst securely, lull'd on Beds of Downe, </l>
          <l>Less soft than the effeminate Lord that fill'd 'em. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e11290">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Be silent, Traytor, this is perfect Raving; </l>
          <l>Your Valour has been paid in the Success; </l>
          <l>What you have done was Duty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e11340">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <p>True, it was; </p>
          <p>I must confess that it was Duty all. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e11380">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>To shew us then you have not mix'd our Cause </l>
          <l>With private and particular Revenge, </l>
          <l>Resolve, before tomorrow Sun appears, </l>
          <l>To quit Urania to Prince Ferdinand, </l>
          <l>Or be for ever banisht from Our Kingdom; </l>
          <l>And, Daughter, resolve you to meet his Love, </l>
          <l>And make Cesario to your Heart a Stranger, </l>
          <l>Or else expect to feel the worst of Tortures; </l>
          <l>Consult your safest way. Come, Gentlemen, </l>
          <l>And from a grateful King you all shall find </l>
          <l>The just Reward that's due to Truth and Honour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e11540">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <p>Ah my prophetick Fear! To night, Cesario. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e11580">Aside. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e11590">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <p>To night, my fair Remembrancer. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e11620">Aside to Uran. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e11640">Exeunt <hi>King, Ferd. Osw. Fab. Vincent. Sigism. </hi>and Soldiers. Manent Cesario and Urania. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e11680">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>Good Heaven! Can this be real? what, all gone! </l>
          <l>I, that this morning was the Lord of Thousands, </l>
          <l>Am not the Owner now of one poor Servant: </l>
          <l>Banisht from Love, or Naples; this is hard: </l>
          <l>But yet indeed 'tis not a wonder here, </l>
          <l>In this unhospitable Court of Naples. </l>
          <l>So my unhappy Brother fell before me, </l>
          <l>Who, for the slaying of this King's Court Minion, </l>
          <l>Was doom'd for ever from his Native Soil. </l>
          <l>Oh Tachmas! what e'er Corner of the World </l>
          <l>Now hides thy exil'd Head? Thy wretched Brother, </l>
          <l>The poor Cesario too must share thy Fate. </l>
          <pb n="17" xml:id="ep000683-013-b"/>
          <l>Yes; we will hasten to some Rural Seat, </l>
          <l>And never more in Cursed Courts be great: </l>
          <l>And when I go t' injoy Her Sacred Charms, </l>
          <l>What though I quit the World in those dear Arms! </l>
          <l>Oh with what glory will th' exchange be given, </l>
          <l>When I shall Lose Earth only, and find Heaven! </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e11920">Exit Cesa. </stage>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="ep000683-e11940">
        <head>ACT III. SCENE I. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e11960">Enter <hi>King, Ferdinand, Oswell</hi>, Guards, and Attendants. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e11980">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <p>GOne! 'tis impossible they should escape. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e12010">
          <speaker>Osw. </speaker>
          <l>We've searcht o'er all the Court, but 'twas in vain, </l>
          <l>Cesario and Urania in the Night </l>
          <l>Fled from the Palace, but which way they took, </l>
          <l>Not all our care can learn. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e12090">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>Curses pursue him. </l>
          <l>Some Whirlwind snatch him up, and on the back </l>
          <l>Of his Rough Wings, transport the wandering Ravisher, </l>
          <l>And Drop his Cursed Head into the Sea; </l>
          <l>Or land him in some cold, remote, wild Desart; </l>
          <l>There to inhabit amongst Brutes and Savages, </l>
          <l>O' th' two the Innocenter Beasts of Prey. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e12180">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord, it is not Rage can help us now, </l>
          <l>But e'er they are fled too far make swift pursuit, </l>
          <l>Leave not a Corner of my Realm unsearcht: </l>
          <l>Prepare me Men and Horse immediately: </l>
          <l>I'll after 'em my self. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e12250">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>Most Royal Sir. </l>
          <l>See at your Feet, an Injur'd Prince thus kneels, </l>
          <l>And begs that trust may be repos'd in him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e12300">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Thy Suit is granted; Haste, delay not then, </l>
          <l>Bring him alive or dead, I care not which. </l>
          <l>O that I cou'd Command a flash of Lightning; </l>
          <l>Or usurp one minute the Prerogative of Death. </l>
          <l>That I might shoot ruin as sudden on 'em, </l>
          <pb n="18" xml:id="ep000683-014-a"/>
          <l>As Waters fall from Mountains, but away, </l>
          <l>There is no danger now like our delay. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e12390">Ex. King, Attendants. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e12410">Ex. Omn. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e12420">Scene, <hi>A Wood.</hi>
        </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e12440">Enter Cesario, and Urania disguised. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e12470">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <l>Come, my Souls Joy, let not such painted griefs </l>
          <l>Press down thy Spirits, the darkness but presents </l>
          <l>Shadows of fear; for it is that secures us </l>
          <l>From dangerous pursuit. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e12530">
          <speaker>Ura. </speaker>
          <l>Wou'd it were day. </l>
          <l>My apprehension is so full of horrour, </l>
          <l>I think each found the airs light motion makes, </l>
          <l>To be my Father threatning our ruins, </l>
          <l>With all the storm of his impending Vengeance. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e12600">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <l>Fear not that thunder blast, whose Bolts too far to reach us, </l>
          <l>Wrapt in the Arms of Night that favours Lovers, </l>
          <l>We hitherto have scaped his eager search. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e12650">
          <speaker>Ura. </speaker>
          <l>But when will it be day, the light has comfort, </l>
          <l>Our first of useful sences being lost, </l>
          <l>The rest are less delighted. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e12700">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <p>The early Cock </p>
          <p>Has sung his Summons to the days approach▪ </p>
          <p>'Twill instantly appear, why starts my Love? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e12750">
          <speaker>Ura. </speaker>
          <p>Heard you no sound? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e12780">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <p>Sound! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e12810">
          <speaker>Ura. </speaker>
          <p>Some amazing sound. </p>
          <p>Pray listen. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e12850">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <l>'Tis thy fear suggests </l>
          <l>Illusive fancies. Under Loves protection </l>
          <l>We may presume of safety, but retire, </l>
          <l>And under yon kind Tree repose a while. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e12910">Ex. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e12920">Enter four Banditti. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e12940">
          <speaker>1 Band. </speaker>
          <p>Well, my dear Comrades of the Pad, prithee how Long have we, Brother Rogues, hung in a knot together. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e12970">
          <pb n="19" xml:id="ep000683-014-b"/>
          <speaker>2 Band. </speaker>
          <p>Hung together! hum, I don't like that word hanging▪ </p>
          <p>But if you mean, how long we have fairly robb'd together— </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e13010">
          <speaker>1 Band. </speaker>
          <l>Robb'd; pox, that's as bad as t'other; </l>
          <l>Give it a genteeler Name for shame, since we, </l>
          <l>Four Noble Captains, Sons of Thunder, </l>
          <l>And Brothers of Mercury, have been planted </l>
          <l>In the Post of Honour, and given the Words of Command, </l>
          <l>Stand, and deliver. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e13100">
          <speaker>2 Band. </speaker>
          <p>I, this is something like. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e13130">
          <speaker>3 Band. </speaker>
          <p>'Tis, let me see, some five Summers, And almost as many Winters. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e13160">
          <speaker>1 Band. </speaker>
          <l>And in all that time, I have been musing </l>
          <l>And hammering to find out, whether the Mystery of Thieving </l>
          <l>Be an Art, or a Science. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e13210">
          <speaker>3 Band. </speaker>
          <p>Oh fie, fie, a Science! most certain, and a Liberal Science too; for the People give all, and we take all. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e13240">
          <speaker>Omnes. </speaker>
          <p>Ay, Ay; A Liberal Science, A Liberal Science. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e13270">
          <speaker>1 Band. </speaker>
          <l>But come, Less Prattle, and more Business; </l>
          <l>For if these Eves-Droppers of mine have not damnably deceived me, </l>
          <l>Here must be Game abroad: I'm certain, </l>
          <l>I heard talking hard by, and if the Devil does not play booty, </l>
          <l>We shall have a Prize quickly. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e13340">
          <speaker>3 Band. </speaker>
          <p>Say you so? hush then, and sculk. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e13370">They retire to the side of the Stage. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e13380">Re-enter Cesario and Urania. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e13410">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <p>Sure, my Cesario, this is more than Fancy! </p>
          <p>Did you not hear some talk? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e13460">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <p>These must be Robbers: </p>
          <p>No matter; I've a Sword ne'er fail'd me yet; </p>
          <p>Though I'd not stain it with the Blood of Villains. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e13510">
          <speaker>2 Band. </speaker>
          <p>I think, I have you, Sir. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e13540">Lays hold on Ces. left Arm. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e13560">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <p>Thy Death thou hast; </p>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e13590">Cesario <hi>Runs him through</hi>. </stage>
          <p>But there's yet more to do e'er I am ta'en. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e13620">They fight off, Band. give way. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e13640">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <p>My Lord, Cesario, whither do you run? </p>
          <p>Come back, and shun, by flight, the Villains Swords: </p>
          <p>He's lost, he's lost! what will become of me! </p>
          <p>Whether, Oh! whether? which way shall I take! </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e13710">Ex. confusedly, at the wrong Door. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e13720">Re-enter Cesario bloody, his Sword drawn. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e13740">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>Urania! my Love, my Life, where art thou? </l>
          <l>My Soul! speak to me, 'tis Cesario calls. </l>
          <pb n="20" xml:id="ep000683-015-a"/>
          <l>By Heavens! I fear she has forsook the place, </l>
          <l>And wanders in the dark to find me out. </l>
          <l>Oh! I could rave; but see, the Day appears. </l>
          <l>Blest Lamp of Heaven, lead, lead me to Urania; </l>
          <l>With thy kind rising Beams guide me once more </l>
          <l>To those dear Eyes, thy Sister-Twins of Light, </l>
          <l>Or shrowd me, Gods, in Everlasting Night. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e13880">Ex. Ces. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e13900">Scene changes to another Part of the Wood. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e13910">Enter Urania. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e13930">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>The Day begins to break, and trembling Light, </l>
          <l>As if affrighted with this Night's Disaster, </l>
          <l>Steals through the farthest, Air, and by degrees </l>
          <l>Salutes my weary Longings; yet 'tis welcome, </l>
          <l>Though it betray me to the worst of Fate </l>
          <l>Love and Desire e'er suffer'd: Oh Cesario! </l>
          <l>Thy wisht for Presence wou'd have checkt these Passions, </l>
          <l>And shot Delight through all the Mists of Sadness: </l>
          <l>But thou art lost; and all my Joys are fled; </l>
          <l>Ne'er to return without thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e14060">Enter First and Third Banditti. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e14080">
          <speaker>1 Band. </speaker>
          <l>Have we found you! </l>
          <l>Seize her, Fabrichio, our Companion's Blood, </l>
          <l>Shed by your Hero, you shall now atone for. </l>
          <l>Drag her along, and tye her to yon' Tree, </l>
          <l>Where we, by turns, will quench our furious Appetites. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e14160">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>Kill me; Oh! kill me; rather let me dye </l>
          <l>Than live to see the Jewel that adorns </l>
          <l>The Souls of vertuous Virgins ravisht from me! </l>
          <l>Do not add Sin to Sin, and, at a Price </l>
          <l>That ruines me, and not enriches you, </l>
          <l>Purchase Damnation: Do not, do not do't. </l>
          <l>Sheath here your Swords, and my departing Soul, </l>
          <l>Like your good Angel, shall sollicite Heaven </l>
          <l>To dash out your Offences. See, here's Gold and Jewels; </l>
          <l>Take all, nay, had I more you should command, </l>
          <l>But do not stain my Vertue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e14290">
          <pb n="21" xml:id="ep000683-015-b"/>
          <speaker>3 Band. </speaker>
          <p>Ay, this is something; </p>
          <p>I love a Lass that pays well for her Pleasure. </p>
          <p>Come, let's stop her Mouth, I long till we're aboard her. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e14340">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <p>Help, Murder, Murder, a Rape. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e14370">Ex. Band. dragging Uran. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e14390">Enter Cesario. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e14410">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <p>For ever gone, yet I am still alive! </p>
          <p>Unpitying Gods, why have you snatcht her from me? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e14450">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e14470">within. </stage>
          <p>Help, Help, a Rape! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e14490">
          <speaker>3 Band. </speaker>
          <p>Stop her Mouth. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e14520">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <p>Ha! do I dream, or was't Urania's Voice? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e14560">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e14580">within. </stage>
          <p>Help, Murder, a Rape! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e14600">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <p>Help! to that Fair distrest quick let me fly: </p>
          <p>Not a departing Soul wou'd mount with half the Wings </p>
          <p>To reach his Heaven, as I to rescue mine. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e14650">Ex. hastily. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e14660">The Scene draws, and discovers Urania ty'd to a Tree by the Hair, the Banditti's on each side of her. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e14690">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <p>Yet, yet, be merciful and take my Life: </p>
          <p>Oh barbarous Men; how can you be thus cruel? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e14730">
          <speaker>3 Band. </speaker>
          <p>Barbarous d'ye call us? nay if this be cruel </p>
          <p>We'll try a kinder way of Love to please you. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e14770">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <p>Dear Sir, if ever Vertue, Mercy, Pity dwelt in your noble Breast! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e14800">
          <speaker>1 Band. </speaker>
          <p>If ever Passion, and warm Desire </p>
          <p>Dwelt in my boyling Veins, I love thee. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e14840">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <p>Is this Love? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e14870">
          <speaker>1 Band. </speaker>
          <p>No, but though this be not, </p>
          <p>We'll shew thee what it is before we part. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e14910">Enter Cesario with his Sword drawn, he drives 'em off. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e14930">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>Dogs, Blood-hounds, Cannibals; Death! do you fly? </l>
          <l>Your Crimes so heavy, and your Heels so light. </l>
          <l>Stay, Satyrs, stay, you vanishing Furies, stay, </l>
          <l>And take your dear Damnation e'er you go. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e15000">Unbinds Uran </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e15020">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <p>My kind Cesario, this is double Joy, </p>
          <p>To be preserv'd, and hold thee in my Arms. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e15070">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>Yes, in thy Arms thy blest Cesario lives; </l>
          <l>Thy dear, thy soft, thy charming, and I hope </l>
          <l>Thy unpolluted Arms, for say, my Soul, </l>
          <l>Art thou unspotted still? as (if there be </l>
          <l>Those Guardian-Gods that succour Vertue) sure </l>
          <pb n="22" xml:id="ep000683-016-a"/>
          <l>Heaven has not suffer'd those infernal Monsters, </l>
          <l>To rifle this dear Casket of Divinity. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e15170">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <p>I am yet spotless, thank your happy self, </p>
          <p>My lovely Champion, whose delivering Hand </p>
          <p>Has freed my darling Honour. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e15220">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <p>I believe thee, </p>
          <p>For thou'rt all Truth, the Innocence on that Face </p>
          <p>Says thou art chaste, the guilty cannot speak </p>
          <p>So heavenly as thou dost. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e15280">Enter Tachmas in the Habit of a Hermet. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e15300">
          <speaker>Tach. </speaker>
          <l>What mournful Pair is this, whose very Looks </l>
          <l>Inform me they are loaden with Misfortunes? </l>
          <l>Ha! 'tis Cesario, by my Wrongs, my Brother! </l>
          <l>Oh Alphonzo! Oh thou most barbarous King! </l>
          <l>By Heaven, I find more Gratitude 'mong Beasts, </l>
          <l>Than ever dwelt within the Court of Naples. </l>
          <l>The Blessings of the Day upon you both. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e15420">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>We thank you, Reverend Father; and if Pity </l>
          <l>E'er dwelt within your Breast, Ah, shew it now! </l>
          <l>Shew it to us, the most unhappy Pair, </l>
          <l>That e'er were punisht by offended Heaven. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e15480">
          <speaker>Tach. </speaker>
          <l>Who e'er you are, you look indeed most wretched; </l>
          <l>And Charity obliges me to help you. </l>
          <l>Under yon' Mountain, in the Earths deep Hollow, </l>
          <l>I have a Cell; please you to walk that way; </l>
          <l>What Comforts that can yield you shall command. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e15550">
          <speaker>Ces. </speaker>
          <l>Eternal Blessings crown you, for this Goodness: </l>
          <l>Come, my dear Saint, let's to this Hermet's Cell, </l>
          <l>And take that Refuge his poor Mansion yields; </l>
          <l>None can fear Danger where Religion shields. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e15610">Ex. Omnes. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e15620">The Scene changes to the Palace. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e15630">Enter King attended. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e15650">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>No Tydings yet! no News from Ferdinand! </l>
          <l>Curses and Plagues pursue this pair of Monsters, </l>
          <l>Sink, sink 'em in a Whirlpool of Confusion. </l>
          <l>If they are fled by Land, gape, gape thou Earth, </l>
          <l>And take into thy Womb the stinging Vipers: </l>
          <pb n="23" xml:id="ep000683-016-b"/>
          <l>But if by Sea, if they that way 〈◊〉 〈◊〉, </l>
          <l>Blow Winds, and raise ah Everlasting storm, </l>
          <l>Till you have laid 'em in a Wat'ry Grave. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e15760">
          <speaker>Attend. </speaker>
          <p>My Liege, they may be found. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e15790">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>They may, they shall. </l>
          <l>Not the deep Center of the Earth shall hide 'em. </l>
          <l>Nay, were they guarded by a band of Furies, </l>
          <l>And kept secure in the Infernal Court. </l>
          <l>I wou'd my self Assault the brazen Gates, </l>
          <l>And in dispight of Hell compleat my Vengeance. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e15870">
          <speaker>Attend. </speaker>
          <l>Do not torment your self, great Sir, with passion, </l>
          <l>All care imaginable's ta'ne to find'em. </l>
          <l>Prince Ferdinand himself is in purshit, </l>
          <l>And no disguise can hide 'em from his sight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e15940">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Disguise! by Heauen had I but follow'd 'em, </l>
          <l>Not all the shapes of Proteus should secure 'em. </l>
          <l>Argus with all his hundred watchful Eyes, </l>
          <l>Had been but blind to my discovering Vengeance; </l>
          <l>And when I'd got the Fugitives in my Power, </l>
          <l>I'd use the Infamous abandon'd Miscreants, </l>
          <l>The profligated Vagrants with less Mercy </l>
          <l>Than she has done my Peace, or he her Honour. </l>
          <l>Oh like a Faulcon I'd the Quaries seize, </l>
          <l>And grind and tear their Souls out by degrees. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e16080">Ex. Omn. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e16090">Scene changes to the Hermets Cell. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e16100">Enter Cesario and Urania. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e16130">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <l>My Dear Urania, Miracle of Women. </l>
          <l>Was ever Love so great, so true as thine; </l>
          <l>Claspt in thy snowy Arms, I find more bliss, </l>
          <l>Than Scepter'd Pride, and Crown'd ambition tastes, </l>
          <l>In all their gust of Power, and wreaths of Gold. </l>
          <l>But my sweet Excellence, I've been unkind. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e16220">
          <speaker>Ura. </speaker>
          <p>Unkind! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e16250">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <l>Unkind, my Angel, </l>
          <l>To take such Beauty, born a Kingdoms Heir, </l>
          <l>Light of my World, and Treasure of my Soul, </l>
          <l>Nurst up in all the softnesses of Courts, </l>
          <l>And poorly strip thee to these homely Weeds, </l>
          <pb n="24" xml:id="ep000683-017-a"/>
          <l>Misery and want, and lodg'd in Woods and Caves: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e16330">
          <speaker>Ura. </speaker>
          <l>Whilst thou art with me, they are Palaces, </l>
          <l>For the Reception of an Eastern Monarch, </l>
          <l>Abandon Crowns and Courts for Woods and Caves: </l>
          <l>And is that all, can thy Urania do </l>
          <l>No greater Miracle for Love than this? </l>
          <l>True Love shou'd quit the World, to grov'llng Minds </l>
          <l>Resign that worthless Toy, the gewgaw Globe, </l>
          <l>And leave the bandied Ball for Fools to play with. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e16440">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <l>Mirrour of Goodness, thou art all Divine; </l>
          <l>The Trojan Youth whose dazled Eyes survey'd </l>
          <l>Three Tempting, Courting Goddesses at once, </l>
          <l>Did not behold thy worth. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e16500">Enter Tachmas. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e16520">
          <speaker>Tac. </speaker>
          <l>How fares my Son? </l>
          <l>What are you still opprest with Melancholy? </l>
          <l>Come, you're to blame, for though your Cheer be mean, </l>
          <l>Your Company a wretched poor old Man, </l>
          <l>Here is Content, and sure in that alone </l>
          <l>Lies all the happiness Man can desire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e16600">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <l>Most Reverend Sir, you shew such wondrous goodness, </l>
          <l>We never shall have Power to recompense, </l>
          <l>But oh forgive us if our weighty griefs, </l>
          <l>Too heavy to be born, pull down this sadness. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e16660">
          <speaker>Tac. </speaker>
          <p>Alas, Cesario! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e16700">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <p>Ha! thou knowst me sure. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e16730">
          <speaker>Tac. </speaker>
          <p>As thou didst once, thy wretched Brother Tachmas. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e16770">Discovers himself. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e16780">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <l>By Heaven and Earth, by all that we call sacred, </l>
          <l>'Tis he; my Brother. Oh let me thus Clasp thee, </l>
          <l>Crush thee into my heart, my dearest Tachmas. </l>
          <l>Methinks I hold half Heaven when I embrace thee. </l>
          <l>See my Urania: now if thou shed'st tears, </l>
          <l>Let'em be tears of Joy to see my Brother, </l>
          <l>Banisht from Naples by thy Cruel Father, </l>
          <l>For killing his base, cringing, fawning Favourite. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e16910">
          <speaker>Ura. </speaker>
          <l>I Joy to see the Brother of Cesario, though in affliction. </l>
          <l>Oh my dearest Lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e16960">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <l>How does my Love? Methinks I see </l>
          <l>A sickly fading on thy lovely Cheeks, </l>
          <pb n="25" xml:id="ep000683-017-b"/>
          <l>A languid paleness on those drooping Roses, </l>
          <l>As thou wou'dst sink beneath the weight thou bear'st. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e17020">
          <speaker>Ura. </speaker>
          <l>Indeed, Cesario, I am wondrous faint, </l>
          <l>My weary'd Limbs, and my long sleepless Eyes, </l>
          <l>The Nights keen Blasts, and all my frights and fears, </l>
          <l>Have press'd a little rudely on my health; </l>
          <l>And this too tender Frame bends down before 'em. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e17100">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <l>And all this for Cesario, Curst Cesario, </l>
          <l>The Impious Fatal Cause of all thy Sufferings, </l>
          <l>The Atlas Load of thy o'er-burthening woes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e17170">
          <speaker>Ura. </speaker>
          <l>Oh hold, this is too much to hear and live, </l>
          <l>Shake not your Peace for me, that shock will sink me; </l>
          <l>For I can bear all Sorrows, but Cesario's. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e17230">
          <speaker>Tac. </speaker>
          <l>Dear, Faithful Pair. </l>
          <l>Were all Hearts join'd like these, the Erring World </l>
          <l>Would shake her guilt off, with her blushing shame, </l>
          <l>And the revolving Age of gold return. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e17290">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <l>My Friend and Brother, my Beloved, kind Tachmas, </l>
          <l>This fainting sweetness wants thy helping care: </l>
          <l>Your Roots and Water are not for her diet, </l>
          <l>Is there no way to purchase other food? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e17360">
          <speaker>Tac. </speaker>
          <l>Hard by there is a little Neighbouring Village, </l>
          <l>Where we may be supplied with necessaries. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e17400">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <l>Droop not, fair Flower, since we may yet find Peace. </l>
          <l>Though now we're like the first unhappy pair, </l>
          <l>Cast from that Paradise where once we were, </l>
          <l>Like Fugitives banisht our native home, </l>
          <l>And destin'd through unpeopled Worlds to roam: </l>
          <l>Yet we may hope a smiling Morn more fair, </l>
          <l>For sure, (to banish all unjust dispair) </l>
          <l>Such truth as thine is Heavens peculiar care. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e17500">Ex. omnes. </stage>
        <trailer>The End of the Third Act. </trailer>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="ep000683-e17520">
        <pb n="26" xml:id="ep000683-018-a"/>
        <head>ACT IV. SCENE I. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e17540">Urania, Sola. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e17560">
          <speaker>Ura. </speaker>
          <l>HOW long, my Dear Cesario, shall I want </l>
          <l>Thy presence, to drive all these troubles hence▪ </l>
          <l>My Soul is heavy, and my Eye-lids feel </l>
          <l>A pressing weight that fain won'd shut out light, </l>
          <l>And let in Peace; hush my lull'd Sorrows silent, </l>
          <l>And give my feeble strength a short repose. </l>
          <l>More Clouds do gather round my Eyes, 'tis strange, </l>
          <l>I am not us'd to be inclin'd to sleep, </l>
          <l>Whilst the day shines. I'll take what nature offers, </l>
          <l>It may discharge my waking Melancholy; <stage xml:id="ep000683-e17690">Sits down. </stage>
          </l>
          <l>I feel it gently slide upon my Sences: </l>
          <l>Take me you Heavenly Rulers to your Care, </l>
          <l>And let my Dreams be nothing but Cesario. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e17740">Lies down. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e17750">Enter Ferdinand, and Oswell, Attendants. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e17780">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>I cannot find 'em, sure the Prince of Darkness, </l>
          <l>Or some of his Commission'd Fiends, have snatcht 'em </l>
          <l>From the Orb of Light to hide their guilty shames </l>
          <l>In his own sable shades, black as their Crimes: </l>
          <l>There's not a Corner in this spreading Realm, </l>
          <l>But we have searcht with strictest diligence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e17860">
          <speaker>Osw. </speaker>
          <p>My Lord, here lies a Woman, Dead I think. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e17890">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>A Woman, ha! By Heaven and Earth 'tis she, </l>
          <l>And wrapt in the dull leaden Arms of sleep. </l>
          <l>But where's Cesario? Where lies he Conceal'd? </l>
          <l>I've happiness by halves, if he escapes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e17960">
          <speaker>Osw. </speaker>
          <l>He cannot be far off, 'twere best, my Lord, </l>
          <l>Behind yon Thicket to conceal your self, </l>
          <l>Till you have got 'em both within your Snave. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e18010">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>You Counsel well. Let us a while retire. </l>
          <l>By Heaven, I keep a Jubilee within me; </l>
          <l>Riot in Joy, and Revel in delight, </l>
          <pb n="27" xml:id="ep000683-018-b"/>
          <l>To think how bravely I shall take revenge. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e18070">Ex. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e18080">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>Defend me Heaven! Do I dream still, or wake? <stage xml:id="ep000683-e18110">Uran. wakes. </stage>
          </l>
          <l>What horrid Visions have appear'd before me! </l>
          <l>Methought I saw Cesario gash'd with Wounds, </l>
          <l>And Ferdinand all o'er dy'd in his Blood, </l>
          <l>Whilst my Unkind and Cruel Father stood </l>
          <l>Triumphing over him, and with a smile, </l>
          <l>Rejoic'd to see his Soul and Body part. </l>
          <l>But why shou'd I give credit to a Dream, </l>
          <l>An airy Vision fram'd by 〈◊〉 fancy, </l>
          <l>Deluding my weak sence with 〈◊〉 and shadow? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e18240">Enter Cesario with a Basket of Meat, Tachmas with Drink. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e18270">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <l>Look up, Urania, cast thy Sorrow off, </l>
          <l>See, I have brought thee Food to cheer thy Spirits. <stage xml:id="ep000683-e18320">They all sit down. </stage>
          </l>
          <l>Angels protect her, with how much delight </l>
          <l>She feeds upon the homely fare of Peasants. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e18350">Enter <hi>Ferdinand, Oswell</hi>, and Attendants. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e18370">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>Do you not want Attendants to your Banquet? </l>
          <l>Nay let not us disturb you, we are Friends, </l>
          <l>And only come to take repast with you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e18420">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <l>Curst Fate! <stage xml:id="ep000683-e18450">The Guards seize Cesario and Tachmas. </stage>
          </l>
          <l>Surpriz'd, Unarm'd! and made so tame a Sacrifice! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e18490">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <p>Now, now, I see too late my Dreams were true. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e18520">
          <speaker>Tach. </speaker>
          <l>Oh, Sir, I beg you wou'd not let me suffer. </l>
          <l>Alas, I'm Innocent, my Charity, </l>
          <l>Oblig'd me to assist the miserable▪ </l>
          <l>Let not your Vengeance fall on an old Man, </l>
          <l>But spare my Age. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e18590">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>Thou art below my anger. </l>
          <l>Be gone, and keep thy Life, not worth my taking. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e18630">
          <speaker>Tach. </speaker>
          <l>How has my Hypocrite Tongue belyed my Heart. </l>
          <l>Think not, mistaken Tyrant, that the fear <stage xml:id="ep000683-e18670">Aside. </stage>
          </l>
          <l>Of Death, makes me so poor a Suppliant. </l>
          <l>When I descend thus low, I only stoop, </l>
          <l>To borrow Life, to lend it my Cesario. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e18720">Ex. Tach. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e18740">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <p>Now, Sir, for you. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e18770">To Cesario. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e18790">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <l>Me! I despise thy rage. </l>
          <pb n="28" xml:id="ep000683-019-a"/>
          <l>Let all the Tortures Malice can invent </l>
          <l>Be laid on me, I can endure 'em all; </l>
          <l>But do not dare to touch that Angel-Form, </l>
          <l>Whose unexampled Vertue is alone </l>
          <l>Enough t'atone for all her Sexes Frailty. </l>
          <l>Take heed how you provoke the Gods, by hurting </l>
          <l>That brighest, nearest Image of themselves. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e18890">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>Young angry Sir, spend not your Breath in vain: </l>
          <l>Keep it to curse the Hour thou saw'st that Face: </l>
          <l>I have a Scourge for thee, I have, bold Lord, </l>
          <l>Fierce as the Vengeance of an angry God, </l>
          <l>And swifter than a Pestilence; for You, <stage xml:id="ep000683-e18960">To Uran. </stage>
          </l>
          <l>In whom I once had treasur'd up my Soul, </l>
          <l>You're in my Power; my Love is turn'd to Hate, </l>
          <l>And thou, before thy Face, shalt see her die. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e19010">To Cesario. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e19030">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>O bloody Tyrant! aim your Rage at me; </l>
          <l>Send me to Ruine, kill me, wrack me, burn me; </l>
          <l>Do any thing, so you'll but save her Life: </l>
          <l>Think, when you murder that Celestial Form, </l>
          <l>You wound all Mankind at the dismal Blow; </l>
          <l>Not only all the mourning Globe, the Gods </l>
          <l>Themselves will suffer when such Vertue bleeds. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e19120">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <p>Most amorous Raptures. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e19150">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>Do not touch one Hair </l>
          <l>Of that dear Gallant, God-like Man; on mine, </l>
          <l>My Head alone pour all your impious Vengeance. </l>
          <l>Live, my kind, dearest Lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e19210">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>Not Fate shall save him, </l>
          <l>Nor Heaven it self keep thee from my Revenge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e19250">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>How I disdain thy Rage, 〈◊〉 shew thy Malice; </l>
          <l>Kill me as barbarously as thou art base: </l>
          <l>But as I die, I'll send my last kind Looks, </l>
          <l>Sighs, Prayers and Life into Cesario's Eyes; </l>
          <l>Nay, though you scatter all my sprinkled Ashes </l>
          <l>Around the World, each Atome of my Dust, </l>
          <l>Shall find a Soul, and fly into his Bosome. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e19350">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <p>O mighty Love! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e19380">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <l>So brave! nay then I'll find a means to tame you. </l>
          <l>Attend me to my Chariot with the Princess, </l>
          <l>But to your Horse's Tayl tye fast that Slave, </l>
          <l>And drag 〈◊〉 to the King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e19440">
          <pb n="29" xml:id="ep000683-019-b"/>
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>Hold! Hold! yet hold! </l>
          <l>You do not sure mean this Barbarity: </l>
          <l>How can you look on him, and be so cruel? </l>
          <l>See how he stands like a tame suffering Saint, </l>
          <l>And smiles i'th' midst of all his Miseries. </l>
          <l>If not for him, shew pity then to me, </l>
          <l>And though he be your Prisoner use him nobly. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e19530">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <p>I'm deaf to all Intreaties. Drag him forward. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e19560">Ex. Omnes. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e19570">The King discover'd melancholy, some Attendants standing by him; </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e19590">A Song, and Symphony of Musick within. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e19600">
          <lg type="song">
            <head>SONG. </head>
            <byline>Written by a Person of Quality. </byline>
            <lg n="1">
              <head>1. </head>
              <l>LONG time, alas! our Mournful Swains </l>
              <l>Have been with Fears oppress'd: </l>
              <l>And pensive walk'd along the Plains, </l>
              <l>Pitying their Flocks distress. </l>
              <l>Their Fences all were open laid, </l>
              <l>No Ewes their Lambs cou'd keep, </l>
              <l>Foxes and Rav'nous Wolves were made </l>
              <l>The Guardians of their Sheep. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
              <head>2. </head>
              <l>Pan was not worshipp'd as before, </l>
              <l>But saw his learned Rules, </l>
              <l>And Iustice all turn'd out of door </l>
              <l>By Arbitrary Fools. </l>
              <l>Phillis for Pan her Charms engag'd </l>
              <l>But cou'd no Pity draw. </l>
              <l>They sacrific'd to Pagan rage, </l>
              <l>Phillis as well as Law. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
              <pb n="30" xml:id="ep000683-020-a"/>
              <head>3. </head>
              <l>At length came Strephon on the Plain, </l>
              <l>At whose dread Sight did run, </l>
              <l>And vanish each Tyrannick Swain </l>
              <l>Like Mists before the Sun. </l>
              <l>Then his Brave Head with Garlands Crown, </l>
              <l>And grudge him not your Wealth. </l>
              <l>Ah Shepherds! as you prize your own </l>
              <l>Pray for great Strephon's Health. </l>
            </lg>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e20010">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>No more; no more; cease all your Harmony, </l>
          <l>It suits not with a Wretch so curst as I: </l>
          <l>Yet why, unpitying Heaven, this hard Decree! </l>
          <l>There might have been some milder Doom for me. </l>
          <l>Why was my Daughter </l>
          <l>Destin'd to punish him who gave her Breath, </l>
          <l>And by her Flight to seal a Father's Death? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e20100">Enter Fabio hastily. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e20120">
          <speaker>Fabio. </speaker>
          <p>Where's the King? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e20150">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <p>Here; what portends thy Haste and busie Countenance? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e20180">
          <speaker>Fab. </speaker>
          <l>Haste, my good Lord! </l>
          <l>When Fortune points me out the Instrument, </l>
          <l>And happy Messenger to please my King; </l>
          <l>Do I not ought to fly like Mercury, </l>
          <l>And pour the Joy into his Royal Ears. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e20260">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Has thy Intelligence brought me any Knowledge </l>
          <l>Of Ferdinand? Speak, is Urania found? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e20320">
          <speaker>Fab. </speaker>
          <l>The News I bring my gracious Lord, </l>
          <l>Concerns the Prince, and how my Heart flows o'er, </l>
          <l>That I am pointed out by Heaven, </l>
          <l>The first, and happy Messenger. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e20380">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <p>Proceed, and we'll reward thee. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e20410">
          <speaker>Fab. </speaker>
          <l>Reward, alas! </l>
          <l>All my Ambition aims but at your Favour; </l>
          <l>My Soul was never Mercenary: </l>
          <l>It is my Duty to wear out my Life </l>
          <l>In Services for you and the whole State, </l>
          <l>Whereof, although I am no able Member— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e20490">
          <pb n="31" xml:id="ep000683-020-b"/>
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <p>He's mad. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e20520">
          <speaker>Fab. </speaker>
          <p>It is with Joy then, my good Lord. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e20550">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <p>Tell me thy News in short, or thy Life pays for't. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e20580">
          <speaker>Fab. </speaker>
          <l>Alas, my Life is the least thing to be minded: </l>
          <l>He is no faithful Subject would refuse </l>
          <l>To kill his Wife and Children, after that </l>
          <l>To hang himself to do his King a Service. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e20640">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Villain, why dost thou wrack my Expectation? </l>
          <l>Answer me quickly without Circumstance, </l>
          <l>Where is the Prince? be brief, or— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e20690">
          <speaker>Fab. </speaker>
          <p>The Prince! I know not, my good Lord. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e20720">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Traytor! didst not prepare me to expect </l>
          <l>News of the Prince, pronouncing thy self happy </l>
          <l>In being the Messenger? Is he in health, answer to that? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e20770">
          <speaker>Fab. </speaker>
          <p>Indeed, my Lord, I know not. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e20800">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Hang up the Slave; I shall become the Scorn </l>
          <l>Of my own Subjects. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e20840">
          <speaker>Fab. </speaker>
          <l>But, with your Royal Licence, I am able </l>
          <l>To produce those that do. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e20880">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <p>Where? whom? speak that, and quickly save thy Life. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e20910">
          <speaker>Fab. </speaker>
          <p>He waits without, Sir. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e20940">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <p>Haste, and bring him in. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e20970">Ex. Fab. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e20990">Re-enter Fabio, with Oswell. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e21020">
          <speaker>Oswell. </speaker>
          <l>Health to the King: the Prince, my Master, Sir, </l>
          <l>With fair Urania, and the General, </l>
          <l>I left within less than a League o'th' City, </l>
          <l>And came before to bring the joyful Tidings. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e21090">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Are they then found, thou welcome Harbinger? </l>
          <l>Seiz'd and brought back, Oh! let the Satyrs dance it; </l>
          <l>The sweet Birds sing it; let the Winds be wanton; </l>
          <l>And, as they softly with an Evening Whisper, </l>
          <l>Steal through the curled Locks of the lofty Woods, </l>
          <l>Let 'em, in their sweet Language, seem to murmur, </l>
          <l>This was the Day that Crown'd a King's Revenge. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e21180">Enter Messenger. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e21200">
          <speaker>Messeng. </speaker>
          <p>My Lord, Prince Ferdinand. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e21240">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Conduct him in. </l>
          <pb n="32" xml:id="ep000683-021-a"/>
          <l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000683-e21280">Enter Ferdinand. </stage>Thou welcom'st Guest my Court yet ever harbour'd: </l>
          <l>Oh I want Power to recompense thy Care. </l>
          <l>Where be the Fugitives? Speak, Ferdinand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e21330">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <p>They wait without, my Lord. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e21360">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <p>Bring 'em in. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e21390">Exit Fabio. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e21410">Re-enter with Cesario and Urania guarded; Cesario and Urania kneel. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e21460">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>With my Soul trembling, like a fearful Criminal, </l>
          <l>With Terrour struck at sight of his great Judge: </l>
          <l>Behold the wretched, poor Cesario falls, </l>
          <l>Not to beg Life, since Death I have deserv'd, </l>
          <l>But that you'd Mercy shew to this dear Innocence, </l>
          <l>A Virgin, though my Bride. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e21550">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>O Royal Sir! </l>
          <l>I kneel to you, as Heaven when I offend, </l>
          <l>Not to beg Life, unless my dear Cesario, </l>
          <l>By your Consent, be given to my Arms. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e21620">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Rise! </l>
          <l>I've heard you both; and, Sir, your Suit will grant; </l>
          <l>Death thou hast merited, Death thou shalt have: </l>
          <l>Thy Torments, by degrees, shall rise to kill thee; </l>
          <l>And what will plague thy Soul, thy Latest Gasp </l>
          <l>Shall see Urania married to this Prince. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e21710">
          <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
          <l>It is a studied Tyranny; but, Sir, </l>
          <l>All this, and more, I'd bear, might she live happy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e21750">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>Live, my Cesario I Canst thou think I'll live? </l>
          <l>Live in the Arms of him my Soul abhors! </l>
          <l>No, cruel Father, Nature shall not bind me: </l>
          <l>I will forget 'twas you that gave me Life, </l>
          <l>And, in despight of Duty, be his Bride: </l>
          <l>We'll mount above, far, far beyond your reach; </l>
          <l>Where in a glorious Clowd, we'll Arm in Arm, </l>
          <l>Look down and smile with Scorn on that gay nothing. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e21860">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Furies and Death then I will quite put off, </l>
          <l>The name of Father, take as little notice </l>
          <l>Thou art my Off-spring, as the surly North </l>
          <pb n="33" xml:id="ep000683-021-b"/>
          <l>Does of the Snow, which when it has engender'd, </l>
          <l>It's wild Breath scatters through the Earth forgotten. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e21930">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <p>Sir, she's your Daughter. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e21960">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Do not call her so. </l>
          <l>There's not one drop of my Blood in her Veins. </l>
          <l>She makes her self a Bastard, and deserves </l>
          <l>To be cut off like a disorder'd Branch, </l>
          <l>Disgracing the fair Tree from whence she sprung. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e22030">
          <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
          <p>But yet, my Lord. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e22060">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>I'm deaf, inexorable as Seas </l>
          <l>To th'Prayers of Mariners: </l>
          <l>Oswell, be't your care, </l>
          <l>To lodge that hated Slave in a dark Dungeon; </l>
          <l>And confine her close Prisoner to her Chamber. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e22140">Ex. <hi>King, Ferd. </hi>Attended. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e22160">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <l>Is this for Kindness, or for Cruelty? </l>
          <l>Ah no, he gives me this short moment's sight, </l>
          <l>That I may lose my Heaven with greater torment. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e22210">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>No, my Cesario, we'll both die together: </l>
          <l>For when thou'rt gone, oh what a weary Load </l>
          <l>Will Life be to me! </l>
          <l>But when you see me die, will you be kind? </l>
          <l>And pity my hard fate, when you behold </l>
          <l>My panting Breast laid open, and that Heart, </l>
          <l>Where my dear Lord once Reign'd, all torn and mangled? </l>
          <l>Will you look pale, and with a trembling sigh, </l>
          <l>Let a kind Pearl fall trickling from your Eye? </l>
          <l>Say, will you do all this for poor Urania? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e22350">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <l>Not do all this for thee; If th' inraged King </l>
          <l>Will wreak his barbarous Vengeance in thy Veins, </l>
          <l>Thy sacred Veins, and the unthinking Gods </l>
          <l>Dare see it done; shall not I mourn for thee? </l>
          <l>Doubt not that pious Tribute of my Eyes. </l>
          <l>Shall not my Dew fall at thy setting Sun? </l>
          <l>Not weep to see thee bleed! I'll make my Eyes </l>
          <l>Start from their Spheres, to view the killing object: </l>
          <l>And when thy sweetness draws near to Heaven, </l>
          <l>My fainting, bleeding Heart, </l>
          <l>Shall just keep Life enough to break with thine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e22480">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>My kindest Lord, now with full Tides of Joy, </l>
          <l>I can meet death, since he has made me thine. </l>
          <l>My Soul's all Rapture, all Delight; grim Death, </l>
          <pb n="34" xml:id="ep000683-022-a"/>
          <l>Whose ghastly Visage frights the trembling World, </l>
          <l>To me's all Gay, and with a charming Smile, </l>
          <l>Does with sweet Wreaths and Flowery Garlands come, </l>
          <l>My Bridal Pleasures Blossom on my Tomb. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e22570">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <l>Now you transport my ravisht sense too high, </l>
          <l>The worth of Ages, and thy Sex's glory, </l>
          <l>Is all summ'd up in thee; but must you die! </l>
          <l>Must this Celestial Light fall like a Meteor! </l>
          <l>This blooming Spring fade like a wither'd Autumn! </l>
          <l>Must this fair Book of Life, writ by Heaven's Hand, </l>
          <l>The Legend of a God, be all defac'd? </l>
          <l>And must I see it done! oh my Urania, </l>
          <l>I never was a Toward till this moment. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e22690">
          <speaker>Osw. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord, we wait too long; the King Commanded </l>
          <l>The Princess to her Chamber, you to Prison. </l>
          <l>We must obey him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e22740">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <l>'Tis indeed your duty. </l>
          <l>Resist not Destiny. My Love obey him; </l>
          <l>And leave Cesario with his griefs. Farewel. </l>
          <l>Farewel, for ever, my belov'd Urania, </l>
          <l>Till we shall meet again above the Stars. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e22830">
          <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord, my Life, my Soul, my All, Farewel. </l>
          <l>Grief choaks my words, and I can say no more. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e22870">Ex. <hi>Ura. Osw.</hi>
        </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000683-e22890">
          <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
          <l>Come; Gentlemen, now lead me to my Fate, </l>
          <l>For Death's the only thing I wish to find. </l>
          <l>I think there are some here have follow'd me: </l>
          <l>Where I have sought him oft, but ne'r fled from him. </l>
          <l>But it is past, <hi>Cesario▪ </hi>now's no more. </l>
          <l>My Fame, Life, Honour's gone: yet what is Death? </l>
          <l>To think no more: and Honours but a Breath. </l>
          <l>But my Urania's lost! nought could provoke </l>
          <l>My Soul to pain like that dire killing stroke. </l>
          <l>Oh that last Wound has toucht so near my Heart, </l>
          <l>That Fate's whole Quiver wants another Dart. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000683-e23040">Ex. Omn. </stage>
        <trailer>The End of the Fourth Act. </trailer>
      </div>
      <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="ep000683-e23060">
        <pb n="35" xml:id="ep000683-022-b"/>
        <head>ACT V. </head>
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000683-e23080">
          <head>SCENE I. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e23100">Scene, <hi>A Field</hi>. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e23120">Enter <hi>Tachmas, Vincentio, Sigismond</hi>, and Souldiers. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e23140">
            <speaker>Vin. </speaker>
            <l>MY Fellow Souldiers, why we're thus met here, </l>
            <l>This noble Youth, the brave, the valiant Tachmas, </l>
            <l>The banisht Brother to your lov'd Cesario, </l>
            <l>Can best inform you; my Heart swells with grief, </l>
            <l>And cannot tell the story; speak, my Lord, </l>
            <l>And be assur'd, you're amongst Men, whose Souls </l>
            <l>Do claim an equal share in your Misfortunes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e23250">
            <speaker>Tach. </speaker>
            <l>Then to you Souldiers, props of this great Kingdom, </l>
            <l>Behold I come uncall'd from Banishment, </l>
            <l>And give my Life into your noble hands, </l>
            <l>I come a Tale of horrour to relate. </l>
            <l>I come to shew when Monarchs sleep in Peace, </l>
            <l>What worthless trifles they esteem poor Souldiers, </l>
            <l>May I have leave to speak? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e23340">
            <speaker>Sould. </speaker>
            <p>Yes, Speak, speak Tachmas. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e23380">
            <speaker>Tach. </speaker>
            <l>Alas, I fear the subject is ungrateful, </l>
            <l>But yet it does concern the general good. </l>
            <l>That Soul of Valour, great Cesario, he, </l>
            <l>Who has, like Lightning, purg'd the air of Naples, </l>
            <l>From all the hot Infections Foreign War </l>
            <l>Cou'd threaten, and shall he </l>
            <l>Whose very name was great as Fate it self, </l>
            <l>To all his Enemies, now basely die? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e23500">
            <speaker>Sigis. </speaker>
            <p>Die! no, he's damn'd that dares but mutter it. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e23530">
            <speaker>Vin. </speaker>
            <l>If they who first occasion'd it were so, </l>
            <l>'Twou'd bring much Comfort to all honest Hearts. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e23570">
            <speaker>Tach. </speaker>
            <l>His Death, past all Redemption, is Concluded. </l>
            <l>His Death to whom they owe their Lives. Oh Souldiers, </l>
            <l>You've seen i' th' heat and bravery of a Fight, </l>
            <l>How he'd cheer up his faint, dishearten'd Troops; </l>
            <l>Even when his Body seem'd but all one Wound, </l>
            <pb n="36" xml:id="ep000683-023-a"/>
            <l>That it appear'd a little Island, Circled </l>
            <l>Round with the purple Deluge of his Blood, </l>
            <l>Who when Wars Queristers, the big-mouth'd Drums, </l>
            <l>And surly Trumpets, sung his Armies Dirge, </l>
            <l>That fatal Musick swell'd his sprightly Sence, </l>
            <l>More than soft Hymns at Nuptials. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e23700">
            <speaker>Sigis. </speaker>
            <l>Sir, His Glories </l>
            <l>Are so well known to us, we need not urge </l>
            <l>the'repetition, but 'tis past my thoughts, </l>
            <l>Why on the sudden he shou'd be compell'd </l>
            <l>To yield his Life up. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e23770">
            <speaker>Vin. </speaker>
            <l>Nay, when we return'd </l>
            <l>From our last Victory, when we expected </l>
            <l>He shou'd have had a double Triumph given▪ </l>
            <l>In honour of our Victories, the King, </l>
            <l>And his wise State, receiv'd us as their Foes, </l>
            <l>What cou'd they mean by that? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e23850">
            <speaker>Tach. </speaker>
            <l>I'll tell you, Sir. </l>
            <l>There is in Princes Courts a lean-fac'd Monster </l>
            <l>Term'd Envy (Reigning in Unworthy Breasts,) </l>
            <l>To Fames Heroick Sons, such as can cringe </l>
            <l>With subtle motion to their Prince's smiles, </l>
            <l>Adore his Footsteps, and his awful Nod●, </l>
            <l>And can like Asps instil into his Ears, </l>
            <l>A sweet, yet killing Venom. These thin Souls, </l>
            <l>When the blunt Warriour has on Piles of Wounds </l>
            <l>Built up his Countries Safety, whisper, Beware </l>
            <l>In time, my Lord, least he do grow too great. </l>
            <l>So the poor Souldier is in time of Peace, </l>
            <l>Stript of those Glories purchast in the War. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e24000">
            <speaker>Vin </speaker>
            <p>But Sir, why must he die? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e24030">
            <speaker>Tach. </speaker>
            <l>Only for loving of his Monarch's Daughter. </l>
            <l>Tell me, Is that a Crime deserving Death? </l>
            <l>Speak, if it be, and I will plead no more. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e24080">
            <speaker>Vin. </speaker>
            <l>A Crime! 'Udsdeath, my Lord, he does deserve her: </l>
            <l>H'as bravely fought, and bravely conquer'd for her. </l>
            <l>Speak Fellow Souldiers, shall these Court Mushrooms, </l>
            <l>That live in Peace, and Riotous Luxury, </l>
            <l>Deny a fasting Souldier one poor snap, </l>
            <l>After long abstinence? It may not be: </l>
            <l>And for your foreign Prince, your Ferdinand, </l>
            <pb n="37" xml:id="ep000683-023-b"/>
            <l>We'll spoil his Vaulting, ev'ry Man a Limb, </l>
            <l>Will quickly cool his Courage. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e24200">
            <speaker>Tach. </speaker>
            <l>Yet, Souldiers, tho' I beg you'd save your General, </l>
            <l>Preserve your Loyalties. Oh, for bear the King, </l>
            <l>And his dear sacred Person reverence, </l>
            <l>As if he were a God, and dwelt on Earth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e24260">
            <speaker>Vincen. </speaker>
            <l>We'll save the King and General; but if </l>
            <l>They'll take my Counsel, hang up Ferdinand. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e24310">
            <speaker>Souldiers. </speaker>
            <l>Ay, ay, well said, noble Colonel, Long live </l>
            <l>Our King and General, and a Halter for Ferdinand. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e24360">
            <speaker>Tach. </speaker>
            <l>Let me imbrace you all, all to my Bosom, </l>
            <l>You Limbs of Mars. Who when Fate calls you hence, </l>
            <l>Will leave behind each man a Monument, </l>
            <l>Which shall for Ages last with this Inscription; </l>
            <l>The Sons of Honour, Naples great Preservers. </l>
            <l>Sure to such Men belong those mighty Names, </l>
            <l>Who sav'd their General, yet preserv'd their Fames. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e24470">Ex. Omn. </stage>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="ep000683-e24480">
          <head>SCENE II. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e24500">Urania discover'd Reading. A Song within. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e24520">
            <lg type="song">
              <head>SONG. </head>
              <byline>Written by a Person of Quality. <hi>Sung by </hi>Mrs. Boteler. </byline>
              <lg n="1">
                <head>1. </head>
                <l>COrinna, in the Bloom of Youth, </l>
                <l>Was coy to ev'ry Lover; </l>
                <l>Regardless of the tend'rest Truth, </l>
                <l>No soft Complaints cou'd move her: </l>
                <l>Mankind was hers, and at her Feet </l>
                <l>Lay prostrate and adoring, </l>
                <l>The Witty, Valiant, Rich and Great▪ </l>
                <l>Alike in vain imploring. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg n="2">
                <pb n="38" xml:id="ep000683-024-a"/>
                <head>2. </head>
                <l>But now grown Old she wou'd repair </l>
                <l>The Loss of Time and Pleasure; </l>
                <l>With willing Looks, and wanton Air, </l>
                <l>Inviting ev'ry Gazer: </l>
                <l>But Love's a Summer-Flower, that dies </l>
                <l>With the first Weathers Changing. </l>
                <l>The Lover, like the Swallow, flies </l>
                <l>From Sun to Sun still ranging. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg n="3">
                <head>3. </head>
                <l>Cloe, let this Example move </l>
                <l>Your foolish Heart to Reason: </l>
                <l>Youth is the proper Time for Love, </l>
                <l>And Age is Vertues Season. </l>
              </lg>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e24850">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <l>In vain, alas! you strive to give me Ease: </l>
            <l>Musick to lull my Pains, dull soothing Flattery! </l>
            <l>The pressing weight that hangs upon my Soul, </l>
            <l>Nought but my dear Cesario can remove: </l>
            <l>All Props are weak where the Foundation's Love. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e24930">Enter Oswell. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e24950">
            <speaker>Osw. </speaker>
            <l>O Royal Mourner, lovely in thy Tears! </l>
            <l>Thus low I fall to beg a blushing Pardon, </l>
            <l>For the sad Story I am doom'd to tell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e25000">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <l>How, my Heart trembles! speak, what is't, Sir? </l>
            <l>If there be yet a greater Grief in store, </l>
            <l>Speak it, and kill Urania with the Sound. </l>
            <l>Yes, Oswell, play the generous Executioner: </l>
            <l>Give me the last kind, finishing Stroke of Mercy, </l>
            <l>And end my lingring Torments at a Blow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e25100">
            <speaker>Osw. </speaker>
            <l>The Gods, and all good Powers guard your Life; </l>
            <l>And O that I had dy'd e'er liv'd Commission'd, </l>
            <l>For this ungrateful Charge: doom'd to pronounce </l>
            <l>The only Sound can make Urania wretched. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e25170">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <p>I guess the Horrour, yet I fear to know it. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e25200">
            <speaker>Osw. </speaker>
            <l>And I, thus trembling, stand and fear to utter it, </l>
            <l>Yet you must hear it, yes, the fatal Sound </l>
            <pb n="39" xml:id="ep000683-024-b"/>
            <l>Must reach your Ears, and some curst Tongue must tell you </l>
            <l>Your dear Cesario's murder'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e25270">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <p>Murder'd! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e25300">
            <speaker>Osw. </speaker>
            <p>Yes, murder'd by the King's Command. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e25330">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <p>Enough, Oh cruel Father! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e25360">
            <speaker>Osw. </speaker>
            <l>The Prince, my Master, toucht with his long▪ Sufferings, </l>
            <l>Heard, but too late, of the King's harsh Decree, </l>
            <l>And flew, with Eagle's speed, to stop the Blow, </l>
            <l>But Oh too late! their bloody butchering hands, </l>
            <l>Already were imbru'd in his warm Blood; </l>
            <l>His last words pardon'd his unhappy Rival, </l>
            <l>And as o'th' Ground they lay claspt Arm in Arm, </l>
            <l>Like faithful Friends, they mourn'd each others Fortune. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e25460">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <p>Oh speak no more! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e25490">
            <speaker>Osw. </speaker>
            <l>Yes, I am bound to speak: </l>
            <l>The Prince, as by Cesario's side he lay, </l>
            <l>With truest Tears bathing his bleeding Wounds, </l>
            <l>And, with these words, thrown in like precious Balm, </l>
            <l>Had almost stopt the Journey of his Soul. </l>
            <l>Live, live, (said he) Urania is thy own, </l>
            <l>To make Atonement for thy mighty Wrongs, </l>
            <l>I'll quit my Love. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e25610">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <p>Dissembling Infidel! </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e25640">Aside. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e25650">
            <speaker>Osw. </speaker>
            <l>But when he saw his Veins did ebb too fast, </l>
            <l>And Life flew swift away, he snatcht his Sword, </l>
            <l>And, e'er my Hand cou'd reach to stop the Blow, </l>
            <l>Plung'd it in's Breast, but did not reach his Heart; </l>
            <l>Which when Cesario saw, he graspt his Hands, </l>
            <l>Begging that he would live, and call'd him Friend, </l>
            <l>Go to that widow'd Fair, (said he) the poor Urania, </l>
            <l>But first prepare her for the dismal Story: </l>
            <l>Tell her 'tis now too late for her to grieve; </l>
            <l>And as she ever lov'd her dying Husband, </l>
            <l>Bid her obey the King, who, though unkind, </l>
            <l>Is still my Sovereign, and her Royal Father. </l>
            <l>More he'd have said, but hasty Death rush'd in, </l>
            <l>And his last words bequeath'd you Ferdinand's. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e25840">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <l>Ferdinand's, did he, Cou'd he call me his, </l>
            <l>My unkind Lord, didst thou then think I'd live </l>
            <l>After thy Death, and live within his Arms, <stage xml:id="ep000683-e25900">Aside. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>The Cursed Author of our Cruel Fortunes: </l>
            <pb n="40" xml:id="ep000683-025-a"/>
            <l>Though with a painted shew of Treacherous Grief, </l>
            <l>He cast a mist before thy dying Eyes. <stage xml:id="ep000683-e25940">Aside. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>The Masque's too thin for mine— Pray Sir, retire— <stage xml:id="ep000683-e25960">To Osw. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>And tell Prince Ferdinand, 'twill not be long, </l>
            <l>Ere I am happy in his love— or Heavens— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e26010">Aside. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e26020">
            <speaker>Osw. </speaker>
            <l>I shall obey your Highness— Oh true Woman— <stage xml:id="ep000683-e26050">Aside. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>The living still are valu'd, not the dead—— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e26070">Ex. Osw. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e26090">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <l>It is decreed, I must not stay behind. </l>
            <l>Yes, yes my Father, thou sha't see thy Daughter, </l>
            <l>When all her Veins stream with a purple source; </l>
            <l>Then he may pity me, and shed one tear; </l>
            <l>Sure Nature will compel him to do that. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e26160">Enter Ardelia. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e26180">
            <speaker>Ard. </speaker>
            <l>Madam, the King Commanded me to wait you </l>
            <l>Straight to the Palace. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e26220">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <l>I'll attend his Call. </l>
            <l>Now my Cesario, in what e'er bright Region, </l>
            <l>The Mansion of the blest, where Martyr'd truth, </l>
            <l>And faithful Love in wreaths of Glory shine, </l>
            <l>I'll find thee out, and mix my Soul with thine. </l>
            <l>Think not mistaken King, Cesario's Grave, </l>
            <l>The narrow Gulph of parting Worlds between us, </l>
            <l>Shall be a bar to love resolv'd like mine▪ </l>
            <l>Yes, Dearest Martyr, 'tis by Love decreed, </l>
            <l>That thy Urania at thy Stake shall bleed; </l>
            <l>Since Faith and Truth such poor Rewards are given, </l>
            <l>What is deny'd on Earth, we'll seek in Heaven. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e26390">Ex. </stage>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="ep000683-e26400">
          <head>SCENE III. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e26420">A Prison. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e26430">Cesario discover'd on a Couch. Enter Ferdinand and Oswell. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e26470">
            <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
            <p>You think she may be won then? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e26500">
            <speaker>Osw. </speaker>
            <l>May, most Certain. </l>
            <l>Nay, Sir, you have her own Confession for't, </l>
            <pb n="41" xml:id="ep000683-025-b"/>
            <l>Her foolish Tongue in the last words dropt from her, </l>
            <l>Cou'd not forbear to tell me so; alas, </l>
            <l>What Woman ever yet admir'd the dead, </l>
            <l>When there were living Lovers to be found? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e26580">
            <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
            <l>Then he must die: Oswell, wait you without, </l>
            <l>And let none Enter here, unless the King. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e26630">
            <speaker>Osw. </speaker>
            <p>I shall obey your Orders. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e26660">Ex. Oswell. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e26680">Cesario <hi>Rises▪ </hi>
          </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e26700">
            <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
            <l>More Torments still! Why dost thou bring to plague me, </l>
            <l>The only Person of the World I hate? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e26740">
            <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
            <p>And why that Person of the World so hateful? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e26770">
            <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
            <l>Because that Person poorly entertains </l>
            <l>A sordid Soul within, which shames the Lodging. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e26810">
            <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
            <p>Bold Man! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e26840">
            <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
            <l>Yes, bolder Lord. Thou that darst act </l>
            <l>What Man would blush to think. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e26880">
            <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
            <p>Blush! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e26910">
            <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
            <l>Blush, false Greatness. </l>
            <l>Inglorious titled Wretch, Panthers and Leopards </l>
            <l>Are spotless to thy Stains, those kind Devourers, </l>
            <l>The Innocenter, honourabler Savages; </l>
            <l>They chase blood fairer than the treach'rous Ferdinand, </l>
            <l>Run down their hunted Prey in open Field, </l>
            <l>Not snare'em into toyls, mew'd up for Sacrifice, </l>
            <l>In Dungeon Walls, as thou hast done Cesario. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e27030">
            <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
            <l>Vile Arrogant, how Impudent is guilt? </l>
            <l>When with such Rude, and Villainous Reflections, </l>
            <l>Thou darst impeach the Justice of thy punishment. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e27080">
            <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
            <p>Justice, my bold Tormenter! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e27110">
            <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
            <l>Justice, Miscreant. </l>
            <l>The just reward of thy too bold Ambition. </l>
            <l>As well the tumbling Lucifer might challenge </l>
            <l>His Fall; call his Damnation Martyrdom, </l>
            <l>Plung'd in his Flames for his aspiring Pride, </l>
            <l>As thou in Chains for thine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e27200">
            <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
            <l>Infamous Tyrant, </l>
            <l>How poorly dost thou prop thy Impious Cause, </l>
            <l>And gild the Face of Butchery? Royal Hangman, </l>
            <l>Take thy Face hence, my persecuting Cerberus. </l>
            <l>Sure in the Grave I shall not rest in Peace, </l>
            <l>If Prisons cannot guard me from thy Malice. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e27290">
            <pb n="42" xml:id="ep000683-026-a"/>
            <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
            <l>Malice, alas, can'st think I bear thee Malice! </l>
            <l>Imperial brightness Envy at a shadow! </l>
            <l>Malign thee! yes, when Stars repine at gloe-Worms. </l>
            <l>Oh that thou stoodst but some tall Mountain Cedar, </l>
            <l>With all thy Pride and Glory rais'd up high, </l>
            <l>That I might plow thy Root up with a blast; </l>
            <l>But since a Village Shrub is all my aim, </l>
            <l>And my low Vengeance has no nobler game; </l>
            <l>My blushing shame, withholds my arm of fate. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e27400">
            <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
            <l>A Shrub! that name from him, that needs my pity! </l>
            <l>From him that lives in Torment, I in Pleasure, </l>
            <l>Raptures and Ecstasies, my Jail Companions; </l>
            <l>Whilst Fiends and Goblins haunt thee, even to Thrones, </l>
            <l>Break thy distracted sleeps on Beds of Gold: </l>
            <l>From my Urania's love, her love, poor Prince, </l>
            <l>There Darts that Beam as lights my very Dungeon, </l>
            <l>Imprints a softness, even in Chains and Death, </l>
            <l>Whilst thou, the little object of her hate, </l>
            <l>Must bear about thee an Eternal Hell, </l>
            <l>And beg in vain of that dear Heaven for ease▪ </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e27540">Enter Oswell. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e27560">
            <speaker>Osw. </speaker>
            <p>My Lord the King. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e27590">
            <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
            <p>Now tremble at thy doom. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e27620">
            <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
            <l>Why should I dread the only thing I▪ covet? </l>
            <l>You seek a Life that I desire to lose. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e27660">Enter King. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e27680">Shout within. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e27690">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Hell and Confusion seize their clamorous Throats! </l>
            <l>Oh Ferdinand, I am beset with Ruine, </l>
            <l>My very Slaves oppose my Royal Justice; </l>
            <l>And dare rebel to save a Traytor's Life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e27760">
            <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
            <p>Great, Sir, what storm is this that shakes your quiet? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e27790">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Dost thou not hear the bellowing Crowd proclaim it? </l>
            <l>The scum of Earth, those never-failing Rebels, </l>
            <l>Join with the Souldiers to preserve Cesario: </l>
            <l>But in despight of that ungovern'd Herd, </l>
            <l>A Monarchs hand shall send him from the World. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e27870">Draws and runs at <hi>Cesario, Ferd. </hi>stops him. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e27890">
            <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
            <p>Hold, Sacred Sir. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e27920">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <p>Wilt thou oppose me too? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e27950">
            <pb n="43" xml:id="ep000683-026-b"/>
            <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
            <l>Most sacred Sir, that stroke requires more thought, </l>
            <l>Shou'd you thus cut him off, the incens'd Rabble </l>
            <l>Wou'd throw aside all Duty and Allegiance, </l>
            <l>And on your Royal Head pour all their fury; </l>
            <l>Affection in your stubborn multitude, </l>
            <l>Is a prone Torrent not to be withstood. </l>
            <l>Were you as sacred, Sir, as Heaven it self, </l>
            <l>Yet when you stop the current of their Will, </l>
            <l>They'll break all Bands of duty, and prophane </l>
            <l>That Holiness, to which they'd bound their Faiths. </l>
            <l>Appease them first, which when you have perform'd, </l>
            <l>A private way may finish your Revenge. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e28090">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Must I then crouch and fawn to crawling Mud, </l>
            <l>Wou'd I cou'd Curse the Traytors from the Earth. </l>
            <l>But oh the wretched State of Kings, my Fate </l>
            <l>Will force my Tongue to flatter where I hate. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e28150">Ex. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e28160">
            <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
            <l>Dost thou not think thy self secur'd from harm? </l>
            <l>And with Triumphant smiles dispise our fury? </l>
            <l>Dost thou not think the threatning storm that's near, </l>
            <l>Will cast thee safe ashore, and Shipwrack me? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e28220">
            <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
            <l>How silly and how vain is credulous Man! </l>
            <l>Thy Fear suggests what never enters here. </l>
            <l>I see the Woman brooding in thy Eyes, </l>
            <l>And thy Soul bursting with envenom'd Malice. </l>
            <l>And oh, how poor is he that's Passion's Slave! </l>
            <l>Let me be stript of all my Soul holds dear, </l>
            <l>Rob me of Life, and what's more priz'd, Urania; </l>
            <l>Yet thou shou'dst see how my undaunted Soul </l>
            <l>Cou'd bear it all, and smiling quit the World. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e28340">
            <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
            <l>I'll try this boasted Courage: 'tis resolv'd, </l>
            <l>This hour's thy last, in spite of what can threaten. </l>
            <l>Thou tak'st the Free-hold of my Soul away, </l>
            <l>Urania and that are but one Creature. </l>
            <l>'s Death, I have been a tame Fool all this while, </l>
            <l>Swallow'd my Poison in a fruitless hope; </l>
            <l>But my Revenge as heavy as Iove's wrath, </l>
            <l>Wrapt in a Thunder-bolt is falling on thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e28460">
            <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
            <l>And I can thus undaunted stand the stroke, </l>
            <l>Yes, barbarous Prince, appear in thy true Colours. </l>
            <l>Shake off that dull effeminate Clog, Humanity, </l>
            <l>And if the least remains of Vertue, Honour </l>
            <pb n="44" xml:id="ep000683-027-a"/>
            <l>Hang soft upon thy Soul, freeze, freeze thy Veins, </l>
            <l>Crust'em to Rock, and wall thy heart in Marble, </l>
            <l>Inexorable as the Grave, and deaf as Death. </l>
            <l>Bath in my Blood, and mount me to the Stars. </l>
            <l>But know, when from my glorious Constellation, </l>
            <l>I shall look down upon that dark Abyss, </l>
            <l>Where thou ly'st howling in eternal Flames, </l>
            <l>I'll scorn thee then, as I defie thee now. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e28600">
            <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
            <l>Oh! I am vanquisht by this noble Spirit. </l>
            <l>Come to my Arms; my Arms, nay to my Heart. </l>
            <l>There take possession, and remain for ever. </l>
            <l>Cesario, thou sha't find that I have Honour </l>
            <l>Equals my Love. Oswell, retire a while, </l>
            <l>But first your Sword, and as you love your Master, </l>
            <l>Ask me not why, nor yet dispute my Orders. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e28710">
            <speaker>Osw. </speaker>
            <l>I've ever learnt Obedience to my Prince, </l>
            <l>Tho' I much fear the fatal Consequence. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e28750">Ex. Oswell. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e28770">
            <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
            <l>Cesario, this imbrace makes me thy Friend, </l>
            <l>And with it take this more surprising Present. </l>
            <l>Since 'tis decree'd that one of us must fall, </l>
            <l>Let Fortune hold the Scale: if 'tis my Fate, </l>
            <l>A long farewel at once to Life and Love. </l>
            <l>But if 'tis doom'd this Hand must give thee Death, </l>
            <l>Oh, make but this return with thy last Breath, </l>
            <l>Call me thy Friend, and make Urania mine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e28890">
            <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
            <l>By Heaven, you have with Honour conquer'd me, </l>
            <l>And here I lift a Sword against that Life, </l>
            <l>Which, witness for me, Gods, how fain I'd save, </l>
            <l>Nay were there any way to preserve both, </l>
            <l>But by resigning of the bright Urania; </l>
            <l>Were I as great as the young Macedonian, </l>
            <l>Whose Conquering Arms subdu'd the spacious World, </l>
            <l>I'd quit all Titles to those vanquisht Crowns, </l>
            <l>And build my Happiness on Love and Friendship. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e29020">
            <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
            <l>It will not be, we cannot both possess her; </l>
            <l>And either to resign's Impossible. </l>
            <l>Therefore delay no longer; if thou dost, </l>
            <l>I here call back the name of Friend again; </l>
            <l>And will proceed as an inveterate Foe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e29090">
            <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
            <l>But this Embrace, and then proceed to blood. <stage xml:id="ep000683-e29120">Embrace. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Now Fate, ordain me Love, or give me Death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e29140">
            <pb n="45" xml:id="ep000683-027-b"/>
            <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
            <l>Thou hast thy wish, Urania now is thine; <stage xml:id="ep000683-e29180">Fight, and both wounded. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>And may those powers that give her to your Arms, </l>
            <l>Crown all your Days and Nights with endless Joys. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e29210">Ferd. falls. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e29230">
            <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
            <l>That wish is kind, but oh it comes too late. </l>
            <l>For Death has been too busy with us both, </l>
            <l>And we both fall each others Sacrifice. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e29280">Falls. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e29290">Enter King, Tachmas, Sigismond, Oswell, <hi>and Souldiers</hi>: </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e29320">
            <speaker>Osw. </speaker>
            <p>Behold, </p>
            <l>my Lord, the fatal deed is done; </l>
            <l>See where th' unhappy Rivals, Arm in Arm, </l>
            <l>Are mixing Blood, as they have join'd their Souls. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e29380">
            <speaker>Tach. </speaker>
            <p>How fares my Brother? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e29410">
            <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
            <l>Near my last safe Harbour, </l>
            <l>Let me the little time I have to live, </l>
            <l>Imploy in begging Pardon of my King, </l>
            <l>And one kind farewel word to my Urania. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e29480">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Haste, haste, and bring that most unhappy Innocence; </l>
            <l>Made wretched by a Fathers harsh Decree. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e29520">
            <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
            <l>O Brother, Place me nearer to my Friend: </l>
            <l>No more my Enemy, yet still my Rival, </l>
            <l>My generous Rival, still though't be in Death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e29570">
            <speaker>Ferd. </speaker>
            <l>My dear Cesario, I must bid farewel: </l>
            <l>For cruel Death too hasty draggs me hence. </l>
            <l>Urania hates me, and 'tis time to die. </l>
            <l>But whither I shall go, too cruel Fair, </l>
            <l>The shades of black Despair can only tell. </l>
            <l>Pusht from the World by thy Disdain and Scorn, </l>
            <l>I drop into the dark side of Eternity— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e29680">Dies▪ </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e29690">
            <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
            <p>Farewel, thou Royal Convert of true Honour. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e29720">Enter Ardel. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e29740">
            <speaker>Ardel. </speaker>
            <p>Where, where's the King? oh, Sir, the poor Urania! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e29780">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <p>Ha! what of her? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e29810">
            <speaker>Ardel. </speaker>
            <l>If Horrour and Confusion </l>
            <l>Will lend me Breath to speak. Unhappy Princess! </l>
            <l>Alarm'd by the false Oswell's treach'rous Tongue, </l>
            <l>That your Commands had given Cesario death; </l>
            <l>Her generous Despair for her dear Lord, </l>
            <l>In her own Breast has plung'd her fatal Dagger. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e29910">
            <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
            <l>For me! this was too much. Oh Love! thy Altar </l>
            <l>Was never loaden with so rich a Victim. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e29950">
            <speaker>Ardel. </speaker>
            <p>And all the small remains of life that's left her, She comes to sigh out in his dying Arms. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e29980">
            <pb n="46" xml:id="ep000683-028-a"/>Enter Urania bleeding, her hair hanging loose, led by two Women. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e30010">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <l>Lead, lead me to this dismal scene of Horrour. </l>
            <l>Place me but near to my poor dying Lord, </l>
            <l>And in his Arms, I'll quit the World with pleasure. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e30060">
            <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
            <l>Ye cruel Powers! this stabs my very Soul. </l>
            <l>Is there no Help, no Art, no succouring Angels </l>
            <l>To save her Life? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e30110">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <l>Wer't in the Power of Fate, </l>
            <l>The precious Balm of thy king Tears wou'd do't. </l>
            <l>But 'tis too late. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e30160">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>My dear unhappy Daughter, </l>
            <l>What has thy Rashness done! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e30200">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <l>Nothing but only paid </l>
            <l>The Debts of dying Love, tho' cruel Fate </l>
            <l>Divorc'd me from his Arms, and cancell'd all </l>
            <l>Our marriage Joys; yet in the Grave, in that </l>
            <l>Cold Bridal Bed, I shall not be deny'd </l>
            <l>To lie a sleeping Virgin by thy side. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e30280">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <p>Of all these Ruines only I am Authour! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e30310">
            <speaker>Cesar. </speaker>
            <l>Can then my kind and generous Princess </l>
            <l>Leave all her Greatness, all her blooming Youth, </l>
            <l>Let those dear Eyes, those sparkling Twins of Love, </l>
            <l>And all that mighty Mass of infinite Beauty, </l>
            <l>Lie undistinguish'd in the common Heap </l>
            <l>Of mouldring Dust, ghostly as Death and wither'd </l>
            <l>As naked scraggy Roots of unborn Flowers, </l>
            <l>And all for her unhappy, worthless Slave? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e30410">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <l>Cou'd I do less to shew I lov'd Cesario? </l>
            <l>The meanest of my Sex can live and love, </l>
            <l>Each common Spark inspires that feeble heat, </l>
            <l>To die for Love is only truly great: </l>
            <l>Nor is this all the Glory of my Death, </l>
            <l>You God's I bring my Innocence to Heaven. </l>
            <l>Free from Loves grosser and impurer Charms, </l>
            <l>I die a Virgin in my Husbands Arms. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e30520">Dies. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e30530">
            <speaker>Cesa. </speaker>
            <l>She's dead, she's dead, meet her you Gods, oh meet her: </l>
            <l>Throw open all the shining Gates of Heaven; </l>
            <l>And sally out, thick as the Beams of Day: </l>
            <l>To her Immortal Praise, new tune your Spheres, </l>
            <pb n="47" xml:id="ep000683-028-b"/>
            <l>At her dear Feet your brightest Diadems lay, </l>
            <l>For this is Beauties Coronation Day; </l>
            <l>But still in all her Heavenly Pomp she wants </l>
            <l>Her Loyal Slave, I come, dear Saint, I come. </l>
            <l>Oh let thy Soul one moment stay its slight, </l>
            <l>And take mine with thee to Eternal Light. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e30650">Dies▪ </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e30660">Enter Sigismond. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e30680">
            <speaker>Sig. </speaker>
            <l>Forgive, dread Sir, the uagrateful sounds I bring, </l>
            <l>The popular fury and your Armies Rage </l>
            <l>For their Dear General, and Princes Blood, </l>
            <l>Is swell'd so high, that where the Storm will break </l>
            <l>I tremble but to think; their Impious murmurs </l>
            <l>No less than at your Royal Scepter fly. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000683-e30760">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>My Scepter, why 'tis what I'm weary of: </l>
            <l>It may be Tachmas, 'twill to thee descend: </l>
            <l>But when the Royal Helm is in thy hand, </l>
            <l>Oh let my Wrack thy warning Seamark stand, </l>
            <l>Shun but my Guilt, and with a prosperous Tyde, </l>
            <l>Safe from my Rock the Royal Vessel Guide. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000683-e30850">Exeunt omnes. </stage>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="epilogue" xml:id="ep000683-e30860">
        <pb xml:id="ep000683-029-a"/>
        <head>EPILOGUE. </head>
        <byline>
          <hi>Spoken by </hi>M rs Knight. <hi>Written by </hi>Mr. Durfey. </byline>
        <lg>
          <l>AS a young sprightly Widow of the Town, </l>
          <l>That had some year's the marriage Comforts known. </l>
          <l>Believing She had once the best of Men, </l>
          <l>Resolves to try her Fortune o'er agin: </l>
          <l>So our Young scribling Fool, that found before </l>
          <l>Your kind Indulgence, needs must write once more. </l>
          <l>Plagu'd with an Itch that does through Poets run, </l>
          <l>Who once being enter'd, never can have done. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>He says my Intercession cannot fail, </l>
          <l>And that a pleading Female▪ must prevail. </l>
          <l>I told him, I shou'd never help his Play, </l>
          <l>As having ne'er oblig'd, I mean your way, </l>
          <l>And that in times of War you Women chuse, </l>
          <l>Iust like Iack-Boots, only for present use. </l>
          <l>Till your Convenience serv'd to stand at door, </l>
          <l>Then laid by, by the Footman to be wore. </l>
          <l>Bus'ness of Love moves now no tender Passion, </l>
          <l>Your Heads are buzz'd with bus'ness of the Nation; </l>
          <l>And when your Ladies sigh for a soft word, </l>
          <l>Tou roar, Boy, bring my Pistols, fetch my Sword. </l>
          <l>What Hopes then I cou'd have he well might guess; </l>
          <l>Pray Heav'n▪ these jarring days may quickly cease. </l>
          <l>Women and Misers always pray for peace. </l>
          <l>Plunder of Gold, the Miser's fear does move, </l>
          <l>Ours, that we shall not plunder'd be of Love. </l>
          <l>For to say truth, tho' Souldiers all are brave, </l>
          <l>They're the worst Lovers that our Sex can have. </l>
          <l>For now adays, their duty grows so hard, </l>
          <l>They 're always Resty when they mount our Guard. </l>
          <l>However I must try my Luck▪ If then </l>
          <l>There chance to be amongst you, Gentlemen, </l>
          <l>Any so kind to hear what I can say, </l>
          <l>Them I invoke in favour of this Play. </l>
          <l>It has some Wit, tho' mix'd with many a Fau't, </l>
          <l>Some little Fancy too; but as for Plot, </l>
          <l>There are so many New ones found elsewhere, </l>
          <l>He thought not worth his time to make one here; </l>
          <l>And therefore tho' you can't that Part applaud, </l>
          <l>Clap now, for there's a Pumpkin Plot abread. </l>
        </lg>
        <trailer>FINIS: </trailer>
        <pb xml:id="ep000683-029-b"/>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
