<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Vow Breaker, or The Fair Maid of Clifton</title>
        <author>
<!--Sampson, William-->
          <persName>
            <forename>William</forename>
            <surname>Sampson</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <idno type="dracor" xml:base="https://dracor.org/id/">ep000245</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://earlyprint.org</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull n="TCP source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">The vow breaker. Or, The faire maide of Clifton. In Notinghamshire as it hath beene diuers times acted by severall companies with great applause. By William Sampson.</title>
                <author>Sampson, William, 1590?-1636.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>38 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
                <date>2004 August (TCP phase 1)</date>
                <idno type="marc">99851684</idno>
                <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 21688.</idno>
                <idno type="stc">Greg, II, 510.</idno>
                <idno type="vid">16973</idno>
                <idno type="DLPS">A11435</idno>
                <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2240919226</idno>
                <availability>
                  <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
                </availability>
              </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
            <biblFull n="printed source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">The vow breaker. Or, The faire maide of Clifton. In Notinghamshire as it hath beene diuers times acted by severall companies with great applause. By William Sampson.</title>
                <title type="alt">Vow breaker</title>
                <title type="alt">Vow-breaker, or the fayre maid of Clifton.</title>
                <title type="alt">Faire maide of Clifton.</title>
                <author>Sampson, William, 1590?-1636.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[76] p. : ill. (woodcut)</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Printed by Iohn Norton and are to be sold by Roger Ball at the signe of the Golden Anchor in the Strand, neere Temple-Barre,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication_date">1636.</date>
                <date type="creation_date">1625</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>
                  <p>Mostly in verse.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Signatures: A-I4 K2.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Running title reads: The vow-breaker, or the fayre maid of Clifton.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</p>
                </note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1625">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000245-e100030">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000245-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000245-001-b"/>
        <p>THE VOW BREAKER. OR, THE FAIRE MAIDE of Clifton. </p>
        <p>In Notinghamshire as it hath beene diuers times Acted by severall Companies with great applause. </p>
        <p>By WILLIAM SAMPSON. </p>
        <quote>
          <bibl>Virg: Aen: lib: 2. 77. </bibl>Obstupui, steterantque Comae, &amp; vox fausibus haesit. </quote>
        <p>LONDON. Printed by IOHN NORTON and are to be sold by ROGER BALL at the signe of the Golden Anchor in the Strand, neere Temple-Barre, 1636. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000245-e100100">
        <pb xml:id="ep000245-002-a"/>
        <head>The Illustration. </head>
        <l>THis faithlesse woman, by her friends consent </l>
        <l>Plighted her troth to Bateman! streight not content </l>
        <l>With his revenue! Coveting for more </l>
        <l>Shee marries German for his wealthy store </l>
        <l>There Parents iarr'd, and never could agree </l>
        <l>Till both of them were dround in misery. </l>
        <l>Young Bateman hangs himselfe, for love of her: </l>
        <l>Shee drownds her selfe (guilt plaies the murtherer.) </l>
        <l>His Ghost afrights her, sad thoughts doe her annoy </l>
        <l>(Alive or dead: tis shee, he must enioy.) </l>
        <l>The Morrall is Maides should beware in choise, </l>
        <l>And where they cannot love, divert their voice. </l>
        <l>Parents must not be rash, nor too vnkind, </l>
        <l>And not for wealth to thwart, their Childrens minde. </l>
        <l>All is not gaind, that's got, (ill purchasde wealth, </l>
        <l>Never brought comfort, tranquill, peace, and health.) </l>
        <l>This president, this principle doth allow </l>
        <l>Weddings are made in Heaven, though seald below. </l>
      </div>
      <div type="illustration" xml:id="ep000245-e100290">
        <pb xml:id="ep000245-002-b"/>
        <p>
          <figure>
            <p>Thinke on thy promise aliue or dead I must and will inioy thee. </p>
            <p>Hees come watch mee or I am gone. </p>
            <p>O how happy had I beene if shee had lived. </p>
            <p>O how happy had I beene if hee had lived. </p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000245-e100360">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000245-003-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000245-003-b"/>
        <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL and most vertuous Gentlewoman Mistris Anne Willoughby Daughter of the Right Worshipfull, and ever to be Honoured Henry Wiloughby of Risley, in the County of Derby Baronet. </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Worthiest, and Noble Mistris, </salute>
        </opener>
        <p>THIS infant received breath, and being vnder your noble Fathers roofe (my ever honored Master) and therefore as an Aire-lover belonging to that Hospitable Fahricke, it properly prostrates it selfe to you for a patronnesse. The title of it saith ignorant Censurers (those Critticall Momes that have no language but satirrick Calumnie) sounds grosse, and ignare, expressing smal wit, and lesse judgment, in the Author to dedicate (A vow-breaker) under the <pb xml:id="ep000245-004-a"/>protection of A Lady, of your Candor, beauty, goodnes, and vertues: against those foule mouthd detractors, who asmuch as in their venemous hearts lay; sought to villifie an unblaunchd Laune, a vestall puritie, a truth like Innocence, a temple of sanctitie, the Altar of reall goodnes, against those brainles Momes, I comply my selfe with Plinies naturall similie of the Almond-tree: picke of the Rind, cracke the shell, yet set the kernell upright in earth, and by natures helpe it regaines maturity and growth: so have your noble vertues, even with the Diamond eclipsed darknesse, and from obscurity gaind greater lustre even then when the two eldest sons of sin Enuy, and Malice sought to obscure them: but shee that hath not left the earth, divine Astrea, sacred iustice, the eye, and soule of the law, hath vindicated <pb xml:id="ep000245-004-b"/>those foule mouthd detractors: as you are great in goodnes, so shine there still, and let the Sun-raies of your vertues ever yeild honored hatchments, &amp; portments, to your most noble father, &amp; his honored families, of whom you are a principall Columne: continue ever in that noble pedigree of vertues, which your virgin purity hitherto hath justly maintaind, heaven keepe you from faunning parasites, and busie gossips, and send you a Husband, and a good one, else may you neuer make a Holliday for Hymen, as much happines as tongue can speake, penn write, heart thinke, or thoughts imagine, ever attend on you, your noble father, and all his families, to whom I ever rest, as my bounden duty, </p>
        <closer>
          <signed>A faithfull servant, WILLIAM SAMPSON. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="prologue" xml:id="ep000245-e100420">
        <pb xml:id="ep000245-005-a"/>
        <head>The Prologue to Censurers. </head>
        <l>TRuth saies the Author, this Time will be bold </l>
        <l>To tell a Story, truer ne're was told. </l>
        <l>Wherein he boldly vouches all is true </l>
        <l>That this Time's spoke by vs, or heard by you. </l>
        <l>If Chronicle, that ever yet gain'd favour </l>
        <l>May please true Iudgments: his true endeavour </l>
        <l>From serious houres his gaind it: for vs </l>
        <l>He hopes our labours will be prosperous. </l>
        <l>And yet me thinkes I here some Criticke say </l>
        <l>That they are much abus'd in this our Play. </l>
        <l>Their Magistracy laught at! as if now </l>
        <l>What Ninty yeeres since dy'd, a fresh did grow: </l>
        <l>To those wee answer, that ere they were borne, </l>
        <l>The story that we glaunse at, then was worne </l>
        <l>And held authentick: and the men wee name </l>
        <l>Grounded in Honours Prowesse, Vertues Fame. </l>
        <l>Bring not the Author then, in your mislikes, </l>
        <l>If on the Ages vice, quaintly he strikes </l>
        <l>And hits your guilt! most plainely it appeares </l>
        <l>He like a Taylor that hath lost his sheares </l>
        <l>Amongst his shreds. he knockes upon the board, </l>
        <l>And by the sound themselues they doe affoord. </l>
        <l>If in his scenes, he any vice have hit </l>
        <l>To you farre better knowne then to his wit, </l>
        <l>Tak't to your selves alone: for him, his Penn </l>
        <l>Strikes at the vices, and not mindes the men. </l>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="ep000245-e100700">
        <pb xml:id="ep000245-005-b"/>
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000245-e100710">
          <head>Actus Primus Scena Prima. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e100720">Enter young Bateman meeting Anne. </stage>
          <l>ANNE, My Bateman. </l>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e100740">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>My sweetest Nan? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e100760">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Had I but one entire affected Pearle </l>
            <l>Inestimable unto vulgar censure </l>
            <l>And is there none to play the Theife but thou! </l>
            <l>Oh misery would'st have thy love entransd, </l>
            <l>Without an eccho that would sigh farewell. </l>
            <l>Common curtesie 'mongst rurall Hyndes </l>
            <l>With this formallity disciplines them </l>
            <l>(Kisse at the departure), and you to steale away </l>
            <l>Without my Privity? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e100860">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Pray thee no more? </l>
            <l>Teares are the Heralds to future sorrowes, </l>
            <l>I have collected all that's man together </l>
            <l>And wrastld with affections as with streames, </l>
            <l>And as they strive that doe oppresse the billowes </l>
            <l>So doe I fare in each externall part. </l>
            <l>My Actes are like the motionall gymmalls </l>
            <l>Fixt in a Watch, who winde themselves away </l>
            <l>Without cessation; here if I stay, I finde </l>
            <l>I must be where thou art! which when I am </l>
            <l>Thy fathers rage encreases like a flame </l>
            <l>Fedd by ungentle blastes! my absence </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-006-a"/>
            <l>May worke those bitter sweeteings from his hart </l>
            <l>And smooth the rising furrowes in his brow. </l>
            <l>It is sufficient that I know thee firme </l>
            <l>Fixt as a Rocke in constancy, and love, </l>
            <l>Able to ship-wracke greatnes, and despiseth </l>
            <l>A violated heart, as a disease. </l>
            <l>I goe to Leith as children goe to schoole </l>
            <l>Studying what shall please my Mistris best, </l>
            <l>My lesson cond, I will returne againe </l>
            <l>And dedicate my labours unto thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e101090">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Sweete doe not goe; and yet if that you will </l>
            <l>Leaving me here like a forsaken Lover, </l>
            <l>Prethee forget me not; nay be not angry </l>
            <l>Souldiers in Warre make any saint their owne </l>
            <l>Forgeting those they are devoted too! </l>
            <l>Tis I have vow'd to have thee quicke or dead, </l>
            <l>Flattering honours, nor dissembling beauties </l>
            <l>Workes me not from thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e101180">
            <speaker>Y. Bat. </speaker>
            <l>Sweare not sweete Nan! </l>
            <l>The booke of fate, as now may be unclasp'd </l>
            <l>And record what thou speak'st. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e101220">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Be it writ in brasse </l>
            <l>My love shall be as durable as that! </l>
            <l>Now by this kisse, nay I will second that, </l>
            <l>When I this hand bequeath to any one </l>
            <l>But my sweete Bateman; then may I ever </l>
            <l>From heaven, and goodnes resta cast-away, </l>
            <l>If e're I give this hand, to any one </l>
            <l>But my sweete Bateman. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e101310">
            <speaker>Y. Bat. </speaker>
            <l>Thy constancy I resalute. </l>
            <l>Death onely separates me from thy love. </l>
            <l>Alive or dead I shall enjoy thee then </l>
            <l>Spite of thy fathers frownes. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e101360">Enter Vrsula. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e101370">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>Why then up-with your bag; and baggage, and to Saint Maries presently the Priest stayes, the Clarke whynes to say Amen! and for th'officiall schollers love butterd loaves, an Angell will perswade him to consent, we that live by the sinnes of the <pb xml:id="ep000245-006-b"/>people may dispense with veniall toyes. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e101390">
            <speaker>Y. Bat. </speaker>
            <p>Thou art merry still. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e101410">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>Faith, and shalbe as long as I keepe me out of Cupids mannacles, doost heare Lover? take her now thou hast her i'th vaine trust not we wenches, theirs asmuch truth in us, as in Knightes o'th post; if she sweare love to day, shee'le unsweare it to morrow with a safe conscience; stand not shall I shall I, take me her to have, and to hold, and if eyther of you repent your bargaine within a twelue-month— </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e101430">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <p>What then! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e101450">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>Then you shall fetch no Bacon at Dunmowe; we young wenches in our loves are like Lapwinges, if once we creepe out o'th shells, we run from out ould loves like Scopperells, weomens minds are planetary, and amble as fast as Virginalls Iackes, if you stop 'em not in true time, you marre all your musique. See heres your Fathers. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e101470">Enter ould Boote old Bateman. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e101480">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Alas what wilt thou doe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e101500">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Not shrinke a jot for thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e101520">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>I charge thee on my blessing leave that boy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e101540">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Father! sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e101560">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>Come, come, come. </l>
            <l>Must your appetite be married to beggery </l>
            <l>Is this the onely Phoenix of the World? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-old_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e101600">
            <speaker>O. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Boote, boote, boote, thou art malapert, false, proud, </l>
            <l>A wretched miscreant, and dissembler, </l>
            <l>H' shall enjoy her, shees his lawfull wife </l>
            <l>Thy hand enstated hers, though falsely now </l>
            <l>Thou plaist the counterfet. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e101660">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>Well said ould cocke, would thy spurrs were new rowell'd that thou mightst picke out his eyes. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e101680">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>Still are your eyes gadding that way, know this </l>
            <l>I'le sooner marry thee unto some slave </l>
            <l>Whom mine owne will can subordinate </l>
            <l>Rather then to him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e101730">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Is vertue growne to so absurd a rate </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-007-a"/>
            <l>It gaines no better credit with base wordlings. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-old_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e101760">
            <speaker>O. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Tell me Boote. </l>
            <l>Does not his birth, and breeding equall hers, </l>
            <l>Are not my revenues correspondent </l>
            <l>To equall thine; his purity of bloud </l>
            <l>Runs in as sweete a streame, and naturall heate </l>
            <l>As thine, or hers; his exteriour parts </l>
            <l>May parralell hers, or any others </l>
            <l>In a true harmony of lawfull love. </l>
            <l>Wast not thine owne motion, didst not give way, </l>
            <l>And entercourse to their privacies? </l>
            <l>Didst thou not make me draw conveighances </l>
            <l>Did not th'assurance of thy Lands seeme proball, </l>
            <l>Boote, Boote thou shall not carry it thus </l>
            <l>I'le make thee know theirs justice to be had </l>
            <l>If thou denyst it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e101920">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>Say I grant all this! </l>
            <l>With my selfe having deliberated </l>
            <l>I doe not like 'thassurance of thy Lands </l>
            <l>Thy titles are so bangld with thy debts, </l>
            <l>Which thou wouldst have my daughters portion pay. </l>
            <l>Sir sir, it shall not! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-old_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e101990">
            <speaker>O. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>hang thee hang thee miser! </l>
            <l>Tis thy base thoughts forges these false conceits, </l>
            <l>And but for thy daughter, I'de, I'de, I'de. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e102030">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>I'de come, come. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e102050">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Father? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e102070">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Deere sir spare your fury? </l>
            <l>Anger in old men is a Lunacy </l>
            <l>That woundes the speakers, not the spectators? </l>
            <l>My thoughts are now embarqu'd to goe for Leith </l>
            <l>And see the Warrs, I hope e're my returne </l>
            <l>I shall finde temperate weather in your lookes, </l>
            <l>And all these stormes vanishd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-old_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e102150">
            <speaker>O. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Art thou so built on her fidelity </l>
            <l>Take heede boy; women by kinde are fickle, </l>
            <l>Absence in lovers brings strange events </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-007-b"/>
            <l>Lovers that hourely kisse finde due regard </l>
            <l>But those that absent are oft lose reward. </l>
            <l>I doubt not of her firmenes, but tis common </l>
            <l>An absent lover thrives not with a woman. </l>
            <l>Tis good counsell boy, and worth observance </l>
            <l>But thou darst trust her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e102250">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>With my life sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-old_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e102270">
            <speaker>O. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Goe on then in thy entended purpose </l>
            <l>Noble sir Jarvis whose man thou art, </l>
            <l>I know will furnish thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e102310">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>This works to my designe, and gives free way </l>
            <l>For wealthy Germane to my daughters love. </l>
            <l>Come hither Nan. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e102350">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>I thought the wind was in that doore; by my virginity a young wench were better be heire to a swine-heards chines, then a rich mans bagges! we must be coupld in wed-locke like your Barbary horse, and Spanish Gennet, for breede sake, house to house, and land to land, the devill a jot of love? poore simple virginity, that us'd to be our best Dowry is now growne as bare as a serving-mans cloake that has not had a good nap this seven yeeres. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e102370">Enter Clifton, and a Shoomaker. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-old_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e102380">
            <speaker>O. Ba. </speaker>
            <p>Well Boote time may make us friends. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e102400">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <p>Weele thinke on't Bateman! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e102420">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <p>How many paire of shooes knave ha. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-shoemaker" xml:id="ep000245-e102440">
            <speaker>Sho. </speaker>
            <p>By Saint Hugh sir Jarvis foure thousand paire. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e102460">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <p>For every knave two paire good sauce against kyb'd heeles by my hollidam; well shod, and clad will mak'em fight like men! the North is could, subject to frostes, and snówes, and tis bad fighting without vittle, and cloth! for which I have provided well for both; forty horse loades, and twenty Carrs of vittle, twill stop a good breach in a souldiours belly! my man shall pay thee huffit; my Hollidam! my old Neighbour rich Boote, and Bateman, is this brabling matter ended yet! shall he have her, by my Hollidam not yet, the knave shall serve his Queene first, see the warres, where twill do him good to see <pb xml:id="ep000245-008-a"/>knocks passe as fillips, say i'st done? </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e102480">Enter Miles. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-old_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e102490">
            <speaker>O. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Hees at your service. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e102510">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>By my Hollidam he shall not want for that </l>
            <l>But I am tardy, and my time is precious </l>
            <l>My Hollidam, wheir's this knave? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e102550">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Faith sir trading as other knaves doe! sir yonders the Tailor the Weaver, and I the Miller. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e102570">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <p>My Hollidam knaves all three! put me a Tailor, a Weaver, and a Miller into a bag. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e102590">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>And what then sir? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e102610">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <p>Why he that first comes out will be a knave. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e102630">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Vnder correction sir put me a Justice of peace, an Officiall, an under Sherriffe into a bag. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e102650">Enter Ball Ioshua. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e102660">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <p>And what then knave? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e102680">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Why, and they will not come out, let em' tarry their like knaves as they are. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e102700">
            <speaker>Cilf. </speaker>
            <p>What a knave is this. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e102720">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Sir heres two more appeares! th'one is mad Ball old Huffus man, tho'ther may be a knave in graine for any thing I know i'me sure hees much given to colours hees a Painter-stainer. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e102740">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <p>Y'are both pres'd, and willing to serve the Queene. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e102760">
            <speaker>Bal. </speaker>
            <p>I am bend leather, and will endure it. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e102780">
            <speaker>Iosh. </speaker>
            <p>My name is Marmaduke Ioshua a Painter-stainer by Art, and a limner by profession? I am given to the meanes, and doe fructifie among the brethren, it were obnoxious, and inutiable, and contrary to the sages to presse me. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e102800">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <p>Weele see how you can edifie our Campe. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e102820">
            <speaker>Iosh. </speaker>
            <p>For the sistren commisserate. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e102840">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <p>Come my old neighbours, let our Drum beat a free march weele have a health to Queene Besse, cry St. George, and a fig for St. Dennis. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e102860">Enter Omnes nisi Bateman, Anne. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e102870">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Mistris Vrsula, tis not unknowne that I have lov'd you; <pb xml:id="ep000245-008-b"/>if I die, it shall be for your sake, and it shall be valiantly; I leave an hand-kercher with you, tis wrought with blew coventry; let me not at my returne fall to my old song, she had a clout of mine sow de with blew coventry, and so hang my selfe at your infidelity; desiring Jove to blesse you from better fortunes I leave you. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e102890">Exeunt. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e102900">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>The foole doates, but tis no matter, tis no matter, tis Lady like why should not I have my Monkey to play withall? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e102920">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <p>Prethee leave us. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e102940">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>Heavens blesse me out of your company, for fooles I found you, and so I must leave you in spite of my hart. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e102960">Exit. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e102970">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Now Nan heres none but thou, and I; thy love </l>
            <l>Emboldens me to speake, and cheerfully </l>
            <l>Here is a peece of gold, tis but a little one </l>
            <l>Yet big enough to ty, and seale a knot </l>
            <l>A jugall knot on Earth, to which high heaven </l>
            <l>Now cryes Amen, say thou so too, and then </l>
            <l>When eyther of us breakes this sacred bond </l>
            <l>Let us be made strange spectacles to the world </l>
            <l>To heaven, and earth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e103070">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Amen say I. </l>
            <l>And let heaven loth me when I falsifie. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e103100">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Thou now art like a pollishd jvory Table </l>
            <l>In purenes without; or staine or blemish. </l>
            <l>If thou shouldst soile this whitenes with blacke deedes </l>
            <l>Thinke what a monster thou wouldst make thy selfe. </l>
            <l>I doubt thee not, but give this cautionary. </l>
            <l>Harke the Drum beates, from the armes of love </l>
            <l>I now must burnish in the Armes of warre, adue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e103180">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>When I prove false to thee; oh may I then </l>
            <l>Beheld the scorne of heaven, earth, and men. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000245-e103210">Enter severally. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000245-e103220">Grey, Arguile, Crosse, Souldiours, drume, Colors. </stage>
            <l>As farre as my Commission Arguile </l>
            <l>I have proceeded, we in the trade of warre </l>
            <l>Whose Mart consists in blowes, and batteries, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-009-a"/>
            <l>Are like small Rivers that must keepe their bounds, </l>
            <l>Till the Queene Ocean command them rise. </l>
            <l>Dunbarr can witnes where we skuirmishd last </l>
            <l>I require the hostages be deliverd </l>
            <l>Twixt England, and the federary Lords. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-arguile" xml:id="ep000245-e103310">
            <speaker>Arg. </speaker>
            <l>Peruse this bedroule from Duke Chattenreault </l>
            <l>Wherein their names are, their persons attend </l>
            <l>At Inskeith, and with willingnes are bound </l>
            <l>To attend the mighty Queene of England. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e103360">
            <speaker>Grey. </speaker>
            <p>Lord Claud. Hambleton fourth son of the Duke, Robert Dowglasse brother to the Lord James Stuart! Archibald Dowglasse Lord of Loughennell George Gram second son to the Earle of Menteich; James Coningham son to the Earle of Glencorne; all Hostages to the Queene of England till the Articles be performed betwixt her, and the Federary Lordes. Herald of Armes conduct these noble pledges from the Red Brayes to Inskeith, see'em delivered to James Croft, and George Howard Knights from thence to be embarqd for England. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-crosse" xml:id="ep000245-e103380">
            <speaker>Cro. </speaker>
            <l>I shall my Lord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e103400">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>What number speake your powers </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-arguile" xml:id="ep000245-e103420">
            <speaker>Ar. </speaker>
            <l>Two thousand hardy Scots, </l>
            <l>With glaved blades, bum daggers, and white Kerchers, </l>
            <l>Such as will fight, and face the fiery French. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e103460">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>Our numbers then are eight thousand </l>
            <l>And still we looke for more, sir Francis Leake, </l>
            <l>And gentle Sir, Jarvis; two spirits </l>
            <l>That in peace are lambes, in warr two ravening Lyons. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e103510">A march, Enter Clifton, Souldiers. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e103520">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>A Souldiers wishes blesse my noble Generall. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e103540">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>Thanks valiant Clifton; they can deserve no lesse </l>
            <l>Comming from thee? I see you emulate </l>
            <l>That we should take the glory to our selves, </l>
            <l>I'le give the first Alar'm, youle be one. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e103590">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>I by my Hollidam at warre as at a feast </l>
            <l>I'le scramble for my part, and if I catch a knocke </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-009-b"/>
            <l>That honour which a Souldiour wins in warrs </l>
            <l>Is of low price unles he bring home scarrs </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e103640">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>What number sir Jarvis? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e103660">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>Five hundred, and fifty tall white coates, </l>
            <l>Fellowes that will face a murdering Cannon, </l>
            <l>When it blowes rancks into the Aire as Chaffe </l>
            <l>Yet dreadles they shall stand it, and not shrinke, </l>
            <l>Right Nottingham shire Lads. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e103720">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>Tis well don! </l>
            <l>Our bands are well divided, yours my Lord </l>
            <l>Keepe the greene Bul-warke, mine the west Gate, </l>
            <l>You sir Iarvis the water-ports to Inskeith. </l>
            <l>Pelham from Pelhamus Mount plaies at the Towne </l>
            <l>How now what Trumpets this? </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e103790">A Trumpet, Enter Trumball. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-trumball" xml:id="ep000245-e103800">
            <speaker>Trum. </speaker>
            <l>From the Queene Regent of Scotland I come </l>
            <l>To thee Lord Generall of the English Force. </l>
            <l>She craves a treaty with the Lords of England </l>
            <l>To know why thus they enter on her groundes, </l>
            <l>Depopulate her Countries, Plough her Plaines </l>
            <l>If lawfull cause she finds on enterveiue </l>
            <l>She will subscribe to England, sue for peace, </l>
            <l>Otherwise by Article sheele confirm't; </l>
            <l>This is under her highnes hand, and seale. </l>
            <l>This is my message. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e103910">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>Whats thy name? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-trumball" xml:id="ep000245-e103930">
            <speaker>Trum. </speaker>
            <l>Trumball, Serejant Trumpetter to her Grace. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e103950">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>Her Princely offer we accept Rowge Crosse </l>
            <l>Herrald at Armes, command sir George Howard </l>
            <l>Sir James Crofts, and my son Arthur Grey </l>
            <l>To shew her Grace my Soveraignes grevances </l>
            <l>I'th interim wee'le sheath our burnishd blades </l>
            <l>Which had bene dide in scarlet long ere this. </l>
            <l>But for thy message. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e104030">
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-010-a"/>Enter Trumball. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-trumball" xml:id="ep000245-e104040">
            <speaker>Trum. </speaker>
            <l>I shall report you honourable. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e104060">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>My Hollidam I like not these signes of peace </l>
            <l>These French Flyes worke on advantages </l>
            <l>I'le not trust'em. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e104100">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <p>To prevent which each stand on his guard; your eares my Lord. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e104120">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>Resolve me; doe they kill men ith warrs, and ne're give warning. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e104140">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Not so much time Io! as a theife has at Nottingham Gallowes. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e104160">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>Tirany, tirany; may a not pray insincerity nor request the breethren, and sisters to have care of a departing brother. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e104180">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>No Io! nothing but downe-right blowes, just as you fell Okes, or kill Oxen. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e104200">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>Most heathenish, and diabollicall; and do the shoote Bullets. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e104220">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>I Io, as thicke as haile a man may hit his owne father. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e104240">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>Oh Infidells, and Barbarians; what will not the wicked doe, kill men with bullets! oh these Guns, they are dangerous things they sprung from the whoore, a Fryer was the inventor, and the smell of the Dragon! oh my poore Pusse-cat; sinfull man thou art Io: to bring the poore Pusse forth to dy by a Gun! a poore Pusse, silly harmelesse Pusse. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e104260">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Ty her behind, then if thou runst shee may save thee. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e104280">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>I run! thou prophane translater I scorne to run, my Car, and I will enter battell 'gainst the wicked! I run. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e104300">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <p>Why returne so soone. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e104320">Enter Crosse. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-crosse" xml:id="ep000245-e104330">
            <speaker>Cros. </speaker>
            <l>This my Lord. </l>
            <l>Making for Edenborough to the Queene, </l>
            <l>Nine hundred shot, and five hundred Corslets, </l>
            <l>Came forth of Leith, under the conduct </l>
            <l>Of Mortigue, and Doysells their Colonells. </l>
            <l>We wish'd them peaceably returne to Leith </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-010-b"/>
            <l>Since contrary to all Lawes of Armes </l>
            <l>They now had issud? Mortïgue replide </l>
            <l>They on their masters ground resolved stood </l>
            <l>And from their mistris would not budge a foote </l>
            <l>For any English breathing. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e104450">Exit Crosse. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e104460">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>Were not our promise given to the Queene </l>
            <l>On which they build advantages, i'de make </l>
            <l>These French Rats run as Wolves from fire, </l>
            <l>Bid'em retire, and tell them thus from us </l>
            <l>Weele make them win their ground ere they stand on't. </l>
            <l>Nothing but circumvention in the French. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e104530">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <p>By my Hollidam juglers, constant in nothing but Inconstancy, thats the French Merchandize. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e104550">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>And doe they fight, as it is in the painted cloth, of the nine worthies, of Ioshua, Hector, Caesar, Arthur, Charle-Magne, Iudas, Machabeus, and Godfrey Bollogine. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-miles" xml:id="ep000245-e104570">
            <speaker>Mil. </speaker>
            <l>Yes Io: they doe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e104590">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <l>In the painted cloth Joshua stands formost </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e104610">
            <speaker>Bal. </speaker>
            <l>With his Cat in stead of a Scutchion. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e104630">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <l>Ball thou art full of rebukes— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e104650">Enter Crosse. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-crosse" xml:id="ep000245-e104660">
            <speaker>Cros. </speaker>
            <l>Arme, arme, arme, regardles of true honour </l>
            <l>Your message is defide, and facing the van </l>
            <l>Dischargd a thousand shot, the Crag, and Chappell </l>
            <l>They make a refuge 'gainst our great Artillery </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e104710">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>Let the bow-men shoute their slighted Arrowes, </l>
            <l>As thicke as haile, the Musketteers shall follow </l>
            <l>Alarum then; tis our first enterprise </l>
            <l>When cowards fall the valiant spirits rise. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e104760">Ex. Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e104770">After skirmishes Enter Grey, Arguile, young Bateman with Colors, Clifton, Souldioers, prisoners. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e104780">
            <speaker>Gray: </speaker>
            <l>The Crag, and Chappells ours, and the French </l>
            <l>Like Hares are leapd out of fierce Greyhounds gripes. </l>
            <l>Doysells, and Mortigue, out-ran their Collours, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-011-a"/>
            <l>And with all expedition tooke the Towne. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e104830">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Whose Colors I display. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e104850">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>How many of the French this day are falne? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-arguile" xml:id="ep000245-e104870">
            <speaker>Arg. </speaker>
            <l>Seven score my Lord, and prisoners of noble worth. </l>
            <l>Poiteers, Augois, Burbon, Shamoont, Shaldone, </l>
            <l>Labrosse, and of the English meerely one man slaine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e104910">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>Thanks unto heaven whose arme was our defence, </l>
            <l>What's he that beates the French armes displaid? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e104940">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>A servant of mine, his name Bateman? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e104960">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>Ther's forty Angells for thy good daies service, </l>
            <l>And if thy merit retaine an Ancients place. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e104990">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>I thanke your honour. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e105010">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <l>My prisoner is an Anabaptist, all I desire is that I may </l>
            <l>convert him, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e105040">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <l>It must be in's drinke then, else hees none o'th right </l>
            <l>brethren; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e105070">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>Can noble Arguile, and worthy Clifton </l>
            <l>After these, toiles of bloud, and massacre, </l>
            <l>Let's quench our raging motions in the Grape, </l>
            <l>And in the French-mans Vine drinke his confusion? </l>
            <l>Proud France shall know that our Elizaes Name, </l>
            <l>Drives to confusion those that steale her Fame. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e105140">Ex. Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e105150">Enter Anne, and Vrsula. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e105160">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <p>Do'st thou not beleeve it? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e105180">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>Let me faile of my best wishes, and I doe, I cannot amuse my thoughts to't, thou maist as soone perswade me that a Spiders Web will catch a swarme of Bees as thou marry German! his head's like a Welch-mans Crest on St. Davies day? he lookes like a hoary Frost in December, now Venus blesse me, i'de rather ly by a Statue? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e105200">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Thou art pleasant still. </l>
            <l>In nat'rall things we see that Herbes, and Plants </l>
            <l>In autumne ever doe receive perfection, </l>
            <l>As they, so man, never attaines his height </l>
            <l>Till in the autumne of his growing age </l>
            <l>Experience like a Mistris beautifies him, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-011-b"/>
            <l>With silver haires, badges of experience. </l>
            <l>Of wisdome, honours, counsell, knowledge, arts, </l>
            <l>With all th'endowmens vertue hath in store. </l>
            <l>Contrarily greene headed youth </l>
            <l>Being in the spring or summer of his age, </l>
            <l>Is prone to surfets, riots, intemperancies, </l>
            <l>And all the stocke of ills that vice is queene of; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e105340">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>Thou wrests a good text to an ill sense? but none but fooles would ly in beds of snow that might couch in Roses? but it may bee Cozen; but it may bee Cuz? you follow the fashion of our Country Knights that marry your old London Widowes; tis but keeping a handsome Chamber-maide, they are necessary evills, and will serve with a small Dowery afterwards to make parsons wives! you know my meaning Cuz. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e105360">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <p>He brings wealth, promotion, and tis the way. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e105380">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>To your ruine; to your blacke father presently? cocke him with the herbe Moly that will put bloud in's cheekes? let him be dieted like your Barbary horse? heele neere stand to his tacklings else? feede him with Vipers flesh that will make his white head blacke? doost thou refuse youthfull Bateman to ly with wealthy Germane, reject a Mine of vertue, for a Mountaine of muck? Cupid blesse thee, for i'le sweare, he has blinded thee as blind as a Bat. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e105400">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>I lov'd young Bateman in my childish daies, </l>
            <l>Have vow'd to have him, and he againe to me, </l>
            <l>But what of that, foolish lovers vowes </l>
            <l>Like breath on steele, as soone are of, as on, </l>
            <l>German is wealthy and by him I gaine </l>
            <l>Recourse amongst the modest sagest dames? </l>
            <l>Wealth has a priviledge that beauty cannot, </l>
            <l>Bateman is young, embellish'd with a naturall, </l>
            <l>Active, and generous, unspotted beauty, </l>
            <l>German is old, indebted much to age, </l>
            <l>Yet like ould Aeson, gold can make him young, </l>
            <l>Gold like a second nature can elixate, </l>
            <l>Make the deformed faire, the faire seeme fowle, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-012-a"/>
            <l>And we that love not, must be tide to th'face, </l>
            <l>A sparkling eye, or a smooth pleading tongue </l>
            <l>Will not keepe hospitality with time. </l>
            <l>Maides that love young men gaine their loves by stealth, </l>
            <l>We that love old men, wed not man but wealth? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e105590">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>If I beleeve thee not; may I turne Nun before my probation? to be serious let me touch thy conscience? if young Bateman to whom I know tha'st vow'd thy faith? should at thy falsehood fall into some malevolencies in himselfe, or on thee; t'wood greive thee to have Ballads made on thee, to the tune of the inconstant Lover, and have thy periuries pind on euery Post? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e105610">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <p>Conscience, pray no more o'nt? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e105630">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>No introth for I thinke tha'st asmuch pleasure in't? as a hangd man has of his pardon, or a Dog with a Glasse bottle at's taile? see heres thy father, with him the man that must be, not the fore-man o'th Parish, but a bucke o'th first head. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e105650">Enter Boote, Germane </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e105660">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <p>My lovely Germane? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-germane" xml:id="ep000245-e105680">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>My fairest Mistris? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e105700">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>If I had not rather Kisse a muffe made of Cats-skins, then these mouldy chops of his, wood I might die an Anchoresse. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e105720">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <p>Now neece whats your conceit of this? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e105740">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>Faith Vncle i'me a woman? and they say a woman is a wether-Cocke for mine owne part some are I thinke? and when I thinke they are not i'le tell you my conceit, till then i'le pay you with thinking. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-germane" xml:id="ep000245-e105760">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <l>Sweet beauty, rumor, that betters nothing, </l>
            <l>But disproportionates every act, </l>
            <l>Gives it out thus; that you are affianc'd </l>
            <l>To youthfull Bateman? I wood not have the curse </l>
            <l>Of contract breaking fall upon my head, </l>
            <l>(If it be so, fairely I here acquit you, </l>
            <l>From all engagements twixt your selfe, and me) </l>
            <l>If not, like to a blessing I embrace you. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-012-b"/>
            <l>That joynture which your father most desir'de </l>
            <l>I have confirm'd, nothing now remaines, </l>
            <l>But your reply, or mine, or whose you please? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e105880">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Sir I am yours? </l>
            <l>I lov'de young Bateman with an inward joy </l>
            <l>Affected him beyond a common rate, </l>
            <l>Yet not so farr, but that I might reduce </l>
            <l>My vowes, and my affections to my will, </l>
            <l>For when I saw how disproportionable </l>
            <l>Our jarring fathers were! I then began </l>
            <l>To alienate all love; here I renue </l>
            <l>To whom it comes as free, as bright, and pure </l>
            <l>As are these unstaind Lampes beyond the Moone. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-germane" xml:id="ep000245-e105990">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>Which as a blessing from the heavens I take. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e106010">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <p>You shall be marryed instantly! and Girle thou shalt have one Bagg more for this, it gladdes me yet, thou art so free from Bateman. I look'd for other demonstrations! come German this night wee'le feast, to morrow thou shalt be wedd, At night enfold a maiden in thy bed. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e106030">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>Which if he does, may she dy of the pip, and goe to the grave as a Sallet for the wormes. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e106050">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="ep000245-e106060">
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="ep000245-e106070">
          <head>Actus secundus Scena Prima. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e106080">Enter Mortigue, Doysells, and the Frenchmen in Womens apparell with Pistols. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-mortigue" xml:id="ep000245-e106090">
            <speaker>Mor. </speaker>
            <l>Omit this Doisells, </l>
            <l>They now are healthing, and carrowsing deepe. </l>
            <l>Now is our time to worke a stratagem, </l>
            <l>Gaining these Trenches that oppresse the towne. </l>
            <l>Thus as we are, we passe without suspect, </l>
            <l>Nine Bona Robas nine stout Viragoes, </l>
            <l>Nine manly lasses which will stand the squeake; </l>
            <l>Jove went a wenching, as we goe to'th warrs; </l>
            <l>If this exploit take roote, we build a strength </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-013-a"/>
            <l>That nine months seidge cannot againe redeeme. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-doysells" xml:id="ep000245-e106200">
            <speaker>Do. </speaker>
            <l>The scotch language I am perfect in: </l>
            <l>Encaule your selves the enter on their guard </l>
            <l>Leroy's the word, till then let no man stir </l>
            <l>The second Leroy bids every man to kill. </l>
            <l>Close, and obserue; </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e106260">Enter Clifton, Bateman, Ioshua, Ball, Miles, Souldiers. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e106270">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>Each man betake him to his instruments </l>
            <l>Keepe safe this Port for 'tis the sole defence </l>
            <l>To our new Trenches, and raised Bul-warks; </l>
            <l>If any issue from the Towne give fire, </l>
            <l>And the Alarum shalbe answerd quicke; </l>
            <l>The French are subtle, and in various shapes, </l>
            <l>Combine themselves, therefore to gaine the best, </l>
            <l>Prevent the worst; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e106360">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <l>And they be women, may we not cease on'em for lawfull prize. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e106380">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>To women, and children, be mercifull, </l>
            <l>But trust none, the politicke Fox somtimes </l>
            <l>Wrapps himselfe within the Lions skin, </l>
            <l>So working prey upon the innocent Lambe, </l>
            <l>These French are subtle Foxes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e106440">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <l>I thought so for a man may smell their footings </l>
            <l>As farr as a fitchers; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e106470">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>And they be Foxes we may smell'em out? for as it is in the painted cloath? by fortune came a Fox where grew a pleasant Vine I will no Grapes said the Fox, the fruit is none of mine. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e106490">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Sir have you dispatched me? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e106510">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>My Hollidam thats true? </l>
            <l>What sudaine busines of so maine import </l>
            <l>Calls thee from the warrs, where thou seest </l>
            <l>Resolved spirits rate their lives at nought </l>
            <l>Regardles of all miseries, for honours; </l>
            <l>Thou a proficient in warrs Academ </l>
            <l>Hast profited well; the first day an Ancient </l>
            <l>In single duell taken? I tell thee Bateman </l>
            <l>It has wonne a great impression in my Lord. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-013-b"/>
            <l>Resolve thee so; I would not have thee goe </l>
            <l>To fish for shaddowes and let goe the substance, </l>
            <l>Thou know'st my meaning Bateman. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e106640">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>I conster it? </l>
            <l>That your suspition deemes it to be love, </l>
            <l>In sooth it needes not, such a constant rocke </l>
            <l>My love is built on that it cannot fall. </l>
            <l>I cannot fasten jelousie in my thoughts, </l>
            <l>Knowing her loyaltie; great excuses </l>
            <l>For my intended journey know I none: </l>
            <l>And to frame any were but negatives? </l>
            <l>Yet in my sleepes I have strange visions, </l>
            <l>Which waking I cannot thrust from memory. </l>
            <l>I doe beseech your licence, let me goe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e106760">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>My letters want but sealing, follow me </l>
            <l>To the Generalls Tent. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e106790">Exeunt. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e106800">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Fellow Bateman farwell commend me to my old wind-mill at Rudington, oh the Mooter dish, the Millers thumbe and the maide behinde the Hopper? tell mistresse Vrsula I fight for her sake, and will live as long as I can dy when I can no longer live, yet will love her in spight of her hart, in stead of nutmeggs, and ginger, I send her the three bawbees I got at Dundee. I will fly on her at my returne with the verses out of new Hero, and Leander, oh Vrsula, Vrsula pity me with a dildo, dildo, dillory? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e106820">
            <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
            <p>Commend me to the Bells of S. Maries, and tell'em my Chops water to chime all in? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e106840">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>As it is in the painted cloath, in morning still when thou doost rise see that in minde thou have to spend the day that doth ensue as bed might be thy Grave; commend me to my learned brother Spritchall the Cobler of Notingham brig? and bid him looke up, and give me a coale, wishing him good health, as my cat, and I was at the making hereof? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e106860">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <p>I will be mindfull of you all farewell. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-mortigue" xml:id="ep000245-e106880">
            <speaker>Mor. </speaker>
            <p>Now is the time make your appearance? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e106900">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Shoote shoote. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-doysells" xml:id="ep000245-e106920">
            <speaker>Doy. </speaker>
            <p>An the bred an gad man speare the bonny lasses. </p>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000245-014-a"/>
          <sp who="A11435-bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e106940">
            <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
            <p>Downe with the bonny Bels? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e106960">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>Have some compunction th'are the weaker Vessels for as it is in the painted cloath, be meeke, and gentle, and thy selfe shall finde a quiet conscience, and a tranquill minde. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e106980">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>By'th masse a prety boote halling, hansome pagies each one take one, and examine the prickers? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e107000">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>Thy counsels smels of piety? and thus I begin the conversion of a sinner!— um— she Kisses well verily againe I will edifie on your lips— are you of the Family of Love sister— ha— </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-mortigue" xml:id="ep000245-e107020">
            <speaker>Mor. </speaker>
            <p>An the beanes of me ise a pure lurden? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e107040">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>And what are you prety morsell. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-doysells" xml:id="ep000245-e107060">
            <speaker>Doy. </speaker>
            <p>An the dele an the crag ise a Lardes wife ganging to seeke my Lourden; </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-unassigned" xml:id="ep000245-e107080">
            <speaker>M. </speaker>
            <p>And you are ganging to your Lurden, that your Lurden may catch you by the crag, and claw you are the weame, till your guts garr haggergath, haggergath. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e107100">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>Will you be contented to leave the wicked, and live among the familists, exercising your body in the brether-hoods cause? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-mortigue" xml:id="ep000245-e107120">
            <speaker>Mor. </speaker>
            <p>An the Lard nare thee with an my bare bones. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e107140">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>Kisse againe then— in sincerity she Kisses open mouthed like a zealous sister— </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e107160">
            <speaker>Bal. </speaker>
            <p>And you can wash, and scoure, and helpe to launder the campe, and dresse the booties we steale, and at night be content to Kennell with me in straw. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-unassigned" xml:id="ep000245-e107180">
            <speaker>Sol. </speaker>
            <p>I by Saint Andrew? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e107200">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>Let us congregate our selves, and ponder on their miseries. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-doysells" xml:id="ep000245-e107220">
            <speaker>Doy. </speaker>
            <p>Now is the time each man draw, and fight. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e107240">Shoote, and Alarum. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e107250">Alarums, the French beate of, place themselves on the Walls hanging out a head, Enter Clifton, Souldiers. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e107260">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>Well fought my harts: though we have lost one man </l>
            <l>Whose head they basely pearch upon the Walls. </l>
            <l>Base minded Doysels cowardly Mortigue </l>
            <l>Though all advantages in warr are lawfull </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-014-b"/>
            <l>Th'are not commendable? you came like your selves </l>
            <l>Frenchifi'd truls, to scould us from our Trenches </l>
            <l>But not to beate us? come either of you single, </l>
            <l>And fight with Clifton, if not one, come both, </l>
            <l>And by my Countries honour; no man heere </l>
            <l>Shall dare to touch you but this arme of mine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-doysells" xml:id="ep000245-e107370">
            <speaker>Doy. </speaker>
            <l>Vex not thy selfe old man, tis but one head </l>
            <l>We came for more, but rest suffiz'd with this. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e107400">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>And for that one a thousand dastard French </l>
            <l>Shall deerely pay, Count I shall meete thee? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-mortigue" xml:id="ep000245-e107430">
            <speaker>Mor. </speaker>
            <l>Clifton thou maist! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e107450">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <p>By my Hollidam; our meeting will seeme rough our parting faire? make this thy quarrell, I pronounce thy Queene defective in beauty, vertues, honours, unto my mistris, Englands royall BESSE? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-mortigue" xml:id="ep000245-e107470">
            <speaker>Mor. </speaker>
            <l>Traitor thou lyest? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e107490">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>Have I sturd thy bloud? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-mortigue" xml:id="ep000245-e107510">
            <speaker>Mor. </speaker>
            <p>With such an overture, but thy barbarous head nothing can calme it? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e107530">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>When next we meete we'le try it? </l>
            <l>Each man unto his charge, for one mans head </l>
            <l>A thousand Frenchmen shall be slaughtered. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e107570">Ex. Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e107580">Enter Vrsula. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e107590">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>Good Wives, Widowes, and young wenches, pardon me, for I am touched in conscience to raile on my owne sexe, I blame not those mysogynifts that say women are froward inconstant, and what not; I protest I begin to mistrust mine owne thoughts, I'am quite out of love with all womens goodnes? fie upon us weather-cocks, of all things sublunary the worst of creatures, we painted sepulchers, rotten braveries, silly Ciphers untill mens figures supply us, and yet we cannot render 'em a constant minute; all this is manifest in my new Bride, she that yesterday gave faith to one, the next day married another; and now married shees sicke of the sullens, shee wants youth to enflame, and give satietie a fresh appetite; fie upon us Moone Calves, and created Fooles <pb xml:id="ep000245-015-a"/>be those men that credits us I see i'me cut off. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e107610">Enter young Bateman. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e107620">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>I weare that visage formerly I did, </l>
            <l>Six Moones has not so metamorphos'd me, </l>
            <l>But that I may be knowne? all my friends; </l>
            <l>My familiar sociates, and acquaintance </l>
            <l>Carelessely passe me with a heavy glance </l>
            <l>As if I were some rioter, or prodigall </l>
            <l>Who having ship wrackt reputation </l>
            <l>After an act of banquerout, compounds </l>
            <l>With debitor, and creditour; others </l>
            <l>Shake me by'th hand, but with such lenity </l>
            <l>As if I burnt them? or that I from the warrs </l>
            <l>Had brought home some diseases, as Killing </l>
            <l>As the Plague, or more infectious. </l>
            <l>My father whether for joy or sorrow, </l>
            <l>As teares be answerable to both passions, </l>
            <l>But he wep'd, cride welcome home, and sight, </l>
            <l>As if some drops of bloud fell from his hart </l>
            <l>Heaven has a hand in all things; if that </l>
            <l>My Nan be well, we will dispense with greifes, </l>
            <l>Of lower kindes Kind, cozen Vrsula. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e107830">Musique. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e107840">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>Y'are welcome home sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e107860">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>How fares my sweetest Nan? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e107880">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>Sooth badly, she has beene, Planet-strucke e're since you went? she fell into a Lethargy since noone, a kind of qualme came o're her stomacke like a Crampe or a Convulsion? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e107900">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>The meaning of this Musique? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e107920">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>We had a Wedding to day, and the young fry tickle trench-more. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e107940">Jervis, and Nan are in the Window. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e107950">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>A Wedding, and here this day. </l>
            <l>Blesse me what prodigious Object </l>
            <l>Is yond, that blasts mine eies, and like a theife, </l>
            <l>Steales my understanding! certes tis shee. </l>
            <l>Is it not speake Vrsula? </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000245-015-b"/>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e108010">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>I know not, for had she as many bodies as harts, she might be here, and yonder too. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e108030">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Now by my life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e108050">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>Nay sweare not; if you have any ill language to spare I'le send my Cozen to you presently. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e108070">Exeunt. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e108080">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Strange feares assaile my senses, and begins </l>
            <l>Conflicts of despaires, doubts, and feares, </l>
            <l>And but I have a resolution fixt </l>
            <l>On her fidelity; this frontispice </l>
            <l>And other entertainments might confirme </l>
            <l>Former presages. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e108150">Enter Anne, Vrsula. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e108160">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Who ist would speake with me? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e108180">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>One that may be jealous though he weares no yellow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e108200">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Her sight like to a cordiall has expell'd </l>
            <l>All former grosse suggestions, me thinkes </l>
            <l>I tast my happines e're I touch it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e108240">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Beshrew thy hart for this. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e108260">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>Beshrew your owne false, if their be ill tis of your owne begetting i'le provide Cocke-brothes, and caudles for your old Cock-sparow. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e108280">Exeunt. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e108290">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Shees dumbe with joy, and I like to a man </l>
            <l>Intranc'd with joyes un-utterable, cannot speake? </l>
            <l>But I have lost my selfe, I am awake, </l>
            <l>And see a substance more then dreamers doe, </l>
            <l>Thus in the armes of love I doe enfould thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e108350">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>I doe not know you— touch me not? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e108370">
            <speaker>Y. ba. </speaker>
            <l>I wonder then how I dare know my selfe, </l>
            <l>When thou forget'st me? I had thought </l>
            <l>Had I ben sullide with the sooty Moore, </l>
            <l>Or tan'd with heate like some Egiptian slave, </l>
            <l>Or spoted like the Persian Leopardes, </l>
            <l>Or in the worst forme can be termn'd, </l>
            <l>Or imagin'd, yet thou coulds have knowne me, </l>
            <l>I am thy Bateman Nan! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e108460">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>If you be Bateman; </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-016-a"/>
            <l>T'were best you traveld from my fathers ground </l>
            <l>Least he indite you? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e108500">
            <speaker>Y. ba. </speaker>
            <l>If he should, yet if thou stand the judge </l>
            <l>I know thou wilt acquit me of the crime? </l>
            <l>But thou art pleasant, and like to a tender nurse </l>
            <l>Heightens my infant joyes before it comes, </l>
            <l>Be not so strange, this nicety in you, </l>
            <l>Has not beene usuall. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e108570">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>It must be now for I am married. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e108590">
            <speaker>Y. ba. </speaker>
            <l>I know thou art, to me my fairest Nan. </l>
            <l>Our vowes were made to Heaven, and on Earth </l>
            <l>They must be ratifide, in part they are </l>
            <l>By giving of a pledge, a peice of Gold. </l>
            <l>Which when we broke, joyntly then we swore </l>
            <l>Alive or dead for to enjoy each other, </l>
            <l>And so we will spight of thy fathers frownes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e108670">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>You talke idely sir; these sparks of love </l>
            <l>That were twixt you, and I, are quite extinct </l>
            <l>Pacifie your selfe, you may speede better, </l>
            <l>Youle show much wit, and judgment if you doe? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e108720">
            <speaker>Y. ba. </speaker>
            <l>She floutes me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e108740">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <p>If you will be wise, and live one yeere a batchelour tis ten to one thats odds, I bury my husband, e're I weare out my wedding Ring. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e108760">
            <speaker>Y. ba. </speaker>
            <l>Ha! a Ring, and on the right finger two. </l>
            <l>Thou plaist the cruell murtherer of my joyes </l>
            <l>And like the deadly bullet from a Gun, </l>
            <l>Thy meaning kills me, e're thy words gets vent. </l>
            <l>Whose Ring is that? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e108820">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>My Husbands. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e108840">
            <speaker>Y. ba. </speaker>
            <l>And art thou married! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e108860">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>I am? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e108880">
            <speaker>Y. ba. </speaker>
            <l>When? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e108900">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>This Day? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e108920">
            <speaker>Y. ba. </speaker>
            <l>Accursed Day to whom? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e108940">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>To wealthy German? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e108960">
            <speaker>Y. ba. </speaker>
            <l>To wealthy misery? </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-016-b"/>
            <l>Now my presaging visions doe appeare, </l>
            <l>Th'unusuall gestures of my mornefull friends </l>
            <l>I now perceive was thine; false woman </l>
            <l>As subtle in deceit as thy first grandam, </l>
            <l>She but deceiv'd her selfe, deceiving man </l>
            <l>As thou her jmpe of subtilty has done. </l>
            <l>Strengthen me you ever Hallowed Powers, </l>
            <l>Guard me with patience that I may not curse, </l>
            <l>Because I lov'd her; be assured this, </l>
            <l>Alive or dead thy promise thou shall keepe </l>
            <l>I must, and will enjoy thee? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e109090">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>And may I tell you if youle stay my husbands Funerall. </l>
            <l>I'le promise you i'le mourne, and marry all in a month. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e109120">
            <speaker>Y. ba. </speaker>
            <l>Ah monstrous; she plaies with my disasters </l>
            <l>As boyes with bubbles blowne up into aire, </l>
            <l>You that have care of innocents be my guard </l>
            <l>Least I commit some outrage on my selfe. </l>
            <l>For such an overture, and flood of woes </l>
            <l>Surroundes me; that they almost droun'd </l>
            <l>My understanding; thy perivries shall be writ </l>
            <l>With pens of Diamonds upon Leaves of steele, </l>
            <l>And kept as statutes are to show the world. </l>
            <l>You constant Lovers that have truely lov'd </l>
            <l>Without foule thoughts or lustfull appetites, </l>
            <l>Come waile with me, and when your swelling brests </l>
            <l>Growes big with curses, come sit downe, and sigh </l>
            <l>Such an inconstant faireon I have met </l>
            <l>Whose deeds I shame to nominate, yet she </l>
            <l>Sham'd not to doe them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e109290">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Prety passion this ha, ha, ha? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e109310">
            <speaker>Y. ba. </speaker>
            <l>Take thy good night of goodnes; this night </l>
            <l>Thy bridall-night take leave of sacred vertue? </l>
            <l>Never thinke for to be honest more, </l>
            <l>Never keepe promise, for thou now maist sweare </l>
            <l>To any, thou never mean'st to doe? </l>
            <l>Hold swelling heart, for thou art tumbling downe </l>
            <l>A hill of desperation; darke thoughts </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-017-a"/>
            <l>Assaults my goodnes; but thou shalt keepe promise </l>
            <l>Alive or dead, I will enjoy thee yet. </l>
            <l>I have not curs'd thee yet, remember that; </l>
            <l>And when th'ast staind thy innocent sheetes with lust, </l>
            <l>And with saciety fild thy empty veines, </l>
            <l>Weari'd the night with wanton dalliances, </l>
            <l>More prime then Goates, or Monkeys in their prides; </l>
            <l>Call then to minde how pleasant this had bene </l>
            <l>Had it not bene adulterate; for German </l>
            <l>(Is not thy husband; tis Bateman is the best. </l>
            <l>I have not curs'd thee yet remember that) </l>
            <l>I'le muster up the forces of a man, </l>
            <l>To quench the rising flames that harbor here </l>
            <l>And if I can forget thee, by my hopes I will </l>
            <l>And never curse the Auth'resse of my ill. </l>
            <l>I have not curs'd thee yet! now remember </l>
            <l>Alive or dead tis I that must enjoy thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e109560">Exeunt. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e109570">Enter Vrsula. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e109580">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>By my virginity the Groome cryes to bed, night goes to Goast, how now another Niobe turn'd to stone, blesse me has the Conjurer bene here. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e109600">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Alive or dead I must, and will enjoy thee, </l>
            <l>It was my promise? I cannot chuse but weepe. </l>
            <l>I have not curs'd thee yet, remember that. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e109640">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>Hey day what inundations are here, will you come away, and the Groome should geld himselfe for anger there would be fine sport. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e109660">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <p>I have lost my selfe, and know not where I am! </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e109680">Enter Boote. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e109690">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <p>Come, come, I have daunc'd till every joynt about me growes stiffe but that which should be! to bed wench, the groome he's out-gone thee, he's warming the sheetes the first night I faith. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e109710">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>To bed! oh heavens, would it were to my grave </l>
            <l>So I might never here of my misdeedes </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-017-b"/>
            <l>I have not curs'd thee yet! remember that </l>
            <l>Alive or dead I must, and will enjoy thee </l>
            <l>How like the deadly towling of a Bell </l>
            <l>A peale of sadd presages were his words. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e109780">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <p>Ha, weeping; this is not customary on bridall-nights, Neece who was with your Cuz too night? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e109800">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>Vncle there was a certaine man </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e109820">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>I, I, but where is that certaine man </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e109840">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>There is the woman, but the certaine man is gon </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e109860">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>A certaine man indeede, for whom I now </l>
            <l>Could weepe a Sea, to wash out my pollutions? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e109890">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>But nimble Chaps, tongue Trotter, Neats-Toung Mrs Magpy </l>
            <l>What was this certaine man called </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e109920">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>With reverence Vncle his name was Bateman? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e109940">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>An undermining Knave, I will indite him, </l>
            <l>For daring to set foote upon my ground? </l>
            <l>This day his father hath arrested me </l>
            <l>Vpon an action of a thousand poundes </l>
            <l>A precontract betwixt his son, and thee </l>
            <l>To bed my wench, Bateman shall surely finde </l>
            <l>Me master of my words, when his proves winde. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e110020">Ex. Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e110030">Enter Mortigue meeting Clifton. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e110040">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>Thou keepst thy promise Mortigue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-mortigue" xml:id="ep000245-e110060">
            <speaker>Mor. </speaker>
            <l>In all things as befits a man of worth </l>
            <l>Thou hast abus'd my princely mistris name </l>
            <l>Sully'd her royalties with infamies, </l>
            <l>And from thy throat, as from a Serpents chaps. </l>
            <l>Belch'd poysons 'gainst the Dowager of France; </l>
            <l>To prove these false I made this sally forth </l>
            <l>Onely to combate thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e110140">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>By my Hollidam, </l>
            <l>I'me glad I've wak'd thy temper! </l>
            <l>The end still finds it selfe in every act, </l>
            <l>And so shalt thou in thy presumptuous braves? </l>
            <l>The honour of my mistris makes me young </l>
            <l>Her name shootes majesty into my lookes, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-018-a"/>
            <l>Valour into my hart, strength to this arme </l>
            <l>Which thou shalt feele to thunder on thy Helme, </l>
            <l>Guard thee Frenchman, i'me sure thou canst not fly; </l>
            <l>Bravely i'le kill thee, or else bravely dy. </l>
            <l>Th'art my prisoner Doysells. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e110260">Fight, Clifton disarmes him, Enter Grey, Arguile, Souldiers. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-mortigue" xml:id="ep000245-e110270">
            <speaker>Mor. </speaker>
            <l>Through chance of warre I am. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-arguile" xml:id="ep000245-e110290">
            <speaker>Arg. </speaker>
            <l>Hew him in peeces. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e110310">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>By my Hollidam? </l>
            <l>My life shall stand betweene him, and danger. </l>
            <l>He's my prisoner, and by the Law of Armes, </l>
            <l>Yeilding himselfe a Captive to our mercy, </l>
            <l>His life is ransomable; let our Generall </l>
            <l>Decree his ransome, and after dispose of him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e110380">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>Noble Clifton his ransome is thine owne, </l>
            <l>Dispose of him as thou pleasest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e110410">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>By my Hollidam, and will? </l>
            <l>There take thy Armes, returne backe to Leith </l>
            <l>With our best convoy; I tell thee Mortigue </l>
            <l>My hatred is not capitall, though honour, </l>
            <l>And warrs necessity made me storme; </l>
            <l>When to these walls thou seest my white coates come </l>
            <l>With scaling ladders to assault the Towne </l>
            <l>Be mercifull as I have bin to thee, </l>
            <l>This is all Cliftons ransome. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-mortigue" xml:id="ep000245-e110510">
            <speaker>Mor. </speaker>
            <l>I shall report thee noble! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e110530">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>Thanks noble Clifton, </l>
            <l>Thou still ad'st honour to thy Countries fame, </l>
            <l>Make scaling Ladders, for we straight intend, </l>
            <l>By heavens assistance to mount these walls, </l>
            <l>Courage brave spirits, every act finds end, </l>
            <l>Weele teach the Frenchman keepe within his bounds </l>
            <l>Or send him home full of heroicke wounds </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e110610">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e110620">Young Bateman ins shirt, a halter about his necke. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-young_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e110630">
            <speaker>Y. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>It tis resolv'd! life is too burthensome, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-018-b"/>
            <l>I've borne while I can, and have supprest </l>
            <l>All insurrections pale Death has made. </l>
            <l>It is my terrour that I live to thinke </l>
            <l>I beare a life that is offensive to me. </l>
            <l>Pale monster in thy meagerest aspect </l>
            <l>Come, and affront me; fill thy unpauncht nerves </l>
            <l>With my harts bloud; till with the overture </l>
            <l>Thy never satisfied maw be sated? </l>
            <l>But cowardly monster thou approchest none </l>
            <l>But those that fly thee, and like to greatnes </l>
            <l>Wouldst be so elivated for doing good, </l>
            <l>That of thy selfe thou never didst intend. </l>
            <l>Poore Snakes that are in worldly sorrowes sowrst </l>
            <l>Cannot participate thy Ebon Dart. </l>
            <l>Tis said thou art not partiall, and dost winde </l>
            <l>The Prince, the begger, and the potentate </l>
            <l>All in one mould; but they doe falsifie </l>
            <l>That say thou art so tiranously just, </l>
            <l>For I have sought thee through the unpend groves, </l>
            <l>The shady cells where melancholly walkes, </l>
            <l>And eccho-like thou answerst me with Death, </l>
            <l>But darst not show thy face; the worlds monarch </l>
            <l>In three fits of an Ague di'd. Some flyes, </l>
            <l>Some silly gnats can kill! let me consume </l>
            <l>then maist thou brag thy conquest, that thou slewst </l>
            <l>What neyther love nor hatred could destroy. </l>
            <l>Since thou disdainst me, I disdaine thy power, </l>
            <l>There be a thousand waies to cozen Death </l>
            <l>Behold a Tree, just at her doore a fruitlesse Tree </l>
            <l>That has in autumne cast her leavy boughs </l>
            <l>Sorry to show such fruit as she produces. </l>
            <l>The night seemes silent, sleepe charmes the house, </l>
            <l>And now the periurd woman is a topping, </l>
            <l>I'le clime as high as she, yet i'le not rest, </l>
            <l>My airy ghoast shall find her where she lyes, </l>
            <l>And to her face divulge her perjuries. </l>
            <l>Night be auspicious, draw thy sable weedes, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-019-a"/>
            <l>For day-light is a asham'd of her blacke deeds </l>
            <l>One twich will do't, and then I shall be wed </l>
            <l>As firme unto my grave, as to her bed. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e111050">Falls, hangs, Enter old Bateman ins shirt, &amp; Torch. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-old_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e111060">
            <speaker>O. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>I've miss'd my boy out of his bed to night </l>
            <l>Heavens grant that he be well, for in his eyes </l>
            <l>Sad discontentment sits! till yesterday </l>
            <l>I never saw him so propense to sorrow. </l>
            <l>Nor deepely touch'd with distemperature, </l>
            <l>When I began to tell him of his mistris </l>
            <l>Which I in violence of wordes branded </l>
            <l>With damned perjury; as Heaven knowes </l>
            <l>She has consum'd her goodnes; then would he </l>
            <l>Sit by, and sigh, and with salt teares trilling </l>
            <l>Downe his cheekes, entreat me not to name her, </l>
            <l>Curse her I must not I then would he steale to bed, </l>
            <l>As full of mournfull sorrowes as a sinner. </l>
            <l>Tis almost morne and I suspect him here </l>
            <l>Hovering about this house! oft would he say </l>
            <l>He woo'd her underneath a Plume-Tree, </l>
            <l>And underneath that Tree he vow'd to sit, </l>
            <l>And tell his sorrowes to the gummy boughes </l>
            <l>Though she disdaind to here them? protect me! </l>
            <l>Good Angells guard me, what heavy sight is this </l>
            <l>That like a sullen sadnes reaves my sense, </l>
            <l>Prove false mine eies that this may prove untrue? </l>
            <l>Better you never had seene then to see this. </l>
            <l>Leave your slimy cesternes, and drop out; </l>
            <l>Tis he, tis he, would I could tell a ly </l>
            <l>The falsest one that e're was tould by man </l>
            <l>That this might prove untrue; but tis in vaine </l>
            <l>To darke the Sunne, or wrastle 'gainst the truth </l>
            <l>Murtherers looke out, i'le rowze the thunderer, </l>
            <l>To rowze you from your sleepes! false feinds come out, </l>
            <l>And see a deede, the day wilbe asham'd of </l>
            <l>Caus'd by your perjuries. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000245-019-b"/>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e111390">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>Whoes that which calls </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000245-e111410">Boote, Anne, Vrsula, above. </stage>
            <l>With horrid terrour, and such affrightments </l>
            <l>As when skath fires devast our vilages, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-old_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e111440">
            <speaker>O. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Looke this way monster see thou adultresse </l>
            <l>Behold the miserablest Map of woe </l>
            <l>That ever father mourn'd for; my poore boy </l>
            <l>Hard-harted fate that brought thee to this end, </l>
            <l>Hated Vipers they that were the causers, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e111500">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>How darst thou Bateman come upon my ground </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-old_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e111520">
            <speaker>O. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Curs'd be thy ground, and curs'd be all trees </l>
            <l>That brings forth such abortive fruit as this. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e111550">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>Ha, ha, has— he hang'd himselfe, and sav'd justice a labor! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e111570">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <p>I never look'd for better end of him, he had a malevolent aspect in his lookes, ha, ha, ha! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-old_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e111590">
            <speaker>O. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Laughst thou Crocadile? </l>
            <l>Are miseries lamented with contempts? </l>
            <l>The bookes of fate are not so closely shut, </l>
            <l>But they may open, and record the scornes </l>
            <l>Dwelling in every Region of thy face? </l>
            <l>A fixt decree may be set downe for thine, </l>
            <l>And thou maist Swan-like sing a Funerall O'de, </l>
            <l>Who then shall laugh at thee? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e111680">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>I laugh to see, how well sorrow becomes thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-old_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e111700">
            <speaker>O. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Such dire becomings maist thou never want, </l>
            <l>Thou that wert once the Jewell of these eies, </l>
            <l>Looke here, and see the ruines of pale death. </l>
            <l>How soone a Gorgeous Pallace is suncke downe; </l>
            <l>Though he has surfetted upon this peece </l>
            <l>He has not tane the colour of his cheeke, </l>
            <l>Nature contests with death, and will out-doe him; </l>
            <l>Canst not thou spare one teare to balme him in, </l>
            <l>Nor lend a sigh as sorry for his fall? </l>
            <l>If not to day i'le come againe to morrow, </l>
            <l>So thou wilt shed two teares, and one poore sigh, </l>
            <l>Then gentle Charon will assigne him wafftage; </l>
            <l>Thy greifes are violent, and worke within </l>
            <l>Tis a fowle signe of an unpersant hart </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-020-a"/>
            <l>When as the eyes cannot impart a teare. </l>
            <l>Since none of you will weepe, i'le weepe alone </l>
            <l>Till Niobe like my teares convert to stone. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e111880">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Had you disciplind your sonne in's youth </l>
            <l>You might then have prevented your teares? </l>
            <l>Cause he was bad, and I did shun his evils, </l>
            <l>Must I be held the cause'res of his ils? </l>
            <l>Must my vertues beget his perversnes, </l>
            <l>Or my obedience breede his shamefull death, </l>
            <l>If the World ballance me uprightly just </l>
            <l>I care not then which way you turne the Scales; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-old_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e111970">
            <speaker>O. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Worse then the worst that ever could be nam'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e111990">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <p>My best counsell is that you bury him as the custome of the Country is, and drive a stacke through him; so perhaps I that had no quietnes with him whil'st he liv'd, may sleepe in peace now he's dead. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-old_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e112010">
            <speaker>O. Bat. </speaker>
            <l>I will not curse thee, t'was my boyes request </l>
            <l>Such deedes as these sinke not in oblivion, </l>
            <l>The justnes of my cause I leave to Heaven. </l>
            <l>Maist thou live mother of many children, </l>
            <l>And may they prosper better then did mine. </l>
            <l>Come poore boy these armes have borne thee oft </l>
            <l>I'le have thy picture hung up in my Chamber, </l>
            <l>And when I want thee, I will weepe to that </l>
            <l>Deaths Leaden Plummets draw thine eielids downe, </l>
            <l>Since none will sing sadd obsequies but I, </l>
            <l>I'le call the Linnet, Red-brest, and the Throsle, </l>
            <l>The Nightingale shall beare the burthen two </l>
            <l>For she is exsquisite in tragicke notes, </l>
            <l>Weele have a Funerall hymne, and o're thy herse, </l>
            <l>This womans perjuiries i'le pen in verse. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e112170">Enter </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e112180">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>How now cozen weeping? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e112200">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>Troth Cozen, </l>
            <l>Though griefes of lower kinds assaile me not, </l>
            <l>I never was so touch'd unto the hart, </l>
            <l>Mine eies so flexible are to melt in teares </l>
            <l>I cannot stop'em; I shall be still affraid </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-020-b"/>
            <l>To walke to'th doore when I behold this Tree, </l>
            <l>For feare his Ghost haunte me! I wonder much, </l>
            <l>You could forbeare from passionating. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e112290">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <p>Affraid on's Ghost, as much as of a picture painted o'th wall! thats just like we fooles that rub our shins 'gainst the bed posts in our dreames, and then sweare the faries, pinchd us? he swore he would have me quicke or dead. Let him ly still in's grave I will in my bed, and let consequents prove the rest? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e112310">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>Ghosts Hobgoblins, will with wispe, or Dicke a Tues-day. </l>
            <l>Thy husband wench this morne journyes to New-Castle </l>
            <l>And hardly will returne these twelve Moones, </l>
            <l>Let's feast with him, for Ghosts, and such like toyes </l>
            <l>Leave them to foolish dotards, girles, and boyes. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e112370">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="ep000245-e112380">
        <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="ep000245-e112390">
          <head>Actus Tertius Scena Prima. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e112400">Enter, Anne hastily, pursuing Vrsula, with lights. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e112410">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Keepe of, keepe backe, I charge thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e112430">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>Las cozen i'me not infectious my breath cannot blast you? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e112450">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>It haunts me as my shaddow or a vision? </l>
            <l>It will not let me rest sleepe, nor eat, </l>
            <l>The barricoded doores and iron locks. </l>
            <l>No sooner shut but like a new clasp'd booke </l>
            <l>Their leavy hindges streightway fall asunder, </l>
            <l>And it gets in; I wonder tis not here, </l>
            <l>This is a gentle respit, and not usuall, </l>
            <l>Since German went I never had so much; </l>
            <l>It plaies the centinnell at my beds feete? </l>
            <l>And but it wants the rosie coloured face </l>
            <l>Whom meager death has plaid the Horse-Leech with, </l>
            <l>It would not seeme so ghostly in these eies. </l>
            <l>It beares the perfect forme it us'd to doe. </l>
            <l>As if it never knew immortality </l>
            <l>Nor wasted underneath a Hill of Clay. </l>
            <l>Sometimes as curious limners have pourtraid </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-021-a"/>
            <l>Teares trilling from the weeping Niobe, </l>
            <l>That some would sweare the very picture wept, </l>
            <l>And art of nature got the mastery? </l>
            <l>So did I guesse affluxe of brinish teares </l>
            <l>Came from this Aiery, and unfadom'd Ghost? </l>
            <l>And could the Painters of this age draw sighes </l>
            <l>I could demonstrate sighes, and heavy groanes </l>
            <l>As if a sensible hart had broke in twaine? </l>
            <l>Then would it turne, and cry false woman. </l>
            <l>And leave me to descant on the rest! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e112720">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>You tell me of an object, and a strange one, </l>
            <l>But whose is the resemblance? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e112750">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>I theirs the point, </l>
            <l>For that I must be pardon'd; oh my shame </l>
            <l>That I should be the cause'res of a deed, </l>
            <l>I blush to nominate. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e112800">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>Has it no name! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e112820">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Yes sweete Vrsula, </l>
            <l>But such a one as sadly agrauates </l>
            <l>My woes in repetition; pray leave me </l>
            <l>I am addicted to contemplation </l>
            <l>But rest within my call. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e112880">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>Tis but your fond conceit; I've heard you say that dreames and visions were fabulous; and yet one time I dreamt fowle water ran through the floore, and the next day the house was on fire; you us'd to say Hobgoblins, Fairies, and the like were nothing but our owne affrightments, and ye oh my troth Cuz I once dream'd of a young batchelour, and was ridd with a Night-Mare. But come, so my conscience be cleere I never care how fowle my dreames are. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e112900">Exit. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e112910">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Thou now hast touch'd the point, </l>
            <l>Tis conscience is the Larum Bell indeede </l>
            <l>That makes us sensible of our good or bad? </l>
            <l>You that are Lovers, by me you may perceive </l>
            <l>What is the burden of a troubled minde, </l>
            <l>Take heede of vowes, and protestations </l>
            <l>Which wantonly in dalliancies you make, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-021-b"/>
            <l>The eie of Heaven is on you, and your oaths </l>
            <l>Are registred; which if you breake, blesse me. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e113010">Enter Ghost. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-ghost" xml:id="ep000245-e113020">
            <speaker>Gho. </speaker>
            <l>Thou can'st not fly me, </l>
            <l>There is no Cavern in the Earth's, vast entrailes </l>
            <l>But I can through as pearcant as the light, </l>
            <l>And finde thee, though thou wer't entomb'd in stone, </l>
            <l>Thou can'st not catch my unsubstantiall part, </l>
            <l>For I am aire, and am not to be touch'd. </l>
            <l>From flameing fires of burning Phlegeton, </l>
            <l>I have a time limited to walke, </l>
            <l>Vntill the morning Cocke shall summon me </l>
            <l>For to retire to misty Erebus. </l>
            <l>My pilgrimage has no cessation, </l>
            <l>Vntill I bring thee with me to the place </l>
            <l>Where Rhadamant, and sable Aeacus dwell </l>
            <l>Alive or dead, tis I that must enjoy thee, </l>
            <l>To tell the story where we spirits live </l>
            <l>Would plucke Vermilion from thy Rosie cheekes, </l>
            <l>And make them pale, as Snowy Apennines, </l>
            <l>And from thine eies draw liquid streames of teares </l>
            <l>More full of issue then a steepy Fountaine, </l>
            <l>Alive or dead I must, and will enjoy thee, </l>
            <l>Thinke on thy promise. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e113240">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Distraction like an Ague seizes me, </l>
            <l>I know not whether I see here, or speake, </l>
            <l>My intellectuall parts are frozen up </l>
            <l>At sight of thee, thou fiery Effigies </l>
            <l>Of my wrong'd Bateman. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e113300">Enter Boote, Vrsula. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e113310">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>What weeping againe? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e113330">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Doe you not see it? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e113350">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>See! what? I see nothing but a Bird fly o're the house. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e113370">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>Nor I, but a blinde Buzzard lookes as like her husband as may be. </p>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000245-022-a"/>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e113390">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Are you blinde, or will you make your selves so? </l>
            <l>See! how like a dreadfull magistrate it standes, </l>
            <l>Still pointing at me the blacke offender; </l>
            <l>And like a cunning poysoner, will not kill me, </l>
            <l>But lets me linger on, for daies, and yeares. </l>
            <l>It stares, beckons, points, to the peece of Gold </l>
            <l>We brake betweene us; looke, looke there, here there! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e113470">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>I see nothing, perceive nothing, feele nothing! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e113490">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>Nor I, no quicke thing, neyther cloath'd nor nak'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e113510">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <p>No, no, no! you drancke Baulme, Burrage or Buglosse last night to bed-ward, that makes you thinke on your dreames this morning. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e113530">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>But I will too't, hug, and embrace it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ghost" xml:id="ep000245-e113550">
            <speaker>Gho. </speaker>
            <l>Thy time is not yet come; i'm now exild </l>
            <l>I may not touch thee while thou art with chil'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e113580">Exit Ghost. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e113590">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>you doe not heare it neyther? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e113610">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>Whom should we heare? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e113630">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Young Batemans visage. </l>
            <l>In every limbe as perfect as he liv'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e113660">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>If it be so, 'tis done by sorcery. </l>
            <l>The father has combined, with some witch, </l>
            <l>To vex thy quiet patience, and gaine credit, </l>
            <l>That he would haunt thee dead, as oft he said, </l>
            <l>Hell can put life into a senseles body, </l>
            <l>And raise it from the grave, and make it speake; </l>
            <l>Vse all the faculties alive it did, </l>
            <l>To worke the Devill's hellish stratagems! </l>
            <l>If I but finde he deales in exorcimes </l>
            <l>I'le make him burne to pacifie the Witch, </l>
            <l>But doe not beleive it girle. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e113780">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>'Tis vanish'd in an instant! </l>
            <l>I will not be too confident in my eies, </l>
            <l>Will you grant me leave to visit Bateman? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e113820">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>Visit mine enemy? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e113840">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>I have an inward sorrow bids me doe it, </l>
            <l>I did him wrong to gybe his miseries </l>
            <l>When as he bore the dead Corpes in his armes, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-022-b"/>
            <l>My Genius tels me, I shall have no rest </l>
            <l>Till I have made contrition; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e113900">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>But not to him. </l>
            <l>I'de rather live subiected to a Turke, </l>
            <l>Goe not my girle, i'le feast all thy senses, </l>
            <l>Thy pallat shall with viands be suppli'd, </l>
            <l>Thine eares with heavenly rapture live inspir'd, </l>
            <l>Thine eies with sportive action, and delight, </l>
            <l>Thou shalt have Musique to consume the day, </l>
            <l>And wast the night. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e113990">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Musique! harsh Ravens croake? </l>
            <l>Scritch-Owles shreile, the augurers of night, </l>
            <l>Are first companions for my mellancholy, </l>
            <l>I must goe see him; if this apparition </l>
            <l>Appeare not in his sight, my conjecture </l>
            <l>Shall judge it nothing, but my conscience </l>
            <l>That finds me guilty for my blacke offence; </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e114070">Exit. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e114080">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>Follow her Neece, </l>
            <l>She heares a Plurisie of greifes about her, </l>
            <l>And much I feare the weakenes of her braine </l>
            <l>Should draw her to some ominous exigent! </l>
            <l>Would she had ne're, infring'd her vow to Bateman </l>
            <l>Or I had ne're knowne this wealthy German! </l>
            <l>If he prove harsh to her, i'le make him know, </l>
            <l>An inforc'd hate to vengeance is not slow. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e114170">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e114180">Enter Joshua, his Cat in a string, Miles, Ball. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e114190">
            <speaker>Bal. </speaker>
            <p>Nay sweete Jo. be persuaded. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e114210">
            <speaker>Io. </speaker>
            <p>Persuade me, I scorne to be persuaded? Ball thou art Heathnish, for the offence is foule which thou would'st cloake, I'me not to be persuaded, I will doome the creature, and burne the cloake of her knavery; yet in sincerity I will doe nothing without good colour. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-miles" xml:id="ep000245-e114230">
            <speaker>Mil. </speaker>
            <p>Thy colours, Jo. were better bestowed on course waiting women Madam Makeroones that sell paintings, and stop holes with plaister of Paris. </p>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000245-023-a"/>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e114250">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>Miller, Miller, thou art not mealy mouth'd; those be the Heathen bables, the May-poles of time, and Pageants of vanity, but I will convince them of error, and scoure their pollutions away with the waters of my exhortations. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e114270">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Why should'st thou hang thy Cat? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e114290">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>Thou art saucy, Miller, &amp; ought'st not to Cathechise me so, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e114310">
            <speaker>Bal. </speaker>
            <p>And it were but for Country sake. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e114330">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Sweete Jo. consider thy Cat is thy Countriman, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e114350">
            <speaker>Bal. </speaker>
            <p>Hang a poore Cat for killing a Mouse? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e114370">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Knowing the proverbe too, Cat after Kinde. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e114390">
            <speaker>Bal. </speaker>
            <p>As it is in the painted cloath too; when the Cat's away the Mouse will play. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e114410">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>I, but as it is in the painted cloath, beware in time for too much patience, to Dog or Cat will breede too much offence. She did kill a Mouse, I but when? on the forbidden day, and therefore she must die on Munday. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e114430">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Then shall thy zeale be proclaim'd, for hanging thy Cat on Munday for killing a Mouse on Sunday. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e114450">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>Miller thou art drunke in thy enormities, and art full of the cake of iniquity. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e114470">Gray, Arguile, Clifton. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e114480">
            <speaker>Bal. </speaker>
            <p>Well, to thy execution we commit thee. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e114500">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>Blessed be the instruments of silence; poore Pusse take it not ill that I must hang thee, by that meanes I free thee from bawling Mastifs, and snarling Currs; I have brought thee up of a whelpe, and now will have a care of thy end. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e114520">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <p>A notable exhortation. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e114540">Ties her. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e114550">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <p>List to the sequell; </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e114570">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>When thou art dead, thou shalt not curse me, for my proceedings shall be legall; thou art at the barre of my mercy, and thus I ascend to judgment, as it is in the painted cloath. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e114590">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <p>Harken the inditement. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e114610">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>Tybert the Cat; as it is in the painted cloath, of the Bull, and Cocke, sometimes house-keeper, drudger or scourer to Marmaduke Ioshua, Limner alias painter-stainer, &amp; now the correcter or extirper of vermine, as Rats, Mice, and other waspish animalls; thou art here indited by thy deare Master Marmaduke <pb xml:id="ep000245-023-b"/>Ioshua for breaking of the high-day, what sayst thou for thy selfe? guilty or not guilty? hah. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e114630">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <p>Would she could mew non guilty. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e114650">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>Know'st thou not, thou silly Cat, that thy brethren will not Kill the Calfe nor rost the Mutton nor boyle their flesh Pots on the high-day? was it not decree'd by our learned brother Abolt Cabbidge, Cobler of Amsterdam, that they should be held uncleane, and not worthy of the meanes that did it, and did not expect Cratchet Coole his proud flesh in the Leene for making insurrection on the high day? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e114670">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <p>A point well watred. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e114690">
            <speaker>Ios </speaker>
            <p>Did not Nadab the Sowe-gelder make a gaunt of his gelt for being cumbersome on the high-day? Ha thy silence argues guilt; hast thou not seene the whole conventicle of brothers, and sisters walke to St. Anns, and not so much as a fructifying Kisse on the high— </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e114710">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <p>It seemes the elect Kisse weekely. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e114730">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>And must thou kill a Mouse? oh thou wicked Cat; could'st not turne up the white of the eie for the poore creature? thou gluttonous Cat, thou art now arraigned, I adjudge thee to be hanged this munday, for killing a Mouse yesterday being the high-day. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e114750">Offers to hang her. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e114760">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <p>Stay, stay, a pardon, a pardon! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e114780">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>I am hot in my zeale, and fiery in expedition, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e114800">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <p>Wee'le talke with you hereafter. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e114820">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>I was executing a point of justice, equity, and conscience, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e114840">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <p>A pleasant Tragecomedy, the Cat being scap't, What Trumpets this? </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e114860">Enter Crosse. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-crosse" xml:id="ep000245-e114870">
            <speaker>Cros. </speaker>
            <l>Monlucke, Bishop of Valens, </l>
            <l>Newly anchor'd in the haven of Inskeith, </l>
            <l>Desires safe convoy by your honours forces, </l>
            <l>From the red Brayes to Edenborough Castle, </l>
            <l>The rest on entervew he will impart. </l>
            <l>Such entertainment, as the warre affourds </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-024-a"/>
            <l>The Drum the Fiffe, the thundering Cannon, </l>
            <l>The shrill Trumpets, and all war-like Cymballs, </l>
            <l>Such Musique as in warrs Souldiers measure </l>
            <l>Bestow on him; come he in warr or peace </l>
            <l>He shalbe welcome? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e114990">
            <speaker>Io. </speaker>
            <l>Oh that prophane surplesse, ho, ho, ho. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e115010">Enter Monlucke attendant saluts. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-monlucke" xml:id="ep000245-e115020">
            <speaker>Mon. </speaker>
            <l>Mary, King Dolphins wife, Dowager of France, </l>
            <l>And heire apparant to the Scottish Crowne, </l>
            <l>Hearing of devastations in her Lands, </l>
            <l>And the oppressions that her neighbour Princesse </l>
            <l>With rough hostility grindes her people, </l>
            <l>Me her Legat she sends to Edenburgh, </l>
            <l>To parley with her Mother the Queene Regent, </l>
            <l>And Article A peace twixt her deare sister, </l>
            <l>The Queene of England, and the Lords of Scotland. </l>
            <l>If our conditions may be made with honour, </l>
            <l>This is my message. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e115140">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>Eyther for peace or warre. </l>
            <l>The Queene my Mistris now is arm'd for both, </l>
            <l>For like a vertuous Princesse, and a Mother </l>
            <l>O're us her loving subjects, and her sons, </l>
            <l>She knowing a Kings security rests, </l>
            <l>In the true love, and welfare of her people, </l>
            <l>Rais'd this hostility for to guard her selfe, </l>
            <l>Not to offend, but to defend her owne, </l>
            <l>Her Secretary Sicill now attends </l>
            <l>On the like Embasy for Edenburgh, </l>
            <l>Whither your selfe shall safely be convoy'de. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-monlucke" xml:id="ep000245-e115260">
            <speaker>Mon. </speaker>
            <l>You are an honourable foe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e115280">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>Will the Queene, </l>
            <l>Lay by her nicety, rough fil'd phrase, </l>
            <l>And not articulate too much with England? </l>
            <l>For by the power of warr e're two suns rise </l>
            <l>Weele mount the walls of Leith, and sacrifize, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-024-b"/>
            <l>Her guilded Towres, and her French insulters; </l>
            <l>In flames of fire; we vow to hazard lives, </l>
            <l>And honours in the enterprize. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e115370">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e115380">Enter Anne, with a Torch, Vrsula, Bateman, wailing his Picture. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e115390">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <p>Softly, softly; fie on your creaking shooes, what noise they make; shut the Dores close, it does not here us a jot, looke well to the Darneicke Hangings, that it play not the Court Page with us. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e115410">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>Heer's not so much as a shaddow to affright us, for mine owne part neyther Incubus nor Sucubus can do't; I feare not what a quicke thing can doe, and I thinke y'ore dead things are too quiet to say any harme </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e115430">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Yet all is cleere, no frightfull vision </l>
            <l>Nor Ghostly apparition hauntes me yet; </l>
            <l>Yonders thy father, good powres assist me, </l>
            <l>That I may gaine his patience to heare me, </l>
            <l>And I am hartily satisfied. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-old_bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e115490">
            <speaker>O. Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Pigmalion doated on the peece he made, </l>
            <l>So doe not I upon thy pourtraiture. </l>
            <l>I doe but hang thy faire resemblance here </l>
            <l>To tell me of my immortality. </l>
            <l>How sensible young Cedars are o'th winde, </l>
            <l>When as the aged Oake affronts all stormes </l>
            <l>'Tis death, and natures fault, for the Diamond, </l>
            <l>Of blooming youth, despise decaying age. </l>
            <l>He might have tane thee el'ce, and left thee boy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e115590">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <p>Whom talkes he too? my life Coz, he has a ghost too! Yet I see nothing. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e115610">
            <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
            <l>How now Hyena; why camst thou hyther? </l>
            <l>Com'st thou againe to gybe my miseries? </l>
            <l>Has thy maligneing harted father sent thee </l>
            <l>To scoffe my sorowes? keepe of I charge thee, </l>
            <l>Thou did'st bewitch my poore boy with a Kisse, </l>
            <l>Thy breath is sure infectious, and I feare </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-025-a"/>
            <l>Their's something in thee smells of sorcery. </l>
            <l>Stand at distance. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e115700">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Good sir, use patience, </l>
            <l>That in extremity is soveraigne Balme, </l>
            <l>Teares be my witnes I come to comfort you, </l>
            <l>Yet I see nothing. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e115750">
            <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Teares? 'tis impossible! </l>
            <l>Marble will drop, and melt against the raine, </l>
            <l>And from the cragy Rocks, Fountainous Flouds </l>
            <l>Oft get inforced issues; but to gaine </l>
            <l>Relenting teares from thy obdurate harte </l>
            <l>'Tis impossible, as to force Fire from snow </l>
            <l>Water from flint, say the Sun shall not shine, </l>
            <l>As well upon the begger as the King, </l>
            <l>That is alike indifferent to all. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e115850">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>Good sir remember, </l>
            <l>Forgivenes is an Atribute of Heaven. </l>
            <l>She has a harty sorrow for her sinnes, </l>
            <l>And comes to make attonement, if you please. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e115900">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Still I nothing any where. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e115920">
            <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Pray listen; </l>
            <l>Would not that Physitian be well hang'd </l>
            <l>That for his practise sake Kills his patient, </l>
            <l>And after pleades a sorrow to his freinds? </l>
            <l>She weepes, an evidence of a harty sorrow, </l>
            <l>My boy would not have seene her weepe thus long, </l>
            <l>But hee'd have minister'd comfort I my teares </l>
            <l>Playes the theife with mine eies too. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e116010">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Yet all is safe; sure it was but my dreames, </l>
            <l>Sir you had a son, blesse me 'tis here now. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000245-e116040">Enter Ghost. </stage>
            <l>In the same figure that it us'd to be. </l>
            <l>Peace is more deare, and pretious unto me </l>
            <l>Then a nights rest, to a man turmoil'd in Law. </l>
            <l>My eies set heere un-mou'd, i'le gaze with thee, </l>
            <l>Vntill the windowes of my head drop out. </l>
            <l>But then my minde wilbe afflicted too. </l>
            <l>For what is unseene there, is visible here. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-025-b"/>
            <l>Leade me, i'le follow; though to a desart, </l>
            <l>Or any uncouth place, worke thy vengeance, </l>
            <l>And doe not torture me alive; neyther </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ghost" xml:id="ep000245-e116150">
            <speaker>Gho. </speaker>
            <l>All things keepe their time! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e116170">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Let all times daughters which are daies, convert </l>
            <l>To one day, and bring me to my period, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e116200">
            <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Whom converses she withall? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e116220">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>To her unseene fancies. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e116240">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>See with eies of wonder! see! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e116260">
            <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
            <l>What should I see? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e116280">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Aske you what? why 'tis your son, </l>
            <l>Just as he di'd, looke, looke, there, here, there. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e116310">
            <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Is this thy sorow, com'st thou to mocke me? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e116330">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Just heavens not I! see how it smiles on you, </l>
            <l>On me it hurles a dejected looke. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e116360">Takes the Picture. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e116370">
            <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Because I hang his Picture ne're my bed, </l>
            <l>Com'st thou to laugh me! out out, fond-ling noe! </l>
            <l>See thus I gaze on it; stroke his snowy hands, </l>
            <l>And prune the curled tresses of his locks, </l>
            <l>Which the Arts-man neatly has dishevell'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e116430">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>Good sir; have patience, her's is true sorow, </l>
            <l>And not derision. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e116460">Stands betweene the Picture, &amp; Ghost. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e116470">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Another Ganimede! </l>
            <l>This eye, and yon'd, are one? this front, that lip, </l>
            <l>This cheeke, a litle ruddier showes then that, </l>
            <l>The very ashie palenes of his face, </l>
            <l>The mossie downe still growing on his chin, </l>
            <l>And so his Alablaster finger pointing </l>
            <l>To the bracelet, whereon the peece of gold </l>
            <l>We broke betweene us hangs. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e116560">
            <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Certes shee's madd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e116580">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Pray come hither, </l>
            <l>You shade this Picture from the pearsant Sun, </l>
            <l>And curtaine it, to keepe it from the dust, </l>
            <l>Why are you not as chary then of that? </l>
            <l>It lookes as it were could, alas poore Picture, </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000245-026-a"/>
          <sp who="A11435-bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e116640">
            <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Hee'r's but one Picture! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e116660">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>I say theirs two, </l>
            <l>You will not see this for to save a Curtaine, </l>
            <l>His knotty curles, like to Apollo's tramells </l>
            <l>Neatly are display'd; I'le sweare the Painter </l>
            <l>That made this peece, had the other by it. </l>
            <l>Why doe you not speake too it? 'tis your son, </l>
            <l>May be, he's tongue-tide, and cannot crave blessing, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e116740">
            <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
            <l>I could tell thee, I nail'd him to the Earth </l>
            <l>Riveted a stake quite through his bosome, </l>
            <l>And bid thee goe seeke him; but I love not </l>
            <l>To mocke miseries; i'le take this Picture hence, </l>
            <l>It troubles your sight. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e116800">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>And you'd remove that, I'de thanke you; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e116820">
            <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
            <l>'Tis thy forc'd fancies, and thy guilt together </l>
            <l>persuades thee so; pray thee be a woman, </l>
            <l>Whom thou cam'st to comfort, comforts thee; </l>
            <l>Though I intended to have hurl'd at thee, </l>
            <l>Stings of dishonour, ignominies, reproaches, </l>
            <l>And all the stocke of calumnies, and scorne, </l>
            <l>Which thou art guilty off; now my pity </l>
            <l>Converts them into sorrow for thy sorrowes; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e116910">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>A blessing crowne you for it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e116930">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>And can their be a hope you will forgive me? </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e116950">Exit Ghost. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e116960">
            <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Hartily I doe— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e116980">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>See i'ts gone now. </l>
            <l>As if it vex'd to see your clemency. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e117010">
            <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Distemper not your selfe at fancies; </l>
            <l>Your time hastens to maturity, </l>
            <l>Y'are very big, and may endanger your fruite, </l>
            <l>If you give way to passions. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e117060">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>T'will be abortiue, </l>
            <l>As are my actions, I shall not live </l>
            <l>To take felicity in it! see i'ts here againe. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000245-e117100">
              <pb xml:id="ep000245-026-b"/>Enter Ghost, and Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ghost" xml:id="ep000245-e117110">
            <speaker>Gho. </speaker>
            <l>All things keepe their time. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e117130">
            <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Come goe with me. </l>
            <l>I'le give thee comfortable cordialls </l>
            <l>That shall remove these objects from thine eies, </l>
            <l>Expelling all disastrous accidents, </l>
            <l>And plaine thy thoughts as smooth as innocence, </l>
            <l>Which when thou hear'st, then in rapture boast, </l>
            <l>Thou dread'st no visions, fury, feind nor Ghost. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e117210">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e117220">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Be you my counsellour, and father too, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e117240">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>Whom I admire for noble honesty. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="ep000245-e117260">
        <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="ep000245-e117270">
          <head>Actus Quartus, Scena Prima. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e117280">Enter Clifton, Grey, Arguile, Ioshua, Miles, Ball, Souldiers. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e117290">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>What day is this? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e117310">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>Tues-day the seaventh of May. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e117330">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>This day shall in our English Calender stand </l>
            <l>Eyther to our dishonour, or great fames, </l>
            <l>When Chronicles in after ages tell </l>
            <l>The seventh of May we scal'd the walls of Leith, </l>
            <l>We have begun, dreadlesse of death, and dangers, </l>
            <l>And like to loyall subjects held the rights </l>
            <l>Of our deere Mistris Queene Elizabeth. </l>
            <l>When Captaine Randall gives the Alarum, </l>
            <l>Assault, assault, each man salute his freind, </l>
            <l>Take solemne farewell till this seige have end. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-omnes" xml:id="ep000245-e117440">
            <speaker>Omnes. </speaker>
            <l>Assault, assault. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e117460">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>Holdes every man his charge as we ordred? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e117480">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>I guesse so my Lord; </l>
            <l>Howard with his Launce-tieres quarters </l>
            <l>T'wixt Mount Pelham, and the Sea by West. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-027-a"/>
            <l>Stout Hary Percy with his barbed steedes </l>
            <l>Neighing for action guardes the Tents by East, </l>
            <l>Arguile, with shot marches for the Hill Brey; </l>
            <l>Sir Francis Leeke keepes the water-ports, </l>
            <l>I the greene Bul-warke opposite to Doysells </l>
            <l>With tough hardy Nottingham shire boyes </l>
            <l>Wee'le fall before we fly, by my Hollidam. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e117590">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>I'le man this bul-warke 'gainst proud Mortigue. </l>
            <l>Harke, the Allarum, each man unto his place. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e117620">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e117630">After squirmishes. Enter Grey, meeting Clifton, with Armour. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e117640">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>How goes the day, sir Jaruis? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e117660">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>Ti's bloudy. </l>
            <l>The thunderer, on both sides shootes his boults </l>
            <l>Valour is at the touch-stone of true tryall; </l>
            <l>The French like to so many gods of warre </l>
            <l>Bravely brandish darting fire from steele; </l>
            <l>The valiant Scot Arguile commandes the Hill, </l>
            <l>The Towne-playes fercely; their came a shot </l>
            <l>Of full two hundreth weight into my Tent. </l>
            <l>Doysells has thrice assaulted me. I fac'd him, </l>
            <l>And from his sides, like Libian Hercules, </l>
            <l>I tore the rough Nemean Lion's Skin </l>
            <l>His Armour of good proofe which here I beare, </l>
            <l>And will not part from, but with losse of life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e117800">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>See! Arguile apeares. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-arguile" xml:id="ep000245-e117820">
            <speaker>Arg. </speaker>
            <l>Man the water-ports, </l>
            <l>With all the Engines of defensive warre; </l>
            <l>Well fought Vaughan he mans the trenches bravely </l>
            <l>Young Arthur Grey assaults the stony mures, </l>
            <l>Vn goes the scaleing Ladders, now they mount, </l>
            <l>Now Sommerset, now Read, now Valiant Brey, </l>
            <l>Towring like eager Haukes who shall get high'st! </l>
            <l>Like angery Lions, or incenced Tygers; </l>
            <l>The Frenchmen labour, greedy for the prey, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-027-b"/>
            <l>Now the hardy Scots as swift as Roes, </l>
            <l>Climbe the walls, and tosse the Frenchmen downe, </l>
            <l>Now from the mount their thundring Cannons roare, </l>
            <l>Whose direfull clangors shake their huge structures, </l>
            <l>And like an earth-quake tumble to the Earth, </l>
            <l>Their steeples, Ordinance, Gunners, all at once, </l>
            <l>Now Inskeith, Sutton, Newport, Conway, Fitton, </l>
            <l>As dreadles enter dangers, as their Tents; </l>
            <l>Accursed chance, the Ladders are too short, </l>
            <l>Which gives a treble, vantage to the French. </l>
            <l>Now the foe triumphes, now our white coates fall, </l>
            <l>Now groanes the mother, now the virgin sighs; </l>
            <l>Death wilbe master, neyther party winns </l>
            <l>Now flies the English; now the French follow, </l>
            <l>And now their horse-men fling about the sands, </l>
            <l>Howard counterbuffs their canvasadoes </l>
            <l>Like chaffed Bulls, or foaming Bores they strive </l>
            <l>For mastery; the Frenchmen flie the Towne, </l>
            <l>And seeke for shelter. Now men your Trenches, </l>
            <l>Count Mortigue, and Doysells from the Towne </l>
            <l>Make expedition! now sings the god of warre </l>
            <l>His direfull Antheames; now fight, or never, </l>
            <l>We now are free-men or elce bond-men ever. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e118150">Alarum. Enter Doysells, Mortigue, Souldiers. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-doysells" xml:id="ep000245-e118160">
            <speaker>Doy. </speaker>
            <l>Thou bear'st my armour Clifton; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e118180">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>My Hollidam, </l>
            <l>Thanke me Doysells, I did not take thy head. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-mortigue" xml:id="ep000245-e118210">
            <speaker>Mor. </speaker>
            <l>I came to seeke thee, Grey; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e118230">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>The Towne I see was too hot to hold thee, </l>
            <l>Elce thou'st have nesl'd in thy pent-house still. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e118260">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>Wee'le not articulate. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e118280">Alarums Monluck, Crosse, betweene the Armies. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-monlucke" xml:id="ep000245-e118290">
            <speaker>Mon. </speaker>
            <l>Th'effuse of bloud is great, </l>
            <l>Which had bene better never spent, then ill; </l>
            <l>You of our party, by our commission, </l>
            <l>We doe command your tariance; your Lords </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-028-a"/>
            <l>Of England, and of Scotland we entreat </l>
            <l>A litle patience till your Heralds speake. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-crosse" xml:id="ep000245-e118360">
            <speaker>Cros. </speaker>
            <l>William Cecill the Queenes Secretary, </l>
            <l>Wotton Deane of Canterbury, and Yorke, </l>
            <l>With sir Ralph Sadler joynt Commissioners, </l>
            <l>Commands thee Iohn Lord Grey of Wilton, </l>
            <l>Now Generall of her Majesties forces, </l>
            <l>To make immediate repaire to Edenburgh, </l>
            <l>And present lay by all hostility, </l>
            <l>From this houre untill seven a Clocke at night. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-monlucke" xml:id="ep000245-e118450">
            <speaker>Mon. </speaker>
            <p>The like on your allegiance to Mary Dowager of France, and Queene of Scots, we doe commend. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-mortigue" xml:id="ep000245-e118470">
            <speaker>Mor. </speaker>
            <l>We obey, and instant will give order. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-germane" xml:id="ep000245-e118490">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <l>The like doe you sir Iarvis, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e118510">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <p>Now we have beaten them out of the Towne, they come To composition. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-germane" xml:id="ep000245-e118530">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <l>Give order through our Trenches, Tents, Bul-warks, </l>
            <l>That not a peece of great nor smaller shot </l>
            <l>Prove preiudiciall to the French; untill from us </l>
            <l>You have commission; my Lord of Valens </l>
            <l>I'le waite on you to the commissioners, </l>
            <l>If we have peace 'tis welcome, and if warre. </l>
            <l>We are for eyther object, both we darre. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e118610">Exeunt Mon. Grey. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e118620">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>My Hollidam. </l>
            <l>What a new monster England has begot </l>
            <l>We cannot fight because we want commission? </l>
            <l>Mortigue, Doysells, by my just Hollidam </l>
            <l>It greives me that we must not fight it out. </l>
            <l>Come le'ts shake hands, 'till seven at night all friends </l>
            <l>After such greetings, as on warr depends. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-doysells" xml:id="ep000245-e118700">
            <speaker>Doy. </speaker>
            <l>We dread not chances. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e118720">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e118730">A bed covered with white. Enter Pratle, Magpy, Long-tongue, Barren with a Child, Anne in bed. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e118740">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>Lord, lord, what pretty impes you are in your majorities! </p>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000245-028-b"/>
          <sp who="A11435-magpy" xml:id="ep000245-e118760">
            <speaker>Mag. </speaker>
            <p>Is it a man-child Mother Pratle? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e118780">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>No in-sooth gossip Mag-py it is one of us, heavens blesse thee babie, and a well appointed impe it is. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-long-tongue" xml:id="ep000245-e118800">
            <speaker>Lon. </speaker>
            <p>See how it smiles. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-barren" xml:id="ep000245-e118820">
            <speaker>Barr. </speaker>
            <p>That's a signe of anger, t'will be a shrow I lay my life. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e118840">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>No, no, Mistris Barren, an Infant smileing, and a Lambes bleateing is a signe of fertility it is so in Artimedorus; you frown'd when you were borne, and thats the reason you are so sterill; Artimedorus saith so in his fourth booke. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-magpy" xml:id="ep000245-e118860">
            <speaker>Mag. </speaker>
            <p>What pretty dimples it has! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-long-tongue" xml:id="ep000245-e118880">
            <speaker>Long. </speaker>
            <p>Fathers none nyes. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e118900">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>None nose. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-barren" xml:id="ep000245-e118920">
            <speaker>Barr. </speaker>
            <p>Smooth fore-head! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-magpy" xml:id="ep000245-e118940">
            <speaker>Mag. </speaker>
            <p>Cherry lip! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e118960">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>Had it bene man-child, their had bene three evident signes of an whoremaster; a Roman Nose, Cherry Lip, and a bald pate, for so Artimedorus in his Problems. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-magpy" xml:id="ep000245-e118980">
            <speaker>Mag. </speaker>
            <p>Well, well, whosoever got it, 'tis as like none father as an Apple to a Nut, insooth Gossip Pratle it is. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-long-tongue" xml:id="ep000245-e119000">
            <speaker>Long. </speaker>
            <p>It smiles still! sure it was begot in a merry houre. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-barren" xml:id="ep000245-e119020">
            <speaker>Barr. </speaker>
            <p>Then I was got in a merry vaine; for prais'd be to memory my Mother said I hung the lip at my nativity. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-magpy" xml:id="ep000245-e119040">
            <speaker>Mag. </speaker>
            <p>Lord Mother Pratle doe the Modernes report soe? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e119060">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>I surely Gossip Mag-py, and it is a great signe of frugality if the Starrs, and Planets be concordant, for saith Artimedorus; if it be borne under Venus, it will be faire as you are, if under Sol, Rich as you are, and if under Mercurie. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-magpy" xml:id="ep000245-e119080">
            <speaker>Mag. </speaker>
            <p>Good Mother Pratle what is that god Mercury? is it he that makes the white Mercury waters, Ladies scoure their faces withall! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e119100">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>I surely Gossip, and stop their wrinckles with too, and saith Artimedorus, in his third booke of his Modernes, if borne under Castor, and Pollux, store of children. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-magpy" xml:id="ep000245-e119120">
            <speaker>Mag. </speaker>
            <p>Caster, and Bollux? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e119140">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>You speake broad Gossip, 'tis Pollux. </p>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000245-029-a"/>
          <sp who="A11435-magpy" xml:id="ep000245-e119160">
            <speaker>Mag. </speaker>
            <p>Why Bollux be it then; surely Barren was not borne under Bollux, for she has bene married this seven yeares, and never had childe, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-barren" xml:id="ep000245-e119180">
            <speaker>Bar. </speaker>
            <p>By your favour Gossip Mag-py, you were borne under Caster, and Bollux then, for you had two children before you weare married. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e119200">Enter Vrsula. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e119210">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>Insooth Gossip, she has given you a veny; Good lacke mistris Vrsula, where have you negotiated Your selfe; you should have bene present, and have Negotiated your selfe about the Maxims, and principles Of child-bearing; what? you had a Mother? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e119230">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>And a Father too, Mother mid-night. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e119250">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>No matter for the father; we talke of the surer side, you may be sure to know your mother, when your mother hardly knowes your father; 'tis a very facetious point, as Artimedorus in his booke of dreames sets it downe. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e119270">Enter Boote. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e119280">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>Here comes my Vncle. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e119300">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>Off with your hat sir, you come not here without reverence, see if the little infidell smile not on him, busse, busse, it. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e119320">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <p>Heavens blesse the babe! what wares beare my Little infidell? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e119340">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>Blesse the baby, it has sufficient if it live to be of the sages. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e119360">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <p>I meane carries it an English Pen, and Inke-horne Or a dutch watch tankerd? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e119380">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>Blesse the baby— it has— ey marry has it! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e119400">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <p>Is it a boy, has it a purse, and two pence in't? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e119420">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>Blesse the baby, it has a purse, and no money in't yet, but it may have, and it please the destinies. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e119440">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <p>A purse, and no money, by St Antony I thought the groome went drunke to bed, he stole too't so early— </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e119460">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>Looke how it smiles. </p>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000245-029-b"/>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e119480">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>Admit me to the mother; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e119500">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>Shee's now awake, sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e119520">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>I give my thanks to heaven daughter Nan, </l>
            <l>Whose providence hath made thee a mother, </l>
            <l>Rejoyce thou in the first fruites of thy wombe, </l>
            <l>If any sad distempers trouble thy minde </l>
            <l>Sing lullabies unto this pretty babe, </l>
            <l>And they will vanish; this must be now thy comfort; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e119590">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Just heaven; I might have taken comfort </l>
            <l>In this pretty babe; now it is too late, </l>
            <l>Leave me your blessing Sir; and depart hence, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e119630">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <p>You have some private occasions i'me not to question Neece bring the groaning cheece, and all requisites, I must supply the fathers place, and bid god-fathers. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e119650">Exit. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e119660">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Good women whose helpes I had but now. </l>
            <l>'Tis almost now of that necessity </l>
            <l>It was before: I pray be vigilant, </l>
            <l>For if you slumber, or shut your eie-lids, </l>
            <l>You never shall behold my living corps. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e119720">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>Blesse us daughter say not so! I hope you will not part in a trance, nor steale away in a qualme; come, come what should be your reason? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e119740">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <p>Nothing but a dreame. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e119760">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>An't be a dreame, let me come too it; was it a sorrowfull dreame? Artimedorus saith there be divers kinde of meates engender dreames; as Beanes, long Peason-Lentills, Cole-worts, Garlicke, Onions, and the like; Leekes, Ches-Nuts, and other opening Rootes, as Rad-dish, Carrets, Skirrets, Parsenips; now there is some flesh is provocative too; as the Hart, the Bore, the ould Hare, and Beefe; and then of fowles, as the Crane, Ducke, Drake, Goose, and Bustard; if you tasted any of these they will engender dreames. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e119780">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Pray marke me, and let my words be written </l>
            <l>Within your minds, as in a manuscript, </l>
            <l>That when it proves so, you may say I told it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-long-tongue" xml:id="ep000245-e119820">
            <speaker>Lon. </speaker>
            <l>Peace, and heare her dreame. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000245-030-a"/>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e119840">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Me thought I walk'd along the verdant banks </l>
            <l>Of fertill Trent, at an un-usuall time, </l>
            <l>The winter quarter; when Herbes, and Flowers </l>
            <l>Natures choisest braveries are dead. </l>
            <l>When every saplesse Tree sad's at the roote; </l>
            <l>Yet then, though contrary to nature, </l>
            <l>Vpon those banks where foaming surges beate, </l>
            <l>I gathered Flowers, Roses red, and Damaske, </l>
            <l>Love Pauncies, Pincks, and gentle Daffadils, </l>
            <l>That seldome budds before the Spring time comes, </l>
            <l>Daisies, Cowslopps, Harebells, Marigoulds, </l>
            <l>But not one bending Violet to be seene. </l>
            <l>My apron full I thought to passe away, </l>
            <l>And make a Garland of these fragrancies; </l>
            <l>Just as I turn'd, I spide a lovely person, </l>
            <l>Whose countenance was full of splendancy </l>
            <l>With such embellishings, as I may imagine </l>
            <l>Better then name them; it bad me follow it, </l>
            <l>Then me thought, it went upon the water, </l>
            <l>As firmely as on land; I covetous </l>
            <l>To parley with so sweet a frontis-peece </l>
            <l>Leap'd into th'water, and so dround my selfe. </l>
            <l>Pray watch me well this night; for if you sleepe. </l>
            <l>I shall goe gather Flowers, and then youle weepe </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e120090">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>T'was a strange dreame! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e120110">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>But a very true one; looke you Artimedorus in his third booke of his Moderns saith to dreame of Flowers is very good to a woman in child-bed; it argues she shall soone enjoy her husband; to walke on the Seas specifies to a man, delight, but to a woman a dissolute life, for the Sea is like a harlot, a glicery face, and a broken heart. Come, come, doe you sleepe? wee'le watch; by this good drinke; Gossip Mag-py, I was almost dry. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e120130">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <p>Lay the babe by me that I may Kisse it; </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e120150">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>So, so, she sleepes, come sit round, and lets have a Carrouse to the litle infidell. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e120170">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>I marry sir this is a silent houre, their teeth will not let <pb xml:id="ep000245-030-b"/>their tongues wag. Well drunck Mother mid-night, now will she sweare by this Wine, till she soke the Pot were it a fathome deepe. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e120190">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>By this good liquor, it is so. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e120210">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>Here's sweete swearing, and deepe vowes, she goes to'th bottome at every oath. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-magpy" xml:id="ep000245-e120230">
            <speaker>Mag. </speaker>
            <p>And I'faith Gossip Long-tongue when peipes the Onion out o'th parsley-bed, when shalls come to your feast? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-long-tongue" xml:id="ep000245-e120250">
            <speaker>Lon. </speaker>
            <p>Truely Gossip Mag-py when Caster, and Bollux raignes. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e120270">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>Sweete Mother Pratle what be those Castor, and Bollux? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e120290">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>Twinns daughter that rule most the signe being in Virgo, looke you Gossip Barren, could you once dreame of sore eies you should be sure of children? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-barren" xml:id="ep000245-e120310">
            <speaker>Barr. </speaker>
            <p>Good sooth Mother Pratle, the first time I dream'd, I was with child I got a husband presently. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e120330">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>By this dyet-bread Artimedorus saith so; marke Mistris Vrsula, to dreame to have Lyce, eyther in head or body, in some quantity signifies a proper man well appointed; and by this drinke I dream'd my husband when he came first a woing; came i'th liknes of a Kentish twindle Pippen; that is just, as if two stones grew together, no sooner was I married, but I had two sonnes presently just as Artimedorus saith by this diet-bread. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e120350">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>They have sworne all the Wine, and Banquet away. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-barren" xml:id="ep000245-e120370">
            <speaker>Barr. </speaker>
            <p>I know not what your twindles are, but i'me sure I tender Castor, and Bollux as dearely as any of you; I cannot dreame, heigho— </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e120390">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>You begin to be sleepy; I can prescribe you a medicine of Poppy, Mandragora, and other drowsy Sirrops; heida all a sleepe? if my charge sleepes, let me rest, for by this drinke i'me heavy too— </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e120410">All sleepes. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e120420">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>Their all asleepe I have a heavy slough, </l>
            <l>Come o're my eie-lids; Somisdore hath strucke me, </l>
            <l>I cannot wake, and must give way to rest, </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000245-e120460">
              <pb xml:id="ep000245-031-a"/>Sleepe. Enter Ghost. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ghost" xml:id="ep000245-e120470">
            <speaker>Gh. </speaker>
            <l>Deaths eldest daughter sleepe with silencies </l>
            <l>Has charm'd yond beldams, no jarring clocke </l>
            <l>Nor murmuring winde dares oppose just fate. </l>
            <l>Awake fond mortall ne're to sleepe againe, </l>
            <l>Now is the time I come to claime my promise, </l>
            <l>Alive or dead I must, and will enjoy thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e120540">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Blesse me I was in my dreame againe; ha! </l>
            <l>Mothers, Cozens, Mid-wife, all drown'd in sleepe? </l>
            <l>Then my decreed houre is here set downe </l>
            <l>I must away? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ghost" xml:id="ep000245-e120590">
            <speaker>Gh. </speaker>
            <l>With expedition; </l>
            <l>The Ferry-man attends thee at the verge </l>
            <l>Of Cocitus, and sooty Acheron, </l>
            <l>And he shall waft thee into Tartary, </l>
            <l>Where perjury, and false-hood finds reward </l>
            <l>There shalt thou reade thy history of faults, </l>
            <l>And mong'st the furies finde just recompence, </l>
            <l>I'le bring thee over Turrets, Towres, and Steeples, </l>
            <l>O're shady Groves, brineish Mears, and Brookes, </l>
            <l>The flattring Sea to me is navigable, </l>
            <l>O're steepy Mountaines, and the craggy Rocks, </l>
            <l>Whose heights Kisse Starres, and stop the flying Clouds </l>
            <l>Wee'le through as swift as Swallowes in recourse. </l>
            <l>The Chauntecleere summons my retreat, </l>
            <l>Signing a period to my pilgrimage; </l>
            <l>From nipping frosts, and penetrating blastes </l>
            <l>Could Snowes, blacke thawes, and misty killing deawes. </l>
            <l>I'le lead thee to the ever-flaming Furnace, </l>
            <l>That like a Feaver fed by opposite meates, </l>
            <l>Engenders, and consumes it selfe with heate. </l>
            <l>I'le peirce the Aire as with a thunder bolt, </l>
            <l>And make thy passage free; make speede away </l>
            <l>Thy broken contract, now thou goest to pay. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000245-e120830">
              <pb xml:id="ep000245-031-b"/>Enter. Shee leaving her bed. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-anne" xml:id="ep000245-e120840">
            <speaker>An. </speaker>
            <l>Oh helpe, succour: helpe! wives, cozens, Mid-wives, </l>
            <l>Good Angels guard me, I goe, but cannot tell, </l>
            <l>Whether my journey be, to Heaven or hell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e120880">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>I have slept this houre, how, d'yee cozen? ha? cozen, here; ay me, where, alas no where, ay me she's gon, she's gon. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e120900">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <l>Heigho; what's the matter Mistris Vrsula! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e120920">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>Alas! my cozen, she's gon, she's gon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-marmaduke" xml:id="ep000245-e120940">
            <speaker>Mar. </speaker>
            <l>Mary Jove forbid. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-long-tongue" xml:id="ep000245-e120960">
            <speaker>Long. </speaker>
            <l>I did not like her dreame. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-barren" xml:id="ep000245-e120980">
            <speaker>Barr. </speaker>
            <l>Nor I, I promise you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e121000">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <p>Dispatch every one severall waies some to th'feilds some to'th water-side; las 'tis but a fit, twill be over presently— away away severally. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e121020">Exeunt, and Enter Boote. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e121030">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <p>What meanes this noise! how comes my doores open at this time o'th night; I hope my daughters well, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e121050">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>Oh sir shee is— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e121070">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>Not dead I hope. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e121090">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>I know not that neyther; but whilst we </l>
            <l>After long watching tooke a litle rest </l>
            <l>She's stolne out of her bed, and fled away, </l>
            <l>The doores quite open, and the infant-here. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e121140">Enter Women bringing Anne. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e121150">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>Heaven blesse her; I am strucke dead with griefe </l>
            <l>She has beene subject to distemper'd passions </l>
            <l>Jove grant she works no harme upon her selfe, </l>
            <l>Me thinkes she should not for the infants sake, </l>
            <l>Poore babe it smiles, it lacks no mother yet. </l>
            <l>Till it misse the brest, she cannot be farre </l>
            <l>But they may find her out; their's a great Snow </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-032-a"/>
            <l>Fal'ne this night, and by her foote stepps they may </l>
            <l>Easily trace her, where she is. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e121250">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>Oh misery! </l>
            <l>Behold the saddest spectacle of woe, </l>
            <l>That ever mortall eies tooke notice off. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-prattle" xml:id="ep000245-e121290">
            <speaker>Pra. </speaker>
            <l>We trac'd her through the Snow, step, by step, </l>
            <l>Vntill we came unto the River side, </l>
            <l>Where like a cunning Hare she had indented </l>
            <l>To cozen her persuers, and cozen'd her selfe </l>
            <l>For dround we found her on the River side </l>
            <l>Nigh Collicke Ferry. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e121360">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>Oh my poore girle! </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e121380">Enter Bateman with his Picture. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e121390">
            <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Oh my poore boy! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e121410">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>How happy had I beene if she had liv'd? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e121430">
            <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
            <l>How happy had I beene if he had liv'd? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e121450">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>Whoes that which ecchoes me, playing the wanton </l>
            <l>With my miseries? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e121480">
            <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
            <l>I come to see how sorrow does become thee </l>
            <l>Doo'st thou remember that? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e121510">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>What mak'st thou here, is there no other wracke, </l>
            <l>To worke my miseries higher, but thy selfe, </l>
            <l>And art thou come for that? oh my poore girle. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e121550">
            <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Monster, behold my poore boyes Picture, </l>
            <l>Thou would'st not shed a teare, nor lend a sigh, </l>
            <l>Poore emblem of a penitentiall heart, </l>
            <l>When in these armes I hug'd my dead boyes corpes, </l>
            <l>Now monster, who i'st will weepe or sigh, for thine? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e121610">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>Monster thou troublest me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e121630">
            <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Murderer I will. </l>
            <l>See what the fruites of wealth have brought thee now, </l>
            <l>An everlasting scandall to thy name. </l>
            <l>A conscience full of horror, and black deedes; </l>
            <l>Natures externall superfluities </l>
            <l>Her white, and red Earth, rubbidg, drosse, and oare, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-032-b"/>
            <l>Which she but lent thee to keepe Marts withall, </l>
            <l>Thou hast converted to most grosse abuses, </l>
            <l>Thou wouldst not else have scorn'd my poore boys love, </l>
            <l>To match with wealthy German; see thy fruits, </l>
            <l>Thy bazes, and foundations now are suncke, </l>
            <l>And looke there lyes the ruines of thy workes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e121760">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>Oh misery! my hart-strings cracke with griefe, </l>
            <l>Yet will not burst, oh say, hast thou yet done? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e121790">
            <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
            <l>Noe, I will make thee sensible of thy ils, </l>
            <l>First thou art causer of thy daughters death, </l>
            <l>For thou enforc'd her to the breach of faith; </l>
            <l>Next my sonns ruin, whom parac'd like, </l>
            <l>Thou laugd'st at in his fatall tragedy; </l>
            <l>Whom but a villaine that abjures all lawes, </l>
            <l>That breakes all precepts, both of heave'ns, and mans, </l>
            <l>And natures too could have done this; should I </l>
            <l>Like one that dares affront divinity </l>
            <l>Laugh at thy daughters fall. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e121900">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>Hast thou done yet? </l>
            <l>I doe beseech thee for this infants sake, </l>
            <l>Which sets a smiling brow on miseries, </l>
            <l>And even by instinct, prayes thee to forgive, </l>
            <l>Commiserate my woes; it greives me now </l>
            <l>I did deri'd thy miseries; be but content </l>
            <l>I'le weepe till thou shalt say, it is enough, </l>
            <l>So that we may be friends. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-bateman" xml:id="ep000245-e121990">
            <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
            <l>I cannot chuse. </l>
            <l>But beare a burden in calamities; </l>
            <l>Our angers have like tapers spent themselves, </l>
            <l>And onely lighted others, and not us. </l>
            <l>Striving like great men for supremacy! </l>
            <l>We have confounded one anothers goodnes, </l>
            <l>Come we will be freinds, i'le dig a soleme cell, </l>
            <l>Which shall be hung with sables round about, </l>
            <l>Where we will sit, and write the tragedy </l>
            <l>Of our poore children; I'le ha'it so set downe </l>
            <l>As not one eye that vewes it, but shall weepe </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-033-a"/>
            <l>Nor any eare but sadly shall relent, </l>
            <l>For never was a story of more ruth, </l>
            <l>Then this of him, and her, yet nought but truth. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e122140">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="ep000245-e122150">
        <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="ep000245-e122160">
          <head>Actus Quintus, Scena Prima. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e122170">Enter Arguile, Clifton, Monlucke, Jo. Ball, Miles, Souldiers Mortigue, Doysells, Souldiers on the Walls. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e122180">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>After the hand of warre has raz'd your walls, </l>
            <l>Affrighting peace from your Jvory beds, </l>
            <l>And like the reaper with his angry sickle </l>
            <l>Leaves the Earth full of soares, and wounds, </l>
            <l>Yet after plasters her with her owne crop; </l>
            <l>So come we after warre, bloudy turmoiles </l>
            <l>To bring you peace, which had you sued before, </l>
            <l>Thousands that now ly boweld in the earth </l>
            <l>Had liv'd to memory what we have done. </l>
            <l>Set ope your gates, &amp; with spred armes embrace her </l>
            <l>For which as followes yee have articulated, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-monlucke" xml:id="ep000245-e122300">
            <speaker>Mon. </speaker>
            <l>Which we, Monluck, Bishop of Valence </l>
            <l>Labrosse, Amyens joynt commissioners </l>
            <l>For the most christian King, and Queene, </l>
            <l>Francis, and Mary of France, and Scotland, </l>
            <l>Have Confirm'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-mortigue" xml:id="ep000245-e122360">
            <speaker>Mor. </speaker>
            <l>Doy. Which, we as duty bindes, must obey. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e122380">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <p>The Articles thus followe, The most mighty Princesse Elizabeth by the grace of God, of England, France, and Ireland Queene, defendor of the faith, &amp;c and the most Christian King, Francis, and Mary, by the same grace King, and Queene of France, and Scotland have bore Record upon a reconciliation of peace, and amity to be inviolably kept betweene them, their subjects, Kingdomes, and confines; and therefore in their names it is straitly commanded to all manner of persons, borne under their obeysances, <pb xml:id="ep000245-033-b"/>or being in their services, to lay by all hostility eyther by Sea or Land, and to keepe good peace eyther with other from this time forwards, as they will answer therto, at their utmost perils; long live Elizabeth, Francis, and Mary; </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-omnes" xml:id="ep000245-e122400">
            <speaker>Omn. </speaker>
            <l>Long live Elizabeth, &amp;c. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-mortigue" xml:id="ep000245-e122420">
            <speaker>Mor. </speaker>
            <l>We much desire to heare the Articles, </l>
            <l>On which this peace stands fully ratifi'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e122450">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>They are thirteene in number; </l>
            <l>The principall, and of most effect, are these, </l>
            <l>That the French Souldiers, and all men of warre </l>
            <l>Leave the Realme of Scotland in twenty daies, </l>
            <l>Sixe score Souldiers, onely are excepted, </l>
            <l>Three score of them to remaine at Inskeith, </l>
            <l>And three score, at the Castle of Dun-barr, </l>
            <l>Their wages to be paid from the estates </l>
            <l>of Scotland; and to live lawfull subjects </l>
            <l>To the Lawes, and ordinances of that Realme, </l>
            <l>All fortifications in, or, about Leith, </l>
            <l>Which by the French was built, shalbe defaced, </l>
            <l>That France conveigh not any man of warre </l>
            <l>Nor ammunition into this Land, </l>
            <l>Without a free consent in Parliament, </l>
            <l>Of the three estates of these great Kingdomes. </l>
            <l>That Francis, and Mary King, and Queene of France, </l>
            <l>From henceforth beare not the Armes of England </l>
            <l>Which solely appertaine to our dread Mistris </l>
            <l>The Queene of England, and to no other. </l>
            <l>These as you hope for peace, you must observe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-mortigue" xml:id="ep000245-e122670">
            <speaker>Mor. </speaker>
            <l>We subjects are the hands, Kings are the heads, </l>
            <l>And what the head commands, the hands must act, </l>
            <l>Our barrocadoed portalls shall flie ope, </l>
            <l>And yeild entrance; if war-like Clifton please, </l>
            <l>As we have fought together, so wee'le feast, </l>
            <l>Such viands, as a raized Towne can yeild </l>
            <l>You shall receive; noble sir Francis Leake </l>
            <l>Hath in this manner proclam'd this peace </l>
            <l>On the North-side whom we will gratulate </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-034-a"/>
            <l>Which tearmes of honour, will it please you enter? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e122780">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>By my Hollidam we accept your offer; </l>
            <l>Lay by your armes; still after frayes come feasts, </l>
            <l>To which we Souldiers, are the welcom'st guests; </l>
            <l>Vnbrace our drums, instead of warr's Allarmes, </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000245-e122830">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
            <l>Wee'le meete, like constant lovers, arme in armes </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e122850">nisi Crosse, Bal. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e122860">
            <speaker>Bal. </speaker>
            <p>See, Joshua, is enter'd, one cup of briske Orleance Makes him i'th temper he was when he leap'd into Leene. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-crosse" xml:id="ep000245-e122880">
            <speaker>Cros. </speaker>
            <p>Will he be drunke? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e122900">
            <speaker>Bal. </speaker>
            <p>Most swine-like, and then by the vertue of his good liquor hee's able to convert any Brownisticall sister. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-crosse" xml:id="ep000245-e122920">
            <speaker>Cros. </speaker>
            <p>An excellent quality! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e122940">
            <speaker>Bal. </speaker>
            <p>Nay, in that moode, you shall have him, instead of presenting Piramus, and Thisbe, personate Cato Censorious, and his three sons, onely in one thing he's out, one of Cato's sons hang'd himselfe, and that he refer's to a dumbe show; </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-crosse" xml:id="ep000245-e122960">
            <speaker>Cros. </speaker>
            <p>Me thinks he should hang himselfe for the jest sake. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e122980">
            <speaker>Bal. </speaker>
            <p>As he did his Cat for killing a Mouse on Sunday, see! he has top'd the cannikin already; now will he sing treason familiarly, being sober; aske him why he did it? in sincerity, it was not he, it was his drinke. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e123000">Enter Joshua, reeling with Jacks. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e123010">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>As it is in the painted cloath, in sincerity; good liquor quickens the spirit. </p>
            <l>When from the warrs I doe returne, </l>
            <l>And at a cup of good Ale mourne. </l>
            <l>I le tell how Townes without fire we did burne, </l>
            <l>and is not that a wonder? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e123070">
            <speaker>Bal. </speaker>
            <l>That's more then the painted cloath! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e123090">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <l>I'le tell how that my Generall, </l>
            <l>Enter'd the breach, and scal'd the wall, </l>
            <l>And made the formost battery of all, </l>
            <l>and is not that a wonder? </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000245-034-b"/>
          <sp who="A11435-crosse" xml:id="ep000245-e123140">
            <speaker>Cros. </speaker>
            <l>Admirable! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e123160">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <l>How that we went to take a Fort, </l>
            <l>And tooke it too in warr-like sort </l>
            <l>I'le sweare that a ly is a true report, </l>
            <l>and is not that a wonder? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-crosse" xml:id="ep000245-e123210">
            <speaker>Cros. </speaker>
            <l>Ther's wonder in that, Io! </l>
            <l>How that we Souldiers, had true pay, </l>
            <l>And cloath, and vit'les every day, </l>
            <l>And never a Captaine ran away, </l>
            <l>and is not that a wonder? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e123270">
            <speaker>Bal. </speaker>
            <l>Nay, and but sixe daies to'th weeke. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-joshua" xml:id="ep000245-e123290">
            <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
            <p>Is there any man here desires to edyfie? I am in the humour of converting; I was converted in my drinke, and so are most of my bretheren; I'le stand while I am able, and then will goe sleepe on it. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e123310">Exit Ios. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e123320">
            <speaker>Bal. </speaker>
            <p>Hee's gone both waies; see the French Lords, &amp; our's enter. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e123340">Musique, Enter. Lord Grey, Clifton, Arguile, attendants Monlucke, Mortigue, Doysells, all embrace. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-monlucke" xml:id="ep000245-e123350">
            <speaker>Mon. </speaker>
            <l>On honorable tearmes we now embrace. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e123370">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>If what we articl'd be full perform'd </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e123390">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>They are my Lord in each particular. </l>
            <l>And the French ready to depart the Towne, </l>
            <l>By my Hollidam, they have feasted us. </l>
            <l>Not like to foes but friends, 'tis my wonder, </l>
            <l>That a beseiged Towne could yeild such Cates, </l>
            <l>In such extremities, and exigents, </l>
            <l>Full forty severall messes, yet not one, </l>
            <l>Eyther of fish or flesh, onely one dish, </l>
            <l>Which was the daintiest, (a powder'd horse) </l>
            <l>That, I tooke notice off. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e123500">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>Large stomacks, and empty sallet dishes </l>
            <l>Are the French-mans viandes; his banquetings, </l>
            <l>Cloyes not the stomacke, but gives satiety, </l>
            <l>A fresh appetite; that makes the body </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-035-a"/>
            <l>Active, and full of generous fires, </l>
            <l>Full dishes are like potions unto them, </l>
            <l>I know not whether nicety or want; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e123580">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>By my Hollidam; want, want, </l>
            <l>Give me the English chine, and that feedes men, </l>
            <l>And they that feede well, certainly will fight </l>
            <l>Vnlesse some Woolfe, or maw-Worme be internate; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-arguile" xml:id="ep000245-e123630">
            <speaker>Arg. </speaker>
            <l>I relish your opinion. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e123650">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>Lords of France you may depart at pleasure. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-french_lords" xml:id="ep000245-e123670">
            <speaker>F. Lo. </speaker>
            <l>Prosperity, and peace ever t'wixt France, and England. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-english_lords" xml:id="ep000245-e123690">
            <speaker>E. Lo. </speaker>
            <p>Amen saith England; when France forgets her pride England will honour her, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e123710">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>Come my coemates in warre, </l>
            <l>Our Souldiers instantly shall march for Barwicke, </l>
            <l>The Duke of Norfolke, waites their arrivall. </l>
            <l>Sir Francis Leake shall give them safe conduct, </l>
            <l>You, Arguile, Clifton, and my selfe </l>
            <l>With expedition are for Nottingham, </l>
            <l>To meete our peerlesse princesse Elizabeth </l>
            <l>Who in her progresse there will lay her Court. </l>
            <l>Arguile shall there receive the hostages </l>
            <l>Due to the federary Lords of Scotland, </l>
            <l>Wee'le turne warr's clangors into musik's sweete, </l>
            <l>And like new vested pares in wed-locke meete </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e123840">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e123850">Enter, Miles, and Ball. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e123860">
            <speaker>Bal. </speaker>
            <p>What if it were a Puppet-play? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e123880">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Absurd! absurd! thei'le be out in turning up the white of the eies, besides, ther's none of us can speake i'th nose. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e123900">
            <speaker>Bal. </speaker>
            <p>Yes, Joshua; </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e123920">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Most abhominable! wood'st thou have a Puritan speake to a Play; a Puppet Play! thou ought'st to be burn'd for thy hereticall conceit, why thou poison'd sowter, wood'st thou have a Puritan speake to a Play? still give me the hobby-Horse. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e123940">
            <speaker>Bal. </speaker>
            <p>But who shall play the hobby-Horse, Master Major? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e123960">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>I hope, I looke, as like a hobby-Horse as Master Major I have not liv'd to these yeares, but a man woo'd thinke I should <pb xml:id="ep000245-035-b"/>be old enough, and wise enough, to play the hobby-Horse, aswell as ever a Major on'em all; </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e123980">
            <speaker>Bal. </speaker>
            <p>Not so, cholericke Miles. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e124000">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Let the Major play the hobby-Horse among his bretheren, and he will; I hope our Towne Ladds cannot want a hobby-Horse, have I practic'd my Reines my Carree'res, my Pranckers, my Ambles, my false Trotts, my smooth Ambles, and Canterbury Paces, and shall Master Major put me besides the hobby-Horse? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e124020">
            <speaker>Bal. </speaker>
            <p>Thou wilt not understand me Miles! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e124040">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>I am an asse if I doe not; have I borrow'd the fore Horsebells his Plumes, and braveries, nay had his mane new shorne, and frizl'd, and shall the Major put me besides the hobby-Horse? let him hobby-Horse at home, and he will! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e124060">
            <speaker>Bal. </speaker>
            <p>Thou art impatient. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e124080">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Woo'd it not make a man impatient; am I not going to buy ribbons, and toyes of sweet Vrsula for the Marian, and shall not I play the hobby-Horse? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e124100">
            <speaker>Bal. </speaker>
            <p>Why then, let the Major speake the Oration; </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e124120">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Disgracefull, am not I able to make a narration to the Prince, I have plai'd a Major in my time, with as good dacity as e're a hobby-Horse on'em all; and the Major will prompt me, let him, he shall finde, i'le stand out like a man of Coventry. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e124140">
            <speaker>Bal. </speaker>
            <p>What shall Joshua doe? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e124160">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Not know of it by any meanes, hee'l keepe more stir with the hobby-Horse, then he did with the Pipers at Tedbury Bull-running; provide thou for the Dragon, and leave me for a hobby-Horse. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ball" xml:id="ep000245-e124180">
            <speaker>Ball. </speaker>
            <p>Feare not, i'le be a fiery Dragon, </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e124200">Enter Vrsula. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-miles" xml:id="ep000245-e124210">
            <speaker>Mil. </speaker>
            <p>And I a thund'ring St. George as ever rode on horsebacke, but see younders sweete Vrsula, more white then soote, and blacker then white Snow. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e124230">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>Younder's my Antagonist; a haunts me like a ghost, <pb xml:id="ep000245-036-a"/>'cause I us'd to make him the prologue to be merry, he forsooth conceits 'tis love sir reverence, why Vrsula, Neece Vrsula? </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e124250">Within. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e124260">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>That's my uncle's call, if I stay a litle, he'le fetch me in, which if he does, I may perchance harpe upon a conceit to beate this parboil'd gentlemans love out of my mealy Millers coate. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e124280">Sings. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-miles" xml:id="ep000245-e124290">
            <speaker>Miles. </speaker>
            <l>You dainty Dames so finely dek'd </l>
            <l>In beauties to behold, </l>
            <l>And you that trip it up, and downe </l>
            <l>Like Lambes in Cupid's fould, </l>
            <l>Not farre from Nottingham of late, </l>
            <l>In Clifton, as I heare </l>
            <l>There dwelt a faire, and comely dame, </l>
            <l>For beauty without peere. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e124380">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>How now Master Miles, singing! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e124400">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>I Mistris Vrsula, a very mery lamentable dolefull new Ditty of young Bateman, and his Nan; that ever poore young gentleman should die like a bird on a Tree, for the love to a woman— for here it is in the third staff. </p>
            <l>Her Haire was like the crisped Gold </l>
            <l>Of't times you may perceive, </l>
            <l>The fairest face, the falsest heart, </l>
            <l>And soonest will deceive. </l>
            <p>Mistris Vrsula I give you this as a caution to remember Bateman, and his sweet, your cozen, looke on me, and veiw your selfe were it not pitty I should hang my selfe for love; and that you should die none knowes how? </p>
            <l>Why Vrsula, Neece Vrsula. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e124480">Within. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e124490">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>Alas! what shall we doe? if my uncle comes, hee'le take thee for a Ghost, his braine is so fraught with distempers, and then falls he raging madd, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e124510">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <l>Will he not strike? </l>
            <l>Why Vrsula, Neece Vrsula: </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e124540">Within. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e124550">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <p>Sometimes hee will, so after your fit is over, I'le <pb xml:id="ep000245-036-b"/>prescribe a remedy against love. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e124570">Enter Boote i'ns shirt. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e124580">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <p>Passion on passion! am I growne old, and odious in your eies? what no attendance Mistris! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e124600">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>Oh Lo-oooord sir; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e124620">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <p>What ailes thee woman, what's the matter? ha! why doo'st thou quake, shake, tremble, and shiver? ha! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e124640">
            <speaker>Vrs. </speaker>
            <l>Oh there, there, there! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e124660">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>Bee'st thou the devill, I will talke with thee; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e124680">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <l>Ha, ha, no foole to th'old one, he takes me for a Ghost; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e124700">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>Art thou of aire, of earth, heaven or hell, </l>
            <l>Or art thou of some Incubusses breede? </l>
            <l>Is there more walking Batemans? answer me, </l>
            <l>Or I will beate thy carcas into a forme </l>
            <l>That is full substantiall, and has feeling, </l>
            <p>Seeing, hearing, smelling, and sweete-tasting, Ghost, I'le thunder thee; </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e124770">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <l>Oh, ho, Master Boote, Master Boote. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e124790">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>I; can the devill feele or, is he sensible of beating? </l>
            <l>What art thou! hast thou feeling? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e124820">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>I, and hearing, and seeing too; and you'l let me alone i'le tell you what I am; </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e124840">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>Ghost, i'le confine thee; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e124860">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>'Las sir I'me no Ghost, I am plaine honest Miles the Miller of Ruddington; a gentleman, and a Souldier, </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e124880">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <p>And Miles the Miller of Ruddington gentleman, and Souldier what make you here? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e124900">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <p>Alas sir to borrow a few ribbandes, bracelets, eare-rings wyertyers, and silke girdles, and hand-kerchers for a Morice, and a show before the Queene. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e124920">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <l>Miles you came to steale my Neece. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-midwife" xml:id="ep000245-e124940">
            <speaker>Mi. </speaker>
            <l>Oh Lord sir; I came to furnish the hobby-horse. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-boote" xml:id="ep000245-e124960">
            <speaker>Bo. </speaker>
            <p>Get into your hobby-horse, gallop, and be gon then, or i'le Morisdance you— Mistris waite you on me. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e124980">Exit. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-ursula" xml:id="ep000245-e124990">
            <speaker>Vrs </speaker>
            <l>Farewell good hobby-horse— weehee— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e125010">Exit. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-miles" xml:id="ep000245-e125020">
            <speaker>Mil. </speaker>
            <p>'Tis but a jades tricke Mistris Vrsula; but patience <pb xml:id="ep000245-037-a"/>the enemy to greatnes is my content, and in that humour I will forrage on like the hobby-Horse. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e125040">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e125050">Enter Major Aldermen attendants, Queene, and Lords attendants. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-queen" xml:id="ep000245-e125060">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>Master Major! </l>
            <l>We thanke you for your entertainment, </l>
            <l>And for your princely present, a cup of gold! </l>
            <l>In gratefullnes we backe returne the keyes </l>
            <l>With all the embleames of your government; </l>
            <l>We in our progresse, are a sojourner, </l>
            <l>Not an inhabitant, we will be so with you; </l>
            <l>A welcome fuller of bounty, vertue, love, </l>
            <l>We have not seene; therefore to gratulate </l>
            <l>As a small token of our princely love, </l>
            <l>On, to your former motion made for Trent. </l>
            <l>You'd have it navigable to Gainsborough </l>
            <l>So to Boston, Kingston, Humber, and Hull; </l>
            <l>But, what are the causes? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-magpy" xml:id="ep000245-e125210">
            <speaker>Ma. </speaker>
            <p>By St. Lucy Besse, I am a plaine honest Tanner, my brothers here, one a Shoo-maker, to'ther a Felmonger, we are all downe right toth' th'hide; I ha' noe Lawyers eloquence, our Recorder cannot whistle, but by the bones of sweete St. Lucy welcome, on welcome. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-queen" xml:id="ep000245-e125230">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>I have tasted your welcome, and would faine </l>
            <l>Grant your designe, soe you give reason. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-magpy" xml:id="ep000245-e125260">
            <speaker>Ma. </speaker>
            <p>By St. Lucy, and shall, elce i'm an asse, and my bretheren Dotterells, Give reason, brother Sheeps-kin, second me for I must speake Historiography, History I should say, but these hard words cloy my stomacke, like lumpes of Bacon. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-queen" xml:id="ep000245-e125280">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>Ya'r a merry man Master Major. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-magpy" xml:id="ep000245-e125300">
            <speaker>Ma. </speaker>
            <p>I were a Traitour elce, I woo'd not be merry with thee, Besse still welcome, and welcome; </p>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-queen" xml:id="ep000245-e125320">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>On, to your Charter. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-magpy" xml:id="ep000245-e125340">
            <speaker>Ma. </speaker>
            <l>Thus it was, </l>
            <l>Edward the first from whom we beare our armes, </l>
            <l>Three Crownes displaied in an Azure feilde, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-037-b"/>
            <l>First, 'gan to make our River navigable, </l>
            <l>Small barks it bore, but not of that full weight, </l>
            <l>That were transportable for our affaires, </l>
            <l>In the two Edwards the second, and third, </l>
            <l>Vnto the second Richard it continu'd </l>
            <l>Till Bulling-brooke began! then Harry the fift, </l>
            <l>And Pearcy fell at odds; in which division, </l>
            <l>Dividing of the land; Glendower began </l>
            <l>To stop the water-courses of flowing Trent, </l>
            <l>By that meanes our navigable course was stop'd, </l>
            <l>And where before we usually transported </l>
            <l>With things un-numerous from Hull to us! </l>
            <l>And in returne releiv'd the neighbour coaste, </l>
            <l>With fuell, and commodities of great use. </l>
            <l>As Wooll, Lead, Corne, fruits, and Iron; </l>
            <l>We now have neyther; but with double cost, </l>
            <l>This is the cause why we entreate your Grace </l>
            <l>To signe our pattent, and by St Lucy, Besse; </l>
            <l>Wee'le pray for thee, and that's thy full reward. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-queen" xml:id="ep000245-e125570">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>You shall enjoy your wishes; </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e125590">Enter. Grey, Clifton, Arguile. </stage>
          <sp who="A11435-omnes" xml:id="ep000245-e125600">
            <speaker>Omnes: </speaker>
            <l>Long live Elizabeth; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-queen" xml:id="ep000245-e125620">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>We thanke you; </l>
            <l>Welcome renowned Iohn of Wilton, </l>
            <l>And you the war like Heroes of his traine, </l>
            <l>War-like Clifton; fame has ben before thee, </l>
            <l>And with her shrill Trumpe sent your praises home, </l>
            <l>E're your arivall; rise noble John of Wilton; </l>
            <l>The onely champion of Elizabeth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-grey" xml:id="ep000245-e125700">
            <speaker>Gr. </speaker>
            <l>Peace, and prosperity guard your sacred throne, </l>
            <l>And make your foes submissive like the French; </l>
            <l>Leith is surrenderd, the French quite expuls'd; </l>
            <l>The Scotch inhabiting their native bounds, </l>
            <l>Whom we have found most loyall to your Grace, </l>
            <l>And therefore they require their hostages </l>
            <l>Due to the federary Scottish Lords. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb xml:id="ep000245-038-a"/>
          <sp who="A11435-queen" xml:id="ep000245-e125780">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>And they shall have them; welcome bold Arguile, </l>
            <l>Thanke thou the god of batles, that hast given </l>
            <l>Prosperity to our first enterprise, </l>
            <l>Being the first Batle that we ever wag'd, </l>
            <l>Link'd victory unto a virgin's arme, </l>
            <l>For which we render thee all attributes, </l>
            <l>Guarded by thee, and these our loving subjects, </l>
            <l>We feare noe Spanish force, nor French-mens braves, </l>
            <l>Let Austria bragge; and Rome, and Italy </l>
            <l>Send out their poyson'd Darts; dreadlesse we stand </l>
            <l>Protected by thy never failing power, </l>
            <l>Lord Grey, returne you governour of Barwicke, </l>
            <l>The Duke of Norfolke, for some speciall causes </l>
            <l>We must recall; Arguile shall have his pleadges, </l>
            <l>We but reserv'd them to preserve our selves, </l>
            <l>Clifton; be thou our deputy Leivetenant, </l>
            <l>And Lord warden of Nottingham Castle, </l>
            <l>Our selfe wilbe Leivetenant of the County. </l>
            <l>For Howard, Pellham, Leake, and all the rest </l>
            <l>That in this victory shar'd with dangers, </l>
            <l>They shall participate our princely loves, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-omnes" xml:id="ep000245-e126000">
            <speaker>Omnes: </speaker>
            <l>Heavens blesse your Majesty. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-queen" xml:id="ep000245-e126020">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>I know not how to dignifie your deedes </l>
            <l>Without a large premeditation; </l>
            <l>Grey, and Clifton, Clifton, and war-like Grey </l>
            <l>Fought for our father, brother, and sister </l>
            <l>At Dennis, Roan, Bullen, and at Callice </l>
            <l>The bloudy sweat that Muslborough bredd </l>
            <l>At Edenborough, and now againe at Leith, </l>
            <l>In all which we fortunately conquer'd, </l>
            <l>Thankes unto heaven, next your valiant hands. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-clifton" xml:id="ep000245-e126120">
            <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
            <l>Your Majesty begets a spring of youth </l>
            <l>In me an old decayed Tree of age, </l>
            <l>Worne with as many snowy winters stormes, </l>
            <l>As makes the brauny Oake grow sap-les, </l>
            <l>Leaveles witherd, times period is ruine, </l>
            <l>Yet by my life, my heart retaines 'its vigour. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000245-038-b"/>
            <l>And what we want in deedes, wee'le act in duty, </l>
            <l>To you the Soveraigne mistris of our hearts. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-queen" xml:id="ep000245-e126210">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>Master Maior, and noble Iohn of Wilton, </l>
            <l>And war-like Clifton with all your men of warre </l>
            <l>We this night doe invite you, for our gueasts, </l>
            <l>To sup with us; to morrow wee'le survey </l>
            <l>The underminings, and unpaced greise </l>
            <l>That Mortimer, and Isabell did devise </l>
            <l>To steale their sportive daliancies in, </l>
            <l>Of whom your stately fortresse does retaine </l>
            <l>The Labyrinth (now called Mortimers hole) </l>
            <l>Heaven for our victory we first will pay, </l>
            <l>And praise our subjects that redeem'd the day, </l>
            <l>Proud France, and poysening Spaine, if heave'n us blesse </l>
            <l>A virgin's arme shall quell your mightines. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="A11435-omnes" xml:id="ep000245-e126350">
            <speaker>Omnes: </speaker>
            <l>Long life attend your Majesty. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000245-e126370">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
          <trailer>FINIS. W. S. </trailer>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist">
        <head>Machine-generated castlist</head>
        <list n="162-A11435">
          <item n="77">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-anne</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">77</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="63">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-ursula</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">63</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="54">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-boote</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">54</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="46">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-clifton</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">46</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="39">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-grey</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">39</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="38">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-young_bateman</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">38</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="37">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-joshua</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">37</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="36">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-midwife</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">36</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="26">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-prattle</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">26</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="24">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-ball</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">24</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="23">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-bateman</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">23</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="15">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-old_bateman</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">15</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="15">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-mortigue</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">15</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="13">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-magpy</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">13</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="10">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-crosse</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">10</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="9">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-queen</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="7">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-doysells</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="7">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-barren</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="6">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-arguile</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="6">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-monlucke</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="6">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-long-tongue</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="6">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-ghost</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="5">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-omnes</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="5">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-miles</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="5">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-germane</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="3">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-trumball</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="2">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-unassigned</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="1">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-shoemaker</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="1">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-marmaduke</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="1">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-french_lords</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
          </item>
          <item n="1">
            <seg type="character_name">A11435-english_lords</seg>
            <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
          </item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-digit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber. A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a keyword in context.</p>
        <note target="A11435-004-a-0510">
          <label>c3cie-004-a-0510</label>
          <sic>sanstitie</sic>
          <seg>puritie , a truth like Innocence , a temple of</seg>
          <corr>sanctitie</corr>
          <seg>, the Altar of reall goodnes , against those</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A11435-007-b-3160">
          <label>c3cie-007-b-3160</label>
          <sic>twently</sic>
          <seg>well for both ; forty horse loades , and</seg>
          <corr>twenty</corr>
          <seg>Carrs of vittle , twill stop a good breach</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A11435-008-a-1600">
          <label>c3cie-008-a-1600</label>
          <sic>em'tarry</sic>
          <seg>Why , and they will not come out , let</seg>
          <corr>em' tarry</corr>
          <seg>their like knaves as they are .</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A11435-010-b-0820">
          <label>c3cie-010-b-0820</label>
          <sic>the</sic>
          <seg>from us Weele make them win their ground ere</seg>
          <corr>they</corr>
          <seg>stand on't . Nothing but circumvention in</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A11435-010-b-2380">
          <label>c3cie-010-b-2380</label>
          <sic>flightest</sic>
          <seg>Let the bow-men shoute their</seg>
          <corr>slighted</corr>
          <seg>Arrowes , As thicke as haile , the Musketteers</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A11435-011-a-2760">
          <label>c3cie-011-a-2760</label>
          <sic>Weloh-mans</sic>
          <seg>as thou marry German ! his head's like a</seg>
          <corr>Welch-mans</corr>
          <seg>Crest on St. Davies day ? he lookes like</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A11435-015-a-2470">
          <label>c3cie-015-a-2470</label>
          <sic>Connulsion</sic>
          <seg>came o're her stomacke like a Crampe or a</seg>
          <corr>Convulsion</corr>
          <seg>?</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A11435-016-b-0970">
          <label>c3cie-016-b-0970</label>
          <sic>you le</sic>
          <seg>And may I tell you if</seg>
          <corr>youle</corr>
          <seg>stay my husbands Funerall . I'le promise</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A11435-017-b-0480">
          <label>c3cie-017-b-0480</label>
          <sic>bridall-mights</sic>
          <seg>Ha , weeping ; this is not customary on</seg>
          <corr>bridall-nights</corr>
          <seg>, Neece who was with your Cuz too night</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A11435-017-b-2780">
          <label>c3cie-017-b-2780</label>
          <sic>combare</sic>
          <seg>these false I made this sally forth Onely to</seg>
          <corr>combate</corr>
          <seg>thee .</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A11435-019-b-1020">
          <label>c3cie-019-b-1020</label>
          <sic>a bortive</sic>
          <seg>curs'd be all trees That brings forth such</seg>
          <corr>abortive</corr>
          <seg>fruit as this .</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A11435-019-b-1220">
          <label>c3cie-019-b-1220</label>
          <sic>alabor</sic>
          <seg>— he hang'd himselfe , and sav'd justice</seg>
          <corr>a labor</corr>
          <seg>!</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A11435-020-b-1860">
          <label>c3cie-020-b-1860</label>
          <sic>Cozeni'me</sic>
          <seg>Las</seg>
          <corr>cozen i'me</corr>
          <seg>not infectious my breath cannot blast you</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A11435-024-a-1710">
          <label>c3cie-024-a-1710</label>
          <sic>vertuons</sic>
          <seg>Mistris now is arm'd for both , For like a</seg>
          <corr>vertuous</corr>
          <seg>Princesse , and a Mother O're us her loving</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A11435-028-b-1670">
          <label>c3cie-028-b-1670</label>
          <sic>Pare</sic>
          <seg>; a Roman Nose , Cherry Lip , and a bald</seg>
          <corr>pate</corr>
          <seg>, for so Artimedorus in his Problems .</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A11435-030-a-0060">
          <label>c3cie-030-a-0060</label>
          <sic>a long</sic>
          <seg>Me thought I walk'd</seg>
          <corr>along</corr>
          <seg>the verdant banks Of fertill Trent</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A11435-031-a-0330">
          <label>c3cie-031-a-0330</label>
          <sic>ne'reto</sic>
          <seg>dares oppose just fate . Awake fond mortall</seg>
          <corr>ne're to</corr>
          <seg>sleepe againe , Now is the time I come</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A11435-033-a-0290">
          <label>c3cie-033-a-0290</label>
          <sic>trnth</sic>
          <seg>Then this of him , and her , yet nought but</seg>
          <corr>truth</corr>
          <seg>.</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A11435-036-a-0380">
          <label>c3cie-036-a-0380</label>
          <sic>staya</sic>
          <seg>That's my uncle's call , if I</seg>
          <corr>stay a</corr>
          <seg>litle , he'le fetch me in , which if he</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A11435-036-b-1920">
          <label>c3cie-036-b-1920</label>
          <sic>feeleor</sic>
          <seg>I ; can the devill</seg>
          <corr>feele or</corr>
          <seg>, is he sensible of beating ? What art</seg>
        </note>
        <note target="A11435-037-a-2420">
          <label>c3cie-037-a-2420</label>
          <sic>i'man</sic>
          <seg>By St. Lucy , and shall , elce</seg>
          <corr>i'm an</corr>
          <seg>asse , and my bretheren Dotterells ,</seg>
        </note>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
