<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xml:id="ep000762" xml:lang="eng" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Tamerlane the Great a tragedy : as it is acted by Their Majesties servants at the Theatre Royal / by C. Saunders, Gent.</title>
        <author>
<!--Saunders, Charles-->
          <persName>
            <forename>Charles</forename>
            <surname>Saunders</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A62223.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <p>
            This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is available for reuse, according to the terms of
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>
            . The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
          </p>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull>
              <titleStmt>
                <title>Tamerlane the Great a tragedy : as it is acted by Their Majesties servants at the Theatre Royal / by C. Saunders, Gent.</title>
                <author>Saunders, C. (Charles), fl. 1681.</author>
                <author>Dryden, John, 1631-1700.</author>
                <author>Banks, John, d. 1706.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[10], 60, [1] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Printed for Richard Bentley and M. Magnes ...,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                <date>1681.</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>"... I drew the design of this play, from a late novell, call'd Tamerlane and Asteria ..."--Pref.</note>
                <note>With commendatory verse by John Banks and epilogue by Dryden which describes the author as a boy.</note>
                <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
      <profileDesc>
        <particDesc>
          <listPerson>
            <person xml:id="ep000762-2sl">
              <persName>2. Sl</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000762-isp">
              <persName>Isp</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000762-abd">
              <persName>Abd,</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000762-man">
              <persName>Man</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000762-1slave">
              <persName>1. Slave</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000762-peo">
              <persName>Peo</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000762-zan">
              <persName>Zan</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000762-nan">
              <persName>Nan</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000762-ham">
              <persName>Ham</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000762-both">
              <persName>Both</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000762-odm">
              <persName>Odm</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000762-pr">
              <persName>Pr</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000762-gh">
              <persName>Gh</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000762-peop">
              <persName>Peop</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000762-ch">
              <persName>Ch</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000762-zay">
              <persName>Zay</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000762-ars">
              <persName>Ars</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000762-ax">
              <persName>Ax</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000762-ast">
              <persName>Ast</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000762-baj">
              <persName>Baj</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000762-off">
              <persName>Off</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000762-sl">
              <persName>Sl</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000762-tam">
              <persName>Tam</persName>
            </person>
          </listPerson>
        </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000762-e10">
        <pb xml:id="ep000762-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000762-001-b"/>
        <p>TAMERLANE THE GREAT. A TRAGEDY. As it is Acted by their Maiesties Servants AT THE Theatre Royal </p>
        <p>By <hi>C. SAUNDERS</hi>, Gent. </p>
        <q>
          <l>— Neque adhuc virtus in floribus ulla est, </l>
          <l>Transit in AEstatem post Ver robustior annus, </l>
          <l>Fitque Valens Juvenis— </l>
          <bibl>Ovid. Metam. </bibl>
        </q>
        <p>LONDON. Printed for <hi>Richard Bentley </hi>and <hi>M. Magnes </hi>in <hi>Russel Street </hi>near Covent-Garden, 1681. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="preface" xml:id="ep000762-e150">
        <pb xml:id="ep000762-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000762-002-b"/>
        <head>THE PREFACE. </head>
        <p>THIS Play, as it was Writ only for my divertisement at Vacant Hours, or Recreation after severer Studies, was never design'd to see the light, at least not betray the weakness of its Author so publickly on the Stage, or more universally in Print, had not the Communication of it to one or two Friends spread the rumour of it so far about the Town and Vniversity, that running like Wild-Fire through every place, it kindled a general expectation in all that either knew me in my self, or by my Friends to see it in Publick. </p>
        <p>Nevertheless, their perswasions and inducements cou'd not make me Presume, to trust so far to my own small abilities, or to rely so much on my own weak Iudgment, as to send it forth into the World, until it had past the Censures of some (I may say) the greatest part of the Witty and Iudicious Men of the Town; untill it had receiv'd some Rules for Correction from Mr. Dryden himself, who also was pleas'd to Grace it with an Epilogue, to which it ows no small part of its success. </p>
        <p>After this, I thought I might safely enough commit it to its Fortune, and having had the Approbation of the Greater, I presume it was Protected from falling under the Censure of the Lesser, and half Witted Iudges. </p>
        <p>But no sooner can a young Writer appear in the World, but he is look'd upon by those squint-ey'd Pretenders, to wit, no less than some Notorious Malefactor, or Branded Outlaw, whom all may Prosecute, Attaint, Iudge, Condemn, or what they please, <foreign xml:lang="lat">cum Privilegio</foreign>. </p>
        <p>For passing by some, whose more nice Iudgment, or rather prying appetite, can find faults where few others wou'd suspect them, some whose sharper Wit is Satyrically employ'd in turning the best thoughts into Ridicule, to Ruine a Writer, as it were betwixt Iest and Earnest; There are others who wanting the sense to discern, what is, and where a true Fault lies, nay, sometimes to distinguish it from a Beauty, <pb xml:id="ep000762-003-a"/>will yet in spight of Stupidity have their share too in Damning the Reputation of an Author; and the means they took, was to give out, that this was only an Old-Play Transcrib'd. </p>
        <p>But I hope I may easily unload my self of that Calumny, when I shall testifie that I never heard of any Play on the same Subject, untill my own was Acted, neither have I since seen it, though it hath been told me, there is a Cock-Pit Play, going under the name of the <hi>Scythian Shepherd</hi>, or <hi>Tamberlain the Great</hi>, which how good it is, any one may Iudge by its obscurity, being a thing, not a Bookseller in London, or scarce the Players themselves, who Acted it formerly, cou'd call to Remembrance, so far, that I believe that whoever was the Author, he might e'en keep it to himself secure from invasion, or Plagiary; But let these who have Read it Convince themselves of their Errors, that this is no second Edition, but an entirely new Play. </p>
        <p>Moreover, utterly to overthrow this Objection, I must acquaint you that I drew the design of this Play, from a late Novell, call'd Tamerlane and Asteria, which I'm sure bears not half the Age of the Tragedy before mention'd, and I am confident the Characters are quite different. </p>
        <p>The last and worst aspertion is cast upon me, is, that I was help'd by others in the performance. But if I have not Friends that can clear me of this also, I hope the Congruity of the Style throughout the whole Play will testifie the simplicity of the Author. </p>
        <p>This I think may satisfie my more equal Iudges, that this Trifle is mine own, or if you will, honestly begotten between me, and my Muse, which I hope is yet so Chast, and her Reputation so sound, as not to have her Issue Branded with Plurality of Fathers. </p>
        <p>Thus we see what kind of Criticks we have now-a-dayes, that can lye by the whole sale, and Damn a Play in a Breath, that we may the more easily bear with them who pique at word by word, and thought by thought, in a more modest retail manner. </p>
        <p>I shall not now strive to defend this Trifle in any particular Circumstances, but leave it to those of a more impartial Iudgment; hoping first they may not find as many faults, as they expect, next that they wou'd be so kind as to wink at those which do occur, attributing them to the Youth of the Author, and consequently his want of experience, and Iudgment. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000762-e360">
        <pb xml:id="ep000762-003-b"/>
        <head>To my ingenious Friend Mr. Charles Saunders, on his Play of Tamerlane. </head>
        <l>WHen Night has thrown her sable Vest away, </l>
        <l>And the Sun's mounted on the Wings of day, </l>
        <l>Bright as Parnassus all around he Guilds, </l>
        <l>First the young Trees, and then the Mother Fields, </l>
        <l>To Youth, and Morn such Glories offers he, </l>
        <l>Which Age can only wonder at and see, </l>
        <l>But when the God has reacht the middle way, </l>
        <l>He the World visits with a courser Ray, </l>
        <l>Whips his dull Steeds, and hastens to the Sea, </l>
        <l>Cooling his Tresses on the Amber Shore, </l>
        <l>Then hates what he so well did love before: </l>
        <l>Or as an Infant spring, that from the side </l>
        <l>Of some lone Hill does through the Meadows glide, </l>
        <l>Whose Chrystal Waters as they silent pass, </l>
        <l>Aford the Nymphs both Dress, and Looking Glass, </l>
        <l>Who take the yellow Sands that lye below, </l>
        <l>And on their Heads the Golden Powder throw, </l>
        <l>Whilst the Rich Flood most prodigally decks </l>
        <l>With Rings their fingers, and with Pearls their necks </l>
        <l>In whose clear Stream the Heav'ns delight to play </l>
        <l>Phoebus to wast the tedious Summers Day, </l>
        <l>The Moon and Stars, the live-long Night away, </l>
        <l>Beneath 'tis Spring, above, Eternal Ray, </l>
        <l>It's Winter Bloom, and ev'ry Season May. </l>
        <l>But track these Beauties, and before they've run </l>
        <l>More Miles than Youth has years, they all are gone, </l>
        <l>Strong Tydes molest its ' wanton Course and o're </l>
        <l>It's hoary swelling Head huge Tempests roare, </l>
        <l>And all it's Glebes are Sandy like it's Shore. </l>
        <l>Till sick with Storms and every surly Blast, </l>
        <l>'Tis forc'd to make the Sea its Grave at last. </l>
        <l>On then brave Youth with Harp Divinely strung, </l>
        <l>And sing more sweet than ever Antients sung, </l>
        <l>Than <hi>Orpheus, Homer</hi>, or than Cowley Young; </l>
        <l>E're Age shall come and thou shalt live to see </l>
        <l>That Fumbling time of Love and Poetry. </l>
        <l>Now of the Young, you all the vigor shew, </l>
        <pb xml:id="ep000762-004-a"/>
        <l>And of the Old the solid Iudgment too: </l>
        <l>To you the Merits of e'm both belong, </l>
        <l>Not Alexander fought so very Young, </l>
        <l>Nor Conquer'd he the mighty World so soon </l>
        <l>As you have charm'd, and all the Muses won; </l>
        <l>And wise Minerva, like a Mother fond, </l>
        <l>With her own Wreaths thy darling Temples Crown'd, </l>
        <l>Has thee o're all thy Elder Brothers plac'd, </l>
        <l>And with a Benjamins large Portion grac'd. </l>
        <l>But let me not in wondring at your Youth, </l>
        <l>Forget what's due to Friendship and to Truth. </l>
        <l>Know Wit, like Beauty, pleases where it harms; </l>
        <l>A Checquer'd Serpent 'tis with Sting and Charms: </l>
        <l>And happy's he that never thinks at all, </l>
        <l>And far more happy is that lavish Fool, </l>
        <l>That dully wasts his Fortunes on a Whore, </l>
        <l>Than he that splits upon this dangerous Shore. </l>
        <l>Not Spencer dead, nor Spencer now alive </l>
        <l>Cou'd ever find a way by Wit to thrive: </l>
        <l>It is a Dream of Wealth, a Fairy Land, </l>
        <l>A fickle Treasure grasp'd like Golden Sand, </l>
        <l>Which, as 'tis held, does vanish through the Hand. </l>
        <l>The Lethargy of the best natur'd Mind, </l>
        <l>A Foe to Business, and to all unkind; </l>
        <l>Like that too kills insensible and sure: </l>
        <l>For he with Verse diseas'd, does still the more </l>
        <l>Court his lov'd Plague, and itches to be poor; </l>
        <l>A Mark where vile Pretenders lose their aim, </l>
        <l>And ev'n the best get but an empty Name. </l>
        <l>Launch out young Merchant new set up of Wit, </l>
        <l>The World's before thee, and thy Stock is great, </l>
        <l>Sail by thy Muse, but never let her guide, </l>
        <l>Then without danger you may safely glide </l>
        <l>By happyer Studies steer'd, and quickly gain </l>
        <l>The promis'd Indies of a hopeful Brain, </l>
        <l>Bring home a Man betimes that may Create </l>
        <l>His Country's Glory in the Church, or State. </l>
        <closer>
          <signed>J. Bankes. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="ep000762-e1260">
        <pb xml:id="ep000762-004-b"/>
        <list>
          <head>Drammatis Personae. </head>
          <item>Tamerlane <hi>Emperor of the </hi>Tartars. </item>
          <item>Bajaset <hi>Emperor of the </hi>Turks. </item>
          <item>Sons to Tamerlane. <list>
              <item>Arsanes </item>
              <item>Mandricard </item>
            </list>
          </item>
          <item>Counsellors. <list>
              <item>Odmar </item>
              <item>Abdalla </item>
            </list>
          </item>
          <item>Friends to Arsanes. <list>
              <item>Axalla </item>
              <item>Zanches </item>
            </list>
          </item>
        </list>
        <list>
          <head>Women. </head>
          <item>Asteria <hi>Daughter to </hi>Bajaset </item>
          <item>Ispatia <hi>Wife to </hi>Mandricard </item>
          <item>Zayda <hi>Confident of </hi>Asteria. </item>
          <item>Priests, Guards, Attendants, &amp;c. </item>
        </list>
        <p>Scene Samarcanda. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="prologue" xml:id="ep000762-e1580">
        <pb xml:id="ep000762-005-a"/>
        <head>PROLOGUE. </head>
        <l>HOw modern Prologues differ from the Old! </l>
        <l>Those su'd and pray'd, but these huff, rail, and scold. </l>
        <l>Now sure the Poets of our age presume </l>
        <l>They have out-done the wits of Greece and Rome; </l>
        <l>Who by ill-natur'd Satyr strive t'obtain </l>
        <l>What they by low submission sought to Gain. </l>
        <l>What bold Offendor ever yet found Grace </l>
        <l>By spitting vilely in his Iudges Face? </l>
        <l>Yet they so fondly do themselves esteem, </l>
        <l>They hiss at you, yet think you shou'd Clap them. </l>
        <l>Nay Branding you for Fools in open Pit, </l>
        <l>Hold it your Duty to cry up their Wit. </l>
        <l>Vollies of Curses on your heads they send, </l>
        <l>Damn one of them, They injur'd right pretend; </l>
        <l>And with unreasonable Confidence </l>
        <l>Excuse their Failings by your want of Sense. </l>
        <l>Some things you may not understand, 'tis true; </l>
        <l>'Tis more then Oedipus himself can doe. </l>
        <l>None of your Actions can their Censure pass </l>
        <l>Your Cravat, Wig, French-dress, or Pocket-glass, </l>
        <l>No not so much as Whore— </l>
        <l>Do you dress well? then rudely they Suppose </l>
        <l>Your Taylor made your Wit, as well as Cloths. </l>
        <pb xml:id="ep000762-005-b"/>
        <l>Have you a well-becoming Wig, They'l Swear </l>
        <l>You Bought Your falser Senses in false Hair. </l>
        <l>Thus turn your Wit to Scorn, yet think it much </l>
        <l>If you their husky Farce, or puffy Bombast touch. </l>
        <l>Thus Malecontents wou'd Laws to Rulers give, </l>
        <l>But think it Tyranny if they receive. </l>
        <l>Let not their railings Loyal Poets blind </l>
        <l>That you'r no Fools we by your Patience find </l>
        <l>Fools will be Angry, but you still are Kind. </l>
        <l>Then in that Old, not this New-fangled way </l>
        <l>To you our Author do's his Thanks repay </l>
        <l>For your kind meeting on this happy Day </l>
        <l>If he Offend he do's your Grace Implore, </l>
        <l>And Swears to mend, or Trouble you no more. </l>
        <l>Theives for one Crime have often Scap'd the Rope, </l>
        <l>Nay Priests, and Plotters are not out of Hope. </l>
        <l>Then Spare our Author for a Nobler Fate </l>
        <l>He yet deserves your Pity, not your Hate. </l>
      </div>
      <div type="advertisement" xml:id="ep000762-e2040">
        <pb xml:id="ep000762-006-a"/>
        <head>〈…〉 Magnes, in Russel-Street, near Covent-Garden. </head>
        <p>ALL the Tragedies and Comedies of <hi>Francis Beumont </hi>and <hi>Iohn Flesher</hi>, in one Volume, containing fifty one Plays. </p>
        <p>Tartuff, or the French Puritan. </p>
        <p>Forc'd Marriage, or the Jealous Bride. </p>
        <p>English Monsieur. </p>
        <p>All Mistaken, or the mad Couple. </p>
        <p>Generous Enemies. </p>
        <p>Andromacha; A Tragedy. </p>
        <p>Calisto: or the Masque at Court. </p>
        <p>Country-Wit. A Comedie. </p>
        <p>Destruction of Ierusalem, 2 parts. </p>
        <p>Miseries of Civil War. </p>
        <p>Henry 6. with the Murder of the Duke of Glocester. </p>
        <p>Nero, a Tragedie. </p>
        <p>Gloriana, a Tragedie. </p>
        <p>Sophonisba, or Hanibals overthrow. </p>
        <p>Alexander the Great, or the Rival Queens. </p>
        <p>Mithridates <hi>King of </hi>Pontus. </p>
        <p>Caesar Borgia, <hi>Son of Pope </hi>Alexander 6. </p>
        <p>Oedipus, <hi>King of </hi>Thebes. </p>
        <p>Theodosius, or the Force of Love. </p>
        <p>The Plain Dealer. </p>
        <p>The Town-Fop, or Sir <hi>Timothy Taudry</hi>. </p>
        <p>Abdullazar, or the Moors Revenge. </p>
        <p>Madam Fickle: or the Witty False one. </p>
        <p>The Fond Husband, or the Plotting Sisters. </p>
        <p>The Vertuous Wife, or good luck at last. </p>
        <p>The Fool turn'd Critick, a Comedie. </p>
        <p>Squire Oldsap, or the Night Adventurers. </p>
        <p>The Mistaken Husband, a Comedie. </p>
        <p>Mr. Limberham, or the Kind Keeper. </p>
        <p>Notes and Observations on the Empress of Morocco. </p>
        <p>The Orphan, or unhappy Marriage. </p>
        <p>The Souldiers Fortune. </p>
        <p>Sertorius. A Tragedie. </p>
        <p>Tamberlane the Great. </p>
        <p>King Lear. </p>
        <div type="section" xml:id="ep000762-e2710">
          <head>Novels Printed this Year, 1680. </head>
          <p>The Amours of the King of Tamaran. </p>
          <p>The Amours of the French King and Madam Laniler. </p>
          <p>The Amours of Madam and the Count de-Guich. </p>
          <p>The Pilgrim: A Satyrical Novel on the horrible Villanies of those Persons. </p>
          <p>The Secret History of the Earl of Essex and Queen Elizabeth. </p>
          <p>The Policy of the Clergie of France, to suppress the Protestants of that Kingdom. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="ep000762-e2860">
        <pb n="1" xml:id="ep000762-006-b"/>
        <head>Tamerlane the Great. </head>
        <head>ACT I. Scene I. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e2890">The Curtain being drawn up discovers the Temple of Mahomet, in it <hi>Tamerlane, Mandricard, Odmar, Abdalla, </hi>and Priests who sing the following Hymn. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-pr" xml:id="ep000762-e2920">
          <speaker>Pr. </speaker>
          <l>SIng we, Alha, Lord of Fate, </l>
          <l>Father, Ruler of this State, </l>
          <l>In whose hand are War and Peace, </l>
          <l>Overthrows and Victories </l>
          <l>Sing we to thy Pow'r Divine </l>
          <l>At whose Nod the Heavens Bow, </l>
          <l>To whom Gods Allegiance owe, </l>
          <l>Whose just Favour Kings doth Crown, </l>
          <l>Monarchs perish at whose Frown, </l>
          <l>Sing we at thy Holy Shrine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ch" xml:id="ep000762-e3040">
          <speaker>Ch. </speaker>
          <l>Accept our Thanks, accept our Praise </l>
          <l>Our solemn Vows, our Eulogies, </l>
          <l>The Altars which our Hearts do raise </l>
          <l>Accept the humble Sacrifice. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-pr" xml:id="ep000762-e3100">
          <speaker>Pr. </speaker>
          <l>To thee, Alha, Virgins Sing </l>
          <l>To thee Tune each Tender String, </l>
          <l>Carry'd by an Holy Zeal </l>
          <l>Of the Pious Matrons tell </l>
          <l>To thy Grace Triumphant Youth </l>
          <l>To thee glad Old Age doth Kneel, </l>
          <l>Nor do Kings, thy Power Conceal. </l>
          <l>But all admire, all Confess </l>
          <l>iTs thou Cursest, thou dost Bless </l>
          <pb n="2" xml:id="ep000762-007-a"/>
          <l>To thee owe their Rise, and Growth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ch" xml:id="ep000762-e3230">
          <speaker>Ch. </speaker>
          <l>Accept our Thanks, &amp;c. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-pr" xml:id="ep000762-e3270">
          <speaker>Pr. </speaker>
          <l>See the Trophies see the Spoils </l>
          <l>The glad Harvest of our Toils </l>
          <l>See the Scythian Majesty </l>
          <l>Crown'd with Peace and Victory </l>
          <l>To his Scepter Turk giv'n; </l>
          <l>To him Conquer'd Asia bows </l>
          <l>To him th' Earth her Freedom owes. </l>
          <l>Fear we now no blow of Fate, </l>
          <l>'Tis Iust Alha rules our State, </l>
          <l>And our King's the Care of Heav'n. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ch" xml:id="ep000762-e3420">
          <speaker>Ch. </speaker>
          <l>Accepted are our thanks our Praise </l>
          <l>Our Solemn Vows our Eulogies </l>
          <l>‛ The Altars which our Hearts do raise </l>
          <l>Accepted is the Sacrifice. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e3480">After the Hymn <hi>Tamerlane, Mandricard, Odmar, Abdalla, </hi>with Guards, come forward on the Stage, and the Scene changes to the Pallace. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e3500">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>After our Sacred Rites to Alha paid </l>
          <l>'Tis fit we show our second Thanks in Joy </l>
          <l>And Triumphs which to Victory are due. </l>
          <l>Let Scythia now Arrai'd in all the Pride </l>
          <l>Of Conquer'd Asia dart her Glory to </l>
          <l>The utmost Gades, and to the utmost Ind. </l>
          <l>Let all her sleeping Monarchs rise and see, </l>
          <l>How far her new-got Liberties Extend. </l>
          <l>And as of Old her Vertue has alone </l>
          <l>Assyrian and Pellaean Arms withstood, </l>
          <l>Nor dar'd the flying Parthian to look back </l>
          <l>Upon his Enemy, but by retreat </l>
          <l>Sought Life, not Conquest. Our Faim'd Ancestors </l>
          <l>Then boasted how they could a Foe repel, </l>
          <l>Far greater's our Renown in Glorious Arms, </l>
          <l>Who know to Conquer too, enlarge our sway, </l>
          <l>And Teach the Haughty Ottoman to bow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e3780">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Needless, Great Sir, was that far Boasted Gift </l>
          <pb n="3" xml:id="ep000762-007-b"/>
          <l>That Law which to your Tartary entail'd </l>
          <l>The Turkish Empire, when their Kingly Line </l>
          <l>For want of Heirs should cease, you scorn'd to wait </l>
          <l>The slow Event; (or shou'd it be) to take </l>
          <l>Ev'n Empire at a Gift; but Gazing on </l>
          <l>The Golden Prey, you thought it lookt too great </l>
          <l>To be so cheaply Bought, then Seizing it </l>
          <l>With Danger, and the famous Lot of War </l>
          <l>Made it your Merits due, and Valours right. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e3920">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>That Man who threatn'd all the World with ruin </l>
          <l>That fierce, that yet unconquer'd Bajaset, </l>
          <l>Whose dreadful Name so oft shook Greece with Terror </l>
          <l>And struck her Princes Dumb with fear, That Man </l>
          <l>To whom all Asia Bow'd, has Learnt to Kneel, </l>
          <l>To Tamerlanes more Mighty Pow'r; Avert </l>
          <l>Ye Gods, all Nations Cry, from us the Hand </l>
          <l>Of the all-Conquering God-like Tamerlane. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e4070">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Abdalla, no; the World is pleas'd and silent, </l>
          <l>Amaz'd, and wondring at the sudden Change, </l>
          <l>The happy change of Monarchs, Bless their Stars </l>
          <l>By whose kind influence doubtful Victory </l>
          <l>Flew where Desert, and working Virtue call'd. </l>
          <l>While to your Arms all Nations wisht Success, </l>
          <l>To you who shou'd Revenge the Injur'd Earth </l>
          <l>And for a Tyrant give the World a King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e4180">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Stain not with flatteries the famous Day </l>
          <l>But rather let our Victory appear, </l>
          <l>By her own Trophies absolute, and sure. </l>
          <l>Let Blaze through all our Streets the Captive Moon </l>
          <l>That Superstitious Idol of the Field. </l>
          <l>In Solemn Process March our Slaves of War </l>
          <l>Each Tartar to his Turkish Prey a Guard, </l>
          <l>Your Heads with Lawrel Crown'd, your Hands with Spoils, </l>
          <l>Filling with wel-come Joy the shouting Crowd. </l>
          <l>For a Just Trophie to our own Ambition </l>
          <l>Call here the Captive Monarch to our sight. </l>
          <l>I wou'd Survey each Limb of that Great Man, </l>
          <l>Try his fierce Temper, see what awful Pride </l>
          <l>Held in such fear the Subject Nations. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e4360">
          <pb n="4" xml:id="ep000762-008-a"/>Bajaset and Asteria are brought in Bound. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-baj" xml:id="ep000762-e4390">
          <speaker>Baj. </speaker>
          <l>Death, </l>
          <l>I've view'd thee in a Thousand, Thousand Shapes, </l>
          <l>When not the fear of all thy Murdring Engines, </l>
          <l>E're shook my Soul so much, as now the thought </l>
          <l>Of this Tongue-Combat— give me Patience, Alha! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e4470">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>What Mutters he? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-baj" xml:id="ep000762-e4500">
          <speaker>Baj. </speaker>
          <l>Infectious be my Breath, </l>
          <l>And Blast thee ere thy Taunts can vex my Soul, </l>
          <l>For I conceive I shall be talk'd to Death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e4550">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Think not, O King, we come in Proud Disdain </l>
          <l>To thy fal'n State, or scorn thy Ebbing Fortunes, </l>
          <l>Or with Vain Glory to Commend our Deeds </l>
          <l>Which of themselves do loudly Praise the Doer. </l>
          <l>But as thy Conqueror and Prince to claim </l>
          <l>A just Submission to our Power; Live, </l>
          <l>But to our Mercy owe the Life we Give. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-baj" xml:id="ep000762-e4640">
          <speaker>Baj. </speaker>
          <l>And dost thou think the Glorious Bajaset </l>
          <l>Can stoop so low? speak, Alha, say, my Stars </l>
          <l>Is't just that I who held the fate of Kings </l>
          <l>In this Right Hand, and scatter'd Death's among </l>
          <l>The Tyrants of the World, as fast as words </l>
          <l>Cou'd mingle them; at last shou'd hold my Life </l>
          <l>On any upstart Power? First shall th' Enfeebled Sun </l>
          <l>Stoop down, and Borrow from the Earth his Heat, </l>
          <l>The Stars from Northern Fires take their Light, </l>
          <l>And Gods of Kings shall Mortal Blessings ask </l>
          <l>E're I to thy scorn'd favour own a Debt. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e4790">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Talk on, fond Slave, and Glut thy self with thinking, </l>
          <l>For words and thoughts are all thy Weapons now, </l>
          <l>Which yet thy Abject State shall prove but Vain </l>
          <l>And make thee a much greater— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-baj" xml:id="ep000762-e4850">
          <speaker>Baj. </speaker>
          <l>Emperor! </l>
          <l>The Brave are alwayes so; nor can the Fates </l>
          <l>Debase an inborn Virtue, Oh that Frown </l>
          <l>That Frown suits wondrous well the baleful Brow </l>
          <l>Of an Exalted, Stern, fate-looking Tyrant! </l>
          <l>So stretch thy self Ambitious Arrogance, </l>
          <pb n="5" xml:id="ep000762-008-b"/>
          <l>Stretch on the Wheel of Pride thy streightned Nerves </l>
          <l>Till thy Cramp'd Limbs yield Musick to my Ears, </l>
          <l>Proud, Vain Usurper— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e4960">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Such was Ottoman </l>
          <l>He Built his Throne by Virtue, and I mine </l>
          <l>Speak, if thy Pride can give a Vent to Truth </l>
          <l>Which is the Nobler Title, fairer Name, </l>
          <l>A Crown'd Usurper, or a Captive King? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-baj" xml:id="ep000762-e5040">
          <speaker>Baj. </speaker>
          <l>Gods! that I live to hear that vile Reproach▪ </l>
          <l>By Alla 'tis too much— Now cou'd I fly </l>
          <l>Like some Fierce Lyon scap'd the Hunters Hand </l>
          <l>(His Strength by Rage Improv'd, Rage by Despair) </l>
          <l>Against my Victor— ha, Inform me Slaves </l>
          <l>Who, or from whence was that bold Son of War </l>
          <l>Who durst with me in dreadful Combat Joyn? </l>
          <l>That Chief in sable Arms! for yet I see not </l>
          <l>His Face in all this Crowd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e5160">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Behold thy Greatest </l>
          <l>Most Dreadful Foe, see me Heav'ns fatal Scourge </l>
          <l>Sent from above to Purge the sickly Earth </l>
          <l>By Blood from Bloody Tyrants. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-baj" xml:id="ep000762-e5220">
          <speaker>Baj. </speaker>
          <l>No, fond Man, </l>
          <l>Mistake me not; that Conquerour was one </l>
          <l>One Nobler far, and fairer to behold </l>
          <l>Then any thy throng'd Court do's to my Eyes display. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e5280">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Spightful and false thy base Reproaches are, </l>
          <l>Say Odmar, speak the Valiant Mandricard, </l>
          <l>The Mighty nothing of that Strangers Acts. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e5350">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Not Sir, to Lessen or Eclipse your Fame </l>
          <l>Do I to that brave Strangers high Desert </l>
          <l>Due Honours pay, not that the Fierce Abdalla, </l>
          <l>Wise Odmar, or the Valiant Aldegar </l>
          <l>Did less then God-like acts; yet Sir, to speak </l>
          <l>His Worth I Envy, not those Numerous Bands </l>
          <l>To Conquest by your Royal▪ Conduct led </l>
          <l>Equal'd that Heroes Fame, who follow'd by </l>
          <l>A Guard of Horse in Mournful Black Arra'id </l>
          <l>O're ran our fainting Enemies; none durst </l>
          <l>Withstand him but their War-like Emperor, </l>
          <l>Whose rashness caus'd his Fate, the brave unknown </l>
          <pb n="6" xml:id="ep000762-009-a"/>
          <l>With force Superior drew him to our Camp, </l>
          <l>Threw him into my wide-spread Arms, and Cry'd </l>
          <l>Take here a Present from the Man you hate; </l>
          <l>Then adds, I ask but this for my Reward </l>
          <l>He was a King, be sure you use him so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e5570">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Gods! I shall jealous of my Conquest grow! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e5600">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Nor he, nor Heav'n your Glory cou'd obscure! </l>
          <l>Since Mandricard was sharer in the War: </l>
          <l>For by him fell the great Ortobulus </l>
          <l>The Hopes of Turky, and the Prop of Battel! </l>
          <l>Him did he Disinherit with his Sword, </l>
          <l>And snatch'd his Birth-right World as his Reward. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e5710">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Curse on thy Tongue! what Frenzy broke thy silence? </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e5740">[Aside to Od. </stage>
          <l>Thy Breath has Blasted me, and for a flash </l>
          <l>Of Honour, Damn'd me to Eternal Flames. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e5780">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>My Noble Son— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-baj" xml:id="ep000762-e5810">
          <speaker>Baj. </speaker>
          <l>'Tis false, ye spightful Powrs, </l>
          <l>Ortobulus (I'le ne're believe it) slain </l>
          <l>By that weak Arm, what Millions back'd the Coward? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e5870">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Fair Virtue was his Guard, approach me nigh, </l>
          <l>Embrace me round; now claim thy just Reward </l>
          <l>Ask freely; for the Glory of the Act deserves </l>
          <l>What ere thy Swoln Ambition can Demand. </l>
          <l>What Will not Conquerors on the Brave bestow? </l>
          <l>What sad Disorder moves my Mandricard? </l>
          <l>What foolish Passion dares disturb my Son? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e5970">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Who can withstand the vastness of such Hopes? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e6000">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Have we not giv'n our Word, and can we Lye? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e6030">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Far-bee't from me such Blasphemy to think. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e6060">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>
            <hi>Odmar, Abdalla</hi>, witness to my Vow, </l>
          <l>If ought I can deny to him! I Love </l>
          <l>Above the World, which he can ask with Honour, </l>
          <l>Sudden Destruction seize my Perjur'd Soul. </l>
          <l>Faith is the brightest Jewel of a Crown. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e6140">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Speak my Souls great Ambassador, my Tongue, </l>
          <l>Pronounce thy Message loud; a King Commands: </l>
          <l>O speak what thou desirest most to speak, </l>
          <l>Pard'n Sir, my too rude Carriage, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e6200">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Say Noble Youth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e6230">
          <pb n="7" xml:id="ep000762-009-b"/>
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Low as the Earth two Monarchs I Implore, </l>
          <l>Rather two Gods in saving pity great, </l>
          <l>As Heav'n may bless your Throne with Victory, </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e6280">[To Tam. </stage>
          <l>As Heav'n may raise you higher by your Fall, </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e6310">[To Baj. </stage>
          <l>I beg this Princess from your Royal hands. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e6340">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>With all the force a Virgins Tears can press </l>
          <l>On any Soul, I here implore my Death </l>
          <l>Ten thousand Deaths e're yield my Innocence </l>
          <l>To be polluted by his loath'd Embraces. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-baj" xml:id="ep000762-e6400">
          <speaker>Baj. </speaker>
          <l>Curse him, Asteria, curse the fatal Source </l>
          <l>Of thine, of mine, of the Worlds wretched State, </l>
          <l>Upon a Fathers blessing curse the Race </l>
          <l>Of Perjur'd Tamerlane, there's poyson in it </l>
          <l>And rank Infection, and consuming Plagues. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e6490">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Is she not Fair, my Lord! </l>
          <l>Is she not Innocent as Babes new Born? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e6530">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Mean Soul, degenerate Boy, I charge thee cease, </l>
          <l>Canst thou behold this haughty slave in Chains </l>
          <l>Outdare our Pow'r, and scorn our offer'd favours, </l>
          <l>Nay Curse thee to thy Face, and hold thee worthless </l>
          <l>The gift thou ask'st? deny thee with Contempt? </l>
          <l>And thou yet stoop to him, kneel, pray to him? </l>
          <l>Wipe off, rash boy, thy growing Glories stain </l>
          <l>Or quit the Name of Son— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e6630">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>How all things to my ruin do concur? </l>
          <l>Father, and Daughter, Emperor all are joyn'd </l>
          <l>To make me wretched, O the killing Flames, </l>
          <l>Of a despairing passion, oh my heart! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-baj" xml:id="ep000762-e6690">
          <speaker>Baj. </speaker>
          <l>My Miseries have giv'n me leave to smile </l>
          <l>To see thee Traytor find an Hell on Earth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e6730">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Approach my Fair. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e6760">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Oh I am ruin'd, stain'd, </l>
          <l>With hands scarce cool from my dear Brothers blood </l>
          <l>He catches at the Sister for reward </l>
          <l>And Im'e become a partner in the Murder. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-baj" xml:id="ep000762-e6820">
          <speaker>Baj. </speaker>
          <l>Oh the bold Ravisher, that he shou'd dare </l>
          <l>To touch her— purge then Villain with thy blood </l>
          <l>Her fully'd beauties, Dye. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e6870">[Snatching a Sword from the Guards. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e6880">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Disarm the Traytor, </l>
          <l>Presumptuous Fool, this Act has forfeited. </l>
          <pb n="8" xml:id="ep000762-010-a"/>
          <l>The Life we gave. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-baj" xml:id="ep000762-e6930">
          <speaker>Baj. </speaker>
          <l>Have I driv'n Troops before me </l>
          <l>And am I thus held in by a crowd of Slaves? </l>
          <l>Vile, fearful Mice to pluck the bristled Main </l>
          <l>Of a bound Lyon, rise, my Passion, rise </l>
          <l>Swell every Vein up to an Artery. </l>
          <l>Return the famous Lightning of my Eyes, </l>
          <l>Work, Oh my Heart, my Soul, in my revenge, </l>
          <l>For I am kill'd, choak'd with disdain and fury. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e7030">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>He Raves and we lose time to hear him, hast, </l>
          <l>Take, force him from my sight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-baj" xml:id="ep000762-e7070">
          <speaker>Baj. </speaker>
          <l>Do not think me King, </l>
          <l>One that has nothing but a Life to lose; </l>
          <l>Death! 'tis the common Scourge of coward minds, </l>
          <l>A Goblin hatch'd to fright base vulgar Spirits. </l>
          <l>Life I contemn; nor wou'd I stoop so low </l>
          <l>Beneath my Majesty to take it up, </l>
          <l>Though with my Empire it might be redeem'd, </l>
          <l>Since he must grant it whom I scorn and hate. </l>
          <l>A Grace from Tamerlane wou'd load with shame </l>
          <l>My inward memory far more then all </l>
          <l>My risled Crowns, or the base name of Slave. </l>
          <l>Now, Tyrant, to thy last destruction hear </l>
          <l>What Alha moving in my breast Commands </l>
          <l>Me speak, thy Glory, Tartar, is short liv'd, </l>
          <l>There are a Royal Race of Ottemans, </l>
          <l>(See thy Guards tremble at their very Name) </l>
          <l>And so must thou, I see thy Glory sink </l>
          <l>And Heav'n in Arms against thy Perjur'd Soul </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e7310">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>A way to Death to speedy Torture with him </l>
          <l>His boasted courage this last Act shall frye. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-baj" xml:id="ep000762-e7350">
          <speaker>Baj. </speaker>
          <l>Yes, I will make a Tryal of my Heart </l>
          <l>I'le bear my wrongs with such a noble Courage </l>
          <l>So far Transcending mean Tartarian spirits </l>
          <l>That thou shalt burst with envy to my Fate. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e7420">[Is led off. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e7430">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Thus doth the Naked Beggar gazing stand </l>
          <l>On great Mens wealth and starves, O cursed spight. </l>
          <l>That I must perish all my Joyes in sight. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e7480">[Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <pb n="9" xml:id="ep000762-010-b"/>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e7490">A Wood. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e7500">Arsanes, Axalla. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e7510">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Urge me no more, my Lord, my fate is seal'd, </l>
          <l>And Heav'ns fixt will stands uncontroul'd by chance, </l>
          <l>Now to return (by Heav'n I never will) </l>
          <l>Were as to seek a second Banishment, </l>
          <l>Or Death the lesser evil for returning. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e7580">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>Yet Sir the King— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e7610">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Is most unjust and cruel </l>
          <l>Lead by the voice of every fawning Traytor, </l>
          <l>And gives all power to him that Flatters most. </l>
          <l>My Brother! Yes, by all that's good it was </l>
          <l>That fatal Brother, that ambitious Boy, </l>
          <l>With the deep plotting Odmar wrought my ruine, </l>
          <l>And built their greatness on my ill-tim'd Vertue, </l>
          <l>While I— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e7720">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>While you here in inglorious sorrow </l>
          <l>Quit your just Title to your Fathers Throne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e7760">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>A Throne Axalla, can it yet be news </l>
          <l>My Father owns no Son but Mandricard? </l>
          <l>He shares his Crowns of Lawrel and of Gold, </l>
          <l>And all the shining Scepters of each Clime, </l>
          <l>Where if a friend but chance to name Arsanes, </l>
          <l>Or fetch an inward sigh for his misfortunes, </l>
          <l>A pointed frown marks the kind Spirit dead, </l>
          <l>And choaks with mournful groans his pious wishes. </l>
          <l>Oh my Nerina!— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e7910">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>That fever still, my Lord? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e7940">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>It like the Liver of the Earth-born Monster </l>
          <l>O'respread nine Furlongs of the burning Lake </l>
          <l>Feeds on the fiery Diet of fond hope, </l>
          <l>To be renew'd a prey to black despair. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e8000">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>Yet Sir she may be found </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e8030">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>She may! O trifler, may! </l>
          <l>May be is quite impossible to Love; </l>
          <l>She must— ye Gods, appoint the happy time, </l>
          <l>Like that when softest Hours in Greece I drew </l>
          <pb n="10" xml:id="ep000762-011-a"/>
          <l>Then when the Hospitable Emperor </l>
          <l>Saluted us as Princes, treated us </l>
          <l>At no less rate though both by Law enslav'd, </l>
          <l>An exile I, and she a Pyrates prey. </l>
          <l>Long in that state we liv'd in Bliss and Love, </l>
          <l>I Adanaxus, she Nerina call'd. </l>
          <l>But Oh, my Friend, that Golden Age is past! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e8190">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>Ah, my dear Lord— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e8220">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Speak, Friend— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e8250">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>If any charm </l>
          <l>Of specious truth your passion can o're sway </l>
          <l>And raise belief in your distracted Breast, </l>
          <l>The sight of her— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e8310">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Do not Delude me thus. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e8340">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>No false Delusion, or diverting Fable </l>
          <l>Can here reside, take, take the naked truth, </l>
          <l>Axalla in her rifled Tent beheld, </l>
          <l>Gaz'd on, and knew the fair Nerina's charms. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e8420">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>But did you see her like Nerina? bright </l>
          <l>As the first Sun when on the Eastern Shore </l>
          <l>He Rises fresh, and Decks the Infant Day. </l>
          <l>Did you behold among the Beauteous Crowd </l>
          <l>One by all envy'd, and by all admir'd? </l>
          <l>A Triple Goddess, Fair, Majestick, Wise? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e8510">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>Shee's all, my Lord, that ev'n your Love can speak her; </l>
          <l>And though all bash'd and shrouded o're with Tears </l>
          <l>Yet cou'd not ev'n those thickning Clouds of sorrow </l>
          <l>Obscure the shining lustre of her Eyes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e8570">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Methinks, my Friend, I see those Pearly drops </l>
          <l>When taking on my Breast her last farewell, </l>
          <l>She cast her Ivory Arms about my Neck, </l>
          <l>And cry'd, my Love; Oh shou'd we meet again, </l>
          <l>Nor spoke she this with the least sign of Bliss, </l>
          <l>For with a Smile she promis'd it a truth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e8650">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>As great and faithful as the Sybills Voice, </l>
          <l>And can you then, my Lord, leave all those Joyes </l>
          <l>For want of seeking them? Think, think, Arsanes, </l>
          <l>When this hot Fever has dry'd up to Ashes </l>
          <l>Your slaming Heart, and Parcht your vital Spirits, </l>
          <l>Then you will cry (but oh 'twill be too late) </l>
          <pb n="11" xml:id="ep000762-011-b"/>
          <l>What mass of Golden Treasure have I lost? </l>
          <l>Then curse your self for your unkind distrust, </l>
          <l>Your little Faith to your Axalla's Counsels, </l>
          <l>That ruin'd the unfortunate Arsanes. </l>
          <l>But let's behold, the faithful Danches comes </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e8830">[Enter Danches. </stage>
          <l>From your Great Fathers Court, his joyful look </l>
          <l>Denotes some glad Discovery— The News? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-zan" xml:id="ep000762-e8870">
          <speaker>Zan. </speaker>
          <l>Great Prince! what still may please, and make you happy, </l>
          <l>I went to Samarcanda; but I pass'd, </l>
          <l>Me thought, through Streets block'd up with moving Castles, </l>
          <l>So thick, so numberless the People stood: </l>
          <l>While they with Voices undistinguish'd fill'd </l>
          <l>The Air, that Eccho'd nothing but the Stranger, </l>
          <l>The Stranger is the business of the Court: </l>
          <l>The Sweet Discourse of every Ladies Mouth </l>
          <l>Is, what the Stranger did; to you they owe </l>
          <l>Their Trophies and their Fame. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e9000">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>And is the Court so monstrously infectious, </l>
          <l>That scarce an hour gone thou'st learnt to flatter? </l>
          <l>Speak, speak thy Errand, what of the fair Nerina? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-zan" xml:id="ep000762-e9060">
          <speaker>Zan. </speaker>
          <l>Great Sir! the Lady which your Friend discover'd </l>
          <l>Is Daughter to th' impetuous Bajaset, </l>
          <l>The tender sharer of her Fathers Fate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e9120">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Ha! Withers not my Hand, start not my Eyes </l>
          <l>From their curs'd Orbs? </l>
          <l>Am I not all an Ague? So loud a Clap </l>
          <l>Of sudden Thunder, and yet live? Ye Gods! </l>
          <l>Have I to ruine her my Sword employ'd, </l>
          <l>My greatest Strength her Country to destroy? </l>
          <l>Was it her Father too whose Fate I sought? </l>
          <l>Then on my self, my more than hellish act </l>
          <l>I thus Revenge. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e9230">[Draws his Dagger, which Axalla wrests from him. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e9250">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>Dear Sir. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e9280">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>'Twas friendly done: </l>
          <l>For I confess a death so quiet, and </l>
          <l>So short, had been a Balm to ease my Heart, </l>
          <l>Rather than punishment to expiate </l>
          <l>My great offence; to die? perhaps the News </l>
          <l>Might satisfie some Relicks of the War, </l>
          <l>That their great Enemy is dead— What then? </l>
          <pb n="12" xml:id="ep000762-012-a"/>
          <l>What had I done for Bajaset? what for </l>
          <l>His ruin'd House, his flaming Pallace? what </l>
          <l>In lieu of all his pillag'd Scepters, Crowns? </l>
          <l>What for Nerina's wrongs, whose every Tear </l>
          <l>Deserves a Life? No, no, Axalla, that </l>
          <l>Which can but once be done, let it be long </l>
          <l>In doing. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-zan" xml:id="ep000762-e9470">
          <speaker>Zan. </speaker>
          <l>Dear, my Lord, divert those thoughts </l>
          <l>And go where Piety and Honour call. </l>
          <l>The Royal Slave not brooking his disgrace, </l>
          <l>And yielding not himself to Tamerlane, </l>
          <l>Is most unfaithfully condemn'd to Die. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e9550">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>To Die? Shall then Nerina's Father Die? </l>
          <l>Basely and poorly be a prey to Fate? </l>
          <l>And leave his weeping Daughter all alone, </l>
          <l>'Midst a rude Multitude of Savage Men? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e9620">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>Arsanes cannot think a thought like that. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e9660">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>No, my Axalla, hast we from this place </l>
          <l>With all the swiftness of a Love in fear, </l>
          <l>That he shall come too late, and lose the Prize, </l>
          <l>The Beauteous Prize, for which all that have Souls </l>
          <l>Must needs be Rivals; Guide me, O my Stars, </l>
          <l>Shorten my Journey to my Paradise. </l>
          <l>By all my hopes Nerina's Father lives; </l>
          <l>Then snatching to my self the Glorious Prize, </l>
          <l>I'le reap the Fruit of all my Victories. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e9790">[Exeunt. </stage>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="ep000762-e9800">
        <pb n="13" xml:id="ep000762-012-b"/>
        <head>ACT II. Scene I. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e9820">Bajaset is discover'd on a Scaffold, an Executioner with an Axe, and others with Hallbirds, Swords, &amp;c. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e9850">Enter <hi>Tamerlane, Mandricard, Odmar, Abdalla. </hi>The Executioner being about to strike; Enter in hast Arsanes, and Axalla. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e9890">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>HOld, stay thy bloody hand, I charge thee strike not. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e9920">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>What bold Invader dares thus countermand me? </l>
          <l>Speak, say, what art? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e9960">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Lay down, O mighty Prince! </l>
          <l>A little of thy Thunder, and I'le speak. </l>
          <l>O thou to whose high care Heav'n doth intrust </l>
          <l>The Rule of Nations, Monarch of the Earth, </l>
          <l>So may you Laurels bear from either Pole, </l>
          <l>As you to them shall peaceful Olives joyn, </l>
          <l>And in your Conquests God-like Mercy shew. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e10050">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>The Accent of that Voice I sure have known; </l>
          <l>Nor am I unacquainted with that Face: </l>
          <l>All day I could with patience hear thy Story. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e10100">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Not to recount the Changes of my Life, </l>
          <l>Which but for one, one only happy Fate </l>
          <l>Does not deserve a Name; yet, Sir, I'le tell you, </l>
          <l>There's Glory in that Fate, and to have done </l>
          <l>You Loyal Service, is a Noble Bliss. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e10170">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>By all my Lawrels the Triumphant Stranger! </l>
          <l>O Prince! for I consider thee no less; </l>
          <l>What shall I, what Reward can I repay </l>
          <l>To thy great Vertue? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e10230">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Not a Thirst of Wealth, </l>
          <l>Or Sacred Famine of Reward, or yet </l>
          <l>A vain Ambition to commend my Deeds, </l>
          <l>Made me presume to meet your Royal Eyes. </l>
          <l>But since, Great Sir, you do esteem my Acts </l>
          <l>Worthy a price, O hear the Prayers I make; </l>
          <pb n="14" xml:id="ep000762-013-a"/>
          <l>By Alha, by the Soul of Mahomet, </l>
          <l>By the ne'r-cancell'd Bond of your strict Vow </l>
          <l>In Heav'ns bright Eye, I do conjure thee spare </l>
          <l>The Royal Captives Life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e10370">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Thou cou'd'st not ask </l>
          <l>A thing but this, we cou'd not grant. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e10410">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>O Heav'n! </l>
          <l>If with a Princes Life you needs must Seal </l>
          <l>The Glory of your Conquest, rip these Veins, </l>
          <l>And draw what Blood is left in expiation </l>
          <l>For his dear Life— Oh hold me not in doubt. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e10480">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Did I but think I did the Slave a favour, </l>
          <l>Spight of my Vow by Heav'n he shou'd not live; </l>
          <l>But as 'tis that he fears far worse than Death, </l>
          <l>I by one Act will wisely satisfie </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e10540">[Aside. </stage>
          <l>This Strangers hopes, and glut my own Revenge, </l>
          <l>Yes he shall live; remove the Fatal Pomp, </l>
          <l>And lead him to our Palace; but know, Slave, </l>
          <l>'Tis to this generous Prince thou owst thy Life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-baj" xml:id="ep000762-e10590">
          <speaker>Baj. </speaker>
          <l>For me his Pray'rs; ye Stars shed ruine on him, </l>
          <l>Beg in my Cause? Precacious Fool, be silent. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e10630">[To Ars. </stage>
          <l>Ha.! Villain! why's my Fate so long delay'd, </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e10660">[To the Exec. </stage>
          <l>Is the Axe not sharp enough? or am I held </l>
          <l>Here to be gaz'd at for a Mark, a Shew, </l>
          <l>A Property to please the Idle Vulgar? </l>
          <l>Strike Villain, or I'le spurn thee into Ashes. </l>
          <l>Ha, ha, ha, ha, O I could burst with laughter, </l>
          <l>To see these Apes, these mistaken Fools, </l>
          <l>Who think they have been generous and kind, </l>
          <l>While they are dully cruel; Tyrant, blush, </l>
          <l>And know, wer't thou my Slave, thus would I glut </l>
          <l>My self with vengeance on thee, so farewell, </l>
          <l>And some Plague seize thee e're we meet again. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e10780">[Is led off. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e10790">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Thus to your Prayers we sacrifice our Justice, </l>
          <l>And to your mighty Merits our Revenge. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e10830">[To Arsan. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e10850">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Thus at your Royal Feet I cast my self, </l>
          <l>And may those Pow'rs that rais'd and guard your Throne </l>
          <l>Reward you for this greatest highest favour, </l>
          <l>For which I vow you everlasting Service. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e10910">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Hail, O great Soul of War, matchless in Might! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e10940">
          <pb n="15" xml:id="ep000762-013-b"/>
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Fair Guardian Angel of the Scythian Throne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e10980">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>Desire of Nations, Bulwark of this State. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e11010">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Your Vassal, Princes, knows not to bear </l>
          <l>These loads of Praise, unable to repay </l>
          <l>Your noble kindness ev'n in Thanks. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e11060">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>So may </l>
          <l>You always knit fresh Lawrels to your Brow, </l>
          <l>As we to you our Turkish Conquests owe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e11120">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>'Tis true, I as a Warrior must adore </l>
          <l>Thee in thy Vertues, thy Success admire, </l>
          <l>Thy Actions love, reward thy Loyalty. </l>
          <l>But something nearer calls thee to my Breast, </l>
          <l>Stamps thy dear Image on my Soul, and tells me, </l>
          <l>There is a mightier reason for my love </l>
          <l>Than any I have yet alledged. O Nature, </l>
          <l>My Eyes, my Heart, both challenge thee, my Son! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e11220">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Father, if I may dare to use that Name, </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e11250">[Pulling off his disguise. </stage>
          <l>Behold your wretched Son, your Darling once; </l>
          <l>Now less than Stranger to you, banish'd, spoil'd </l>
          <l>Of all my Honours, Father, Country, Name, </l>
          <l>By their vile Arts, who with false Counsels arm'd </l>
          <l>Against my Innocence your mildest Nature. </l>
          <l>Here could I wish I were for ever fix'd, </l>
          <l>Here breath my last, and leave my flying Soul. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e11330">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Ye Powrs, my Son, the wrong'd Arsanes here! </l>
          <l>Heav'n knows with what regret I rob my Throne of </l>
          <l>So great a Pillar, my Kingdom of so good </l>
          <l>A Prince; Heaven knows how I have mourn'd thy absence, </l>
          <l>And curs'd my fond belief to busy Flatterers. </l>
          <l>Credit me, Prince, I always thought thee injur'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e11420">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>O damn'd, deceitful, spightful Queen of Chance. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e11450">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Hell, that I as a Basilisk cou'd dart </l>
          <l>Poison from my Eyes, and blot his growing Greatness. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e11490">[Aside. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e11500">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>O Mandricard! my other Blessing, share </l>
          <l>This mass of Joy that fills my heaving Breast. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e11550">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>And can the Stranger prove so near a Friend? </l>
          <l>A Brother? Oh that Name! Now by my Arms, </l>
          <l>If ever hate were grounded in my Breast, </l>
          <l>You Valiant Deeds have dispossess'd it all. </l>
          <l>Such Vertue ne'r can find an Enemy: </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e11620">[Imbraces coolly. </stage>
          <pb n="16" xml:id="ep000762-014-a"/>
          <l>Now all the subtilest Plagues of Hell prevent thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e11640">[Aside. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e11650">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>O happy day! the whitest of my Life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e11680">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>All who are present at this Solemn Meeting, </l>
          <l>Behold your Prince, your wish'd for Prince Arsanes; </l>
          <l>In whose just Cause you have so often mutinid, </l>
          <l>And ev'n assail'd our Throne for his revenge▪ </l>
          <l>Receive, take, share with me his Royal Heart, </l>
          <l>And with loud shouts of Joy accompany </l>
          <l>Us to our Palace: Thus from their sad Urn </l>
          <l>Thy Phoenix Vertues to new Glories burn. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e11790">[Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e11800">Odmar manet solus. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e11810">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Furies and Death, and all the Family </l>
          <l>Of dark Infernal Pow'rs, can you see, </l>
          <l>So tamely see me your Chief Instrument </l>
          <l>Sworn to your Counsels, so lost, so successless? </l>
          <l>For this? </l>
          <l>Have I trod in all Paths that Hell-ward led? </l>
          <l>Has Envy lost her Snakes, and Fraud forgot </l>
          <l>Her Art? Is Malice satisfi'd so soon </l>
          <l>To glare, and snarl, and not destroy? for this </l>
          <l>Have Guilty Thoughts disturb'd my Nights, and Blood </l>
          <l>Started my Soul in Fancies, broke my Sleeps. </l>
          <l>Bled the Kings Son committed to my charge, </l>
          <l>An Infant to no-purpose; is it nothing </l>
          <l>That my Themyre supplies his Place, and Name? </l>
          <l>But doth Arsanes still prevent us? Nay, </l>
          <l>He's grown much higher by his fall; our Plots </l>
          <l>To tread him down to Earth have mounted him </l>
          <l>Above the Clouds. This must not on, again </l>
          <l>Brain whet thy sweet Invention, while he climbs, </l>
          <l>That he may fall, and set the World in Flames. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e12050">[Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e12060">Asteria's Apartment. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e12070">Asteria, Zayda. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e12080">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Give, give my Passion vent, or I shall burst; </l>
          <l>Yes, yes, ye Pow'rs 'twas he, 'twas Adanaxus </l>
          <pb n="17" xml:id="ep000762-014-b"/>
          <l>That ruin'd me, my Father, Country, all. </l>
          <l>'Tis the same charming Tongue moves Tamerlane, </l>
          <l>That caught Nerina's Heart, just so he wept, </l>
          <l>And knelt, and pray'd for Mercy at my Feet </l>
          <l>For his own Life; as for my Father's, now </l>
          <l>▪ Tis the same Rival of Andronicus, </l>
          <l>The same Triumpher o're the Graecian Slaves, </l>
          <l>Turkey destroy'd. I and this faithless Man, </l>
          <l>Crown'd with the Pleasures of a Smiling Field, </l>
          <l>While we each others Story did relate </l>
          <l>So tenderly, and with so much concern, </l>
          <l>Promiscuously we gave our Hearts away, </l>
          <l>Born on the Wings of interchang'd Discourse. </l>
          <l>Then first we sigh'd and smil'd, and smil'd and sigh'd, </l>
          <l>And look'd, and wonder'd, and discours'd again, </l>
          <l>While the young God stood laughing on the Plain, </l>
          <l>And wonder'd at our Sympathy of Souls. </l>
          <l>Wou'd you believe it? This same Under-Lover, </l>
          <l>This very Adanaxus, from the World, </l>
          <l>From all Mankind, was chose to work my ruine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-zay" xml:id="ep000762-e12390">
          <speaker>Zay. </speaker>
          <l>Has he not sav'd your Captive Fathers Life? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e12420">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Did he not make him so? O trifling Comfort! </l>
          <l>How now, what Air, what Heav'n is this, what Sky, </l>
          <l>What Country? whither am I led? alass, </l>
          <l>What am I now become? Still, still my Eyes </l>
          <l>Behold those various Images of Death, </l>
          <l>And Fatal Ruine they in Prutia saw. </l>
          <l>All pale, and shiv'ring there my Mother lies, </l>
          <l>And there my Royal Brother bleeding groans; </l>
          <l>All this and more this dear, this trayt'rous Man, </l>
          <l>This smiling false Deceiver has perform'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e12550">To them <hi>Arsanes, Axalla</hi>. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e12570">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>See there, my Lord, and think on what your Friend </l>
          <l>Advis'd you to. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e12610">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>I see my Heav'n near, </l>
          <l>Am ravish'd with the light, wish, and admire, </l>
          <l>Court and hope, yet dare not enter in </l>
          <l>With such a clog of guilt incumber'd round, </l>
          <pb n="18" xml:id="ep000762-015-a"/>
          <l>I tremble at the Presence of my Judge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e12680">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>If Conquest were a Crime it was the Gods, </l>
          <l>Not yours; nor can she blame your hidden fate; </l>
          <l>How full of Fears is Love? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e12730">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Bless me my Stars, </l>
          <l>Oh I'm betray'd, look, Zayda, see that Man, </l>
          <l>Oh let us shun that swearing, perjur'd Man, </l>
          <l>And never let me trust my Heart again. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e12800">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Madam— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e12830">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>What means this rude Assault? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e12860">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Thus low I fall </l>
          <l>To Beauties and to Mercies Shrine, while from </l>
          <l>Their Oracle I learn my Life or Death, </l>
          <l>Present Despair or Happiness. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e12920">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Expound </l>
          <l>These Riddles, Heav'n! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e12960">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Ha! am I grown so strange </l>
          <l>So alter'd, neither known, nor understood? </l>
          <l>Or rather are you so forgetful grown? </l>
          <l>If so, let these recall your Memory, </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e13020">[A Bracelet. </stage>
          <l>The Tender Labour of your busie Love. </l>
          <l>This witness of your Vows. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e13050">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>What shall I say, or do? </l>
          <l>Ungrateful Man!— but let me not recall </l>
          <l>My Grief with Words, and stab my bleeding Wounds. </l>
          <l>The Gods revenge my Injuries— </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e13110">[Is going out. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e13120">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Oh hear </l>
          <l>Your Guilty Penitent his Crime confess. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e13160">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Some weak Evasion, or deluding Fable; </l>
          <l>Oh what excuse, or wile, can you invent, </l>
          <l>In recompence of all my Sufferings? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e13210">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Her every word a bleeding Heart-string cuts, </l>
          <l>Her every Tear a Vein; your Sufferings? </l>
          <l>Oh cast on me the burden of 'em all; </l>
          <l>For I can bear for my. Nerina's quiet </l>
          <l>The Pains of Hell, with Heav'nly delight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e13290">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Ill shall I trust so known an Enemy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e13320">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>An Enemy! what Horrors seize my Soul? </l>
          <l>Oh clear, clear me of that wretched Name. </l>
          <l>Who could have thought the Ridling Fates and meant </l>
          <pb n="19" xml:id="ep000762-015-b"/>
          <l>I shou'd have sin'd in bringing help to him: </l>
          <l>Who gave me birth? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e13390">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>'Tis plain you have betray'd, </l>
          <l>For empty Duty have betray'd your Love. </l>
          <l>What Name could make Nerina to forget </l>
          <l>Her Adanaxus thus—? ah cruel Man! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e13470">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Forget you? had I drunk dull Lethe dry, </l>
          <l>Its Waters had on me wrought small effect. </l>
          <l>Nerina always was, is present here, </l>
          <l>My Mind, my Soul is nothing but Nerina. </l>
          <l>This very impious Act was for Nerina, </l>
          <l>When losing her, I sought in dreadful Battle </l>
          <l>My long wish'd End. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e13600">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Excuses are but vain; </l>
          <l>For by your Actions I your kindness weigh▪ </l>
          <l>Captivity, and shameful Bands are all </l>
          <l>The mighty Gifts of your protested Vows. </l>
          <l>Have I not heard you say? yes, I have heard, </l>
          <l>To me the Tribute of the World was due, </l>
          <l>How fit I was to be a Queen, how well </l>
          <l>A Diadem wou'd with my Beauty Suit. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e13700">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Oh my Nerina, if I then must stand </l>
          <l>Guilty of all the malice of the Stars, </l>
          <l>And what great Heav'n decreed, if it be nothing </l>
          <l>That by my Pray'rs your Royal Father lives: </l>
          <l>Yet sure I've lov'd, and for your love despis'd </l>
          <l>All dangers, oppos'd Princes in your Cause; </l>
          <l>Witness the Fury of Andronicus; </l>
          <l>Nerina may remember too some Months </l>
          <l>Imprisonment, harsh Chains, and hardest usage. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e13840">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>How quickly passes a Womans Rage that loves! </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e13870">[Aside. </stage>
          <l>Now could I lay on Fortune all his Crimes, </l>
          <l>Oh Adanaxus— but I have been wrong'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e13910">[Turning from him. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e13920">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Then Heav'n o'retake me with thy swiftest Justice; </l>
          <l>While from your Mouth I here beg leave to die. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e13960">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Oh how I melt to Tenderness and Love! </l>
          <l>I cannot now dissemble with my Heart, </l>
          <l>Nor curb my Passion with a seeming Fierceness. </l>
          <l>Ah, my dear Lord— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e14020">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Pronounce the Fatal Sentence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e14050">
          <pb n="20" xml:id="ep000762-016-a"/>
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>While your Nerina lives you must not die, </l>
          <l>Your Life is link'd with hers. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e14100">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>And can I hope </l>
          <l>For Absolution? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e14140">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>If you've any Faith, </l>
          <l>See, see it Seal'd, while I due Thanks repay </l>
          <l>To Heav'n, which has restor'd my dearest Lord; </l>
          <l>By this one Gift my Stars have recompenc'd me, </l>
          <l>For Mother, Brother, Father, Country, all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e14210">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Such words as these mix'd with that Grace of Speech, </l>
          <l>Wou'd charm the praying Hermite from his Cell, </l>
          <l>And draw the rigid Cynick's Heart to Love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e14260">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>But see, we are observ'd— </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e14290">[Mandricard passes over the Stage. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e14310">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>'Tis Mandricard, </l>
          <l>That Raven bodes ill Fate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e14360">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Ha! what so close </l>
          <l>Billing? believe me Brother, 'tis too much. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e14400">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Did not you mark his black disorder'd Looks? </l>
          <l>Between his gnashing Teeth what silent Curses </l>
          <l>He mutter'd forth, and threatned us with Frowns? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e14450">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Though he were arm'd with Lightning we'd not fear. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e14480">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Again then we must part— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e14510">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>So willingly? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e14540">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Part now to meet again with greater Joys, </l>
          <l>More Ravishing Delights; mean while we'l live </l>
          <l>On hope. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e14590">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>And nourish Nature with the Thoughts </l>
          <l>Of Joys to come; now drive thy Chariot, Time, </l>
          <l>Incumbent on the Wings of all the Winds; </l>
          <l>Nor cease thy flying Pages to maintain, </l>
          <l>While I and my Nerina meet again </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e14670">[Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e14680">A Garden belonging to the Palace. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e14690">Mandricard alone. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e14710">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Dull, Coward Heart, weak Flesh, and what is worse, </l>
          <l>A Mind ambitious, yet without revenge. </l>
          <l>Rise, Mandricard, let not thy Glory sink </l>
          <l>In vain Complaints, and feeble Murmurings. </l>
          <pb n="21" xml:id="ep000762-016-b"/>
          <l>By this I shou'd have fill'd the World with Ruine, </l>
          <l>And on its Fall my early Glory built: </l>
          <l>By all my Fury I cou'd laugh to feel </l>
          <l>The ruin'd Palace crush my burthen'd Limbs, </l>
          <l>So that Arsanes might partake my Fate. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e14840">To him <hi>Odmar, Abdalla</hi>. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e14860">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>A happy Morning to my Gracious Lord! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e14890">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Gods, that I live to see this hateful day! </l>
          <l>No Serpent wing'd, or Dragon-breathing-flame </l>
          <l>Cou'd raise my Soul to this unbounded rage, </l>
          <l>As doth Arsanes Presence; O ye Furies </l>
          <l>Prepare some sudden deadly Pest to blast him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e14970">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>He's fir'd, and now to blow him into Flames— </l>
          <l>Busie, my Lord, and full of rowling thoughts? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e15010">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Dost thou not see Revenge hang on my Brow? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e15040">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Divide the heavy burthen of your Breast, </l>
          <l>And witness for me, Hell, there's not a Path </l>
          <l>That leads to your Ambition, vast desires, </l>
          <l>Your Odmar dares not tread to make you happy, </l>
          <l>Though with the fatal hazard of his Life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e15120">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>Speak but the word, and I'm a true born Son </l>
          <l>Of Scythian breed, can strangle, poison, kill, </l>
          <l>When e're your Interest shall arm my Fury. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e15180">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Now these are Men according to my wish, </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e15210">[Aside. </stage>
          <l>First swear to keep the Secret— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-both" xml:id="ep000762-e15230">
          <speaker>Both. </speaker>
          <l>Shou'd it be </l>
          <l>To blaspheme Mahomet, we swear. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e15280">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Why sticks </l>
          <l>My Tongue to speak the happy Deed my Mind </l>
          <l>Long since has acted? were you bred in Blood, </l>
          <l>And nurs'd with Milk of Tygers, have you each </l>
          <l>Murder'd your Thousands? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e15350">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>All my Life has been </l>
          <l>But a continual practice how to kill </l>
          <l>Most silent, and most sure, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e15400">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>I from my Youth </l>
          <l>Have conversant in Plots and Treasons been, </l>
          <l>And artfully have study'd by the fall </l>
          <pb n="22" xml:id="ep000762-017-a"/>
          <l>Of Men above me, how to raise my self </l>
          <l>To highest Place, and Power. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e15470">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Instruments </l>
          <l>As fit as Hell cou d make, for my Design. </l>
          <l>How long shall I, like some vile Shrub beneath </l>
          <l>A spreading Oak, stand overshadow'd by </l>
          <l>Arsanes mighty Pow'r? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e15550">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>Does it hit there? this Steel </l>
          <l>Has entred Brass, and cut through Coats of Mail, </l>
          <l>And will serve still to lop or branch or so </l>
          <l>From that tall Oak. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e15610">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>We'l take it by the Roots. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e15640">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>His Heart. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e15670">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>And drink his Blood. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e15700">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>And eat the Corse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e15730">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Like Tartars spoke; the Means? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e15770">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>By force of Arms. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e15800">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>By Stratagem, Fate-working Stratagem. </l>
          <l>Then first the Captive Princes, to deceive </l>
          <l>Must be our care, that she in spight of all </l>
          <l>The tenderness she to Arsanes bears, </l>
          <l>Be brought into your Arms a Glorious Prey. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e15880">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>That serves but for one half of my revenge, </l>
          <l>That for my Love, but what for my Ambition? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e15920">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>You have no sooner thought, but I have acted; </l>
          <l>Lyes are the steps by which black Treason climbs </l>
          <l>Confederacy with Turkey, dark Designs </l>
          <l>With Bajaset, and contracts with the Princess. </l>
          <l>This Head, that Hand can fail in no Attempt. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e16010">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>Where you the Platform lay, I swear to build. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e16040">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>My Noble Lords, now you are Friends indeed, </l>
          <l>I envy not Arsanes now with all </l>
          <l>His crowd of supple Flatterers, that cringe </l>
          <l>And buz about his new-reviving Greatness; </l>
          <l>Let them speak Friendship which you act, and now </l>
          <l>To our great Charges silent as the night, </l>
          <l>And hush'd as our Designs, we go; Farewell. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e16140">[Exeunt Odm. Abd. </stage>
          <l>'Tis sure, these Men with Trayterous Designs </l>
          <l>To the destructive part may much avail. </l>
          <l>But on what Ground to build my happy Love, </l>
          <pb n="23" xml:id="ep000762-017-b"/>
          <l>And how to gain the Fair Asteria's Heart, </l>
          <l>Instruct me, Alha; O Prince, 'tis enough, </l>
          <l>Enough thou see'st to gain her mortal hate, </l>
          <l>That by thy cursed Hand her Brother fell; </l>
          <l>What will she say?— but oh what canst thou say </l>
          <l>In thy excuse? when by thy Hellish Arts </l>
          <l>She hears Arsanes basely, poorly Murder'd? </l>
          <l>Yet, Mandricard, cheer up thy drooping Spirits, </l>
          <l>She loves the Man that sought her Fathers ruine, </l>
          <l>By Heav'n her Brothers Murd'rers less in fault. </l>
          <l>'Tis fix'd; and on that hope I build my Bliss. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e16340">To him Ispatia. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e16360">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>I wou'd not harbour such a jealous thought </l>
          <l>Within my Breast; can Mandricard prove false </l>
          <l>To his Ispatia, O unequal Gods! </l>
          <l>Prevent this mischief; what disast'rous chance </l>
          <l>Has summon'd me to this unhappy place </l>
          <l>With Eyes and Ears, to see and hear his falshood, </l>
          <l>To which my Soul cou'd never credit give? </l>
          <l>But yet I'le smother it, and try if words, </l>
          <l>With all the force of Tears, may turn his mind. </l>
          <l>Health to my Noble Lord, Great Mandricard, </l>
          <l>How fares your Highness? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e16520">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Well, Ispatia, well, </l>
          <l>The better that I hear thee ask me so; </l>
          <l>But I am busie now, leave me, Ispatia. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e16590">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e16620">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>I prithee leave me, </l>
          <l>We shall have idle hours enough for Love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e16660">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>How, my dear Lord? I little did expect </l>
          <l>To meet you thus on this Triumphant Day. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e16700">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Blame then the Fates, not me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e16730">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>Doth any Wound </l>
          <l>Disturb your Rest, my Lord? If so, behold </l>
          <l>Your weak Physitian, do not scorn my help. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e16780">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Thanks to your care, your Mandricard is whole. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e16820">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>My Care? O trifling word— He shou'd have cast </l>
          <l>Away that cool Endearment on the Crowd </l>
          <pb n="24" xml:id="ep000762-018-a"/>
          <l>That fawn'd, and welcom'd him at his return. </l>
          <l>Are all my longing Wishes come to this? </l>
          <l>And is it, is it thus, I must receive you, </l>
          <l>Is this the Fruit of all my early Moans, </l>
          <l>And Midnight-sighs, when shall I hope for Rest </l>
          <l>If I must now despair? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e16920">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>The Curses of </l>
          <l>A Wife are most unsufferable, now cou'd I— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e16960">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>Are not my broken Slumbers worth a Look? </l>
          <l>Not one kind word for all my long Complaints? </l>
          <l>One Smile wou'd be as much as I dare claim, </l>
          <l>Though I cou'd wish for Millions. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e17020">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Give me leave </l>
          <l>I prithee to repose my self a while; </l>
          <l>'Twill add a fresh, and stronger Life to Love. </l>
          <l>Heav'ns! is she senseless? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e17080">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>And can Mandricard </l>
          <l>Think me unwilling to partake his Grief </l>
          <l>That I have always done; and when I heard </l>
          <l>Of any Princes Fate, half dead with fear, </l>
          <l>I listen'd with impatience for the Truth </l>
          <l>Of all the Story of my Life or Death, </l>
          <l>Lest Mandricard shou'd prove that hapless Prince. </l>
          <l>But still those fears did joyfully deceive </l>
          <l>My Heart, reviving with the welcome News, </l>
          <l>The dear, dear hopes of seeing you again, </l>
          <l>So Great, so Glorious! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e17230">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Oh that my inward Pray'rs </l>
          <l>Cou'd move with pity some relenting Pow'r </l>
          <l>To raise a Mountain, or a Sea betwixt us; </l>
          <l>And snatch me from the Daggers of her Tongue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e17290">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>Believe me, Prince, you over-load my Soul </l>
          <l>With Thoughts of what shou'd move such discontent, </l>
          <l>Knowing the innocency of my Breast. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e17340">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>You'r not in fault, Ispatia, give me leave </l>
          <l>To think on those who are. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e17390">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>If to be freed </l>
          <l>From your Ispatia's company be Rest, </l>
          <l>Then I'le not rob you of those pleasing Minutes; </l>
          <l>Though I could willingly for Ages gaze </l>
          <pb n="25" xml:id="ep000762-018-b"/>
          <l>O're all that Field of awful Majesty, </l>
          <l>And wonder how it ever open lay </l>
          <l>To entertain so poor, so mean a Love. </l>
          <l>I go, my Lord, and leave you to your Rest; </l>
          <l>For which I would all Joy, all Bliss resign, </l>
          <l>Your Rest which me delights, for it is mine. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e17520">[Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e17530">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>So, is she gone at last, then farewell Wife, </l>
          <l>And welcome Love, thou highest Bliss of Life. </l>
          <l>While through my Rivals Heart I cut my way, </l>
          <l>And with a Mistress my past dangers pay. </l>
          <l>And this fond Wretch shall the sweet War begin, </l>
          <l>Arsanes shall conclude the Bloody Scene, </l>
          <l>I'le, while they groan in death, enjoy my Queen. </l>
        </sp>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="ep000762-e17630">
        <head>ACT III. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e17650">Ispatia sola, </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e17660">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>HE's gone, he's fled like Water shrunk away, </l>
          <l>The more I strove to hold him fast; Curst Fate! </l>
          <l>When every Matron sprightfully with fresh Joys, </l>
          <l>And every Virgin full of harmless mirth, </l>
          <l>Share the glad Pastimes of this happy day; </l>
          <l>Happy to all but me, whom one wou'd think </l>
          <l>Its Triumphs most concern'd, since Mandricard </l>
          <l>Bears all its mighty weight of crowding Honours, </l>
          <l>The haughty Conqueror Tartary adores. </l>
          <l>Yet after all his far-blown Victories, </l>
          <l>I blush to say this Great, this Glorious Man </l>
          <l>Is vanquish'd, vanquish'd even by his Slave, </l>
          <l>And wears the Fetters of a Captive Maid. </l>
          <l>But sure I have misconstrued all he said; </l>
          <l>He did but try me, my Eyes dazeled </l>
          <l>When I beheld his Gestures, when I thought </l>
          <l>I see him frown, I'le not believe my Thoughts, </l>
          <l>Poor Womens Thoughts are wandring Iealousies; </l>
          <pb n="26" xml:id="ep000762-019-a"/>
          <l>We fancy, dream, and real things suppose. </l>
          <l>Yet go thou silent trial of my Fate, </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e17900">[The Letter. </stage>
          <l>Her Characters I've here exactly drawn, </l>
          <l>And every Letter subtilly have copy'd, </l>
          <l>Which might I think deceive Arsanes self, </l>
          <l>Which he might see, and not perceive the Cheat. </l>
          <l>But oh why do I thus delay my Wishes! </l>
          <l>Within there, Hamzeh, trusty Slave, appear. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e17990">[Enter Hamzeh. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ham" xml:id="ep000762-e18010">
          <speaker>Ham. </speaker>
          <l>Most Honour'd Princess, what's your great Command? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e18040">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>Provide this Letter carefully be sent, </l>
          <l>As from Asteria, to your Royal Lord, </l>
          <l>Be gone; and wing to Mandricard your way, </l>
          <l>Each minute seems an hour, each hour a day. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e18120">[Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e18130">The Palace. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e18140">Enter Tamerlane, Odmar, Abdalla. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e18160">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Make me believe as soon the Stars are faln. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e18190">
          <speaker>Abd, </speaker>
          <l>Yet, Sir, with any but a Fathers Eyes </l>
          <l>Black discontent is seen to hover o're </l>
          <l>His darken'd Brow, his wild unstable Looks </l>
          <l>May render him suspitious. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e18250">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Wash thy Mouth▪ </l>
          <l>Thou foul Fomenter of suggested Lies, </l>
          <l>And politick Deceit, think not you, Slaves, </l>
          <l>We'r ignorant from whom this Message comes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e18310">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>See what your Plotting comes to. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e18340">[To Odmar aside. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e18360">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Dreaded Prince! </l>
          <l>This Tongue was never known to fill your Ears </l>
          <l>With painted fraud, and poisonous deceit, </l>
          <l>My Counsels hitherto ev'n you have thought </l>
          <l>Loyal and wise, and grave as Cicero's, </l>
          <l>And have preserv'd your Happiness as much </l>
          <l>As his did Romes— yet, Sir, your Slave </l>
          <l>Confesses all his Projects had been vain, </l>
          <l>Had not your Vertue perfected those Actions, </l>
          <l>Of which we but the bare Idea shew'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e18500">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>What's all this to Arsanes? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e18540">[Aside. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e18550">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Speak thy Thoughts, </l>
          <pb n="27" xml:id="ep000762-019-b"/>
          <l>And do not flatter, nor thy self, nor me, </l>
          <l>Thy Words fly wide from all thy former Sense; </l>
          <l>Thou nam'dst Arsanes, tedious Slave, proceed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e18620">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Now witness for me all ye Pow'rs Divine, </l>
          <l>And thou that know'st the Secrets of my Heart, </l>
          <l>Punish me strangely, Alha; if I speak </l>
          <l>Ought that I fear'd to speak before the Altar, </l>
          <l>Or swear it on the Alcoran for truth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e18700">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>He's at his Pray'rs now, sure his Conscience bites him, </l>
          <l>Heav'n, he'l confess, we're ruin'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e18740">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Odmar, rise, </l>
          <l>Give me but patience, Gods, to hear him out. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e18790">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Though loath, I must unfold the burning Secret, </l>
          <l>Both for my Conscience, and my Country's sake; </l>
          <l>The proud Arsanes, jealous of the Love </l>
          <l>You show deservedly to Mandricard, </l>
          <l>Bears mighty Projects in his lab'ring Brain, </l>
          <l>Envy, Revenge, with all that nat'ral hate </l>
          <l>He ows his Brother, stir him up against </l>
          <l>The Laws of Man, and Nature; his Ambition </l>
          <l>Flies Sir no lower a pitch, than at your Crown. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e18920">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>Ha! I begin to find him, he talks Sense! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e18950">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Now, Villain, give me Proof, substantial Reason. </l>
          <l>For what the poison of thy Gall has vented, </l>
          <l>Or else by Heav'n thou dy'st. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e19000">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>Ha! goes it so; </l>
          <l>Villain, and Death! Plague of your Stratagems. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e19040">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Scars will remain after their Wounds are whole; </l>
          <l>The highest Palaces stand most to view, </l>
          <l>And are most look'd at, when their Lustre fades. </l>
          <l>Arsanes cannot brook his late disgrace, </l>
          <l>And thou forgiven, blushes with disdain </l>
          <l>That he was banish'd; scarce an hour ago </l>
          <l>The Valiant Mandricard in Pious Suit </l>
          <l>Sought Reconcilement with his raging Brother. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e19160">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>This does not sound like truth, it has no face </l>
          <l>Of Probability. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e19200">[To Odm. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e19220">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>When in a lone </l>
          <l>And vacant place we found your Royal Son. </l>
          <l>But oh how chang'd from what he fain wou'd seem, </l>
          <pb n="28" xml:id="ep000762-020-a"/>
          <l>Must'ring up such a train of impious words, </l>
          <l>And bitter curses; Heav'n, we cou'd scarce believe </l>
          <l>It had been he; but strait approaching nigher, </l>
          <l>We over-heard him in a murmuring Tone </l>
          <l>Say thus; The House of Ottoman shall soon regain </l>
          <l>Its Empire by that Arm it newly fell; </l>
          <l>Hearing all this, the pious Mandricard </l>
          <l>Came near, saluted low the proud Arsanes; </l>
          <l>He frown'd, and lifted high his haughty Head, </l>
          <l>Then flung away, and left us in amazement. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e19400">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>'Twas done as to his well-known Enemies, </l>
          <l>And, Traytor, was it not that Loyal Son, </l>
          <l>That brave Arsanes? (whom by Heav'n I'm proud </l>
          <l>That he should call me Father) was't not he, </l>
          <l>Who spight of all the base indignities, </l>
          <l>Under whose load he sunk to banishment, </l>
          <l>Came with new Strength so wonderfully fierce? </l>
          <l>So unexpected was all kind of Succour, </l>
          <l>Not one among our gazing Troops, </l>
          <l>Scarce I my self, but thought him Mahomet. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e19540">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Too well, dread Prince, he fought, if all were known, </l>
          <l>He has already half eclips'd your Fame, </l>
          <l>Witness all Tartary, which bowing low, </l>
          <l>Kisses the very Ground on which he treads. </l>
          <l>Do not you hear Arsanes mighty Name </l>
          <l>Eccho'd through every Street, long live Arsanes, </l>
          <l>A Thousand Voices ev'n in your Court reply, </l>
          <l>While Tamerlane must stand neglected by, </l>
          <l>And wait upon the Triumphs of his Son. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e19690">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>By Hell thou art the very Soul of lying. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e19720">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Nay more I fear, it is no false report, </l>
          <l>The specious Acts he wrought in your defence, </l>
          <l>Cut but his way into your Peoples Hearts, </l>
          <l>And a wide Path to his Ambition made. </l>
          <l>This I may safely swear, my Lord, he's false. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e19790">
          <speaker>Abd </speaker>
          <l>The same swear I. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e19820">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>You both are Villains, </l>
          <l>False, treacherous, perjur'd, damn'd Villains, </l>
          <l>Whose spotted Souls regard not Innocence, </l>
          <l>Nor Conscience trembles, when you dare accuse it. </l>
          <pb n="29" xml:id="ep000762-020-b"/>
          <l>And now to let you know how little Faith </l>
          <l>Your seeming Counsels fix upon my Soul, </l>
          <l>Call here the Prince Arsanes— spight of yours </l>
          <l>And Mandricards more hateful Policies, </l>
          <l>I'le Crown his Vertue with Rewards so large, </l>
          <l>Shall raise your envy high, as is his Fate. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e19960">Enter Arsanes. </stage>
          <l>Come to my Arms my best, my Loyal Son, </l>
          <l>Let me embrace thee all, my long-wish'd Joys </l>
          <l>At last are come; rise my better self: </l>
          <l>See there the Authors of thy former woes, </l>
          <l>See them, that wou'd renew thy Miseries; </l>
          <l>Villain, is this a Face shews discontent, </l>
          <l>What wild unstable looks are here, what frown, </l>
          <l>What gesture that may render him suspected? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e20060">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>I always thought those Men my Enemies; </l>
          <l>Yet I confess, Great Sir, I have deserv'd </l>
          <l>All that their envy or your juster wrath </l>
          <l>Have made me suffer: For whom e're he be </l>
          <l>So just a Prince thinks false, or but suspects, </l>
          <l>By Heav'n he's false; nay then 'tis a Crime, </l>
          <l>A Crime unpardonable in innocence </l>
          <l>To say she's wrong'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e20160">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>He has a Tongue as smooth </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e20190">[To Odmar aside. </stage>
          <l>As yours, pray Heav'n it may but prove as fatal. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e20220">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>You false, believe me; nor thy Conqueror </l>
          <l>Your injur'd Vertue claims a Recompence </l>
          <l>So large, with guilty thoughts I blushing hear, </l>
          <l>That now to share that Empire you have sav'd, </l>
          <l>With that your Arms have won, will be a light, </l>
          <l>An empty Offering to your vast deserts; </l>
          <l>Men stile us Scythians barbarous and wild, </l>
          <l>But I appeal to the Immortal Pow'rs, </l>
          <l>If ever Rome in all her Pomp cou'd show </l>
          <l>An Act like what Arsanes has perform'd. </l>
          <l>An Act so good, Athens wou'd blush to hear, </l>
          <l>As wanting fit example to compare. </l>
          <l>An Act to brave the Heroes from their Orbs, </l>
          <pb n="30" xml:id="ep000762-021-a"/>
          <l>The famous Senate of unconquer'd Minds, </l>
          <l>Start back, and think their Glory faintly won, </l>
          <l>So much Arsanes has surpass'd their Deeds. </l>
          <l>An Act— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e20460">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Of which I thought the insolence </l>
          <l>Might rather raise your Anger, than your Love, </l>
          <l>To see an Exil'd Slave, who durst return </l>
          <l>Uncall'd to share the Trophies of your Fame. </l>
          <l>Yet let me plead but this in my defence, </l>
          <l>My Duty to so just a Father, and </l>
          <l>So good a Prince, work'd high my ravish'd Soul, </l>
          <l>Nor could my Blood be chill'd with outward fear, </l>
          <l>Or inward grief, but boyling in my Veins, </l>
          <l>As one shou'd say 'twas part of Tamerlanes, </l>
          <l>Stir'd me to go where Fame and Duty call'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e20600">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>Ruin'd as handsomely as Hell cou'd wish us. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e20630">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Now in the Face of thy worst Enemies </l>
          <l>Receive the highest Honours we can give; </l>
          <l>Let loose thy vast Ambition, let it fly </l>
          <l>At Riches, Honour, Love, or once at all. </l>
          <l>Your Word shall guide our Heart, your Wishes bind </l>
          <l>Our Will; your Pray'rs command what e're they crave, </l>
          <l>Ask, and believe it granted e're you speak. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e20720">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>Now cou'd I cut thy Throat instead of his. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e20750">[To Odm. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e20770">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Lawrels, and Crowns are Tamerlanes alone, </l>
          <l>And the Rich Entrails of the Golden Earth </l>
          <l>Serve but to fill the Lustre of his Name. </l>
          <l>It is, Great Sir, a light Request I make, </l>
          <l>And yet in my esteem worth Worlds, so great </l>
          <l>A Prize the fair Asteria seems to me, </l>
          <l>That were I seated on the Scythian Throne, </l>
          <l>With swarms of Tributary Kings about me, </l>
          <l>And subject Princes waiting my Commands, </l>
          <l>By all my wishes I shou'd scarce enjoy </l>
          <l>One moments rest, without the beauteous Bride. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e20930">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Ye Gods, that ever such antipathy </l>
          <l>Shou'd be united; Oh cou'd I but taste </l>
          <l>The sleepy Waters of dull Lethe's Lake, </l>
          <l>That I might now forget those hateful words. </l>
          <l>I tell thee, Prince, thy fond Request is vain, </l>
          <pb n="31" xml:id="ep000762-021-b"/>
          <l>Which nor consists with Duty, nor with Honour. </l>
          <l>She is thy Enemy, Arsanes, cease </l>
          <l>To think of her. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e21050">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Take Heart, Abdalla, see, </l>
          <l>The Prince is Planet-struck, and Tamerlane </l>
          <l>Pursues his ruine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e21120">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Duty bids me not </l>
          <l>Dispute your dread Commands, yet I must blame </l>
          <l>The coldness of my Stars, and too hard Fate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e21170">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>It is not fancy sure disturbs my mind, </l>
          <l>And leads my wav'ring thoughts to jealousie; </l>
          <l>Yet I cou'd shun thee now, Arsanes, here </l>
          <l>Thy dark Request sticks deep: Farewell, and when </l>
          <l>You make your next, if not as a Son, </l>
          <l>Ask what is fitting for a Friend. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e21260">[Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e21270">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>'Tis just, </l>
          <l>As Hell and we cou'd wish. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e21310">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Now is our time, </l>
          <l>To shed out all our Poison on his Soul, </l>
          <l>Which Heav'n nor Arsanes may controul. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e21370">[Exeunt. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e21380">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Now from a fairest Heav'n of surest hope </l>
          <l>Am I thus faln? O sudden turn of Fortune! </l>
          <l>Quite ruin'd e're I scarce perceiv'd a Change. </l>
          <l>Thus stands some mighty Tower, the Bulwark of </l>
          <l>A Nation, shooting up her lofty Head </l>
          <l>Above the Clouds, gaz'd and wonder'd at, </l>
          <l>But in a moment see to Ashes turn'd </l>
          <l>Its tot'ring pride on some base Traytors Guilt, </l>
          <l>And scarce the marks of all its Glory left. </l>
          <l>Thus— But oh the Star that guilds my days. </l>
          <l>She comes; and now my fading sorrows pass, </l>
          <l>Like showry Clouds before the Glorious Sun. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e21520">Enter Asteria. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e21540">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>My dearest Lord, so may you find all Joys </l>
          <l>My Heart can wish you, as you shall unfold </l>
          <l>The Mystick Secret of that sad Complaint </l>
          <l>Just now you sent to Heav'n. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e21600">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Most impious were I </l>
          <pb n="32" xml:id="ep000762-022-a"/>
          <l>Could I while I possess those numerous Worlds </l>
          <l>Of fullest pleasures hanging o're your Brow, </l>
          <l>Those endless Comforts basking in your Eyes, </l>
          <l>And all the Charms which wait upon your Smile, </l>
          <l>Ungratefully and foolishly complain. </l>
          <l>Pard'n me ye Pow'rs, if I have offended, </l>
          <l>For to Arsanes you are wond'rous kind, </l>
          <l>Most bountiful, who in the fair Nerina </l>
          <l>All I can ask, all I can wish, have giv'n. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e21740">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Yes, Adanaxus, we are free to love, </l>
          <l>And I without a crime can give a Heart, </l>
          <l>With Honour, Duty, and a Fathers Will. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e21800">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>What is't I hear? what sudden happiness </l>
          <l>Raps my glad Soul? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e21840">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>'Tis true, as strange. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e21870">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>O Bliss! </l>
          <l>O Harmony! but how the wond'rous Change </l>
          <l>Was wrought, dulls all my busie thoughts to guess. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e21920">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Then first I knelt, and wept, and kiss'd his Feet, </l>
          <l>And told how I had been his Darling from </l>
          <l>My very Infancy, and what Delights </l>
          <l>My Childish Sports afforded him— how dear </l>
          <l>He priz'd my Mother, made him sensible </l>
          <l>Of his past Joys with her, and then conjur'd him </l>
          <l>By her blest Ashes, and Eternal Name, </l>
          <l>To have compassion on me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e22020">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Words like these </l>
          <l>Wou'd charm the rav'ning Wolf with hunger pinch'd, </l>
          <l>With a strange softness to forego his Prey, </l>
          <l>And make him tender as the panting Lamb. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e22080">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>But yet the joyful Grant he had not seal'd, </l>
          <l>When once again I did embrace his Knees, </l>
          <l>And call'd to his remembrance how he liv'd </l>
          <l>By your kind intercession, though he scorns </l>
          <l>The Life you gave; yet frankly he confess'd </l>
          <l>It was a Noble pity in a Mind </l>
          <l>So great as yours. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e22170">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Oh the Angelick Sound! </l>
          <l>Cou'd yet the moving Argument be vain? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e22210">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>It was, my Lord, till turning to a Theme </l>
          <pb n="33" xml:id="ep000762-022-b"/>
          <l>Of more concern, I told him I lov'd, </l>
          <l>How I was lov'd, with what a generous Flame </l>
          <l>You answered my Affections, how by you </l>
          <l>I was protected from the violence </l>
          <l>Of rash Andronicus; and then he smil'd </l>
          <l>And said 'twas nobly done, and as a Lover. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e22310">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>And yet cou'd he deny? Oh what remain'd, </l>
          <l>What cou'd you farther urge? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e22350">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Your Noble Acts, </l>
          <l>Your constant Vertue, and unviolate Faith, </l>
          <l>How weighing not your wrongs then thick upon you, </l>
          <l>Banish'd by your great Fathers jealous rage, </l>
          <l>Your Loyal Vertue still unshook, unconquer'd, </l>
          <l>Brought Kingdoms to his Throne, and Lawrels to his Head. </l>
          <l>This he was strangely taken with, and lost </l>
          <l>Much of his fury; wondred, and grew kind, </l>
          <l>And swore he cou'd not be a Foe to Vertue </l>
          <l>Of so sublime a Nature, then he rose, </l>
          <l>And gave a soft Command, and charg'd me love you, </l>
          <l>Not as a Prince, not as the Tyrants Son, </l>
          <l>But something more than Man, and nearer to the Gods. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e22500">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Thus kneel kind Angels at the Feet of Heav'n, </l>
          <l>When ready to destroy the impious World, </l>
          <l>They with soft Pray'rs recall the bolted Thunder, </l>
          <l>And ev'n o're-take the swiftest Lightnings Course. </l>
          <l>Blest that I am in thy most charming, sweet, </l>
          <l>Prevailing Oratory; thus cou'd we move </l>
          <l>But Tamerlanes far more obdurate Heart, </l>
          <l>Then were we blest. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e22610">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Then were we blest indeed. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e22640">Enter Zayda confus'dly, and in hast. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-zay" xml:id="ep000762-e22660">
          <speaker>Zay. </speaker>
          <l>O dismal Chance, O fatal Destiny! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e22690">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>What means this dreadful Voice, not Croaking Ravens, </l>
          <l>With Midnight-shreiks, e're thus disturb'd my Soul. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-zay" xml:id="ep000762-e22730">
          <speaker>Zay. </speaker>
          <l>Your Father— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e22760">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Say, what can his ill-tim'd Fate, </l>
          <l>Malicious Chance, and inauspicious Stars, </l>
          <l>Do to advance his full-blown Spring of Sorrow? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-zay" xml:id="ep000762-e22810">
          <pb n="34" xml:id="ep000762-023-a"/>
          <speaker>Zay. </speaker>
          <l>Unheard-of Cruelty! the Faithless Tyrant, </l>
          <l>Incens'd by your great Fathers haughty Rage, </l>
          <l>Who though in Chains, with his great Spirit frights </l>
          <l>The Jealous King, and with a Princely scorn </l>
          <l>Vexes his raging Soul; which to Revenge, </l>
          <l>Fierce Tamerlane (O cruel Artifice!) </l>
          <l>Lock'd in an Iron Cage his Rival Slave, </l>
          <l>While he in barbarous Triumph mounted on </l>
          <l>His Shoulders to his Chariot. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e22930">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Savage Prince. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e22960">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>O Cruelty! Oh more than Hellish Torment! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-zay" xml:id="ep000762-e22990">
          <speaker>Zay. </speaker>
          <l>Impatient of his wrongs, the Royal Captive, </l>
          <l>As he through Samarcanda's Streets was led </l>
          <l>A publick Trophy in his moving Prison, </l>
          <l>Against the massy Bars with rage he dash'd </l>
          <l>His Royal Head, while from the fatal Wound </l>
          <l>Gush'd out that Blood, which long the greatest Life </l>
          <l>The World cou'd ever proudly boast preserv'd, </l>
          <l>Who in a Storm of— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e23100">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>O I faint, I faint, </l>
          <l>To hear you out will send my Soul away, </l>
          <l>E're I can to his Fate my Duty pay. </l>
          <l>Farewell, my Lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e23160">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>O my dearest Life, </l>
          <l>Let me, let me support thy fainting Beauties. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e23200">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>O Adanaxus, now we'r lost again. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e23240">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Unhappy Fate! thus ever in our Joys </l>
          <l>A sudden Thunderbolt divides us. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e23280">[Exeunt severally. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e23290">Enter Mandricard alone with a Letter. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e23310">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>What shall I do? shall I not go? not now? </l>
          <l>When thus the true Idea of that Face </l>
          <l>Calls my glad Soul, which we adore in Angels? </l>
          <l>(Great Mandricard, I'le sing thee in my Lap) </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e23380">[Reading. </stage>
          <l>I come, I come, <hi>Asteria, Mercury</hi>, </l>
          <l>Lend me thy winged Buskins, that in thought </l>
          <l>I may in swiftness penetrate the Air. </l>
          <l>O welcome, welcome be thou to my Soul, </l>
          <l>I kiss thee for her sake, whose Ivory Hands </l>
          <pb n="35" xml:id="ep000762-023-b"/>
          <l>Have deep engrav'd these Golden Characters. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e23460">To him Ispatia unseen. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e23480">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>So now, Ispatia, thou hast view'd his Heart, </l>
          <l>And seen it flaming with another Dart; </l>
          <l>Then to compleat the Sum of all my Pains, </l>
          <l>Death is the only Torment that remains. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e23550">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e23560">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>To thee, sweet Saint, I come, I fly to thee. </l>
          <l>But what ill Fates have intercepted me? </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e23600">[Enter Arsanes. </stage>
          <l>Arsanes here? wou'd Hell it were his Ghost, </l>
          <l>Now by my Arms a far more welcome sight. </l>
          <l>Yet now for my defence a well-forg'd Lie, </l>
          <l>With a false shew of Penitential Kindness, </l>
          <l>Will be most exquisite. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e23680">[Coming near and bowing to Arsanes. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e23700">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>What wou'd this Woman? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e23730">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Ha! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e23760">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Art thou </l>
          <l>Offended with the Name, then change the Art: </l>
          <l>For all I yet can see in thee is Woman, </l>
          <l>Forc'd Tears, feign'd Flatteries, and deep Dissembling, </l>
          <l>These seldom sure possess a Manly Breast. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e23830">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>If ought I've done, can be by what I'le do— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e23860">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>There's death in thy deceitful Eyes and Tongue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e23890">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Deceit, and Death, what mean those Mystick words, </l>
          <l>Which strike like double Daggers to my Heart? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e23930">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Art thou not false? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-nan" xml:id="ep000762-e23960">
          <speaker>Nan. </speaker>
          <l>Destructive Fame, thy worst </l>
          <l>Blow all thy lying Trumpets through the World, </l>
          <l>And to all Ears pronounce me false, yet not </l>
          <l>The blasting Breath of all thy hundred Mouths </l>
          <l>Can on my injur'd Vertue cast a blot. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e24030">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>The Careful Pilot riding on the Main, </l>
          <l>May tack about, and shun the highest Rocks; </l>
          <l>But those he fears which skulk beneath the Waves, </l>
          <l>The unseen Instruments of grinning Death. </l>
          <l>You work my ruine, not with Hand, but Heart, </l>
          <l>The lurking Treasure of black Designs. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e24110">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Had I by any other Man been drawn </l>
          <l>In such a Character, so much unlike, </l>
          <pb n="36" xml:id="ep000762-024-a"/>
          <l>So inconsistent with a Princely Mind, </l>
          <l>That Man had with his final ruine brought </l>
          <l>Swift vengeance on himself for what he said; </l>
          <l>By Heav'n! had he but thought it, he had dy'd: </l>
          <l>With you quite otherwise I beg my peace, </l>
          <l>Nature commands you seal my happiness. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e24210">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Ha! are the Wounds I bear so light? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e24240">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>What Wounds? </l>
          <l>This Tongue, this Heart, and Hand are innocent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e24280">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Ask'st thou what Wounds? So did fell Atreus ask </l>
          <l>His fainting brother, drunk with humane Blood, </l>
          <l>And heavy with the weight of his own Bowels </l>
          <l>Set to him as a Banquet; what he ail'd. </l>
          <l>I tell thee Brother, 'twas wretched thing, </l>
          <l>An exil'd Slave, and Heir to Tamerlane. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e24380">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Is that not blotted out? I'le hear no more; </l>
          <l>Since you my Friendship, and my love contemn, </l>
          <l>I scorn all Treaties of a further Peace. </l>
          <l>Come on, Revenge; like Wolves, and spotted Tygers </l>
          <l>We'l live together in perpetual strife, </l>
          <l>And when we meet it must be always War. </l>
          <l>Of which be this the Sacred, binding Gage. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e24470">Throw him the Letter and Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e24480">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>'Twas boldly spoke, and much unlike himself, </l>
          <l>He ne'r profess'd himself my Foe till now. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e24520">To him Axalla. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e24540">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>Saw you not Mandricard, my Lord? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e24580">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>I did; </l>
          <l>Behold this witness of his treacherous hate. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e24620">[Opening the Letter. </stage>
          <l>Dazle my Eyes? or is it from Asteria? </l>
          <l>What sudden madness seizes my lost Senses? </l>
          <l>And makes me think what is impossible? </l>
          <l>'Tis all delusion— Ha— from my Nerina! </l>
          <l>Directed too to Mandricard? Oh Heav'n! </l>
          <l>At her Apartment. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e24720">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>Oh the Monster Woman! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e24750">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>'Tis sure some feign'd device! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e24780">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>Her own false Hand, </l>
          <pb n="37" xml:id="ep000762-024-b"/>
          <l>Her Hand that writes her Hearts unconstant Love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e24820">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>How oft have I such tender Characters, </l>
          <l>Of the same size and make, lock'd in my Breast, </l>
          <l>And kiss'd and worship'd 'em like little Idols. </l>
          <l>They'r like— what though they are? so polish'd Glass </l>
          <l>Resembles Chrystal mimically Fair, </l>
          <l>And is not so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e24900">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>But Women are most Women. </l>
          <l>When they are truly Hypocrites. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e24940">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>But my Nerina, glory of her Sex, </l>
          <l>How have I always thought her more than Woman! </l>
          <l>In whom th' Almighty Painter had exprest </l>
          <l>The Fairest Pattern of exactest Angels, </l>
          <l>Her Soul he drew the very Lively Image </l>
          <l>Of some bless'd Saint, or ever-happy Martyr; </l>
          <l>But oh she of that Rank of Angels Proves, </l>
          <l>Whose due Commission's only to destroy, </l>
          <l>Arm'd with fierce Judgments of the Wrath Divine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e25060">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>Then shun those Judgments which you see so nigh, </l>
          <l>So plain, so manifest, and now shou'd you— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e25100">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>I cannot, and I pray thee do not curse her, </l>
          <l>'Tis punishment enough sh'as giv'n her self </l>
          <l>To one that is unconstant as her self, </l>
          <l>And I with pity leave her to her choice. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e25160">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>O the glad Sound! and will you quit this fondness, </l>
          <l>And follow Honour, and hunt after Fame? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e25200">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>No, my Axalla, think not I can see </l>
          <l>Her Beauties in my presence ravish'd from me, </l>
          <l>And all the Sacred Store prophanely rifl'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e25260">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>Then work your just Revenge, on him, on her, </l>
          <l>On all— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e25300">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Be hush'd, and dare not name Revenge; </l>
          <l>The Name of Brother aws my rising Fury, </l>
          <l>And for Nerina, she is yet so dear, </l>
          <l>I'le suffer all things for her, quit my Honours, </l>
          <l>My hopes of Scepters, and my right to Crowns, </l>
          <l>Nay her dear self for her more certain ease. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e25390">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>Strangely resolv'd! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e25420">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Like Love undone by Fate, </l>
          <l>Oh cou'd I tell where blear-ey'd Sorrow dwells, </l>
          <pb n="38" xml:id="ep000762-025-a"/>
          <l>Where bellowing out her Soul in discontent, </l>
          <l>The empty Walls reverberate her woe. </l>
          <l>To some such place, Axalla, let us fly; </l>
          <l>There will I on some cold hard Stone lay down </l>
          <l>My mournful Head, while from my furrow'd Cheeks </l>
          <l>My frequent Tears promiscuously fall; </l>
          <l>One day I will bewail my own misfortunes, </l>
          <l>Another will I kindly dedicate </l>
          <l>To the lov'd Memory of Nerina's Father. </l>
          <l>Whole Months and Years in tedious sorrow pass, </l>
          <l>For my Nerina, that false, much-lov'd Maid, </l>
          <l>Complain of all my angry Foes above, </l>
          <l>With mournful sighs the hollow Ecchoes move, </l>
          <l>And the last Groans of a departing Love. </l>
          <l>To Heav'n these only Vows, these Pray'rs I'le make, </l>
          <l>Nerina may her fatal Choice forsake, </l>
          <l>And from her bosom cast the lurking Snake. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e25670">[Exeunt. </stage>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="ep000762-e25680">
        <head>ACT IV. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e25700">A Councel-Table. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e25710">Enter <hi>Tamerlane, Odmar, Abdalla</hi>, with other Lords and Attendants. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e25730">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>'TIs time to look about me, I have slept </l>
          <l>Too long, lull'd into visionary Dreams </l>
          <l>Of fleeting pleasures, which I waking, find </l>
          <l>Most dangerous, and for a seeming Son </l>
          <l>My Bosom has receiv'd the worst of Foes. </l>
          <l>Arsines fled? and Conference with Turkey? </l>
          <l>O Viper, Parricide, but say, my Friends. </l>
          <l>What timely Fortune has his Crimes reveal'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e25850">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>Ev'n that which ruines all Conspiracies, </l>
          <l>A squeamish Conscience, and a light Reward. </l>
          <l>The Ministers he hir'd to his Designs </l>
          <pb n="39" xml:id="ep000762-025-b"/>
          <l>Stand Witnesses against him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e25910">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Bring 'em forth. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e25940">Exit Odmar, and re-enters with two Slaves. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e25960">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Now act the Villains home, now is your time. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e25990">[Aside to Slaves. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e26000">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Friends to our Crown, for Friends you seem to be, </l>
          <l>Whose care has been employ'd to serve our State </l>
          <l>From those apparent Dangers threatned it. </l>
          <l>We charge you in our Holy Prophets Name </l>
          <l>Lay forth the Traytors Heart before our Eyes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e26070">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Swear on the Alcoran your Accusations </l>
          <l>Are just and true— Oh the unhappy Prince. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e26110">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>S'heart, well play'd Fox, he seems to hear with grief </l>
          <l>What he suborns false Witnesses to swear. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e26150">[Aside. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-1slave" xml:id="ep000762-e26160">
          <speaker>1. Slave. </speaker>
          <l>By all the Orders of Tartarian Pow'rs </l>
          <l>Bound by Allegiance to our Sovereign, </l>
          <l>We here are present to accuse and swear </l>
          <l>Arsanes guilty of these Articles: </l>
          <l>No more than which himself did testifie, </l>
          <l>And gave us in Commission to perform. </l>
          <l>First that this Prince holds private Conference </l>
          <l>With the surviving Race of Bajaset. </l>
          <l>That with the fair Asteria's Love enflam'd, </l>
          <l>He seeks his Rival Brothers hated Life; </l>
          <l>Then with Axalla that he doth combine, </l>
          <l>To Poison Tamerlane our Royal Master, </l>
          <l>And with Asteria to usurp his Throne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e26380">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Treach'ry unheard beyond the Thought of Man! </l>
          <l>But tell me, Friend, where bides the Traytor? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e26420">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Speak, </l>
          <l>Say any where. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e26460">[Aside to the Slave. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-sl" xml:id="ep000762-e26470">
          <speaker>Sl. </speaker>
          <l>n a lone Wood, my Lord, </l>
          <l>After a long Complaint against the Prince▪ </l>
          <l>His Royal Brother; full of envious hate </l>
          <l>And proud disdain; after he had rehears'd </l>
          <l>All his pretended wrongs in Banishment </l>
          <l>Receiv'd; blushing Scarlet deep with Shame, </l>
          <l>He rose to an Arraignment of the State, </l>
          <l>And our establish'd Laws— </l>
          <l>Then impiously against his Father rag'd, </l>
          <l>And swore Revenge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e26590">
          <pb n="40" xml:id="ep000762-026-a"/>
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>Methinks now Stratagem </l>
          <l>Comes on to something. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e26630">[Aside. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e26640">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>These are practis'd Villains. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-2sl" xml:id="ep000762-e26670">
          <speaker>2. Sl. </speaker>
          <l>Himself he said was streight for Prusia bound, </l>
          <l>Where the young Rebel Princes wait his coming. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e26720">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Perdition on the Viper! how he bites! </l>
          <l>Could e're such baseness spring from Tamerlane. </l>
          <l>Is this his Piety so far renown'd? </l>
          <l>That Loyalty which seem'd inviolable? </l>
          <l>Those Oaths that cou'd have forc'd all Heav'n believe him? </l>
          <l>Is this his scorn of Honours and Rewards? </l>
          <l>And did he starve his hungry Appetite, </l>
          <l>That with a stronger Fury he might run </l>
          <l>Wolf-like upon our Life and Diadem? </l>
          <l>And gaping, swallow all the Golden Prey. </l>
          <l>Fly, fly, Arsanes, breath on what Soil thou wilt </l>
          <l>Thy hated Life, though every Sea shou'd joyn </l>
          <l>In one vast Ocean, their assistant Floods </l>
          <l>To part us ever, though thy adverse Feet </l>
          <l>In unknown Tracks kick at our upper Earth, </l>
          <l>Though o're the Starry Pole thou soaring fly'st </l>
          <l>Above old Winter, and deep Beds of Snow, </l>
          <l>Our painted Vengeance shall pursue thy Soul, </l>
          <l>And spy thee in thy darkest Caverns hid, </l>
          <l>Pierce through thy Mansion with our sharp Revenge, </l>
          <l>Or send our Curses, where we cannot reach. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e26970">[Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e26980">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>See there, Arsanes, how the rowling Waves </l>
          <l>Come on amain, and dash thee on the Rock. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e27030">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>Methinks we two now like the Sea-born Giants, </l>
          <l>Great Otus, and tall Ephaltes stand, </l>
          <l>And grow out all their Acres in a moment. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e27100">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Our Fortunes Friend in this vast Enterprise </l>
          <l>Have made us free to give the Scythian Throne </l>
          <l>To whom we please; Come, Mandricard, and claim </l>
          <l>Thy vast Possessions, ask us Heav'n next, </l>
          <l>And we'l do more with these two Fertile Brains, </l>
          <l>Then e're Briareus with his hundred Hands. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e27210">[Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e27220">
          <pb n="41" xml:id="ep000762-026-b"/>Asteria's Apartment. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e27230">Who is discover'd lying on a Couch, a Cupid in Soft Musick descends over her and Sings. </stage>
        <lg>
          <head>Song. </head>
          <lg>
            <l>HOw pleasant Vertue are thy Slumbers, </l>
            <l>Sound thy Sleeps, and sweet thy Dreams, </l>
            <l>While thee no Fear, no Guilt incumbers, </l>
            <l>Danger frights, or Thought condemns? </l>
          </lg>
          <lg n="1">
            <head>2. </head>
            <l>Thou naked with resistless Armour </l>
            <l>Dost thy self revenge, and shield, </l>
            <l>Thou silent art so sweet a Charmer, </l>
            <l>To thy Reasons all must yield. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg n="2">
            <head>3. </head>
            <l>On thy fair Brow sits smiling Honour, </l>
            <l>Iustice waits thy awful Voice, </l>
            <l>Thou Heir to Blessings art, thou Owner </l>
            <l>Of Rich Fortunes Richest Ioys. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg n="3">
            <head>4. </head>
            <l>Thou, what is Heav'ns greatest Blessing, </l>
            <l>Art the Darling Child of Love, </l>
            <l>Though Heav'n yet hinder from possessing, </l>
            <l>It will all thy Pains remove. </l>
          </lg>
        </lg>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e27500">[The Cupid ascends. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e27520">Asteria awakes in great disorder. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e27540">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>What Mystick Objects entertain my Soul, </l>
          <l>And hold me in amazement? how confus'd </l>
          <l>Are all my Thoughts, kind Joys with Troubles mixt, </l>
          <l>Hope with dread Fear, disorder'd mass of Fancy! </l>
          <l>The End seem'd good, but oh that End is vain, </l>
          <l>As fleeting as its Shade, as womanish </l>
          <l>And fond a Dream, as to my weary'd Eyes </l>
          <l>Thought cou'd suggest, or Mimick Fancy play. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e27640">
          <pb n="42" xml:id="ep000762-027-a"/>Is going out. Enter Mandricard staying her. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e27660">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>So on fair Paphos Isle the wanton Queen </l>
          <l>Her Shelly Chariot drawn with sporting Doves, </l>
          <l>Had lightly enter'd in a smiling Calm, </l>
          <l>Ready to cruise upon her Parent Seas, </l>
          <l>When from a-far the Warlike God espy'd her, </l>
          <l>And brought her back to more substantial Pleasures. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e27750">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>What means this fatal Comet to our House, </l>
          <l>Near what new birth of mischief does he shine? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e27790">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>At length my Pray'rs are heard, my Vows have reach'd </l>
          <l>The Deity, to which they were address'd. </l>
          <l>Accept, O Fairest Pow'r, from a Prince, </l>
          <l>The Faithful Sacrifice of Humblest Thanks, </l>
          <l>For all the Blessings you have pour'd upon him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e27860">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>What Blessings, or what Prince? yet shou'd there be </l>
          <l>Any my tenderness has gratifi'd, </l>
          <l>He's chose an ill Ambassador I'm sure </l>
          <l>To pay his just Acknowledgments, which needs </l>
          <l>Must taste ungrateful from the Man I hate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e27930">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Heav'n, how discordant are her Hand and Tongue! </l>
          <l>Think not, <hi>Asteria, Mandricard </hi>cou'd trust </l>
          <l>To any Second his most Bosom Secret, </l>
          <l>I the Receiver-kneel to pay the Debt. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e28000">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>If you from me a Kindness did receive, </l>
          <l>I'm sure 'twas small, and may be paid with ease. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e28040">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>How unconcern'd she speaks, and looks disdain! </l>
          <l>Yes, Madam, Heart for Heart is easie change; </l>
          <l>Flames will meet Flames, and Fires joyn with Fires, </l>
          <l>Ravage through all, and leave no middle space. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e28100">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Rav'st thou, or do my Ears drink in a Sound </l>
          <l>As real, as 'tis monstrous? Oh my Stars, </l>
          <l>Protect me, and remove the hateful Object. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e28150">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Yet Princess, your fair Hand has otherwise </l>
          <l>Decipher'd me— the Glorious Mandricard— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e28200">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>My Hand! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e28230">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Your Hand, which on the happy Paper prest </l>
          <l>The Praises of your much lov'd Mandricard. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e28280">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Curst be that Hand that writes thee ought but Fiend, </l>
          <pb n="43" xml:id="ep000762-027-b"/>
          <l>Curst be that Tongue that speaks thee ought but Monster. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e28320">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Unfold, Great Alha, this Mysterious Secret! </l>
          <l>Come, you dissemble, and a modest shame </l>
          <l>Defers our Joys. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e28380">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>I'de clasp a Serpent sooner; </l>
          <l>Had my base Hand e're thus bely'd my Heart, </l>
          <l>As an infectious Limb I'de tear it from </l>
          <l>My tainted Body, for the Wild Beasts, or Flames. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e28440">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>You need not now, Asteria, use such Language, </l>
          <l>There are no Oaths, no Promises, no Vows </l>
          <l>To be kept now: Sure Death has swallow'd all, </l>
          <l>And cold Arsanes in their ruine lies. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e28520">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Yes, I will keep 'em still to punish thee, </l>
          <l>My Faith shall be the Scourge of my Revenge, </l>
          <l>My Constancy shall keep thee on a Rack </l>
          <l>Of Everlasting Torments, and my Oaths </l>
          <l>Shall one by one strike thee with mad despair; </l>
          <l>Thou art my Slave, and thou shalt live like one. </l>
          <l>Thinkest thou, fond Fomenter of my Grief, </l>
          <l>I do not hate that Man to Death, nay Hell, </l>
          <l>That caus'd Arsanes Ruine? Proud Prince, I do; </l>
          <l>Remember, Sir, my Brothers, Fathers Wrongs, </l>
          <l>And blush to ask a Grace of me; to love? </l>
          <l>No not to look, or visit me with Monsters. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e28670">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>You treat me, Fair one, so severe a way, </l>
          <l>As forces me to plead in my defence. </l>
          <l>If in the War your Brother fell, not I, </l>
          <l>But Fortune guiding my far-wandring Steel, </l>
          <l>Cut off the forward Youth— </l>
          <l>For your Great Fathers, and Arsanes Wrongs, </l>
          <l>I'm innocent as harmless Infants are. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e28770">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>You innocent! so's Hell; so is your Train </l>
          <l>Of Fellow-Villains, Infernal Ministers, </l>
          <l>Are they not Prince? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e28820">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>What e're you'l have 'em be </l>
          <l>They are, they must; and which of 'em but dares </l>
          <l>Offer to plead his Innocence, he dies. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e28870">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Fine Flatterer! thus did that supple Tongue </l>
          <l>Sooth Tamerlane to hate the best of Princes: </l>
          <l>Nor have you ended there, but cherish still </l>
          <pb n="44" xml:id="ep000762-028-a"/>
          <l>Your Breast with thinking with what subtle Art </l>
          <l>You spread your Snares to catch the Prey design'd, </l>
          <l>And glory in the Murderous Success. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e28960">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>How sweet her Looks, yet dreadful to approach! </l>
          <l>Madam, a Prince repentant begs your Pardon, </l>
          <l>And as the Fury of the Scythian Sword </l>
          <l>Is now asswag'd, untaught to hurt or kill, </l>
          <l>So let your Anger be allay'd with mildness; </l>
          <l>So will the World in peaceful Triumph sit, </l>
          <l>And smilling, pall the envious Fates designs. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e29060">To them Ispatia. </stage>
          <l>Ha! whence that Hellish Fury like her self </l>
          <l>Has brought her here? Curse on the twining Serpent! </l>
          <l>Shall I ne'r shake her off! by Heav'n it comes! </l>
          <l>A swift Contrivance whets my sudden Thought, </l>
          <l>Which shall divide us ever, far as Heav'n, </l>
          <l>Or far as Hell their Center hold from Earth. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e29140">[Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e29150">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>Art thou the watry Sourse from whence this Stream, </l>
          <l>These daily gushings of my Mourning Eyes </l>
          <l>Burst forth, and almost drown my fainting Heart? </l>
          <l>Are those the Comets, whose dire Influence </l>
          <l>Sheds Ruine on me; is there in that Voice </l>
          <l>So sweet an Harmony, so full of Charms, </l>
          <l>It can bewitch the Sense of Mandricard? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e29250">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Yes, Mandricard has learnt to stoop to me, </l>
          <l>And at my Feet his daily Homage pay, </l>
          <l>Which thus I scorn, and spurn ev'n into Wind. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e29310">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>Unsufferable Creature, does she scorn him? </l>
          <l>Oh more, far more than this, I cou'd endure </l>
          <l>Her Love; contemn him? nay that is not all, </l>
          <l>She Rivals me, and yet professes scorn; </l>
          <l>Is't not enough you have ensnar'd his Love? </l>
          <l>Caught with a Golden Bait his yielding Heart? </l>
          <l>But you must on his Honour raise contempt, </l>
          <l>And make him cheap— Oh Torture, Oh my Soul! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e29410">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Know then, Ispatia, if you are resolv'd </l>
          <l>To sound my Heart, I frankly must confess </l>
          <l>I hate him, hate my Brothers Murderer </l>
          <pb n="45" xml:id="ep000762-028-b"/>
          <l>To death, and pray the Gods he may so love, </l>
          <l>So burn with Passion, till I pity him, </l>
          <l>Which Furies first shall do unto the Damn'd. </l>
          <l>Nay do not rage, but thank me that I hate him, </l>
          <l>For had I lov'd, Ispatia, had I lov'd, </l>
          <l>You might have found him lock'd within my Arms, </l>
          <l>Not prostrate at my Feet, nor had you e're </l>
          <l>Have been admitted to reprove me for it, </l>
          <l>As now you do. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e29570">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>'Tis like I shou'd not, Captive, </l>
          <l>Nor am I now perhaps, by your good leave; </l>
          <l>Yet I'le maintain the happiness I've sought, </l>
          <l>Stay here and pierce through either Heart, as far </l>
          <l>As Sharp ey'd Jealousie can look. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e29640">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Compleat </l>
          <l>With this one Promise then my Happiness, </l>
          <l>To hold him ever after from my sight. </l>
          <l>But see, he comes— </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e29700">[Enter Mandricard with a Priest. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e29720">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>A Priest! what Omens now </l>
          <l>Swell big that holy Harbinger of Fate? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e29760">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>This holy Man, Ispatia, as of old </l>
          <l>He joyn'd our Hands before the smiling Gods, </l>
          <l>So wou'd he now our Hearts; one Kiss upon </l>
          <l>The Sacred Alcoran, and our Love is Seal'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e29830">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>Blest Alteration! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e29860">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>O thrice happy Hour! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e29890">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>What sudden Ague seizes my chill'd Limbs? </l>
          <l>How my Eyes dazle, and my Senses swim! </l>
          <l>What have we done, my Lord? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e29940">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>O nothing, nothing, </l>
          <l>'Tis but a Fit, a Qualm, a certain Scout, </l>
          <l>Or flying Messenger from Deaths Tribunal, </l>
          <l>To summon thee to Everlasting Rest. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e30000">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>What means my Lord? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e30030">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Oh 'tis a Sovereign Balm, </l>
          <l>A Cure to all Distempers— to be plain, </l>
          <l>The Book was poison'd, and thou hast drunk the Venom. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e30080">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>O Traytor! yet e're I expire, hear me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e30110">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Speak quickly then. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e30140">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>Not long ago, my Lord, you did receive </l>
          <pb n="46" xml:id="ep000762-029-a"/>
          <l>A Letter from that Princess. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e30180">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Me! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e30210">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>With all </l>
          <l>The Pow'r of Penitence I here implore </l>
          <l>Your Pardon. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e30260">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>What means the Fury? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e30290">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>In her Name </l>
          <l>You took, embrac'd it, lock'd within your Bosom </l>
          <l>The outward Manuscript, within your Heart </l>
          <l>The sweet Contents. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e30350">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Which do enrich my Soul! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e30380">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>But now, ungrateful Man, be't spoke at last. </l>
          <l>To fright thy Lawless Passion be it spoke; </l>
          <l>I, not Asteria, wrote those Fatal Words </l>
          <l>Which cause my Death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e30450">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Then wou'd to Mahomet </l>
          <l>They may prove thy Damnation too. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e30500">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Oh Heav'n! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-isp" xml:id="ep000762-e30530">
          <speaker>Isp. </speaker>
          <l>Well, Traytor, thou hast had thy Fatal Wish, </l>
          <l>As it is sure I die; but know base Poisoner, </l>
          <l>Thy wily Treasons have not set thee free, </l>
          <l>Nor will Ispatia leave thee even in Death, </l>
          <l>I'le fright thee in thy Dreams, I'le haunt thee waking, </l>
          <l>I'le scourge thy Conscience with Whips of Remorse. </l>
          <l>The Sting of Serpents shall be nothing to it. </l>
          <l>Yes, I will have Revenge, I will; I'le strike </l>
          <l>Thee mad with terror, when thou dar'st approach </l>
          <l>My Rivals Beauties; Clasp her, and I'le glide </l>
          <l>All Cold between, and dash the fancy'd Joy. </l>
          <l>O <hi>Alha, Mahomet</hi>, O Courteous Heav'n, </l>
          <l>Give me but Power as here I yield my Soul </l>
          <l>Up to your Mercy in Deaths cruel Pangs. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e30710">[Dies. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e30720">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Remove the hated Body from my sight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e30750">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>And are there Pow'rs in Heav'n, and can they see </l>
          <l>This Sacrilegious Mischief go unpunish'd? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e30790">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>What ever Deities in Heav'n there are, </l>
          <l>They prove the Deed, and smile upon the Doer. </l>
          <l>And thus by giving thee reward it; now Priest. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e30840">[Mandricard and the Priest take her up, and are carrying her off. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e30860">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Look down, O Mahomet, from Heav'n, behold </l>
          <pb n="47" xml:id="ep000762-029-b"/>
          <l>My hard distressed Fortune; save, oh save </l>
          <l>A Virgins Chastity, unsoil'd, unstain'd, </l>
          <l>And right with Miracles thy Pow'r contemn'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e30930">Enter Axalla and Zanches, their Swords drawn. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e30960">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>This way, this way the mournful Ecchoe calls. </l>
          <l>Oh the bold Traytors, Sacrilegious Villains. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e31000">[They fight, Mandricard and the Priest are beaten off. </stage>
          <l>They run, they fly; now injur'd Vertue, seek </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e31030">[To Ast. </stage>
          <l>Thy safe Retreat, while I pursue the Villains. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e31060">[Exeunt. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e31070">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Who e're you be just Mahomet reward you. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e31110">[Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e31120">SCENE a Wood. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e31130">Arsanes sitting melancholly on a Green Bank, while his Page sings this SONG. </stage>
        <lg>
          <l>BEhold ye Sylvans that frequent </l>
          <l>This silent, sighing, mourning Grove; </l>
          <l>Behold the Fountains, Birds lament, </l>
          <l>Vnhappy Damons fatal Love. </l>
          <l>Chloris to him her Heart denies, </l>
          <l>For which the gentle Shepherd dies. </l>
          <l>
            <hi>Ch. Chloris </hi>to him &amp;c. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Bright Chloris fairest of her kind, </l>
          <l>That charm'd with Smiles the yielding Swain, </l>
          <l>False Chloris falser than the Wind, </l>
          <l>That turns his Fairy Ioys to Pain. </l>
          <l>Her Vows, her Oaths which tir'd Heav'n, </l>
          <l>Were for so many Curses giv'n. </l>
          <l>Ch. Her Vows, her Oaths &amp;c. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Then fill with hollow Sighs the Day, </l>
          <l>With Cypress strow the mourning Green; </l>
          <l>Let nothing fresh, let nothing gay </l>
          <l>O're all the fading Plain be seen; </l>
          <l>for see the Swain lies bleeding there, </l>
          <l>Wounded by Love, dead with Despair. </l>
          <l>Ch. For see the Swain &amp;c. </l>
        </lg>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e31500">
          <pb n="48" xml:id="ep000762-030-a"/>
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Thus in a Chaos of cold discontent </l>
          <l>I pass the weary Minutes, breathing forth </l>
          <l>My daily Passions from my wasted Spirits; </l>
          <l>Unhappy, wretched Prince, how Destiny </l>
          <l>Allots unjust misfortunes to thy Youth! </l>
          <l>Which to others is a flowing Spring of good, </l>
          <l>To thee's a frosty Winter of cold Sorrow. </l>
          <l>Oh my Nerina! how thy doubtful Faith </l>
          <l>Strikes deep my Heart; nor can I think thee false </l>
          <l>To thy false Hand against thy Vertue plead. </l>
          <l>So, thus— I may gaze here till I am blind, </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e31640">[Looking on the Letter. </stage>
          <l>But never here shall satisfaction find. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e31660">[Throwing it away. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e31670">Enter in hast Axalla and Zanches. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e31700">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>Live, live Arsanes. </l>
          <l>In just Obedience to your great Commands </l>
          <l>I went to the Apartment of Asteria; </l>
          <l>Where first I heard what seiz'd my Soul with horror, </l>
          <l>And num'd my Senses with a Marble Fear; </l>
          <l>I heard, Arsanes, your Nerina shrieking, </l>
          <l>With all the Struglings of a Ravish'd Maid. </l>
          <l>When from her Chamber rush'd in furious hast </l>
          <l>The Villain Mandricard, and the prophaner </l>
          <l>Villain a Priest, who grasp'd the Sacred Store. </l>
          <l>Rais'd by the Pow'r of so just an Anger, </l>
          <l>Your Old Mans Blood glow'd with a Youthful Heat, </l>
          <l>While with our Swords I and the Faithful Zanches </l>
          <l>Pursu'd the Traytors, forc'd 'em quit their Treasure, </l>
          <l>And made 'em thankful to their Stars for Life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e31930">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>O Golden Minute! Thanks O Gracious Heav'n! </l>
          <l>And thou its kindest happiest Instrument. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e31970">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>What Past before her fair Hand will unfold, </l>
          <l>This Letter to your Hand she charg'd me bring. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e32010">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>They'r welcome on what ever Errand sent, </l>
          <l>Axalla, see the wond'rous mighty Proof </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e32060">[Reading. </stage>
          <l>Of her wrong'd Innocence, she writes, not she, </l>
          <l>But fond Ispatia, as dying she confess'd, </l>
          <l>Was Author of those Lines which drove us hither </l>
          <l>In so much Fury, and so much Despair. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e32120">
          <pb n="49" xml:id="ep000762-030-b"/>
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>'Tis as Axalla's Heart cou'd wish it shou'd be. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e32160">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>How cou'd I trust these Characters which are </l>
          <l>Unlike, as Faith and Falshood, Love and Hate, </l>
          <l>Hope and Despair; and shou'd I then have curst, </l>
          <l>Curst her sweet Vertue for anothers Crime? </l>
          <l>Such words wou'd sure have blasted me, such words </l>
          <l>Had gave my Heart the lie, had swoln my Tongue </l>
          <l>With its own Venome, nay had press'd and grip'd </l>
          <l>My thoughtful Sense with wrecks of dire remorse, </l>
          <l>And the black Scourge of self-tormenting Conscience. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e32270">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>But see, my Lord, the tenderest words she writes! </l>
          <l>See at the end of her Complaints her Pray'rs, </l>
          <l>She begs Protection from your Royal Hands. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e32320">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Protect her! yes, against the Universe, </l>
          <l>Brother, and Father; Fortunes Darts, and Fates </l>
          <l>Decrees, the business of our Watchful Eyes </l>
          <l>Shall be to mark her Enemies, our Strength </l>
          <l>And well-collected Vertue be her Guard </l>
          <l>Where e're she moves: Let us not wast in words </l>
          <l>One moment of our Life, these happy Hours, </l>
          <l>A swift Obedience calls our Hearts and Hands, </l>
          <l>For from Nerina came the soft Commands. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e32440">[Exeunt. </stage>
      </div>
      <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="ep000762-e32450">
        <head>ACT V. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e32470">Arsanes, Asteria. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e32480">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>WIth equal Joy, as when the first-born Man </l>
          <l>Through a sweet Paradise led his Infant Bride, </l>
          <l>With all the Pleasures of a welcome Love </l>
          <l>Do I unsatiate with Asteria's Charms </l>
          <l>Pass the glad day. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e32560">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Did not my Fathers Fate </l>
          <l>Oppose the sweet delights of growing Love, </l>
          <l>This day I cou'd with mighty Queens dispute </l>
          <l>The Number of bless'd Minutes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e32620">
          <pb n="50" xml:id="ep000762-031-a"/>
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Oh my Soul. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e32650">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>My Heart, I can profus'dly wish! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e32680">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>My all that I can ask, and Heav'n can give. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e32710">Enter Abdalla, with Guards. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e32730">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>Or I'm mistaken, or </l>
          <l>This is the Traytor, apprehend him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e32770">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Whom? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e32800">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>Arsanes, Sir, me thinks you much resemble </l>
          <l>That great, out-witted States-man Prince. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e32850">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>'Tis he; Slave, speak thy Errand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e32880">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>From Tamerlane. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e32920">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>No more; 'tis Blasphemy </l>
          <l>To ask, or to dispute the Cause, I go </l>
          <l>Where e're he calls to shameful Bands, or Death. </l>
          <l>Lead on— but oh, my Heart, forget her not </l>
          <l>Asteria— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e33000">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e33030">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>We must not wait </l>
          <l>Fond Lovers tedious parting's; Lead away. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e33070">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Farewel, Fair Star, for ever. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e33100">[Is led off. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e33110">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>He's gone, he's gone; </l>
          <l>Hurry'd away by Traytors to his Death, </l>
          <l>And oh, ye Pow'rs, I had not power to speak </l>
          <l>My last Farewel; Ile follow though, and pierce </l>
          <l>Without regard of Life or Being, through </l>
          <l>All that does, can oppose me; break through Fire, </l>
          <l>Through Flames, o're Mountains pass, and swelling Seas, </l>
          <l>Through Files of Tartars, Swords, Lances, Javelins. </l>
          <l>Arm'd with resistless Love, and Rage, I'le fly </l>
          <l>Like Lightning in a moment to his Cell, </l>
          <l>With all the force of parting Love embrace him. </l>
          <l>Bath with my Widow-Tears his panting Breast, </l>
          <l>Bask in his Eyes, share that Eternal Rest </l>
          <l>His Noble Soul shall claim among the Blest. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e33280">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e33290">
          <pb n="51" xml:id="ep000762-031-b"/>Mandricard is discovered asleep, the Ghost of Ispatia by him with a Dagger in her Hand, threatning him. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-gh" xml:id="ep000762-e33320">
          <speaker>Gh. </speaker>
          <l>Rest, rest, my Soul, at last great Heav'ns Care, </l>
          <l>Let never Innocence of Heav'n despair. </l>
          <l>Thus sent, thus arm'd, an injur'd Shade I come </l>
          <l>To scourge thee, Prince, for thy untimely Doom. </l>
          <l>Thy Conscience thus just Alha does unseal, </l>
          <l>And to thee all the horrors of thy Crimes reveal. </l>
          <l>With Frenzy shalt thou rage, with Sorrow groan, </l>
          <l>And in deep thought thy dazled Senses drown. </l>
          <l>An inward Hell thee, Poisoner, shall burn▪ </l>
          <l>Nor shalt thou ever to thy self return. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e33450">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e33460">Mandricard rises frighted and raging. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e33480">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>I wou'd have torn her, and have sacrific'd </l>
          <l>Her Members to Ispatia's wandring Ghost; </l>
          <l>Nay haunt me not, dear Shade, I've sworn to do it, </l>
          <l>With as much Art I'le work thy Rivals Fate, </l>
          <l>As th' wiliest Devil of 'em all can wish. </l>
          <l>What Sorcery this Turkish Beauty bears! </l>
          <l>Ha! where so swiftly fled! have Harlots Wings? </l>
          <l>Then to the Icarian Flood I'le steer my Course, </l>
          <l>Drain it, and rob the unexperienc'd Boy </l>
          <l>Of his ill-manag'd Quills, born on whose Force </l>
          <l>I'le mount, and catch her in her hottest Chace. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e33640">Enter Odmar, Abdalla. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e33660">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord, Lord Mandricard. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e33700">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Did not you see a Monster up the Hill. </l>
          <l>Sharp radiant Arrows arm'd her Magick Eyes, </l>
          <l>Her Face, or no Face, or her double Face, </l>
          <l>Shew'd crooked, Nature shrowded by false Art, </l>
          <l>These well-known marks make ill for her escape. </l>
          <l>Hey follow, seek, 'tis worth our pains, and more, </l>
          <l>Millions to one but we shall seize the Witch. </l>
          <l>See ho! see there o're yonder Plain she fleets! </l>
          <pb n="52" xml:id="ep000762-032-a"/>
          <l>O for an Arrow from Diana's Quiver! </l>
          <l>Spread wide your Nets, mark where to Autumn Gray </l>
          <l>The verdant Spring is chang'd, that, that's her Road, </l>
          <l>Made hoary by her Sorcery and Charms. </l>
          <l>She's near, she's near; my Nostrils draw the Scent </l>
          <l>Of Paints, of Powders, Daubings, strong Perfumes, </l>
          <l>A Whore will scent a Mile— so nimble— ha, </l>
          <l>'Tis noble Sport, so hei, follow, so hei. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e33890">[Runs up and down, and out. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e33900">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Was ever such a Change in Nature wrought! </l>
          <l>So sudden, yet so perfect! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e33940">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>This your Plots, </l>
          <l>Your Stratagems have done, had I been heard, </l>
          <l>He had e're this have worn a Crown by Arms </l>
          <l>Nobly atchiev'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e34000">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Thine were the means to sure </l>
          <l>Destruction, this we may amend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e34040">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>Ha, ha! </l>
          <l>Dost thou not see our hopes in frenzy drown'd? </l>
          <l>Brave had you fell my way, as shameful this. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e34090">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>We'l follow him— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e34120">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>In vain. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e34150">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Our Counsels may— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e34180">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>Make him a Fool, as they have made him mad. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e34210">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>What shall I do? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e34240">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>Die in the Act like Men. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e34270">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Or live, and work more Ruine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e34300">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>And be found </l>
          <l>Traytors at last, most infamous and base. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e34340">A Noise of Fighting. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e34350">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>What Noise is that? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e34380">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>'Tis the dear Shout of Battle, </l>
          <l>Abdalla, to thy lov'd Vocation. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e34430">[Exit </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e34440">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Go, </l>
          <l>I'le follow, and thy dangerous Fortunes share. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e34480">[Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e34490">
          <pb n="53" xml:id="ep000762-032-b"/>The Scene opening, discovers <hi>Tamerlane, Odmar, Abdalla</hi>, encountring <hi>Axalla, Zanches</hi>, and others. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e34520">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>Arsanes, live; or perish all thy Friends. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-peo" xml:id="ep000762-e34560">
          <speaker>Peo. </speaker>
          <l>Revenge, Revenge our Prince Arsanes wrongs. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e34600">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>They fly, they fly; see, O the wrong'd Arsanes, </l>
          <l>Thy Succour nigh. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e34650">[Tam. and his Party give back▪ </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-abd" xml:id="ep000762-e34670">
          <speaker>Abd. </speaker>
          <l>We must not thus give up </l>
          <l>To Slaves our Lawrels while Abdalla lives. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e34720">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>Die then perfidious, base, eternal Villain! </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e34750">[Kills Abdalla. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e34770">A Retreat is sounded on Tamerlanes side, the Scene closes. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e34790">Enter Tamerlane, Odmar. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e34810">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Dead or alive he will my Ruine prove. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e34840">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Dispatch him strait. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e34870">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>You'r rash, and unadvis'd; </l>
          <l>Prove thy self worthy of the Name thou bear'st </l>
          <l>Our Counsellor, or die. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e34920">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Your Slaves Advice </l>
          <l>Meets your Commands; let, Sir, Arsanes live; </l>
          <l>Free him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e34980">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Ha! say'st thou! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e35010">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>These Reports will quell </l>
          <l>Th' incensed Crowd; while I in Ambush laid </l>
          <l>In some dark secret Corner of the Palace, </l>
          <l>Rush on him swell'd with pride, and reeling with </l>
          <l>The drunkenness of Love, end him, my Lord, </l>
          <l>Big with large expectations of delight, </l>
          <l>And from your Royal Scepter take the Guilt. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e35100">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Thou art my Soul, my Empires Prop, and Refuge, </l>
          <l>Who hast reviv'd it sinking from its Ashes; </l>
          <l>Next to our own, when thy Blest Hand performs </l>
          <l>The happy Work of thy projecting Brain, </l>
          <l>I'le Crown thy Head with Lawrel and with Gold, </l>
          <l>Boasting of thee our Life and Throne to hold. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e35180">[Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e35190">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Now Odmar, for thy share expect no less </l>
          <l>Than Scepters for thy dear contriving Wit; </l>
          <pb n="54" xml:id="ep000762-033-a"/>
          <l>Ha, ha, ha, ha, to see the Shallow King </l>
          <l>Expect Security and Bliss from me. </l>
          <l>Vain Fools who think we work for any Ends </l>
          <l>But for our own— How tamely the dull Crowd </l>
          <l>Lay down their Arms, and leave their Prince defenceless; </l>
          <l>Die, die, Arsanes, and live Mandricard, </l>
          <l>And I thy happy Father; with what ease </l>
          <l>Odmar a Crown has purchas'd to his Race! </l>
          <l>Me thinks I see my numerous Royal Offspring </l>
          <l>Steal softly by, all Crown'd; no more, let others </l>
          <l>By Blood and Civil Wars an Empire gain. </l>
          <l>Tis Fraud alone false Titles can maintain. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e35390">[Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e35400">A Chamber. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e35410">Enter Arsanes. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e35430">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>I wonder how the Grave and Wise define </l>
          <l>Th' uncertain motions of ambiguous Chance, </l>
          <l>While equally she flatters, and destroys. </l>
          <l>'Tis true I'm free, live, have large promises </l>
          <l>To Love and Reign, as my high Birth requires. </l>
          <l>But oh, what safety's in that Freedom found </l>
          <l>From the sweet quiet of the Mind exil'd! </l>
          <l>That I in Chains! </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e35530">[Enter Axalla. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e35550">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e35580">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>What hast my Friend, </l>
          <l>To view this Load of Shame? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e35620">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>Ha, Prince. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e35650">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>I said my Shame. </l>
          <l>Am I not mark'd in every Limb a Villain? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e35690">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>This Temper suits not with your Fate, my Lord, </l>
          <l>Thick Crowds of Friends expect you at the Court, </l>
          <l>Waiting to Crown your vast Desert with Honour. </l>
          <l>Which Tamerlane by me commands you take. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e35760">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>What sort of Honour is to Rebels due? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e35790">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>Rebells? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e35820">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Am I not one? how came I here? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e35850">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>Leave those jealous Thoughts: </l>
          <l>Rank'd in long Rows the gazing People stand </l>
          <pb n="56" xml:id="ep000762-033-b"/>
          <l>An endless Multitude; while smiling Virgins </l>
          <l>From Windows, mixt with Joyful Matrons, lean, </l>
          <l>All hoping, and all wishing, praying too </l>
          <l>For your Approach; Arsanes is the Sound, </l>
          <l>The only Sound the Gods can hear from Earth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e35950">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Triumphant Villain that I am! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e35980">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>Ha! Villain! </l>
          <l>Fool that I am to court a dreaming Zealot </l>
          <l>To sublime Honours; stupid, thankless Prince; </l>
          <l>Is this the Character our love deserves? </l>
          <l>Traytors and Villains! Oh the hateful Name! </l>
          <l>Go, Prince, and as thy unman'd Soul requires, </l>
          <l>Neglecting Palaces, in Dungeons dye, </l>
          <l>Slave-marking Iron press with vilest pain </l>
          <l>Those Limbs, which Sword, Steel, Fire have sustain'd. </l>
          <l>Farewell, Arsanes, neither Prince, nor Man. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e36110">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Hold, Noble Friend; pard'n, oh Axalla, pard'n </l>
          <l>A few rash words; the Act in you was good, </l>
          <l>Friendlike, and Just; and were it not forbid, </l>
          <l>Forbid by Duty, it were so in me; </l>
          <l>But oh! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e36190">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>Still dreaming? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e36220">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Oh my Innocence </l>
          <l>Thou sacred fort, fair Guardian of my Breast, </l>
          <l>Where art thou fled? me thinks I'm left alone, </l>
          <l>Disarm'd, defenceless, since I saw thee last. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e36280">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>Still in the tedious maze of fearful doubts! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e36310">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Where e're I turn I see my Ruine nigh. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ax" xml:id="ep000762-e36340">
          <speaker>Ax. </speaker>
          <l>Mark then your surest way to Life or Death, </l>
          <l>Bright Honour, or base Shame; the King, Arsanes, </l>
          <l>Brooks heavily the scorn of his Commands, </l>
          <l>Your Friends their ill accepted Love repent, </l>
          <l>And sad Nerina all in Tears protests </l>
          <l>She never thought Arsanes cou'd deny </l>
          <l>Her any thing. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e36460">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Hold, thou hast said enough; </l>
          <l>Words of such wond'rous sense, so moving, full </l>
          <l>With Arguments of such prevailing Pow'r, </l>
          <l>Wou'd raise the dull Lethargick from his Dream; </l>
          <l>That Threefold Chain of Duty, Friendship, Love, </l>
          <pb n="56" xml:id="ep000762-034-a"/>
          <l>Wou'd bind the Roving Sylvan Honours Slave; </l>
          <l>Faith draws the Wills of Men to my defence, </l>
          <l>Duty and Love Auxiliary Gods. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e36560">[Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e36570">Odmar solus. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e36580">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Traytor! 'tis a Name of vast import! </l>
          <l>Not arm'd with furbish'd Brass, nor lock'd in Steel, </l>
          <l>He bears the noiseless Weapons of Deceit. </l>
          <l>Lies politick, and subtle Flatteries </l>
          <l>Raise him to trust; what cannot Villains trusted? </l>
          <l>We change, destroy, make Princes, and unmake. </l>
          <l>Unenvy'd be henceforth Cassander fam'd, </l>
          <l>Dire Sylla, Close Sejanus, Cruel Marius, </l>
          <l>Seditious Gracchi, God-like Catiline, </l>
          <l>With all the Glorious Traytors of each Age; </l>
          <l>Not the false Smerdis with his Magick Train </l>
          <l>Could sound the dark Abyss of Odmars Plots. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-peop" xml:id="ep000762-e36800">
          <speaker>Peop. </speaker>
          <l>Long live Great Tamerlane, and Prince Arsanes. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e36850">[Shout within. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e36860">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Hark, now me thinks I see this Lover come </l>
          <l>Hot with desire; see how the too rash Fool </l>
          <l>With what large hasty steps he meets half way </l>
          <l>My Daggers Point; now, Heart, for thy Revenge! </l>
          <l>Heav'n guide my Hand where I resolve to strike! </l>
          <l>Here will I make my Vigilant Retreat, </l>
          <l>All Passages but through this Gate are bar'd </l>
          <l>To the dear Lodgings of his lov'd Asteria; </l>
          <l>While the dark Night shall shrow'd me and my Guilt. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e36980">[Retreats. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e36990">Enter Mandricard. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e37010">
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>No not so much as one poor Cypress Torch </l>
          <l>To light her to her Grave— ah the much-wrong'd Ispatia! </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e37060">[Odmar rushes on him and stabs him with a Poniard. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e37080">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>As sure a Thrust as ever Malice made. </l>
          <l>Lye there thou empty Blaze of Fame; while I </l>
          <l>Run with false Tears, devulger of thy Fate. </l>
          <l>Oh how the Crowd will fret! the Prince Arsanes, </l>
          <l>The Noble Prince lies murder'd in the way. </l>
          <l>Help, help, the Prince is murder'd. oh, oh, oh, oh. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e37170">[Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-man" xml:id="ep000762-e37180">
          <pb n="57" xml:id="ep000762-034-b"/>
          <speaker>Man. </speaker>
          <l>Darkness and Horror! whither am I going? </l>
          <l>What greedy Horse-leech sucks my Vital Blood, </l>
          <l>And draws me to a Being like Ispatia's? </l>
          <l>Laugh, laugh, ye Furies, and ye Devils grin, </l>
          <l>Scourge me with Scorpions, punish me with Flames, </l>
          <l>Eternal Flames; tear, consume, devour me, </l>
          <l>Let Hell surround me with her greatest Torments, </l>
          <l>Severest Plagues prepar'd for blackest Souls; </l>
          <l>But turn the wrong'd Ispatia from my sight, </l>
          <l>Ispatia's Presence is a Thousand Hells. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e37330">[Dies. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e37340">Re enter Odmar with a dark Lanthorn. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e37360">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>But to be sure thou'rt dead, it much concerns. </l>
          <l>By Heav'n 'tis Mandricard, Death, Furies, Hell, </l>
          <l>And thou, curst Hand, false Author of my woe, </l>
          <l>Thou Traytor to my Will, and Rebel to my Aim; </l>
          <l>Oh the black Curse of Chance— </l>
          <l>And plague of Accidents! so gross an Error </l>
          <l>Was wrought sure by the envy of the Stars. </l>
          <l>My Mandricard, my Son, oh, oh, my Son. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e37480">Enter Tamerlane. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e37500">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Keep back the Rabble, and your selves retreat, </l>
          <l>While I survey and mourn my hapless Son. </l>
          <l>Well, Friend, thou'st done the business. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e37550">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Very well, </l>
          <l>To make the Strumpet Fortune frisk and laugh. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e37590">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>What mean you Friend? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e37620">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>I mean there is in Heav'n </l>
          <l>A Jubilee among Arsanes Stars. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e37670">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>That he's come there— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e37700">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>That he is not come there. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e37730">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Thy Mystick Speech I cannot comprehend, </l>
          <l>Nor sound thy Sense, no nor thy Ghastly Looks. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e37770">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>This will explain 'em all— </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e37800">[Points to Mandric. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e37820">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>By all the Gods </l>
          <l>'Tis Mandricard, Curst Villain— Oh my Son. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e37870">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Ha, ha, ha. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e37900">
          <pb n="58" xml:id="ep000762-035-a"/>
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>What wou'd thy Mirth? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e37930">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>Seeing once a Corse </l>
          <l>On a Black Beer to gloomy Pluto born. </l>
          <l>●laught to see the Sympathetick Crowd </l>
          <l>Howl, yell, lament, as they were Parents all. </l>
          <l>What was the Corse to them, or they to it? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e38010">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Yet Ridling, Slave? what hoa my Guards— who waits? </l>
          <l>Seize there the Murderer. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e38050">[Enter Guards. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-odm" xml:id="ep000762-e38060">
          <speaker>Odm. </speaker>
          <l>I scorn to perish by a Fate so base. </l>
          <l>Thus do the Noble dye— </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e38100">[Stabs himself. </stage>
          <l>What mean those Tears? </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e38120">[To Tam. </stage>
          <l>Know, King, thou shou'dst have shed those very Tears </l>
          <l>Some twenty years ago, when Mandricard </l>
          <l>Your Son, my Charge, a tender Infant dy'd; </l>
          <l>Then the wish'd Glory of my days began; </l>
          <l>He dey'd; I to his room my Son advanc'd, </l>
          <l>My own Themyre, suppos'd your Mandricard. </l>
          <l>My swell'd Ambition yet did higher aim, </l>
          <l>A King, at least the Father of a King </l>
          <l>I was resolv'd to raise my self. Think, Sir, </l>
          <l>By me how oft Arsanes has been made </l>
          <l>By me a Traytor, never of himself. </l>
          <l>This was the last unlucky Cheat I acted, </l>
          <l>Which the curst Fates had otherwise decreed, </l>
          <l>And turn'd on me the Ruines of my Wish. </l>
          <l>Scarce can I more; my Death comes swiftly on; </l>
          <l>While from my Actions I this Glory draw, </l>
          <l>None cou'd but <hi>Odmar, Odmars </hi>Plots destroy. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e38360">[Dies. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e38370">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Remove the wretched Bodies from my sight, </l>
          <l>The hated Traytor, and the curst Impostor! </l>
          <l>First let 'em hang a publick Spectacle </l>
          <l>In our high Road which to the Palace leads, </l>
          <l>Then when all Eyes are glutted with the sight, </l>
          <l>Cast 'em to Birds and Beasts a welcome Prey. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e38450">Enter an Officer. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-off" xml:id="ep000762-e38460">
          <speaker>Off. </speaker>
          <l>Prepare, Great Tamerlane, for your defence, </l>
          <l>Uproars and Tumults every where are ris'n. </l>
          <l>Fame of Arsanes Death has arm'd the Crowd, </l>
          <pb n="59" xml:id="ep000762-035-b"/>
          <l>With Fury, Rage, Suspicions, Frenzies, Fears, </l>
          <l>Your self the sole Promoter of his Fate </l>
          <l>Are sworn, arraign'd, on you they vow Revenge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e38560">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Hast quickly, and with Trumpets Sound pronounce </l>
          <l>The Rumour false; their lov'd Arsanes lives; </l>
          <l>By blest mistake 'tis Mandricard is fal'n. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000762-e38630">[Exit off. </stage>
          <l>Call to my Arms the Noble Prince Arsanes, </l>
          <l>And his fair Mistress; at last my Eyes are open, </l>
          <l>Unseal'd to Truth, I see and am confirm'd </l>
          <l>No close Conspiracy, or black Design, </l>
          <l>But Love, and only Love, their Hearts did joyn. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e38700">Enter Arsanes and Asteria. </stage>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e38730">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Thanks, O Propitious Heav'n, thanks my Stars, </l>
          <l>And all ye Angels Guards of Innocence, </l>
          <l>Which have restor'd, and brought into his Right </l>
          <l>The wrong'd Arsanes, welcome O my Son, </l>
          <l>Thy Enemies are dead, the Impostors dead, </l>
          <l>And with them all Suspitions of thy Faith, </l>
          <l>Thy Injuries are dead— Oh my Arsanes, </l>
          <l>A Father in the Face of Heav'n salutes thee </l>
          <l>A happy Bridegroom, from a Fathers Hand, </l>
          <l>Receive thy Fairer Vertues, Fair Reward. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e38870">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>O Extasie! Oh Paradise of Joy! </l>
          <l>I come scarce hoping for a Pard'n, and find </l>
          <l>A full Reward, Inestimable Treasure, </l>
          <l>Eternal Bliss; nor is it Fairy Treasure! </l>
          <l>No, no, I have it here, I hold it, grasp it, </l>
          <l>A Real Pleasure, and Substantial Good. </l>
          <l>But oh let not the fulness of my Joy </l>
          <l>Make me unmindful of the Noble Giver. </l>
          <l>Oh, my Asteria— </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e38990">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e39020">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Thus let us kneel, </l>
          <l>With Thanks unto our Father. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ast" xml:id="ep000762-e39060">
          <speaker>Ast. </speaker>
          <l>Our Preserver! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e39090">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Our new Creator, thus let us lie prostrate, </l>
          <l>And wonder at our sudden Happines. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-tam" xml:id="ep000762-e39130">
          <speaker>Tam. </speaker>
          <l>Rise and believe it granted; now witness Heav'n, </l>
          <pb n="60" xml:id="ep000762-036-a"/>
          <l>And ye kind Stars, that smile upon our Throne, </l>
          <l>With what untroubled Joy I joyn the Hands </l>
          <l>Of the blest Loyal Pair. </l>
          <l>The Sacred Tye just Alha shall confirm, </l>
          <l>And as we Sign, Seal your Eternal Loves. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000762-ars" xml:id="ep000762-e39220">
          <speaker>Ars. </speaker>
          <l>Thanks O our Royal Father, God-like Prince, </l>
          <l>And double Author of my happy Being. </l>
          <l>So may Great Alha all your Actions Crown, </l>
          <l>And with Eternal Blessings Guard your Throne. </l>
          <l>As I your worthy Praises loudly sing, </l>
          <l>The Kindest Father, and the Justest King. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000762-e39310">[Exeunt. </stage>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="epilogue" xml:id="ep000762-e39330">
        <pb xml:id="ep000762-036-b"/>
        <head>EPILOGUE, By Mr. DRYDEN. </head>
        <lg>
          <l>LAdies, the Beardless Author of this Day, </l>
          <l>Commends to you the Fortune of his Play. </l>
          <l>A Woman Wit has often grac'd the Stage, </l>
          <l>But he's the first Boy-Poet of our Age. </l>
          <l>Early as is the Year his Fancies blow, </l>
          <l>Like young Narcissus peeping through the Snow; </l>
          <l>Thus Cowley Blossom'd soon, yet Flourish'd long, </l>
          <l>This is as forward, and may prove as strong. </l>
          <l>Youth with the Fair shou'd always Favour find, </l>
          <l>Or we are damn'd Dissemblers of our kind. </l>
          <l>What's all this Love they put into our Parts? </l>
          <l>'Tis but the pit-a-pat of Two Young Hearts. </l>
          <l>Shou'd Hag and Gray-Beard make such tender moan, </l>
          <l>Faith you'd e'en trust 'em▪ to themselves alone, </l>
          <l>And cry let's go, here's nothing to be done. </l>
          <l>Since Love's our Business, as 'tis your Delight, </l>
          <l>The Young, who best can practise, best can Write. </l>
          <l>What though he be not come to his full Pow'r, </l>
          <l>He's mending and improving every hour. </l>
          <l>You sly She-Iockies of the Box and Pit, </l>
          <l>Are pleas'd to find a hot unbroken Wit, </l>
          <l>By management he may in time be made, </l>
          <l>But there's no hopes of an old batter'd Iade; </l>
          <l>Faint and unnerv'd he runs into a Sweat, </l>
          <l>And always fails you at the Second Heat. </l>
        </lg>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
