<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000249" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Thebais</title>
        <author>
          <persName xml:lang="eng">Seneca</persName>
          <persName>
            <forename>Lucius</forename>
            <surname>Annaeus</surname>
            <addName>Seneca</addName>
            <genName>minor</genName>
          </persName>
          <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q2054</idno>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A11909_03.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="A11909-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
        </bibl>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Seneca his tenne tragedies, translated into Englysh.</title>
            <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus, ca. 4 B.C.-65 A.D.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>225 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2007 October (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99852323</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 22221.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, III, p. 1105-6.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">17639</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11909</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2248540344</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Seneca his tenne tragedies, translated into Englysh.</title>
            <title type="alt">Tragedies. English</title>
            <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus, ca. 4 B.C.-65 A.D.</author>
            <author>Heywood, Jasper, 1535-1598,</author>
            <author>Neville, Alexander, 1544-1614,</author>
            <author>Studley, John, 1545?-1590?,</author>
            <author>T. N. d. 1617,</author>
            <author>Newton, Thomas, 1542?-1607.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[4], 65, 64-217, [1] leaves.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>In Fleetstreete neere vnto Saincte Dunstans church by Thomas Marsh,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
            <date type="publication_date">1581.</date>
            <date type="creation_date">1562</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Editor's dedication signed: Thomas Newton.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>In verse.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>A reprinting of the following translations previously published separately: "Hercules furens", "Thyestes", and "Troas" by Jasper Heywood; "¦edipus" by Alexander Neville (a revised version); "Medea" and "Agamemnon" by John Studley; and "Octavia" (not by Seneca) by Thomas Nuce. Prints for the first time "Hippolytus" and "Hercules Oetæus" translated by Studley, and "Thebais" translated by Thomas Newton.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A"; the last leaf is blank.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <person xml:id="ep000249-A11909">
            <persName>A11909</persName>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
      <textClass>
        <classCode scheme="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q80930</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1581">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
    <listRelation>
      <relation name="wikidata"
                   active="https://dracor.org/entity/ep000249"
                   passive="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q15427808"/>
    </listRelation>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3" type="tragedy" xml:id="ep000249-e100030">
        <pb n="40" xml:id="ep000249-044-a"/>
        <head>THE THYRD TRAGEDY OF L. ANN AEVS Seneca: entituled Thebais, translated out of Latin into Englishe, by Thomas Newton. 1581. </head>
        <argument>
          <head>The Argument. </head>
          <p>LAIVS King of Thebes, hadde by his Wyfe and Queene IOCASTA, a Sonne named OEDIPVS: Who being yet in his Mothers Wombe, APOLLO his Oracle pronounced, that by the handes of that childe, King LAIVS the father should bee murthered. The feare whereof caused the King to commaund him to be put to death. The Kinges heardman, who had the charge to see this done, on thone side mooued with compassion ouer a tender weakeling: and on the otherside, afraid to incurre the King his maisters displeasure, contented himselfe onely to boare two hoales through the Infants two feete, and with certayne plyable Twigges beinge thrust through the same, hong him vp on a tree by the Heeles: supposing that heereby hee should commit a lesse crime in suffring the childe to perishe by famine, then in playing the Butcher himsefe. It fortuned, that one PHORBAS heardman to POLYBIVS King of Corynth, passing by that way &amp; hearing a yong Childe cyre, went and cut him downe, and caryinge him to Corynth, it so fell out that at length hee was giuen for a present <pb xml:id="ep000249-045-a"/>or gyft to MEROPE, Wyfe to the said King POLYBVS. This OEDIPVS afterward going to Thebes, in a certayne sedicious hurly burly in the countrey there, vnawares and vnwitting slewe King LAIVS his Father. About which tyme the City of Thebes, and Countrey there about was meruelously infested with a monster called Sphinx: who propounding a certaine Riddle, or obscure question to such as passed that way, and deuouringe as many, as coulde not assoyle the same. To him that coulde assoile it and so rid the Countrey from that so vgly and daungerous a monster, the mariage of Queene IOCASTA, and the kingdome of Thebes was promysed as a recompence: OEDIPVS after many others, taking the matter in hand, assoyled the Ryddle, &amp; slew the monster. Whereupon marying the Queene, not knowing her to bee his owne Mother, had by her foure Chyldren: ETHEOCLES, POLYNICES, ANTIGONE, &amp; ISMENE. In the end, hauing knowledg, how first hee had kylled his Father, and then incestuously maryed his Mother, hee forsooke his kingdome being continually infested wyth the plague, &amp; (as one ashamed to loke any man in the face) pulled out his own Eyes, and hid himselfe in corners and solitary places. His Sonnes ETHEOCLES &amp; POLYNICES agreed to raigne enterchaungeably, that is to wit, ETHEOCLES, one yeare, and POLYNICES the other. ETHEOCLES hauing raigned his yeare, refused according to the articles of agrement, to resigne the Crowne to his brother for the next yeare. Whereupon they fel to mortal warres, and in the end meaning by combat to ende the matter, they mutually slew one the other. And note that this Tragedy, was left by the Authour vnperfect, because it neyther hath in it, Chorus, ne yet the fifth Acte. </p>
        </argument>
        <list>
          <head>The names of the speakers. </head>
          <item>OEdipus. </item>
          <item>Nuntius. </item>
          <item>Antigone. </item>
          <item>Iocasta. </item>
        </list>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="ep000249-e100110">
          <pb n="41" xml:id="ep000249-045-b"/>
          <head>THE FIRSTE ACTE. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000249-e100120">OEdipus. Antigone. </stage>
          <l>DEare Daughter, vnto Father blynde </l>
          <l>a Staffe of steady stay, </l>
          <l>To weary Syre, a comfort greate, </l>
          <l>and Guide in all his way: </l>
          <l>And whom to haue begotten, I </l>
          <l>may glad and ioyfull bee: </l>
          <l>Yet leaue me now, thy haplesse Syre, </l>
          <l>thus plungde in misery. </l>
          <l>Why seekst thou meanes, still to direct </l>
          <l>my stalking steppes aright? </l>
          <l>Let mee I pray thee headlong slyde </l>
          <l>in breaknecke tumbling plight. </l>
          <l>I betttr shall and sooner fynde a way my selfe alone </l>
          <l>To rid mee out of all the thrall wherein I now am throwne. </l>
          <l>Whereby both heauen shall eased bee, and earth shall want the sight </l>
          <l>Of mee vile wretch, whom, guilt hath made a most abhorred wight. </l>
          <l>Alas, what litle triffling tricke hath hitherto bene wrought </l>
          <l>By these my hands? what feate of worth or maistry haue I sought? </l>
          <l>In deede, they haue me helpt to pull myne eyes out of my head: </l>
          <l>So that ne Sunne, ne Moone I see, but life in darknesse lead. </l>
          <l>And though that I can nothing see, yet is my guilt and cryme </l>
          <l>Both seene and knowne, &amp; poyncted at, (woe worth the cursed tyme.) </l>
          <l>Leaue of thy hold, let lose thy hand, good daughter, let mee goe: </l>
          <l>Let foultring foote light where it will, let it (this once) be so. </l>
          <l>Ile trudge, and runne, Ile skudde, and raunge, Ile hasten to the hill </l>
          <l>Of craggy stiepe Cytheron, there I hope to worke my will. </l>
          <l>Where earst Actaeon lost his lyfe by straunge, and vncouth death, </l>
          <l>Whom bawling Dogges, and hunting Hounds bereft of vitall breath: </l>
          <l>Where once Agaue (bedlemlike) raungd vp and downe the woode </l>
          <l>With Systers hers, enspired all with Bacchus raging moode. </l>
          <l>And pleasing well her selfe in that her fact and mischiefe donne, </l>
          <l>Pitcht on a Poale the grisly head of him that was her Sonne. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000249-046-a"/>
          <l>Where Zethus with his ruffling Crew of Gallantes young and stoute </l>
          <l>Dragd, hald, and puld, the hateful corps of Dirce, all aboute. </l>
          <l>Where bushie bloudied brambles show which way the Bull her drew: </l>
          <l>Nere where dame Ino from a Rocke her selfe in Sea downe threw. </l>
          <l>So that poore mother though she ment t'auoyde one fault by flight: </l>
          <l>Yet she therby a worse procur'd, while like a seely wight </l>
          <l>She bother selfe and eke her sonne from Scyron hurled downe </l>
          <l>Entending both her selfe and him in foaming Sea to drowne. </l>
          <l>Oh happy, yea thryse happy they, that had so good an bap: </l>
          <l>And whom such mothers pitiful earst daudled in theyr lap. </l>
          <l>Yea yet there is in these same woods an other place to mee </l>
          <l>That's due by right, and rightly may me challenge as his fee. </l>
          <l>Where I am Infant out was layed, al Fortunes to abide: </l>
          <l>I thyther wil direct my course of try what may betyde. </l>
          <l>Ile neither stop ne stay til that I be arryued there, </l>
          <l>For guyde I recke not, neyther force for Stumbling any where. </l>
          <l>Why stay I thus like dastard drudge to hasten vnto it? </l>
          <l>Sith wel I know it lotted is to be my graue and Pit? </l>
          <l>Let me myne owne Cytheron mount enioy in quiet state, </l>
          <l>It is myne old and auncient bower, appoynted me by fate. </l>
          <l>I pray thee be not discontent that I should (aged) die, </l>
          <l>Euen there, where life I should haue lost in pueling infancy. </l>
          <l>I yeild me heere with willing hart vnto those tortures all </l>
          <l>That earst to me were due, and which to others haue befall: </l>
          <l>To thee I speake O bloudy mount, fierce, cruel, styepe and fell, </l>
          <l>As well in that thou sparest some, as that thou some dost quell. </l>
          <l>This carion corps, this sinful soule, this carcasse here of myne </l>
          <l>Long tyme agone by right good Law and propertye is thine. </l>
          <l>Now yet at length perfourme the hest that earst enioyned was </l>
          <l>To thee by those my parentes both, now bring their doome to passe. </l>
          <l>My hart euen longeth till I may so fully satisfy </l>
          <l>By this my death that their decree, that glad I am to die. </l>
          <l>Ah Daughter, Daughter, why wouldst thou thus keepe mee gaynst my mynd? </l>
          <l>In this so vile incestuous loue? thou art but now to kind. </l>
          <l>Oh stay me not I thee desire, behold, behold, I heare </l>
          <l>My Fathers ghost to bidde me come apace, and not to feare. </l>
          <l>O Father myne I come, I come, now father ceasse thy rage: </l>
          <l>I know (alas) how I abus'd my Fathers hoary age: </l>
          <l>Who had to name King Laius: how hee doth fret and frye </l>
          <l>To see such lewd disparagement: and none to blame but I. </l>
          <pb n="42" xml:id="ep000249-046-b"/>
          <l>Wherby the Crowne vsurped is, and he by murther slayne. </l>
          <l>And Bastardly incestuous broode in Kingly throne remayne. </l>
          <l>And loe, dost thou not playnly see, how he my panting Ghost </l>
          <l>With raking pawes doth hale and pull, which grieues my conscience most? </l>
          <l>Dost thou not see how he my face bescratcheth tyrant wyse? </l>
          <l>Tel mee (my Daughter) hast thou seene Ghostes in such griefly guyse? </l>
          <l>Antig I see &amp; marke each thing ful well. Good father leaue this mind. </l>
          <l>And take a better if you can: from this your selfe vnwynd. </l>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e100930">
            <speaker>Oed. </speaker>
            <l>O what a beastly cowardise is in this breast of myne? </l>
            <l>Was I so stout and venturous in pulling out myne Eyen? </l>
            <l>And shall all courage be employd agaynst one onely part </l>
            <l>Of Body, and from other partes shall valour wholly start? </l>
            <l>Let none of all these puling trickes nor any faint excuse </l>
            <l>Thus daunt thy sprites, let no delay to basenes thee enduce: </l>
            <l>Dispatch at once, why lingre I, as one that's loth to dye? </l>
            <l>Why liue I? ist because I can no longer mischieues trye? </l>
            <l>Yes that I can, wretch though I be: and therfore tel I thee, </l>
            <l>Deare Daughter, that the sooner thou mightst hence depart from mee. </l>
            <l>Depart a mayd and Virgin hence, for feare of after claps: </l>
            <l>Since villany to Mother shewde, its good to doubt mishaps. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e101060">
            <speaker>Anti. </speaker>
            <l>No force, no power, no violence, shall make me to withdraw </l>
            <l>My duty vnto thee my Syre, to whom I vow myne awe. </l>
            <l>I will not be disseuered, ne pulled from thy syde. </l>
            <l>I will assist thee, whyle that breath shal in this Breast abyde. </l>
            <l>My Brothers twayne let them contend, and fight for Princelye swaye </l>
            <l>Of wealthy Thebes: where whilom raignd King Labdacke many a day. </l>
            <l>The greatest share and portion that I do loke to haue </l>
            <l>Out of my Fathers Kingdome, is my Fathers lyfe to saue. </l>
            <l>Him neither shall Etheocles my elder brother take </l>
            <l>Away from mee, who now by force the Thebane realme doth rake. </l>
            <l>Ne Polynices, who as now is Mustring men apace. </l>
            <l>From Argos Land: with ful entent his brother to displace. </l>
            <l>No, though the world went all on wheeles: though Ioue should from aboue </l>
            <l>Hurle flashing flakes vpon the Earth, all shall not quayle my loue. </l>
            <l>No, though his thumping thunderbolt (when wee togeather stand) </l>
            <l>Should light betweene vs, where as we are plighted hand in hand) </l>
            <l>Yet wil I neuer thee forsake, but held my handfast still: </l>
            <l>Therefore its boateles father deare, to countermaund my will </l>
            <l>In this my full resolued mynd. Forbid me if you please. </l>
            <l>But surely I will be your guide in weale, woe, dole, &amp; case. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000249-047-a"/>
            <l>And maugre al your sharpe reprofes (though much against your mind) </l>
            <l>I wil direct your steppes and gate, that you your way may fynd: </l>
            <l>Through thick &amp; thinne, through rough and smoth I wil be at an ynch </l>
            <l>In hill and dale, in wood &amp; groue, Ile serue at eu'ry pinch. </l>
            <l>If that you goe where daunger lies, and seeke your owne annoy, </l>
            <l>You shall wel proue, that I to leade the daunce wil not be coy. </l>
            <l>Aduyse your selfe therfore, of twayne to which I guyde shall be: </l>
            <l>My count is cast, I am ful bent with you to liue and die. </l>
            <l>Without me perish can you not: but with me, wel you may, </l>
            <l>It booteth not, in other sort to moue me ought to saye. </l>
            <l>Here is an huyge Promontory that elboes into Sea </l>
            <l>Let vs from thence throw downe our selues, and worke our last decay, </l>
            <l>If that ye wil. Here also is a flinty Rocke besyde, </l>
            <l>Which if you please shal serue our turnes: Heere beaten with the tyde </l>
            <l>Bee craggy Cliffes, let's goe to them: Here runnes a gulphy streame </l>
            <l>With force afore it dryuing stones as bigge as mountaine beame. </l>
            <l>What say you? shall wee drench our selues within this fomy Flood? </l>
            <l>Goe where you wil, take which you list, do as you deeme it good. </l>
            <l>Conditionally that I may first receyue the wound of death: </l>
            <l>I recke no whit, I ready stand to yeld vp vitall breath. </l>
            <l>I neyther draw you to nor froe: but euen as best you thinke </l>
            <l>So doe, so deale. Would you so fayne Deathes bitter cup to drinke? </l>
            <l>My lord and Father, take you death so greate a boone to bee? </l>
            <l>If that you dye (this I assure) die first you shall me see. </l>
            <l>If life in shew more pleasaunt seme, if so you rather chuse, </l>
            <l>I am to wayte vpon you still and neuer will refuse. </l>
            <l>But chaunge this mynde wherein you rest, take hart a grace, and show </l>
            <l>The noble magnanimity that earst in you did flow: </l>
            <l>Resist these panges, subdue these dumpes by valour of the mynd, </l>
            <l>Let manly courage qualify these your affections blynd. </l>
            <l>Tis great dishonor thus to yeeld your selfe to dolor thrall, </l>
            <l>No storme of aduerse hap thus ought a Princes hart t'appall. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e101590">
            <speaker>Oedip. </speaker>
            <l>This geare surmounteth far the reach of my capacity: </l>
            <l>I am astonn'd, I feele my selfe rapt with an extasie, </l>
            <l>Is this not wonder of so lewd, and of so curst a tree </l>
            <l>Such fruite to grow? of graceles Syre so good a child to see? </l>
            <l>Is it not straunge that in a house distaynd in villany </l>
            <l>Such noble shew of towardnes and vertuous gyftes should lye? </l>
            <l>Let me some speach to thee direct, dame Fortune: how haps this </l>
            <l>That here my daughter so vnlike to wretched father is? </l>
            <pb n="43" xml:id="ep000249-047-b"/>
            <l>Degenerating from his steps, and with such vertue fraught, </l>
            <l>As in her Fathers cursed house she neuer yet was taught? </l>
            <l>Is it (I pray thee) credible, that out of me should spring </l>
            <l>Such yssue, as should geuen be to any honest thinge? </l>
            <l>No truely, no: it cannot bee (my fates ful well I know) </l>
            <l>None such, (vnlesse to doe me scart and mischiefe) would be so. </l>
            <l>T'encrease the heape of myne annoy no straunge effect shall want. </l>
            <l>Dame Nature in her Creatures wil new affectes emplant. </l>
            <l>The Ryuer shall returne his course to Fountayne backe agayne, </l>
            <l>Dan Phoebus Lamp shall bring the Night, and Night shal day remain, </l>
            <l>So that my grieuous miseryes with surplusage may grow. </l>
            <l>But be as tis: I for a whyle wil play my part also, </l>
            <l>And shew some sparke of piety, my fault to counteruayle: </l>
            <l>With murtdroue knife, my woeful dayes to end I wil not fayle. </l>
            <l>The onely helpe for Oedipus, the onely safety is </l>
            <l>To ridde himselfe, and so redeeme that Hellish fact of his. </l>
            <l>Let mee take vengeance on my selfe for wronges to father donne, </l>
            <l>Whose Death is yet vnexpiate, by mee his cursed sonne. </l>
            <l>Why dost thou shake and tremble thus thou hand, not good for ought? </l>
            <l>Why flaggrest thou to stabbe him in, who Syre to spoyle hath brought? </l>
            <l>That punishment which hether to by pulling out myne eyes </l>
            <l>Thou hast inflicted on me, is but as a sacrifyce, </l>
            <l>Or guerdon due for villany which I committed haue </l>
            <l>With mother myne. Now Daughter sloute, leaue of pretences braue, </l>
            <l>Alledge no gloses: but with speede let goe thy Fathers hand: </l>
            <l>Thou mak'st me die a lingring death within this loathed land. </l>
            <l>Thou thinkst I am aliue, but I am dead long while agoe: </l>
            <l>To this my hateful Corps at length the rytes of Buriall show. </l>
            <l>Thou meanest well, (I know) but yet therin thou dost offend: </l>
            <l>Though colour for thy piety I see thou dost pretend. </l>
            <l>But piety it canot be, to dragge thus vp and downe </l>
            <l>Thy Fathrs Corpes vnburied through City, Field, and Towne. </l>
            <l>For bee that doth enforce a man agaynst his will to dye: </l>
            <l>And he that stayeth him that would fayne dye, most willingly, </l>
            <l>Are both alike in equall fault, and stand in egall plight. </l>
            <l>To hinder one that would be dead is morthring him outright. </l>
            <l>Yet not so great as thother is. I would be more content </l>
            <l>To haue my death commaunded me, then from me to be set. </l>
            <l>Desist from this thy purpose (Mayd) my lyfe and death both are </l>
            <l>To dispose at my liberty, with choyse to spill or spare, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000249-048-a"/>
            <l>I willingly resigned the Crowne of Thebane soyle: yet I </l>
            <l>Do still retaine vpon my selfe the entyre Soueraygntye. </l>
            <l>If I may make accompt of thee as of a trusty feare, </l>
            <l>And true compagnion at assayes: deliuer euen heere </l>
            <l>Into thy Fathers hand a Sweard: but tell me, dost thou reach </l>
            <l>The Sword embrewd in fathers bloud, wherewith my sonnes empeach </l>
            <l>The course of Law, possessing it and kingdome all by force? </l>
            <l>Where so it is doubt is there none, but cleane without remorse </l>
            <l>There bee the Floudgates opned wyde, to al licencious lust. </l>
            <l>And thriftlesse trades: I al my clayme therein do rake in dust, </l>
            <l>And cleane forsake. Let both my Sonnes by Legacy enioy </l>
            <l>The same, wherewith they surely shall contriue non smal annoy. </l>
            <l>For mee pyle rather vp a stacke of wood set all on fyre, </l>
            <l>That I therein may thrust my selfe: that is my chiefe desyre: </l>
            <l>And make an end at once of all this carrion Tarkasse vyle. </l>
            <l>Where is the surging wauous Sea? why stay I all this whyle? </l>
            <l>Bring mee to some stiepe breaknecke fall: bring me where Ismene flood </l>
            <l>With swift and horned course doth runne, bring me wheras my blood. </l>
            <l>With goaryng push of sauage beastes may out be let at once. </l>
            <l>To some Gulfe bring me, where the fall and tide may crush my Bones. </l>
            <l>If needes thou wilt my guyde remayne, as oft thou dost me tell) </l>
            <l>Bring me that am dispos'd to dye, where Sphiox that Monster fell </l>
            <l>With double shape apposed them that passed by the way, </l>
            <l>Propounding Riddles intricate, and after did them slay. </l>
            <l>There would I bee, that place I seeke: thy Father thyther bring </l>
            <l>Into that Monsters Cabin dire thy Monstrous Father fling. </l>
            <l>That though that Monster be dispatcht, the place may bee supplyde </l>
            <l>With one as badde or worse then bee: there wil I farre and wyde </l>
            <l>In tearmes obscure report and tell my heauy lucklesse lot. </l>
            <l>The misteries whereof the bearers, vnderstandeth not. </l>
            <l>Geue eare to that which I shal speake, marke thou Assyrian borne, </l>
            <l>Consider this thou Thebane, where Duke Cadmus men were torne </l>
            <l>And slayne in wood by Serpentes rage: where Dirce seely trull </l>
            <l>In humble sort at Aulter lies: aduert my tale at full </l>
            <l>Thou, that in Lacedaemon dwelles, and honorst Castors grace, </l>
            <l>And Pollux eake, two brethren twynnes. Fynd out this doubtful case. </l>
            <l>Or thou that dwelst in Elis towne or by Parnassus hill, </l>
            <l>Or thou that till'st Baeotia ground, there reaping gayne at wil. </l>
            <l>Hearke, listen well, and flatly say, if euer heretofore </l>
            <l>That murdrous monster Sphinx of Thebes that men in peeces tore, </l>
            <pb n="44" xml:id="ep000249-048-b"/>
            <l>In all his riddles askt the like, or of so straunge a sort? </l>
            <l>Or whether so insolubly his termes he cold report? </l>
            <l>The Sonne in Law to Graundfather, the Riual of his Syre: </l>
            <l>The Brother of his litle Babes: to Brethren, father dire: </l>
            <l>The Graundmother at euery byrth to Husband (graceles Elfe) </l>
            <l>Brought forth a Sonne or Daughter, which was Nephew to her selfe. </l>
            <l>How say you Syrs, in Ryddle darke, who hath so good insight, </l>
            <l>That able is the sense hereof t'vnfold and tell aryght? </l>
            <l>As for my selfe, although the Sphinx I whylome put to foyle: </l>
            <l>Yet myne owne heauy destenie I scarcely can assoyle. </l>
            <l>Why dost thou (Daughter) labour loose in vsyng further speech? </l>
            <l>To alter this my stony hart why dost thou mee beseech? </l>
            <l>I tel thee playne. I fully meane this bloud of mynt to spill. </l>
            <l>That long with Death hath struggling kept: and thereupon I will </l>
            <l>Descend to darke infernall Lake: for this same darknes blynd </l>
            <l>Of both myne eyes is nothing such, as fact of myne should fynd. </l>
            <l>It were my Blisse to bee in Hell in deepest dungeon fast: </l>
            <l>Now that which should long since haue bene, I wil perfourme at last. </l>
            <l>I cannot be debard from Death: wilt thou deny me glaue </l>
            <l>Or Sword, or knife? wilt thou no toole for mischiefe let me haue? </l>
            <l>Wilt thou both watch and ward each way, where daunger lies in wayte? </l>
            <l>Shall such a sinful Caytife wretch as I, be kepe so straite? </l>
            <l>Wilt thou not suffer me with Coard to breake my hatefull Necke? </l>
            <l>Canst thou kepe mee from poysonous herbes? hast thou them al at beck? </l>
            <l>What shall it thee preuayle to take for mee such earnest care? </l>
            <l>Death ech where is: and wayes to death in thousand corners are. </l>
            <l>Herein hath God good order tane, that euery felie Foe, </l>
            <l>May take away an others life, but Death hee cannot so. </l>
            <l>I seeke not anye toole to haue: this desprate mynd of myne </l>
            <l>Can vse the seruice of my hand, my threede of lyfe t'vntwine. </l>
            <l>Now hand, thy maister at a pinch assist to worke his feate, </l>
            <l>Helpe him with all thy power and strength, t'exployt his purpose great. </l>
            <l>I poynt thee not in this my Corps vnto one place alone: </l>
            <l>Alas, each part of me with guilt is plaunch and ouergrowne. </l>
            <l>In which soeuer part thou wilt, thy Massacre beginne, </l>
            <l>And seeke to bring me to my death which way thou mayst it winne. </l>
            <l>In pieces crush this body all, this hart that harbors sinne </l>
            <l>Pluck out, out all my entrailes pull, proceede, and neuer linne </l>
            <l>To gash and cut my wezand pype. My vaynes asender scratch, </l>
            <l>And make the Bloud come spowting out, or vse that other match, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000249-049-a"/>
            <l>Which heretofore thou vsed haste: digge where myne eyes earst stood: </l>
            <l>And let these woundes gush out apace much mattry filth and blood. </l>
            <l>Hale out of mee this loathed soule that is so hard and stout: </l>
            <l>And thou deare father Laius stand vp and looke about: </l>
            <l>Behold where euer that thou standst: I Vmpyre doe the make, </l>
            <l>And eyed Iudge of all my plagues that iustly heere I take. </l>
            <l>My Fact so lewde, so horrible, so loathsome to bee tolde </l>
            <l>I neuer thought with any pryce or tormentes manifolde </l>
            <l>Could haue full expiation: ne thought I it inough </l>
            <l>To die this death: or in one part to be beslasshed through. </l>
            <l>By piecemeale I am well content to suffer tormentes all </l>
            <l>And euen by piecemeale for to die: for plagues to plague mee call. </l>
            <l>Exact the punishment that's due: I heere most ready stand </l>
            <l>To satisfie with any death that law and righte hath scand. </l>
            <l>My former smartes, when as mine eyes I raked out with pawes, </l>
            <l>Were but as tastes of sacrifice, somewhat to helpe my cause. </l>
            <l>Come therefore (Father) neare to mee, and thrust this hand of myne </l>
            <l>More nearer into euery wound. It sweru'de and did decline </l>
            <l>For feare, when first it tooke th'assay mine eyes to ransacke out. </l>
            <l>I beare it still in memory, my eyes then star'de about </l>
            <l>And seemed to disswade the hand from doing of the charge </l>
            <l>Whereto it was enioyned tho, and had Commission large. </l>
            <l>Thou shalt well thinke that OEdipus dissembleth not a white </l>
            <l>But what his word hath warranted, his deede hath firmely quit. </l>
            <l>Thy stoutnes then, was not so great when eyes thou pulledst out </l>
            <l>As was thy man a●oden, when thou threwst them from thee round about. </l>
            <l>Now, by those Gyeholes thrust thy hand into the very braine: </l>
            <l>That part where death attempted was, let death be sought againe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e103160">
            <speaker>AN. </speaker>
            <l>Vndaunted Prynce, must noble Syre, with humble mynde. I sue </l>
            <l>That I your Daughter may be bolde to vse some speech to you: </l>
            <l>And that you would with patience digest my poore aduise: </l>
            <l>My suite is not to draw your minde to thinges, that earst in price </l>
            <l>You highly held, me to the view of glittring Pallace olde, </l>
            <l>Ne brauery of your noble Realme, scarce able to bee tolde: </l>
            <l>But that you would these yrefull fittes, by trace of time now quaild, </l>
            <l>With patient minde sustayne and beare: this vertue neuer faylde </l>
            <l>In any Prynce of such a spright as in your noble Grace </l>
            <l>Appeareth bryght: it fitteth not that such should once abase </l>
            <l>Themselues as thralles to Sorrowes checke 〈◊〉 the conquest yeelde </l>
            <l>To aduerse hap lyke 〈…〉 </l>
            <pb n="45" xml:id="ep000249-049-b"/>
            <l>It is no prayse, syr, though perhappes you so your reckening cast </l>
            <l>To make of lyfe so small accoumpt, and thus to bee agast </l>
            <l>At euery wagging of a leafe, and combersome myschaunce: </l>
            <l>No, no, tis vertue in such case high courage to aduaunce. </l>
            <l>And when thinges are at worst, to shew true magnanimitie: </l>
            <l>Not lyke a Meycocke, cowardly at eche alarme to flee. </l>
            <l>Hee that hath tride all fortunes spight and worldly wealth despisde, </l>
            <l>And constantly hath borne all bruntes that are to be deuisde, </l>
            <l>Mee thinks no cause hath, why he needes to ende his breathing dayes </l>
            <l>Or wish himselfe in graue: for why, starcke crauens vse such wayes. </l>
            <l>But as for him, that's drencht in dole and wrapt in carking care, </l>
            <l>Whose pensius plight can be no worse, nor tast of sowrer fare, </l>
            <l>That man hath cause well pleas●● to be: sith hee in safety standes, </l>
            <l>And pykes hath past, and now is free from feare of further bandes. </l>
            <l>Put case the Gods would weave the webbe of further woe to thee, </l>
            <l>What more can any of them doe thy grieues to amplifie? </l>
            <l>Nay, thou thy selfe, (although thou wouldst) canst adde thereto no more, </l>
            <l>Vnlesse thou thinke thy selfe, to haue deserued death therefore. </l>
            <l>And yet, thou arte not worthy death: my reason is, because </l>
            <l>Through ignoraunce thou didst a fact contrary to the lawes. </l>
            <l>And therefore Father thinke your selfe most guiltlesse in the case, </l>
            <l>And (maugre Gods) stand on your guarde, my counsell sound embrace: </l>
            <l>For doubtlesse you an innocent are deem'de and thought to bee, </l>
            <l>And are in deede: what makes you thus in dumpes and dolefull glee? </l>
            <l>What cause so great should so enchaunt your conscience, and your wits, </l>
            <l>To seeke your owne decay and spoyle? what meane faint hearted fits? </l>
            <l>That thus in hast you would so faine abandon this your lyfe </l>
            <l>And goe to hell, where torment dwelles and grisly ghostes be ryfe. </l>
            <l>You would not see Sun, Moone, ne Starre: no more you can: your eyes </l>
            <l>Are blynd: you faine would leaue your Court, and Countries miseries. </l>
            <l>Why so you may, and so you doe. These all are put to sacke, </l>
            <l>That now alyue, aswell as dead you feele of these the lacke. </l>
            <l>You flee from Mother, Wyfe, and Chylde, you see no man alyue: </l>
            <l>What more can death dispatch away but life doth now depriue? </l>
            <l>your lords, your knights, your courtly traine, your kingly state &amp; crowne </l>
            <l>Your graund Affaires, your waighty charge is gone &amp; brought abowne. </l>
            <l>From whom, from what, do you thus flee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e103660">
            <speaker>OEdi. </speaker>
            <l>From none but from my selfe </l>
            <l>Who haue a breast full fraught with guilte: who, wretched caitiffe Elte </l>
            <l>Haue all embrude my hands with bloud. From these apace I flee </l>
            <l>And from the heauens and Gods therein: and from that villanie </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000249-050-a"/>
            <l>Which I most wicked wretch haue wrought. Shall I treade on thys ground? </l>
            <l>Or am I worthy so to doe, in whom such trickes abound? </l>
            <l>Am I to haue the benefite of any Element? </l>
            <l>Of Ayre for breath, of water moyst, or Earth for nourishment? </l>
            <l>O Slaue forlorne, O beastly wretch, O Incestmonger vyle, </l>
            <l>O Varlet most detestable, O Peysaunte full of guile. </l>
            <l>Why doe I with polluted Fyst, and bloudy pawes presume </l>
            <l>To touch thy chast and comely hand? I foame, I fret, I fume </l>
            <l>In hearing any speake to mee. Ought I heare any tell </l>
            <l>Or once of Sonne or Father speake, syth I did Father quell? </l>
            <l>Would God it were within my power my Senses all to stop, </l>
            <l>Would God I could these Eares of myne, euen by the stumps to crop. </l>
            <l>If that might bee, then (daughter) I should not haue heard thy voyce. </l>
            <l>I, I thy Syre, that thee be got by most incestuous choise. </l>
            <l>Beegetting of thee, makes my crymes moe then they were before: </l>
            <l>Remorse thereof both gnaw and grype my conscience more and more. </l>
            <l>Ofttymes that which myne Eyes not see, with Eares that doe I heare, </l>
            <l>And of my Facts afore time done the inward wound I beare. </l>
            <l>Why is there stay made of my doome? Why am I spard so long? </l>
            <l>Why is not this blind head of myne throwne damned ghosts among? </l>
            <l>Why rest I on the Earth, and not among infernall Sprightes? </l>
            <l>Why pester I the company of any mortall Wightes? </l>
            <l>What myschiefe is there more behind? to aggrauate my care? </l>
            <l>My Kingdome, Parents, Children, Wit and Vertue quayled are </l>
            <l>By sturdy stormes of froward Fate: nothing remaynde but teares, </l>
            <l>And they bee dryde, and Eyes be gon: my hardned heart forbeares </l>
            <l>Such signes of grace: leaue of therefore, and make no more adde: </l>
            <l>A minde so mated with dispayre no suytes will slowpe vnto. </l>
            <l>I practize some straunge punishments agreeing to my deede: </l>
            <l>But what proportion can bee found of plagues vnto my meede? </l>
            <l>Whose Fortune euer was so bad? I was in sooner borne, </l>
            <l>But seely Infant Iudgde I was in peeces to be torne. </l>
            <l>My mother in whose wombe I lay, forth had not mee yet brought </l>
            <l>And yet euen then I feared was: and straight my death was sought. </l>
            <l>Some Babes soone after they bee borne, by stroke of death depart: </l>
            <l>But I poore soule, before my byrth adiudged was to dart </l>
            <l>Of death: some yet in Mothers wombe, ere any light they see </l>
            <l>Doe taste the dint of hasty Fate, while Innocents they bee. </l>
            <l>Apollo by his Oracle pronounced sentence dyre </l>
            <l>Vpon mee being yet vnborne, that I vnto my Syre </l>
            <pb n="46" xml:id="ep000249-050-b"/>
            <l>Should beastly parricide commit: and therevpon was I </l>
            <l>Condemned straight by Fathers doome. My Feete were by and by </l>
            <l>Launcde through, &amp; through with yron Pins: hangde was I by the Heeles </l>
            <l>Vpon a Tree: my swelling plants the printe thereof yet feeles: </l>
            <l>As pray to Beastes, cast out also, to cramme theyr greedy Iawes </l>
            <l>In Mount Cytheron, and to fill the griping Vulturs Mawes. </l>
            <l>Such Sauce to tast full lyke was I, was others heeretofore </l>
            <l>Descended of the royall Sangue, with smart (perforce) haue bore. </l>
            <l>But see the chaunce: I thus condemn'de by Dan Apollos hest </l>
            <l>And cast to beasts by Fathers doome, and euery way distrest, </l>
            <l>Could finde no death: no death on mee durst seyze his lordly Pawe, </l>
            <l>But fled from mee, as though I had not beene within his Lawe. </l>
            <l>I verified the Oracle, with wicked hand I kilde </l>
            <l>Myne owne deere Father, and vnwares his guiltlesse bloud I spilde. </l>
            <l>Shall any satisfaction redeeme so vile an Acte? </l>
            <l>May any kinde of Piety purge such a shamefull fact? </l>
            <l>I rested not contented thus. For Father beeing slayne, </l>
            <l>I fell in linkes of lawlesse Loue with Mother: Oh what payne </l>
            <l>And grudge of minde sustaynde I there? in thinking on the same, </l>
            <l>To tell our wicked wedlocke Yoake, I loath, I blush, I shame. </l>
            <l>I may not well this geare conceale, Ile tell it: out it shall: </l>
            <l>Though to my shame it much redound, it may augment my thrall. </l>
            <l>I will display straunge villanies, and them in number many, </l>
            <l>Most beastlike parts, most lewde attempts, to bee abhorr'de of any. </l>
            <l>So filthy, and so monstruous, that (sure I thinke) no Age </l>
            <l>Will them belieue to haue bene done: so cruell was my rage, </l>
            <l>That euen ech cutthroate Partrcide thereat may be ashamde </l>
            <l>To heare it nam'de: and with disdaine straight wayes will be enflamde. </l>
            <l>My handes in Fathers bloud embrude to Fathers Bed I brought. </l>
            <l>And haue with Mother myne, his Wife, incestuous practyse sought. </l>
            <l>To myschiefe adding mischiefe more: I wis my fault to Sire, </l>
            <l>Is slender in comparison: my gracelesse fond desire </l>
            <l>Could not bee staide, till solemnely the mariage Knot was knit </l>
            <l>Twixt mee and Mother myne, alas for want of grace and wit. </l>
            <l>How plungde am I in myschiefe still? how is the measure full </l>
            <l>Of horrours vile, which doe my minde and heart asunder pull? </l>
            <l>And least the heape of these my woes might seeme to bee too skant, </l>
            <l>My Mother (she my Wyfe that is) yong issue doth not want. </l>
            <l>Can any crime in all the World more haynous be surmisde? </l>
            <l>If any may: by wicked Impes the same I haue deuisde. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000249-051-a"/>
            <l>My Realme and Crowne I haue resignde, which I receiued as hyre </l>
            <l>For murdring most vunaturally the king, my Lord, and Syre, </l>
            <l>Which Crowne now since, twixt both my sonnes hath kindled mortall war. </l>
            <l>And all the countrey by the ears remains at deadly iarre. </l>
            <l>I know ful wel what destenies to this same Crowne belonges. </l>
            <l>None without Bloud the same shall weare, and most accursed wrongs. </l>
            <l>This mynd of myne (who Father am) presageth many ills: </l>
            <l>And gloomy dayes of slaughter dyre: the plot that murther willes. </l>
            <l>Already is contriu'd and cast: all truth of word and deede </l>
            <l>Is quight exild, al promise broke of pactes afore decreed. </l>
            <l>Etheocles, thone of my sonnes who now in princely throne </l>
            <l>Beates all the sway, meanes stil to keepe the Diademe alone. </l>
            <l>Poore Polynices th'o other sonne, thus beyng dispessest, </l>
            <l>And kept by force from Kingly rule his humble sute addrest </l>
            <l>Vnto the Gods this wrong to wreake, this breach of league and oth </l>
            <l>T'auenge and plague: he Argos soyle end Greekish Cttyes both </l>
            <l>Perswades t'assist him in this warie, this quarel to mayntayne: </l>
            <l>That he in Thebes (as promise was) might haue his turne to raygne. </l>
            <l>The ruyne that to wearied Thebes shall greeuously befall </l>
            <l>And bring the pompous state therof adowne, shal not be small. </l>
            <l>Fire, sword, glaue, wounds, &amp; thwacking thumps, shal light vnto their share, </l>
            <l>And that ere long: and mischieues worse (it any worse there are) </l>
            <l>And this shall hap, that all the worlde may know it is the race </l>
            <l>And yssue of a curied Syre that darraygnes such a case. </l>
            <l>Though other causes none there were to moue you (sic) to liue, </l>
            <l>Yet is this one sufficient, that you by awe may dryue </l>
            <l>Your sonnes my Brethren tarring thus to vnity and peace: </l>
            <l>For you their Father only may theyr furies cause to tease. </l>
            <l>You and none els may turne away thoccassons of this warre: </l>
            <l>These bransicke youthes from further rage you onely may dibarre. </l>
            <l>By this your meanes the countrey shall their quiet peace enioy </l>
            <l>And Brethren ioyntly reconcild shal worke no more ennoy. </l>
            <l>If you therefore this mortall life thus to your selfe deny: </l>
            <l>You many thousandes shal vndoe, whose states on you relye. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e104850">
            <speaker>Oed. </speaker>
            <l>What? canst thou make me to beleue, that any sparke of grece </l>
            <l>Or loue to Syre, or honesty in them hath any place, </l>
            <l>Which thirst for one on others bloud, which after kingdomes gape, </l>
            <l>Whose whole delight is villany, werre, wurther, guile and rape? </l>
            <l>Such hateful ympes on mischiefe set, such wicked Termagosites, </l>
            <l>As to be sonnes of such a Syre with shame may wake their vauntes. </l>
            <pb n="47" xml:id="ep000249-051-b"/>
            <l>At one bare woord to tel thee all: thy brethren two are bent </l>
            <l>Vppon all mischiefe, wayghing not what loosenes they frequent. </l>
            <l>When flingbrayne rage ensots their heades, they care not they a rush </l>
            <l>Vpon what Deuelish vile attemptes they geue the desprat push. </l>
            <l>And as they are conceau'd and borne in most abhorred sort, </l>
            <l>So still deuoyde of Grace they thincke all villany but sport. </l>
            <l>Theyr Fathers shame and wretched state moues them no whit at all, </l>
            <l>To Countrey they no reckning make what massacre befall. </l>
            <l>Their myndes are rauisht with desyre ambitiously to raygne. </l>
            <l>I know their driftes, and what they hope at length by shiftes to gayne. </l>
            <l>And therfore sith the case so standes I leyfer had to die </l>
            <l>With poasting speede whyle in my house there is none worse then I. </l>
            <l>Ahlas, deare Daughter what adoe dost thou about me make? </l>
            <l>Why liest thou prostrate at my knees? why dost thou trauaile take, </l>
            <l>To conquere my resolued mynd with this thy spiced phraze </l>
            <l>Of fayre entreatie? these thy wordes my flynty hart amaze. </l>
            <l>Dame Fortune hath none other bayte to bryng me to her lure </l>
            <l>Then this alone: til now I still vnbanquisht did endure. </l>
            <l>No Creatures words but thyne alone could pearce this hart of myne, </l>
            <l>Ne from a purpose resolute my setled mynd butwyne. </l>
            <l>Thou conquere canst thaffections fond that in my breast do boyle, </l>
            <l>Thou teachest grace to fathers house, and zeale to natiue soyle. </l>
            <l>Each thing to me delightful is which iumpeth with thy wil: </l>
            <l>Commaund me (Daughter) I thy hestes am ready to fufill. </l>
            <l>Old Oedipus if thou enioyne, wil passe th' Aegaean Sea: </l>
            <l>And flashing flakes of Aetna Mount, with mouth he dare assay. </l>
            <l>He boldly dare obiect himselfe to raumping Dragons claw </l>
            <l>Which rag'd, &amp; sweld and venime spit apace, when as he saw </l>
            <l>Dan Hercules away to steale his golden Aples all </l>
            <l>In Gardens of Hesperides. At thy commaund, he shall </l>
            <l>His Entrails offer vnto iobbe of greedy Vulturs Byll: </l>
            <l>At thy commaund, content he is in life to linger still. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="ep000249-e105240">
          <pb xml:id="ep000249-052-a"/>
          <head>THE SECONDE ACTE. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000249-e105250">Nuntius. OEdipus. Antigone. Iocasta. </stage>
          <l>REnowmed Prynce, of royall Race </l>
          <l>and Noble lygne yspronge: </l>
          <l>The Thebans dreading much the drife </l>
          <l>of this your childrens thronge, </l>
          <l>And warlicke garboyle now in hand, </l>
          <l>most humbly pray your Grace </l>
          <l>For Countreys safety, downe to set some order in the case. </l>
          <l>They bee not threates and menacies that thus their mindes affright: </l>
          <l>The mischiefe is more neere then so: the Enmy is in sight. </l>
          <l>For Polynices he that is your younger sonne of twayne, </l>
          <l>Doth clayme the crowne, and in his turne in Thebes requires to raigne </l>
          <l>According vnto couenaunts made: which quarrell to decite </l>
          <l>Hee purposeth the dene of sword, and maritall force t'abide. </l>
          <l>With him he brings a mighty Troupe from eu'ry part of Greece, </l>
          <l>Sir, seuen Dukes, hesieging Thebes are minded it to fleese. </l>
          <l>Helpe noble King, els are wee lyke to perishe man and chylde, </l>
          <l>These bloudy broyles of ciuill warre from vs protect and shyelde. </l>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e105430">
            <speaker>O Edi. </speaker>
            <l>Am I one like to stop the rage of any wicked act? </l>
            <l>Am I one like to cause these Youthes to leaue their bloudy fact? </l>
            <l>Am I a maister like to teach what lawes of loue do meane? </l>
            <l>Should I not then from former quise digresse in nature eleane? </l>
            <l>They treade their Fathers steps aright, they play my lawlesse prankes: </l>
            <l>Like Syre, like Sonnes, like Tree, like fruite: I con them harty thanks: </l>
            <l>By this I know them for my Sonnes, and praise their towardnesse: </l>
            <l>I would they should by peeuish partes, whose Sonnes they be, expresse. </l>
            <l>Shew forth you noble Gallante ympes, what metled minds you beare, </l>
            <l>Shew forth by deedes your valor great, let lofty sprights appeare. </l>
            <l>Surmount and dimme my prayses all, Eclypse my glory quight: </l>
            <l>Attempt some enterprise in which your Syre may haue delight </l>
            <l>To haue till now remaynd in life: hereof I haue no doubt: </l>
            <l>For well I know your practise is straunge feates to bring about. </l>
            <l>Your byrth and ligne from whence you spronge, assures me of no lesse </l>
            <l>Such noble Bloudes must needes atchiue some doughty worthinesse. </l>
            <pb n="48" xml:id="ep000249-052-b"/>
            <l>Your Weapons and Artillery for warre bring out with speede, </l>
            <l>Consume with flame your natiue Soyle, and desolation breede </l>
            <l>In eu'ry house within the Land: a hurly burly make </l>
            <l>Confusedly of eu'ry thinge. Make all the Realme to quake, </l>
            <l>And in exile theyr dayes let end make leuell with the ground </l>
            <l>Eche fenced Fort and walled Towne: The Gods and all confound, </l>
            <l>And throw their Temples on their heads: Their Images deface, </l>
            <l>And melt them all: turne vpstdowne eche house in eu'ry place. </l>
            <l>Burne, spoyle, make hauocke, leaue no iote of City free from fyre, </l>
            <l>And let the flame begin his rage within my Chamber dyre. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e105700">
            <speaker>AN. </speaker>
            <l>Syr, banish these vnpatient panges, let plagues of Common wealth </l>
            <l>Entreate your Grace, sith vpon you stayth all their hope and health. </l>
            <l>Procure your sonnes to reconcile themselues, as brothers ought, </l>
            <l>Establishe peace betwene them both, let meanes of loue be sought. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e105750">
            <speaker>OEd. </speaker>
            <l>Oh daughter, see and well beholde howe I to peace am bent? </l>
            <l>And how to end these garboyles all I seeme full well content? </l>
            <l>My minde (I tell thee) swelles with yre: within my entralles boyles </l>
            <l>Abundaunt stoare of Choller fell: such restlesse rage turmoyles </l>
            <l>My inward Soule, that I must yet some greater matter brew: </l>
            <l>Which may the Realme enwrap in bale, and cause them all to rue. </l>
            <l>That which my rashe and heady sonnes haue hitherto begon </l>
            <l>Is nothing in respect of that wich must by me be don. </l>
            <l>This ciuill warre is nothing like to that which I deuise: </l>
            <l>These trifling broyles for such a Sea of harmes cannot suffice. </l>
            <l>Let brother cut the brothers throate with murthrous knife in hand: </l>
            <l>Yet is not this ynough to purge the mischieues of this lend. </l>
            <l>Some haynous Fact, vnheard of yet, some detestable deede </l>
            <l>Must practisde bee: as is to mee. and myne by Fates decreed. </l>
            <l>Such custome haunts our cursed race: such guise our house hath caught: </l>
            <l>My vise incestuous Bed requires, such pageaunts to be wraught. </l>
            <l>To me your Father Weapons reach, my selfe heere let me shrowde </l>
            <l>In couert of these queachy wooddes: and let me be allowde </l>
            <l>To lurke behinde this Craggy Rocke, or els my selfe to hyde </l>
            <l>On backside of some thickset hedge: where lying vnespide, </l>
            <l>I hearken may what marketfolkes in passing to and froe </l>
            <l>Do talke: and what the countrey Clownes speake, as by way they goe. </l>
            <l>There (syth with eyes, I cannot see) with eares yet may I beare </l>
            <l>How cruelly my Sonnes by warre do one the other teare. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e106000">
            <speaker>IOC. </speaker>
            <l>A fortunate and happy Dame Agaue may be thought, </l>
            <l>Who (though with bloudy hands) her sonne to fatell death she brought, </l>
            <l>And from the shoulders chopt his head, and bore the same about </l>
            <l>In bloudy hand, at Bacchus feast withau th'inspired rout </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000249-053-a"/>
            <l>Of sacrificers, quartering poore Pentheus mangled lymmes: </l>
            <l>Though this her cruell facte, somewhat her commendation dymmes: </l>
            <l>Yet euen in these her phrantick fits shee stayde her selfe in time </l>
            <l>From further harme, not adding more to aggrauate her crime. </l>
            <l>My guilt were light, if I had not some others guilty made: </l>
            <l>And yet is this but matter light: I tooke a biler trade. </l>
            <l>For, Mother I am vnto those that in all vice excell, </l>
            <l>And who in most abhorred sinnes condignely beare the bell. </l>
            <l>To all my woes and myseries there wanted onely this, </l>
            <l>That I should loue my Countreyes foe, who Polynices is. </l>
            <l>Three snowy Wynters passed are, and Sommers three be gone, </l>
            <l>Synce be an exilde wretch abroade hath lead his lyfe in moane: </l>
            <l>And sought his bread among the fremmd: till now compell'de perforce. </l>
            <l>Hee craues reliefe of Greekish Kings, on him to haue remorse. </l>
            <l>Hee maried hath the Daughter of Adrastus, who at becke </l>
            <l>Rules Argiue people, swaying them with awe of Princely checke: </l>
            <l>And he t' aduaunce his sonne in law to his most lawfull right </l>
            <l>Hath with him brought from seuen Realmes a warlike Crue to fight. </l>
            <l>What doome I should in this case geue, which syde I wish to winne, </l>
            <l>I cannot tell: my minde amazde, yet doubtfull rests therein. </l>
            <l>Th'one of my Sonnes (as right it is) requyres the Crowne as due: </l>
            <l>I knowe it so accorded was: his cause is good and true. </l>
            <l>But in such sort, by force of Armes to relie maunde the same, </l>
            <l>Is ill and most vnnaturall, herein he is to blame. </l>
            <l>What shall I doe, what may I say? I mother am to both: </l>
            <l>And thus my Sonnes at deadly feud to see I am full loth. </l>
            <l>Without the breach of mother zeale I can no way deuise: </l>
            <l>For what good had I wishe to th'one, thence th'others harme doth rise. </l>
            <l>But though I loue them both alyke, yet sure my heart enclynes </l>
            <l>To him that hath the better cause: though wronged thus, he pynes: </l>
            <l>As one by frowning fortune thrilde from piller vnto post: </l>
            <l>His Credite, Countrey, friendes, and wealth, and treasure being lost. </l>
            <l>The weaker side I will support, and further al I can, </l>
            <l>Most mercy alwayes should vt shewde vnto th'oppressed man. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e106390">
            <speaker>NV. </speaker>
            <l>While (Madame) you waymenting here your heauy plaints declare </l>
            <l>And waste the time, my Lords your Sonnes in taunged battayle are: </l>
            <l>Eche Captains bright in Armour standes, the Trumpet sounds amain, </l>
            <l>And Standard is aduanc'de, amid the thronge of eyther traine. </l>
            <l>In marshall ray full prest to fight stand seuen worthy Kynges: </l>
            <l>And eche of them a warlicke troupe of valiaunt Souldiers bringes. </l>
            <pb n="49" xml:id="ep000249-053-b"/>
            <l>With courage not behynd the best, the Thebanes marche apace: </l>
            <l>And like right ympes of Cadmus brood, do slash at Enmies face. </l>
            <l>The Souldiers force and willingnes on eyther side to fyght, </l>
            <l>Appeares: in that they nothing lesse pretend them shameful flight. </l>
            <l>See how their trampling to and froe, the dust to Skies doth reare, </l>
            <l>And what a Cloud of Smoke in Campe the horses make t'appeare. </l>
            <l>And if my feare dismay me not: It all be true I see: </l>
            <l>Me thinkes I view their glittering glaues begoard with bloud to bee. </l>
            <l>Me thinkes I see the Voward thrill and shake their Pikes in hand: </l>
            <l>Me thinkes I see the Gydons gay, and Streamers where they stand: </l>
            <l>Wherein is wrought by curtous skill, in Letters all of Gold </l>
            <l>The Scotchion, Poeste, Name and Armes of euery captayne bold. </l>
            <l>Make hast, be gone, dispatch. (Madame) Cause Brethren to agree: </l>
            <l>Betwyxt them stay this quarell, least a slaughter great ye see. </l>
            <l>So shall you to your Children loue, to each syde peace restoare: </l>
            <l>The mothers mediation may heale vp all the Soare. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="ep000249-e106620">
          <head>THE THIRDE ACTE. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000249-e106630">Antigone. Iocasta. Nuntius. </stage>
          <l>POast, poast, be gone, and trudge for life: </l>
          <l>Queene mother make no stay: </l>
          <l>That twixt my Brothers, perfect league </l>
          <l>and truce continue may. </l>
          <l>You that be Mother to them both, </l>
          <l>vse your auctority: </l>
          <l>Out of their handes their weapons wrest, </l>
          <l>and make them warres defye. </l>
          <l>Your bared Breastes which once they suckt, </l>
          <l>hold out amid their Swordes: </l>
          <l>Beare of the brunt of all their blowes, or end this warre with wordes. </l>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e106750">
            <speaker>Ioc. </speaker>
            <l>Thy talke I like, I wil be gone: Ile goe with might and mayne: </l>
            <l>This head of myne I ieoperd wil, betwene them to be slayne. </l>
            <l>In thickest thronge of all the Troupes I purposd am to stand, </l>
            <l>And try what grace, or curtesy rimaynes in eyther Bonde. </l>
            <l>If Brothers beare malicious myndes each other to subdue, </l>
            <l>Let them first onset geue on wee, and me to death pursue. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000249-054-a"/>
            <l>If eyther of them be endude with any sparke of grace, </l>
            <l>Or Natures lawes or Filiall awe doth any whit embrace, </l>
            <l>Let him at mothers suite lay downe his Pikes and glaues of warre, </l>
            <l>And weapons of hastility let him abandon farre. </l>
            <l>And he that cancard stomacke beares his Brother there to quell, </l>
            <l>Forgetting Nature, let him first with me his Mother mell. </l>
            <l>These headdy youthes from further rage I seely Trot wil staye: </l>
            <l>I wittingly will not behold such mischiefe cary sway. </l>
            <l>Or if I liue to see the same, it shal not bee alone. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e106910">
            <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
            <l>The Standardes are displayd in field, the Ennemyes are prone </l>
            <l>To fall to fight: the clashing noyse of weapons heare you may. </l>
            <l>Much murther, death, and dreadfull dule, cannot be far away. </l>
            <l>Their stony hartes goe mollify, with sugred termes perswade </l>
            <l>Their wilful myndes O Queene, before they furiously inuade </l>
            <l>The one the other: yonder see how they in armour bright </l>
            <l>Bestirre themselues from place to place: (O dire and dismall sight.) </l>
            <l>My trickling teares, my blubbring Eyes, may put you out of doubt </l>
            <l>That all is true which I haue sayd: looke, looke, how al the route </l>
            <l>On eyther part doth slowly march as loth (belike) to trye </l>
            <l>By dent of Swerd so straunge a case: But both my brothers hie </l>
            <l>Apace, to grapple force to force, and ioyne with handy blowes: </l>
            <l>This day wil breeede the bitter smart of euer during woes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e107050">
            <speaker>Ioc. </speaker>
            <l>What whirlewynd swift might I procure to beare me through the ayre? </l>
            <l>What monstruous flying Sphinx wil helpe, that I were quickly there? </l>
            <l>Of all the Byrdes Stimphalides (with winges so huge and large </l>
            <l>That Phoebus rayes they shadowed quight) wil any take the charge </l>
            <l>To cary mee to yonder place? what rauenous Harpye Burd </l>
            <l>With vgly talantes all with flith, and dirty dung befurde, </l>
            <l>(Which hungrestarud King Phineus, that had put out the Eyes </l>
            <l>Of children his) wil at this pinch a meane for me deuyse, </l>
            <l>That I aloft may hoysed bee, and with al spede be set, </l>
            <l>Where yonder cruel armies two in open field be met? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e107160">
            <speaker>Nune. </speaker>
            <l>Shee runnes apace, like one of wit and senses all distract: </l>
            <l>No Arrow swifter out of Bow: no Ship with Sayle ful thwackt </l>
            <l>With wynd at will more way can make with motion such shee flyes </l>
            <l>As glyding Star whose leames do drawe a Furrow longe in Skyes. </l>
            <l>As much agast she trottes apace: and now in Campe she standes: </l>
            <l>Her presence and arriuall there hath parted both the Bandes. </l>
            <l>At mothers great entreaty made, the bloudy broyle is husht: </l>
            <l>And where before with goring Glaue the one at thother pusht, </l>
            <l>With ful entent to kill and slay, appeas'd is now their yre </l>
            <pb n="50" xml:id="ep000249-054-b"/>
            <l>And they well pleasd to bend to peace, as she doth them require. </l>
            <l>The Sword agayne in sheath is put, that lately out was drawne </l>
            <l>To pash out Braynes of Brothers Scull: she ceasseth not to fawne </l>
            <l>Vpon them both, their strife to stint: her gray and hoary haires, </l>
            <l>Her Snow whyte lockes with tears besprent in ruthful sort she ●eates. </l>
            <l>She Motherlike seekes how to linke their hartes in one assent, </l>
            <l>With brynish teares she wettes the cheekes of him that's malcontent. </l>
            <l>That Child that staggryng longe doth stand, with mother to dispute, </l>
            <l>May seeme vnwilling mynd to beare to yeeld to Mothers sute. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="ep000249-e107350">
          <head>THE FOVRTH ACTE. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000249-e107360">Iocasta. Polynices. </stage>
          <l>AGaynste mee onely turne the force </l>
          <l>of wreckful Sword and Fyre: </l>
          <l>Let all the Youthes with one accord </l>
          <l>repay to me that hyre, </l>
          <l>That earnde I haue by due deserte: </l>
          <l>let both the gallant Band </l>
          <l>Of them that come from Argos soyle, </l>
          <l>and them of Thebane Land </l>
          <l>Come runne vpon me all at once: let neither freend ne foe </l>
          <l>Refrayne a whit his bloudy blade at this my wombe to throw. </l>
          <l>This wombe, this wombe, wherein I bare these wilful Brethren here </l>
          <l>Beget by hym that was my sonne, and eke my wedded fere. </l>
          <l>Dismembre this my Body vyle: cast all my lymmes abrode: </l>
          <l>I am their mother: child wyfe throwes for them I once abode. </l>
          <l>You two, my sonnes, neede I to speake, to wil you leaue your yre? </l>
          <l>Ist not your partes, in such a case t'accomplish my desyre? </l>
          <l>Wil you not plight the faythful league of true and perfect loue? </l>
          <l>Wil you not ioyntly quarrels all at Mothers sute remoue? </l>
          <l>That this shalbe as I request, come, geue me both, your handes </l>
          <l>Whyle yet they vndystayned be, and cleane from murther standes. </l>
          <l>What cryme you heretofore haue done, agaynst your wil it was. </l>
          <l>And al that spot which staynes your same, by Fortune came to passe. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000249-055-a"/>
          <l>This haynons Act, this franticke coyle you can no wise excuse▪ </l>
          <l>But wittingly and willingly sound counsell yee refuse. </l>
          <l>It resteth free within your choyse: of these take which yee list: </l>
          <l>If peace delight for mothers sake this brabling broyle vntwist. </l>
          <l>If such a lewde outrage as this more pleasaunt seeme to bee: </l>
          <l>Behold, the same and greater too yee may commit on mee. </l>
          <l>Who beeing mother, heere oppose my selfe betwene you twayne: </l>
          <l>Ere you do one an other kill, I needes must first be slayne. </l>
          <l>Take either therefore quight away this straunge vngodly iarre. </l>
          <l>Or if you will not: mee dispatch, who stay your wished warre? </l>
          <l>Ahlas in this my pensiue plight to whom should I dyrect </l>
          <l>My piteous plaint, and earnest suyte? to whom might I detect </l>
          <l>Myne inward griefe and throubed heart? which of them were I best </l>
          <l>T'encounter first and fast embrace, to breede my surest rest? </l>
          <l>I loue them both euen equally, affection like I beare </l>
          <l>To either party: mother fond and parciall els I weare. </l>
          <l>The one of them these three yeares space bath liu'de in banishment. </l>
          <l>But it all couenaunts may be kept, as at the first was ment, </l>
          <l>The other now as turne doth fall, must trudge an otherwhile, </l>
          <l>And learne to know what tis to liue so long in like exile. </l>
          <l>Wae worth this hapiesse heauy hap: shall I not liue the day, </l>
          <l>To see my sonnes together once in one selfe place to stay? </l>
          <l>Shall neuer I behold them both to better concord bent? </l>
          <l>Is all affection naturall within them both so spent? </l>
          <l>Then, Polynices, come thou fyrst, embrace thy Mother deare? </l>
          <l>Thou that hast trauaild many a myle, and languisht many a yeare. </l>
          <l>That many a storme abidden haste, and many a brunt sustainde, </l>
          <l>And wearied long with sharpe exile, from Mothers sight bene wainde: </l>
          <l>Come vnto mee, and neerer stand, put vp thy Sword againe </l>
          <l>Into thy sheath: thy shyuering Speare (that out of hand so faine </l>
          <l>Would be dischargd at Brothers throate) within this ground sticke fast. </l>
          <l>This Shielde of thine lay also downe. It makes mee sore agast. </l>
          <l>It is so bigge, it will not let this louing breast of myne. </l>
          <l>To ioyne and debonairely meete with that sweete heart of thine: </l>
          <l>Take of thy helmet from thine head, the Thonge thereof vuty. </l>
          <l>That I thy Vifuge may behold, and all thy face descry. </l>
          <l>Why dost thou backward turne thy head? and glauncest still thine Eye, </l>
          <l>And takèst keepe of brothers hand for feare of villany? </l>
          <l>Thy body all with these myne Armes I will defend and hyde? </l>
          <l>If hee attempt thy bloud to spill, his murthrdus blade shall glyde </l>
          <pb n="51" xml:id="ep000249-055-b"/>
          <l>First through these tender sydes of myne: why standst thou so amazd? </l>
          <l>Dost thou distrust thy Mothers loue? thinkst thou her kindnes razd? </l>
          <l>Poly. I feare in deede, distrusting sore, Syre, Damme &amp; all my kinne: </l>
          <l>And thinke that truthles treachery in hartes of all hath bin. </l>
          <l>Dame Natures lewes are flung at heele, and naught esteemed be: </l>
          <l>No fayth in kinred planted is, ne true syncerity. </l>
          <l>Synce I by proofe haue seene and felt what hurly burly growes </l>
          <l>Betwixt vs Brethren: and from thence what Sea of mischiefe flowes: </l>
          <l>I may suspect no faster fayth in Mother to remayne: </l>
          <l>Its not vnlike, but shee likewyse wil prankes as bad mayntaine. </l>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e108090">
            <speaker>Ioc. </speaker>
            <l>Thy sword in hand fast clasped keepe: On heade thy Basnet tye: </l>
            <l>On Left Atme holde thy Targat sure, and on thy Gard relye. </l>
            <l>At all poyntes armd prepared stand: all future doubtes preuent: </l>
            <l>Be sure to see thy Brother first t'vnarme himselfe content. </l>
            <l>And now to thee Etheocles some speech I am to vse: </l>
            <l>Thou first wast cause of all this warre, doe not therfore refuse </l>
            <l>Downe first to lay thy brawling Blade, and yeld to Reasons lore: </l>
            <l>If name of peace so hateful be, if that thou any more </l>
            <l>Entendst this warre to prosecute, in this so sauage sort, </l>
            <l>Let mother yet this curtesy from thee (her sonne) extort </l>
            <l>That some small tyme of trusty truce thou wilt with willing mynd </l>
            <l>Consent vnto: til I my Sonne thy Brother most vnkind </l>
            <l>May after flight goe kisse end oel, now first or last of all. </l>
            <l>Whyle I for peace entreaty make, you men vnarmd I call </l>
            <l>To listen vnto that I say: thy Brother feareth thee: </l>
            <l>And thou fearst him: and I feare both. But this my feare you see </l>
            <l>Is nothing for my selfe at all, but for th'auayle of both. </l>
            <l>Why seemest thou thy naked sword to put in sheath so loth? </l>
            <l>Be glad to take the benefyte of any litle stay: </l>
            <l>In matters lewde tis wysedome good to stand vpon delay. </l>
            <l>You enter into such a warre, wherein he speedeth best </l>
            <l>That vanquisht is: both of you feare to be by fraud distrest </l>
            <l>Through practisd meanes and subtil plois of Brothers spitefull drift, </l>
            <l>Or ouerteacht by pollicy of some deuysed shift. </l>
            <l>But if deceiue or be deceyu'd by him that is our Frend </l>
            <l>Wee needes must be: in such a case wee shall the lesse offend </l>
            <l>In suffring wrong then doyng harme: But feare thou not a whit, </l>
            <l>You both from ambusht treacheryes your Mother wil acquit. </l>
            <l>What say you Sonnes: shall this request of myne with you preuayle. </l>
            <l>Or shall I curse my luckelesse fate, and on my Fortune rayle. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000249-056-a"/>
            <l>And iudge your Sire an happy man, in that he liueth blinde </l>
            <l>And cannot see the thing which I beholde with pensiue minde? </l>
            <l>In comming vnto you, did I bring with mee this intent, </l>
            <l>To ende these broyles? or did I come to see some dyre euent? </l>
            <l>Etheocles, some what appeasde, hath pitcht his Speare in ground, </l>
            <l>And not a weapon bloud to sheel, in hand of his is found. </l>
            <l>Now Polynices, vnto thee my former suite I bring, </l>
            <l>Regard thy Mothers mournefull plight, and yeelde vnto the thing </l>
            <l>That shee with teares entreates to haue. O Sonne, at length I see, </l>
            <l>I hold with hands, I kisse with mouth, I touch with ioyfull glee </l>
            <l>This Face of thyne, the sight whereof I wanted haue so longe: </l>
            <l>And haue more often wished for, then can bee tolde with tonge. </l>
            <l>Thou hast from natiue Soyle bene chasde to Coaste of forraigne king, </l>
            <l>And crossed bene with trouncing force of frowning Fortunes sting. </l>
            <l>Thou many a Storme, and many a brunt in many a foming Sea, </l>
            <l>In Wandring sort and banisht guise, didst oftentimes assay. </l>
            <l>Thy Mother at thy Spousall feast was absent farre away, </l>
            <l>And could not doe such nuptiall Rytes as tell for such a day. </l>
            <l>Into thy wedding Chamber shee brought thee, ne yet thy Bryde, </l>
            <l>Ne yet in solemne sorte the house with herbes and odours plide: </l>
            <l>Ne yet did with a Ryband white the wedding Torches tye, </l>
            <l>As vse and custome willes to bee at such solemynitie. </l>
            <l>Adrastus, Father to thy Wife, and father in lawe to thee, </l>
            <l>With Daughter his, hath not defraide much store of golde or Fee. </l>
            <l>No Dower hath he bestowde on her, her wealth was very small, </l>
            <l>Of Citties, Landes, and Reuenewes hee gaue her none at all. </l>
            <l>Warre, Warre: is it thou onely hadst, by taking her to Wyfe: </l>
            <l>In lew of other gyfts, hee helpes to kindle all this Stryfe. </l>
            <l>Thou Sonne in lawe arte vnto him, that is our Countreyes Foe: </l>
            <l>Thy Natiue soyle thou leauest, and to forraigne Courts dost goe. </l>
            <l>Thou feedest now at Straungers boarde, and makest more accoumpt </l>
            <l>Of new acquaintaunce got abroade; as though it did surmount </l>
            <l>The friendship of thy countrey heere: thou art a banisht wight, </l>
            <l>And liu'st in exile, for no fault, but through thy brothers spight. </l>
            <l>In thee appeares resemblaunce playne of all thy Fathers Fate, </l>
            <l>In which there lacketh not so much as thoyse of wedded Mate. </l>
            <l>Whom with as ill mischaunce and hap as euer Fathers was, </l>
            <l>Thou haste in lucklesse houre and time of mariage brought to passe. </l>
            <l>O Sonne, thy mothers onely hope, for whom such care I take: </l>
            <l>Whose sight, now after many yeares, doth mee most ioyfull make. </l>
            <pb n="52" xml:id="ep000249-056-b"/>
            <l>For whom I haue full many a time to Gods deuoutly praide: </l>
            <l>Whereas in deede, thy new retourne to mee, may well bee saide </l>
            <l>To take away as great a ioye, and bring as great a griefe, </l>
            <l>As it to these myne aged yeares is comfort and reliefe. </l>
            <l>I prostrate at the Oracle, besought Apollos Grace </l>
            <l>To tell mee, when I should not neede to further feare thy case. </l>
            <l>Who flowting this my fond demaund, anone did flatly tell, </l>
            <l>And spake these words, which yet (I trow) I doe remember well. </l>
            <l>Thou fearst thy son, least harme he take, as is a mothers guise: </l>
            <l>But thou I say more cause shalt haue, to feare him otherwise. </l>
            <l>For if this warre vnraisde had bene I should thy presence lacke: </l>
            <l>And if thou wert not, Thebane Land might free remayne from Sacke. </l>
            <l>The sight of the doth cost vs all a hard and nipping price, </l>
            <l>Yet doth it like thy mother well: so that her sound aduice </l>
            <l>In this one thing thou follow will. Dispatch these Armies hence: </l>
            <l>Euen presently, whyle yet of bloud there hath not bene expence. </l>
            <l>So foule a Fact to bee so neere, is haynous out of doubt: </l>
            <l>I shake, I quake to thinke thereon, in euery Ioynt throughout. </l>
            <l>My hayre stands vpright euen for feare, two brethren thus to see </l>
            <l>Aloofe, and ready one to chop at th'other, cruelly. </l>
            <l>How neere was I (poore Mother theirs, a bloudier act t'haue seene.) </l>
            <l>Then father blind yet euer saw, or euer yet would weene? </l>
            <l>And though my feare be ouerpast and th'act vnbrought to passe: </l>
            <l>My selfe yet doe I wretched thincke, that done so neere it was. </l>
            <l>By all the throwes for tenne months space, in wombe when I thee bare, </l>
            <l>And for thy Sisters sake both twaine, which shine in vertue rare: </l>
            <l>And by those Eyehoales of thy Syre, for which with wrekefull Pawe </l>
            <l>Hee pulld his Eyes, because (vnwares) hee stained Natures lawe, </l>
            <l>I thee beseech from Thebane Walles sent backe these armed Bandes, </l>
            <l>Which threatning all our throates to cut, against our Countrey stands: </l>
            <l>Yea though you presently depart: yet are you much to blame, </l>
            <l>And there is due vnto you both, a lot of during shame: </l>
            <l>Because this Countrey round about hath pestred bene with powre, </l>
            <l>And troupes of Souldiours stout and braue, it ready to deuowre. </l>
            <l>With pensiue hearts a mourning minds, these Eyes of ours haue seene </l>
            <l>Your prauncing couriers with their Feete, spoile Theban Medowes greene. </l>
            <l>Wee oft haue seene your houlty Peeres in warlike Chariot ride: </l>
            <l>And oft our houses to haue brunt with wildfier haue bene spide. </l>
            <l>And last of all. An act wee sawe (which euen to Thebes is straung.) </l>
            <l>Two Brethren warring mortally, all Natures bondes to chaung. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000249-057-a"/>
            <l>Ech one in th'Army sawe this sight, the people witnesse bee. </l>
            <l>Your Systers two, and Mother I this all did plainly see. </l>
            <l>Your Father, hee may thanke himselfe: that he did not behold </l>
            <l>This lamentable spectacle and hauockes manifold. </l>
            <l>Call now to thy remembraunce heere, thy Father OEdipus, </l>
            <l>Whose doome, did Facts (by errour done) euen plague, &amp; punishe thus. </l>
            <l>With Fyre, &amp; sword subuert not cleane (good Sonne) thy countrey deare, </l>
            <l>And Thebes whereof thou wouldst be king) surcease with force to teare. </l>
            <l>What Bedlem pang enchaunts thy mind? what might thy meaning bee? </l>
            <l>Thou claymst a Realme, which to subuert thou geeuest lycence free. </l>
            <l>In seeking thus a countryes rule: a countrey thou destroyest: </l>
            <l>Which thou thine own would make, thou marr'st, &amp; (as twere none) annoyest. </l>
            <l>Heereby thou hindrest much thy selfe, in that thou makest spoyle, </l>
            <l>And burnest vp both Corne and Grasse, and keep'st a shamefull coyle, </l>
            <l>In chasting men out of their homes: (O desprate witlesse parte) </l>
            <l>What man aliue, to waste his owne, can thus find in his harte? </l>
            <l>These thinges that thou commaundest thus by rage of sword &amp; flame </l>
            <l>To bee consum'de: an other man thou thinkst doth owe the same. </l>
            <l>If thus for princely Chayre you twayne by th'Eares your title try: </l>
            <l>The state of Realme and Commonwealth will totter soone awry. </l>
            <l>Seeke it, while yet your Countrey standes vnblemisht by decay: </l>
            <l>It so t'enioy, and so to raigne, I coumpt the better way. </l>
            <l>Ah, canst thou finde in heart to burne, and spoyle these houses braue? </l>
            <l>The lyke whereof in all the worlde besides, thou canst not haue: </l>
            <l>Canst thou destroy and ruinate the noble Thebane wall, </l>
            <l>To whose first building stones apace at Dan Amphions call </l>
            <l>Came dauncing of their owne accord, through tunes of warbling harpe: </l>
            <l>And coucht themselues in order right vpon the Turrets sharpe, </l>
            <l>Without all helpe of worckmans hand, or Pully vp to draw </l>
            <l>Such pieces as most waighty were? Wilt thou by lawlesse law </l>
            <l>Throw downe these worthy Monuments? wilt thou from hence conuay </l>
            <l>And cary with thee all these spoyles? wilt thou such pageaunts play? </l>
            <l>Thy Fathers old acquainted mates, wilt thou by force surpryze </l>
            <l>And leade as captiue where thou goest in proude triumphing wise? </l>
            <l>Shall these thy cutthroate Souldiors dragge and hale the mothers old? </l>
            <l>Shal they, graund Matrons tied in chaines, from husbands armes vnfold? </l>
            <l>Shall Thebane Maydes, &amp; Damselles chaste of freshe and lusty Age, </l>
            <l>Bee mingled with the raskal rout, and hamperd bee in Cage? </l>
            <l>Shall they as presents, forced bee in dabbling dirt to toyle </l>
            <l>Vnto the mynsing Mistresses, and Trulles of Argoa Soyle? </l>
            <pb n="53" xml:id="ep000249-057-b"/>
            <l>Shall I thy seely Mother trudge with Pinyond hands behinde? </l>
            <l>Shall I this triumph of my Chiled to furnish bee assignde? </l>
            <l>Canst thou with grudgelesse minde, behold thy Countreyfolkes arow, </l>
            <l>Slayne, mangled, spoylde, in peeces hewen, thus to their deathes to got? </l>
            <l>Canst thou bring in a deadly Foe, thy Countrey to subdue? </l>
            <l>Shall streates of Thebes runne all with bloud? shall all the Countrey rue </l>
            <l>Thy comming home with flame and fyre? hast thou an heart so hard? </l>
            <l>A breast so tipt with flint? a mynde to rage so well preparde? </l>
            <l>If thus thou fare, and swell with yre whiles yet thou art no King: </l>
            <l>What wilt thou bee in Princely throne, if thou shouldst win the Ring? </l>
            <l>Surceasse therefore and qualifie this outrage of thy mynde: </l>
            <l>In thee let all thy Countrey, grace and Princely myldnes finde. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e109720">
            <speaker>POL. </speaker>
            <l>Would you me haue, my selfe so much to loyall duties yeeld, </l>
            <l>As that I should a Pylgrims life like wandring Beast in field </l>
            <l>Skud vp and downe from place to place, without both house &amp; home, </l>
            <l>And fleeing natiue soyle, bee forst in forraigne Landes to roame? </l>
            <l>What other plagues, could you award in iustice vnto mee, </l>
            <l>If I my fayth or sacred Oath had broken caytifly? </l>
            <l>Shall I beare all the punishment for that vile villains guile? </l>
            <l>And shall hee false deceiptfull wretch at my misfortunes smyle? </l>
            <l>Shall hee in wealth still flaunt it out, and keepe this iolly coyle? </l>
            <l>Shall hee for sinnes rewarded bee? and I still put to foyle? </l>
            <l>Well, well, goe to, bee as bee may: you bid mee wander hence: </l>
            <l>I am content: your hard decree t'obay is my pretence. </l>
            <l>But tell mee whyther shall I goe? Assigne mee to some place: </l>
            <l>Bylike, you would that brother myne should still with shamelesse face </l>
            <l>Possesse my stately Pallaces, and reuell in his ruffe, </l>
            <l>And I thereat to holde my peace, and not a whit to snuffe, </l>
            <l>But like a Countrey Mome to dwell in some poore thatched Cot: </l>
            <l>Allow mee poore Exyle such one: I rest content, God wot. </l>
            <l>You know, such Noddyes as I am, are woont to make exchaung </l>
            <l>Of Kingdomes, for poore thatched Cots, bee like this is not straung. </l>
            <l>Yea more: I, matcht now to a Wyfe of noble ligne and race </l>
            <l>Shall like a seely Dottipoll liue there in seruile case, </l>
            <l>At becke and checke of queenely Wyfe, and like a kitchin drudge </l>
            <l>Shall at Adrastus lordly heeles, (my Wyues owne Father) trudge. </l>
            <l>From Princely Port to tumble downe into poore seruile state, </l>
            <l>Is greatest griefe that may betyde by doome of frouncing fate. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e109990">
            <speaker>IOC. </speaker>
            <l>If that thou gape so greedely a Kingly Crowne to weare: </l>
            <l>And that thou canst not rest content, till thou a Scepter beare: </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000249-058-a"/>
            <l>Behold ech quarter of the world affoordeth Kingdomes store. </l>
            <l>No doubt thou mayst winne some of them, if that thou seke therfore. </l>
            <l>On one syde here, lies Tmolus mount, a soyle bethwact with Vines: </l>
            <l>There runnes Pactolus noble streame with golden Send and mynes. </l>
            <l>On that syde crookt Maeander glydes through midst of Phrygia fieldes: </l>
            <l>On this syde Hebrus swift of course much fruict to Thracia yeldes. </l>
            <l>Nere thereunto lies Gargarus, renoumd each where for Corne, </l>
            <l>And Troian Xanthus swelling floud, that pricke and price hath borne. </l>
            <l>There Sestos and Abidus stand in mouth of Ionian Sea, </l>
            <l>Which now is called Hellespont: and here an other waye </l>
            <l>Are countreys, which more Eastward lye. There Lycia full of Creekes </l>
            <l>And Hauens strong is situate: these kingdomes, he that seekes, </l>
            <l>Is like to winne: these would I haue thee conquere with thy Sword: </l>
            <l>These, these to winne let King Adrast to thee his ayd affoorde. </l>
            <l>In some of these, let him thee make a King: in Thebes as yit, </l>
            <l>Suppose thy father Oedipus in seat of King to sit. </l>
            <l>Thy banishment much better is to thee, then this returne, </l>
            <l>Sith all thy drift is cruelly to wast, to spoyle, and burne. </l>
            <l>Thy banishment reputed is to grow through others crime: </l>
            <l>This thy retourne, in such a sort to Kingly state to clyme, </l>
            <l>Is ill and faulty euery way: with this thy warlicke crue </l>
            <l>Thou shalt do better Realms to seeke, where bloudy guilt ne grue. </l>
            <l>Yea, this thy Brother, whom thou dost pursue with deadly hate </l>
            <l>Whose life, whose health, whose house thou dost with curses dire rahate </l>
            <l>Wil ayde thee with all powre he canne: himselfe will also goe </l>
            <l>And serue in field for thyne auayle, gaynst him that is thy foe. </l>
            <l>Aduaunce thy powre, march boldly forth to take this warre in hand. </l>
            <l>Wherein thy parentes wish thee good, and wil thy helpers stand. </l>
            <l>A Kingdome got mischieuously, and snatcht with grudge of mynd, </l>
            <l>More greeuous is then exiles al, of what soeuer kind. </l>
            <l>Of warre, the doubtful hazardes all set downe before thy syght, </l>
            <l>And throughly waigh thuncertayne chaunce, that longes to martial fight. </l>
            <l>Though al the power of Grece thou bring thy quarel to mayntayne, </l>
            <l>And though great armed multitudes of Souldiours thou remayne: </l>
            <l>Yet chaunce of warre stil doubtful hanges, and hard it is to know, </l>
            <l>Who cary shal the victory, thou or thy vowed foe. </l>
            <l>Mars to no party tyed in: what he decrees, shal be, </l>
            <l>As chaunce allots, so falles it out: this dome abydeth free. </l>
            <l>Sword, hope and feare makes equall those, betwene whom otherwyse </l>
            <l>Great oddes there is: blynd Fortunes lot the case betweene them tryes. </l>
            <pb n="54" xml:id="ep000249-058-b"/>
            <l>Thy rash attempt with cryme begonne, gropes after doubtful gayne: </l>
            <l>And fond deuyses enterprisd oft reape deserued payne. </l>
            <l>Admit that all the Gods in heauen did further thy request, </l>
            <l>And to promote thy hoat desyre both willing were, and prest: </l>
            <l>Yet al thy frendes are fled away, and al recoyled backe, </l>
            <l>And Souldiours here and there in Fieldes are come to deadly wracke. </l>
            <l>Although thou ioy hereat receyue, although the spoyles thou take </l>
            <l>Of vanquisht Brother, yet the palme of victory must slake, </l>
            <l>And not to thee be geuen whole. What kind of warre (alas) </l>
            <l>Is this, thinkst thou? ist not more straunge then euer any was? </l>
            <l>Wherin if he that victor is, ioy therein any whyt, </l>
            <l>Most execrable wickednes he (doubtles) doth commit. </l>
            <l>This Brother thyne, whom now so faine thou wouldst bereaue of breath, </l>
            <l>I wis, if he were once dispatcht, thou wouldst bewale his death. </l>
            <l>And therfore make no more adoe, but ceasse from wicked bral, </l>
            <l>Ridde countrey out of trembling feare, and parentes dole forestal. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e110580">
            <speaker>Poly. </speaker>
            <l>What, shal my Brother for this vyle and shamefull breach of pacie </l>
            <l>Goe skotfree thus? shal he receyue no guerdon for his fact? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e110610">
            <speaker>Ioc. </speaker>
            <l>Feare not my Sonne, he shall be payd, and payd agayne, I trow: </l>
            <l>He shalbe King and raygne in Thebes, his payne shal euen be so. </l>
            <l>A payne in grayne I warrant him. And if thou doubtful be, </l>
            <l>Let Graundsyre Laius and thy Syre examples be to thee. </l>
            <l>Sir Cadmus wil the same display, and Cadmus ofspring all </l>
            <l>Can witnes be that none in Thebes yet raygnd without a fall. </l>
            <l>None yet the Theban Scepter swayd, that hath not felt the whippe. </l>
            <l>And promise breach made most of them from regall Crowne to skippe. </l>
            <l>Now if thou wilte, thou mayst insert within this bedroll heere </l>
            <l>Thy Brother. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e110720">
            <speaker>POLY. </speaker>
            <l>Mary, that I wil, in shame hath he no peere. </l>
            <l>And vnto mee it seemes a world of blisse to bee a king </l>
            <l>And dye with Kings. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e110760">
            <speaker>POC. </speaker>
            <l>Thy case doth thee in rank of exiles bring. </l>
            <l>Raygne Kinge, but yet a loathed wight vnto thy Subiectes all. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e110790">
            <speaker>POLY. </speaker>
            <l>For that I neyther recke ne care what shall to me befall. </l>
            <l>That Prince that feares disdaynful hate, vnwilling seemes to raynge. </l>
            <l>The God that swayes the Golden Globe, together hath these twayne </l>
            <l>Conioynd and coupled Hate and Rule: and him do I suppose </l>
            <l>To be a noble King indeede, that can supplant his foes, </l>
            <l>And Subiectes cancred hate suppresse. A King is often stayed </l>
            <l>From doyng many thinges he would, when Subiectes loue is wayed. </l>
            <l>But vnto them that do repyne to se him sit aloft, </l>
            <l>He may more rigour boldly shew, and pare their pates more oft. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000249-059-a"/>
            <l>He that will loue of Subiectes winne, with Elemency must raygne: </l>
            <l>A King that's hated, cannot long in Kingly seate remayne. </l>
            <l>For Kingdomes Kinges can best describe, what preceptes needfull are. </l>
            <l>Mell thou in cases of Exile: for Kingdomes take no care. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000249-A11909" xml:id="ep000249-e110930">
            <speaker>Pol. </speaker>
            <l>To be a King, I would engage to force of flaming Fire, </l>
            <l>Both Countrey, house, land, Wyfe, and Chyld, to compasse my desyre. </l>
            <l>No Fee, to purchase Princely seate, ne labour coumpt I lost: </l>
            <l>A Kingly Crowne is neuer deare, what euer price it cost. </l>
          </sp>
          <closer>
            <signed>Thomas Newtonus, Cestreshyrius. </signed>
          </closer>
          <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back></back>
  </text>
</TEI>
