<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000247" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Hercules Furens</title>
        <author>
<!--Seneca, Lucius Annaeus-->
          <persName>
            <forename>Lucius Annaeus</forename>
            <surname>Seneca</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A11909_01.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="A11909-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull n="TCP source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">Seneca his tenne tragedies, translated into Englysh.</title>
                <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus, ca. 4 B.C.-65 A.D.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>225 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
                <date>2007 October (TCP phase 1)</date>
                <idno type="marc">99852323</idno>
                <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 22221.</idno>
                <idno type="stc">Greg, III, p. 1105-6.</idno>
                <idno type="vid">17639</idno>
                <idno type="DLPS">A11909</idno>
                <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2248540344</idno>
                <availability>
                  <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
                </availability>
              </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
            <biblFull n="printed source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">Seneca his tenne tragedies, translated into Englysh.</title>
                <title type="alt">Tragedies. English</title>
                <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus, ca. 4 B.C.-65 A.D.</author>
                <author>Heywood, Jasper, 1535-1598,</author>
                <author>Neville, Alexander, 1544-1614,</author>
                <author>Studley, John, 1545?-1590?,</author>
                <author>T. N. d. 1617,</author>
                <author>Newton, Thomas, 1542?-1607.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[4], 65, 64-217, [1] leaves.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>In Fleetstreete neere vnto Saincte Dunstans church by Thomas Marsh,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication_date">1581.</date>
                <date type="creation_date">1561</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>
                  <p>Editor's dedication signed: Thomas Newton.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>In verse.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>A reprinting of the following translations previously published separately: "Hercules furens", "Thyestes", and "Troas" by Jasper Heywood; "¦edipus" by Alexander Neville (a revised version); "Medea" and "Agamemnon" by John Studley; and "Octavia" (not by Seneca) by Thomas Nuce. Prints for the first time "Hippolytus" and "Hercules Oetæus" translated by Studley, and "Thebais" translated by Thomas Newton.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A"; the last leaf is blank.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
                </note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
      <profileDesc>
        <particDesc>
          <listPerson>
            <person xml:id="ep000247-ep000247">
              <persName>A11909</persName>
            </person>
          </listPerson>
        </particDesc>
        <textClass>
          <classCode scheme="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q80930</classCode>
        </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1561">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1" type="tragedy" xml:id="ep000247-e100030">
        <pb n="1" xml:id="ep000247-004-a"/>
        <argument>
          <head>The Argument of this Tragedy. </head>
          <p>IVno the Wyfe and sister of Iupiter, hating his bastard broode, cometh downe from heauen, complayning of all his iniuries done to her, deuising also by what despight she may vexe his base Sonne Hercules. And hauing by experience proued, no toyles to be to hard for him, findeth the meanes to make his owne hand his owne vengeance. Hercules therefore returning now from Hell (from whence he was enioyned to fet Cerberus) and finding that the Tyrant Lycus had inuaded his countrey, destroieth the tyrant. For the which victory as hee sacrificeth to his Goddesse, wrathfull Iuno strikes him into a sodayne frensy: Wherewith he beinge sore vexed, thynking to slea the Children and Wyfe of Lycus, in steede of them, killeth his owne Wyfe and Children in his madnes. This done hee sleapeth. Iuno restoreth to him agayne his Wits. He being wakt, seing his Wyfe and Children slayne by his owne hand, at last also would kill himselfe. </p>
        </argument>
        <list>
          <head>THE SPEAKERS </head>
          <item>Iuno. </item>
          <item>Chorus. </item>
          <item>Megara. </item>
          <item>Amphitrion. </item>
          <item>Lycus. </item>
          <item>Hercules. </item>
          <item>Theseus. </item>
        </list>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="ep000247-e100140">
          <head>THE FIRST ACTE. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000247-e100150">Iuno alone. </stage>
          <l>I Syster of the Thunderer, </l>
          <l>(for now that name alone </l>
          <l>Remaynes to me) Ioue euermore </l>
          <l>as though deuorst and gone, </l>
          <l>And temples of the highest ayre </l>
          <l>as wydowe shunned haue, </l>
          <l>And beaten out of skyes aboue </l>
          <l>the place to Harlots gaue. </l>
          <l>I must go dwell beneath on ground, for Whoores do hold the sky. </l>
          <l>From hence the Beare in parte aboue of ycy peale full hy, </l>
          <l>A haughty starre the greekish shyps by Seas doth gurde about: </l>
          <l>From this way, whence at spring time warme the day is loased out, </l>
          <l>Europaes bearer through the waues of Tyria shynes full bright. </l>
          <l>From thence, their stormy fearefull flocke to Ships, and seas affright, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000247-005-a"/>
          <l>The wandring daughters here and there of Atlas vpward sway. </l>
          <l>With staring bush of hayre from hens Orion Gods doth fray: </l>
          <l>And Perseus eke his glitteryng starres of golden glosse hath here. </l>
          <l>From hence the twynnes of Tyndars stocke do shine, a signe full clere: </l>
          <l>And at whose byrth first stode the grounde that erst went to and fro. </l>
          <l>Nor onely Bacchus now himselfe, or Bacchus mother lo, </l>
          <l>Haue clymd to Gods: least any parte should from rebuke be free, </l>
          <l>The skies the Gnossian strumpets crownes do beare in spight of mee. </l>
          <l>But I of old contemptes complayne: me, one dire, fierce, and shrewde </l>
          <l>Thebana land with wicked broode of Ioues base daughters strewde, </l>
          <l>How oft hath it a stepdame made? though vp to heauen should ryse, </l>
          <l>The conqueryng drabbe Alcmena now, and hold my place in skyes, </l>
          <l>And eke her sonne to promisd starres obtayne the worthy way, </l>
          <l>At byrth of whom the staying worlde so long deferd the day, </l>
          <l>And Phoebus slow frome morning sea began to glister bright, </l>
          <l>Commaunded long in th' Ocean waues to hyde his drowned lyght. </l>
          <l>Yet shall my hates not leaue them so, a wrathful kindled rage </l>
          <l>His mynd in madnes shall stirre vp, and yre that may not swage </l>
          <l>Shall euermore (all peace layd downe) wage warres eternally. </l>
          <l>What warres? what euer hideous thinge the earth his ennemy </l>
          <l>Begets, or what soeuer sea or ayre hath brought to syght </l>
          <l>Both dredfull, dire, and pestilent, of cruel fiercest might, </l>
          <l>T'is tierd and tam'd: he passeth all, and name by ills doth rayse, </l>
          <l>And all my wrath he doth inioy, and to his greater prayse </l>
          <l>He turnes my hates: whyle tedious toyles to much I him behest, </l>
          <l>He proues what father him begot: both thence where light opprest </l>
          <l>Hath sea, and where it showde agayne, where Titan day doth trayne, </l>
          <l>And with his brand approaching nere doth dye those Aethiops twaine, </l>
          <l>His strengh vntamde is honoured: and God eche where is hee </l>
          <l>Now calde in worlde, and now more store of monsters want to mee, </l>
          <l>And laboure lesse to Hercles is t'acomplish all my will, </l>
          <l>Then me to bydde: at ease he doth myne imperies fulfyl. </l>
          <l>What cruel hestes of tyrante now so fyerce a yong man may </l>
          <l>Preuayle to hurt? for lo he beares for weapons now awaye </l>
          <l>What once he fearde, and put to flight: he armed comes at syde </l>
          <l>With Lyon fyerce and Hydra both: nor land suffiseth wyde, </l>
          <l>But broake he hath the threshold loe of that infernall Ioue. </l>
          <l>And spoyls with him of conquerd king he drawes to Gods aboue. </l>
          <l>But that's but light, broke is the league of sprites that there do dwell. </l>
          <l>I saw my selfe, I saw him lo (the night now gone, of hell </l>
          <pb n="2" xml:id="ep000247-005-b"/>
          <l>And Ditis tamde) throw out abroade before his fathers sight </l>
          <l>His brothers spoyles. Why drawes he not opprest and bound by might </l>
          <l>Hymselfe in chaynes that equall thynges to Ioue by lot doth hold? </l>
          <l>And beare the rule of captiue hel, and way to Styxe vnfolde? </l>
          <l>Vp opened is from lowest ghostes the backward way to skye, </l>
          <l>And sacred secrets of dire death in open sight do lye. </l>
          <l>But he (the dredful den of sprites brake vp ful fierce and stout </l>
          <l>Euen ouer mee doth tryumph lo, and with proude hand about </l>
          <l>The foule blacke dogge by Grekish townes he leades from hel away. </l>
          <l>When seene was vgly Cerberus I saw the fading day, </l>
          <l>And fearefull sunne: euen me lykewyse a trembling dread opprest, </l>
          <l>And looking on the fylthy neckes of conquerd monstruous beast, </l>
          <l>I feared much myne owne behestes: but light things I complayne, </l>
          <l>For heauen I may be frayde, lest he may get the highest rayne, </l>
          <l>That lowest wonne, the sceptors from his father wil he take, </l>
          <l>Nor hee to starres (as Bacchus dyd) his way wil gently make: </l>
          <l>The way with ruine will he seeke, and hee in empty skyes </l>
          <l>Wil reygne alone with force displayd hys haughty hart doth ryse, </l>
          <l>And he that heauen it selfe by force of his might gotted bee, </l>
          <l>It bearyng learnd: quite vnderneth the world his head set hee. </l>
          <l>Nor once his shoulders bowde the prayse of suth a mighty mas: </l>
          <l>And midst of heauen on Hercles necke alone (loe) setled was. </l>
          <l>His necke vnwryde the starres aboue and skyes did only stay: </l>
          <l>And me likewyse oppressyng him, to Gods he seekes the way. </l>
          <l>Goe ire, goe on, and beate hym downe that great things doth inuent </l>
          <l>Match thou with him, and with thy handes now thou thy selfe him rent. </l>
          <l>Such hates why dost thou meditate? let all wyld beastes now go: </l>
          <l>And weary Euristheus now be free from geeuing charges mo. </l>
          <l>The Tytans daryng once of Ioue to breake the impery </l>
          <l>Send out: let loase the denne abroade of mount of Sicilye. </l>
          <l>The Doricke land that with the turne of gyant quakes afrayd, </l>
          <l>Let it bring forth the dredful neckes of monster vnder layd. </l>
          <l>Let yet the haughty moone about some other beastes beget, </l>
          <l>But these he ouercame. Seekes thou a match t'alcides yet? </l>
          <l>Ther's none, except hymselfe: let him agaynst himselfe rebell. </l>
          <l>Let present be from bottome deepe vpraysd of lowest hell </l>
          <l>Th'Eumenides, let flaming lockes of theyrs the fires out flinge, </l>
          <l>And furious hands bestowe aboute the stroakes of vipers sting. </l>
          <l>Go now ful prowde, and scale the skyes to seates of gods make waye. </l>
          <l>Now must thy battels wages be ful cleere loe shynes the daye. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000247-006-a"/>
          <l>Despyse mans workes thinkst thou fierce wight that hell and soules alow </l>
          <l>Thou hast escapt? nay here I wil another hel thee show. </l>
          <l>In deepe miste hid I wil call vp from bottome low of hell </l>
          <l>Beyond the wayes of gylty ghostes debateful goddesse fell. </l>
          <l>Wheras the roaring dreadful den resoundes with cryes about. </l>
          <l>From depest bond of Ditis raygne beneath I wil fet out, </l>
          <l>What so is left. Let hateful hurt now come in anger wood, </l>
          <l>And fierce impyety imbrew himselfe with his owne bloud. </l>
          <l>And errour eke, and fury arm'd agaynst it selfe to fight. </l>
          <l>This meane, this meane, let wrath of myne now vse to shewe my might. </l>
          <l>Beginne ye seruantes now of hell: the feruent burning tree </l>
          <l>Of Pyne shake vp: and set with snakes her dreadful flocke to see. </l>
          <l>Let now Megaera bring to sight, and with her mournful brand. </l>
          <l>For burning rage bring out of hell a huge and direful brand. </l>
          <l>Do this, require you vengeance due, and paynes of hel his spoyle, </l>
          <l>Strike through his breast, let fyercer flame, within his bosome boyle. </l>
          <l>Then which in Aetna fornace beates, so furiously to see. </l>
          <l>That mad of mind and witles may Alcides driuen bee </l>
          <l>With fury great through pearced quight, my selfe must first of all </l>
          <l>Be mad. Wherfore doth Iuuo yet not into raging fall? </l>
          <l>Mee, me, ye Furyes, systers three throwne quite out of my wit </l>
          <l>Tosse fyrst, if any thing to do, I do endeuour yet </l>
          <l>For stepdame meete: let now my hates be turnd another way, </l>
          <l>Let him (returnd) his babes behold in safety I you pray. </l>
          <l>And strong of hand come home, I haue now found the day at length. </l>
          <l>In which may greatly mee auayle the hated Hercles strength. </l>
          <l>Both mee and eke hym selfe let him subdue and wish to die </l>
          <l>Returnd from hel, yea let it here be my commodity, </l>
          <l>That he of Ioue begotten is: here present wil I stand, </l>
          <l>And that his shaftes goe streyght from how, I wil direct his hand, </l>
          <l>The mad mans weapons will I guide, euen Hercles fyghtyng, lo, </l>
          <l>At length Ile ayde. This gylt once done then leefull is that so </l>
          <l>His father may admit to saies those gylty haades of his </l>
          <pb n="3" xml:id="ep000247-006-b"/>
          <stage xml:id="ep000247-e101430">Chorus. </stage>
          <l>THe fading starres now shyne but seelde in sighte </l>
          <l>In stipye skye, night ouercome with day </l>
          <l>Plucks in her. fyres, while spronge agayne is light. </l>
          <l>The day starre drawes the cleresome beames theire waye. </l>
          <l>They cye signe of haughtye poale agayne, </l>
          <l>With seuen starres markt, the Beares of Arcadye, </l>
          <l>Do call the light with ouerturned wayne. </l>
          <l>With marble horse now drawne, hys waye to hye </l>
          <l>Doth Titan toppe of Oetha ouer spred </l>
          <l>The bushes bright that nowe with berryes bee </l>
          <l>Of Thebes strewde, by daye do blushe full redde. </l>
          <l>And to returne doth Phabus syster flee. </l>
          <l>Now labor harde beginnes, and euerye kynde </l>
          <l>Of cares it styrres, the Shepehearde doth vnfolde: </l>
          <l>His flockes vnpende, do grase their foode to fynde, </l>
          <l>And nippes the grasse with hoary frost full colde. </l>
          <l>At will doth play in open medow faire </l>
          <l>The Calfe whose brow did damme yet neuer teare, </l>
          <l>The empty Kyne their vdders doe repayre. </l>
          <l>And lyght with course vncertayne here and there, </l>
          <l>In grasse full soft the wanton kidde hee flynges. </l>
          <l>In toppe of boughe doth sitte with chaunting songe, </l>
          <l>And to the Sunne newe rose to spreade her wynges, </l>
          <l>Bestirres her selfe her mourneful nestes amonge </l>
          <l>The Nightingall. and doth with byrdes aboute </l>
          <l>Confuse resound with murmure mixedryfe </l>
          <l>To witnes day; his sayles to wynde set out </l>
          <l>The shypman doth committe in doubt of lyfe. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000247-007-a"/>
          <l>Whyle gale oswynde the slacke sayles filles full strayte, </l>
          <l>He leaning ouer hollow rocke doth lye, </l>
          <l>And either his begiled hookes doth bayte, </l>
          <l>Or els beholdes and feeles the pray from hye with paised hand. </l>
          <l>The trembling fish he feeles with line extent. </l>
          <l>This hope to them to whom of hurtles lyfe. </l>
          <l>Is quiet rest, and with his owne content, </l>
          <l>And lytle, house, such hope in fieldes is ryfe </l>
          <l>The troblous hopes with rolling whirlewynd great, </l>
          <l>And dredful feares their wayes in cityes keepe. </l>
          <l>He proude repayre to prince in regall seate, </l>
          <l>And hard court gates without the rest of sleepe </l>
          <l>Esteemes, and endles happynes to hold </l>
          <l>Doth gather goods, for treasure gaping more, </l>
          <l>And is ful pore amid his heaped gold. </l>
          <l>The peoples fauour him (astonied sore) </l>
          <l>And commons more vnconstant then the sea, </l>
          <l>With blast of vayne renoume liftes vp full proude. </l>
          <l>He selling at the brawling barre his plea, </l>
          <l>Full wicked, sets his yres and scoulding loud </l>
          <l>And woordes to sale, a fewe hath knowne of all </l>
          <l>The careles rest, who mindfull how doth flitte </l>
          <l>Swift age away, the tyme that neuer shall </l>
          <l>Returne agayne do holde: while fares permitte, </l>
          <l>At quiet liue: the lyfe full quickly glydes </l>
          <l>With hastned course, and with the winged day </l>
          <l>The wheele is turnde of yere that hedlong slides, </l>
          <l>The sisters hard perfourme their taskes alway, </l>
          <l>Nor may agayne vntwist the threede once sponne. </l>
          <l>Yet mankind loe vnsure what way to take </l>
          <pb n="4" xml:id="ep000247-007-b"/>
          <l>To meete the greedy destenyes doth ronne </l>
          <l>And willingly wee seke the Stigian lake. </l>
          <l>To much Alcides thou with stomacke stoute </l>
          <l>The sory sprites of hell dost hast to see. </l>
          <l>With course prefixt the fares are brought aboute </l>
          <l>To none once warnd to come may respite bee </l>
          <l>To none to passe their once appointed day, </l>
          <l>The tombe all people calde by death doth hyde </l>
          <l>Let glory him by many landes awaye </l>
          <l>Display, and fame throughout all cityes wyde </l>
          <l>Full babling praise, and euen with skye to stande </l>
          <l>Auaunce and starres: let him in chariot bright </l>
          <l>Ful haughty goe: let me my natiue land </l>
          <l>In safe and secrete house keepe close from sight. </l>
          <l>To restful men hoare age by course doth fall, </l>
          <l>And low in place, yet safe and sure doth lye, </l>
          <l>The poore and base estate of cottage small: </l>
          <l>The prowder pompe of minde doth fall from hye. </l>
          <l>But sad here comes with losed lockes of heare </l>
          <l>Loe Megara with litle company, </l>
          <l>And stowe by age drawes Hercles father neare </l>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="ep000247-e102230">
          <pb xml:id="ep000247-008-a"/>
          <head>THE SECOND ACTE. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000247-e102240">Megara. </stage>
          <l>O Guider great of heauen, &amp; of the world O Iudge full hie, </l>
          <l>Yet now at length apoinct a meane of carefull miserie. </l>
          <l>And ende of our calamitie. To mee yet neuer day </l>
          <l>Hath careles shin 'de: the ende of one affliction past away </l>
          <l>Beginning of an other is: an other ennemy </l>
          <l>Is forthwith founde, before that hee his ioyfull family </l>
          <l>Retourne vnto an other fyght hee taketh by behest: </l>
          <l>Nor any respite giuen is to him nor quiet rest: </l>
          <l>But whyle that he commaunded is: straight him pursueth shee </l>
          <l>The hatefull Iuno. Was yet once from toyle and labour free </l>
          <l>His infants age? the monsters (lo) he venquisht hath and slayne, </l>
          <l>Before he knew what monsters ment. The skaled serpents twayne </l>
          <l>Their double neckes drew on toward him, agaynst the which to ryse, </l>
          <l>The infant crept to meete with them, the serpents glittring eyes </l>
          <l>Lyke fyre, with quiet carelesse brest he looking last vpon, </l>
          <l>With countnance cleere, hard wrested knots of them he caught anon: </l>
          <l>And strangling then the swelling throates of them with tender hand, </l>
          <l>To Hydra prelude made. the beast so swyfte of Maenale land. </l>
          <l>That with much Golde bare vp full bright his beautified head, </l>
          <l>Is caught in course. of Nemey wood likewise the greatest dread </l>
          <l>The Lyon prest with Hercles armes hath roarde with dreadfull crie. </l>
          <l>What should I speake of stables dyre, of steedes of Bystonye? </l>
          <l>Or King cast out himselfe for foode his horses fierce to fill? </l>
          <l>And bristled beast in thicke tops woont of Erymanthus hill? </l>
          <l>The boare of Maenalye, the woods of Arcady to shake? </l>
          <l>And Bull that did no litle dread to hundred peoples make? </l>
          <l>Among the flocks of Hesper lande that hence farre distant bee, </l>
          <l>The sheepherde of Cartesian coast of triple shape to see </l>
          <l>Is slayne, and driuen is the pray from farthest parte of weast, </l>
          <l>Citheton quak't when by him past to sea the well knowne beast. </l>
          <l>He being bid to make by coastes of sommer sunne his way, </l>
          <l>And parched landes which sore with heate doth boyle the middell day, </l>
          <l>The mountaynes brake on either side and rampiers all vndoon, </l>
          <l>Euen vnto swyft and raging sea hath made a way to roon. </l>
          <pb n="5" xml:id="ep000247-008-b"/>
          <l>Then entring in of plenteaus wood, the pleasant gardeins gay, </l>
          <l>The waking dragons golden spoyles with him he brought away. </l>
          <l>The Lerna monsters numerous ill what neede to tell haue I? </l>
          <l>Hath he not him with fyre at length subdewde, and taught to dye? </l>
          <l>And which were woont with wings abrode to hyde the day from sight, </l>
          <l>Euen from the cloudes he sought &amp; braue the Stimphale birdes to flight. </l>
          <l>Not him subdewde who euer lyes in bed vnmacht at night </l>
          <l>The wyddowe queene of them that tooke to Thermodont their flight. </l>
          <l>Nor handes that well durst euterprise his noble trauayles all </l>
          <l>The filthy labour made to shrynke of foule Augias hall. </l>
          <l>What vayle all these? he wants the world which oft defended he. </l>
          <l>And th earth well knowes the worker of his quietnes to be </l>
          <l>Away from earthe: the prosperous gilt that beareth happy swey. </l>
          <l>Is vertue callde, and now the good to wicked doe obay. </l>
          <l>The right doth stand in might of armes, feare treadeth downe the lawe. </l>
          <l>Before my face with cruell hand, euen presently I sawe </l>
          <l>Reuengers of theyr fathers reygne, the sonnes with sworde downe cast, </l>
          <l>And of the noble Cadmus eke himselfe the ofspring last </l>
          <l>Then slayne: I lawe his regall crowne at once from him away </l>
          <l>With head bereft. Who Thebes alas enough bewayle nowe may? </l>
          <l>The fertile land of Gods, what lorde now quakes it for to knowe? </l>
          <l>Out of the fieldes of which somtime, and fruictfull bosome lowe, </l>
          <l>The youth vpsprong with swarde in band preparde to battell stoode: </l>
          <l>And walls of which Amphion one of mighty Ioue his broode, </l>
          <l>Hath built with sounding melody in drawing to the stones: </l>
          <l>To towne of whom the parent chiefe of Gods not onely ones </l>
          <l>Heauen being left hath come. this land that Gods aboue alway </l>
          <l>Receiu'de, and which hath made them Gods, and (leefull beete to say) </l>
          <l>Perhaps shall make, with lothsome yoake of bondage is prest downe. </l>
          <l>O Cadmus stocke, and citezens of olde Amphions towne, </l>
          <l>Whereto are yee nowe fall'ne? dread yee a cowardly exull thus, </l>
          <l>His coastes to dwell in, lacking, and to ours iniurious? </l>
          <l>Who through the worlde pursues the gilts and wrong by sea and land, </l>
          <l>And cruell sceptors broken hath with iust and ryghtfull hand, </l>
          <l>Nowe absent serues, and what he eal'de in other doth sustayne: </l>
          <l>And now doth bannysht Lycus holde of Hercles Thebes the rayne. </l>
          <l>Yet shall he not: he shall come home, and him with vengeaunce quight, </l>
          <l>And sodaine rise to starres: he will soone flude the way to light, </l>
          <l>Or make it ells. returne thou safe, repayre to thine in haste: </l>
          <l>And conquerour to conquer'de house yet come agayne at laste. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000247-009-a"/>
          <l>Ryse vp my spouse, and darknes vecye repell'de of helly shade </l>
          <l>Breake vp with hand, if no way may for thee kept backe bee made, </l>
          <l>And passage be shut vp, returne with world vprent by might. </l>
          <l>And whatsoeuer is the possest byneath in darkest night, </l>
          <l>Send dut with thee, as when the tops of haughty hylles vndoon </l>
          <l>A headlong passage making through for hasty floude to roon </l>
          <l>Thou somtime stoodst, whan with great might of thyne a sunder broake </l>
          <l>The Tempye woods wyde open lay: and beaten with thy stroake </l>
          <l>The mount, now here, now there fell downe: and rampier tente of stay, </l>
          <l>The raging brooke of Thessaly did roon a newe found way. </l>
          <l>Thy parentes so, thy sonnes, thy land repayring home to see, </l>
          <l>Breake out, and lowest bonde of things out bringing thence with thee, </l>
          <l>And what soeuer greedy age in all these long yeares race </l>
          <l>Hath hid, shew forth, &amp; ghosts that haue forgot theyr former case, </l>
          <l>And people vp before thee driue that fearefull are of light. </l>
          <l>Vnworthy spoyles for thee they are, if thou but bring to sight </l>
          <l>What bidden is. great thinges, but farre to much I speake for mee, </l>
          <l>Vnwotting of myne owne estate. when shall I hap to see, </l>
          <l>The day when thee, and thy right hand, I may embrace agayne, </l>
          <l>And slowe returnes, nor yet of me once myndefull, may complayne? </l>
          <l>To thee for this O guide of Gods, vntamed Bulls shall bring </l>
          <l>Their hundred necks: to thee O Queene of fruits on earth that spring </l>
          <l>I'le geue thee secret sacrifice: to thee with much fayth loe </l>
          <l>Long fyre brands at Eleusis towne full silent wyll I throe. </l>
          <l>Then to my brethren shall I thinke to bee restort de agayne </l>
          <l>Theyr soules, and eke himselfe aliue and guiding of his reyne </l>
          <l>My father for to flouryshe yet. If any greater might </l>
          <l>Dor keepe thee shet, we followe thee: with thy returne to fight </l>
          <l>Defend vs all, or els to hell drawe downe vs all to thee. </l>
          <l>Thou shalt vs drawe, no God shall rayse, vs vp that broken bee. </l>
          <pb n="6" xml:id="ep000247-009-b"/>
          <stage xml:id="ep000247-e103290">AMPHITRYON, MEGARA. </stage>
          <l>O Faythfull fellowe of our bloud, with chaste true faythfullnes </l>
          <l>The Bridebed keeping, and the sonne of haughty Hercules, </l>
          <l>Conceiue in mynde some better thinges, and take good heart to thee: </l>
          <l>He will come home, as after all his labours wounteth hee, </l>
          <l>Of more renowne </l>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e103350">
            <speaker>ME. </speaker>
            <l>What wretches doe most chiefly wishe of all. </l>
            <l>They soone beleue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e103380">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>Nay what they feare to much lest it may fall, </l>
            <l>They thinke it neuer may bee shoon'de, nor rid by remedy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e103410">
            <speaker>ME. </speaker>
            <l>Beleefe is ready still to dreade the woorser mysery. </l>
            <l>Deepe drown'de, &amp; whellm'de, &amp; farthermore with all the world full lowe </l>
            <l>Oppressed downe, what way hath he to light agayne to goe? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e103450">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>What way I pray you had he then when through the burning coste, </l>
            <l>And tumbling after maner of the troubled Sea vp toste </l>
            <l>He went by sands: and freate that twyse with ebbe away doth slip, </l>
            <l>And twyse vpflowe: and when alone with his forsaken ship, </l>
            <l>Fast caught he stucke in shallowe foordes of shelfye Syrtes sande, </l>
            <l>And (nowe his ship on grounde) did passe throught seas a foote to land? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e103520">
            <speaker>ME. </speaker>
            <l>Iniurious fortune vertue most of men most stout and strong </l>
            <l>Doth seldome spare: no man alyue himselfe in safety long, </l>
            <l>To perills great and daungers may so often times out cast, </l>
            <l>Whom chaunce doth often ouerslip, the same it findes at last. </l>
            <l>But cruell loe, and greeuous threats euen bearing in his face, </l>
            <l>And such as he of stomacke is, doth come euen such of pace, </l>
            <l>Proude Lycus who the sceptors shakes in hande of other king, </l>
            <l>The plentuous places of the towne of Thebes gouerning, </l>
            <l>And euery thinge about the whych with fertile soyle doth goe </l>
            <l>Sloape Phocis, and what euer doth Ismenus ouerfloe, </l>
            <l>What euer thing Cithaeron seeth with haughty top and hye, </l>
            <l>And slender Isthmos Ile, the which betweene two seas doth lye. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000247-010-a"/>
            <stage xml:id="ep000247-e103650">Lycus. Megara. Amphitrion. </stage>
            <l>NOt I of natiue countrey howres possesse the auncient right </l>
            <l>Vnworthy heir, nor yet to me are noble men of might </l>
            <l>The grandfathers, nor stocke renownd with titles hie of name, </l>
            <l>But noble vertue: who so boastes of kinred whence he come, </l>
            <l>Of others vertue makes his vaunt, but got with fearful hand </l>
            <l>My sceptors are obtaynd: in sword doth all my safety stand. </l>
            <l>What thee thou worst agaynst the will of cytesyns to get, </l>
            <l>The bright drawne sword must it defend: in forrayne countrey set </l>
            <l>No stable kingdome is. But one my pompe and princely might </l>
            <l>May ratify once ioynd to me with regall forche ful bright, </l>
            <l>And chambers Megara: of stocke of such nobility </l>
            <l>Let vpstart state of myne take shape. I do not thinke that shee </l>
            <l>Refuse it will, or in the bed with mee despyse to lye. </l>
            <l>But if with proude vnbridled mynde shee stubburn do denye, </l>
            <l>Then quite I purpose to destroy the house of Hercules </l>
            <l>The hate of men will then my pryde, and peoples speach oppres. </l>
            <l>Chiefe knacke of kingdome is to beare thy subiectes hates eche one. </l>
            <l>Lets proue her then, chaunce geuen hath to vs a place alone. </l>
            <l>For shee her head in fold of vayle ful sad and wofully </l>
            <l>Enwrapt the Gods that are her guides for succour standes fast by, </l>
            <l>And at the syde of her doth leane Alcides father trewe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e103870">
            <speaker>Meg. </speaker>
            <l>What thing doth this destroyer of our stocke agayne anew </l>
            <l>Prepare? what proueth he? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e103900">
            <speaker>Ly. </speaker>
            <l>O Queene that name renowmed hye </l>
            <l>And tytle takste of regall stocke ful gentle and easily </l>
            <l>A litle whyle receiue and heare my wordes with pacient eare, </l>
            <l>If alwayes men eternal hates should one to th' other beare, </l>
            <l>And rage be gone out of the hart should neuer fall away, </l>
            <l>But th'happy still should armour holde, th'vnhappy stil obay, </l>
            <l>Then shall the battayles nothing leaue: with wide fieldes then the lande </l>
            <l>Shall lie vntild, with vnderlayd to housen fiery brand </l>
            <l>Then ashes deepe shal ouerwhelme the buried people all. </l>
            <l>Expedient is to conquerour to wish that peace befall: </l>
            <l>To conquerd nedefull partner of the kingdome come to me: </l>
            <l>Let's toyne our myndes, take here this pledge of faith and truth to thee. </l>
            <pb n="7" xml:id="ep000247-010-b"/>
            <l>My right hand touch. Why wishest thou with cruell face and moode? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e104040">
            <speaker>Meg. </speaker>
            <l>Should I abyde, that I the hand sprinkt with my fathers bloud, </l>
            <l>Should touch, and double death imbrewd of both my brethren? nay </l>
            <l>First shall sunne ryse extinguish quitte, and West shal bring the day: </l>
            <l>First faythful peace betweene the snowes and fiers there shalbe tryde, </l>
            <l>And Scilla shall t' Ausonius fyrst ioyne his Sicilian syde: </l>
            <l>And fyrst, the fleetyng floud that with swift turnes of course doth flowe </l>
            <l>Euripus with Euboik waue shall stand ful stil and slow. </l>
            <l>My father, th'empire, bretherne, house, thou. hast me cleare bereft, </l>
            <l>My countrey to: what may be more? one thing to me is left, </l>
            <l>Then brother, father, kingdome, house, that dearer is to mee </l>
            <l>The hate of thee, the which to me with people for to be </l>
            <l>In commune woe I am: how great is myne alonly part? </l>
            <l>Rule on ful proude, beare vp ful hye thy sprites and haughty hart: </l>
            <l>Yet God the proude behynd theyr backes doth follow them to wreake. </l>
            <l>I know the Thebane kingdomes: what should I the mothers speake, </l>
            <l>Both suffring, and aduentring gyltes? what double mischiefe done? </l>
            <l>And mixed name of spouse at once, of father and of sonne? </l>
            <l>What brether as double tentes? or what as many roages also? </l>
            <l>The mother proude of Tantals brood congeald in mourning Ice, </l>
            <l>And sory stone yet flowes with teares in Phrygian Sipylye. </l>
            <l>Himselfe like wyse erected vp his sealed heade awrye. </l>
            <l>Euen Cadmus measuring throughout th'Illyrian landes in flight, </l>
            <l>Behynd him left of body drawne long slymy markes in sight. </l>
            <l>All these examples wayte for thee: rule thou as likes thy will, </l>
            <l>Whyle thee our kingdomes wonted fates do call and oft hap yll. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e104300">
            <speaker>Ly. </speaker>
            <l>God to, these fierce and furious wordes thou woman mad refraine, </l>
            <l>And imperyes of princes learne of Hercles to sustayne. </l>
            <l>Though I the scepters gotten by the force of war do beare, </l>
            <l>In conquering hand &amp; all do rule without the law his feare. </l>
            <l>Which armes subdue, a few wordes yet to thee now speake I shall </l>
            <l>For this my cause thy father did in bloudy battel fall: </l>
            <l>Thy brethren fell, the weapons kepe no measurable stay. </l>
            <l>For neither easily tempred be, nor yet repressed may </l>
            <l>The drawne swordes yre, the battels doth the bloud delite out shedde. </l>
            <l>But he yet for his kingdome fought, wee altogether led </l>
            <l>With wicked lust: yet th'end of war is now complayned, loe, </l>
            <l>And not the cause, but now let all remembraunce therof goe: </l>
            <l>When conquerour hath weapons left, the conquerds part should be </l>
            <l>To leaue his hates. Not I that thou with lowly bended knee </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000247-011-a"/>
            <l>Mee raygning worship should'st, require: euen this doth mee delight. </l>
            <l>That thou thy myseries do'st beare with mynde so stout vpright. </l>
            <l>Thou for a king a spouse art meete, let's ioyne our beds anone. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e104480">
            <speaker>ME. </speaker>
            <l>A trembling colde doth run throughout my bloudles lims ech one. </l>
            <l>What hainous thinge comes to myne eares? I fear'de not then at all, </l>
            <l>When (all peace broake) the noyse of warre did by the city wall </l>
            <l>Resounde about, I bare all that vnfearefully to see, </l>
            <l>I feare the wedding chambers: nowe I captiue seeme to mee. </l>
            <l>Let heauy chaynes my body greeue, and eke with hunger long </l>
            <l>Let lingring death be slowly brought, yet shall no force full strong </l>
            <l>My truthe subdue: for euen thine owne Alcides will I dye. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e104570">
            <speaker>LY. </speaker>
            <l>Doth then thy husband droun'de in hell geue thee this stomack hic? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e104590">
            <speaker>ME. </speaker>
            <l>The hells alowe he toucht, that he the height againe might get. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e104610">
            <speaker>LY. </speaker>
            <l>The heauy paise oppresseth him of all the earth full great. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e104630">
            <speaker>ME. </speaker>
            <l>Hee with no burdein shall be prest, that heauen it selfe sustayn'de. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e104650">
            <speaker>LY. </speaker>
            <l>Thou shalt be forst. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e104670">
            <speaker>ME. </speaker>
            <l>He wots not how to die, that is constrain'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e104690">
            <speaker>LY. </speaker>
            <l>Speake, what may rather I prepare then wedding newe for thee. </l>
            <l>More royall gyft? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e104720">
            <speaker>ME. </speaker>
            <l>Thine owne death els, or els the death of mee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e104740">
            <speaker>LY. </speaker>
            <l>Thou shalt mad woman die. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e104760">
            <speaker>ME. </speaker>
            <l>I shall then to my husbande go. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e104780">
            <speaker>LY. </speaker>
            <l>More then my Sceptors is to thee a seruaunt loued so? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e104800">
            <speaker>ME. </speaker>
            <l>How many hath this seruant slayne of kings with hendy stroake? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e104820">
            <speaker>LY. </speaker>
            <l>Why doth he yet a king then serue, and still sustayne his yoake? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e104840">
            <speaker>ME. </speaker>
            <l>Take once away the hard behests, what's vertue then at last? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e104860">
            <speaker>LY. </speaker>
            <l>Do'st thou it vertue counte, to bee to beasts, and monsters cast? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e104880">
            <speaker>ME. </speaker>
            <l>T'is vertues part, to tame the things, that all men quake to know. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e104900">
            <speaker>LY. </speaker>
            <l>Him great things bragging, darknes deepe of tartare presse ful low. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e104920">
            <speaker>ME. </speaker>
            <l>There neuer may from ground to stars an easy passage be. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e104940">
            <speaker>LY. </speaker>
            <l>Of whom begot, the housen then of Gods through pearceth he? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e104960">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>O wretched wife of Hercles great, thy words a whyle now spare. </l>
            <l>My parte it is, the father of Alcides to declare. </l>
            <l>And his true stocke, yet after all of man so stoute as this </l>
            <l>So famous deebes, and after all appeas'de with hand of his </l>
            <l>What euer Titan rysen vp, doth see, or els at fall, </l>
            <l>And after all these monsters tam'de, and Phlegrey sprinkled all </l>
            <l>With wicked bloud, and after Gods defended all on hye, </l>
            <l>Is not his father yet well knowne? or Ioue doe we beelye? </l>
            <l>Beleeue it yet by Iunoes hate. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e105060">
            <speaker>LY. </speaker>
            <l>Why do'ste thou sclaunder Ioue? </l>
            <l>No mortall kinred euer may be mixt with heauen aboue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e105090">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>To many of the Gods in skyes is this a common trade. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e105110">
            <speaker>LY. </speaker>
            <l>But were they euer seruauntes yet, before they Gods were made? </l>
          </sp>
          <pb n="8" xml:id="ep000247-011-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e105130">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>Of Delos Ile the sheepherde loe the flocks of Pherey fed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e105150">
            <speaker>LY. </speaker>
            <l>But through all coasts he wandred not abroade as banished. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e105170">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>Whom straying mother first brought forth wandring loud to sight. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e105190">
            <speaker>LY. </speaker>
            <l>Yet Phoebus did no monsters feare, or beasts of cruell might. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e105210">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>First Dragon with his bloud embrew'd the shalts of Phoebus lo. </l>
            <l>Howe greeuous ills euen yet full yong he bare, doe you not knoe? </l>
            <l>From mothers wombe the babe out thrown with lightning flame from hie, </l>
            <l>Euen next his lightning Father stoode forthwith aboue in skye. </l>
            <l>What? he him selfe that guides the starres, &amp; shakes the clouds at will, </l>
            <l>Did not that Infant lurke in Den of hollowe caued hill? </l>
            <l>The byrthes so great full troublous pryce to haue loe alwayes ought: </l>
            <l>And euer to be borne a God, with coste full great is bought. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e105300">
            <speaker>LY. </speaker>
            <l>Whom thou a miser see'st, thou mai'st know him a man to bee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e105320">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>A miser him deny yee may, whom stout of heart yee see. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e105340">
            <speaker>LY. </speaker>
            <l>Call we him stout, from shoulders hye of whom the Lyon throwne </l>
            <l>A gift for mayden made, and eke his Club from hand fell downe, </l>
            <l>And paynted side with purple weede did shyne that he did weare? </l>
            <l>Or may we him call stout of heart, whose staring lockes of heare </l>
            <l>With ointment slowde? who hands renownde &amp; knowne by prayses hye </l>
            <l>To sound vnmeete for any man of timber did applye, </l>
            <l>With barbarous mytar cloasting in his forhead rounde about? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e105420">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>The tender Bacchus did not blushe abroade to haue layde out </l>
            <l>His brayded heares, nor yet with hand full soft the Thyrsus light </l>
            <l>For to haue shooke, what time that he with pace vnstout in sight </l>
            <l>His long train'de batbarous garment drew with golde full fayre to see. </l>
            <l>Still vertue after many workes is woont releast to bee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e105480">
            <speaker>LY. </speaker>
            <l>Of this the house of Euritus destroyde doth witnesse beare, </l>
            <l>And virgins flockes that brutishly by him oppressed weare. </l>
            <l>No Iuno did commaunde him this, nor none Eurystheus loe. </l>
            <l>But these in deede his owne workes are. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e105530">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>Yet all yee doe not knoe, </l>
            <l>His worke it is, with weapons of his owne hand vanquished </l>
            <l>Both Eryx, and to Eryx ioyn'de Antaeus Lybian ded: </l>
            <l>And aulters which with slaughter of the straungers flowing fast, </l>
            <l>Busyris well deserued bloud likewise haue drunke at last. </l>
            <l>His deede it is, that he that met the wounde, and sworde is slayne </l>
            <l>Constrain'de to suffre death before those other Geryons twayne. </l>
            <l>Nor ene all onely Geryon doth with one hand conquer'de lye. </l>
            <l>Thou shalt among these be which yet with none adulterye </l>
            <l>Haue wedlocke hurt. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e105640">
            <speaker>LY. </speaker>
            <l>What is to Ioue, to king is leefull thyng: </l>
            <l>To Ioue thou gau'ste a wyfe, thou shalt nowe geue one to a kyng. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000247-012-a"/>
            <l>And euen of thee shee shall it learne to bee a thing not newe, </l>
            <l>Her husband euen approuing it the better man t'ensewe. </l>
            <l>But if shee stubberne to be matcht with me deny it still, </l>
            <l>Then euen by force a noble childe of her beget I will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e105710">
            <speaker>Meg. </speaker>
            <l>O Creons ghosts and all yee Gods of th house of Labdacus, </l>
            <l>And wedding forches blasing bryght, of wicked Oedipus. </l>
            <l>To this my wedding geue yee nowe our wonted destenyes. </l>
            <l>Now, now yee bloudy daughters all of Aegypts king likewyse, </l>
            <l>Bee here whose hands defyled are with so much bloud out spilt: </l>
            <l>One daughter lacks of Danaus, I wyll fyll vp the gylt. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e105780">
            <speaker>Ly. </speaker>
            <l>Because that stubburnely thou do'st refuse my wedding so, </l>
            <l>And fear'ste a king, thou shalt know what the Scepters now may do. </l>
            <l>Embrace thyne aulters, yet no God shall euer take away </l>
            <l>Thee from my hands: no not although with world vpturned, may </l>
            <l>Alcides victor yet agayne to Gods aboue returne. </l>
            <l>The woods on heapes together cast, let all their temples burne </l>
            <l>Euen throwne vpon theyr heads: his wyfe, and all his flocke at laste </l>
            <l>With vnderlayed fyre, let one wood pyle consume and waste. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e105870">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>This only bowne I father of Alcides aske of thee, </l>
            <l>Which well may me beseeme to craue, that I fryst slayne may hes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e105900">
            <speaker>LY. </speaker>
            <l>Who all appoyncts with present death to haue their punishment, </l>
            <l>He tyrunt wot not how to be: more sundry greeues inuent. </l>
            <l>Restrayne the wretched man from death, commaunde that th'happy dye. </l>
            <l>I, while with beames prepar'de to burne the pyle encreaseth hye, </l>
            <l>Will him with vowing sacrifyce that rules the seas entreate. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e105960">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>Oh chiefest powre of Gods, and oh of heauenly things so great </l>
            <l>The guyde, and parent eke, with whose throwne thunderbolts do shake </l>
            <l>All things humane throughout the world of king so cruell slake </l>
            <l>The wicked hande: but why do I to Gods in vayne thus cry? </l>
            <l>Where euer thou be, heare me soone. why start so sodaynely </l>
            <l>The temples thus with moouing shakte? Why roareth out the graund? </l>
            <l>The noyse of Hell from bottome deepe byneathe hath made a sound: </l>
            <l>Wee herde are, loe it is the sound of Hercules his pace. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb n="9" xml:id="ep000247-012-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e106050">
            <stage xml:id="ep000247-e106060">Chorus. </stage>
            <l>O Fortune hating men of stoutest brest, </l>
            <l>How ill rewards dost thou to good deuyde? </l>
            <l>Eurystheus raynes at home in easy rest, </l>
            <l>Alcmendes sonne in euery battayle tryde, </l>
            <l>To Monsters turnes hys hande that Skyes dyd stay: </l>
            <l>And cruell Neckes cuts of, of hydous Snake, </l>
            <l>And Apples brynges from Systers mokt away, </l>
            <l>When once to sleepe hys watchefull Eyes beetake, </l>
            <l>Dyd Dragon set ryche fruicte to ouersee. </l>
            <l>Hee past the Scythian bowres that straye abroade, </l>
            <l>And those that in their countreys straungers bee </l>
            <l>And hardned top of frosen freate hee troade, </l>
            <l>And sylent Sea with bankes full dumme about. </l>
            <l>The Waters hard want there their floudes to sloe. </l>
            <l>And there before the Shyps full Sayles spred out </l>
            <l>Is worne a pathe for Sarmates wylde to goe. </l>
            <l>The Sea doth stande to mooue in course agayne. </l>
            <l>Nowe apt to beare the Ship, nowe horsemen bolde </l>
            <l>The Queene that there doth ouer Wydowes rayne, </l>
            <l>That gyrds her Wombe wyth gyrth of glittring gold, </l>
            <l>Her noble spoyle from body drawne hath shee </l>
            <l>And shyelde, and bandes of breast as whyte as snowe, </l>
            <l>Acknowledging the Conquerour with Knee. </l>
            <l>Wyth what hope drawne to headlong Hell alowe, </l>
            <l>So bolde to passe the vnreturned wayes </l>
            <l>Saw'ste thou Proserpines rayne of Sicylye? </l>
            <l>Wyth Southern wynde, or Western there no seas </l>
            <l>Aryse wyth waue and swellinge Surges hye. </l>
            <l>Not there of Tyndars stocke the double broode </l>
            <l>Two starres the fearefull Shyps doe ayde and guide. </l>
            <l>Wyth gulph full blacke doth stande the slouthfull floode </l>
            <l>And when pale death with greedy teeth so wyde. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000247-013-a"/>
            <l>Vnnumbred Nations hath sent downe to sprightes </l>
            <l>Wyth one Boateman all ouer feryed bee. </l>
            <l>God graunt thou maist of Hell subdue the rightes </l>
            <l>And vnreuoked webs of Systers three. </l>
            <l>There kyng of many people raygneth hee. </l>
            <l>Who when thou did'st wyth Nestors Pylos fight, </l>
            <l>Pestiferous handes applide to matche with thee </l>
            <l>And weapon bare with triple mace of might: </l>
            <l>And prickt with litle wounde he fled away, </l>
            <l>And lorde of death hymselfe did feare to dye. </l>
            <l>Breake Fate by force: and let the sight of day </l>
            <l>To sorry sprightes of Hell apparant lye </l>
            <l>And porche vnpast shew way to Gods aboue. </l>
            <l>The cruell lordes of sprightes wyth pleasaunt song </l>
            <l>And humble bowne full well could Orpheus moue, </l>
            <l>Whyle he Eurydicen them craues among. </l>
            <l>The Arte that drew Woods, Byrds, and stones at will: </l>
            <l>Which made delay to Floudes of flitting flight </l>
            <l>At sound whereof the sauage Beastes stoode still </l>
            <l>With tunes vnwont doth Ghosts of hell delight </l>
            <l>And clearer doth resounde in darker place: </l>
            <l>And weepe wyth teares did Gods of cruell brest: </l>
            <l>And they which faultes with to seuere a face </l>
            <l>Doe seeke, and former gylt of Ghosts out wrest: </l>
            <l>The Thracian Daughters wayls Eurydicen. </l>
            <l>For her the Iudges weeping sit also. </l>
            <l>Wee conquer'de are, chy efe kyng of death sayd then </l>
            <l>To Gods (but vnder this condition) goe, </l>
            <l>Behynde thy husbandes backe keepe thou thy way, </l>
            <l>Looke thou not backe thy Wyfe before to see. </l>
            <l>Than thee to sight of Gods hath brought the day </l>
            <l>And gate of Spartane Taenare present bee. </l>
            <l>Loue hates delay, nor coulde abyde so long. </l>
            <l>His gyft, hee lost, while hee desires the syght. </l>
            <l>The place that coulde be thus subdew'de with song </l>
            <l>That place may soone bee ouercome by myght. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="ep000247-e106750">
          <pb n="10" xml:id="ep000247-013-b"/>
          <head>THE THYRDE ACTE. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000247-e106760">Hercules. </stage>
          <l>O Comfortable guyde of light, and honour of the skye, </l>
          <l>That cōpasting both Hemyspheres with flaming chariot hye </l>
          <l>Thy radiant head to ioyful lands about the world dost bring, </l>
          <l>Thou Phoebus pardon geue to me, if any vnlawful thing </l>
          <l>Thyne eyes haue seene: (commaunded) I haue here to light out set </l>
          <l>The secretes of the worlde: and thou of heauen to guider gret, </l>
          <l>And parent eke, in flashe out throwne of lightning hide thy fyght. </l>
          <l>And thou that gouernest the seas with seconde sceptors syght. </l>
          <l>To bottome synke of deepest waues: who so from hye doth see, </l>
          <l>And dreading yet with countnaunce newe the earth desil'de to bee, </l>
          <l>Let him from hence turne backe his sight, and face to heauen vpholde, </l>
          <l>These monstrous sights to shun: let twayn this mischiefe great behold, </l>
          <l>Hee who it brought, and shee that bad. for paynefull toyles to mee, </l>
          <l>And laboures long, not all the earth thought wide inough may bee </l>
          <l>For Iunoes hate: things vncome to all men I did see, </l>
          <l>Vnknowne to soone, and spaces wyde that darke and shadefull bee </l>
          <l>Which woorser poale geues dyrer Ioue to raygne and rule therein. </l>
          <l>And yet if thyrde place pleased more for mee to enter in, </l>
          <l>I there coulde raygne. the Chaos of eternall nyght of hell, </l>
          <l>And woorse then night, the dolefull Gods I haue that there doe dwell, </l>
          <l>And Fates subdu'de, the death contemn'de I am return'de to light. </l>
          <l>What yet remaynes? I sawe and show'de the spryghts of hell to sight: </l>
          <l>Appoynt, if ought be moe, do'ste thou my hands so long permit </l>
          <l>Iuno to ceasse? what thing byd'st thou to be subdued yet? </l>
          <l>But why doe cruell souldiars holde the holy temples wyde? </l>
          <l>And dread of armour sacred porche beset on euery syde? </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000247-014-a"/>
          <stage xml:id="ep000247-e107030">Amphitryon, Hercules, Theseus. </stage>
          <l>DOo eyther els my great desyres delude and mocke myne eyes? </l>
          <l>Or hath the tamer of the world and Greekes renowme likewyse, </l>
          <l>Forsooke the silent howse, besette with cloude full sadde to see? </l>
          <l>Is this my sonne? my members loe for ioy amased bee. </l>
          <l>Oh sonne, the sure and sauegard late of Thebes in misery, </l>
          <l>See I thy body true indeede? or els deceiu'de am I </l>
          <l>Mockt with thy sprite? art thou the same? these brawnes of armes I know </l>
          <l>And shoulders, and thy noble handes from body hie that grow. </l>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e107120">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Whens (father) happes this vglines, and why in mourning clad </l>
            <l>Is thus my wyfe? how happes it that with filth so foule bestad </l>
            <l>My children are? what misery doth thus my house appresse? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e107160">
            <speaker>Am. </speaker>
            <l>The father in law is slayne: the kingdome Licus doth possesse. </l>
            <l>Thy sonnes, thy parent and thy wyfe to death pursueth hee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e107190">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Vngrateful laud, doth no man come that will an ayder bee. </l>
            <l>Of Hercles house? and this behelde so great and haynous wronge </l>
            <l>Hath th'ayded world? but why were, I the day in playnt so long? </l>
            <l>Let then my dye and this renoume let strength obtayne in haste, </l>
            <l>And of Alcider enmies all let Lycus be the last. </l>
            <l>I driuen am to goe to shedde the bloud of enmye out. </l>
            <l>Watch Theseu that no sodayne strength beset vs here aboute: </l>
            <l>Me warres require, embracing yet deferre O father deare, </l>
            <l>And wyfe deferre them: Lycus shall to hell this message beare </l>
            <l>That I am now returnd. The, Shake of O Queene ont of thyne eyes </l>
            <l>This weping face, and thou synce that thy sonne is safe likewyse </l>
            <l>Thy drupping teares refrayne: yf yet I Hercles euer knew </l>
            <l>Then Lycus shall for Creon paye the paynes to him ful due. </l>
            <l>T'is lyght, he shal, he doth and that's to light he hath it done. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e107340">
            <speaker>Am. </speaker>
            <l>Now God that can them bring to passe, spede wel our wishes soone, </l>
            <l>And come to helpe our weary woes. O noble harted mate </l>
            <l>Of my stout sonne, of his renowne declare vs all the rate: </l>
            <l>How long away doth leade to place where sory sprites doth dwell, </l>
            <l>And how the hard and heauy bondes the dog hath borne of hell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e107400">
            <speaker>The. </speaker>
            <l>The deedes thou dost constrayne to tell, that euen to mynde secure </l>
            <l>Are dredful yet and horrible, scant yet the trust is sure </l>
            <pb n="11" xml:id="ep000247-014-b"/>
            <l>Of vitall ayre, sore blunted is the sharpnesse of my sight, </l>
            <l>And dulled eyes do scant sustayne to see th'vnwoonted light. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e107450">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>Yet Theseus throughly ouercome what euer feare remaynes </l>
            <l>In bosome deepe, nor do thou not of best fruict of thy paynes </l>
            <l>Beguilde thy selfe. What thing hath once to suffre beene a care, </l>
            <l>To haue remembred it is sweete. those dredfull haps declare. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e107500">
            <speaker>TH. </speaker>
            <l>All ryght of worlde, and thee lykewyse I praye that bearst the rayns </l>
            <l>In kingdome wyde, and thee, for whom all round about in vayne </l>
            <l>Thy mother throughout Aetna sought, that secret things alowe </l>
            <l>And hid in ground, it freely may bee lawfull for to showe. </l>
            <l>The Spartane land a noble toppe of hyll aduaunceth hye, </l>
            <l>Where Taenarus with woods full thick the Sea doth ouerly. </l>
            <l>The house of hatefull Ditis here his mouth doth open set, </l>
            <l>And rocke of hyll aboue doth gape, and with a denne full gret </l>
            <l>A huge and gaping cleft of ground with Iawes full wyde doth lye, </l>
            <l>And way full broade to people all doth spred to passe thereby. </l>
            <l>Not straight with darkenes doth begin the way that blindes the sight. </l>
            <l>A litle lingring brightnes loe behinde of late left light, </l>
            <l>And doubtfull glittring yet of sonne afllicted falles alowe, </l>
            <l>And mocks the sight: such light is wont vndoubtedly to showe </l>
            <l>The dawne of day, or twylight els at edge of euening tyde. </l>
            <l>From hence to hollowe places voyde are loaste the spaces wyde, </l>
            <l>To which needes peryshe must all kinde of men that once are throwne. </l>
            <l>Nor it a labour is goe, the way it selfe leades downe. </l>
            <l>As oft the ships agaynst theyr willes doth tosse the swelling surge, </l>
            <l>So downward doth that headlong way, and greedy Chaos vrge: </l>
            <l>And backe agayne to drawe thy pace thee neuer doe permit </l>
            <l>The sprits who what they catch hold fast. alowe within doth flit </l>
            <l>In chanell wyde with silent foorde the quiet lake of lethe. </l>
            <l>And cares doth rid: and that there may to scape agayne from death </l>
            <l>No meane be made, with many turnes and windings euery way </l>
            <l>Foldes in his floude. in such sorte as with waue vnsure doth play </l>
            <l>Maeander wandring vp and downe, and yeldes himselfe vnto, </l>
            <l>And doubtfull stands, if he toward banke, or backe to spryng may goe. </l>
            <l>The foule and filthy poole to see of slowe Cocytus lyes. </l>
            <l>On th'one the Grype, on th'other side the mournefull Howlet cries, </l>
            <l>And sad lucke of th'unhappy Strix likewise resoundeth there. </l>
            <l>Full vglily in shady bowes blacke Locks of lothsome heare, </l>
            <l>Where Taxus tree doth ouer leane, which holdeth slouthfull sleepe, </l>
            <l>And hunger sad with famisht Iawe that lyes his place to keepe, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000247-015-a"/>
            <l>And shame to late doth hide his face that knowes what crimes it hath, </l>
            <l>Both feare, and quaking, funerall, and fretting raging wrath, </l>
            <l>And mourning dyre doth follow on, and trembling pale disease, </l>
            <l>And boystrous battayles set with sworde: and hid beyond all thease </l>
            <l>Doth slouthfull age his lingring pace help forth with staffe in hand. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e107900">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>Of corne and wyne in hell alowe is any fertile land? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e107920">
            <speaker>TH. </speaker>
            <l>No ioyfull Meades do there bring forth with face so greene &amp; fayre, </l>
            <l>Nor yet with gentill Zephyrus wagges ripened corne in th'ayre. </l>
            <l>Nor any tree hath there such bowes as doe bryng apples out. </l>
            <l>The barrayne compasse of deepe soyle full filthy lyes about, </l>
            <l>And withred with eternall drought the lothsome land doth waste </l>
            <l>And bond full sad of thinges, and of the worlde the places laste: </l>
            <l>The ayre vnmoued stands, and night sits there full darke to see </l>
            <l>In slouthfull world, all thinges by dread full horrible there bee. </l>
            <l>And euen farre worse then death it selfe, is place where death doth bide. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e108020">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>What? he that doth those places darke with regall sceptor guide, </l>
            <l>In what seate set, doth he dispose and rule those peoples light? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e108050">
            <speaker>TH. </speaker>
            <l>A place there is in turne obscure of Tartarus from sight? </l>
            <l>Which mist full thick with fearefull shade doth holde and ouergoe. </l>
            <l>From hence a double parted streame from one wellspring doth floe: </l>
            <l>The tone, much like a standing poole (by this the gods doe sweare) </l>
            <l>The which the sacred Stygian lake with silent floude doth beare: </l>
            <l>The t'other fierce with tumult great is drawen his course to goe, </l>
            <l>And Acheron with raging floud the stones dryues to and froe </l>
            <l>Vnsaylable. with double foorde is rounde about beset </l>
            <l>Agaynst it Ditis pallace dyre, and manston house full gret </l>
            <l>In shadefull woode is couered: from wide den here the posts </l>
            <l>And thresholds of the tyrant hang, this is the walke of ghosts: </l>
            <l>This of his kingdome is the gate: a fielde about it goes, </l>
            <l>Where sitting with a countnaunce proude abroade he doth dispose </l>
            <l>Newe soules, a cruell maiesty is in the God to knowe: </l>
            <l>A frowning forehead, which yet of his brethren beares the showe, </l>
            <l>And so great stocke: there is in him of Ioue the very face, </l>
            <l>But when he lightens: and great part of cruell kingdomes place, </l>
            <l>Is he himselfe the lorde thereof: the sight of whom doth feare, </l>
            <l>What euer thing is fear'de. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e108250">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>Is fame in this poynet true, that there </l>
            <l>Such rygours are, and gilty Ghosts of men that there remayne </l>
            <l>Forgetfull of theyr former faulte, haue their deserued payne? </l>
            <l>Who is the rector there of ryght, and iudge of equity? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e108300">
            <speaker>TH. </speaker>
            <l>Not onely one extorter out of faultes in seate set hye </l>
            <pb n="12" xml:id="ep000247-015-b"/>
            <l>The iudgements late to trembling soules doth there by lot awarde: </l>
            <l>In one appoyncted iudgement place is Gnossian Minos harde, </l>
            <l>And in an other Radamanthe: this crime doth Aeac heare. </l>
            <l>What eche man once hath done, he feeles: and guilt to th'author the are </l>
            <l>Returnes, and th'hurtfull with their owne example punisht bee. </l>
            <l>The bloudy cruell captaynes I in pryson shee did see, </l>
            <l>And backe of tyrant impotent euen with his peoples hande </l>
            <l>All torne and cut. what man of might with fauour leades his lande, </l>
            <l>And of his owne lyfe lorde reserues his hurtlesse handes to good, </l>
            <l>And gently doth his empyre guide without the thyrst of blood, </l>
            <l>And spares his soule, he hauing long led forth the lingring dayes </l>
            <l>Of happy age, at length to heauen doth eyther finde the wayes, </l>
            <l>Or ioyfull happy places ells of fayre Elysius woode. </l>
            <l>Thou then that here must be a iudge abstayne from man his bloode, </l>
            <l>Who so thou be that raygnest kyng: our gyltes are there acquit </l>
            <l>In greater wyse. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e108480">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>Doth any place preseript of lymite shit </l>
            <l>The gylty Ghosts, and as the fame reportes, doth cruell payne </l>
            <l>The wicked men make tame that in eternall bondes remayne? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e108520">
            <speaker>TH. </speaker>
            <l>Ixion roll'de on whyrling wheele is tost and turned hye: </l>
            <l>Vpon the necke of Sisyphus the mighty stone doth lye. </l>
            <l>Amyd the lake with thyrsty Iawes olde Tantalus therein </l>
            <l>Pursues the waues, the water streame doth wet and washe his chin, </l>
            <l>And when to him nowe ofte deceyu'de it doth yet promise make, </l>
            <l>Straight flits the floud: the fruicte at mouth his famyne doth forsake. </l>
            <l>Eternall foode to fleeing foule doth Tytius hart geue still: </l>
            <l>And Danaus daughters doe in vayne theyr water vessells fill. </l>
            <l>The wicked Cadmus daughters all goe raging euery way: </l>
            <l>And there doth greedy rauening byrde the Phiney tables fray. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e108630">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>Nowe of my sonne declare to me the noble worthy fight. </l>
            <l>Brings he his willing vnckles gyft, or Plutocs spoyles to sight? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e108660">
            <speaker>TH. </speaker>
            <l>A dyre and dredfull stone there is the slouthfull foordes fast bye, </l>
            <l>Where sluggish freat with waue aston'd full dull and slowe doth lye: </l>
            <l>This lake a dredfull fellow keepes both of attire and sight, </l>
            <l>And quaking Ghosts doth ouer beare and aged vgly wyght: </l>
            <l>His Bearde vnkempt, his bosome foule deform'de in filthy wyse </l>
            <l>A knot byndes in, full lothesome stand in head his hollowe eyes: </l>
            <l>He Feary man doth steare about his Boate with his long Ore. </l>
            <l>He driuing nowe his lightned Ship of burden towarde the Shore, </l>
            <l>Repayres to waues: and then his way Alcides doth requyre, </l>
            <l>The flocke of Ghosts all geuing place: alowde cryes Charon dyre, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000247-016-a"/>
            <l>What way attemptest thou so bolde? thy hastening pace here stay. </l>
            <l>But Nathales Alcmenaes sonne abyding no delay, </l>
            <l>Euen with his owne poale bet he dothe full tame the shipman make, </l>
            <l>And clymes the ship: the barke that coulde full many peoples take, </l>
            <l>Did yelde to one: he sat, the boate more heauy like to breake </l>
            <l>Whith shyuering ioyntes on eyther syde the lethey floud doth leake. </l>
            <l>Then tremble all the monsters huge, the Centaures fierce of myght, </l>
            <l>And Lapithes, kindled with much wyne to warres and bloudy fight. </l>
            <l>The lowest Chanelles seeking out of Stygian poole a downe, </l>
            <l>His Lerney labour sore affright his fertile heads doth drowne. </l>
            <l>Of greedy Ditis after this doth then the house appere. </l>
            <l>The fierce and cruell Stygian dogge doth fray the spirites there, </l>
            <l>The which with great and roaring sounde his heads vpshaking three, </l>
            <l>The kingdome keepes his vgly head with filth full foule to see </l>
            <l>The serpentes licke: his hayres be fowle with vypers set among, </l>
            <l>And at his crooked wrested tayle doth hysse a Dragon longe: </l>
            <l>Lyke yre to shape, when him he wyst his pace that way to take, </l>
            <l>His bristle hayres he lifteth vp with fierce vp bended snake: </l>
            <l>And sounde sent out he soone perceyues in his applyed eare, </l>
            <l>Who euen the sprits is wont to sent as soone as stoode more neare </l>
            <l>The sonne of loue, the doubtfull dogge strait couched downe in denne, </l>
            <l>And eche of them did feare. beholde with dolefull barking then </l>
            <l>The places dumme he makes a dred, the threatning serpent stout </l>
            <l>Through all the fieldes about doth hysse: the bawling noyse sent out </l>
            <l>Of dredfull voyce from triple mouth, euen sprits that happy bee </l>
            <l>Doth make afrayde. from left side then strayte way vndoeth hee </l>
            <l>The cruell Iawes, and Lyons head once slayne in Cleon fielde </l>
            <l>Agaynst him sets, and couer doth himselfe with mighty shielde. </l>
            <l>And bearing in his conquering hande a sturdy club of Oke, </l>
            <l>Nowe here, now there he rolleth him about with often stroke: </l>
            <l>His stripes he doubles: he subdew'de his threates asswaged all, </l>
            <l>And all his heads the weary dogge at once full lowe let fall, </l>
            <l>And quite out of the denn he fled, full greatly feared (set </l>
            <l>In regall throne) both king and queene, and bad him to bee fet. </l>
            <l>And me likewyse they gaue for gyft to Hercles crauing mee. </l>
            <l>The monsters heauy neckes with hand then stroaking downe all three, </l>
            <l>In lynked chayne he byndeth faste forgetting then his strength </l>
            <l>The dogge the watchefull keeper of the kingdome darke at length </l>
            <l>Layth downe his eares full sore affray'de: and suffring to be led, </l>
            <l>And eke acknowledging his lorde, following wyth lowly hed, </l>
            <pb n="13" xml:id="ep000247-016-b"/>
            <l>With tayle that snakes theron doth beare he both his sides doth smight. </l>
            <l>But after that to Taenare mouth we came, and clearenes bright </l>
            <l>Had strooke his eyes of light vnknowne, good stomacke yet agayne </l>
            <l>He takes although once ouercome, and now the happy chayne </l>
            <l>He raging shakes: he had almost his leader pluckt from place, </l>
            <l>And headlong backward drawne to hell, and moued from his pace. </l>
            <l>And euen to my handes Hercles then his eyes did backward cast, </l>
            <l>Wee both with double ioyned strength the dogge out drawne at last </l>
            <l>For anger woode, and battells yet attempting all in vayne, </l>
            <l>Brought vp to world, as soone as he the cleere ayre sawe agayne, </l>
            <l>And spaces pure of bryght fayre poale had once behelde with eye, </l>
            <l>The nyght arose: his sight to ground he turned by and by, </l>
            <l>Cast downe his eyes, and hatefull day forthwith he put to flight, </l>
            <l>And backward turnd away his looke, and streight with all his might </l>
            <l>To th' earthe he falles: and vnderneath the shade of Hercles then </l>
            <l>He hyd his head. therewith there came a great resorte of men </l>
            <l>With clamour glad, that did the bay about theyr forheads bryng: </l>
            <l>And of the noble Hercules deserued prayses sing. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000247-e109350">Chorus. </stage>
          <l>EVrystheus borne with swiftned birth in hast, </l>
          <l>Did bid to bottome of the Worlde to go: </l>
          <l>This onely lackt of labours all at last, </l>
          <l>To spoyle the Kyng of thyrde estate also. </l>
          <l>The dongeons darke to enter ventred hee, </l>
          <l>Where as the way to sprits farre of doth bring </l>
          <l>Full sadde, and woode so blacke and fear'de to bee: </l>
          <l>But full with flocke full great him following. </l>
          <l>As great a preasse as flocke in cyties streetes, </l>
          <l>To see the Playes of Theatre newe wrought: </l>
          <l>As great as at Eléus thundrer meetcs, </l>
          <l>When Sommer fift the sacred game hath brought: </l>
          <l>As great as when comes houre of longer night, </l>
          <l>And willing quiet sleepes to bee extent, </l>
          <l>Holdes equall Libra Phoebus Chariots light, </l>
          <l>A sorte the secrete Ceres doe frequent, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000247-017-a"/>
          <l>And from theyr howsen left doe hast to comme, </l>
          <l>The Atticke priestes the nyghte to celebrate: </l>
          <l>Such heape is chaste beneath by fieldes so dumme. </l>
          <l>With age full slowe some taking forth their gate </l>
          <l>Full sad, and fillde with life so long now led: </l>
          <l>Some yet doe runne the race of better yeares, </l>
          <l>The virgins yet vnioynde to Spowses bed, </l>
          <l>And yonglings eke on whom grow yet no heares </l>
          <l>And Infant lately taught his mothers name. </l>
          <l>To these alone, (that they the lesse might feare) </l>
          <l>Is graunted night to ease with foreborne flame. </l>
          <l>The rest full sad by darke doe wander theare: </l>
          <l>As is our mynde, when once away is fled </l>
          <l>The lyght, when eche man sorry feeles to bee </l>
          <l>Deepe ouer whelmde with all the earth his hed. </l>
          <l>Thick Chaos standes, and darknesse fowle to see, </l>
          <l>And colour ill of night, and slouthfull state </l>
          <l>Of silent World, and diuers Cloudes about. </l>
          <l>Let hoary age vs thyther bring full late. </l>
          <l>No man comes late to that, whence neuer out, </l>
          <l>When once hee is come, turne agayne he may. </l>
          <l>To hast the hard and heauy Fate what vayles? </l>
          <l>This wandring heape in wyde landes farre away, </l>
          <l>Shall goe to Ghosts: and all shall geue their sayles </l>
          <l>To slowe Cocytus all is to thee enclinde, </l>
          <l>Both what the fall, and rise of sonne doth see: </l>
          <l>Spare vs that comme, to thee wee death are signde: </l>
          <l>Though thou be slow, our selues yet haste doe wee. </l>
          <l>Fyrst houre, that gaue the lyfe, it loast agayne. </l>
          <pb n="14" xml:id="ep000247-017-b"/>
          <l>TO Thebes is come the ioyfull day, </l>
          <l>Your Aulters touch yee humbylly, </l>
          <l>The fat fayre Sacrifices slay. </l>
          <l>Maydes myxte with men in cumpany </l>
          <l>Let them in solempne Flockes goe royle: </l>
          <l>And nowe wyth yoake layde downe let cease </l>
          <l>The Iillers of the fertile Soyle. </l>
          <l>Made is wyth hande of Hercles peace </l>
          <l>Betweene the morne and Hespers Glade, </l>
          <l>And where Sonne holding myddle seate, </l>
          <l>Doth make the Bodyes caste no Shade. </l>
          <l>What euer grounde is ouerweate </l>
          <l>Wyth compasse longe of Seas abought, </l>
          <l>Alcydes laboure taemde full well. </l>
          <l>Hee ouer foordes of Tartare brought </l>
          <l>Returnde appeased beeinge Hell. </l>
          <l>There is remayning nowe no feare, </l>
          <l>Nought lyes beyonde the Hell to see. </l>
          <l>O Priest thy staring Lockes of heare </l>
          <l>Wrappe in wyth loued Poplar tree. </l>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="ep000247-e110010">
          <pb xml:id="ep000247-018-a"/>
          <head>THE FOVRTHE ACTE. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000247-e110020">Hercules, Theseus, Amphitryon, Megara. </stage>
          <l>WIth my reuenging right hand slayne now Lycus loe the ground </l>
          <l>With groueling face hath smit: then who soeuer fellow found </l>
          <l>Of Tyraunt was, partaker of his paynes did also lye. </l>
          <l>Nowe to my father sacrifice and Gods victor will I, </l>
          <l>And aulters that deserue it, with slayne offrings reuerence. </l>
          <l>Thee, thee O mate of all my toyles I pray and my defence </l>
          <l>O warrefull Pallas, in whose left hand thy cleare shielde Aegis shakes </l>
          <l>Fierce threats, whead that eche thing stone that looke vpon it makes. </l>
          <l>Let tamer of Lycurgus nowe, and of red Sea be heare, </l>
          <l>That poynct of speare with Iuye greene in hand doth couer'de beare: </l>
          <l>And two Gods powre, doth Phoebus, and his Syster to I pray </l>
          <l>The sister meeter for her shaftes, but hee on th'harpe to play: </l>
          <l>And what soeuer brother ells of myne doth dwell in sky, </l>
          <l>Not of my stepdame brother, bring yee hyther by and by </l>
          <l>Your plentuous flocks, what euer haue all th' Indians fruicts brought out, </l>
          <l>And what sweete odours th' Arabickes doe get in trees about, </l>
          <l>To th' aulters bring: let vapour fat and fume smoke vp full hye, </l>
          <l>Let rounde about the Poplar tree my hayres now beautifye </l>
          <l>Let th'oliue bowe thee hyde with braunche accustom'de in our lande </l>
          <l>Theseu: for foorthwith reuerence the thundrer, shall my hande, </l>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e110230">
            <speaker>TH. </speaker>
            <l>O Gods the builders of the towne, and which of Dragon fell, </l>
            <l>The wilde woods vens, and noble waues likewise of Dirces well, </l>
            <l>And Tyrian house enhabite eke of straunger wandring king. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e110270">
            <speaker>HE. </speaker>
            <l>Cast into fyres the frankencense. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e110290">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>Sonne fyrst thy hands flowing </l>
            <l>With bloudy slaughter, and the death of enmy purify. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e110320">
            <speaker>HE. </speaker>
            <l>Would God the bloud of hatefull head euen vnto Gods on hye </l>
            <l>I might out shed, for lycour loe more acceptable none </l>
            <l>Myght th' aulters stayne: nor sacrifice more ample any one </l>
            <l>Nor yet more plentyfull may bee to Ioue aboue downe cast, </l>
            <l>Then king vniust. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e110380">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>Desyre that now thy father ende at last </l>
            <l>Thy labours all: let quietnes at length yet gieuen bee, </l>
            <l>And rest to weary folke. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e110420">
            <speaker>HE. </speaker>
            <l>I will thee prayers make, for mee </l>
            <pb n="15" xml:id="ep000247-018-b"/>
            <l>And Ioue ful meete in this due place let stand the haughty skye, </l>
            <l>And land, and ayre, and let the starres dryue forth eternally </l>
            <l>Their course vnstayde: let restful peace kepe nations quietly, </l>
            <l>Let labour of the hurtles land all yron now occupye, </l>
            <l>And swordes lye hyd: let tempest none ful vyolent and dyre </l>
            <l>Disturbe the sea: let from the skyes no flash of lightning fyre </l>
            <l>Fall downe whyle Ioue ful angry is: nor yet with winter snowe </l>
            <l>Encreased flood the ground vpturnde, and field quyte ouerthrowe, </l>
            <l>Let poysons cease: and from hensforth let vp from ground aryse </l>
            <l>No greeuous hearbe with hurtful sappe: nor fierce and fell lykewyse </l>
            <l>Let tyrantes raygne but if to sight some other mischiefe bringe </l>
            <l>The ground yet shall, let it make hast: and any monstruous thinge </l>
            <l>It it prepare let it be myne, but what meanes this? myd day </l>
            <l>The darkenes haue incloas'd aboute lo Phoebus goeth his way </l>
            <l>With face obscure without a clowde who dryues the day to flight, </l>
            <l>And turnes to east? from whence doth now his dusky hed the night </l>
            <l>Vnknowne bring forth? whence fil the poale so many rownde about </l>
            <l>Of daytyme starres? lo here behold my laboure first ful stout </l>
            <l>Not in the lowest parte of heauen the Lyon shyneth bryght, </l>
            <l>And feruently doth rage with yre, and byttes prepares to fyght. </l>
            <l>Euen now loe he some star wil take, with mouth full wyde to see </l>
            <l>He threatning standes, and fires out blowes and mane vp rustleth he </l>
            <l>Shaking with necke the haruest sad of shape, what euer thinge, </l>
            <l>And what soeuer winter colde in frosen tyme doth bring, </l>
            <l>He with one rage wil ouerpasse, or spring tyme bull he will </l>
            <l>Both seeke and breake the neckes at once. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e110700">
            <speaker>Am. </speaker>
            <l>what is this sodayne ylle? </l>
            <l>Thy cruel count'naunce whether sonne dost thou cast here and there? </l>
            <l>And seest with troubled daseld syght false shape of heauen appere </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e110740">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>The land is tam'de the swelling feas their surges did asswage, </l>
            <l>The kingdomes lowe of hell lykewyse haue felt and knowne my rage, </l>
            <l>Yet heauen is free, a labour meete for Hercules to proue. </l>
            <l>To spaces high I wil be borne of haughty skies aboue </l>
            <l>Let th' ayre be skaeld, my father doth me promise starres t'obtayne. </l>
            <l>What if he it denyde? all th' earth can Hercles not contayne, </l>
            <l>And geeues at length to gods, me calles of one accorde beholde </l>
            <l>The whole assembly of the gods, and doth their gates vnfolde, </l>
            <l>Whyle one forbyddes, receyu'st thou mee, and openest thou the skye, </l>
            <l>Or els the gate of stubburne heauen draw after me do I? </l>
            <l>Do I yet doubt? I euen the bondes from Saturne wyll vndoe, </l>
            <l>And euen agaynst the kingdome prowde of wicked father loe </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000247-019-a"/>
            <l>My graundsyre loase. let Titans now prepare agayne their fight </l>
            <l>With me theyr captaine raging: stones with woods I will down smight </l>
            <l>And hye hilles tops with Centaures full in right hande will I take. </l>
            <l>With dauble mountayne now I will a stayre to Gods vp make. </l>
            <l>Let Chyron vnder Ossa see his Pelion mountayne gret: </l>
            <l>Olympus vp to heauen aboue in thyrd degree then set </l>
            <l>Shall come it selfe, or ells be cast. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e110940">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>Put farre away from thee </l>
            <l>The thoughts that ought not to be spoake: of mynde vnsounde to see, </l>
            <l>But yet full great, the furious rage asswage and lay away. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e110980">
            <speaker>HE. </speaker>
            <l>What meaneth this? the Gyauntes doe pestiferous armes assay, </l>
            <l>And Tityus from the sprights is fled, and bearing torne to see </l>
            <l>And empty bosome, loe howe neere to heauen it selfe stoode hee? </l>
            <l>Cythaeron falles, the mountayne hie Pallene shakes for feare, </l>
            <l>And torne are Tempe. he the tops of Pindus caught hath here, </l>
            <l>And Octhen he, some dredfull thing threatning doth rage about </l>
            <l>Erynnis bringing flames: with stripes she soundes nowe sharken out, </l>
            <l>And burned brandes in funeralles, loe yet more neare and neare </l>
            <l>Throwes in my face: fearce Tisyphone with head and vgly heare </l>
            <l>With serpentes set, nowe after dogge fet out with Hercles hand, </l>
            <l>That empty gate shee hath shut vp, with bolte of fyry brande, </l>
            <l>But loe the stocke of enmious king doth hidden yet remayne, </l>
            <l>The wicked Lycus seede: but to your hatefull father slayne </l>
            <l>Euen now this right hande shall you sende let nowe his arrowes light </l>
            <l>My bowe out shoote: it seemes the shaftes to goe with such a flight </l>
            <l>Of Hercles. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e111150">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>Whether doth the rage and fury blinde yet goe? </l>
            <l>His mighty Bowe he drewe with hornes together driuen loe, </l>
            <l>And quiuer loaste: great noyese makes with violence sent out </l>
            <l>The shaft, and quight the weapon flewe his middle necke throughout, </l>
            <l>The wound yet left. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e111210">
            <speaker>HE. </speaker>
            <l>His other broode I ouerthrow will quight, </l>
            <l>And corners all. What stay I yet? to me a greater fyght </l>
            <l>Remaynes then all Mycenes loe, that rockye stones should all </l>
            <l>Of Cyclops being ouerturn'de with hande of myne, downe fall. </l>
            <l>Let shake both here, and there the house, with all stayes ouerthrowne, </l>
            <l>Let breake the poasts: and quight let shrinke the shaken piller downe: </l>
            <l>Let all the Pallace fall at once. I here yet hidden see </l>
            <l>The sonne of wycked father. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e111300">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>Loe his flattring handes to thee </l>
            <l>Applying to thy knees dooth craue his lyfe with piteous mone. </l>
            <l>O wicked gylt, full sad, and eke abhorde to looke vpone, </l>
            <l>His humble right hand caught he hath, and raging rounde about </l>
            <l>Him rolled twyse, or thryse hath cast. his head resoundeth out, </l>
            <pb n="16" xml:id="ep000247-019-b"/>
            <l>The sprinkled houses with the brayne of him throwne out are wet. </l>
            <l>But shee poore wretch her little sonne in bosome hyding yet </l>
            <l>Loe Megara, like one in rage doth from the corners flee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e111390">
            <speaker>HE. </speaker>
            <l>Though runagate in bosome of the thundrer hid thou bee, </l>
            <l>This right hand shall from euery where thee seeke, and bring to sight. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e111420">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>Wher goest thou wretch? what lurking dens, seekst thou to take, or flight? </l>
            <l>No place of sauegarde is if once bee Hercles styrde with yre: </l>
            <l>But doe thou rather him embrace, and with thy meeke desyre </l>
            <l>Assay t'asswage him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e111470">
            <speaker>ME. </speaker>
            <l>Husband spare vs I beseech thee nowe, </l>
            <l>And knowe thy Megara, this sonne thy countenaunce doth showe, </l>
            <l>And bodyes pytche: behould'st thou howe his hands vp lyfteth hee? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e111510">
            <speaker>HE. </speaker>
            <l>I holde my stepdame: followe on due penaunce paye to mee, </l>
            <l>And bounden Ioue from fylthy bonde deliuer free away: </l>
            <l>But I before the mother will this litle monster slay. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e111550">
            <speaker>ME. </speaker>
            <l>Thou mad man whither goest thou? wylt thou thine owne bloude sheade? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e111570">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>Th'infant with fathers fyry face astonnted all for bread, </l>
            <l>Died euen before the wounde: his feare hath tooke away his lyfe. </l>
            <l>And now likewise his heauy club is shaken towarde his wyfe: </l>
            <l>He broaken hath the bones, her head from blocklyke body gone </l>
            <l>Is quight, nor any where it stayes, dar'ste thou this looke vpone </l>
            <l>To long lyu'de age? If mouruing doe the greeue, thou hast then loe </l>
            <l>The death preparde. Doe thou thy breast vppon his weapons throe, </l>
            <l>Or ells this club with slaughter stayn'de of monsters slayne that Bee, </l>
            <l>Nowe hyther turne. thy parent false, vnfit for name of thee </l>
            <l>Ryd hence away, least he should be to thy renowne a let. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e111680">
            <speaker>TH. </speaker>
            <l>Which way the father toward thy death dost thou thy selfe cast yet? </l>
            <l>Or whyther goest thou mad man? flee and lye thou cloasely hid, </l>
            <l>And yet from handes of Hercules this onely myschiefe rid. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e111720">
            <speaker>HE. </speaker>
            <l>T'is well, the house of shameful king is now quight ouerthrowne. </l>
            <l>To thee O spouse of greattest Ioue I haue loe beaten downe </l>
            <l>This offred flocke: I gladly haue fulfill'de my wyshes all </l>
            <l>Full meete for thee, and Argos now geue other offrings shall. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e111770">
            <speaker>AM. </speaker>
            <l>Thou hast not sonne yet all perform'de, fill vp the sacrifise. </l>
            <l>Loe th'offring doth at th'aultars stande, it waytes thy hand likewyse </l>
            <l>With necke full prone: I geue my selfe, I roon, I follow loe. </l>
            <l>Mee sacrifice. what meaneth this? his eyes rolle to and froe, </l>
            <l>And heauines doth dull his sight. see I of Hercules </l>
            <l>The trembling hands? downe falles his face to sleepe and quietnes, </l>
            <l>And weary necke with bowed head full fast doth downeward shrynke, </l>
            <l>With bended knee: nowe all at once he downe to ground doth sinke, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000247-020-a"/>
            <l>As in the woods wylde Ashe cut downe, or Bulwarke for to make </l>
            <l>A Hauen in Seas. Liu'ste thou? or els to death doth thee betake </l>
            <l>The selfe same rage, that hath sent all thy famyly to death? </l>
            <l>It is but sleepe, for to and fro doth goe and come his breath. </l>
            <l>Let tyme bee had of quietnesse, that thus by sleepe and rest </l>
            <l>Great force of his disease subdew'de, may ease his greeued brest. </l>
            <l>Remoue his weapons seruants, least he mad get them agayne. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e111930">
            <stage xml:id="ep000247-e111940">Chorus. </stage>
            <l>LEt th'ayre complayne, and eke the parent great </l>
            <l>Of haughty Sky, and fertile land throughout, </l>
            <l>And wandring waue of euer mouing freat. </l>
            <l>And thou before them all, which lands about </l>
            <l>And trayn of Sea thy beames abroade dost throe </l>
            <l>With glittring face, and mak'st the night to flee, </l>
            <l>O feruent Titan: bothe thy lettinges loe </l>
            <l>And rysing, hath Alcides seene wyth thee: </l>
            <l>And knowne lykewise hee hath thy howsen twayne. </l>
            <l>From so great ills release yee nowe hys brest, </l>
            <l>O Gods release: to better turne agayne </l>
            <l>His ryghter mynde, and thou O tamer best </l>
            <l>O sleepe of toyles, the quietnesse of mynde, </l>
            <l>Of all the lyfe of man the better parte, </l>
            <l>O of thy mother Astrey wynged kynde, </l>
            <l>Of hard and pyning death that brother arte, </l>
            <l>With truth mingling the false, of after state </l>
            <l>The sure, but eke the worste foreteller yet: </l>
            <l>O Father of all thynges, of Lyfe the gate, </l>
            <l>Of lyght the rest, of nyght and fellowe fyt, </l>
            <l>That com'st to Kyng, and seruaunt equally, </l>
            <l>And gently cherysshest who weary bee, </l>
            <l>All mankynde loe that dreadfull is to dye, </l>
            <l>Thou doost constrayne long death to learne by thee. </l>
            <l>Keepe him fast bounde wyth heauy sleepe opprest, </l>
            <l>Let slomber deepe his Limmes vntamed bynde, </l>
            <pb n="17" xml:id="ep000247-020-b"/>
            <l>Nor soner leaue his vnright raginge breaste </l>
            <l>Then former mynd his course agayne may fynd. </l>
            <l>Loe layd on ground with full fierce hart yet still </l>
            <l>His cruel sleepes he turnes: and not yet is </l>
            <l>The plague subdude of so great raging yll </l>
            <l>And on great club the weary head of his </l>
            <l>He wont to laye, doth secke the staffe to fynde </l>
            <l>With empty handes his armes out casting yet </l>
            <l>With mouing vayne: nor yet all rage of minde </l>
            <l>He hath layd downe, but as with Sowthwind greate </l>
            <l>The waue once vext yet after kepeth still </l>
            <l>His raging long, and though the wind now bee </l>
            <l>Asswaged swelles, shake of theis madde and yll </l>
            <l>Tossinges of mynde, returne let piety, </l>
            <l>And vertue to the man, els let be so </l>
            <l>His mynde with mouing mad toste euery waye: </l>
            <l>Let errour blynd, where it begun hath, go, </l>
            <l>For naught els now but only madnes maye </l>
            <l>Thee gyltles make: in next estate it standes </l>
            <l>To hurtles handes thy mischiefe not to know. </l>
            <l>Now stroken let with Hercules his handes </l>
            <l>Thy bosome sounde: thyne armes the worlde allow </l>
            <l>Were wonte to beare, let greuous strypes now smyte </l>
            <l>With conquering hande, and lowde complaying cryes, </l>
            <l>Let th'ayre now heare, let of darke pole and nighte </l>
            <l>The Queene them hear, and who ful fyercely lyes </l>
            <l>That beares his neckes in mighty chaynes fast bounde, </l>
            <l>Low lurking Cerberus in deepest caue. </l>
            <l>Let Chaos all with clamour sad resound, </l>
            <l>And of broad sea wide open wafting waue. </l>
            <l>And th'ayre that felt thy weapons beter yet, </l>
            <l>but felt them though. </l>
            <l>The breastes with so great yls as these beset, </l>
            <l>With litle stroake they must not beaten bee. </l>
            <l>Let kingdomes three sound with one playnt and crye, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000247-021-a"/>
            <l>And thou neckes honour and defence to see, </l>
            <l>His arrowe strong longe hanged vp on hye, </l>
            <l>And quiuers light the cruell stripes now l'myte </l>
            <l>On his fierce backe his shouldars strong and stout </l>
            <l>Let oken club now strike and poast of might </l>
            <l>With knots ful hard his brestee load all aboute. </l>
            <l>Let euen his weapons so great woes complayne </l>
            <l>Not you pore babes mates of your fathers praise, </l>
            <l>With cruell wound reuenging kinges agayne: </l>
            <l>Not you your lims in Argos barriars playes, </l>
            <l>Are taught to turne with weapons strong to smie </l>
            <l>And strong of hand yet euen now daring loe </l>
            <l>The weapons of the Scithian quiuer light </l>
            <l>With stedy hand to paise set out from bow. </l>
            <l>And stags to perce that saue them selues by flight </l>
            <l>And backes not yet ful maend of cruel beast. </l>
            <l>To Stigian hauens goeye of shade and night </l>
            <l>Goe hurtles soules, whom mischiefe hath opprest </l>
            <l>Euen in fyrst porch of lyfe but lately had, </l>
            <l>And fathers fury goe vnhappy kind </l>
            <l>O litle children, by the way ful sad </l>
            <l>Of iourney knowen. </l>
            <l>Goe see the angry kynges. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="ep000247-e112790">
          <pb n="18" xml:id="ep000247-021-b"/>
          <head>THE FIFTHE ACTE. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000247-e112800">Hercules, Amphitry on, Theseus. </stage>
          <l>WHat place is this? what region? or of the world what coast? </l>
          <l>Where am I? vnder ryse of sunne or bond els vttermost. </l>
          <l>Of th'ycy beare or els doth here of sea of Hespery </l>
          <l>The fardest ground appoynt a bond for th'ocean sea to lye? </l>
          <l>What ayre draw we? to weary wight what ground is vnderset? </l>
          <l>Of truth we are returnd from hell whence in my house downe bet </l>
          <l>See I these bloudy bodyes? hath not yet my mynd of cast </l>
          <l>Th'infernall shapes? but after yet returnd from hel at last </l>
          <l>Yet wander doth that belly heape before myne eys to see? </l>
          <l>I am asham'de to graunt, I quake, I know not what to me, </l>
          <l>I cannot tell what greeuou yll my mynde before doth know. </l>
          <l>Where is my parent? where is shee with goodly childrens show </l>
          <l>My noble harly stomackt spouse why doth my left syde lacke </l>
          <l>The lyons spoyle? which way is gone the couer of my backe? </l>
          <l>And selfe same bedde ful soft for slepe of Hercules also? </l>
          <l>Where are my shaftes? where is my bow? then from my liuing who </l>
          <l>Could plucke away? who taken hath the spoyles so great as these </l>
          <l>And who was he that feared not euen sleepe of Hercules? </l>
          <l>To see my conquerour me lykes, yt lykes me hym to know </l>
          <l>Ryse victor vp, what new sonne hath my father gotten now </l>
          <l>Heauen beynge left? at byrth of whom myght euer stayd bee </l>
          <l>A longer night then, was in myne? what mischiefe do I see? </l>
          <l>My children loe do lye on ground with bloudy slaughter slayne? </l>
          <l>My wyfe is kild: what Lycus doth the kingdome yet obtayne? </l>
          <l>Who durst so haynous giltes as these at Thebes take in hand </l>
          <l>When Hercles is returnd? who so Ismenus waters land, </l>
          <l>Who so Acteons fieldes or who with double seas beset </l>
          <l>The shaken Pelops kingdomes dost of Dardan dwell on yet </l>
          <l>Helpe me: of cruel slaughter show who may the author bee. </l>
          <l>Let rage my yre and all: my foe he is who so to me </l>
          <l>Shewes not my foe dost thou yet hyde Alcides victorly? </l>
          <l>Come forth, euen whether thou reuenge the cruel charyots hye </l>
          <l>Of Bloudy Thracian king or yf thou Gerions catell quight </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000247-022-a"/>
          <l>Or lordes of Lybia, no delay there is with thee to fight. </l>
          <l>Beholde I naked stande, although euen with my weapons loe </l>
          <l>Thou me vnarmed sette vppon. Wherfore fleeth Theseus soe, </l>
          <l>And eke my father from my syght? theyr faces why hyde they? </l>
          <l>Deferre your weepings, and who did my wyfe and children sley </l>
          <l>Thus all at once, me tell. Wherfore O father dost thouwhusht? </l>
          <l>But tell thou Theseu, but Theseu with thy accustom'd truste. </l>
          <l>Ech of them sylent hydes away their bashefull count'naunces, </l>
          <l>And priuily they shed their teares in so great ils as these, </l>
          <l>Of what ought wee asham'de to be? doth ruler yet of might </l>
          <l>Of Argos towne, or hateful band of sowldiars apt to fight </l>
          <l>Of Lycus dying, vs oppresse with such calamity? </l>
          <l>By prayse of all my noble actes I do desyre of thee </l>
          <l>O father, and of thy great name approu'de to me alway </l>
          <l>The prosperous powre declare to mee, who did my houshold flay? </l>
          <l>Whose pray lay I? </l>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e113300">
            <speaker>A. </speaker>
            <l>Let thus thyne ylles in sylens ouerpas. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e113320">
            <speaker>He. </speaker>
            <l>That I should vnreuenged bee? Am, Reuenge oft hurtful was. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e113340">
            <speaker>He </speaker>
            <l>Did euer man so greeuous yls without reuenge sustayne? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e113360">
            <speaker>A </speaker>
            <l>Who's euer greater fearde. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e113380">
            <speaker>H. </speaker>
            <l>Then these O father yet agayne </l>
            <l>May any greater thing, or els more greuous feared be? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e113410">
            <speaker>Am. </speaker>
            <l>How great apart is it thou wotst of thy calamity? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e113430">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Take mercy father, lo I lift to thee my humble hands. </l>
            <l>What meaneth this? my hand fleeth backe, some priuy gylt their standes </l>
            <l>Whence comes this bloud? or what doth mean flowing with death of child </l>
            <l>The shaft imbrewd with slaughter once of Lerney monster kilde? </l>
            <l>I see my weapons now, the hand I seeke no more to witte. </l>
            <l>Whose hand could bend this bow but myne? or what right at me but it, </l>
            <l>Could string the bow that vnto mee euen scantly doth obay? </l>
            <l>To you I turne: O father deare, is this my gylt I pray? </l>
            <l>They held their peace: it is myne own. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e113530">
            <speaker>Am. </speaker>
            <l>Thy greuous woe is there, </l>
            <l>The cryme thy stepdames: this mischaunce no falt of thyne hath here. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e113560">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>From euery part now father throw in wrath thy thunders mighte, </l>
            <l>And of thy sonne forgetful now with cruel hand requighte </l>
            <l>At least thy nephewes, let the world that beares the starrs sounde out. </l>
            <l>And let both th'one and th'other poale, flyng downe thy flames aboute: </l>
            <l>And let the bankes of Caspyan sea my bounden body teare, </l>
            <l>And gredy foule. Wherfore do of Prometheus lacke heare </l>
            <l>The rockes? with huge and haughty top let now prepared be, </l>
            <l>Both feeding beastes and foules, the syde of Caucas turne to see, </l>
            <l>And bare of woods, the yle that bridge of Scithe that therby standes </l>
            <pb n="19" xml:id="ep000247-022-b"/>
            <l>Simplegas ioynes, both here and there let it my bounden handes </l>
            <l>Stretch out abroade: and when with course return'de accustomd'ly </l>
            <l>They shall togeather dryue, and shall the rockes tosse vp to skye </l>
            <l>With bankes togeather beyng thrust, and eke the middle seay, </l>
            <l>Let me bet weene the mountaynes lye vnquiet restlesse stay </l>
            <l>But building vp with wood throwne on a heaped plie on hie </l>
            <l>My body thus with wicked bloud besprinct, why burne not I? </l>
            <l>So, so yt mus be done: to hell I Hercles will restore. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e113740">
            <speaker>Am. </speaker>
            <l>Not yet his hart astonted lackes his ragyng tumult sore, </l>
            <l>But wraths hath turnd: and which of rage is property and yre </l>
            <l>Agaynst himselfe he rageth now </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e113780">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>The furies places dire </l>
            <l>And dungeon depe of sprites in hell and place of tormentry </l>
            <l>To gylty ghostes and banishment yf any yet do lye </l>
            <l>Beyond Erebus, yet vnknowen to Cerberus and mee, </l>
            <l>There hyde me ground to farthest bond of Tartarus to see. </l>
            <l>To tary there Ile goe. O brest of myne to fierce and stoute: </l>
            <l>Who you my children thus disperst through all my house about, </l>
            <l>May worthely enough bewayle? in all my euils yet </l>
            <l>This countnaunce hard can neuer weepe, a sword now hether set: </l>
            <l>My shaftes reach hether, hyther reach my mighty club also: </l>
            <l>To thee my weapons breake I will, to thee my sonne a two </l>
            <l>Ile knappe my bowes, and eke my clubbe, this blocke of heauy wayghte </l>
            <l>Shal to thy sprites be burned loe: this selfe same quiuer frayght </l>
            <l>With Lerney shaftes to funerall of thyne shall like wyse goe. </l>
            <l>Let all my weapons penance pay and you vnhappy to </l>
            <l>Euen with my weapons burne I wil, O stepdames handes of myne. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e113950">
            <speaker>Th. </speaker>
            <l>Who euer yet to ignoraunce hath geuen name of cryme? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e113970">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Ful oftentymes did errour greate the place of gylt obtayne. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e113990">
            <speaker>Th. </speaker>
            <l>T'is neede to be a Hercles now, this heape of yll sustayne. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e114010">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Not so, hath shame yet geuen place with fury drowned quight: </l>
            <l>But peoples all I rather should dryue from my wicked sight. </l>
            <l>My weapons, weapons </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e114050">
            <speaker>Theseus. </speaker>
            <l>I quickly craue to mee </l>
            <l>Withdraw to be restoard agayne: if sound my mynd now bee, </l>
            <l>Restore to me my weapons: if yet last my rage of mynd, </l>
            <l>Then father flee: for I the waye to death my selfe shal fynde. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e114100">
            <speaker>Am. </speaker>
            <l>By sacred holy kynreds rightes, by force and duty all </l>
            <l>Of both my names; if eyther me thy brynger vp thou call. </l>
            <l>Or parent els, and (which of good men reuerenced are) </l>
            <l>By these hoare hayres, I the besech my desert age yet spare, </l>
            <l>And wery yeares of house falne downe the one alonly stay, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000247-023-a"/>
            <l>One onely light to mee, with yls afflicted euery way </l>
            <l>Reserue thy selfe: yet neuer hath there happ'ned once of thee </l>
            <l>Fruite of thy toyles: still eyther I the doubtful sea to see </l>
            <l>Or monsters feard: who euer yet hath bene a cruell king </l>
            <l>In all the world to ghostes allow, and aulters both hurtinge, </l>
            <l>Of me is feard: the father of thee absent stil to haue </l>
            <l>The feuite, the touching, and the sight of thee at length I craue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e114230">
            <speaker>He. </speaker>
            <l>Wherfore I longer should sustayn my life yet in this light, </l>
            <l>And linger here no cause there is, all good lost haue I quighte, </l>
            <l>My mynd, my weapons, my renoume, my wife, my sonnes, my handes, </l>
            <l>And fury to no man may heale and lose from gylty handes </l>
            <l>My mynd defyeld: needes must with death he heald so haynous yll. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e114290">
            <speaker>Th. </speaker>
            <l>Wilt thou thy father IIay? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e114310">
            <speaker>He. </speaker>
            <l>Least I shoulde do it die I will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e114330">
            <speaker>Th. </speaker>
            <l>Before thy fathers face? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e114350">
            <speaker>He. </speaker>
            <l>I taught him mischief for to see. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e114370">
            <speaker>Th. </speaker>
            <l>Thy deedes marking rather that should of al remembred bee, </l>
            <l>Of this one only cryme I do a pardon of thee craue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e114400">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Sall he geue pardon to himselfe, that to none els it gaue? </l>
            <l>I beeing bidden prayse deseru'd, this deede mine owne doth proue. </l>
            <l>Helpe father now, if eyther els thy piety thee moue, </l>
            <l>Or els my heauy fate, or els the honour and renowne. </l>
            <l>Of stained strength, my weapons bringe, let fortune be throwen downe. </l>
            <l>with my right hand. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e114470">
            <speaker>Th. </speaker>
            <l>The prayers which thy father makes to thee </l>
            <l>Are stronge enough, but yet likewyse with weeping loe of me </l>
            <l>By moued yet: aryse thou vp, and with thy wonted myght </l>
            <l>Subdue thyne yls: now such a mynde vnmeete to beare vpright </l>
            <l>No euill hap, receyus againe loe now with manhode gret </l>
            <l>Thou must preuayle. euen Hercules forbyd with yre to fret. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e114540">
            <speaker>HE. </speaker>
            <l>Alyue, I hurt: but if I dye I take the gylt also. </l>
            <l>I hast to ridde the world of cryme euen now before me lo </l>
            <l>A wicked monster cruel, and vntamed fierce and flout </l>
            <l>Doth wander: now with thy ryght hand beginne to goe aboute </l>
            <l>A greate affayre, yea more then all thy twyse sixe labours long. </l>
            <l>Yet stayst thou wretch, that late agaynst the children wast so stronge, </l>
            <l>And fearful mother now except restoard my weapons see, </l>
            <l>Of Thracian Pindus eyther I wil feare downe euery tree, </l>
            <l>And Bacchus holly woods and tops of mount Cythaeron hye </l>
            <l>Burne with myselfe, and al 'at once with all their housen I </l>
            <l>And with the Lordes therof the roofes with goddes of Thebes all </l>
            <l>The Thebane temples euen vppon my body will let fall: </l>
            <l>And wyl be hyd in to wne vpturnd: if to my shoulders might </l>
            <pb n="20" xml:id="ep000247-023-b"/>
            <l>The walles themselues all cast theron shall fall a burden light, </l>
            <l>And couerd with seuen gates I shall not be enough opprest, </l>
            <l>Then all the wayght wheron the worlde in middle part doth rest, </l>
            <l>And partes the Goddes vppon my head Ile turne and ouerthrow </l>
            <l>My weapons geue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e114730">
            <speaker>Am. </speaker>
            <l>This word is meete for Hercles father lo </l>
            <l>With this same arrow slaine behold thy sonne is tombled downe, </l>
            <l>This weapons cruell Iuno lo from handes of thyne hath throwne, </l>
            <l>This same wil I now vse, loe see how leaps with feare afright </l>
            <l>My wretched harte, and how it doth my careful body smight. </l>
            <l>The shaft is set therto thou shalt a mischiefe lo do now </l>
            <l>Both willing it and wotting: tel, what thing commaundest thou? </l>
            <l>I nothing craue my doloure let in saf'ty standeth now. </l>
            <l>To kepe my sonne alyue to mee that onely do canst thou </l>
            <l>O Theseu, yet I haue not scapte great'st feare that happen can </l>
            <l>Thou canst mee not a miser make, thou mayst a happy man </l>
            <l>So order euery thyng thou dost, as all thy cause in hand, </l>
            <l>And fame thou mayst wel know in strayght and doubtful case to stande </l>
            <l>Thou liu'st, or diest: this slender soule that light is hence to flee, </l>
            <l>Weried with age and no lesse bet with greuous ils to see, </l>
            <l>In mouth I holde so slowly to a father with such slaye </l>
            <l>Doth any man geue lyfe? I wil no longer bid delay, </l>
            <l>The deadly sword throughout my breast to strike I wil apply, </l>
            <l>Here, here the gylt of Hercules euen sound of mynd shall lye. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e114930">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Forbeare O father now forbeare, with draw thy hand againe. </l>
            <l>My manhood yeld thy fathers will, and impery sustaine. </l>
            <l>To Hercles labours now like wyse, let this one labour goe, </l>
            <l>Let me yet liue, lift vp from ground th'afflicted lims with woe </l>
            <l>O Theseu of my parent: for from Godly touch doth flee </l>
            <l>My wicked hand. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e115000">
            <speaker>Am? </speaker>
            <l>I gladly do this hand embrace to mee. </l>
            <l>By this I beyng slayed will goe, this meuing to my brest </l>
            <l>Ile slake my woes, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e115040">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>what place shall I seeke ronnagate for rest? </l>
            <l>Where shall I hyde my selfe? or in what land my selfe engraue? </l>
            <l>What Tanais, or what Nilus els, or with his Persyan waue </l>
            <l>What Tygris violent of streame, or what fierce Rhenus flood, </l>
            <l>Or Tagus troublesome that flowes with Ibers treasures good </l>
            <l>May my ryght hand now wash from gylt? although Maeotis cold </l>
            <l>The waues of all the Northen sea on me shed out now wolde, </l>
            <l>And al the water ther of shoulde now pas by my two handes, </l>
            <l>Yet wil the mischiefe deepe remayne, alas into whet landes </l>
            <l>Wilt thou O wicked man resort? to East or westerne coste? </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000247-024-a"/>
            <l>Ech where wel knowen, all place I haue of banishment quight loste </l>
            <l>From me the warlde doth flee a back, the starres that sydelyng roue </l>
            <l>Do back warde dryue their turned course, euen Cerberus the soue </l>
            <l>With better count'naunce did behold O faythfull friend I saye, </l>
            <l>O Theseu seeke same lurking place, farre hence out of the way </l>
            <l>O thou a warder of mens gyltes what euer Iudge thou hee </l>
            <l>That hurtful men dost loue, repay a worthy thanke to me: </l>
            <l>And my desertes. I thee beseech, to ghostes of hell againe </l>
            <l>Send me that once escaped them: &amp; subiect to thy raine </l>
            <l>Restore me yet to those thy bandes, that place shal me wel hyde: </l>
            <l>And yet euen that place knowes me wel </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000247-ep000247" xml:id="ep000247-e115260">
            <speaker>Th. </speaker>
            <l>Our land for thee doth bide </l>
            <l>Him Mars his hande acquite agayne and made from slaughter free </l>
            <l>Restoard to armoure, loe that land (Alcides) calles for thee, </l>
            <l>Which wontes to quite the gods, and proue them Innocent to be. </l>
          </sp>
          <trailer>HERE ENDETH THE FIRST Tragedye of Seneca, called Hercules furens, translated into Englishe by Iasper Heywood studente in Oxenforde. </trailer>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back></back>
  </text>
</TEI>
