<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000251" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Oedipus</title>
        <author>
          <persName xml:lang="eng">Seneca</persName>
          <persName>
            <forename>Lucius</forename>
            <surname>Annaeus</surname>
            <addName>Seneca</addName>
            <genName>minor</genName>
          </persName>
          <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q2054</idno>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A11909_05.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="A11909-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull n="TCP source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">Seneca his tenne tragedies, translated into Englysh.</title>
                <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus, ca. 4 B.C.-65 A.D.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>225 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
                <date>2007 October (TCP phase 1)</date>
                <idno type="marc">99852323</idno>
                <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 22221.</idno>
                <idno type="stc">Greg, III, p. 1105-6.</idno>
                <idno type="vid">17639</idno>
                <idno type="DLPS">A11909</idno>
                <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2248540344</idno>
                <availability>
                  <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
                </availability>
              </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
            <biblFull n="printed source">
              <titleStmt>
                <title type="_245">Seneca his tenne tragedies, translated into Englysh.</title>
                <title type="alt">Tragedies. English</title>
                <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus, ca. 4 B.C.-65 A.D.</author>
                <author>Heywood, Jasper, 1535-1598,</author>
                <author>Neville, Alexander, 1544-1614,</author>
                <author>Studley, John, 1545?-1590?,</author>
                <author>T. N. d. 1617,</author>
                <author>Newton, Thomas, 1542?-1607.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[4], 65, 64-217, [1] leaves.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>In Fleetstreete neere vnto Saincte Dunstans church by Thomas Marsh,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication_date">1581.</date>
                <date type="creation_date">1560</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>
                  <p>Editor's dedication signed: Thomas Newton.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>In verse.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>A reprinting of the following translations previously published separately: "Hercules furens", "Thyestes", and "Troas" by Jasper Heywood; "¦edipus" by Alexander Neville (a revised version); "Medea" and "Agamemnon" by John Studley; and "Octavia" (not by Seneca) by Thomas Nuce. Prints for the first time "Hippolytus" and "Hercules Oetæus" translated by Studley, and "Thebais" translated by Thomas Newton.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A"; the last leaf is blank.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                  <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
                </note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <person xml:id="ep000251-A11909">
            <persName>A11909</persName>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
      <textClass>
        <classCode scheme="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q80930</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1560">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
    <listRelation>
      <relation name="wikidata"
                   active="https://dracor.org/entity/ep000251"
                   passive="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q972143"/>
    </listRelation>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="5" type="tragedy" xml:id="ep000251-e100030">
        <pb xml:id="ep000251-082-a"/>
        <head>THE FIFTH TRAGEDY OF SENECA, ENGLISHED The yeare of our Lord M. LX. </head>
        <byline>BY ALEXANDER NEVYLE. </byline>
        <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000251-e100050">
          <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, MAISTER DOCTOR WOTTON: ONE OF THE Queenes Maiesties priuy Counsayle: Alexander Neuyle wisheth Helth, with encrease of Honor. </head>
          <p>THis sixtenth yeare of myne age (righte honorable) reneweth a gratefull memory of your great goodnes towardes mee: (for at Baptisme your honor vouchsafed to aunsweare for mee): and causeth mee thus boldly to present these greene and vnmelowed fruicts of my first trauailes vnto you: as signes and testimonies of a well disposed minde vnto your honor. Albeit when first I vndertoke the translation of this present Tragoedy, I minded nothing lesse, than that at any tyme thus rudely transformed it shoulde come into the <pb n="76" xml:id="ep000251-082-b"/>Printers hands. For I to none other ende remoued him, from his naturall and lofty style, to our corrupt and base, or as some men (but vntruly) affyrme it, most barbarous Language: but onely to satisfy the instant requests of a few my familiar frends, who thought to haue put it to the very same vse, that SENECA himselfe in his Inuention pretended: Which was by the tragicall and Pompous showe vpon Stage, to admonish all men of their fickle Estates, to declare the vnconstant head of wauering Fortune, her sodayne interchaunged and soone altered Face: and lyuely to expresse the iust reuenge, and fearefull punishments of horrible Crimes, wherewith the wretched worlde in these our myserable dayes pyteously swarmeth. This caused me not to be precise in following the Author, word for word: but sometymes by addition, somtimes by subtraction, to vse the aptest Phrases in geuing the Sense that I could inuent. Whereat a great numbre (I know) will be more offended than Reason or Wysedome woulde they should bee. Thus as I framed it to one purpose: so haue my frends (to whom I can not well deny any thyng that Frendshyps ryght may seeme iustly to requyre) wrested it to another effect: and by this meanes blowen it abroade, by ouerrash and vnaduised printing. By whych fond deede I know vndoubtedly I shall receyue the poysoned infamies, of a number of venemous tonges, Wherefore (ryght honorable) as I geue these the first Fruicts of my trauayle vnto you: declaring therein the great goodwyll and duety that I owe vnto your Honor, for the noble disposition of your vertuous mynde: so am I driuen humbly to require your strong ayde, and assured defence agaynst <pb xml:id="ep000251-083-a"/>the sclaunderous assaults of such malicious mouths, which obtayned: I shalbe the better encouraged agaynst an other time, to bestow my trauaile in matters of farre greater weighte and importaunce. In the meane season (desiring your Honour to take these simple Attemptes of myne in good part:) I leaue you to the tuition of the right high and mighty God: Who keepe you long in health, &amp; graunt you many happy yeares: with encrease of Honor. </p>
          <closer>
            <signed>All your Honours to commaund. Alexander Neuile. </signed>
          </closer>
        </div>
        <div type="preface" xml:id="ep000251-e100090">
          <head>❀ THE PREFACE TO the Reader. </head>
          <p>BEHOLD HERE BEFORE THY Face (good Reader) the most lamentable Tragedy of that most Infortunate Prince O Edipus, for thy profit rudely translated. Wonder not at the grosenesse of the Style: neyther yet accounte the Inuentours Dylygence dysgraced by the Translators Neglygence: Who thoughe that he hath somtimes boldly presumed to erre from his Author, rouing at randon where he list: adding and subtracting at pleasure: yet let not that engender disdaynefull suspition with in thy learned breast. Marke thou rather what is ment by the whole course of the History: and frame thy lyfe free from such mischiefes, wherewith the World at this present is vniuersally ouerwhelmed, The wrathfull vengeaunce of God prouoked, the Body plagued, the mynde and Conscience in midst of deepe deuouring daungers most terribly assaulted. <pb n="77" xml:id="ep000251-083-b"/>In such sort that I abhorre to write: and euen at the thought thereof I tremble and quake for very inward griefe and feare of minde: assuredly perswading my selfe that the right high and immortall God, will neuer leaue such horrible and detestable crimes vnpunished. As in this present Tragoedy, and so forth in the processe of the whole hystory, thou maist right well perceyue. Wherein thou shalt see, a very expresse and liuely Image of the inconstant chaunge of fickle Fortune in the person of a Prince of passing Fame and Renown, midst whole fluds of earthly blisse: by meare misfortune (nay rather by the deepe hidden secret Iudgements of God) piteously plunged in most extreame miseries. The whole Realme for his sake in straungest guise greuously plagued: besides the apparaunt destruction of the Nobility: the generall death and spoyle of the Comminalty: the miserable transformed Face of the City, with an infinite number of mischiefes more, which I passe ouer vnrehersed. Onely wish I all men by this Tragicall hystory (for to that entent was it written) to beware of Synne: the ende whereof is shamefull and miserable. As in the most infortunate fall of this vnhappy Prince right playnely appeareth. Who by inward gripe of fearefull consuming Conscience wretchedly tormented: beholding the lamentable state of his vile infected Realmes, wasted by the burning rage of priuy spoyling Pestilence, finds himselfe in tract of time, to be th'onely plague &amp; misery of the almost quight destroied City. Wherevpon calling together his Priests and Prophets, &amp; asking counsaile of the Gods by them, for present remedy in those euils, wherewith the Realme was than vniuersally ouerflowen: aunswere was made that the Plague should neuer ceasse, till king LAIVS death were throughly reuenged: and the bloudy Murtherer driuen into perpetuall exile. Which aunswere receiued, OEDIPVS, farre more curious in bowlting out the truth, than carefull of his own Estate: sodainly slides into an innumerable company of dredfull miseries. For as soone as he had once the perfect vewe of his own detestable deedes, and wicked misdemeanour cast before his eyes, together with the <pb xml:id="ep000251-084-a"/>vnnaturall killing of his Father LAIVS, the incestuous Mariage of his Mother IOCASTA, the preposterous order of his ill misguyded lyfe, with a hundred moe like mischiefes, which chaste &amp; vndefiled eares abhorre to heare: fretting Fury common enemy &amp; tormentor to corrupted consciences pricking him forward, all inflamed with Phrensie and boyling in inward heate of vile infected minde, hee rooteth out his wretched eyes vnnaturally, bereaueth his Mother her life (though earnestly requested thereto) beastly, &amp; in the ende in most basest kind of slauery, banisht, dieth miserably. Leauing behind him vnto all posterities, a dredfull Example of Gods horrible vengeaunce for sinne. Such like terrors as these requireth this our present Age, wherein Vice hath chiefest place, &amp; Vertue put to flight, lies as an abiect, languishing in great extremity. For the which cause, so much the rather haue I suffred this my base translated Tragoedy to be published: from his Author in word &amp; verse somewhat transformed, though in Sense litle altered: and yet oftentimes rudely encreased with mine owne simple inuention: more rashly (I confesse) than wisely, wishing to please all: to offend none. But whereas no man liues so vprightly, whom slaundring tonges leaue vndiffamed, I referre my selfe to the Iudgement of the wisest, litle esteeming the preiudiciall mouthes of such carping Marchaunts, whych suffer no mens doings almost to scape vndefiled. In fine, I beseech all to gether (if so it might be) to beare with my rudenes, &amp; consider the grosenes of our owne Countrey language, which can by no meanes aspire to the high lofty Latinists stile. Myne onely entent was to exhorte men to embrace Vertue and shun Vyce, according to that of the right famous &amp; excellent Poet Virgil </p>
          <quote>Discite iusticiam moniti, &amp; non temnere diuos. </quote>
          <p>This obtayned: I hold my selfe throughly contented: In the meane season I ende: wishing all men to shun Sin, the plaine (but most perilous) pathway to perfect infelicity. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="dramatis" xml:id="ep000251-e100130">
          <list>
            <pb n="78" xml:id="ep000251-084-b"/>
            <head>The Speakers names. </head>
            <item>OEdipus. </item>
            <item>Chorus. </item>
            <item>Tiresias. </item>
            <item>Sanex. </item>
            <item>Iocasta. </item>
            <item>Creon. </item>
            <item>Manto. </item>
            <item>Phorbas. </item>
            <item>[Nuntius] </item>
          </list>
        </div>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="ep000251-e100240">
          <head>THE FIRST ACTE. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000251-e100250">OEDIPVS the King. IOCASTA the Queene. </stage>
          <l>THe Night is gon: and dredfull day </l>
          <l>begins at length t'appeere: </l>
          <l>And Phoebus all bedim'de with Clowdes, </l>
          <l>himselfe aloft doth reere. </l>
          <l>And glyding forth with deadly hue, </l>
          <l>a dolefull blase in Skies </l>
          <l>Doth beare: Great terror &amp; dismay </l>
          <l>to the beholders Eyes. </l>
          <l>Now shall the houses voyde bee seene, with Plague deuoured quight? </l>
          <l>And slaughter that the night hath made, shall day bring forth to light. </l>
          <l>Doth any man in Princely throne reioyce? O brittle Ioy, </l>
          <l>How many ills? how fayre a Face? and yet how much annoy </l>
          <l>In thee doth lurke, and hidden lies? what heapes of endles strife? </l>
          <l>They iudge amisse, that deeme the Prince to haue the happy life. </l>
          <l>For as the Mountaynes huge and bie, the blustring windes withstand. </l>
          <l>And craggy Rocks, the belching fluds do dash, and driue fro land: </l>
          <l>Though that the Seas in quiet are, and calme on euery side: </l>
          <l>So kingdoms great all Windes and Waues of Fortune must abide. </l>
          <l>How well shund I my Father deare Polybius Scepters late? </l>
          <l>Exil'de, bereft of carefull feare, in Pilgrims happy state: </l>
          <l>I call the Gods to witnes this, and Stars that glyde in Skyes. </l>
          <l>A Kingdome is befauln to mee. I frare least thereof ryse </l>
          <l>A mischiefe, (mighty Ioue,) to great I feare, alas I feare </l>
          <l>Least these my handes haue reft the life, or thee my Father deare. </l>
          <l>Apollo byds mee this beware, and yet a mischiefe more Foretels. </l>
          <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e100510">
            <speaker>IOC. </speaker>
            <l>Can any greater bee than that you tolde before? </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000251-085-a"/>
            <l>Of Father slayne by sonnes own hand? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e100540">
            <speaker>OE. </speaker>
            <l>(O thrice vnhappy state.) </l>
            <l>With horror all dismaide I stand in dred of threatned fate. </l>
            <l>I am ashamed my destinies fowle (O Queene) to thunder out, </l>
            <l>And openly to blase my feare my trembling minde doth dout: </l>
            <l>Yet out it goes. Phoebus me bids my Mothers Bed to fly. </l>
            <l>As though that I her Sonne, with her incestuously should ly. </l>
            <l>This feare, and onely this me causde my fathers kingdome great </l>
            <l>For to forsake. I fled not thence when feare the minde doth beat. </l>
            <l>The restlesse thought still dreds the thing, it knows can neuer chaunce. </l>
            <l>Such fansies now torment my heart, my safety to aduaunce, </l>
            <l>And eke thyne euer sacred lawes (O Nature) for to keepe </l>
            <l>A stately Scepter I forsooke, yet secret feare doth creepe </l>
            <l>Within my breast: and frets it still with doubt and discontent, </l>
            <l>And inward pangues which secretly my thoughts a sunder rent. </l>
            <l>So though no cause of dred I see, yet feare and dred I all, </l>
            <l>And scant in credit with my selfe, my thoughts my minde appall </l>
            <l>That I cannot perswaded be though reason tell mee no, </l>
            <l>But that the Web is weauing still of my decreed wo. </l>
            <l>For what should I suppose the cause? a Plague that is so generall, </l>
            <l>And Cadmus country wholy spoyles, and spreds it selfe through all? </l>
            <l>Should mee, amongest so huge a heape of plagued Bodies spare? </l>
            <l>And we alone amongst the rest reserude to mischiefes are? </l>
            <l>O heauy hap. And bide I stil alone the spoyle to see? </l>
            <l>Of Cities great, of men, of beasts, by plague that wasted bee? </l>
            <l>And thou amongst so many ils, a happy lyfe to lead, </l>
            <l>Couldst once perswade thy selfe (O wretch) without all feare or dread. </l>
            <l>Of Phoebus secret Iudgements to, and that in Kinges estate? </l>
            <l>Thou, thou, infected hast the ayre, in such a filthy rate. </l>
            <l>Thou art the onely cause of woe: by thee these euils rise, </l>
            <l>By thee to graue on such a sorte, this wretched people plies. </l>
            <l>The firy flaming frying heate, afflicted hearts that wasts, </l>
            <l>Is not relieude as wont it was by cold and pleasaunt blasts. </l>
            <l>The gentle western windes haue left with healthfull puffes to blow, </l>
            <l>And now the fiery Dog with blase of boyling heate doth glow. </l>
            <l>The Sunne in Leo burns so hoate, and so the earth doth broyle, </l>
            <l>That fluds and hearbes are dryed vp, and nought remaynes but soyle, </l>
            <l>So throughly schorcht and stued with heate, that moisture all is gone, </l>
            <l>And now amongst so many fluds, remaynes alas not one. </l>
            <l>The places dry are onely seene the streames are drunken vp. </l>
            <l>And water that doth yet remayne: the soaking Earth doth sup. </l>
            <pb n="79" xml:id="ep000251-085-b"/>
            <l>The Moone with clowds quight over cast, all sadly forth she glides, </l>
            <l>And dolefull darksom shades of night the whole worlde ouer hides. </l>
            <l>No Star on high at all doth shine, but black and heli●ke hue </l>
            <l>Hath ouershaded all the Skyes, whence deadly mists ensue. </l>
            <l>The corne that wonted was to growe and fruitfully to spring, </l>
            <l>Now to the voyded Barnes nought els, but empty stalkes doth bring. </l>
            <l>No part of all our kingdome is free from destruction: </l>
            <l>But all together run and rush, to vtter confusion. </l>
            <l>The old men with the yong (alas:) the Father with the chylde </l>
            <l>The plague consumes. Both man &amp; wife, all beasts both tame &amp; wylde </l>
            <l>Are spoyled by the Pestilence. No pompe at all remaynes, </l>
            <l>That wonted was in Funeralles, to ease the mourners paynes. </l>
            <l>Alas this spoile of people made, by plague hath dryde myne eyes: </l>
            <l>And secretly within my breast, the griefe it boyling fryes. </l>
            <l>And that, that wonted is to hap, in most extremest ills: </l>
            <l>My tearees are dry and glutting griefe my wretched breast it fills. </l>
            <l>The crased father beares the son, vnto theyr dampish graues: </l>
            <l>And after him with burden like, the Mother comes and raues: </l>
            <l>And euen lamenting as they stand, 〈…〉 both they fall, </l>
            <l>And mourners new in like estate, for them and theirs they call. </l>
            <l>Who likewise in the midst of all their toyle and paynfull payne </l>
            <l>Do drop into the graue they digd, and so the place doe gayne </l>
            <l>That was prepar'de for others erst. A hell it were to heere </l>
            <l>The horror, and the miseries that euery where appeere. </l>
            <l>A Tombe is made for noble men, fast on the people die, </l>
            <l>And in, their burdens fling. Great Pieres all vnregarded lye. </l>
            <l>For lack of Graues, to Ashes cleane their bodyes some doe wast: </l>
            <l>And some halfe burnt doe leaue them there, and home away for hast </l>
            <l>They run, &amp; more they fetch, and then wood, fier, graue, and all </l>
            <l>Doth want. And downe for very griefe the wretched mysers fall. </l>
            <l>No prayers auaile. No Arte can help this raging Plague t'appease: </l>
            <l>For none almost is left aliue each others woe to ease. </l>
            <l>Before thine aulters heere O God my feeble hands I hold, </l>
            <l>Requiring all my destinies, at once with courage bold. </l>
            <l>And that by death I may preuent, my Countrey prest to fall. </l>
            <l>For this, and only this (O God) vpon thy name I call. </l>
            <l>Let mee not be the last that dies: The last that goes to Graue. </l>
            <l>Graunt this, and then (O mighty Ioue) my full request I haue. </l>
            <l>O cruell Gods vnkinde: O more than thrise vnhappy Fates: </l>
            <l>That onely mee denied is, that lyghtes on all Estates. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000251-086-a"/>
            <l>I meane a speedy death (alas) these euils to preuent </l>
            <l>And deadly woes that doe my heart with restlesse rage torment. </l>
            <l>Leaue of thy blubbering teares (O foole, )&amp; fly these kingdomes foylde </l>
            <l>With rotten plagues &amp; Botches bile, and graves ech where dispoylde. </l>
            <l>All which diseases thou vnhappy guest didst bring with thee </l>
            <l>Dispatch. Away. Goe hence. At least, vnto thy parents flee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e101410">
            <speaker>IO. </speaker>
            <l>What bootes it 〈…〉, great with piteous plaints to aggregate. </l>
            <l>Stoutly to beare aduersity, 〈…〉 estate. </l>
            <l>When dred and daunger most assayle: when cruell Cares doe crush </l>
            <l>Thy princely breast, Thē oughtst thou most to beare and bide the push. </l>
            <l>It is no poinct of courage stout to yeelde to fortunes frown. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e101470">
            <speaker>OED. </speaker>
            <l>Nay, Feare could neuer cause mee sloupe nor Fortune cast mee down. </l>
            <l>My manly winds was neuer thraule to vaine and peauish feares, </l>
            <l>But euermore in each 〈…〉 courage beares. </l>
            <l>No not a thousand glistering swords, nor Mars himselfe in fielde. </l>
            <l>Can once dismay my Countenaunce, or cause my heart to yeelde. </l>
            <l>The very Giaunts fierce and huge in fight withstand I dare. </l>
            <l>That Monster Sphinx whose riddels through the world renowmed are, </l>
            <l>Could not dismay my deedles heart, nor cause my courage slide </l>
            <l>For all the terrors I behold. I did that Fury byde. </l>
            <l>I saw him belching Gobs of bloud, I viewde full well the fielde </l>
            <l>That all to spatterd lay with bloud, and bones quight ouerheelde. </l>
            <l>And when that he on Mountaynes top with mouth full huge to see. </l>
            <l>Stoode gaping all with greedy Iawes to feede and pray on mee, </l>
            <l>Oft fluttering with his fearefull wynges and shaking oft his rayse, </l>
            <l>Began full like a Lyon fierce with threates mee to assayle. </l>
            <l>Of whom straight way the Riddell I, it rusht into myne eares </l>
            <l>With roring sound His winges he claps, the Rock for hast hee teares. </l>
            <l>Desiring with my Bowels still his greedy Iawes to glut: </l>
            <l>But I full soone assoyled had the question that he put. </l>
            <l>And all the subtile poincts ther of, and twisted knots vntwinde. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e101680">
            <speaker>IO. </speaker>
            <l>What makes you wish for death to late, and waue your wordes in wind. </l>
            <l>You might haue died than (you know) for Sphinx so nobly slain. </l>
            <l>This kingdom vnto you, and yours for euer shall remain. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e101720">
            <speaker>OED. </speaker>
            <l>The ashes of that Monster vile, agaynst vs doth rebell. </l>
            <l>That vile mishapen lothsome Beast, that raging Feend of Hell. </l>
            <l>Is cause of all the plague that doth this mournfull City smight. </l>
            <l>Now only this remaynes alone, if Phoebus heauenly might, </l>
            <l>Can any meanes inuent for vs, or way of mercy make: </l>
            <l>Whereby these burning Plagues at length may haply chasice to slake. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb n="80" xml:id="ep000251-086-b"/>
          <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e101790">
            <stage xml:id="ep000251-e101800">Chorus. </stage>
            <l>O More then thrise renowned Stock </l>
            <l>of auncient Cadmus Race. </l>
            <l>O mighty Thebes City great, </l>
            <l>O heauy ruthfull Case. </l>
            <l>Loe now you lye all desolate, </l>
            <l>with Plague deuoured quight. </l>
            <l>Both you and all your Husbandmen. </l>
            <l>(Oh miserable sight.) </l>
            <l>O fowle and feareful Fate (alas) what causeth all this aid? </l>
            <l>O God whence springs this Pestylence that vs tormenteth so? </l>
            <l>No age, no shape, no forme is sparde, but all confounded lye. </l>
            <l>Thus happiest now the man I count, whose chaunce was first to dye. </l>
            <l>For hee hath shund a thousand ills, which wretched Eyes haue seene: </l>
            <l>And mischiefes great that vs doe presse from him are taken cleane. </l>
            <l>O God withhold thy fury great, thy Plagues from vs remoue. </l>
            <l>Ceasse of afflicted Soules to scourge, who thee, both serue and loue. </l>
            <l>Powre downe on them diseases fowle, that them deserued haue. </l>
            <l>A Guerdon iust for sinne (Oh God) this this of thee wee craue, </l>
            <l>And onely this. We aske no more, the cause and all is thyne, </l>
            <l>A thing not vsde of Gods it is, from pity to declyne. </l>
            <l>My heart doth vant, and trembling cold through all my lims doth run, </l>
            <l>As oft as I remembring, count the noble Stockes vndun, </l>
            <l>By death and dolfull destenies that ouerwhelmed lye, </l>
            <l>And yet alas the people stil to Graue doe faster hye. </l>
            <l>In long Aray all in a rancke by thousandes on a roe, </l>
            <l>On euery side, in euery streate to buriall fast, they goe. </l>
            <l>The seuen broade wyde open Gates, are not enough forway, </l>
            <l>But throngd the people pestred stand still in a fearefull stay, </l>
            <l>And in the mydst of all theyr toyle with corses on their backes, </l>
            <l>The number that before doth poast the hinder number slackes. </l>
            <l>The corses in the streates doe lye and Graue on Graue is made. </l>
            <l>But all in vayne. For nought it boots the plague cannot be stayde. </l>
            <l>The sacrifices don to Gods haue to to ill successe. </l>
            <l>And such straunge sights &amp; signes doe rise that nought els I can gesse, </l>
            <l>But that at hand with gastly pawes, is vtter destruction, </l>
            <l>With thousand ills accompayned and extreme confusion. </l>
            <l>The sheepe of rot by heapes as thick, as dogges doe fall and dye, </l>
            <l>And belching out their wasted lunges, on grounde doe sprawling lye. </l>
            <l>And I my selfe of late did see: (a sight vnseene before,) </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000251-087-a"/>
            <l>As our high priest stoode sacrifising at the Temple dore, </l>
            <l>And strake with grieuous bloudy wound the golden horned Bull </l>
            <l>When downe with liueles lump he drops and members made full dull. </l>
            <l>And all the woude wide bleeding gapes &amp; black goar'sbloud out spues. </l>
            <l>And yet the blade vnsprinckled was. The bloud it boyling fiues </l>
            <l>And bubbles on the ground. Alas what do these things portend? </l>
            <l>Oh mighty Ioue at length vouchsafe some good and happy end. </l>
            <l>At length withhold thy hand (O God) and health vnto vs send. </l>
            <l>Nothing (alas) remaynes at all, in wonted old estate, </l>
            <l>But all are turned topset downe, quight voyd and desolate </l>
            <l>The famting horse for 〈…〉 back his burden tats. </l>
            <l>Aud after on his maisters brest his liueles lyms he squats: </l>
            <l>Who cries for help :but all in vain the beasts in field that bide </l>
            <l>Unkept: vnknowen wayes and pathe do raunge and ouerstride. </l>
            <l>The Bull 〈…〉 and meate are in field all faintyng lyes. </l>
            <l>And, all his flocke dispersed quight the fely Shephard dyes. </l>
            <l>The herdman eke amongst his beasts his fatal breath expiers </l>
            <l>And to the heuens with piteous cries commends his last desters. </l>
            <l>The Harts without all feare of wolues do lyue in wretched peace. </l>
            <l>The rage, and wrathful roring sounds of ramping Lions cease. </l>
            <l>The vengeaunce wyld outragious Beares are now as tame as sheepe </l>
            <l>The vgly Serpent that was wont, the Rocky Dennes to keepe. </l>
            <l>Oft quaffing poisoned Venom sups in inward heat shee boyles, </l>
            <l>And all inflamd and schorcht ,in vayne for lenger lyfe she toyles. </l>
            <l>The woods are 〈…〉 with fresh and lyuely hue, </l>
            <l>The wonted shades are gon. All things are quight out of their Que: </l>
            <l>No greenish grasse on ground doth grow, the earth no moisture soupes. </l>
            <l>The Vine withouten any sap, his drowsy head down drowpes. </l>
            <l>What shal I say? all 〈…〉 out of course, </l>
            <l>And as they seeme to me ,are lyke ,to fare still worse and worse. </l>
            <l>O mighty God aboue when ende these euerduryng yls? </l>
            <l>When cease 〈…〉 bloud thus fierce and raging spils? </l>
            <l>I thinck but we almost alyue, there do no men remayne: </l>
            <l>Whom dolful Darts 〈…〉 on earth haue left vnslayne. </l>
            <l>I thinck the darcksome shades of hell where filthy fluds do flow, </l>
            <l>Where plages and vile diseases too, where dredfull horrors grow, </l>
            <l>And all the furies brasten loose do mischiefes on vs throw, </l>
            <l>With Botch &amp; biane of sundry kindes which sothern blasts do blow, </l>
            <l>And wrekful vexed hagges of hell do dreath and on vs bringe: </l>
            <l>The angry feddes of hell I thinke their vengeaunce, on vs flinge </l>
            <pb n="81" xml:id="ep000251-087-b"/>
            <l>And out their mortall poyson spue which they agaynst vs beare. </l>
            <l>Lo see how greedy death on vs with scowling eyes doth leare. </l>
            <l>See, see. Oh Ioue how fast hee throwes his Dartes. Not one he spares </l>
            <l>But all confounds. His thretning force, withstand no Creature dares. </l>
            <l>No doubt the lothsom Feryman the sinfull soules that traynes </l>
            <l>Through stincking fluds, his labour loths that he for vs sustaynes. </l>
            <l>Such presse by plumps to him is made which still renews his paynes. </l>
            <l>But harke yet monsters more than these, the Fame abroade doth fly </l>
            <l>That hellishe Dogges with bawling sound were heard to howle and cry, </l>
            <l>And the the ground with trembling shooke, and vnder feele did moue. </l>
            <l>And dreadfull blasing Comets bright were seene in Skies aboue. </l>
            <l>And gastly shapes of men besides, to wander on the ground. </l>
            <l>And wood, and trees on euery syde, did fearefully resound. </l>
            <l>Besides all this straung Ghosts were seene in places where they stoode. </l>
            <l>And Ryuers more then one or two, that ran all blacke goorb bloode. </l>
            <l>O cruell plague, O vile disease, farre worse then speedy death. </l>
            <l>O wee vnhappy thrise and more, who doe prolonge our breath. </l>
            <l>In these accursed dayes and tymes. But harke to mee a while. </l>
            <l>When first this lothsome plague begins these Mysers to defile, </l>
            <l>It takes them thus. A feareful Cold through al their bones doth run,] </l>
            <l>And Cold and Heate togeather mixt, their sences all benome. </l>
            <l>Than litle lothsome markes appeare, and all their bodies spot. </l>
            <l>And all their members flaming glow, and burning fast doe rot. </l>
            <l>The Lights, the Lungs, the heart, the Guts, and all that inwarde lies. </l>
            <l>And all the secret partes iscorcht, with deadly, I fier fries. </l>
            <l>The bloud all clotterd in their Cheekes, in cluster lies by lumps. </l>
            <l>And it and heate together makes, great, straung, and ruddy bumps. </l>
            <l>And bloud and flesh congeled stands, in Face as stiffe as stake. </l>
            <l>And Eyes in head fast fixed set, and often trickling make. </l>
            <l>And downe apace whole fluds they steame, and clots &amp; drops doe trill, </l>
            <l>And all the skin from of their Face, by flakes and scales doth pill. </l>
            <l>A thousand fearefull sounds at once, into their eares doe rush. </l>
            <l>And lothsome bloud out of their Nose, by stilling streames doth gush. </l>
            <l>The very anguish of their heart doth cause them for to shake. </l>
            <l>And what with payne &amp; heale, and feare, their weried lims doe quake. </l>
            <l>Then some the running Ryuers haunt, and some on ground doe wallow. </l>
            <l>And some agayne their thirst to slake, cold water gulping swallow. </l>
            <l>Thus all our country tost with plague in Griefe it waltering lies. </l>
            <l>And still desiring for to dye, a thousand deathes it dyes. </l>
            <l>But God to heare them then is prest: and death to none denyes. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000251-088-a"/>
            <l>Besydes al this, the church some do frequent: but not to pray, </l>
            <l>But onely for to glut the Gods, with that that they do say. </l>
            <l>But who is this that comes to Court in hast with poasting pace? </l>
            <l>What? ist Creon that noble Prince (for deedes and stately race?) </l>
            <l>Or doth my mynd opprest with care thinges false for true contriue? </l>
            <l>Creon it is long looked for, his sight doth me reuyue. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="ep000251-e103060">
          <head>THE SECONDE ACTE. </head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000251-e103070">
            <head>The first Scene. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000251-e103080">OEDIPVS. CREON. </stage>
            <l>FOr feare my body chilles, alas, </l>
            <l>and trembling all I stand </l>
            <l>In quakinge dread. I seke and toyle, </l>
            <l>these mischiefes to withstand. </l>
            <l>But al in vayne I spend my thoughtes </l>
            <l>it wil not be, I see, </l>
            <l>As long as all my sences thus </l>
            <l>by cares distracted bee. </l>
            <l>My mynd desyrous stil (Oh God,) the truth for to vnfold, </l>
            <l>With doubtful Dread is daunted so, that it can scant vpholde </l>
            <l>It selfe. O Brother beare, if way or meane of health thou know, </l>
            <l>Declare it out and sticke not all the truth to me to show. </l>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e103210">
              <speaker>Cre. </speaker>
              <l>The Oracle (most noble king) ys darke, and hidden lies. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e103230">
              <speaker>Oed. </speaker>
              <l>Who doubtful health to sicke men brings, all health to them denies. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e103250">
              <speaker>Cre. </speaker>
              <l>Apolloes vse yt is the troth in darkesome dens to hold. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e103270">
              <speaker>Oed. </speaker>
              <l>And Oedipus of Gods it hath thinges hidden to vnfold: </l>
              <l>Speake out, tell all, and spare not man: all doubtes I can discus. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e103300">
              <speaker>Cre. </speaker>
              <l>Apollo then (most noble King) himselfe commaundeth thus. </l>
              <l>By exile purge the Princes seat, and plague with vengeance due </l>
              <l>That haples wretch, whose bloudy handes of late King Laius slue: </l>
              <l>Before that this perfourmed bee, no hope of milder ayer: </l>
              <l>Wherfore do this (O King) or else All hope of helpe dispayre. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="82" xml:id="ep000251-088-b"/>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e103360">
              <speaker>Oe, </speaker>
              <l>Durst any man on earth attempte, that noble Prince to slay? </l>
              <l>Shew me the man that I may him dispatch out of the way. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e103390">
              <speaker>Cre. </speaker>
              <l>God graunt I may it safely tel: the hearyng was to terrible, </l>
              <l>My senses all amased are: it is a thing so horrible, </l>
              <l>That I abhorre to vtter it (oh God) for feare I quake </l>
              <l>And euen at the very thought my lims beginne to shake. </l>
              <l>Assoone as I Appollos Church, had entred in affrayd, </l>
              <l>Vppon my face flat downe I fell, and thus to him I prayd. </l>
              <l>Oh God if euer thou didst rue, on wretched misers state, </l>
              <l>If euer men opprest thou easd, or didst their cares abate, </l>
              <l>If euer thou in present neede didst present helpe declare, </l>
              <l>If euer thou afflicted Hartes with cares consumd didst spare: </l>
              <l>Shew now thy wonted elemency and pitty knowne of yore. </l>
              <l>Scant had I sayd: Resounding all the mountaynes thondring rore: </l>
              <l>And filthy feendes spout out their flames out of their darksome caues. </l>
              <l>And woods do quake, and hilles do moue, and vp the surging waues </l>
              <l>Do mount vnto the skies aloft, and I amased stand. </l>
              <l>Still looking for an aunsweare at Apollos sacred hand. </l>
              <l>When out with ruffled hayre disguisd the: Prophet comes at last: </l>
              <l>And when that shee had felt the heate of mighty Phoebus blast. </l>
              <l>All puffyng out she swelles in rage, and pattring still she raues, </l>
              <l>And scant she entred had into Apollos shyning caues, </l>
              <l>When out a thundring voyce doth brust that's farre aboue mans reach. </l>
              <l>So dreadful seemed then to me the mighty Phoebus speach. </l>
              <l>Than thus he spake aud thus at length into myne cares he rusht </l>
              <l>Whyle sprawling stil the Prophet lay before the doores in dust. </l>
              <l>The Thebane City neuer shal be free from plagues (quoth he,) </l>
              <l>Except from thense the Kingkiller forthwith expulsed bee: </l>
              <l>Vnto Apollo knowen he was, or euer he was borne. </l>
              <l>Do this: or else no hope of health, to this, the gods haue sworn. </l>
              <l>And as for thee, thou shalt not long in quiet state indure, </l>
              <l>But with thy self wage war thou shalt &amp; war thou shalt procure </l>
              <l>Vnto thy children deare: &amp; crepe agayn thou shalt into thy mothers wombe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e103710">
              <speaker>Oed. </speaker>
              <l>Loke what the Gods commaunded haue accomplished shalbe. </l>
              <l>Nor neuer shal these eyes of myne abyde the day to see, </l>
              <l>A King of kingdome spoyld by force, by guyle or crast supprest. </l>
              <l>A kinge to kinges the prop ought be, and chiefest cause of rest: </l>
              <l>No man regardes his death at all whom liuing he doth feare, </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000251-089-a"/>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e103770">
              <speaker>Cr. </speaker>
              <l>Great cause makes mee my Princes death conceale and closly beare </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e103790">
              <speaker>Oed. </speaker>
              <l>Ought any cause of feare or griefe, the duty for to let? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e103810">
              <speaker>Cre. </speaker>
              <l>The threatning of the prophesyes, do stil my breast beset. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e103830">
              <speaker>Oe. </speaker>
              <l>Let vs (sith God commaunds) forthwith some good attonement make </l>
              <l>If any way, or meanes there be their wrathful rage to slake. </l>
              <l>Thou God that sits on seate on high, and al the world dost guide, </l>
              <l>And thou by whose commaundement the Starres in Skies do glide: </l>
              <l>Thou, thou that onely ruler art of Seas, of Floods, and all. </l>
              <l>On thee and on thy Godhead great, for these requestes I call. </l>
              <l>Who so hath slayne king Laius, oh Ioue I do thee pray. </l>
              <l>Let thousand ils vpon him fall, before his dying day. </l>
              <l>Let him no health ne comfort haue, but al to crusht with cares, </l>
              <l>Consume his wretched yeares in griefe, &amp; though that death him spares </l>
              <l>Awhyle. Yet mischiefes all, at length vppon him light. </l>
              <l>With all the euils vnder Sun, that vgly monster smight. </l>
              <l>In exile let him liue a Slaue, the rated course of life. </l>
              <l>In shame, in care, in penury in daunger and in strife. </l>
              <l>Let no man on him pity take, let all men him reuyle. </l>
              <l>Let him his Mothers sacred Bed incestuously defyle. </l>
              <l>Lim him his father kill. And yet let him do mischiefes more. </l>
              <l>What thing more haynous can I wish then that I wisht before? </l>
              <l>Let him do all those illes I say, that I haue shund and past. </l>
              <l>All those and more (if more may be) oh God vpon him cast. </l>
              <l>Let him no hope of pardon haue: but sue and all in vayne. </l>
              <l>All hellish Furies on him light, for to encrease his payne. </l>
              <l>O Ioue powre downe thy fury greate, thy thundring thumpes out throw </l>
              <l>Let Boreas boysterous blastes and stormy plagues vpon him blow </l>
              <l>Consume him quight. Fret out his guttes with pockes and botches vile </l>
              <l>Let all diseases on him light that wretched bodyes fyle. </l>
              <l>Let these and more (if more may be) vppon that Monster fall. </l>
              <l>Let Harpies pawes and greedy paunche deuoure his members all. </l>
              <l>Let no man him regard: or seeke his limmes in grade to lay: </l>
              <l>But let him dye ten thousand deathes before his dying day. </l>
              <l>By this my Kingdome I do sweare, and Kingdome that I left </l>
              <l>By al my Countrey Gods that bene in Temples closely kept, </l>
              <l>I sweare, I vow, I do protest, and thereto witnes take: </l>
              <l>The Starres, the Seas, the Earth and all that ere thy hand did make. </l>
              <l>Except that I my selfe forthwith this bloudy monster find, </l>
              <l>To wreake the wrath of God some way with solempne oth I bynde. </l>
              <pb n="83" xml:id="ep000251-089-b"/>
              <l>And so my father, Polybius his happy dayes out lyue. </l>
              <l>And so my mother Merope, no mariage new contriue: </l>
              <l>As he shall dye that did this deede, and none shal him excuse. </l>
              <l>Whoso he be here I protest for that he shortly rues: </l>
              <l>But where this wicked deede was don Creon now tell me playne: </l>
              <l>Both by what meanes? &amp; where: and how Ring Laius was slayne. </l>
              <l>Creon. Passing through Castalia woods &amp; mountayns heapt with snoe </l>
              <l>Where groues and scrubs, and bushes thicke &amp; brambles sharp do groe. </l>
              <l>A threepathd crooked way there is that diuersly doth goe. </l>
              <l>One vnto Bacchus citty bends that Phoce doth hight, </l>
              <l>The other to Olenius, forth stretcheth out aright: </l>
              <l>The third that reacheth through the vales and by the riuers lyes </l>
              <l>Tends downe vnto the Bancks wherby Eleia, water plyes </l>
              <l>There vnawares (O piteous chaunce) a troup of theues entraps </l>
              <l>The noble prince, and murders him hence spring these great mishaps </l>
              <l>which heape you realms with hideous woes and plagues on euery side, </l>
              <l>By iust decree of heauenly powers which can no murder bide. </l>
              <l>But see Tiresias where he coms with old and trembling pace. </l>
              <l>I thincke Apolloes heauenly might haue brought him to this place. </l>
              <l>See where he comes: and Manto too, his steps directing stayes </l>
              <l>Tis he who for your grace (O king) and for your countrie prayes </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="ep000251-e104410">
            <pb xml:id="ep000251-090-a"/>
            <head>THE SECOND ACTE. THE SECOND SCENE. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000251-e104420">OEDIPVS. TYRESIAS. MANTO. </stage>
            <l>COme holy priest (to Phoebus next) </l>
            <l>these doubtfull aunswers lose: </l>
            <l>And whom that destnies will to dye, </l>
            <l>Straightwayes to me disclose. </l>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e104470">
              <speaker>TY. </speaker>
              <l>Renowmed Prince, though still I stand </l>
              <l>in silence dumme dismayde: </l>
              <l>And though by inwarde feare of mynde </l>
              <l>my lingring tonge is stayde: </l>
              <l>Yet pardon me (O noble Prince,) and geue me leaue a while. </l>
              <l>From lack of sight springs Ignoraunce which powre hath to exile </l>
              <l>Vnspotted Truth from doubtfull breasts. This thing ful well you knoes, </l>
              <l>But whither God and Countrey calles, with willing minde I goe. </l>
              <l>Let deadly fatall destentes, be boulted out at length. </l>
              <l>O King if I of greener yeares had now my wonted strength: </l>
              <l>This matter soone discust should be, and I would take in hande, </l>
              <l>My selfe in presence of the Gods, in temple for to stande. </l>
              <l>A mighty Oxe all coulourd white, vp on the Aulters reare, </l>
              <l>Which neuer yet on weried necke, the croked yoake did beare. </l>
              <l>And Manto thou, O daughter mine, mine onely prop and stay: </l>
              <l>The secret hidden misteries, and sacred signes out say. </l>
              <l>M A. The beast before the Aulter stands. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e104650">
              <speaker>T Y. </speaker>
              <l>To Gods a prayer make, </l>
              <l>And on the holy Aulters cke, some pleasaunt odors shake. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e104680">
              <speaker>M A. </speaker>
              <l>Tis done. And all the fiers fierce, with incence bright doe flame. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e104700">
              <speaker>T Y. </speaker>
              <l>O Manto now what signes seest thou? how doe thy matters frame? </l>
              <l>What? doth the fire, the Sacrifice encompas rounde about? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e104730">
              <speaker>MA. </speaker>
              <l>Not so. But first it mounts aloft, and streight it flasheth out. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e104750">
              <speaker>TY. </speaker>
              <l>Well Yet, how doth the sacred flame all shining bright and cleare </l>
              <l>It selfe on high vnto the Skies, with sparkelting flakes vpreare? </l>
              <l>Or doth it oft rebounding backe, it selfe, from Skyes vnfould? </l>
              <l>Or all with rumbling roring noyse, about the place ist rould? </l>
              <pb n="84" xml:id="ep000251-090-b"/>
              <l>Or dim'd with smoke, ist tost from place, to place, now heere, now theare? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e104810">
              <speaker>MA. </speaker>
              <l>Not one. But diuerse, colours mixt the flame doth with it beare. </l>
              <l>Much like vnto the Rainbow, which with sundry paynted hues </l>
              <l>Foreshewes vnto the husbandmen the weather that ensues. </l>
              <l>What colour it wants, or what it hath, to me is like vncertayne. </l>
              <l>Now is it black, now blue, now red, and euen now agayne </l>
              <l>Quight out it is. Yet once agayn, all fierce it flashing flames: </l>
              <l>But lo, yet mischiefs more then this, vnluckely it frames. </l>
              <l>The fier quight a sunder parts, and flame with flame doth fight. </l>
              <l>O father I abhorre to see, this vgly lothsome sight. </l>
              <l>The Wyne to blud is turned quight, and all the Prynces hed, </l>
              <l>With thicke black clouds encompast is, with smoke all ouerspred. </l>
              <l>O father tell what this portends? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e104940">
              <speaker>TY. </speaker>
              <l>What should I tell alas? </l>
              <l>My mynde for feare astonied stands, and trembling cold doth pas </l>
              <l>Through all my lims. What shall I say? or where shall I begin? </l>
              <l>O cruell Plagues, O wrekfull Gods, O vengeaunce due for sin. </l>
              <l>Some dyre and blouddy deed (Alas) these hydeous signes declare. </l>
              <l>What's that the Gods would haue reuealde, and yet doe bid beware </l>
              <l>To vtter it? By certaine signes their wrath is oft descride: </l>
              <l>Such signes appeere, and yet they seeme their fury great to hide. </l>
              <l>They are ashamde: I wot nere what. Come hither, quickly bring </l>
              <l>Some salt with thee, and it vpon the sacrifice goe fling. </l>
              <l>What? are their lookes pleasant and milde, and doe they gently bide </l>
              <l>The touching of thy sacred hands? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e105070">
              <speaker>MA. </speaker>
              <l>What may this thing betide? </l>
              <l>The Bull (a wonder great to see) his head on hie he lifts </l>
              <l>And turned still vnto the East, from thence it alway shifts, </l>
              <l>Still lothing as hee seemes to me, of heauen to see the light, </l>
              <l>Oft scouling with his blearing eyes with gastely ruthfull sight. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e105130">
              <speaker>TY. </speaker>
              <l>But doth one blow then driue to ground, or more the one they haue? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e105150">
              <speaker>MA. </speaker>
              <l>The Heifer as it seemde, enflamd with courage stoute and braue </l>
              <l>Vpon the mortall Blade did rush, and there hirselfe destries: </l>
              <l>When out the bloud it foming spoutes, and mounts vnto the Skies. </l>
              <l>The brawny Bull twise stroke or thrise, with groueling groning tyres, </l>
              <l>And toyling vp and down he moyles. And still to liue desires. </l>
              <l>And yet at length with much ado, his brutish breath expiers. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e105220">
              <speaker>TY. </speaker>
              <l>What? doth the wounde wide open gape, or is it closed vp? </l>
              <l>Or doth the deepnes of the hole, the bloud in soking sup? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e105250">
              <speaker>MA. </speaker>
              <l>Out of the wounded Heifers breast Black bluish waters rush. </l>
              <l>As for the Bull, but little bloud, out of his wounds doth gush. </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000251-091-a"/>
              <l>It back rebounds, and from his Mouth &amp; Eyes by streames doth flow. </l>
              <l>But what these dreadfull signes portend the Gods aloane doe know. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e105300">
              <speaker>TY. </speaker>
              <l>By this vnhappy Sacrifice, great feares within mee rise. </l>
              <l>But tell mee now: In the inner parts, what secret hidden lies? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e105330">
              <speaker>MA. </speaker>
              <l>O Father what meanes this (alas) that more then wonted guise </l>
              <l>The Inwards stir? and shake my hands, and heauing oft arise, </l>
              <l>The bloud by streames out of the vaynes, full straungly skips aloft. </l>
              <l>The heart all schorcht and hidden lies, and strykes are seene full oft, </l>
              <l>Of Colour very wan and pale: The chiefest parts doe want. </l>
              <l>The Lyuer blackish gall out spurts, and somwhat rysing pants. </l>
              <l>And that, that myschiefes great, to kingdoms doth foreshow: </l>
              <l>Two heads are seene, and yet both heads one skin doth ouergrow </l>
              <l>And ouerheales them quight, But yet the skin, it is so thin </l>
              <l>That easely one may discerne what lieth hid therein. </l>
              <l>And that which horror doth encrease, a man may plainly see </l>
              <l>How both the heart, the Lights, and Lungs, and all disturbed bee. </l>
              <l>The fearefull noyse and sound you heere is not of beasts, but fier </l>
              <l>That roaring on the Alters makes, presaging wrekefull yre </l>
              <l>Of angry Gods who doe foretell some purpose that they haue, </l>
              <l>For to reuenge some foule misdeede that vengeance iust doth craue. </l>
              <l>No part his proper place obserues, nor keepes his order due: </l>
              <l>But altogether quight disguisde, with an vnwonted hue. </l>
              <l>Mishapen, out of frame, transformde, displaced quight (alas) </l>
              <l>What thing is that the Gods entend ere long to bring to pas? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e105540">
              <speaker>OEd. </speaker>
              <l>Why than declare from whence, and why these deadly signes arise, </l>
              <l>With courage stout I will it heare, it shall not once aggrise </l>
              <l>By valiaunt mynd. Extremest ils haue power to banish feare. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e105580">
              <speaker>TY. </speaker>
              <l>You will wishe that vnhard which you so much desyre to heare. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e105600">
              <speaker>OEd. </speaker>
              <l>Yet sence the Gods wil haue him known tell me (I say) his name </l>
              <l>That siue your King. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e105630">
              <speaker>TY. </speaker>
              <l>Nor wing, nor womb of Bird or beast that same </l>
              <l>Can tell (O king) new sacrifice, new meanes we must inuent. </l>
              <l>From dredfull darke infernall damps some Fury must be sent </l>
              <l>These mischifes great for to vnfolde. Or els King Ditis hee, </l>
              <l>That Empyre keepes on griesly Ghosts, entreated needes must bee </l>
              <l>These things forthwith for to disclose. Tell who shall haue the charge, </l>
              <l>A King thou art, than maist not thou go through those kingdoms large. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e105710">
              <speaker>OEd. </speaker>
              <l>Than noble Creon thou shalt goe, this payne is first for thee: </l>
              <l>Who must this crown and kingdome great enioy after mee. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="ep000251-e105740">
          <pb n="81" xml:id="ep000251-091-b"/>
          <head>THE THIRDE ACTE. </head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000251-e105750">
            <head>THE FIRST SCENE. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000251-e105760">Oedipus. Creon. </stage>
            <l>THough that thy Face where sadnes sits </l>
            <l>in heauy mourning guise, </l>
            <l>Nought els portend, but dedly griefes, </l>
            <l>and mischiefes stil to ryse: </l>
            <l>Yet tel some meanes wherby at length </l>
            <l>the Gods we may appease, </l>
            <l>And purchasen to our Kingdomes wast, </l>
            <l>some hope of health and ease. </l>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e105850">
              <speaker>Cre. </speaker>
              <l>Alas you byd me that disclose which feare doth byd me hyde. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e105870">
              <speaker>Oed. </speaker>
              <l>It that the Thebane Citties great, by doleful plagues destryde. </l>
              <l>Perce not thy hart: yet oughtest thou. these Kingdomes for to rue, </l>
              <l>Which were vnto thy brothers house, of auncient title due. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e105910">
              <speaker>Cre. </speaker>
              <l>You wish the thing to know, which you wil wish vnknown at length. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e105930">
              <speaker>Oed. </speaker>
              <l>Why so? a simple remedy of litle force and strength </l>
              <l>Is ignoraunce of our estate when daungers vs betyde. </l>
              <l>But what? wilt thou so great a good for common safety hide? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e105970">
              <speaker>Cre. </speaker>
              <l>Irkesome Medcines and perilous in sickness I abhorre: </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e105990">
              <speaker>Oed. </speaker>
              <l>And I likewyse at Subiects hands disdayne to take a dorre, </l>
              <l>Speake out with speed, or else by proofe of torment thou shalt find </l>
              <l>How daungerous a case it is to gawle a Princes mynd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e106030">
              <speaker>Cre. </speaker>
              <l>Kinges often vse to wish vntolde, which they bad tel before. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e106050">
              <speaker>Oed. </speaker>
              <l>Go to, dispatch and cease in time to vexe me any more. </l>
              <l>Except that thou forthwith to me this heinous deede disclose: </l>
              <l>The gods I do protest, to death for al thou onely goes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e106090">
              <speaker>Cre. </speaker>
              <l>O pardon me most noble king. O let me hold my pes, </l>
              <l>Of al the gracis Princes graunt, what fauour may be lesse? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e106120">
              <speaker>Oed </speaker>
              <l>As though the silence hurts not more both king and countries weale: </l>
              <l>Then spech oft tymes: which subiects thoughts to Prices both reueale? </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000251-092-a"/>
              <l>Dispatch at once, stir me no more thou knowst my guise of olde. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e106160">
              <speaker>CRE. </speaker>
              <l>Silence denied, what priuileage may silly Subiect holde? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e106180">
              <speaker>OED. </speaker>
              <l>A traytor he is, who stlence keepes, when king commaunds to speake. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e106200">
              <speaker>CRE. </speaker>
              <l>Then pardon my constrayned speach, sith silence for to breake </l>
              <l>You me compell. A dolefull tale (O king) my tongue must tell, </l>
              <l>And which I feare your maiesty will not interpret well. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e106240">
              <speaker>OED. </speaker>
              <l>Was euer man rebukt for that, that he was bid to say? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e106260">
              <speaker>CRE. </speaker>
              <l>Well than since needes I must: I am contented to obay. </l>
              <l>A wood there is from City farre, enhaunst with stately trees: </l>
              <l>Where many a plant, and her be doth grow, which Phoebus neuer sees: </l>
              <l>With euer during bushes greene, the Cypresse there doth ryse, </l>
              <l>And puts his alde aud leffty had withing the cloude Skyes. </l>
              <l>The auncient Time eaten Oke with crooked bended lims. </l>
              <l>The Teyl tree fine: The Alder which in Neptunes kingdoms swims, </l>
              <l>The Bayes with bitter beries eke the Elmes deere friends to Vynes </l>
              <l>And many a noble tree besides, as Mirtles, 〈…〉 </l>
              <l>Amidst them all, one tree there is with large out 〈…〉 </l>
              <l>Whose roring sound, &amp; craking noyse the lesser woods Icharmes, </l>
              <l>And ouershades them all: a Tree of monstrous huge estate, </l>
              <l>Beset with fearefull woods: there is that dyre, and dreadfull gate, </l>
              <l>That leades to lothsome Lymbo Lake, and pyts that euer flowe. </l>
              <l>Where choked miry mud doth streame with slimy course full flowe. </l>
              <l>Here when the priest was entred in with comely aged pace, </l>
              <l>He stayed not: No neede there was, for night was still in place. </l>
              <l>Than all the ground wyde open gapes, &amp; smouthering vapours ryse, </l>
              <l>And fyre and smoke, &amp; styfling stink, mounts vp vnto the Skyes. </l>
              <l>The Priest with wayling werde iclad, his fatall red out tooke: </l>
              <l>And entring in, in blacke Aray, full often times it shooke. </l>
              <l>With heauy cheere and dolful pace: his hoary haire was twynde </l>
              <l>With bowes of mortall Ewe. A tree wherewith the mourners winde, </l>
              <l>Theyr mourning heads, &amp; Garlands make. In this guise all arayde, </l>
              <l>The sacred Priest doth enter in, with trembling lims dismayde: </l>
              <l>Than in the Sheepe and Oxen blacke, by backwarde course are drawn. </l>
              <l>And odoures sweete, &amp; Frankencence, on flaming fyres are thrown. </l>
              <l>The beasts on burning, Altars cast, do quake with schorched lims: </l>
              <l>And bloudy streames with fyre mixt, about the Aultars swims. </l>
              <l>Than on the darke internall Gods, and him that rules them all: </l>
              <l>With deadly shriking voyce aloude, the Prophet gins to call. </l>
              <l>And rouls the Magick verse in mouth, and hidden Artes doth proue: </l>
              <l>Which eyther power haue to appease or els the Gods to moue, </l>
              <l>Thair bloudy streaming Lycours black, with broyling heate doe boyle: </l>
              <pb n="86" xml:id="ep000251-092-b"/>
              <l>And all the Beasts consume and burn. The Prophet than to toyle </l>
              <l>Begins. And mixed wyne and Mylke vpon the Aultars throwes. </l>
              <l>And all the Dongeon darke, and wyde with streaming blood it flowes. </l>
              <l>Than out with thundring voyce agayne the Prophet calles and cryes. </l>
              <l>And straight as much with mumbling mouth he champs in secret wyse </l>
              <l>The trees do turne. The Riuers stād. The ground with roring shakes. </l>
              <l>And all the world as seemes to mee, with fearefull trembling quakes. </l>
              <l>I am heard, I am heard, than out aloude the Priest began to cry: </l>
              <l>Whan all the dampned soules by heapes abrode outrushing fly. </l>
              <l>Then woods with rumbling noyse, doe oft resounding make. </l>
              <l>And Heauen, and Earth together goe. And bowes and trees do crake. </l>
              <l>And Thunders roore. And Lightnings flash. And waues aloft doe fly. </l>
              <l>And ground retyres: and Dogs doe bawl: and Beastes are heard to cry. </l>
              <l>And whyther long of Acheron, that lothsom Flud that flowes </l>
              <l>All stinking streames: or of the earth, that out her Bowels throwes, </l>
              <l>Free place to Sprights to geue: or of that fierce infernall Hound, </l>
              <l>That at such times doth bustling make with chayns, &amp; railing sound. </l>
              <l>The Earth al wide it open gapes. And I did see on ground, </l>
              <l>The Gods with colour pale and wan, that those dark kingdoms keepe. </l>
              <l>And very night I saw in deede, and thousand shapes to creepe, </l>
              <l>From out those filthy stinking Lakes, and lothsom pits of Hell. </l>
              <l>Where all the euils vnder Son, in darksom shades doe dwell. </l>
              <l>So quaking all for feare I stoode with minde right sore apalde, </l>
              <l>Whilst on those Gods with trembling mouth the Priest full often calde. </l>
              <l>Who all at once, out of theyr dens did skip with griesly Face. </l>
              <l>And Monsters grim, and stinging Snakes seemd wander in that place. </l>
              <l>And all the fowlest Feendes of Hell, and Furies all were theare. </l>
              <l>And all transformed Ghosts &amp; sprights, that euer Hell did beare. </l>
              <l>With Cares, and all Diseases vyle, that mortall mynds doe crush, </l>
              <l>All those, and more I sawe out of those Dungeons deepe to rush, </l>
              <l>And Age I sawe, with riueled Face, and Neede, &amp; Feare, and Death. </l>
              <l>And Fyre, and flames, &amp; thousand ills out fro those Pits to breath. </l>
              <l>Then I was gon: and quight amazd. The wenche in worser case. </l>
              <l>And yet of olde, acquaynted with her Fathers Artes she was. </l>
              <l>The Priest himselfe vnmooued stoode, and boldly cited owt: </l>
              <l>Whole Armies of king Ditis men, who clustring in a Rowt: </l>
              <l>All flittring thin like Cloudes, disperst abrode in Ayre doe fly. </l>
              <l>And bearing sundry shapes and formes doe scud aboue in Sky, </l>
              <l>A thousand woods I thinke haue not so many leaues on trees. </l>
              <l>Ten thousand medowes fresh haue not so many flowers for bees. </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000251-093-a"/>
              <l>Ten hundred thousand riuers not so many Foule can show: </l>
              <l>Nor all the drops and streams, and gulphes that in the Seas do flow, </l>
              <l>If that they might be wayed, can sure so great a number make </l>
              <l>As could those shapes and formes that flew from out of Limbo lake. </l>
              <l>Both Tantalus and Zetus too, and pale Amphions Ghost: </l>
              <l>And A gaue, and after her ten thousand Sprightes do post. </l>
              <l>Than Pentheus, and more and more, in like estate ensue: </l>
              <l>Til out at length comes Laius with foule and grisly hue: </l>
              <l>Vncomly brest in wretched plight with fylth all ouergrowne: </l>
              <l>All perst with wounds, (I loth to speake) with bloud quight ouerflown </l>
              <l>A Miser ryght as seemd to me, and most of Misers all: </l>
              <l>Thus in this case, at length he spake, and thus began to call. </l>
              <l>O Cadmus cruel Citty vyle, that stil delightste in bloud, </l>
              <l>O Cadmus thou, which kinsmens death, accountst as chiefest good. </l>
              <l>Teare out the bloudy Bowels of your Children, learne of me, </l>
              <l>Do that, and rather more, then you would byde the day to see </l>
              <l>Like ills as late on mee are light. Loe mothers loue (alas) </l>
              <l>Hath causd the greatest misery that ere in Theba was. </l>
              <l>The Countrey with the wrath of Gods at this tyme is not tost. </l>
              <l>Nor yearth nor ayre infect is not the cause that all bene lost. </l>
              <l>No No. A bloudy King is cause of all these mischiefes great: </l>
              <l>A bloudy wretch: A wretched child that sits in Fathers Seate: </l>
              <l>And Mothers bed defyles (O wretch) and entreth in agayne, </l>
              <l>In places whence he came from once and doubleth so her payne, </l>
              <l>Whilst that hee fils the haples wombe wher in himselfe did lie </l>
              <l>With graceles seede and causeth her twise childbirthes pangues to try: </l>
              <l>Vnhappy Sonne, but Father worse and most vnhappy hee, </l>
              <l>By whom the lawes of sacred shame so sore confounded bee. </l>
              <l>For that that very bestes (almost) do all abhorre to do, </l>
              <l>Euen of his mothers body he hath brothers gotten two. </l>
              <l>O mischiefe great: O dredful deede, then Sphinx, O monster more: </l>
              <l>Example vnto ages all of Gods foretold before. </l>
              <l>But I thee, thee, that Scepter holdst, thy Father wil pursue, </l>
              <l>And wreacke my selfe on thee and thyne with plagues &amp; vengeance due. </l>
              <l>All restles rage of spite and paine I will vppon thee blow, </l>
              <l>And all the furies foule of hell vppon thee I will throw. </l>
              <l>I wil subuert thy Houses cleane, for this thy lothsome lust: </l>
              <l>I wil do this thou wretch: And thee, and thyne consume to dust. </l>
              <l>Wherfore dispatch at once (I say) into exile driue your King. </l>
              <l>That ground that first of all he leaues, with fresh grene grasse shall spring. </l>
              <pb n="87" xml:id="ep000251-093-b"/>
              <l>And sweete, and pleasaunt Ayre, and healthfull blasts shall ryse, </l>
              <l>And all the euills vnder Sun, that mortall men surprise: </l>
              <l>The Pocks, the Piles, the Botch, the blaine, &amp; death with him shall fly. </l>
              <l>And with him mischiefs all shall passe, and Monsters vnder Sky. </l>
              <l>And as for him I know hee would depart with willing mynde: </l>
              <l>But I will clog his Feete, and hands, his way he shall not finde. </l>
              <l>But groping with his aged staffe, shall passe from place to place. </l>
              <l>This shall he doe. And none shall rue vpon his ruthfull case. </l>
              <l>Rid you the Monster from the Earth, for Heauen let mee alone. </l>
              <l>No sooner sayd, but straight away, his dreadfull Ghost was gone. </l>
              <l>And fast by thousands after him, th'other Sprights in hyde: </l>
              <l>Than Cold &amp; trembling feare began through all my bones to glyde. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e107530">
              <speaker>OED. </speaker>
              <l>The thing I alwayes fearde, I see vpon mee now is layde: </l>
              <l>But slender props they are (God wot) whereby your Treason is stayde. </l>
              <l>Meropa my Mother deare, shall mee from this defend: </l>
              <l>Polybius eke shall purge mee quight, from Actions all, that tend </l>
              <l>To murder, or to incest vile, they both shall mee excuse. </l>
              <l>In such a case no meanes at all of tryall I refuse. </l>
              <l>Lay what you can vnto my charge. No fault in mee remayns. </l>
              <l>The Thebanes long or I came heere, of Laius death complayns. </l>
              <l>My Mother yet alyue, my Father still in like estate. </l>
              <l>No, no, this is some doltishe drift, of yon false Prophets pate. </l>
              <l>Or else some mighty God aboue, doth beare me no good will, </l>
              <l>And seekes by Plagues on mee to wreke, his wrathfull vengeaunce stil. </l>
              <l>Ah Sir I am glad at length I smell your drifts and fetches fyne. </l>
              <l>I know the whole confederacy your sleights I can vntwyne. </l>
              <l>That beastly Priest, that blearayed wretch beelyes the Gods and mee: </l>
              <l>And thee thou Traytour in my place hath promist king to bee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e107700">
              <speaker>CRE. </speaker>
              <l>Alas would I my Sister of, her lawfull kingdome spoyle? </l>
              <l>Thinke you such treason may haue place in brothers breast to boyle? </l>
              <l>Yf that myne Oth could me not keepe content with my degree: </l>
              <l>But that contemning meane estate, I would clime aloft to bee. </l>
              <l>Yet should ill Fortune mee deter, from such attempts I trowe: </l>
              <l>Whose guise it is on Princes heads, huge heapes of Cares to throwe. </l>
              <l>I would aduise your grace betimes this charge from you to cast: </l>
              <l>Least lingring long all vnawares, you be opprest at last. </l>
              <l>Assure your selfe, in baser state, more safer you may liue: </l>
              <l>And shun a thousand Cares, &amp; Griefs: which Princes hearts doe riue. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e107810">
              <speaker>OED. </speaker>
              <l>And dost thou me exhort thou slaue my kingdome for to leaue? </l>
              <l>O faythlesse head. O shamelesse heart, that could such treasons weaue? </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000251-094-a"/>
              <l>Darst thou attempt thou villayne vile this thing, to me to breake? </l>
              <l>And fearst thou not in such a cause so boldly for to speake. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e107860">
              <speaker>CRE. </speaker>
              <l>I would perswade them so (O King) who freely might possesse </l>
              <l>Their Realmes such piteous cares I see, do Prynces hearts oppresse: </l>
              <l>But as for you of force you must your Fortunes chainge abyde. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e107900">
              <speaker>OED. </speaker>
              <l>The surest way for them that gape for kingdoms large, &amp; wyde, </l>
              <l>Is first things meane, and rest, and peace, and base estate to prayse: </l>
              <l>And yet with Tooth and Nayle, to toyle to mount aloft alwayes. </l>
              <l>So often times, most restlesse beastes doe chiefly rest commend. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e107950">
              <speaker>CRE. </speaker>
              <l>Shall not my seruice long suffice my truth for to defend? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e107970">
              <speaker>OED. </speaker>
              <l>Time is the onely meanes for such, as thou to worke theyr will. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e107990">
              <speaker>CRE. </speaker>
              <l>It is so syr, but as for mee, of goods I haue my fill. </l>
              <l>A great resort. A pleasaunt life: from Princely cares exempt. </l>
              <l>All these might (surely) mee disswade from such a foule attempt. </l>
              <l>There is no day almost (O King) the whale yeare thorow out, </l>
              <l>Where in some royall gyfts are not from countreys round about </l>
              <l>Vnto mee sent, both Golde, and pearles, and things of greater cost, </l>
              <l>Which I let passe, least I should seeme but vainly for to bost. </l>
              <l>Besides the life of many a man hath bin preserude by mee. </l>
              <l>In such a bilsfull state (O King) what can there wanting bee? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e108090">
              <speaker>OE. </speaker>
              <l>(Good Fortune can no meane obserue, but stil she preaseth higher.) </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e108110">
              <speaker>CRE. </speaker>
              <l>Shall I than guiltlesse die (alas,) my cause and all vntryde? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e108130">
              <speaker>OED. </speaker>
              <l>Were vnto you at any time my life, my deedes discride? </l>
              <l>Did any man defend mee yet? or els my causes pleade? </l>
              <l>And guiltlesse yet I am condemn'de to this you doe mee leade, </l>
              <l>And mee expresse example giue, which I entend to take. </l>
              <l>What measure you doe meat to mee, lyke measure must I make. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e108190">
              <speaker>CRE. </speaker>
              <l>The minde which causelesse dred appawls, true cause of feare bewraies </l>
              <l>That conscience is not guiltles sure, which euery blast dismates. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e108220">
              <speaker>OED. </speaker>
              <l>Hee that in midst of perilles deepe, and daungers hath bene cast, </l>
              <l>Doth seeke all meanes to shun like ills as hee hath ouerpast. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e108250">
              <speaker>CR. </speaker>
              <l>So hatreds ryse. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e108270">
              <speaker>OE. </speaker>
              <l>Hee that to much doth vse ill will to feare, </l>
              <l>Unskilfull is: and knowes not how, hee ought him selfe to beare </l>
              <l>In kings estate. For feare alone doth Kingdomes chiefly keepe. </l>
              <l>Than hee that thus doth arme himselfe from feare all free may sleepe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e108320">
              <speaker>CRE. </speaker>
              <l>Who so the cruell tyrant playes, and guiltlesse men doth smight, </l>
              <l>Hee dreadeth them that him doe dread, so feare doth chiefly light </l>
              <l>On causers chiefe. A iust reuenge for bloudy mindes at last. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e108360">
              <speaker>OED. </speaker>
              <l>Come take this traytor vile away, In dongeon deepe him fast </l>
              <l>Enclose. There for his due deserts, let him abide such payne </l>
              <l>And scourge of minde (as meete it is) false traytors to sustayne. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="88" xml:id="ep000251-094-b"/>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e108400">
              <stage xml:id="ep000251-e108410">Chorus. </stage>
              <l>SEt, see, the myserable State, </l>
              <l>of Prynces carefull lyfe. </l>
              <l>What raging storms? what bloudy broyles? </l>
              <l>what toyle? what endlesse stryfe </l>
              <l>Doe they endure? (O God) what plagues? </l>
              <l>what griefe do they sustayne? </l>
              <l>A Princely lyfe: No. No. (No doubt) </l>
              <l>an euer duringe payne. </l>
              <l>A state ene fit for men on whom Fortune woulde wreke her will. </l>
              <l>A place for Cares to couch them in. A doore wyde open still </l>
              <l>For griefes and daungers all that ben to enter when they list. </l>
              <l>A king these Mates must euer haue, it bootes not to resist. </l>
              <l>Whole fluds of priuy pinching feare, great anguishe of the minde: </l>
              <l>Apparant plagues, &amp; dayly griefes. These playfayres Princes finde. </l>
              <l>And other none, with whom they spend, and passe theyr wretched dayes. </l>
              <l>Thus hee that Princes liues, and base Estate together wayes: </l>
              <l>Shall finde the one a very hell, a perfect infelicity: </l>
              <l>The other eke a heauen right, exempted quight from mysery. </l>
              <l>Let OEdipus example bee of this vnto you all, </l>
              <l>A Mirrour meete. A Patern playne, of Princes carefull thrall. </l>
              <l>Who late in perfect Ioy as seem'de, and euerlasting blis, </l>
              <l>Triumphantly his life out led, a Myser now hee is, </l>
              <l>And most of wretched Misers all, euen at this present tyme, </l>
              <l>With doubtfull waues of feare Itost, subiect to such a Cryme </l>
              <l>Whereat my tongue amased stayes, God graunt that at the last, </l>
              <l>It fall not out as Creon tolde. Not yet the worst is past, </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="ep000251-e108680">
          <pb xml:id="ep000251-095-a"/>
          <head>THE FOVRTH ACTE. </head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000251-e108690">
            <head>THE FIRSTE SCENE. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000251-e108700">OEdipus. Iocasta. </stage>
            <l>MY mynde with doubtfull waues of dread, </l>
            <l>is tossed to and fro, </l>
            <l>I wot not what to say (Alas) </l>
            <l>I am tormented so. </l>
            <l>For all the Gods on me doe cry, </l>
            <l>for paynes and vengeaunce due. </l>
            <l>They say that these my guiltlesse hands. </l>
            <l>king Laius lately slue. </l>
            <l>But this my conscience voyde of crime </l>
            <l>and mynde from mischiefe free: </l>
            <l>To Gods vntried, to mee well known denies it so to bee: </l>
            <l>Full well I doe remember once, by chaunce I did dispatch, </l>
            <l>A man who sought by force with mee presumptuously to match. </l>
            <l>His purpose was (a fond attempt) my Chariot for to stay, </l>
            <l>This I remember well enough, the strife was in the way. </l>
            <l>And he a man well steept in yeares, and I a lusty bloud, </l>
            <l>And yet of meere disdayne and pride in vayne hee mee withstood. </l>
            <l>But this from, Thebes farre was done, a croked three pathd way, </l>
            <l>That was the place in which we fought: it hard by Phocis lay. </l>
            <l>Deare Wyfe resolue my doubts at once, and mee expresly tell. </l>
            <l>How old was Laius the King whan this mischaunce befell? </l>
            <l>Was he of fresh and lusty yeares? or stricken well in age </l>
            <l>When he was kilde? O ease my thoughts of this tormenting rage. </l>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e108940">
              <speaker>IOC. </speaker>
              <l>Betwixt an old man an a yong: but nearer to an olde. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e108960">
              <speaker>OED. </speaker>
              <l>Were there great Bands of men with him his Person to vpholde? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e108980">
              <speaker>IOC. </speaker>
              <l>Some by the way deceiued were, and some deterd by payne. </l>
              <l>A fewe by toyle and labour long, did with their Prince remayne. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109010">
              <speaker>OE. </speaker>
              <l>Were any slayne in his defence? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109030">
              <speaker>IO. </speaker>
              <l>Of one report is rife, </l>
              <l>Who constant in his princes cause full stoutly lost his lyfe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109060">
              <speaker>OED. </speaker>
              <l>It is enough, I knowe the man that hath this mischiefe done. </l>
              <l>The number and the place agrees. The time vntried alone </l>
              <l>Remaynes: Than tell what time hee died, and when that he was slaine. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109100">
              <speaker>IOC. </speaker>
              <l>Tis ten yeares since: you now reuiue my chifest cares againe. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="ep000251-e109120">
            <pb n="89" xml:id="ep000251-095-b"/>
            <head>THE FOVRTH ACTE. THE SECOND SCENE. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000251-e109130">Senex. OEdipus. </stage>
            <l>THe Corinth people all (O King) </l>
            <l>in Fathers place to rayn </l>
            <l>Doe call your Grace: Polybius doth </l>
            <l>eternall rest obtayn. </l>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109180">
              <speaker>OED. </speaker>
              <l>O God what Fortune vyle doth mee </l>
              <l>oppresse on euery side? </l>
              <l>How doe my sorrowes still encrease? </l>
              <l>Tell how my Father dide. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109230">
              <speaker>SEN. </speaker>
              <l>No sicknesse (sir) but very age did of his life him reaue. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109250">
              <speaker>OED. </speaker>
              <l>And is hee dead: in deede? not slayne? what ioy may I conceave? </l>
              <l>How may I now triumph? the Gods to witnesse I doe call, </l>
              <l>To whom are known my hidden thoughts and secret workings al: </l>
              <l>Now may I lift to skyes my hands, my hands from mischiefe free. </l>
              <l>But yet the chiefest cause of feare remayneth still to mee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109310">
              <speaker>SEN. </speaker>
              <l>Your Fathers kingdom ought al dred out of your mind to driue. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109330">
              <speaker>OED. </speaker>
              <l>That I confesse. But secret thoughts my trembling heart do riue </l>
              <l>With inward doubt of deepe distresse, my Mother I do feare. </l>
              <l>This grudge is that continually my heart doth rent and teare. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109370">
              <speaker>SEN. </speaker>
              <l>Do you your Mother feare? on your return that onely slayes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109390">
              <speaker>OED. </speaker>
              <l>I feare not her: but from her sight, a godly zeale mee frayes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109410">
              <speaker>S. </speaker>
              <l>What will you her a Wydow leaue? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109430">
              <speaker>OE. </speaker>
              <l>Now, now, thou woūdst my heart. </l>
              <l>This, this, and onely this (alas,) is cause of all my smart. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109460">
              <speaker>SEN. </speaker>
              <l>Tell me (O king) what doubtfull feare? doth presse thy princely brest: </l>
              <l>Kings councels I can well conceale that ben with Cares opprest. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109490">
              <speaker>OED. </speaker>
              <l>Least as Apollo hath forefolde, I should a Mariage make </l>
              <l>With myne owne Mother: only this fowle feare doth make me quake. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109520">
              <speaker>SEN. </speaker>
              <l>Such vayne &amp; peuysh feares, at length from out your breast exyle. </l>
              <l>Meropa your Mother is not in deede, you do your selfe beguile. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109550">
              <speaker>OED. </speaker>
              <l>What vauntage should it be to her adopted Sonnes to haue? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109570">
              <speaker>SEN. </speaker>
              <l>A kingdom she shall gayne thereby. Her Husband layde in graue. </l>
              <l>The chiefest prop to stay her Realmes from present confusion, </l>
              <l>In children for to haue: and hope of lawfull succession. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000251-096-a"/>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109610">
              <speaker>OED. </speaker>
              <l>What are the meanes whereby thou dost these secrets vnderstand. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109630">
              <speaker>SEN. </speaker>
              <l>My selfe (your grace) an Infant gaue into your fathers hand. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109650">
              <speaker>OED. </speaker>
              <l>Didst thou me to my Father geue? Who than gaue me to thee? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109670">
              <speaker>SEN. </speaker>
              <l>A Sheparde str; that wanted on Cytheron Hills to bee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109690">
              <speaker>OE. </speaker>
              <l>What made thee in those woods to raunge? what hadst thou there to do? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109710">
              <speaker>SEN. </speaker>
              <l>Vpon those Hils my Beasts I kept, somtime a Sheepeherde to. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109730">
              <speaker>OE. </speaker>
              <l>What nots, what priuy marks hast thou, wherby thou dost me kno? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109750">
              <speaker>SE. </speaker>
              <l>The holes that through your feete are borde from whence your name did gro. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109770">
              <speaker>OE. </speaker>
              <l>Declare forthwith what was his name that gaue me vnto thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109790">
              <speaker>SE. </speaker>
              <l>The kings chief Shephard than that was, deliuered you to mee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109810">
              <speaker>OE. </speaker>
              <l>What was his name? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109830">
              <speaker>SE. </speaker>
              <l>O king old mens remembrance soone doth fayle: </l>
              <l>Obliuion for the chiefest part, doth boary heads assayle. </l>
              <l>And drowns their former memory of things long out of mynde. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109870">
              <speaker>OE. </speaker>
              <l>What? canst thou know the man by sight? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109890">
              <speaker>S. </speaker>
              <l>Perhaps I should him finde, </l>
              <l>And know by Face. Things ouer whelmd by time, and quight opprest. </l>
              <l>A small marke oft to mynde reuokes, and fresh renues in brest. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109930">
              <speaker>OE. </speaker>
              <l>Sirs bid the Herdmen forth with driue theyr Beasts to Aulters all. </l>
              <l>Away with speede, make hast, the Master Sheepherds to mee call. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e109960">
              <speaker>SE. </speaker>
              <l>Sith that your destiny this doth hyde, and Fortune it detayne </l>
              <l>And closely keepe, let it be so, from opening that refrayne. </l>
              <l>That long canceald hath hidden lyen, that seeke not to disclose: </l>
              <l>Such things outsercht and found oftimes agaynst the sercher goes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e110010">
              <speaker>OE. </speaker>
              <l>Can any mischiefe greater be? than this that now I feare. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e110030">
              <speaker>SE. </speaker>
              <l>Aduise you wel remembre fyrst what weight this thing doth beare: </l>
              <l>That thus you goe about to search, and slit with Tooth and Nayle, </l>
              <l>Obserue the golden meane: beware beare still and equall sayle. </l>
              <l>Your Countreys wealth (O King) your lyfe, and all vpon this lyes. </l>
              <l>Though you stir not, bee sure at length your Fortune you escryes. </l>
              <l>A happy state for to disturbe doth nought at all behoue. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e110100">
              <speaker>OE. </speaker>
              <l>When things be at the worst, of them a man may safely moue. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e110120">
              <speaker>SE. </speaker>
              <l>Can you haue ought more excellent? than is a Prynces state? </l>
              <l>Beware least of your Parents found it you repent to late. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e110150">
              <speaker>OE. </speaker>
              <l>No (father) no I warrant that: repent not I (I trow.) </l>
              <l>I seeke it not to that entent. I haue decreed to know, </l>
              <l>The matter at the full. Wherefore I will it now pursus. </l>
              <l>Lo Phorbas: where hee trembling coms, with comely aged hue. </l>
              <l>To whom of all the kinges flocke than, the care and charge was due. </l>
              <l>Dost thou his name, his speach his Face, or yet his person know? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e110220">
              <speaker>SE. </speaker>
              <l>Me thinks I should haue seene his Face, and yet I cannot show </l>
              <l>The places where I haue him seene, small time brings such a chainge, </l>
              <pb n="90" xml:id="ep000251-096-b"/>
              <l>As well acquaynted Faces ost, to vs appeare still strainge. </l>
              <l>This looke is neyther throughly known, nor yet vnknown to mee, </l>
              <l>I cannot tell: I doubt it much, and yet it may bee hee. </l>
              <l>In Laius tyme long since when hee these Kindomes great did keepe? </l>
              <l>Wast thou not on Citheron hils chiefe Shepard to his sheepe? </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="ep000251-e110300">
            <head>THE FOVRTH ACTE. THE THIRDE SCENE. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000251-e110310">Phorbas. Senex. OEdipus. </stage>
            <l>SOmetime a charge of sheepe I had, </l>
            <l>vnworthy though I weer. </l>
            <l>And did vpon those hills chiefe rule </l>
            <l>on other Shepards beare. </l>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e110360">
              <speaker>SE. </speaker>
              <l>Knowst thou not me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e110380">
              <speaker>PH. </speaker>
              <l>I cannot tell. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e110400">
              <speaker>OE. </speaker>
              <l>Didst thou once geue this man </l>
              <l>A Childe. Speake out, why dost thou stay? </l>
              <l>if so, declare it than. </l>
              <l>Why dost thou blush and doubting stand, </l>
              <l>troth seeketh no delay? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e110460">
              <speaker>PH. </speaker>
              <l>Things out of minde you call agayne, almost quight worne away. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e110480">
              <speaker>OE. </speaker>
              <l>Confesse thou slaue, or els I sweare, thou that constrayned bee </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e110500">
              <speaker>PH. </speaker>
              <l>In deede I doe remembre once, an Infant yong by mee, </l>
              <l>Delyuered was vnto this Man: but well I wot in vayne, </l>
              <l>I know he could not long endure, nor yet alyue remayne. </l>
              <l>Long since he is dead (I know it well) hee liues not at this day. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e110550">
              <speaker>SE. </speaker>
              <l>Eo? God forbid, he liues no doubt, and long may liue I pray. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e110570">
              <speaker>OE. </speaker>
              <l>Why dost thou say the child is dead, that thou this man didst giue? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e110590">
              <speaker>PH. </speaker>
              <l>With Irons sharp his feete were board, I know he could not liue, </l>
              <l>For of the sore a swelling rose, I saw the bloud to gush </l>
              <l>From out of both the wounds: and down by powring streames to flush. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb xml:id="ep000251-097-a"/>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e110630">
              <speaker>SEN. </speaker>
              <l>Now stay (O king) no farther now, you know almost the troth. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e110650">
              <speaker>OE. </speaker>
              <l>Whose child was it?  tell me forthw. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e110670">
              <speaker>PH. </speaker>
              <l>I dare not for mine Othe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e110690">
              <speaker>OE. </speaker>
              <l>Thine Oth thou slaue? Some fyre here. Ile charme thine Othe and thee, </l>
              <l>With fyre &amp; flames: except forthwith thou tell the troth to mee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e110720">
              <speaker>PH. </speaker>
              <l>O pardon me, though rade I seeme, I seeke nor to withstand name? </l>
              <l>Your graces minde: (most noble king.) My life is in your hand. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e110750">
              <speaker>OED. </speaker>
              <l>Tell me the troth, what child, &amp; whose, What was his Mothers </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e110770">
              <speaker>P. </speaker>
              <l>Born of your wyfe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e110790">
              <speaker>OE. </speaker>
              <l>O gaping earth deuour my body quight: </l>
              <l>Or else thou God that ruler art of houses voyde of light, </l>
              <l>To Hell my Saule with thunder boltes to Hell my Soule down dryue. </l>
              <l>Where griesly Ghosts in darkenesse deepe, and endlesse payne do lyue. </l>
              <l>For thee alone, these Plagues doe rage. For thee these mischiefes ryse. </l>
              <l>For thee, the Earth lyes desolate. For thee thou wretch the Skies </l>
              <l>Infected are. For thee, for thee, and for the filthy lust, </l>
              <l>A hundred thousand guiltlesse men, consumed are to dust. </l>
              <l>O people throw: cast heapes of stones vpon this hatefull Hed: </l>
              <l>Bath all your swords within my brest: you furies ouershed </l>
              <l>My restlesse thoughts, with raging woes and plungde in seas of pain. </l>
              <l>Let mee those hōrrors still endure, which damned soules sustain. </l>
              <l>You citizens of Stately Thebes vex me with torments dile. </l>
              <l>Let Father, Son, and Wyfe, and all with vengeance me pursue. </l>
              <l>Let those that for my sake alone with plagues tormented bee </l>
              <l>Throw darts, cast stones, fling fier and flames, and tortures all on mee. </l>
              <l>O shame: O slaunder of the World: O hate of Gods aboue. </l>
              <l>Confounder O of Nature thou to lawes of sacred loue, </l>
              <l>Euen from thy birth an open Foe. Thou didst deserue to dye </l>
              <l>As soone as thou wast born. Go, go, vnto the Court thee hye, </l>
              <l>There with thy Mother (slaue) triumph reioyce as thou maist do. </l>
              <l>Who hast thy house encreased with vnhappy children so. </l>
              <l>Make haste with speede, away, some thing thy mischiefs worthy finde. </l>
              <l>And on thy selfe wrecke all the spight of thy reuenging minde. </l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="91" xml:id="ep000251-097-b"/>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e111040">
              <stage xml:id="ep000251-e111050">Chorus. </stage>
              <l>FOrtune the guide of humaine lyfe doth al things chaunge at will. </l>
              <l>And stirring stil, with restles thoughts our wretched mindes doth fill. </l>
              <l>In vayn men striue their stats to kepe when hideous tempests rise: </l>
              <l>And blustring windes of daungers deepe sets death before their eyis. </l>
              <l>Who saith he doth her fauning feele? &amp; chaungeth not his minde, </l>
              <l>When fickle fight of Fortunes wheele doth turne by course of kinde. </l>
              <l>These greuous plagues from priuat house to princely Thrones do flow, </l>
              <l>And oft thier minds with cares they souse and thick vpon them strow. </l>
              <l>Whole heapes of griefe and dyre debate, a wofull thing to see: </l>
              <l>A Princely lyfe to mysers state, conuerted for to bee. </l>
              <l>O OEdipus thy fatall fall, thy dreadfull mischiefs ryght. </l>
              <l>Thy dolfull state, thy mysery, thy thrise vnhappy plight: </l>
              <l>These things shall blase through all the world: what heart may then reioyce </l>
              <l>At thy distresse? I can no more: my teares doe stop my voyce. </l>
              <l>But what is he that yonder stamps? and raging puffs and blowes. </l>
              <l>And often shakes his vexed head, some mischiefe great hee knowes. </l>
              <l>Good sir your countnaunce doth import some great and fearefull thing, </l>
              <l>Tell vs therefore (if that you may) what newes from Court you bring. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="ep000251-e111240">
          <head>THE FIFTE ACTE. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000251-e111250">NVNTIVS. </stage>
          <l>When OEdipus accursed wretch, </l>
          <l>his fatall fals had spied, </l>
          <l>To hell be damnd his wretched soule </l>
          <l>and on the Gods he cryed </l>
          <l>For vengeaunce due. And posting fast </l>
          <l>with franticke moode griesly hue, </l>
          <l>Vnto his dole full Court hee went, </l>
          <l>his thoughts for to pursue. </l>
          <l>Much like a Lion ramping wylde, his furious head that shakes. </l>
          <l>And roares with thundring mouth alowd, and often gnashing makes, </l>
          <l>None otherwise this miser farde. A lothsome sight to see. </l>
          <l>Besides himselfe for very rage, he still desires to dye. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000251-098-a"/>
          <l>And rowling round his wretched Eyes with vysage pale and wan: </l>
          <l>Ten thousand Curses out he powres. Himselfe the vnhappiest man </l>
          <l>Of all that liue, he doth account: as iustly he may doe. </l>
          <l>A wretch, a slaue, a caitife vyle. The cause of all our woe. </l>
          <l>And in this case enflamd with spight he cries, he stamps, he raues. </l>
          <l>And boyling in his secret thoughts, he still desyres to haue </l>
          <l>All torments vnder sun that may his Cares conceiude encrease. </l>
          <l>O wretched wyght, what should hee doe? What man may him release? </l>
          <l>Thus foming all for rage at mouth, with sighes, and sobs, &amp; grones, </l>
          <l>His damned head ten thousand times, as oft his weryed bones </l>
          <l>He beats. And often puffing makes, and roares, and swels, &amp; sweats. </l>
          <l>And on the Gods for death hee calles, for Death hee still entreats, </l>
          <l>Three times he did begin to speake: and thryse his tong did stay. </l>
          <l>At length he cried out alowd: O wretch. Away, away. </l>
          <l>Away thou monstrous Beast (he sayd:) wilt thou prolong thy lyfe? </l>
          <l>Nay rather some man strike this breast with strooke of bloudy knyfe. </l>
          <l>Or all you Gods aboue on mee your flaming fiers outcast: </l>
          <l>And dints of Thunderbolts down throw. This is my prayer last. </l>
          <l>What greedy vile deuouring Gripe, vpon my guts will gnaw? </l>
          <l>That Tigre fierce my hatefull limmes will quight asunder draw? </l>
          <l>Loe, here I am you Gods: Lee, heere, wreke now on me your will. </l>
          <l>Now, now you fyry Feendes of Hell, of vengeaunce take your fill. </l>
          <l>Send out some wilde outragious beast send Dogs mee to deuoure. </l>
          <l>Or els all ils you can deuise, at once vpon me powre. </l>
          <l>O wofull soule. O sinfull wretch. Why dost thou feare to dye? </l>
          <l>Death only rids from woes thou knowst. Than stoutly Death defle. </l>
          <l>With that his bloudy fatall Blade, from out his sheath he drawes. </l>
          <l>And lowd he rores, with thundring voice. Thou beast why dost thou pawse? </l>
          <l>Thy Father cursed caitife thou, thy Father thou hast slayne </l>
          <l>And in thy Mothers bed hast left an euerduring slayne. </l>
          <l>And Brothers thou hast got: nay Sons thou liest: thy Brothers all </l>
          <l>They are. Thus for thy monstrous lust thy Countrey down doth fall. </l>
          <l>And thinkst thou than for all these ils enough so short a payne? </l>
          <l>Thynkst thou the Gods will be apeasde, if thou forth with be slayne? </l>
          <l>So many mischiefes don: and ist enough one stroke to byde? </l>
          <l>Account'ste thou it sufficient paynes, that once thy sword should glide </l>
          <l>Quight through thy guilty breast for all? why than dispatch and dye. </l>
          <l>So maist thou recompence thy Fathers death sufficiently. </l>
          <l>Let it be so: what mends vnto thy Mother will thou make? </l>
          <l>Vnto thy children what? these plagues (O wretch) how wilt thou slake? </l>
          <pb n="92" xml:id="ep000251-098-b"/>
          <l>That thus for thee thy countrey mastes? Ohe push shall ende them all. </l>
          <l>A proper fetch. A fine deuise. For thee a worthy fall. </l>
          <l>Inuent thou monstrous beast forthwith: a fall euen worthy for </l>
          <l>Thy selfe inuent: whom all men hate and loth, and doe abhor. </l>
          <l>And as dame Natures lawfull course is broke (O wretch) by thee. </l>
          <l>So let to such a mischiefe great, thy Death agreeing bee. </l>
          <l>O that I might a thousand times, my wretched lyfe renewe. </l>
          <l>O that I might reuyue and dye by course in order dewe. </l>
          <l>Ten hundred thousand times &amp; more: than should I vengeance take </l>
          <l>Vpon this wretched head. Than I perhaps in part should make </l>
          <l>A meete amends in deede, for this my fowle and lothsom Sin. </l>
          <l>Than should the proofe of payne reproue the life that I liue in. </l>
          <l>The choyse is in thy hand thou wretch, than vse thine owne discretion. </l>
          <l>And finde a meanes, whereby thou maist come to extreame confusion. </l>
          <l>And that, that oft thou maist not doe, let it prolonged bee. </l>
          <l>Thus, thus, maist thou procure at length an endlesse death to thee. </l>
          <l>Serch out a death whereby thou mayst perpetuall shame obtayne: </l>
          <l>And yet not dye. But still to liue in euerlasting payne. </l>
          <l>Why stayst thou man? Go to I say: what meane these blubbring teares? </l>
          <l>Why weepst thou thus? Alas to late. Leaue of thy foolysh feares. </l>
          <l>And ist enough to weepe thinkst thou? shall teares and wayling serue? </l>
          <l>No wretch it shall not be. Thou dost ten thousand deaths deserue. </l>
          <l>Myne eyes doe dally with mee I see, and teares doe still out powre. </l>
          <l>Shall teares suffice? No, no, not so I shall them better scowre, </l>
          <l>Out with thine Eyes (he sayd:) and than with fury fierce enflam'de. </l>
          <l>Like to a bloudy raging Feend and monstrous beast vntamde. </l>
          <l>With fiery flaming spotted Cheekes his breast he often beats. </l>
          <l>And scratch, and teare his Face hee doth and Skin a sunder freats. </l>
          <l>That scarse his eyes in head could stand so sore he them besets. </l>
          <l>With furious fierce outrageous minde hee stamps and cries alowd: </l>
          <l>And roares &amp; rayles, with ramping rage. Thus in this case he stood, </l>
          <l>Perplext, and vexed sore in minde, with deadly sighs and teares. </l>
          <l>When sodenly all franticklike himselfe from ground hee reares. </l>
          <l>And rooteth out his wretched Eyes, and sight a sunder teares. </l>
          <l>Than gnasheth he his bloudy Teeth, and bites, and gnawes, &amp; champs, </l>
          <l>His Eyes all bathd and brude in bloud, for fury fierce he stamps. </l>
          <l>And raging more than needes (alas,) his Eyes quight rooted out: </l>
          <l>The very holes in vayne hee scrapes so sore the wretch doth dout: </l>
          <l>Least sight should chaunce for to remayne he rents and mangels quight </l>
          <l>His Face, his Nose, his Mouth, and all whereon his hands do light </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000251-099-a"/>
          <l>Hee rygs and ryues. Thus fowly rayd (alas) in piteous plight: </l>
          <l>At length his head aloft he lifts, and therewith geues a shright. </l>
          <l>And whan he sees that all is gone, both light, and sight, and all. </l>
          <l>Than schriching out: he thus begins vpon the Gods to call. </l>
          <l>Now spare you Gods, now spare at length my countrey prest to fall. </l>
          <l>I haue done that you did cōmaund: Your wraths reuenged bee. </l>
          <l>This wretched looke, this mangled face, is fittest now for mee. </l>
          <l>Thus speaking, down the blackish bloud by streams doth gushing flow </l>
          <l>Into his mouth. And clottred lumps of flesh the place doth strow </l>
          <l>Wherein hee standes. </l>
          <l>Beware betimes, by him beware, I speake vnto you all. </l>
          <l>Learne Iustice, truth, and feare of God by his vnhappy fall. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000251-e112300">Chorus. </stage>
          <l>MAns lyfe with tumbling fatal course of fortunes wheele is rowld, </l>
          <l>To it giue place for it doth run all swiftly vncontrowld. </l>
          <l>And Cares &amp; teares are spent in vayn, for it cannot be slayed: </l>
          <l>Syth his decree of heauenly powers perforce must be obayed. </l>
          <l>What mankind byded or does on earth it commeth from aboue, </l>
          <l>Then wayling grones powrd out in griefe do nought at all behoue. </l>
          <l>Our life must haue her pointed course, (alas) what shall I say. </l>
          <l>As fates decree, so things do run, no man can make them stay. </l>
          <l>For at our byrth to Gods is known our latter dying day. </l>
          <l>No Prayer, no Arte, not God himselfe may fatall fates resist. </l>
          <l>But fastned all in fixed courte, vnchaunged they persist. </l>
          <l>Such ende them still ensues as they appointed were to haue, </l>
          <l>Than fly all feare of Fortunes chaung, leeke hot to lyue a slaue </l>
          <l>Enthrald in bondage vyle to feare. For feare doth often bring </l>
          <l>Destnies that dreaded ben and mischiefs feard vpon vs fling. </l>
          <l>Yea many a man hath come vnto his fatall ende by feare. </l>
          <l>Wherefore set peuish feare aside, and worthy courage beare. </l>
          <l>And thou that subiect art to death. Regard thy latter day. </l>
          <l>Thinke no man blest before his ende. Aduise thee well and stay. </l>
          <l>Be sure his lyfe, and death, and all, be quight exempt from mysery: </l>
          <l>Ere thou do once presume to say: this man is blest and happy. </l>
          <l>But out alas, see where he coms: a wretch withouten Guide, </l>
          <l>Bereft of sight. Halfe spoyld of lyfe: without all Pomp, and Pride </l>
          <l>(That vnto Kings Estate belonge.) </l>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="ep000251-e112550">
            <pb n="93" xml:id="ep000251-099-b"/>
            <head>THE FIFTE ACTE. THE SECOND SCENE. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000251-e112560">OEdipus. Chorus, Iocasta. </stage>
            <l>WEll, well, tis done: more yet? No, no, </l>
            <l>no mischiefs more remaynee. </l>
            <l>My Fathers Rytes performed are. </l>
            <l>What God on Mysers paynes </l>
            <l>That rues within this Cloud hath rolde, </l>
            <l>and wrapt my wretched Pate. </l>
            <l>Ah sir: this is a life alone. </l>
            <l>This is a happy State. </l>
            <l>This is a case ene fit for thee, </l>
            <l>for thee thou wretch, for thee. </l>
            <l>From whose accursed sight the Sun, the Stars and all doe flee. </l>
            <l>Yet mischiefs more, who giues to doe? The dreadfull day I haue </l>
            <l>Escapt. Thou filthy Paracide: thou vile mischieuous Slaue. </l>
            <l>Vnto thy right hand nought thou owst, all things performed bee. </l>
            <l>O woe is mee that euer I liu'de this lucklesse day to see. </l>
            <l>Where am I now? Alas, alas, the light and all doth mee </l>
            <l>Abhor: O wretched OEdipus this looke is first for thee. </l>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e112740">
              <speaker>CHO. </speaker>
              <l>See, see, where Iocasta coms, with fierce and furious moode, </l>
              <l>Quight past her selfe. For very rage shee frets and waxeth woode. </l>
              <l>Much like to Cadmus daughter mad, who late hir Sonne did kill. </l>
              <l>Fayne would she speake her mynde: for seare (alas) she dares not: still </l>
              <l>Shee stayes, and yet from out her breast these ills haue quight exilde </l>
              <l>All shame fastnes. See how shee lookes, with coūt'naunce fierce &amp; wilde. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e112810">
              <speaker>IO. </speaker>
              <l>Fayne would I speake, I am afraide. For what should I thee call </l>
              <l>My Son? doubt not. Thou art my Son. My Son thou art for all </l>
              <l>These mischiefs great: alas, alas I shame my Son to see. </l>
              <l>O cruell Son. Where dost thou turn thy Face? Why dost thou flee </l>
              <l>From me. From me thy Mother deare? Why dost thou shun my sight? </l>
              <l>And leaue me thus in misery, with Cares consumed quight. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e112880">
              <speaker>OE. </speaker>
              <l>Who troubles me? Let me alone. I thought not to be founde: </l>
              <l>Who now restores myne Eyes to mee, Mother? or Mothers sounde? </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000251-100-a"/>
              <l>Our labour all is spent in vayne, now may wee meete no more. </l>
              <l>The Seas deuide those meetings vile that wee haue had before. </l>
              <l>The gaping earth deuide vs both, th'one from th'other quight. </l>
              <l>Still let our feete repugnant bee. So shall I shun the light </l>
              <l>That most of all me grieues. So shall I space obtaine to wayle </l>
              <l>These bleeding woes on euery side, that doe my thoughtes assayle. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e112970">
              <speaker>IOC. </speaker>
              <l>The Destentes are in fault. Blame them, Alas, alas, not wee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e112990">
              <speaker>OED. </speaker>
              <l>Spare now. Leaue of to speake in vayne, spare now O Mother mee, </l>
              <l>By these Reliques of my dismembred body I thee pray. </l>
              <l>By myne vnhappy Children pledges left. What shall I say? </l>
              <l>By all the Gods I thee beseech. By all that in my name </l>
              <l>Is good or bad, let mee alone. Alas you are to blame </l>
              <l>To trouble mee. You see what hell my haplesse heart doth payne. </l>
              <l>You see that in my Conscience ten thousand horrors raine. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e113070">
              <speaker>IOC. </speaker>
              <l>O dying heart: O sindrownd soule. Why dost thou faint alas? </l>
              <l>Why dost thou seeke and toyle in vayne these ills to ouerpas? </l>
              <l>What meane these sighes, &amp; scalding teares? why dost thou death refuse? </l>
              <l>Thou mate of all his mischiefs thou, by whose meanes onely rues </l>
              <l>The law of nature all: by whom, Ah, Ah, confounded lies, </l>
              <l>Both God, and man, and beast, and all that eyther liues or dies. </l>
              <l>Die thou, dispatch at once thrust through thy vile incestuous brest: </l>
              <l>Thou hast none other meanes (alas) to set thine heart at rest. </l>
              <l>Not thou, if God him selfe, if he his flaming fiers should throw </l>
              <l>On thee, or mischiefs all by heapes vpon thy body strow </l>
              <l>Couldst once for thy deserued ills due paines or vengeaunce pay: </l>
              <l>Some meanes therefore to wreak Gods wrath vpon thy selfe assay. </l>
              <l>Death, death now best contenteth mee, then seeke a way to dye. </l>
              <l>So maist thou yet at length finde end for all thy misery. </l>
              <l>O Son lend mee thy hand: sith that thou art a Paracyde. </l>
              <l>This labour last of all remaynes, this labour thee doth byde. </l>
              <l>Dispatch rid mee thy mother deare from all my deadly woe </l>
              <l>It will not be: no prayers auaile. Thy selfe this deede must doe. </l>
              <l>Take vp this sword. Goe to, with this thy husbande late was slayne. </l>
              <l>Husband? thou term'st him false: hee was thy syer: O deadly payne. </l>
              <l>Shal I quight through my brest it driue? or through my throte it thrust? </l>
              <l>Canst thou not choose thy wound? away: die, die, (alas) thou must. </l>
              <l>This hateful womb then wound (O wretch) this, this with thine own hand </l>
              <l>Strike, strike it hard: (O spare it not) sith both a husband, and </l>
              <l>(The same a Son it bare.) </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e113330">
              <speaker>CHOR. </speaker>
              <l>Alas, alas, shee is slaine, she is slayne, dispatched with a push: </l>
              <l>Who euer sawe the like to this: see how the bloud doth gush. </l>
              <pb n="94" xml:id="ep000251-100-b"/>
              <l>O heauy doulfull case: who can this dyrefull sight enduer </l>
              <l>Which for the hideousnesse thereof might teares of stones procuer. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ep000251-A11909" xml:id="ep000251-e113380">
              <speaker>OED. </speaker>
              <l>Thou God, thou teller out of Fates. On thee, on thee, I call, </l>
              <l>My Father onely I did owe, vnto the Destnies all. </l>
              <l>Now twise a Paracide, and worse than I did feare to bee: </l>
              <l>My Mother I haue slayne. (Alas) the fault is all in mee. </l>
              <l>O OEdipus accursed wretch, lament thine owne Calamity, </l>
              <l>Lament thy state, thy griefe lament, thou Caitife borne to misery. </l>
              <l>Where wilt thou now become (alas?) thy Face where wilt thou hyde: </l>
              <l>O myserable Slaue, canst thou such shamefull tormentes byde? </l>
              <l>Canst thou which hast thy Parents slain? Canst thou prolong thy life? </l>
              <l>Wilt thou not dye? deseruing Death: thou cause of all the griefe, </l>
              <l>And Plagues, and dreadfull mischiefs all that Thebane City prease. </l>
              <l>Why dost thou seeke by longer life, thy sorrowes to encrease? </l>
              <l>Why dost thou toyle and labour thus in vayne? It will not bee. </l>
              <l>Both God, and man: and beast, and all abhorre thy Face to see </l>
              <l>O Earth why gapst thou not for? why doe you not vnfolde </l>
              <l>You gates of hell mee to receaue? why doe you hence withholde? </l>
              <l>The fierce Infernall Feends from me, from me so wretched wight? </l>
              <l>Why breake not all the Furyes lose this hatefull head to smight </l>
              <l>With Plagues? which them deserued hath (alas) I am left alone, </l>
              <l>Both light, and sight, and comfort all from mee (O wretch) is gone. </l>
              <l>O cursed head: O wicked wight, whom all men deadly hate. </l>
              <l>O Beast, what meanst thou still to liue in this vnhappy state? </l>
              <l>The Skies doe blush and are ashamd, at these thy mischiefes great </l>
              <l>The Earth laments, the Heauens weepe, the Seas for rage doe freat. </l>
              <l>And blustring rise, and stormes doe stir, and all thou wretch for thee. </l>
              <l>By whose incest, and bloudy deedes all things disturbed bee. </l>
              <l>Quight out of course, displaced quight, O cursed fatall day. </l>
              <l>O mischiefes great, O dreadfull times, O wretch, away, away. </l>
              <l>Exile thy selfe from all mens sight, thy life halfe spent in misery, </l>
              <l>Goe end consume it now outright in thrise as great calamity. </l>
              <l>O lying Phoebe thine Oracles my sin, and shame surmount: </l>
              <l>My Mothers death amongst my deedes; thou neuer didst recount. </l>
              <l>A meete Exploict for me that am to Nature deadly Foe. </l>
              <l>With trembling fearefull pace goe forth, thou wretched monster goe, </l>
              <l>Grope out thy wayes on knees in darke thou miserable Slaue. </l>
              <l>So maist thou yet in tract of time due paynes, and vengeaunce haue, </l>
              <l>For thy mischeuous lyfe. Thus, thus, the Gods themselues decree. </l>
              <l>Thus, thus, thy Fates: thus, thus, the skyes appoint it for to bee. </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000251-101-a"/>
              <l>Then headlong hence, with a mischiefe hence, thou caitife vyle away. </l>
              <l>Away, away, thou monstrous Beast. Goe, Run. Stand, stay, </l>
              <l>Least on thy Mother thou doe fall. </l>
              <l>All you that wearyed bodies haue, with sickenesse ouerprest. </l>
              <l>Loe, now I fly: I fly away, the cause of your vnrest. </l>
              <l>Lift vp your heads: a better state of Ayre shall strayght ensewe </l>
              <l>Whan I am gone: for whom alone, these dreadfull myschiefs grewe. </l>
              <l>And you that now, halfe dead yet liue in wretched misers case. </l>
              <l>Help those whom present torments presse forth, hye you on apace. </l>
              <l>For loe, with me I cary hence, all mischiefes vnder Skyes. </l>
              <l>All cruell Fates, Diseases all that for my sake did ryse, </l>
              <l>With mee they goe: with me both griefe, Plague, Pocks, Botch, &amp; all </l>
              <l>The ills that eyther now you presse, or euer after shall. </l>
              <l>With me they goe, with me: these Mates bin meetst of all for mee. </l>
              <l>Who am the most vnhappiest wretch that euer Sun did see. </l>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back></back>
  </text>
</TEI>
