<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The royal shepherdess a tragi-comedy, acted by His Highness the Duke of York's servants.</title>
        <author>
<!--Shadwell, Thomas-->
          <persName>
            <forename>Thomas</forename>
            <surname>Shadwell</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <idno type="dracor" xml:base="https://dracor.org/id/">ep000734</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A59445.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <p>
            This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is available for reuse, according to the terms of
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>
            . The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
          </p>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull>
              <titleStmt>
                <title>The royal shepherdess a tragi-comedy, acted by His Highness the Duke of York's servants.</title>
                <author>Shadwell, Thomas, 1642?-1692.</author>
                <author>J. F. (John Fountain). Rewards of vertue.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[8], 81, [1] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Printed for Henry Herringman ...,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                <date>1669.</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>Adaptation of: The rewards of vertue / John Fountain.</note>
                <note>"This play, before I took it in hand, was wrote by one Mr. Fountain of Devonshire ... I have added little to the story, onely have represented that in action, which was expressed by him in long narrations"--Epistle to the reader, signed Tho. Shadwell.</note>
                <note>First ed. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000734-e10">
        <pb xml:id="ep000734-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000734-001-b"/>
        <p>THE ROYAL Shepherdess. </p>
        <p>A TRAGI-COMEDY, ACTED By his Highness the Duke of York's Servants. </p>
        <q>
          <l>Non Quivis videt immodulata Poemata Iudex. </l>
          <bibl>Hor. de arte Poet. </bibl>
        </q>
        <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Henry Herringman</hi>, at the Sign of the Blew-Anchor, in the Lower-walk of the New-Exchange, 1669. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="to_the_reader" xml:id="ep000734-e120">
        <gap extent="2" reason="missing" unit="pages"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000734-002-a"/>
        <p>I have added little to the Story, onely have represented that in Action, which was expressed by him in long Narrations: For we find (though the French do often relate the most considerable Actions in their Plays, especially in their Tragedies) the English will not be content without seeing such Actions done, and this is one, of those many things, that make our English Plays so much exceed the French: But this was long ago observed by Horace: <q>
            <l>Segnius irritant animos demissa per aurem, </l>
            <l>Quam quae sunt oculis subjecta sidelibus. </l>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>I have endeavour'd to carry on these few Humors, which were but begun by him; and (to satisfie the Concupiscence as Mr. Iohnson calls it, of Jigge and Song) I designed as fit occasions for them as I could, there being in the former Play but one short Song which is the last but one. </p>
        <p>Where it is possible, I have kept the Scenes unbroken, and with as proper a connexion as I could. What I have besides added I need not tell you, being I fear so much worse that his, that you will easily distinguish it. </p>
        <p>I shall say little more of the Play, but that the Rules of Morality and good Manners are strictly observed in it: (Vertue being exalted, and Vice depressed) and perhaps it might have been better received had neither been done in it: for I find, it pleases most to see <pb xml:id="ep000734-002-b"/>Vice incouraged by bringing the Characters of debauch'd people upon the Stage, and making them pass for fine Gentlemen who openly profess Swearing, Drinking, Whoring, breaking Windows, beating Constables, &amp;c. and that is esteem'd among us a Gentile gayety of Humour, which is contrary to the Customs and Laws of all civilized Nations. But it is said, by some, that this pleases the people, and a Poets business is onely to endeavour that: But he that debases himself to think of nothing but pleasing the Rabble, loses the dignity of a Poet, and becomes as little as a Jugler, or a Rope-Dancer; who please more then he can do: but the office of a Poet is, <q>
            <l>Simul &amp; jucunda, &amp; idonea dicere vitae. </l>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>Which (if the Poets of our age would observe it) would render 'em as usefull to a Commonwealth as any profession whatsoever. </p>
        <p>But I have too long troubled you with a Discourse of this Play, which (let me say what I will of it) you will judge of as you please: But if you consider, after such an Infinite number of Playes, when <q>
            <l>(Nil intentatum nostri liquère Poetae.) </l>
          </q>How difficult it is to write even an indifferent one● (as none but those that cannot write think it easie) Methinks it were but an ordinary piece of Humanity <gap extent="2" reason="missing" unit="pages"/>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="ep000734-e330">
        <pb xml:id="ep000734-003-a"/>
        <head>Dramatis Personae. </head>
        <list>
          <label>BAsilius, </label>
          <item>King. </item>
          <label>Theander </label>
          <item>Prince. </item>
          <label>Endymion </label>
          <item>A worthy Lord of small Fortune. </item>
          <label>Pyrrhus </label>
          <item>A Creature of the Kings. </item>
          <label>Neander </label>
          <item>A vain, cowardly, vicious effeminate Lord. </item>
          <label>Geron </label>
          <item>An old Jealous Fop that has married a young Wife. </item>
          <label>Priest.— </label>
          <item/>
          <label>Queen.— </label>
          <item/>
          <label>Cleantha </label>
          <item>Niece to the King. </item>
          <label>Evadne </label>
          <item>Servant to the Queen. </item>
          <label>Urania </label>
          <item>One that was a Shepherdess, and preferr'd by the Prince to wait on Cleantha. </item>
          <label>Phronesia </label>
          <item>A vain foolish Woman, Wife to Geron. </item>
          <label>Cleopatra </label>
          <item>Mother to Vrania; conceal'd by the name of Parthenia. </item>
          <label>
            <hi>Messengers, Officers, Shepherds</hi>, and <hi>Shepherdesses, Nymphs</hi>, and <hi>Satyrs, Priests </hi>of Mars, &amp;c. </label>
          <item/>
        </list>
        <p>SCENE ARCADIA. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="masque" xml:id="ep000734-e750">
        <pb n="1" xml:id="ep000734-003-b"/>
        <head>THE ROYAL SHEPHERDESSE. </head>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="ep000734-e770">
          <head>THE FIRST ACT. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e790">Enter Pyrrhus, Endymion, Neander. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e810">
            <speaker>Pyr. </speaker>
            <l>BEliev't my Lords, they say the Prince does Wonders. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e840">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <l>They say he kills a world of men indeed; </l>
            <l>But 'faith I think the wonder had been greater </l>
            <l>If he had made but half so many live. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e890">
            <speaker>Endy. </speaker>
            <l>Perchance, my Lord, you'd have him turn Physitian. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e920">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <l>Rather than Butcher, 'tis the Nobler Trade. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e950">
            <speaker>Endy. </speaker>
            <l>But they are his Enemies he kills, </l>
            <l>Men that offend, and do deserve to die. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e990">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <l>O! then I think you'l praise the Hangman next, </l>
            <l>You give a definition of his Trade. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e1030">
            <speaker>Pyrr. </speaker>
            <l>If I do not mistake your humour Sir, </l>
            <l>You were never taken with this dying, </l>
            <l>It is a thing does marr a Courtier much. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e1080">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <l>‛ Thank Heav'n, I am not yet so mad to wish for't; </l>
            <l>Let Broken-Merchants, and the busie Rout </l>
            <l>That durt the Streets, when their designs miscarry, </l>
            <l>Cry that there's nothing Certain in this World, </l>
            <l>I think there's less in that which is to come: </l>
            <l>Here I'm sure of something, I'm a Lord, </l>
            <l>And live with men: But to be turn'd a grazing </l>
            <l>In the Elizian-Fields (that men do talk of) </l>
            <l>Among Philosophers, n'ere could make a Legg. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e1200">
            <speaker>Endy. </speaker>
            <l>Fie, fie, Neander! this is too prophane, </l>
            <l>And relisheth far more of Beast than Man. </l>
            <gap extent="2" reason="missing" unit="pages"/>
            <pb n="4" xml:id="ep000734-004-a"/>
            <l>Arcadia shall Command those Provinces, </l>
            <l>Who lately thought our long and happy peace </l>
            <l>Had soften'd so our Minds, that now we were </l>
            <l>Fit to be Lo●ded over by their Wills: </l>
            <l>But strange it is, to see the King so little </l>
            <l>Joy'd with the news, that still he bears a Face </l>
            <l>More troubled than Sicilian Seas in storms. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e1360">
            <speaker>Pyrr. </speaker>
            <l>'Tis for the Love of that poor Shepherdess, </l>
            <l>The Prince not Ten months since took from a Cottage </l>
            <l>As he was a hunting, and gave the fair </l>
            <l>Cleantha for a Present. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e1430">
            <speaker>Endy. </speaker>
            <stage xml:id="ep000734-e1450">aside </stage>
            <l>Alas! my poor Urania! how doth </l>
            <l>Thy harder Fortune vindicate my Choice? </l>
            <l>Who now dares say Endymion loves to low, </l>
            <l>When he loves her that can make Princes die; </l>
            <l>No more, no more, we must scorn Cottages </l>
            <l>Those are the Rocks from whence our Jewels come. </l>
            <l>Gold breeds in barren Hills, the brightest Stars </l>
            <l>Shine o're the poorer Regions of the North. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e1560">Enter King. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e1580">
            <speaker>Pyrr. </speaker>
            <l>Here comes the King▪ Endymion, pray retire, </l>
            <l>It is not fit you should be privy to his Thoughts. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e1630">
            <speaker>Endy. </speaker>
            <l>I'le try if I can hear what resolution </l>
            <l>The Kings enrag'd Passion makes him take. <stage xml:id="ep000734-e1670">He retires. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e1680">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Pyrrhus! how thrives my Love? I have </l>
            <l>Intrusted you with all I am, and all I wish for. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e1730">
            <speaker>Pyrr. </speaker>
            <l>Sir, I have already done, </l>
            <l>What Language and Rewards have power to do </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e1770">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>And what return am I to hope for then? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e1800">
            <speaker>Pyrr. </speaker>
            <l>There's little hope: This Ermin will not be </l>
            <l>Perswaded from the whiteness she so Loves. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e1840">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Poor Country Girl, where can she find Words </l>
            <l>Or Resolution when you do assault her? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e1880">
            <speaker>Pyrr. </speaker>
            <l>When I first </l>
            <l>Mention'd the business to her, all alone, </l>
            <l>Poor soul she blush'd, as if already she </l>
            <l>Had done some harm by hearing of me speak. </l>
            <pb n="5" xml:id="ep000734-004-b"/>
            <l>Whilst from her pretty Eyes two Fountains run </l>
            <l>(So true, so Native) down her fairest Cheeks, </l>
            <l>As if she thought her self oblig'd to weep </l>
            <l>That all the World was not as good as she. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e1980">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>Heaven! how does this Carriage please me! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e2010">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>This Modesty of hers inflames me more. </l>
            <l>As springs are hottest in the coldest weather. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e2050">
            <speaker>Pyrr. </speaker>
            <l>Her Tears so innocently begg'd my pity, </l>
            <l>That I was straight turn'd over to her side, </l>
            <l>And had forgot the Cause for which I strove▪ </l>
            <l>Till rallying agen, I once more gave </l>
            <l>A new assault, and urg'd her to answer: </l>
            <l>All her reply was no: then humbly pray'd me, </l>
            <l>Not to be Cruel to a poor weak Maid, </l>
            <l>Who had not any thing, in all the World, </l>
            <l>To give her value but her Innocence; </l>
            <l>With such Success as this I often have </l>
            <l>Assail'd her Vertue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e2180">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Ah Pyrrhus! where will this Tyrant end? shall I </l>
            <l>Still be Priest, and Sacrifice, and Altar too, </l>
            <l>Unto a Passion, I can satisfie, </l>
            <l>But never Conquer? What poor things are Kings? </l>
            <l>What poorer things are Nations to obey </l>
            <l>Him whom a petty Passion does Command? </l>
            <l>Heav'n! why was man made so ridiculous? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e2280">
            <speaker>Pyrr. </speaker>
            <l>Your Majesty sayes that of your self, </l>
            <l>Which were Impiety in any else, </l>
            <l>But once to think. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e2330">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Men but Flatter me. </l>
            <l>Oh Fate! why were not Kings made more than men? </l>
            <l>Or why will people have us to be more? </l>
            <l>Alas! we govern others, but our selves </l>
            <l>We cannot rule, like to our Eyes, that see </l>
            <l>All other things, but Cannot see themseves. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e2410">
            <speaker>Pyrr. </speaker>
            <l>Sir, do not discompose your self; you may </l>
            <l>Soon Queench this mighty Flame, and where your Prayers </l>
            <l>Have not prevail'd, your Power may Command: </l>
            <l>Who in Arcadia dares resist your Will? </l>
          </sp>
          <gap extent="2" reason="missing" unit="pages"/>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e2500">
            <pb n="8" xml:id="ep000734-005-a"/>
            <speaker>clean. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord 'tis true, Let's to the Queen— </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e2540">
            <hi>Exeunt all but </hi>Evadne. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e2560">Enter Neander. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e2580">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>How does this Minute transport my soul with Joy, to have the blessed priviledge to be with fair Evadne? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e2620">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>I am glad it makes some body happy. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e2650">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>With her who has my Heart.— </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e2680">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <l>Have I it? pray my Lord take it agen. </l>
            <l>I would not be troubled with keeping such a Bawble for the World. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e2720">
            <speaker>Nean </speaker>
            <p>She whom great Nature (now grown wanton) made to look upon, and scorn her other Works. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e2750">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>My Lord Neander! I see you are resolv'd not to study to no purpose, you will have out your Complement, let me say what I please: but I must take liberty to leave you in the middle of it. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e2790">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Nay, Madam, I beseech you be not so unkind. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e2820">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>Nay now I have put you out of your Complement; I care not if I stay a little longer. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e2850">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Madam! you are Cruel! how do you Kill? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e2880">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>Kill Neander? No sure then you would not be so near me. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e2920">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>I ne're could fear death from so fair a hand as yours. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e2950">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>I believe indeed, my Lord, you fear death least from the hands of a Woman, which is the Reason you chuse to stay here at Court among the Ladies, rather than go to War with the Prince. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e2980">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Madam!— You Ladies have a Priviledge. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e3010">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>Yes, my Lord, ●it's sometimes a priviledge to speak Truth. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e3040">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>'Faith Madam, you may say what you please. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e3070">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>Pardon me, my Lord, it would please me much better if I could say you were in the War in Thessaly. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e3110">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Truly Madam, I could give you very good reasons why I went not to the War with the Prince. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e3140">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>I believe you can, and so can every body else that knows your Lordship: The first and Chiefest reason was a certain tenderness you have for the preservation of your Person, some scandalous people stick 〈◊〉 to call it fear. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e3170">
            <pb n="9" xml:id="ep000734-005-b"/>
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Do not judge so Madam; I can assure you it was for very different reasons. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e3200">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>You will give very much satisfaction to the World, if you say what they are. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e3230">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Why then, to tell you the truth, Madam, I am somewhat troubled with Corns that I cannot without pain wear a riding Boot▪ and then I am strangely subject to the Tooth-ach, which makes me very unsit to lie in the Field, which indeed were the two main Reasons made me refuse the War. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e3260">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>What pity 'tis so brave a Mind should be so unluckily hindred from shewing it self. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e3290">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>I perceive you railly, Madam. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e3320">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>I see Sir, you are a man of a quick apprehension. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e3350">Enter Priest. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e3360">
            <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
            <p>How now Daughter? what do you here? my Lord I do not desire your Lordship should make any addresses to my Daughter, her Fortune is too humble for your thoughts. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e3390">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <l>Your servant, Madam. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000734-e3430">[Aside] </stage>Pox on this Formal Priest.— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e3440">Exit. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e3450">
            <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
            <l>Well now Evadne, my dear Child, thou art </l>
            <l>Come forth upon the Worlds great Stage, and it </l>
            <l>Must be my care first to advise thee, then </l>
            <l>To pray for thee: Yet thou art innocent, </l>
            <l>(Oh maist thou still be so my Child) yet know'st not </l>
            <l>Ought but the holy practices of cells, </l>
            <l>Where vertuous Matrons have instructed thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e3550">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <l>But now the Scene is chang'd, the Queens Commands </l>
            <l>Have brought me to the Court to wait on her; </l>
            <l>The employment truly noble: and I have </l>
            <l>In her the brightest pattern of true vertue </l>
            <l>That all the world can boast of. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e3620">
            <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
            <l>But thou'lt find </l>
            <l>Few more besides whose wandring paths are safe: </l>
            <l>Those of thy Sex thou't find so strangely vain, </l>
            <l>That they think they have wash'd, and patch'd, and cutl'd </l>
            <l>Themselves ev'n into little Deities: </l>
            <l>They do believe that wanton men speak truth, </l>
            <l>When to consume those hours, they care not for, </l>
          </sp>
          <gap extent="2" reason="missing" unit="pages"/>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e3730">
            <pb n="12" xml:id="ep000734-006-a"/>
            <speaker>Phro. </speaker>
            <p>Ay, Madam, is it not? would you be willing to be us'd so? Besides, Madam, no man in the Court offers to speak to me, but he thinks 'tis Love. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e3760">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>He thinks you are so handsome, perhaps, that it is impossible for any man to look upon you without being smitten. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e3790">
            <speaker>Phro </speaker>
            <p>That may be something, as you say, Madam, but I will never put up this Injury: Marry me to keep me honest, quoth ' a? I'le never endure it, while I ha' breath:— See Madam— where he comes— do but observe him. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e3820">Enter Geron. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e3840">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>I have brought my self into a sweet condition, like an old fool as I am, why could not I remember how many I had Cuckolded my self, and to think I should not be serv'd in the same kind, were to suppose neither Wickedness, nor Justice in the World. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e3870">
            <speaker>Phro. </speaker>
            <p>Look, Madam upon this Mischievous Count'nance. </p>
            <p>
              <stage xml:id="ep000734-e3910">Geron <hi>to himself </hi>
              </stage>How could I imagine that any of these sort of Women would keep themselves honest three minutes, when they fear'd neither the danger of taking Savin, nor a great Belly? Heaven! what a Condition am I in!— now do I plainly perceive the pain that poor Children indure at the coming of their Teeth, by the coming of my Horns— Oh Phronesia! are you there? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e3940">
            <speaker>Phro. </speaker>
            <p>Yes! you old Fumbling Sot I am here.— </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e3970">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>Fare you well. <stage xml:id="ep000734-e4000">Ex. Evadne. </stage>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e4010">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>O wicked Phronesia! how have you us'd me? whom have you appointed now to do me the Courtesie?— my Lord Pirrhus— he is of a black Complexion, and that never fails;— My Lord Endymion's a Poet forsooth, and prevails with Sonnets;— and for my Lord Neander,— the Priest convinc'd him the other day, that Adultery was a very great Sin, and that's reason enough for him to lie at Rack and Manger; I am sure my head must ake for't. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e4080">
            <speaker>Phro. </speaker>
            <p>Let it ake on, you old Fop, you marry'd me to keep me honest, did you? I'le honest you; I will go instantly and meet 'em all three▪ <stage xml:id="ep000734-e4120">Exit. </stage>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e4130">
            <pb n="13" xml:id="ep000734-006-b"/>
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>But I'le follow you close at the heels, and prevent your recreation!— <q>
                <l>If any Man be weary of his life, </l>
                <l>Let him at Threescore marry such a Wife. </l>
              </q>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e4190">Exeunt. </stage>
          <trailer>The End of the First Act. </trailer>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="ep000734-e4210">
          <head>THE SECOND ACT. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e4230">Enter Pyrrhus and Urania. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e4260">
            <speaker>Pyrr. </speaker>
            <l>COme fair Urania, think upon the honour </l>
            <l>To be a Mistress to a King, sounds it not Well? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e4310">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <l>It is an Honour I should not envy her </l>
            <l>That sought my ruine! I will ne're forsake </l>
            <l>My Vertue, for a little outward splendor. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e4360">
            <speaker>Pyrr. </speaker>
            <l>Is Love a Vice Urania? why did Nature </l>
            <l>Make us all Vicious, when she did immerse </l>
            <l>Love in the very beings of all Creatures: </l>
            <l>Go search the Universe, and shew me there </l>
            <l>What but affrighted man is not as free </l>
            <l>To satisfie his Love as Thirst or Hunger; </l>
            <l>Beasts ne're dispute the Lawfulness of what is Natural. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e4460">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <l>'Tis well, my Lord, when you intend </l>
            <l>Unlawful Loves to instance not in men </l>
            <l>But Beasts— but let me ever be </l>
            <l>Of that affrighted Number that follow vertue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e4520">
            <speaker>Pyrr. </speaker>
            <l>Come, come, Urania! Love, like men, was free, </l>
            <l>E're Pow'r and Laws had taught 'em both the use </l>
            <l>Of Chains, and Fetters: Nature ne're Confin'd </l>
            <l>Her No lest Creature to the Narrow'st Prison, </l>
            <l>Nor gave him Inclinations to torment him, </l>
            <gap extent="2" reason="missing" unit="pages"/>
            <pb n="16" xml:id="ep000734-007-a"/>
            <l>And with a holy Flame, my Sighs and Tears </l>
            <l>Have been as pure, as are those Gales and Springs </l>
            <l>which in Elizium do refresh the blest: </l>
            <l>And yet thou hast not pitty'd him that loves thee, </l>
            <l>Even though thou be'st as gentle, and as soft </l>
            <l>As morning dew just melting into Ayre. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e4690">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <l>What shall I serve you in my Lord? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e4720">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>Permit </l>
            <l>Me to enjoy the Title of your servant, </l>
            <l>And pay my fire with equal flames again. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e4770">
            <speaker>Vran. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord, I were ingrateful if I should not. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e4800">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>Then be not so, but (to be short) I fear </l>
            <l>The Kings approach, and therefore if thou'lt promise </l>
            <l>This night to sleep within my armes (being first </l>
            <l>Authoriz'd by Hymens Priest) </l>
            <l>I'le free thee from the Kings unlawful Love. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e4880">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <l>What's to be done in this sad Exigence?— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e4910">aside. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000734-e4930">(To him) </stage>My Lord, I will, but satisfie me, how? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e4940">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>You must appoint the King to meet you there, </l>
            <l>In yonder Grotto, and oblige him to </l>
            <l>The Language, and the time of Love, soft Whispers, </l>
            <l>And the Night; and I'le prepare </l>
            <l>Some other Woman to supply your place; </l>
            <l>This will gain time till to morrow, when </l>
            <l>I'le own you to the King to be my Wife: </l>
            <l>Then the respect to all my Loyal services </l>
            <l>Will make him quench his now Unruly Passion. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e5050">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <l>Ah, who will be so wicked as to meet him? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e5080">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>Enow, ne're fear it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e5110">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <l>Sure 'tis impossible! </l>
            <l>What Woman would consent to such an Act? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e5150">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>Ten thousand, Madam! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e5180">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <l>But they shall not for me, </l>
            <l>I'le rather chuse a Thousand times to die, </l>
            <l>Then own a wretched Life, sav'd at the rate </l>
            <l>Of so much infamy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e5240">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>Come, be content, </l>
            <l>Chaste Soul; I'le do what you shall well approve; </l>
            <pb n="17" xml:id="ep000734-007-b"/>
            <l>My dear, I must retire, I fear the King: </l>
            <l>Now act thy part, and then confide in me; </l>
            <l>Be happy fair Urania, I am blest </l>
            <l>That my employment is to do thee service. <stage xml:id="ep000734-e5330">Ex. Endymion. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e5340">
            <speaker>Vran. </speaker>
            <l>Ah, dear Endymion! how could I weep </l>
            <l>If tears were able but to wash away </l>
            <l>The blackness of my Crime? now thou hast thought </l>
            <l>To lead me from the Labyrinth of my Woes, </l>
            <l>The next thing I must think must be to cheat </l>
            <l>All thy Innocent expectations, which </l>
            <l>〈…〉 to my self, </l>
            <l>〈…〉 Soul; </l>
            <l>
              <gap extent="1" reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" unit="lines"/>
            </l>
            <l>
              <gap extent="1" reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" unit="lines"/>
            </l>
            <l>〈…〉 King. </l>
            <l>〈…〉 Showres allay you thus your Beams? </l>
            <l>〈…〉 and more are due to my Misfortunes. </l>
            <l>〈…〉 this, Pyrrhus told me you had consented. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e5560">
            <speaker>Vran. </speaker>
            <l>With what Face can I say yes to the King? </l>
            <l>Tho' I but feign consent, and mean to cheat him,— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e5610">Aside. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>It is Immodest sure— it cannot fit </l>
            <l>A Womans Mouth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e5640">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Are you not yet resolv'd? </l>
            <l>What means this doubt? Consent to my desires, </l>
            <l>And you shall live ador'd and fear'd by all; </l>
            <l>The Kingdom shall rejoyce at all your smiles, </l>
            <l>And tremble at your frowns: But if you do not— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e5710">
            <speaker>Vran. </speaker>
            <l>Is there no other way to save my life? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e5740">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Come, do not trifle thus to tempt my rage. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e5770">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <l>Good Sir, be not angry; I will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e5800">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>My dear Urania! now be happy, let's withdraw </l>
            <l>This place is much too publick for our Love.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e5850">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <l>Let me not lose all Modesty at once, </l>
            <l>But let Sin take possession by degrees, </l>
            <l>I have some sparks of Vertue yet remaining </l>
            <l>Which will require some time to quench. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e5910">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>I am impatient of delays, in this </l>
          </sp>
          <gap extent="2" reason="missing" unit="pages"/>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e5960">
            <pb n="20" xml:id="ep000734-008-a"/>
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>A death from your fair hand, I wou'd embrace. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e5990">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>Ay, this kind of dying put's a man to no pain, but to be run through the Lungs, or shot through the Body is mighty inconvenient. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6020">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Ay, 'faith is it.— </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6050">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>But 'tis honourable. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6080">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>For my part, I cannot possibly find what honour there is in having Oylet-holes made in a mans body: 'Slife a Mans body is not made to see through, is it? and yet I know some Duelling Coxcombs so often run through, as if their bodies were intended Through-fares for Swords.— </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6110">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>But I hope you have more prudence then to venture that danger. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6140">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>If I be run through, may I be pickl'd up when I am dead like a Sturgeon, &amp; be seru'd up to the Table of an old 〈…〉 surer. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6170">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>I will say this in your Commendations, 〈…〉 presents it self, I believe there is not a man in 〈…〉 as your self, I mean so swift of Foot. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6200">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Not so, Madam, indifferent, indifferent 〈…〉 </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6230">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>But suppose Sir I should stand in need of a Champion. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6260">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>O Madam! your Eyes will revenge your Quarrels. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6290">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>Or they must be unreveng'd for you! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6320">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Nay, Madam, in a Lady's Cause I can be a Lyon. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6350">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>When you meet with a Lamb. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6380">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <l>Nay, Madam! I have Courage, but I must confess, </l>
            <l>'Tis a thing a man may better spare then any of his </l>
            <l>Goods and Ghattels. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6430">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>Yes, yes, you have Courage, witness the going to The War when you were commanded! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6460">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>It was not want of that; But who the Devil, that had a plentifull Estate, like me, and might live among these pretty Ladies at the Court, would go to lie without Sheets, with Stones and Blocks, for Pillows, and be most honourably Lowsie, and damnably nettl'd, for a company of ungrateful Fellows, that live Luxuriously at home, and laugh at the Honourable Affairs abroad? and when they have done, they value these Mighty men of War, just as a man does a Creditor that Duns him for Money lent, which he never intended to pay. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e6490">
            <pb n="21" xml:id="ep000734-008-b"/>Enter Geron. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6510">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>What would this old jealous Fop have? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6540">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>Nay, now I will not hang my self yet: I'le be reveng'd on this Lord first— My Lord— </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6570">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Pox o' this Rogue, how I scorn any one that's below me, What say you Geron? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6610">
            <speaker>(Geron </speaker>
            <stage xml:id="ep000734-e6640">aside.) </stage>
            <p>Furies pursue him. </p>
            <p>How does your Lordship? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6680">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Very well! how does your Lady? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6710">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>'Tis he has done it, a Curse on him. <stage xml:id="ep000734-e6740">Aside. </stage>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6750">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Why how now? what do you Conjure? what's the matter? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6780">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>I need not Conjure, I know the Father now. <stage xml:id="ep000734-e6810">To himself. </stage>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6820">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Why what do'st thou mutter man? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6850">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>My Lord! why shou'd you ask for my Wife? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6880">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Because I am Civil. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6910">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>Because I am a Cuckold. <stage xml:id="ep000734-e6940">Aside. </stage>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6950">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Pox on thee, why do'st not speak out? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e6980">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>Your Servant, my Lord, suppose by this time my Lord Endymion has left the Queen. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e7020">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>I beseech you let me wait on your Ladyship <stage xml:id="ep000734-e7050">Exeunt. </stage>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e7060">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>This is the man! 'tis he; Why should he ask for my Wife? Suppose I have a Wife, what's that to him, must he needs be asking for her presently? This Rascal Neander, this Villain that I dare not say any thing to; not because he's Valiant, for then it would not grieve me, but because he's a Lord, which he could no more help, then I can that I am a Cuckold: Here's another Lord too. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e7100">Enter Endymion. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e7120">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <p>O Geron! how is't with you? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e7160">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>Your Servant, my Lord. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e7190">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <p>How does Phronesia? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e7230">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>Here's another, what Two Lords to make one Cuckold? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e7260">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <p>What, are you mute? has any Misfortune befaln your Wife? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e7290">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>Too much has befaln me I am sure: 'Sdeath I am Cuckolded and laught at too; you do not well my Lord to use me thus. </p>
            <gap extent="2" reason="missing" unit="pages"/>
            <pb n="24" xml:id="ep000734-009-a"/>
            <l>And her great Titles reckon'd up, whilst she, </l>
            <l>Does in her Closet, weep she is not less, </l>
            <l>Poor Endymion! how little dar'st thou think </l>
            <l>My Thoughts; or I dare say them to thee? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e7390">
            <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
            <l>Should Endymion speak, </l>
            <l>You then would hate him for his Confidence, </l>
            <l>A Crime of which he never can be guilty. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e7450">
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <l>Nay, should he speak, in that he would forfeit </l>
            <l>The very thing I love him for, that rest </l>
            <l>He finds in the Elizium of his thoughts, </l>
            <l>And those true satisfactions which he takes </l>
            <l>In being all the World unto himself. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e7530">Enter 〈…〉 </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e7550">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <l>Sir, I beseech you 〈…〉, </l>
            <l>It would incense my Father 〈…〉 against me </l>
            <l>If he shou'd see you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e7600">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <l>Madam, never mind </l>
            <l>What old Gray people in their Wisdom talk of, </l>
            <l>They'd Cross us out of Envy to our youth; </l>
            <l>For when the Wine of Love is drawn out of 'em, </l>
            <l>They live some years by its Vinegar, spight. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e7670">
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <l>Poor Lady, how she's pester'd with yon gaudy Nothing. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e7700">Enter Phronesia, <hi>and after </hi>Geron. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e7730">
            <speaker>Phro. </speaker>
            <p>O Madam! we shall have a Ball to night, The Queen will entertain his Majesty, and desires your Highness to be ready. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e7760">
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <p>I attend her pleasure. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e7790">
            <speaker>Ger </speaker>
            <p>Hell take that Clogg of mine; how overjoy'd she is to have an opportunity to show her self, and lay baits for young Gudgeons? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e7820">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Let me Consider how I may look <stage xml:id="ep000734-e7850">He puls out of his Pocket a Looking-glass. </stage>amiably in the sight of the Ladies; let me see, a Patch or two here, and a little more red here— very well; this Face of mine cannot chuse but charm them! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e7860">
            <pb n="25" xml:id="ep000734-009-b"/>
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>Well Minion, there's a Ball; but let me but see you dare to look upon any man but my self there, and by all the villanies of thy Sex, I'le tear thy flesh from thy bones, and hang thy Skeleton up in a Physick School. <stage xml:id="ep000734-e7890">She shrinks from him. </stage>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e7900">
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <p>How now Geron, what in passion with your Wife? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e7940">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>O no: and ' please your Highness I cannot be angry with any one I love so well. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e7970">
            <speaker>Phro. </speaker>
            <p>Ah, Madam! he threatens to tear my flesh from my bones, and't please your Highness. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e8000">
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <p>Geron! do you know before whom you do this? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e8040">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>Certainly, my dear, thou art distracted, how com'st thou to mistake thy self so; Madam, I have a great Tenderness for her as I have for my own eyes, Heaven knows. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e8070">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>They deserve much alike; his Eyes are Blood-shot, Rhumatick and Blind, and his Wife Ugly, Insolent and Froward. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e8100">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>If thou knew'st, my dear Phronesia, how great a value I have for thee, thou would'st not thus have injur'd me. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e8140">
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <p>So, this is well; but Urania and Evadne let us go wait upon the Queen: Neander, stay you here. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e8200">Ex. Clean. Uran. Evad. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e8210">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>I like not that so well, I love this Evadne most abominably. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e8250">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>Prithee! my Dear, harbour not so ill thoughts of thy loving Husband till death; Geron— you Strumpet, I'le make you know what 'tis to use me thus. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e8290">
            <speaker>Phro. </speaker>
            <p>My Lord Neander help, or this old Wizard will murder me; Avant Belzebub. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e8340">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <l>Hold Geron! </l>
            <l>Here's a Fellow I may show my Valour on; <stage xml:id="ep000734-e8390">Aside. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>He is old, and Cowardly: Oh, that all Hectors had the </l>
            <l>Same discretion in the Choice of their men that I have, </l>
            <l>They would not be so often beaten as they are; Now </l>
            <l>Will I prove as good a Knight Errant as the best of 'em, </l>
            <l>And rescue this distress'd Lady. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e8450">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <l>Huswife, to morrow will come.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e8480">
            <speaker>Phro. </speaker>
            <p>My Lord! 'Pray take my part against this wicked old Jealous, Toothless, Impotent fellow. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e8510">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Do you hear Sir! do but dare to think of injuring this Lady, </p>
          </sp>
          <gap extent="2" reason="missing" unit="pages"/>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e8560">
            <pb n="28" xml:id="ep000734-010-a"/>
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <p>Alas! dear Sir! you injure me to think that that same Evening that gives pain to you; Can give me pleasure. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e8590">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>My dear! I am not sick. </l>
            <l>I onely am a little indispos'd, </l>
            <l>I'le beg your pardon to retire this night, </l>
            <l>But pray stay you, and take no further Care, </l>
            <l>Till at your own appartment I see you </l>
            <l>To morrow morning. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e8670">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>Sir! your will is still my Law. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e8700">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Once more good Night— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e8730">Ex. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e8740">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>Poor Prince! now little do'st thou think </l>
            <l>How soon thou art to meet with her thou fly'st, </l>
            <l>That wife that still has been so constant! </l>
            <l>Oh! how ridiculous </l>
            <l>Just Heaven does make the wayes of men, </l>
            <l>When they forsake the wayes of Vertue. </l>
            <l>This brave Prince, </l>
            <l>(At whose Victorious Armies Greece now trembles) </l>
            <l>When he contrives inglorious actions, shall </l>
            <l>At the same time, be pity'd by his servants, </l>
            <l>And a poor Girl shall up-braid him, in </l>
            <l>Contriving to preserve him vertuous: </l>
            <l>How do men ravel back to Child-hood, when </l>
            <l>They cease to be thy Children, sacred Vertue! </l>
            <l>And need the Care of every little person, </l>
            <l>That what they call for may not do 'em harm. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e8920">
            <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
            <l>Not to be subject to temptation is </l>
            <l>A priviledge onely had in th' other world, </l>
            <l>And yet I hope, Madam, what you design </l>
            <l>Will him from his intended Crime defend, </l>
            <l>Use you the means, and Heaven will crown the End. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e8990">Exeunt. </stage>
          <trailer>The End of the Second Act. </trailer>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="ep000734-e9010">
          <pb n="29" xml:id="ep000734-010-b"/>
          <head>THE THIRD ACT. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e9030">Enter King and Pyrrhus. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e9060">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>GOod morrow, my Lord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e9090">
            <speaker>Pyrr. </speaker>
            <l>A good day to your Majesty. </l>
            <l>A day as pleasant as your night has been. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e9130">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Ah Pyrrhus! I wish it indeed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e9170">
            <speaker>Pyrr. </speaker>
            <l>I hope your Majesty has been well enough diverted </l>
            <l>This night.— </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e9210">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Yes, my Lord, tho' not as you suppose, </l>
            <l>I've been diverted from those wild desires </l>
            <l>That made me first injure my self, and then </l>
            <l>Unlord my Confident, but I have ask'd pardon </l>
            <l>Of Heaven, and my own Majesty, and now </l>
            <l>I beg it too from you, my Loyal Pyrrhus; </l>
            <l>Forgive me that I have profan'd thy faith, </l>
            <l>By such Commands, that thou art bound to ask </l>
            <l>Blest Heav'n forgiveness for thy Loyalty. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e9330">
            <speaker>Pyrr. </speaker>
            <l>Your Majesty I hope will give me leave </l>
            <l>To wonder at this Change, and understand it, </l>
            <l>When you shall please to think me fit for't. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e9380">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>I'le tell thee all— when now the Night </l>
            <l>Grew blak enough to hide a sculking action, </l>
            <l>I softly stole </l>
            <l>To yonder Grotto, through the upper Walks, </l>
            <l>And there found my Urania; but I found her, </l>
            <l>I found her Pyrrhus, not a Mistress, but </l>
            <l>A Goddess rather, which made me to be, </l>
            <l>No more her Lover, but her Worshipper: </l>
            <l>She onely whisper'd to me as she promis'd, </l>
            <l>Yet never heard I any voice so loud, </l>
            <l>And tho' her Words were gentler far than those </l>
            <l>That holy Priests do speak to dying Saints; </l>
          </sp>
          <gap extent="2" reason="missing" unit="pages"/>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e9560">
            <pb n="32" xml:id="ep000734-011-a"/>
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <l>Heaven bless you— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e9590">Ex King. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>— when Ev'ry thing is green </l>
            <l>Must poor Cleantha onely wither, and never </l>
            <l>Know a Spring? Was I made onely high </l>
            <l>Like Rhodope, and Haemus, or the Alps, </l>
            <l>To dwell with everlasting Winter? to wear Snow, </l>
            <l>When every Valley is adorn'd with Roses? </l>
            <l>Well I must die, then I may also be </l>
            <l>Happy as other Folks; the Grave looks Wistly, </l>
            <l>Like my Fortune, there I shall not see </l>
            <l>Poor Villagers more blest in Love then I, </l>
            <l>And there I shall be able to make appear </l>
            <l>Cleantha and Endymion Equall are; </l>
            <l>Then possibly some of Cleantha's Earth </l>
            <l>May prove a little Flower, and look fresher </l>
            <l>Then when it was a part of a great Princess. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e9810">Enter Urania. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e9830">
            <speaker>Vran. </speaker>
            <l>Madam! the Queen expects your Highness. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e9860">
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <l>I'le wait on her.— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e9890">Ex. Cleantha. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e9900">
            <speaker>Vran. </speaker>
            <l>Endymion is return'd! what shall I do? </l>
            <l>To be at once both Just and Civil too. </l>
            <l>If I could satisfie Endymion's Love, </l>
            <l>I shou'd unjust to great Theander prove; </l>
            <l>That Prince who to so mean a thing as I, </l>
            <l>(Bred in a little Cottage) did bestow </l>
            <l>His Noble Heart, which is a Present fit </l>
            <l>For any Princess fruitful Greece can boast of: </l>
            <l>From whom if I could give my Love, I would not. </l>
            <l>Why did I give my Promise then last night? </l>
            <l>And yet the Generous Endymion </l>
            <l>Will sure forgive me when he knows the Cause: </l>
            <l>He's here; Heaven forgive me, what I'm forc'd to. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e10100">Enter Endymion. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e10120">
            <speaker>Endy. </speaker>
            <l>Madam! I come upon my Knees to beg your pardon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e10150">
            <speaker>Vran. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord, it is not well to mock me further, </l>
            <l>You have deluded me enough already: </l>
            <pb n="33" xml:id="ep000734-011-b"/>
            <l>Thus we that are so easie to bestow </l>
            <l>Our Love, the greatest Treasure we possess, </l>
            <l>Are still neglected by ungrateful men; </l>
            <l>But I had thought to have found more truth in you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e10230">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>Madam! 'twas my allegiance forc'd me from you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e10260">
            <speaker>Vran. </speaker>
            <l>Those men, who dare offer such injuries, </l>
            <l>Never want bolduess to excuse their Crimes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e10300">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>Had I refus'd t'obey my Kings Command, </l>
            <l>You could not think me Worthy of your Love. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e10340">
            <speaker>Vran. </speaker>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000734-e10370">aside </stage>He speaks a Truth, I ought, but dare not own, </l>
            <l>What a fond Fool was I to be so forward </l>
            <l>In trusting a Court Lord, to believe </l>
            <l>You e're would marry one of my mean Fortune. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e10410">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>Dear Vrania, I appeal to'th Gods </l>
            <l>Who are honour'd when they'r witnesses to truth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e10460">
            <speaker>Vran. </speaker>
            <l>Make no more Vows, I am not to be deceiv'd agen, </l>
            <l>I was too foolish to believe your last: Farewell, my Lord. </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000734-e10510">Aside. </stage>The Powers above forgive me.— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e10520">Ex. Vran. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e10530">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>How much unlike Vrania is this Passion? </l>
            <l>Who us'd to be all Calm, and gentle still: </l>
            <l>And sure would be so, did not my unlucky </l>
            <l>Stars, that never meant me good, incline </l>
            <l>Her to this Anger.— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e10610">Ex. Neander. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e10620">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <l>Your servant, my Lord! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e10650">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>‛ Curse on this vain, Fop.— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e10680">Ex. Endym. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e10690">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Are you so stout; Farewell.— Well! I wonder whom the Devil intends I shall marry with? I have been a servant, as they call't; that is, I have Ly'd, and Sworn, and spent Money upon every Lady about the Court, and still am as far from having one of them as the very'st Evnuch is; nay more, for they say Evnuchs have a Trick now a-dayes to please the Ladies Exceedingly:— I was in most hopes of Evadne, and love her best: but the old Priest forbids her to see me, or speak with me; Here she comes! I will force her to hear me— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e10730">Enter Evadne <hi>in haste</hi>. </stage>Dear Apple of my Eye! why this haste? thou hast wounded me, and then thou fly'st me. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e10760">
            <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
            <p>There is a sufficient reason for't. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e10790">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Must then Neander die? </p>
          </sp>
          <gap extent="2" reason="missing" unit="pages"/>
          <lg>
            <pb n="36" xml:id="ep000734-012-a"/>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000734-e10870">Cho. of 3. </stage>Here our own proper Flocks of Sheep </l>
            <l>We may in pleasant safety keep. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Here a perpetual Spring does cloath the Earth, </l>
            <l>And makes it fruitful with each seasons birth. </l>
            <l>In this fair Climate every day </l>
            <l>Is fresh and green as May, </l>
            <l>And here no beauty can decay. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000734-e10980">Cho. of 3. </stage>Thus, thus live we, </l>
            <l>As the Elements free </l>
            <l>Each day and each night </l>
            <l>Is Crown'd with delight </l>
            <l>Without either Envy or Strife </l>
            <l>This is the Iolly Shepherds life. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg n="2">
            <head>2. </head>
            <l>Free from all Cares in pleasant Shades, </l>
            <l>And fragrant Bowres, we spend the day; </l>
            <l>(Bowers which no Heat, nor Cold invades; </l>
            <l>Which all the year are fresh and gay) </l>
            <l>Each does his Loving Mate imbrace, </l>
            <l>And in soft pleasures melts the Hours away, </l>
            <l>So Innocently that no Face, </l>
            <l>Of Nimph or Shepherd can a guilt betray: </l>
            <l>And having Ease, the Nurse of Poetry, </l>
            <l>We sing the stories of our Loves, </l>
            <l>As Chaste as Turtle-Doves, </l>
            <l>Free from all Fear and Iealousie </l>
            <l>From every Envious Eye: </l>
            <l>For every Man possesses but his own, </l>
            <l>No Shepherd sighs, nor Shepherdess does frown: </l>
            <l>No Ambition here is found, </l>
            <l>But to be Crown'd </l>
            <l>Lord or Lady of the May; </l>
            <l>And on that solemn day, </l>
            <l>For Singing to have praise </l>
            <l>Or for inditing to deserve the Bayes, </l>
            <l>Thus, thus, live we, &amp;c. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg n="3">
            <pb n="37" xml:id="ep000734-012-b"/>
            <head>3. </head>
            <l>In the Cool Evening, on the Lawns we play, </l>
            <l>And merrily pass our time away. </l>
            <l>We dance, and run, and pipe, and sing, </l>
            <l>And Wrastle in a Ring. </l>
            <l>For some gawdy Wreaths of Flowers, </l>
            <l>Cropt from the fruitful Fields, and Bowers. </l>
            <l>By some pretty Nymps compos'd, </l>
            <l>By their fair hands to be dispos'd, </l>
            <l>To those ambitious Shepherds, who </l>
            <l>With Vertuous Emulation strive to do </l>
            <l>What may deserve the Garlands, and (obtain'd) </l>
            <l>Are prouder far than Princes that have gain'd </l>
            <l>In fight their Valours prize, </l>
            <l>Or ever stubborn Nation's Victories; </l>
            <l>Whilst in the adjoyning Grove the Nightingale </l>
            <l>Does tell her mournful Tale, </l>
            <l>And does our Pleasures greet, </l>
            <l>With each Note, </l>
            <l>So sweet, so sweet, so sweet </l>
            <l>From her pretty jugging, jugging throat. </l>
            <l>It does each Breast inspire </l>
            <l>With loving heat and with Poetick Fire. </l>
            <l>Thus, thus live we, &amp;c. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg n="4">
            <head>4. </head>
            <l>We live aloof from Destiny, </l>
            <l>(That onely quarrells with the Great) </l>
            <l>And in this Calm Rretreat, </l>
            <l>(Content with Nature uncorrupted) we </l>
            <l>From splendid miseries of Courts are free; </l>
            <l>From pomp, and noise, from pride, and fear, </l>
            <l>From Factions, from divisions Cleer, </l>
            <l>Free from brave beggery, smiling strife. </l>
            <l>This is indeed a Life: </l>
          </lg>
          <gap extent="2" reason="missing" unit="pages"/>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e11690">
            <pb n="40" xml:id="ep000734-013-a"/>
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <l>O Gods! banish Endymion: desire Evadne to come </l>
            <l>To me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e11750">
            <speaker>Vran. </speaker>
            <l>I will— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e11780">Ex. Vrania. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e11790">
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <l>Wretched Cleantha! is thy Love a Crime, </l>
            <l>A Crime to him thou lov'st? must it be ruine </l>
            <l>To a person, if thou but affect'st him? </l>
            <l>Have I some Plague that I must thus destroy, </l>
            <l>Whom I embrace? or is my Destiny </l>
            <l>Grown Paradoxical, and proves my Love </l>
            <l>To be true Hatred?— </l>
            <l>O Death! thou art not half so Cruel yet, </l>
            <l>In thy destructions of the Prosp'rous, </l>
            <l>As in not killing Wretches that would die. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e11920">Enter Endymion. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e11940">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>Vrania does not well to treat me thus: </l>
            <l>I took no leave of her, but I have told her </l>
            <l>The reasons why my Love forbad it me, </l>
            <l>Yet she persists in Cruelty. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e12010">
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <l>He's here— </l>
            <l>His Count'nance betokens grief. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e12050">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>To be thus angry and accuse me of </l>
            <l>Slighting a poor deluded Maid </l>
            <l>In spight of all my Vows of Love to her— </l>
            <l>The Princess still is Gracious to me: </l>
            <l>I had best intreat her to perswade my now </l>
            <l>Provok'd Vrania She's here; </l>
            <l>But she's alone, I dare not interrupt her Thoughts. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e12150">
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <l>Good morrow, my Lord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e12180">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>Your pardon, Madam, if unthought of, I </l>
            <l>Have rushed on your Retirement. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e12220">
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <l>Your Presence will better it. </l>
            <l>'Pray what News from Argos? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e12270">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>Madam, the Report was brought last night to Cortu </l>
            <l>Had nothing on't of Truth: I found all quiet, </l>
            <l>But onely for the disturbance which we made </l>
            <l>Our selves by our Arrival in the Night. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e12330">
            <pb n="41" xml:id="ep000734-013-b"/>
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <l>I am glad my Lord your danger was no more. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e12360">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>You oblige me Madam to undergo </l>
            <l>Much greater danger for your Highness then </l>
            <l>This could have prov'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e12410">
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord! you have already </l>
            <l>Serv'd me beyond what I can recompence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e12450">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>Madam! t'has been your Highness's pleasure still </l>
            <l>To honour with two great respects the little </l>
            <l>Merits of your mean Servant, who's advanc'd </l>
            <l>When numbred in the lowest rank of those </l>
            <l>That have been Fortunate to do you service. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e12520">
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <l>You add still to my debts, my Lord, yet are </l>
            <l>No way injurious, since you make me rich </l>
            <l>In having such a Noble Creditor: </l>
            <l>But pray, my Lord, tell me, (as one concern'd </l>
            <l>Much in your Fortunes) what's the Cause </l>
            <l>Your Lordship has not worn of late that rest </l>
            <l>Upon your looks which heretofore appear'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e12610">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>Madam, it is for you to wear that rest who are </l>
            <l>Plac'd in that upper Region where there is </l>
            <l>No Wind, but a little Bark, i'th midst </l>
            <l>Of a great Sea, subject to every Wave, </l>
            <l>And every gust of Wind, can ne're pretend </l>
            <l>To this blest ' State. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e12690">
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord; you have som griefs that are particular. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e12720">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>For my troubles, Madam, </l>
            <l>Alas; their objects would appear so small </l>
            <l>To your great Eye, you'd think I did affront you </l>
            <l>Shou'd I dare say them to you. Could the Lyon </l>
            <l>In his Midnight-walks hear some poor Worms </l>
            <l>Complain for want of little drops of dew, </l>
            <l>What pity could that noble Creature have, </l>
            <l>Who never wanted small things, for those poor </l>
            <l>Ambitions? yet these are their concernments, </l>
            <l>And but for want of these they pine and die. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e12840">
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <l>I hope my Lord what is your Trouble may </l>
            <l>Not be augmented by my knowing it, </l>
            <l>Else I shall never think ought small that can </l>
            <gap extent="2" reason="missing" unit="pages"/>
            <pb n="44" xml:id="ep000734-014-a"/>
            <l>Thus to instruct you in Astronomy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e12920">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>I am lost in wonder:— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e12950">Aside. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Madam, 'tis not strange, </l>
            <l>If I'm proud of what you blush at, but </l>
            <l>I am sure your unbounded wit to morrow </l>
            <l>Will with much greater reason quite deny it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e13000">
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord, you think no woman can be constant </l>
            <l>To what she sayes a day, but your Vrania: </l>
            <l>But till you have try'd, pray have more Charity, </l>
            <l>You'l after have more Faith: my Lord Farewell: </l>
            <l>The Gods forgive my breach of Modesty— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e13080">Aside. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e13090">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>What have I heard! </l>
            <l>Was't not enough to lose my dear Urania, </l>
            <l>Unless I also did adore the hand </l>
            <l>That snatch'd her from me, Cleantha Loves Endymion </l>
            <l>But Fool it cannot be; ne're may I know </l>
            <l>Her Noble breast harbour a thought so low.— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e13200">Exeunt. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <trailer>The End of the Third Act. </trailer>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="ep000734-e13220">
          <head>THE FOURTH ACT. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e13240">Enter Neander. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e13260">
            <speaker>〈◊〉. </speaker>
            <p>I Was (at least in my own conceit) in probability of winning the sweet Evadne; and now, that not onely her ugly Father, but the Queen too should forbid her to see me or speak to me; it is what I cannot, will not bear: Though Fate it self say, I shall do it, I am resolv'd that old grey Priest and his Mistress the Queen, shall be the subjects of my Revenge: and yet I am not ambitious to show my Valour so far, as to be hang'd for't neither— I think I ha't; If I can do this, 'twill be the sweetest part of my Revenge, to live, and tread, and spit upon their Graves: I have sent for Geron, a Rogue sit for my purpose, for he is Covetous to Extremity, and I have Gold to bribe him, and which is <pb n="45" xml:id="ep000734-014-b"/>lucky above my Wishes, the Priest and Queen have chec'kd him lately, and countenanc'd his Wife against him, which torments him so, that I believe he would be glad to be hang'd on any terms.— Here he is. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e13310">Enter Geron. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e13330">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>Consume him he's here— </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e13360">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <l>Dear Geron, let him embrace thee that </l>
            <l>Perhaps is thy best Friend. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e13410">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <l>Perhaps, with a Curse to him— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e13440">Aside. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>No, my Lord, you are a Friend to my Wife. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e13460">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <l>Geron! give me your hand. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e13500">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <l>Wou'd I had your Heart's blood.— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e13530">Aside. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e13540">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <l>Give me your Hand, Geron. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e13580">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <l>My Good Lord! you do me too much honour. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e13610">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <l>I beg your pardon heartily that I presum'd to </l>
            <l>Count'nance your ugly, impertinent, ill-natur'd, vain </l>
            <l>Wife against you, you that are so worthy an honest Knight; </l>
            <l>It was Ignorance of her, and you made me do it. I protest it was. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e13670">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>What the Devil does he mean by this?— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e13700">Aside. </stage>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e13710">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Upon my Honour Geron it was; had I not been a stranger to her ill Qualities. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e13750">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>I am afraid you know 'em too well.— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e13780">Aside. </stage>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e13790">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>I should never have encourag'd her in her Insolence to you. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e13820">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>What does all this tend to?— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e13850">Aside. </stage>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e13860">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>For I am well satisfy'd, a Man, especially an old Man that has had experience of the vanity of the World, ought to have an absolute Dominion over his Wife. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e13890">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>My Lord, this is a Truth! I would you had acknowledg'd sooner; for my abominable Wife, instead of being humbled, is ●ncourg'd by the Court. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e13920">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>I know though too late now, your Wife is froward, Foolish, petulant, wanton, proud, expensive, disobedient, Ungrateful.— </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e13950">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>'Tis too true; but a Plague on him, I am afraid he has </p>
            <gap extent="2" reason="missing" unit="pages"/>
            <pb n="48" xml:id="ep000734-015-a"/>
            <p>Night resum'd his desires, and that Vrania has promis'd it in earnest. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e14020">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>But Vrania will contradict that— </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e14060">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>No; she ask'd the Princess liberty to leave the Court a day or two for some private business or other, and is now absent. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e14090">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Excellent Geron! but how shall we carry this story? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e14130">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>My Wife; who shall still be ignorant of the matter. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e14160">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Admirably invented: thou shal't have the Talents; besides if thy Wife shou'd discover thee or me, if she be question'd, we'l face her down in't and she shall hang for't. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e14190">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>That Argument prevails with me more then the Talents: whether she betrays us or no, we'l do that my Lord. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e14220">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>With all my heart, Excellent Geron: for the Priest, thou shalt go to him, and subtilly perswade him that the Queen has made an appointment to meet me in the Grotto, and that I to avoid suspition am to be in Womans Cloaths. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e14260">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>My Lord, he'll ne're believe it. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e14290">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Do thou confirm it by ten thousand Oaths. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e14320">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>That will be dang'rous. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e14350">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>Not at all: But think on the Talents, and the death of thy Wife man: Thou maist perswade the Priest to meet her to prevent it in a Womans loose habit, and then bring the King to see them. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e14380">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>But the Priest will soon undeceive the King. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e14410">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <p>No, no, fear not that, the King will be so inrag'd: 'tis ten to one he kills 'em both without Examination; if not, you and I, who will be the first Accusers will swear 'em both down in't; think upon Revenge and Profit. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e14440">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>My Lord— I'le do't about the time of this Even'ng Sacrifice for the Victory of Theander. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e14480">Enter Endymion <hi>with a Guard.</hi>
          </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e14510">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>What means this? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e14540">
            <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
            <l>O Endymion's banish'd. </l>
            <l>And this Guard is to convey him out of the </l>
            <l>Kings Dominions; let him be hang'd and </l>
            <l>He will.— let us about our business— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e14610">
                <hi>Ex. Geron </hi>and Nean. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e14640">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>May I not see the Princess for </l>
            <l>Whom I am banish'd before I go? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e14680">
            <pb n="49" xml:id="ep000734-015-b"/>
            <speaker>Officer. </speaker>
            <l>No, no, along Sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e14710">
            <speaker>1. Sould. </speaker>
            <l>Pray Sir, go a little faster. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e14750">
            <speaker>2. Sould. </speaker>
            <l>Prethee, let the Gentleman alone, soft </l>
            <l>And fair goes far, and the Gentleman </l>
            <l>Considers he has far to go. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e14810">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>Farewell than brave Cleantha, may'st thou never </l>
            <l>Once think Endymion suffers for thy sake: </l>
            <l>And farewell dear Vrania, I will love thee </l>
            <l>On those hard Rocks I now must dwell upon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e14900">
            <speaker>Officer. </speaker>
            <p>What's this muttering? Along Sir. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e14930">
            <speaker>2. Sould. </speaker>
            <l>Good Gentleman! he's loath to leave the Princess </l>
            <l>I warrant him. <stage xml:id="ep000734-e14980">Enter Cleantha. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e15000">
            <speaker>1. Sould. </speaker>
            <l>Here she comes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e15040">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>The Princess!— Great Princess pardon </l>
            <l>My glorious sufferings; forgive me that <stage xml:id="ep000734-e15080">Kneels. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>I ever saw the Light, or liv'd a Minute: </l>
            <l>That you are injur'd thus by him whose being </l>
            <l>Is not worth your meanest thought. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e15120">
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <l>Ah, my Lord, affront me not: </l>
            <l>Rise brave Endymion! 'Tis my misfortune: </l>
            <l>Thou art too low already. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e15180">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>Fortune made me low to be advanc'd by a hand </l>
            <l>More Worthy than her own. <stage xml:id="ep000734-e15220">Rises. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e15230">
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <l>My Noble Lord! </l>
            <l>I have undone you! what can I give you now </l>
            <l>In recompence of Liberty, and all </l>
            <l>The pleasures you must loose </l>
            <l>In a sad banishment, for her who onely </l>
            <l>Can be afflicted at your sufferings. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e15310">
            <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
            <l>Madam, you have Enough to give to pay </l>
            <l>So mean a debt, if you will call it one </l>
            <l>A thousand times. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e15360">
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <l>Name it, and take it, dear </l>
            <l>Endymion, though it be my life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e15410">
            <speaker>Endy. </speaker>
            <l>Madam! </l>
            <l>Then grant me this request: use every art </l>
            <l>To make your Hours as blest as I shall pray </l>
            <l>They may be many; and never let a thought </l>
            <gap extent="2" reason="missing" unit="pages"/>
            <pb n="52" xml:id="ep000734-016-a"/>
            <l>My impatience to be troublesome to others. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e15500">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>You grieve for Endymion, when all Arcadia </l>
            <l>Rejoyces at the Victory of </l>
            <l>Theander, which this Evening we shall Celebrate </l>
            <l>With Sacrifices, and with other Rites, for whom </l>
            <l>We will prepare a publick Triumph: </l>
            <l>Compose your self, and let not others see </l>
            <l>Your shame. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e15620">
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <l>My Shame they ne're <stage xml:id="ep000734-e15650">Aside. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>Shall see; Call it my Glory, so it is. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e15670">Enter Pyrrhus. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e15690">
            <speaker>Pyrr. </speaker>
            <l>Sir, the Sacrifice is ready for the </l>
            <l>Altar, and the Priests wait your Royal presence </l>
            <l>For the Execution. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e15740">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Niece! think on what I've said, and follow us. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e15770">Ex. King and Pyrr. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e15800">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>Come, dear Cleantha, prithee be not sad, </l>
            <l>The Prince of Macedon will be fitter for </l>
            <l>Your noble Blood which is deriv'd from Kings. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e15870">
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <l>And some other will be fitter for him </l>
            <l>Then I, unless he likes a broken heart. </l>
            <l>Besides the Prince is Contracted already to </l>
            <l>The Queen of Thrace's eldest Daughter. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e15940">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>She is long since dead. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e15970">
            <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
            <l>Who can tell that, Madam; I am apt to believe </l>
            <l>If she had her Kingdom yet the Prince would find </l>
            <l>Her out. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e16020">Enter Phronesia. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e16040">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>What News with you? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e16070">
            <speaker>Phro. </speaker>
            <l>News that does import your Majesty.— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e16100">Whisper. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e16110">Enter Geron. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e16130">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>Madam! the Queen and your Highness are expected at the Temple▪ this will be a night of Joy. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e16160">
            <speaker>Clean </speaker>
            <l>That brings me nought but sorrow; the name of joy </l>
            <l>Is odious to me, since Endymion's gone. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e16210">
            <pb n="53" xml:id="ep000734-016-b"/>
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <p>Art thou sure of this Phronesia? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e16250">
            <speaker>Phro. </speaker>
            <p>Yes, Madam, doubt it not. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e16280">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>The Gods amend all once more, I'le prevent it: </l>
            <l>But first I'le to the Temple; Come Cleantha. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e16330">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <l>What have you told the Queen </l>
            <l>What I enjoyn'd you? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e16370">
            <speaker>Phro. </speaker>
            <p>I have, and she is resolv'd to Circumvent him: Come to the Temple, haste.— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e16400">Ex. Phron. </stage>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e16410">
            <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
            <p>Thus far it goes well; I have with many Oaths and Protestations confirm'd the Priest in the belief that Neander in Womans Cloaths is this night to meet the Queen: it takes admirably— The Talents are my own, and this wife of mine is dead already. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e16450">The Scene changes to the Temple. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000734-e16460">After the Sacrifice, there is a Consort of Martial Musick, and two or three of the Salii or Priests of Mars sing as follows. </stage>
          <floatingText>
            <body>
              <div type="song" xml:id="ep000734-e16520">
                <lg n="1">
                  <head>1. </head>
                  <l>ALL Praises to the God of War, </l>
                  <l>Who in our Battels gives Success, </l>
                  <l>By whom we now Victorious are, </l>
                  <l>Who does not onely us with Conquests bless, </l>
                  <l>But 'tis his Pow'r that gives us Peace. </l>
                  <l>Arcadia now may safely that enjoy, </l>
                  <l>Thessalians cannot that destroy: </l>
                  <l>For brave Theander has our Foes opprest, </l>
                  <l>And by his Noble Toyls procur'd our Rest. </l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="2">
                  <head>2. </head>
                  <l>In vain they did their Heedless Force oppose, </l>
                  <l>Against such Courage, and such Conduct too, </l>
                  <l>Such as requir'd more strong and numerous Foes▪ </l>
                  <l>Fit for his Noble fury to subdue. </l>
                  <l>Oh how he thunder'd in the Van, </l>
                  <l>Godlike he threaten'd, and did more than man●. </l>
                </lg>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
          <gap extent="2" reason="missing" unit="pages"/>
          <sp xml:id="ep000734-e16770">
            <pb n="56" xml:id="ep000734-017-a"/>
            <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
            <l>Heaven bless you Madam.— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e16800">to her— Exit. Queen. </stage>
            </l>
            <l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000734-e16820">To himself. </stage>And make you see your Crime </l>
            <l>In it's own horrid shape e're you attempt it, </l>
            <l>And yet she bears it with so much assurance </l>
            <l>I could believe her Innocent, yet why </l>
            <l>Should Geron dare to invoke all the Gods </l>
            <l>To testifie it; if it be false, what can </l>
            <l>Provoke him to this Villany? If true, </l>
            <l>She never will acknowledge it to me </l>
            <l>What ere it be; 'tis worth my venturing </l>
            <l>To be undeceiv'd.— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e16930">Ex. </stage>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="ep000734-e16940">
            <head>The Third Scene. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000734-e16970">Enter King, Geron and Pyrrhus. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e17000">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Is't possible? my Queen an Adultress? </l>
              <l>It cannot be: Be sure Sir, if you accuse her </l>
              <l>Falsly, ye shall not onely die, but </l>
              <l>Linger out a wretched life in Torments. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e17060">
              <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
              <l>Sir! if I lye, let me have what death </l>
              <l>The witty'st Cruelty can invent. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e17100">
              <speaker>Pyrr. </speaker>
              <l>I am amaz'd! the Queen and Priest </l>
              <l>In Womans Cloathes? strange Circumstance </l>
              <l>To meet in Grotto, this Night? Sure 'tis </l>
              <l>Impossible. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e17160">
              <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
              <p>Sir, I am content to dye fort, if you see not your self all this to Night. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e17190">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <p>In the mean time, you'l be content to be secur'd? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e17220">
              <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
              <p>Sir with all my heart. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e17250">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <p>Guard! take Geron, and secure him till further order. </p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000734-e17290">Enter Guard, and seizes him. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e17300">
              <speaker>Pyrr. </speaker>
              <p>Sir! this dreadful news amazes me! </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e17330">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Ah Pyrrhus? in this very Grotto </l>
              <l>I met Urania, and forgot the Queen, </l>
              <l>Tho' then I thought her faithful. </l>
              <l>And as free from any Carnal thoughts </l>
              <l>At 〈◊〉 departed Souls in th' other world. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e17420">
              <pb n="57" xml:id="ep000734-017-b"/>
              <speaker>Pyrr. </speaker>
              <l>The Gods grant this meeting prove no worse </l>
              <l>Than that did. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e17460">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <p>O Heav'n! methinks I see 'em already in their Lust, yet sure it cannot be; if I find this Accusation false, it had been better for this fellow he never had been born. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e17490">
              <speaker>Pyrr. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, you may yet prevent it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e17520">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>I may for this time, but I will not harbour </l>
              <l>That Devil Jealousie within my breast </l>
              <l>For all this World can give me: I am resolv'd </l>
              <l>To see the certainty my self; and if </l>
              <l>It prove untrue, my Queen shall live with freedom, </l>
              <l>As she has ever done, in all my Thoughts, </l>
              <l>And her Accuser fall her Sacrifice: </l>
              <l>But if she can forget her former Vertue, </l>
              <l>I can take as much pleasure to see her blood </l>
              <l>Drop from the fatal Sword, as e're I did </l>
              <l>To see it blushing on her Cheek, when first </l>
              <l>I thought her modest▪ </l>
              <l>Look! where they come— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e17670">Enter Queen and Priest. </stage>
              </l>
              <l>Let us withdraw; it may be we shall </l>
              <l>Discover something. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e17700">
              <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
              <l>And nothing is more Common </l>
              <l>Then this, which is not thought a sin, because </l>
              <l>It seems an Impulse of Nature. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e17750">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Hear'st thou Pyrrhus? I am distracted! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e17790">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>The King. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e17820">
              <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
              <l>All happiness attend your Majesty. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e17850">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>I must contain! how do you Madam? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e17880">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>Always happy whilst your Majesty is so. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e17910">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>And what are you discoursing of? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e17940">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>Nothing! but good with this good person sure. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e17970">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>What●s that you talk of which is not Sin </l>
              <l>Because an impulse of Nature?— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e18010">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>What do you mean Sir? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e18040">
              <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
              <l>I know not how we came by Chance to speak </l>
              <l>How little wantonness is thought a sin </l>
              <l>Because it seemeth an Impulse of Nature. </l>
              <l>Whereas the Vertuous still fix their Eyes </l>
              <gap extent="2" reason="missing" unit="pages"/>
              <pb n="60" xml:id="ep000734-018-a"/>
              <l>It has been very long, two hours at least: <stage xml:id="ep000734-e18130">Enter a Lord of the Councel. </stage>
              </l>
              <l>It's bad enough for certain: here it comes! </l>
              <l>My Lord, you have been long; but I expect </l>
              <l>No good; and therefore care not if you had </l>
              <l>Been longer. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e18180">
              <speaker>Lord. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, before I can satisfie your Expectations, </l>
              <l>I must humbly pray you will be pleas'd to pardon </l>
              <l>The intreating your Answer to a Question </l>
              <l>On which all we have done depends. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e18240">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>What's that? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e18270">
              <speaker>Lord. </speaker>
              <l>I may seem too insolent: but the whole Truth </l>
              <l>Of all the Examination does depend </l>
              <l>Upon't; that is, Whether your Majesty </l>
              <l>Did not one night Command a little Lady, </l>
              <l>That waits on the Princess, one Vrania, </l>
              <l>To attend you in that Grotto, where </l>
              <l>The Queen and Priest were seiz'd on▪ </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e18370">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>I did. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e18400">
              <speaker>Lord. </speaker>
              <l>And she was there? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e18430">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>She was. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e18460">
              <speaker>Lord. </speaker>
              <p>Is your Majesty assur'd it was she, or might it be the Queen? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e18490">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <p>Ha!— her Whispers were like the Queens: Pyrrhus knows I told him so. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e18530">
              <speaker>Lord. </speaker>
              <l>Be happy then great Prince; </l>
              <l>Your Queen is Innocent; your Priest is holy, </l>
              <l>And Geron and Neander onely are </l>
              <l>The Criminals. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e18610">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Are you assur'd of this? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e18640">
              <speaker>Lord. </speaker>
              <l>Yes Sir; it was the Hellish contrivance of </l>
              <l>Geron and Neander brought them both together. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e18700">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Why did not the Queen reveal this? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e18730">
              <speaker>Lord. </speaker>
              <l>She rather would have dy'd then have disclos'd </l>
              <l>Your S●mmo●● to Vrania, which with your Majesties </l>
              <l>Pardon, she's pleas'd to call your dishonour. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e18790">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>My Lord it was; but pray relieve my Wonder </l>
              <l>And tell me the whole Story. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e18830">
              <speaker>Lord. </speaker>
              <p>Sir, in this Confession of Geron and Neander, and Phronesia, <pb n="61" xml:id="ep000734-018-b"/>which we, (having found them Tripping in some part of the Story) by threatning Tortures, have extorted from 'em: Your Majesty may fully read the Story of the Innocence of the Queen and Priest, and of the guilt of these Barbarous Wretches. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e18890">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Blest ' Heaven! how are thy wayes just like thy Orbes, </l>
              <l>Involv'd within each other: yet still we find </l>
              <l>Thy Judgements are like Comets that do blaze, </l>
              <l>And fright, but die withall, whilst all thy Mercies </l>
              <l>Are like the Stars which ofttimes are obscur'd, </l>
              <l>But still remain the same behind the Clouds. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e18970">
              <speaker>Pyrr. </speaker>
              <l>May all your Doubts and Fears thus terminate▪ </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e19000">
              <speaker>Lord. </speaker>
              <l>Thus are you shaken to be more confirm'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e19030">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Send for <hi>Vrania, Pyrrhus</hi>! she shall wear </l>
              <l>This day the just rewards of Virtue; I </l>
              <l>Will visit my brave Queen, who rather chose </l>
              <l>To die unjustly as a Criminal </l>
              <l>Then I should justly be so term'd, </l>
              <l>For which I will proclaim my Fault since she </l>
              <l>Will have the Glory of concealing it. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000734-e19130">Enter Evadne. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e19150">
              <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
              <l>The King seems pleas'd, as he has reason. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e19180">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>My Lord! let the Councel remove </l>
              <l>Into the Hall, where before all the Court </l>
              <l>I'le bring my Queen in Triumph there to hear </l>
              <l>Her base Accusers sentenc'd.— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e19240">
                  <hi>Ex. all but </hi>Evadne▪ </stage>
              </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e19260">
              <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
              <l>I was told I should find Cleantha here— </l>
              <l>Why did I beg to leave my Cell? </l>
              <l>(Where I did never injure any one) </l>
              <l>To see this place, and in so little time </l>
              <l>To do more mischief than whole Generations </l>
              <l>Can parallel? how much </l>
              <l>Had it been better I had ever dwelt </l>
              <l>In those Retirements, where small Sins seem great▪ </l>
              <l>And great Devotions small, then to be here </l>
              <l>Where the blood of Queens and Priests had like </l>
              <l>To have been sacrific'd to the Malice of </l>
              <l>Wicked men? (had not the Gods taken the Cause </l>
            </sp>
            <gap extent="2" reason="missing" unit="pages"/>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e19430">
              <pb n="64" xml:id="ep000734-019-a"/>
              <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
              <l>How's this? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e19460">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>What mean'st thou? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e19490">
              <speaker>Gent. </speaker>
              <l>See Sir, see, </l>
              <l>Those Cheeks that lately Beauty wore, now pale </l>
              <l>With guilt. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e19540">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Her Crime! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e19570">
              <speaker>Gent. </speaker>
              <l>She is with Child. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e19600">
              <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
              <l>It is impossible; she cannot dissemble so much Vertue, </l>
              <l>I'le engage my Life she's Innocent. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e19640">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>How know you this? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e19670">
              <speaker>Gent. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, being sent in haste by my Lord Pyrrhus, </l>
              <l>To bring her to your Majesty, by chance </l>
              <l>I learn't of one o'th' Servants of the Princess </l>
              <l>Near to what place he thought she was: </l>
              <l>I made Enquiry there, at a small house </l>
              <l>I was acquainted at; The Woman told me, </l>
              <l>She thought she I enquir'd for was in the house: </l>
              <l>And asking of me many Circumstances, </l>
              <l>She told me it was surely she: but told me too, </l>
              <l>As a great Secret, That she was with Child, </l>
              <l>But that she said she was Marry'd; </l>
              <l>As did her Mother who this morning left her, </l>
              <l>At this I went to Vrania, who confes't it, </l>
              <l>But would not tell me who her Husband was, </l>
              <l>And was very loth to come with me, though </l>
              <l>I told her, your Majesty had sent for her. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e19870">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>And is this truth Urania? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e19910">
              <speaker>1. Lord. </speaker>
              <l>Speak to the King. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e19950">
              <speaker>Vran. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis true. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e19980">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>And who's your Husband? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e20010">
              <speaker>Lord. </speaker>
              <l>be not: sham'd to name your Husband, Madam, </l>
              <l>'Twill be your shame if you name none. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e20050">
              <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
              <l>I am not asham'd to name him, but affraid— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e20080">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>〈◊〉 is't, speak? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e20110">
              <speaker>Vran. </speaker>
              <l>〈…〉 not disobey, and by my Lord </l>
              <l>Am autho● 〈…〉 him, when </l>
              <l>〈…〉 question'd, who's more tender </l>
              <l>〈…〉 his own. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e20180">
              <pb n="65" xml:id="ep000734-019-b"/>
              <speaker>1. Lord. </speaker>
              <l>Name him! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e20220">
              <speaker>Vran. </speaker>
              <l>It is the Great Theander. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e20260">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>The Prince! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e20290">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>What are you marry'd to the Prince! </l>
              <l>Marry'd to Theander?— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e20340">Rises in a Fury. </stage>
              </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e20350">
              <speaker>Vran. </speaker>
              <l>O pardon me, Great King, </l>
              <l>That I refus'd not to be taken from </l>
              <l>A Cottage, to the bosome of a Prince, </l>
              <l>On such Conditions as we dar'd to call </l>
              <l>The Gods to Witness. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e20420">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Whether she be his Wife, </l>
              <l>Or onely dares affirm it, though she were </l>
              <l>More to me then my Eyes, she should </l>
              <l>Die e're I sleep. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e20480">
              <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
              <l>Upon my Knees I beg, </l>
              <l>Great Sir, you will recall this hasty Sentence; </l>
              <l>It is the Princes fault, not hers. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e20530">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>I will hear </l>
              <l>No Intercessions— by the Honour of a King, </l>
              <l>I swear it.— The Prince in some few hours </l>
              <l>Will be in Town;— if what she sayes be false, </l>
              <l>This news shall be his welcome: but if true, </l>
              <l>'Tis fit his coming be too late to save her. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e20610">
              <speaker>Vran. </speaker>
              <l>Ah, Great Prince, pity the distress'd who has </l>
              <l>No friend to plead her Cause; all I affirm </l>
              <l>Is truth; Theander is my Witness, see <stage xml:id="ep000734-e20670">
                  <hi>Takes a Letter out of her bosome. </hi>
                </stage>
              </l>
              <l>That Noble Name; this I receiv'd from him </l>
              <l>Not three dayes since. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000734-e20710">King reads it and gives it to the Queen. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e20720">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis so; but know Vrania! </l>
              <l>My Crown would prove too heavy for your off-spring, </l>
              <l>Fit onely for Cottages; it will behove you to </l>
              <l>Prepare for death this day within Two hours. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e20790">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>Sir hold! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e20820">
              <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
              <l>I beseech your Majesty— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e20850">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>I charge you on your Loyalty to hold; </l>
              <l>I swear again this day within two hours </l>
              <l>I'le see her head off▪ Marshall take her hence, </l>
            </sp>
            <gap extent="2" reason="missing" unit="pages"/>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e20920">
              <pb n="68" xml:id="ep000734-020-a"/>
              <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
              <p>Peace, wicked Woman! </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e20950">
              <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
              <p>O vile Woman! 'tis you that have brought me to this! must I be cut in pieces? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e20980">
              <speaker>Phro. </speaker>
              <p>Truly loving Husband you must, and be given to Doggs too, but they'l have but ill Commons of you; you will be mighty tough; besides you have so many diseases, that if you were divided into as many pieces as there are hairs in your Beard, each Morsel would own a several Malady: for my part I would not advise any Dog that I have a kindness for to taste of you, for fear of endangering his health. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21010">
              <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
              <p>O thou abominable filthy Hag, if thou wert to be serv'd so first, it would not trouble me. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21040">
              <speaker>Phro. </speaker>
              <p>O Sir, you would have drawn me in, but I shall live to tread upon your Grave! you know it were ill manners for me to be hang'd before my Husband! but how does your Lordship? will you have some Greek-wine to comfort your cold stomack, you'l die with the fear on't else before to morrow morning; but I beseech you, my Lord, do not forget, if you do live till then, to have a Nose-gay, and a pair of white Gloves, with clean Linnen too, for the Execution! Men of quality are always very cleanly when they go to be hang'd. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21070">
              <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
              <p>O! what will become of me? I shall never be able to indure it. Oh! you old cowardly Sot! this comes of your confessing; Rogue. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21100">
              <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
              <p>This may thank your villanous design, with a Curse to you, I was onely drawn in. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21130">
              <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
              <p>You deserve to be hang'd Rascal, and will be so. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21160">
              <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
              <p>'Twill be some comfort to me to have a Lord suffer with me, but 'twould be more honour to me, if that Lord were a wiser man. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21190">
              <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
              <p>O! you old Dog! that I could come at you. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21220">
              <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
              <p>That I could poyson you with my breath, but that 'twould put you out of your pain, which is your immoderate fear. </p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000734-e21250">Enter Priest. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21260">
              <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
              <p>Peace be here! </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21290">
              <speaker>Phro. </speaker>
              <p>You come as seasonably as can be, for the Traytors are at Civil War. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21320">
              <pb n="69" xml:id="ep000734-020-b"/>
              <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
              <p>Away, woman, and interrupt 'em not. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21350">
              <speaker>Phro. </speaker>
              <p>I will not take my leave on you, for I intend to see my dear Husband again, at least before you be cut into Messes, Farewell.— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e21380">Ex. Phron. </stage>
              </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21390">
              <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
              <p>I am now come to speak to you as dying men. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21420">
              <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
              <p>Ay, ay, you old Rascal Geron, whom may that thank? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21460">
              <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
              <p>A villanous Lord that corrupted a poor innocent man as I was: a Curse on him for drawing me in. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21490">
              <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
              <p>A Curse upon an old Cowardly Rogue, to let his fear betray us. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21520">
              <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
              <p>Come, 'tis not now a season to quarrel with one another, but to make peace with the Gods: I am come to prepare you for your deaths, and first Neander I begin with you. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21560">
              <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
              <p>'Pray Sir begin with him, he needs it most! he has alwayes been the most perfidious, impious Wretch. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21590">
              <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
              <p>I need it most? I scorn to be prepar'd any more then your self, if you go to that, with that ugly, pocky Whore-masters face of your own. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21620">
              <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
              <p>Sir, it's no matter what he sayes; he has as much malice to good men, as Whores have to honest Women </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21650">
              <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
              <p>I must first begin with you my Lord. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21680">
              <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
              <p>Look there, he knows who has most need on't. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21710">
              <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
              <p>Peace Wisard, peace! do you say this to me? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21740">
              <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
              <p>Peace stupid Wretches, I command you: and confess, and repent of your most horrid Crimes. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21770">
              <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
              <p>Well Sir, I have done; and I do confess from the bottom of my heart— O you old dry, raw-bon'd, wretched, decrepit-Cuckold you, to bring me to this. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21800">
              <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
              <p>Heav'n! what impiety is this? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21830">
              <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
              <p>Ay Sir! you see his Devotion? O! Villainous wicked man. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21860">
              <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
              <p>Sir! hold your Tongue! my Lord, 'tis time now to be sensible of your sad condition. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21890">
              <speaker>Ger. </speaker>
              <p>Ay Sir! so it is, if you knew as much as I do of his wickedness, you'd say so. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21920">
              <speaker>Nean. </speaker>
              <p>Well Sir! I do confess, I'le torment the Rogue <stage xml:id="ep000734-e21950">Aside. </stage>I have many Sins to repent of— First— I have been naught with that old fellow's Wife. </p>
            </sp>
            <gap extent="2" reason="missing" unit="pages"/>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e21990">
              <pb n="72" xml:id="ep000734-021-a"/>
              <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
              <l>If pitty poor Urania could do thee good, </l>
              <l>Thou hast enough on't. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e22040">
              <speaker>Vran. </speaker>
              <l>I do confess I'm marry'd to the Prince; </l>
              <l>But he will witness for me 'twas th' effect </l>
              <l>Of his own Choice: I never presum'd </l>
              <l>To think it till he told me it should be so; </l>
              <l>Since when how faithful I have been to him </l>
              <l>Witness! Oh! Heaven! and all those Pow'rs that dare </l>
              <l>Acquit whom Kings condemn; and tho' for this </l>
              <l>I now must suffer death, I cannot wish </l>
              <l>I had not don't, since 'twas the Prince's pleasure, </l>
              <l>Whom to contradict, to me were worse then death. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e22160">
              <speaker>Gent. </speaker>
              <l>Alas! I pity her, her Case is too severe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e22190">
              <speaker>Vran. </speaker>
              <l>And yet I feel </l>
              <l>That death is bitter, 'tis an Enemy </l>
              <l>Looks cruelly on those who have no friends: </l>
              <l>'Tis hard to undergo the greatest Task alone; </l>
              <l>But 'tis my Fate, and Heaven must be obey'd— </l>
              <l>— 'Tis a long hazard that we run in death, </l>
              <l>And a short warning rather does disturb </l>
              <l>Then sit us for it; were't not for this, </l>
              <l>I could be well content to close these Eyes </l>
              <l>That have of late beheld so little pleasure. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e22310">
              <speaker>Marsh. </speaker>
              <l>She draws Tears from my Eyes; I was not wont </l>
              <l>To be so soft. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e22350">
              <speaker>Vran. </speaker>
              <l>But I too long </l>
              <l>Detain you with Complaints, whose business is </l>
              <l>To see me die: Live happy brave Theander, </l>
              <l>May all thy Sorrows die with thy Vrania, </l>
              <l>And all those Joyes live with thee which she took </l>
              <l>〈◊〉 thy contents▪— May'st thou be happy in </l>
              <l>A Princess, great as thy own Merits, bright </l>
              <l>As thy own eyes, and vertuous as </l>
              <l>Are all thy Thoughts; and may she honour thee </l>
              <l>As truly as thy poor Vrania did. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e22500">
              <speaker>Execu. </speaker>
              <l>Are you ready, Madam? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e22530">
              <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
              <l>Who is this? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e22560">
              <speaker>Gent. </speaker>
              <l>Madam, 'tis your Destiny. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e22590">
              <pb n="73" rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000734-021-b"/>
              <speaker>Vran. </speaker>
              <l>O, it is he </l>
              <l>Sir, you can instruct me what I am to do; </l>
              <l>I never yet saw any body die. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e22640">
              <speaker>Gent. </speaker>
              <l>Madam, you must kneel. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e22670">
              <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
              <l>How will he strike? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e22700">
              <speaker>Gent. </speaker>
              <l>With all the mercy that he can. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e22730">
              <speaker>Execu. </speaker>
              <l>When you have ended all you have to say, </l>
              <l>Pray kneel with your Face that way, and give </l>
              <l>Some sign when I shall strike. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e22780">
              <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
              <l>I will. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e22810">
              <speaker>Evad. </speaker>
              <l>I cannot stay to see't; Farewell, dear Vrania. <stage xml:id="ep000734-e22850">Exit. Evad. </stage>
              </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e22870">
              <speaker>Vran. </speaker>
              <l>When I am dead, pray Sirs suffer none </l>
              <l>But my Mother to fit me for my Grave; </l>
              <l>She will be careful of me, she will pay </l>
              <l>Holy devotions for me, and bedew </l>
              <l>With pious Tears that face she still has lov'd: </l>
              <l>And may the Gods give comforts in her sorrows, </l>
              <l>And all those Stars which have been hard to me </l>
              <l>Be merciful to her— May my misfortune </l>
              <l>Work in her onely a more true content </l>
              <l>In the low Sphere she so securely moves in▪ </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e22990">
              <speaker>Execu. </speaker>
              <p>I think she'l ne're a done prating, they all keep such a coile when they come to die: Wou'd the King wou'd please to forbid all Speeches upon Scaffolds. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e23020">
              <speaker>Vran. </speaker>
              <l>Sirs! Farewel, pray present </l>
              <l>My humble Service to my Noble Princess, </l>
              <l>With thanks for all her Favours, in my life, </l>
              <l>And Charity in death— bless'd Gods assist me.— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e23080">Kneels. </stage>
              </l>
              <l>Pray expect the Sign. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e23100">
              <speaker>Execu. </speaker>
              <l>I shall.— </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000734-e23130">
              <hi>Enter in haste </hi>Parthenia Vrania's Mother </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e23160">
              <speaker>Parth. </speaker>
              <l>Stay stay the fatal Blow. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e23190">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>What's this? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e23220">
              <speaker>Par. </speaker>
              <l>A miserable Mother come to save her onely Child. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e23250">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Executioner do your Office. <stage xml:id="ep000734-e23280">One of the Gent. layes hold of the Executioner. </stage>
              </l>
              <gap extent="2" reason="missing" unit="pages"/>
              <pb n="76" xml:id="ep000734-022-a"/>
              <l>To dawn upon me, and instruct me, those </l>
              <l>Are neerer it, who kneel in humble Cells, </l>
              <l>Then such as stand on Tiptoe on high Towers. </l>
              <l>For now Theander makes Urania more </l>
              <l>A Princess, then a Kingdom could, by courting </l>
              <l>Her as a Shepherdess, and shews the World, </l>
              <l>That more then Chance conduc'd to her Greatness. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e23400">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Why did you not tell Theander the whole truth? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e23440">
              <speaker>Par. </speaker>
              <l>Sir, he marry'd her at Court, and I knew not of it </l>
              <l>Till he we was gone to the War in Thessaly: </l>
              <l>For witness of all this, I do invoke </l>
              <l>Those Pow'rs, who never testifie untruths; </l>
              <l>And here produce those small Remains of Greatness </l>
              <l>Misfortune yet hath left me; See, Sir, here <stage xml:id="ep000734-e23530">She shews several rich Iewels. </stage>
              </l>
              <l>That so fam'd Jewel which so many Kings </l>
              <l>Of Thrace have worn, and with such veneration </l>
              <l>Have still preserv'd on an old Prophesie, that </l>
              <l>This should preserve the Thracian Family. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e23600">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Pyrrhus! 'tis all true! Go tell the Queen and Princess this: </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000734-e23640">Ex. Pyrr. </stage>
              <l>I need no Testimony but those words, </l>
              <l>All Queens might blush to hear from Cottagers, </l>
              <l>But is it possible so mean a place </l>
              <l>So long should hold great Cleopatra? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e23700">
              <speaker>Par. </speaker>
              <l>Know, great Prince (and know it too </l>
              <l>From one who has experimented Greatness) </l>
              <l>When I had satisfy'd my self in my </l>
              <l>Endeavours of regaining my lost Rights, </l>
              <l>And saw 'em all unprosperous, (as if </l>
              <l>Heaven long enough had given one Family </l>
              <l>The priviledge to govern others) </l>
              <l>I was as well content to be the first </l>
              <l>Must learn to act with common people, </l>
              <l>As he who first was call'd from them to rule. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e23820">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Great Queen, </l>
              <l>The Prophesie is now fulfill'd, That Jewel </l>
              <l>Will serve to satisfie the World as much </l>
              <pb n="77" xml:id="ep000734-022-b"/>
              <l>Of all you say, as your own Words have me: </l>
              <l>And thus preserves the Thracian Family,— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e23900">Embraces Urania. </stage>
              </l>
              <l>Dear Daughter! still be happy and forgive </l>
              <l>Our ignorance; I cannot love thee better </l>
              <l>Then at that very time I did condemn thee, </l>
              <l>I could as well have sentenc'd my two Eyes; </l>
              <l>And pardon me, dear Sister, if I first— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e23970">Salutes Cleopatra. </stage>
              </l>
              <l>Ask'd pardon where I most did need it. </l>
              <l>Call the Queen, and tell <hi>Cleantha Vrania </hi>is alive. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e24020">
              <speaker>Par. </speaker>
              <l>Now, my dear Daughter thou art safe within my Armes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e24050">
              <speaker>Vran. </speaker>
              <l>Madam, it onely did belong to you </l>
              <l>Who gave me life, thus to preserve it too.— <stage xml:id="ep000734-e24090">Trumpets within. </stage>
              </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e24100">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>What's this? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e24130">
              <speaker>Gent. </speaker>
              <l>The Prince is come. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e24160">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>What will Theander say to see his dear Vrania </l>
              <l>Thus attir'd at his return? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e24220">
              <speaker>Uran. </speaker>
              <l>He'l say you'r mercifull. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000734-e24250">Enter Queen, Cleantha and Pyrrhus. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e24280">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Madam, see here great Cleopatra </l>
              <l>And call her Sister; take Cleantha! </l>
              <l>Her thou hast wept for: Pyrrhus has told you all. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000734-e24360">Enter Theander. </stage>
              <l>My Son! never more welcome! never <stage xml:id="ep000734-e24390">
                  <hi>The Prince fixes his Eyes on </hi>Urania. </stage>
              </l>
              <l>Did more Joy spring from more Sorrow. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e24420">
              <speaker>Thean. </speaker>
              <l>Bless me dread Sir! </l>
              <l>What Scene does entertain me? Are your Joyes </l>
              <l>Exprest by Sacrifice? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e24470">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Theander, take, </l>
              <l>Take thy Vrania, and wonder not </l>
              <l>At any thing but her. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e24540">
              <speaker>Thean. </speaker>
              <l>My Triumphs are more dreadful than my Conquests. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e24570">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>My Son be happy </l>
              <l>In thy best Choice; let not thy wonder make </l>
              <gap extent="2" reason="missing" unit="pages"/>
              <pb n="80" xml:id="ep000734-023-a"/>
              <l>'Twill be but gratitude in me to do </l>
              <l>Some of their business for them, and reward </l>
              <l>So brave a Vertue as Endymion owns, </l>
              <l>And make him great for his Cleantha too. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e24690">
              <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
              <l>Is Endymion return'd? O happy hour! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e24730">
              <speaker>Thean. </speaker>
              <l>The War in Thessaly has found an happy end, </l>
              <l>And there I've left </l>
              <l>Those hands that made that Scepter stoop, who, now, </l>
              <l>Want but a Scene to do new wonders in, </l>
              <l>And this may prove rebellious Thrace, if you </l>
              <l>Sir, think fit I wear that Crown Vrania gives me; </l>
              <l>In this Conquest, the brave Endymion </l>
              <l>Shall be my second; what shall I not expect from </l>
              <l>Such vertue and such valour when they meet? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e24880">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>I have of late receiv'd such mercies, that </l>
              <l>I cannot think of any thing which looks </l>
              <l>Like Cruelty. Therefore wonder not </l>
              <l>All that you ask so soon is granted you, </l>
              <l>Cleantha; Take then your Endymion; be </l>
              <l>More blest in him than Greatness e're could make you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e24980">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>And now you'r doing works of mercy Sir, </l>
              <l>I beg for the sake of this glorious day </l>
              <l>Which is a day of mercy to us all, </l>
              <l>That Geron and Neander may not die </l>
              <l>But suffer Banishment for life. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e25070">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>What you propose has much of Piety; </l>
              <l>I'le not deny't: and now I've one request </l>
              <l>To you my honour'd Priest, your leave </l>
              <l>That Pyrrhus my best Confident may serve </l>
              <l>The fair Evadne </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e25160">
              <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
              <l>You oblige me Sir to make me see </l>
              <l>My poor Evadne is so much your care, </l>
              <l>It shall be mine; she still shall think that best </l>
              <l>Your Majesty is pleas'd to chuse for her. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000734-e25230">Enter Endymion. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e25250">
              <speaker>Thean. </speaker>
              <l>Endymion! why so slowly to thy Joyes? <stage xml:id="ep000734-e25290">
                  <hi>Kneels and kisses </hi>Cleantha <hi>'s hand</hi>. </stage>
              </l>
              <l>Reap here the fruits of Gratitude and Mercy. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e25330">
              <pb n="81" xml:id="ep000734-023-b"/>
              <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
              <l>Welcome my Lord. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e25360">
              <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
              <l>My Lord, you'r welcome from your Banishment. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e25390">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>You've onely now this Ladies leave to ask </l>
              <l>For any thing you'd have. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e25430">
              <speaker>Endym. </speaker>
              <l>I am happy in your Royal mercy Sir, </l>
              <l>And hope in time to be so too in hers. </l>
              <l>Madam, I hope your Highness has the Charity </l>
              <l>To pardon your poor Servant, who was the </l>
              <l>Unwilling occasion of so much injury </l>
              <l>To so Noble a Princess. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e25510">
              <speaker>Clean. </speaker>
              <l>You need not fear </l>
              <l>Your Sentence when Cleantha is your Judge. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e25560">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Let us all away, and satisfie our selves with what </l>
              <l>We have so long travail'd with, and let the World </l>
              <l>Learn from this story, Those that are vertuous </l>
              <l>Cannot be long in Clouds; Innocence conceal'd is the </l>
              <l>Stoln pleasure of the Gods, which never ends </l>
              <l>In shame as that of Men does oft times, but </l>
              <l>Like the Sun breaks forth, when he has </l>
              <l>Gratify'd another World, and to our Eyes appears </l>
              <l>More Glorious through his late obscurity. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000734-e25670">
              <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
              <l>The Impious here a while may find some Rest, </l>
              <l>But in the End the good are onely blest. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="ep000734-e25710">Ex. omnes. </stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
