<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The true tragedie of Richard Duke of York and the death of good King Henrie the Sixt, with the whole contention betweene the two houses Lancaster and Yorke, as it was sundrie times acted by the right honourable the earle of Pembrooke his seruants.</title>
        <title>King Henry VI. Part 3</title>
        <author>
<!--Shakespeare, William, (1564-1616.)-->
          <persName>
            <forename>William</forename>
            <surname>Shakespeare</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <idno type="dracor" xml:base="https://dracor.org/id/">ep000851</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://earlyprint.org</idno>
          <availability>
            <p>
            This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is available for reuse, according to the terms of
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>
            . The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
          </p>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull>
              <titleStmt>
                <title>The true tragedie of Richard Duke of York and the death of good King Henrie the Sixt, with the whole contention betweene the two houses Lancaster and Yorke, as it was sundrie times acted by the right honourable the earle of Pembrooke his seruants.</title>
                <title>King Henry VI. Part 3</title>
                <author>Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[80] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>By P.S[hort] for Thomas Millington, and are to be sold at his shoppe vnder Saint Peters Church in Cornwal,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                <date>1595.</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>A corrupt and shorter version, possibly a memorial reconstruction, of "Henry VI, part 3" by William Shakespeare, which first appeared in finished form in the First Folio.</note>
                <note>Signatures: A-E.</note>
                <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                <note>Running title reads: The tragedie of Richard D. of Yorke, and Henrie the sixt.</note>
                <note>Some pages tightly bound.</note>
                <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000851-e10">
        <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000851-001-a"/>
        <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000851-001-b"/>
        <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000851-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000851-002-b"/>
        <p>The true Tragedie of Richard <hi>Duke of Yorke, and the death of </hi>good King Henrie the Sixt, </p>
        <p>
          <hi>with the whole contention betweene </hi>the two Houses Lancaster and Yorke, as it was sundrie times acted by the Right Honourable the Earle of Pembrooke his seruants. </p>
        <p>Printed at London by P. S. for Thomas Millington, <hi>and are to be sold at his shoppe vnder Saint Peters Church in Cornival. </hi>1595. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="play" xml:id="ep000851-e90">
        <pb xml:id="ep000851-003-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000851-003-b"/>
        <head>The true Tragedie of Richard Duke of Yorke, and the good King Henry the Sixt. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000851-e110">Enter Richard Duke of Yorke, The Earle of <hi>Warwicke, The Duke of </hi>Norffolke, <hi>Marquis Montague, Edward Earle of March, Crookeback Richard▪ </hi>and the yong <hi>Earle of Rutland, </hi>with Drumme and Souldiers, with white Roses in their hats. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e160">
          <speaker>Warwike. </speaker>
          <l>I Wonder how the king escapt our hands. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e190">
          <speaker>Yorke. </speaker>
          <l>Whilst we pursude the horsemen of the North, </l>
          <l>He slilie stole awaie and left his men: </l>
          <l>Whereat the great Lord of Northumland, </l>
          <l>Whose warlike eares could neuer brooke retrait, </l>
          <l>Chargde our maine battels front, and therewith him </l>
          <l>Lord Stafford and Lord Clifford all abrest 〈…〉 </l>
          <l>Brake in and were by the hands of common Souldiers slain. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e300">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Lord Staffords father Duke of <hi>Buckhingham, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Is either slaine or wounded dangerouslie, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-004-a"/>
          <l>I cleft his Beuer with a downe right blow: </l>
          <l>Father that this is true behold his bloud. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e380">
          <speaker>Mont </speaker>
          <l>And brother heeres the Earle of Wiltshires </l>
          <l>Bloud, whom I encountred as the battailes ioind. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e440">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Speake thou for me and tell them what I did. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e480">
          <speaker>York. </speaker>
          <l>What is your grace dead my L▪ of <hi>Summerset? </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e520">
          <speaker>Norf. </speaker>
          <l>Such hope haue all the line of Iohn of <hi>gates. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e570">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Thus doe I hope to shape king Henries head. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e620">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>And so do I victorious prince of Yorke, </l>
          <l>Before I see thee seated in that throne </l>
          <l>Which now the house of Lancaster vsurpes, </l>
          <l>I vow by heauens these eies shal neuer close. </l>
          <l>This is the pallace of that fearefull king, </l>
          <l>And that the regall chaire? Possesse it Yorke: </l>
          <l>For this is thine and not king Henries heires. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e740">
          <speaker>York </speaker>
          <l>Assist me then sweet <hi>Warwike, </hi>and I wil: </l>
          <l>For hither are we broken in by force. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e790">
          <speaker>Norf. </speaker>
          <l>Weele all assist thee, and he that flies shall die. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e820">
          <speaker>York. </speaker>
          <l>Thanks gentle <hi>Norffolke. </hi>Staie by me my Lords, </l>
          <l>and souldiers staie you heere and lodge this night: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e870">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>And when the king comes offer him no </l>
          <l>Violence, vnlesse he seek to put vs out by force. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e910">
          <speaker>Rich </speaker>
          <l>Armde as we be, lets staie within this house? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e940">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>The bloudie parlement shall this be calde, </l>
          <l>Vnlesse Plantagenet Duke of Yorke be king </l>
          <l>And bashfull Henrie be deposde, whose cowardise </l>
          <l>Hath made vs by words to our enemies. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e1020">
          <speaker>York. </speaker>
          <l>Then leaue me not my Lords: for now I meane </l>
          <l>To take possession of my right. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e1060">
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-004-b"/>
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Neither the king, nor him that loues him best, </l>
          <l>The proudest burd that holds vp <hi>Lancaster. </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Dares stirre a wing if Warwike shake his bels. </l>
          <l>Ile plant <hi>Plantagenet: </hi>and root him out who dares? </l>
          <l>Resolue thee <hi>Richard: </hi>Claime the English crowne. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000851-e1170">Enter king Henrie the sixt, with the Duke of <hi>Excester, </hi>The Earle of <hi>Northumberland▪ </hi>the Earle of Westmerland and <hi>Clifford, </hi>the Earle of <hi>Cumberland, </hi>withred Roses in their hats. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e1240">
          <speaker>King </speaker>
          <l>Looke Lordings where the sturdy rebel sits, </l>
          <l>Euen in the chaire of state: belike he meanes </l>
          <l>Backt by the power of Warwike that false peere, </l>
          <l>To aspire vnto the crowne, and raigne as king. </l>
          <l>Earle of <hi>Northumberland▪ </hi>he slew thy father. </l>
          <l>And thine <hi>Clifford: </hi>and you both haue vow'd reuenge, </l>
          <l>On him, his sonnes, his fauorites, and his friends. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e1360">
          <speaker>Northu. </speaker>
          <l>And if I be not, heauens be reuengd on me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e1390">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>The hope thereof, makes Clifford mourn in steel. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e1430">
          <speaker>West. </speaker>
          <l>What? shall we suffer this, lets pull him downe. </l>
          <l>My hart for anger breakes, I cannot speake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e1470">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Be patient gentle Earle of <hi>Westmerland. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e1510">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>Patience is for pultrouns such as he </l>
          <l>He durst not sit there had your father liu'd? </l>
          <l>My gratious Lord: here in the Parlement, </l>
          <l>Let vs assaile the familie of Yorke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e1570">
          <speaker>North. </speaker>
          <l>Well hast thou spoken cosen, be it so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e1600">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>O know you not the Cittie fauours them, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-005-a"/>
          <l>And they haue troopes of soldiers at their becke? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e1640">
          <speaker>Exet. </speaker>
          <l>But when the D. is slaine, theile quicklie slie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e1670">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Far be it from the thoughtes of Henries hart, </l>
          <l>To make a shambles of the parlement house. </l>
          <l>Cosen of <hi>Exeter, </hi>words, frownes, and threats, </l>
          <l>Shall be the warres that Henrie meanes to vse. </l>
          <l>Thou facetious duke of Yorke, descend my throne, </l>
          <l>I am thy soueraigne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e1770">
          <speaker>York. </speaker>
          <l>Thou art deceiu'd: I am thine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e1800">
          <speaker>Exet. </speaker>
          <l>For shame come downe he made thee D. of <hi>York. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e1840">
          <speaker>York. </speaker>
          <l>Twas mine inheritance as the kingdome is. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e1870">
          <speaker>Exet. </speaker>
          <l>Thy father was a traytor to the crowne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e1900">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Exeter thou art a traitor to the crowne. </l>
          <l>In following this vsurping <hi>Henry. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e1960">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>Whom should he follow but his naturall king. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e1990">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>TRUE Clif and that is Richard Duke of Yorke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e2040">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>And shall I stande while thou sittest in my throne? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e2070">
          <speaker>York. </speaker>
          <l>Content thy selfe it must and shall be so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e2100">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Be Duke of <hi>Lancaster, </hi>let him be king. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e2140">
          <speaker>West. </speaker>
          <l>Why? he is both king &amp; Duke of <hi>Lancaster, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And that the Earle of Westmerland shall mainetaine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e2200">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>And Warwike shall disproue it. You forget </l>
          <l>That we are those that chaste you from the field </l>
          <l>And slew your father, and with colours spred, </l>
          <l>Marcht through the Cittie to the pallas gates. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e2270">
          <speaker>Nor. </speaker>
          <l>No Warwike I remember it to my griefe, </l>
          <l>And by his soule thou and thy house shall rew it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e2320">
          <speaker>West. </speaker>
          <l>Plantagenet of thee and of thy sonnes, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-005-b"/>
          <l>Thy kinsmen and thy friendes, Ile haue more liues, </l>
          <l>Then drops of bloud were in my fathers vaines. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e2380">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>Vrge it no more, least in reuenge thereof, </l>
          <l>I send thee Warwike such a messenger, </l>
          <l>As shall reueng his death before I stirre. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e2440">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Poore <hi>Clifford, </hi>how I skorn thy worthles threats </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e2480">
          <speaker>York. </speaker>
          <l>Wil ye we shew our title to the crowne, </l>
          <l>Or else our swords shall plead it in the field? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e2520">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>What title haste thou traitor to the Crowne? </l>
          <l>Thy father was as thou art Duke of <hi>Yorke, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Thy grandfather <hi>Roger Mortimer </hi>earle of <hi>March, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>I am the sonne of Henrie the Fift who tamde the <hi>French, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And made the Dolphin stoope, and seazd vpon their </l>
          <l>Townes and prouinces. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e2640">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Talke not of France since thou hast lost it all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e2680">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>the Lord protector lost it and not I, </l>
          <l>When I was crownd I was but nine months old. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e2720">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>You are olde enough now and yet me thinkes you lose, </l>
          <l>Father teare the Crowne from the Vsurpers head▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e2760">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Do so sweet father, set it on your head. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e2790">
          <speaker>Mont. </speaker>
          <l>Good brother as thou lou'st &amp; honorst armes, </l>
          <l>Lets fight it out and not stand cauilling thus. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e2830">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Sound drums and trumpets &amp; the king will sly. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e2860">
          <speaker>York, </speaker>
          <l>Peace sonnes: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e2890">
          <speaker>Northum. </speaker>
          <l>Peace thou and giue king Henry leaue to speake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e2930">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Ah <hi>Plantagenet, </hi>why seekest thou to depose me? </l>
          <l>Are we not both both Plantagenets by birth, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-006-a"/>
          <l>And from two brothers line allie discent? </l>
          <l>Suppose by right and equitie thou be king, </l>
          <l>Thinkst thou that I will leaue my kinglie seate </l>
          <l>wherein my father and my grandsire sat? </l>
          <l>No, first shall warre vnpeople this my realme, </l>
          <l>I and our colours often borne in <hi>France, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And now in England to our harts great sorrow </l>
          <l>Shall be my winding sheete, why saint you Lords? </l>
          <l>My titles better farre than his. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e3100">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Proue it Henrie and thou shalt be king? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e3140">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Why Henrie the fourth by conquest got the Crowne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e3180">
          <speaker>York. </speaker>
          <l>T'was by rebellion gainst his soueraigne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e3210">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>I know not what to saie my titles weake, </l>
          <l>Tell me maie not a king adopt an heire? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e3250">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>What then? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e3280">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Then am I lawfull king For Richard </l>
          <l>The second in the view of maine Lords </l>
          <l>Resignde the Crowne to Henrie the fourth, </l>
          <l>Whose heire my Father was, and I am his. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e3360">
          <speaker>York </speaker>
          <l>I tell thee he rose against him being his </l>
          <l>Soueraigne, &amp; made him to resigne the crown perforce. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e3400">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Suppose my Lord he did it vnconstrainde, </l>
          <l>Thinke you that were preiudiciall to the Crowne? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e3440">
          <speaker>Exet. </speaker>
          <l>No▪ for he could not so resigne the Crowne, </l>
          <l>But that the next heire must succeed and raigne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e3480">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Art thou against vs, Duke of <hi>Exceter? </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e3520">
          <speaker>Exet. </speaker>
          <l>His is the right, and therefore pardon me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e3550">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>All will reuolt from me and turne to him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e3580">
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-006-b"/>
          <speaker>Northum. </speaker>
          <l>Plantagenet for all the claime thou laist, </l>
          <l>Thinke not king Henry shall be thus deposde? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e3640">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Deposde he shall be in despight of thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e3670">
          <speaker>North. </speaker>
          <l>Tush <hi>Warwike, </hi>Thou art deceiued? tis not thy </l>
          <l>Southerne powers of <hi>Essex, Suffolke, Norffolke, </hi>and of </l>
          <l>Kent that makes thee thus presumptuous and proud, </l>
          <l>Can set the Duke vp in despight of me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e3760">
          <speaker>Cliff. </speaker>
          <l>King Henrie be thy title right or wrong, </l>
          <l>Lord Clifford vowes to fight in thy defence. </l>
          <l>Maie that ground gape and swallow me aliue, </l>
          <l>Where I do kneele to him that slew my father. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e3840">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>O <hi>Clifford, </hi>how thy words reuiue my soule. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e3880">
          <speaker>York. </speaker>
          <l>Henry of Lancaster resigne thy crowne. </l>
          <l>What mutter you? or what conspire you Lords? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e3940">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Doe right vnto this princelie Duke of <hi>Yorke, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Or I will fill the house with armed men, </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e3990">Enter Souldiers. </stage>
          <l>And ouer the chaire of state where now he sits, </l>
          <l>Wright vp his title with thy vsurping bloud. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e4020">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>O <hi>Warwike, </hi>heare me speake. </l>
          <l>Let me but raigne in quiet whilst I liue, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e4070">
          <speaker>York. </speaker>
          <l>Confirme the crowne to me and to mine heires </l>
          <l>And thou shalt raigne in quiet whilst thou hu'st. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e4110">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Conuey the souldiers hence, and then I will. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e4140">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Captaine conduct them into Tuthill fieldes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e4180">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>What wrong is this vnto the Prince your son? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e4210">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>What good is this for England and himselfe? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e4250">
          <speaker>Northum. </speaker>
          <l>Base, fearefull, and despairing <hi>Henry. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e4290">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>How hast thou wronged both thy selfe and vs? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e4320">
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-007-a"/>
          <speaker>West. </speaker>
          <l>I cannot staie to heare these Articles. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e4350">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e4360">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>Nor I, Come cosen lets go tell the Queene. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e4390">
          <speaker>Northum. </speaker>
          <l>Be thou a praie vnto the house of <hi>Yorke, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And die in bands for this vnkingly deed. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e4440">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e4450">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>In dreadfull warre maist thou be ouercome, </l>
          <l>Or liue in peace abandon'd and despisde. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e4490">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e4500">
          <speaker>Exet. </speaker>
          <l>They seeke reuenge, and therefore will not yeeld my Lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e4530">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Ah <hi>Exeter? </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e4570">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Why should you sigh my Lord? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e4600">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Not for my selfe Lord <hi>Warwike, </hi>but my soone, </l>
          <l>Whom I vnnaturallie shall disinherit. </l>
          <l>But be it as it maie: I heere intaile the Crowne </l>
          <l>To thee and to thine heires, conditionallie, </l>
          <l>That here thou take thine oath, to cease these ciuill </l>
          <l>Broiles, and whilst I liue to honour me as thy king and Soueraigne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e4690">
          <speaker>York. </speaker>
          <l>That oath I willinglie take and will performe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e4720">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Long liue king <hi>Henry. Plantagenet </hi>embrace him? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e4760">
          <speaker>King </speaker>
          <l>And long liue thou and all thy forward sonnes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e4790">
          <speaker>York. </speaker>
          <l>Now Yorke and Lancaster are reconcilde. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e4840">
          <speaker>Exet. </speaker>
          <l>Accuist be he that seekes to make them soes, </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e4870">Sound Irumpets. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e4880">
          <speaker>York </speaker>
          <l>My Lord Ile take my leaue, for Ile to Wakefield </l>
          <l>To my castell. </l>
          <l>
            <hi>Exit Yorke </hi>and his sonnes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e4950">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>And Ile keepe London with my souldiers. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e4990">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e5000">
          <speaker>Norf </speaker>
          <l>And Ile to Norffolke with my followers. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e5040">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e5050">
          <speaker>Mont. </speaker>
          <l>And I to the sea from whence I came. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e5080">Exit. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e5090">
            <pb xml:id="ep000851-007-b"/>Enter the Queene and the <hi>Prince. </hi>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e5120">
          <speaker>Exet. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord here comes the Queen, Ile steale away. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e5150">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>And so will <hi>I. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e5190">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>Naie staie, or else I follow thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e5220">
          <speaker>King </speaker>
          <l>Be patient gentle <hi>Queene, </hi>and then Ile staie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e5260">
          <speaker>Quee. </speaker>
          <l>What patience can there? ah timerous man, </l>
          <l>Thou hast vndoone thy selfe, thy sonne, and me, </l>
          <l>And giuen our rights vnto the house of <hi>Yorke. </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Art thou a king and wilt be worst to yeeld? </l>
          <l>Had I beene there, the souldiers should haue tost </l>
          <l>Me on their launces points, before I would haue </l>
          <l>Granted to their wils. The Duke is made </l>
          <l>Protector of the land: Sterne Fawconbridge </l>
          <l>Commands the narrow seas. And thinkst thou then </l>
          <l>To sleepe secure? I heere diuorce me Henry </l>
          <l>From thy bed, vntill that Act of Parlement </l>
          <l>Be recalde, wherein thou yeeldest to the house of <hi>Yorke. </hi>
          </l>
          <l>The Northen Lords that haue forsworne thy colours, </l>
          <l>Will follow mine if once they see them spred, </l>
          <l>And spread they shall vnto thy deepe disgrace. </l>
          <l>Come sonne, lets awaie and leaue him heere alone. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e5480">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Staie gentle <hi>Margaret, </hi>and here me speake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e5520">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>Thou hast spoke too much alreadie, therefore be still. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e5550">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Gentle sonne <hi>Edwarde, </hi>wilt thou staie with me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e5590">
          <speaker>Quee </speaker>
          <l>I, to be murdred by his enemies. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e5620">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e5630">
          <speaker>Prin. </speaker>
          <l>When I returne with victorie from the field, </l>
          <l>Ile see your Grace, till then Ile follow her. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e5670">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e5680">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Poore <hi>Queene, </hi>her loue to me and to the prince <pb xml:id="ep000851-008-a"/>Her sonne, </l>
          <l>Makes hir in 〈…〉 thus forget hir selfe. </l>
          <l>Reuenged maie shee be on that accursed Duke. </l>
          <l>Come cosen of <hi>Exeter, </hi>staie thou here, </l>
          <l>For Clifford and those Northern Lords be gone </l>
          <l>I feare towards <hi>Wakefield, </hi>to disturbe the Duke. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e5800">Enter <hi>Edward, </hi>and <hi>Richard, </hi>and <hi>Montague. </hi>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e5840">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Brother and cosen <hi>Montague, </hi>giue mee leaue to speake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e5880">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Nay, I can better plaie the Orator. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e5910">
          <speaker>Mont. </speaker>
          <l>But I haue reasons strong and forceable. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e5940">Enter the Duke of <hi>Yorke. </hi>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e5960">
          <speaker>York </speaker>
          <l>Howe nowe sonnes what at a iarre amongst your selues? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e5990">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <p>No father, but a sweete contention, about that which concernes your selfe and vs, The crowne of England father. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e6020">
          <speaker>York. </speaker>
          <l>The crowne boy, why Henries yet aliue, </l>
          <l>And I haue sworne that he shall raigne in quiet till </l>
          <l>His death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e6080">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>But I would breake an hundred othes to raigne one yeare. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e6110">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>And if it please your grace to giue me leaue, </l>
          <l>Ile shew your grace the waie to saue your oath, </l>
          <l>And dispossesse king Henrie from the crowne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e6170">
          <speaker>Yorke </speaker>
          <l>I prethe Dicke let me heare thy deuise. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e6210">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Then thus my Lord. An oath is of no moment </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-008-b"/>
          <l>Being not sworne before a lawfull magistrate. </l>
          <l>Henry is none but doth vsurpe your right, </l>
          <l>And yet your grace stands bound to him by oath. </l>
          <l>Then noble father resolue your selfe, </l>
          <l>And once more claime the crowne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e6300">
          <speaker>Yorke </speaker>
          <l>
            <hi>I, </hi>saist thou so boie▪ why then it shall be so. </l>
          <l>I am resolude to win the crowne, or die. </l>
          <l>Edward, thou shalt to <hi>Edmund Brooke </hi>Lord <hi>Cobham, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>With whom the Kentishmen will willinglie rise: </l>
          <l>Thou cosen <hi>Montague, </hi>shalt to Norffolke straight, </l>
          <l>And bid the Duke to muster vppe his souldiers, </l>
          <l>And come to me to Wakefield presentlie. </l>
          <l>And Richard thou to London strait shalt post, </l>
          <l>And bid <hi>Richard Neuill </hi>Earle of Warwike </l>
          <l>To leaue the cittie, and with his men of warre, </l>
          <l>To meete me at Saint Albons ten daies hence. </l>
          <l>My selfe heere in Sandall castell will prouide </l>
          <l>Both men and monie to furder our attempts. </l>
          <l>Now, what newes? </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e6600">Enter a Messenger. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e6610">
          <speaker>Mes. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord, the Queene with thirtie thousand men, </l>
          <l>Accompanied with the Earles of <hi>Cumberland, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Nurthumberland and <hi>Westmerland, </hi>and others of the </l>
          <l>House of <hi>Lancaster, </hi>are marching towards <hi>Wakefield, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>To besiedge you in your castell heere. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e6740">Enter sir Iohn and sir <hi>Hugh Mortimer. </hi>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e6770">
          <speaker>Yorke </speaker>
          <p>A Gods name, let them come. Cosen Montague post you hence: and boies staie you with me. </p>
          <l>Sir Iohn and sir <hi>Hugh Mortemers </hi>mine vncles, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-009-a"/>
          <l>Your welcome to Sandall in an happie houre, </l>
          <l>The armie of the Queene meanes to besiedge vs. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e6870">
          <speaker>Sir <hi>Iohn. </hi>
          </speaker>
          <l>Shee shall not neede my Lorde, weele meete her in the field. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e6910">
          <speaker>York </speaker>
          <l>What with fiue thousand souldiers vncle? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e6940">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>I father, with fiue hundred for a need, </l>
          <l>A womans generall, what should you feare? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e6980">
          <speaker>York. </speaker>
          <l>Indeed, manie braue battels haue I woon </l>
          <l>In <hi>Normandie, </hi>when as the enimie </l>
          <l>Hath bin ten to one▪ and why should I now doubt </l>
          <l>Of the like successe? I am resolu'd Come lets goe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e7050">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Lets martch awaie, I heare their drums. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e7080">Exit. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e7090">Alarmes, and then Enter the yong Earle of Rutland and his Tutor. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e7110">
          <speaker>Tutor. </speaker>
          <l>Oh flie my Lord, lets leaue the Castell, </l>
          <l>And flie to Wakefield straight. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e7160">Enter Clifford. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e7180">
          <speaker>Rut. </speaker>
          <l>O Tutor, looke where bloudie Clifford comes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e7220">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>Chaplin awaie, thy Priesthood saues thy life, </l>
          <l>As for the brat of that accursed Duke </l>
          <l>Whose father slew my father, he shall die. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e7270">
          <speaker>Tutor </speaker>
          <l>Oh Clifford spare this tender Lord, least </l>
          <l>Heauen reuenge it on thy head: Oh saue his life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e7320">
          <speaker>Clif </speaker>
          <l>Soldiers awaie and drag him hence perforce: </l>
          <l>Awaie with the villaine. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e7360">Exit the Chaplein. </stage>
          <l>How now, what dead alreadie? or is it feare that </l>
          <l>Makes him close his eies? Ile open them. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e7400">
          <speaker>Rut. </speaker>
          <l>So lookes the pent vp Lion on the lambe, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-009-b"/>
          <l>And so he walkes insulting ouer his praie, </l>
          <l>And so he turnes againe to rend his limmes in sunder, </l>
          <l>Oh <hi>Clifford, </hi>kill me with thy sword, and </l>
          <l>Not with such a cruell threatning looke, </l>
          <l>I am too meane a subiect for thy wrath, </l>
          <l>Be thou reuengde on men, and let me liue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e7500">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>In vaine thou speakest poore boy: my fathers </l>
          <l>Bloud hath stopt the passage where thy wordes shoulde enter. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e7540">
          <speaker>Rut. </speaker>
          <p>Then let my fathers blood ope it againe? he is a Man, and Clifford cope with him. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e7580">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>Had I thy brethren here, their liues and thine </l>
          <l>Were not reuenge sufficient for me. </l>
          <l>Or should I dig vp thy forefathers graues, </l>
          <l>And hang their rotten coffins vp in chaines, </l>
          <l>It could not slake mine ire, nor case my hart. </l>
          <l>The sight of anie of the house of <hi>Yorke, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Is as a furie to torment my soule. </l>
          <l>Therefore till I root out that curssed line </l>
          <l>And leaue not one on earth, I le liue in hell therefore. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e7750">
          <speaker>Rut. </speaker>
          <l>Oh let me praie, before I take my death. </l>
          <l>To thee I praie: Sweet Clifford pittie me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e7820">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>
            <hi>I, </hi>such pittious my rapiers point affords. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e7860">
          <speaker>Rut. </speaker>
          <l>I neuer did thee hurt, wherefore wilt thou kill mee? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e7890">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>Thy father hath. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e7920">
          <speaker>Rut. </speaker>
          <l>But twas ere I was borne▪ </l>
          <l>Thou hast one sonne, for his sake pittie me, </l>
          <l>Least in reuenge thereof, 〈◊〉 God is iust▪ </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-010-a"/>
          <l>He be as miserablie slaine as I. </l>
          <l>Oh, let me liue in prison all my daies, </l>
          <l>And when I giue occasion of offence, </l>
          <l>Then let me die, for now thou hast no cause. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e8040">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>No cause? Thy Father slew my father, therefore Die. </l>
          <l>Plantagenet <hi>I come </hi>Plantagenet, </l>
          <l>And this thy sonnes bloud cleauing to my blade, </l>
          <l>Shall rust vpon my weapon, till thy bloud </l>
          <l>Congeald with his, doe make me wipe off both. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e8120">Exit. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e8130">Alarmes, Enter the Duke of <hi>Yorke solus. </hi>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e8150">
          <speaker>Yorke </speaker>
          <l>Ah <hi>Yorke, </hi>post to thy castell, saue thy life, </l>
          <l>The goale is lost thou house of <hi>Lancaster, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Thrise happie chance is it for thee and thine, </l>
          <l>That heauen abridgde my daies and cals me hence, </l>
          <l>But God knowes what chance hath betide my sonnes: </l>
          <l>But this I know they haue demeand themselues, </l>
          <l>Like men borne to renowne by life or death: </l>
          <l>Three times this daie came Richard to my sight, </l>
          <l>And cried courage Father: Victorie or death. </l>
          <l>And twise so oft came Edward to my view, </l>
          <l>With purple Faulchen painted to the hilts, </l>
          <l>In bloud of those whom he had slaughtered. </l>
          <l>Oh harke, I heare the drums? No waie to flie: </l>
          <l>No waie to saue my life? And heere I staie: </l>
          <l>And heere my life must end. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e8380">Enter the <hi>Queene, Clifford, Northumberland, </hi>and souldiers. </stage>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-010-b"/>
          <l>Come bloudie <hi>Clifford, </hi>rough <hi>Northumberland, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>I dare your quenchlesse furie to more bloud: </l>
          <l>This is the But, and this abides your shot. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e8450">
          <speaker>Northum. </speaker>
          <l>Yeeld to our mercies proud <hi>Plantagenet. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e8490">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>I, to such mercie as his ruthfull arme </l>
          <l>With downe right paiment lent vnto my father, </l>
          <l>Now Phaeton hath tumbled from his carre, </l>
          <l>And made an euening at the noone tide pricke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e8560">
          <speaker>York. </speaker>
          <l>My ashes like the Phoenix maie bring forth </l>
          <l>A bird that will reuenge it on you all, </l>
          <l>And in that hope I cast mine eies to heauen, </l>
          <l>Skorning what ere you can afflict me with: </l>
          <l>Why staie you Lords? what, multitudes and feare? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e8640">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>So cowards fight when they can flie no longer: </l>
          <l>So Doues doe pecke the Rauens piersing tallents: </l>
          <l>So desperate theeues all hopelesse of their liues, </l>
          <l>Breath out inuectiues gainst the officers. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e8700">
          <speaker>York. </speaker>
          <l>Oh <hi>Clifford, </hi>yet bethinke thee once againe, </l>
          <l>And in thy minde orerun my former time: </l>
          <l>And bite thy toung that slaunderst him with cowardise, </l>
          <l>Whose verie looke hath made thee quake are this. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e8770">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>I will not bandie with thee word for word, </l>
          <l>But buckle with thee blowes twise two for one. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e8810">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>Hold valiant Clifford for a thousand causes, </l>
          <l>I would prolong the traitors life a while. </l>
          <l>Wrath makes him death, speake thou <hi>Northumberland. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e8880">
          <speaker>Nor. </speaker>
          <l>Hold Clifford doe not honour him to much, </l>
          <l>To pricke thy finger though to wound his hart: </l>
          <l>What valure were it when a curre doth grin, </l>
          <l>For one to thrust his hand betweene his teeth, </l>
          <l>When he might spurne him with his foote awaie? </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-011-a"/>
          <l>Tis warres prise to take all aduantages, </l>
          <l>And ten to one, is no impeach in wanes. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e8980">Fight and take him. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e8990">
          <speaker>Cliff. </speaker>
          <l>I, I▪ so striues the Woodcocke with the gin. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e9020">
          <speaker>North. </speaker>
          <l>So doth the cunnie struggle with the net. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e9050">
          <speaker>York </speaker>
          <l>So triumphs theeues vpon their conquered </l>
          <l>Bootie: So true men yeeld by robbers ouermatcht. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e9090">
          <speaker>North. </speaker>
          <l>What will your grace haue done with him? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e9120">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>Braue warriors Clifford &amp; Northumberland </l>
          <l>Come make him stand vpon this molehill here, </l>
          <l>That armde at mountaines with outstretched arme, </l>
          <l>And parted but the shaddow with his hand. </l>
          <l>Was it you that reuelde in our Parlement▪ </l>
          <l>And made a prechment of your high descent? </l>
          <l>Where are your messe of sonnes to backe you now? </l>
          <l>The wanton <hi>Edward, </hi>and the lustie <hi>George? </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Or where is that valiant Crookbackt prodegie? </l>
          <l>Dickey your boy, that with his grumbling voice, </l>
          <l>Was wont to cheare his Dad in mutinies? </l>
          <l>Or amongst the rest▪ where is your dawning <hi>Rutland? </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Looke <hi>Yorke? </hi>I dipt this napkin in the bloud, </l>
          <l>That valiant Clifford with his rapiers point, </l>
          <l>Made issue from the bosome of thy boy. </l>
          <l>And if thine eies can water for his death, </l>
          <l>I giue thee this to drie thy cheeks with all. </l>
          <l>Alas poore <hi>Yorke: </hi>But that I hate thee much, </l>
          <l>I should lament thy miserable state? </l>
          <l>I prethee greeue to make me merrie Yorke? </l>
          <l>Stamp▪ raue and fret, that I maie sing and dance. </l>
          <l>What: hath thy fierie hart so parcht thine entrailes, </l>
          <l>That not a teare can fall for Rutlands death? </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-011-b"/>
          <l>Thou wouldst be feede I see to make me sport. </l>
          <l>Yorke cannot speake, vnlesle he weare a crowne. </l>
          <l>A crowne for Yorke? and Lords bow low to him. </l>
          <l>So: hold you his hands, whilst I doe set it on. </l>
          <l>I, now lookes he like a king? </l>
          <l>This is he that tooke king Henries chaire, </l>
          <l>And this is he was his adopted aire. </l>
          <l>But how is it that great <hi>Plantagenet, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Is crownd so soone, and broke his holie oath, </l>
          <l>As I bethinke me you should not be king, </l>
          <l>Till our Henry had shooke hands with death, </l>
          <l>And will you impale your head with Henries glorie, </l>
          <l>And rob his temples of the Diadem </l>
          <l>Now in his life against your holie oath? </l>
          <l>Oh tis a fault too too vnpardonable. </l>
          <l>Off with the crowne, and with the crowne his head, </l>
          <l>And whilst we breath, take time to doe him dead. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e9730">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>Thats my office for my fathers death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e9760">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>Yet stay: &amp; lets here the Orisons he makes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e9790">
          <speaker>York. </speaker>
          <l>She wolfe of <hi>France, </hi>but worse than Wolues of <hi>France: </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Whose tongue more poison'd than the Adders tooth: </l>
          <l>How ill beseeming is it in thy sexe, </l>
          <l>To triumph like an Amazonian trull </l>
          <l>Vpon his woes, whom Fortune captiuates? </l>
          <l>But that thy face is visard like, vnchanging, </l>
          <l>Made impudent by vse of euill deeds: </l>
          <l>I would assaie, proud Queene to make thee blush: </l>
          <l>To tell thee of whence thou art, from whom deriude, </l>
          <l>Twere shame enough to shame thee, wert thou not shamelesse. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-012-a"/>
          <l>Thy father beares the type of king of <hi>Naples, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Of both the Siss●les and <hi>Ierusalem, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Yet not so wealthie as an English yeoman. </l>
          <l>Hath that poore Monarch taught thee to insult? </l>
          <l>It needes not, or it bootes thee not proud Queene, </l>
          <l>Vnlesse the Adage must be verifide: </l>
          <l>That beggers mounted, run their horse to death. </l>
          <l>Tis beautie, that oft makes women proud, </l>
          <l>But God he wots thy share thereof is small. </l>
          <l>Tis gouernment, that makes them most admirde, </l>
          <l>The contrarie doth make thee wondred at. </l>
          <l>Tis vertue that makes them seeme deuine. </l>
          <l>The want thereof makes thee abhominable. </l>
          <l>Thou art as opposite to euerie good, </l>
          <l>As the Antipodes are vnto vs, </l>
          <l>Or as the south to the Septentrion. </l>
          <l>Oh Tygers hart wrapt in a womans hide? </l>
          <l>How couldst thou draine the life bloud of the childe, </l>
          <l>To bid the father wipe his eies withall, </l>
          <l>And yet be seene to beare a womans face? </l>
          <l>Women are milde, pittifull, and flexible. </l>
          <l>Thou indurate, sterne, rough, remorcelesse. </l>
          <l>Bids thou me rage? why now thou hast thy will </l>
          <l>Wouldst haue me weepe? why so thou hast thy wish. </l>
          <l>For raging windes blowes vp a storme of teares, </l>
          <l>And when the rage allied the raine begins. </l>
          <l>These teares are my sweet Rutlands obsequies, </l>
          <l>And euerie drop begs vengeance as it fals, </l>
          <l>On thee fell <hi>Clifford, </hi>and the false French woman. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e10300">
          <speaker>North. </speaker>
          <l>Beshrew me but his passions moue me so, </l>
          <l>As hardlie can I checke mine eies from teares. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e10340">
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-012-b"/>
          <speaker>York. </speaker>
          <l>That face of his the hungrie Cannibals </l>
          <l>Could not haue tucht, would not haue staind with bloud </l>
          <l>But you are more inhumaine, more inexorable, </l>
          <l>O ten times more then Tvgers of <hi>Arcadia. </hi>
          </l>
          <l>See ruthlesse Queene a haplesse fathers teares. </l>
          <l>This cloth thou dipts in bloud of my sweet boy, </l>
          <l>And loe with teares I wash the bloud awaie. </l>
          <l>Keepe thou the napkin and go boast of that, </l>
          <l>And if thou tell the heauie storie well, </l>
          <l>Vpon my soule the hearers will sheel teares, </l>
          <l>I, euen my soes will sheel fast falling teares, </l>
          <l>And saie, alas, it was a pitteous deed. </l>
          <l>Here, take the crowne, and with the crowne my curse, </l>
          <l>And in thy need such comfort come to thee, </l>
          <l>As now I reape at thy two cruell hands. </l>
          <l>Hard-harted <hi>Clifford, </hi>take me from the world, </l>
          <l>My soule to heauen, my bloud vpon your heads. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e10570">
          <speaker>North. </speaker>
          <l>Had he bin slaughterman of all my kin, </l>
          <l>I could not chuse but weepe with him to see, </l>
          <l>How inlie anger gripes his hart. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e10630">
          <speaker>Quee. </speaker>
          <l>What weeping ripe, my Lorde <hi>Northumberland? </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Thinke but vpon the wrong he did vs all. </l>
          <l>And that will quicklie drie your melting tears. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e10690">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>Thears for my oath thears for my fathers death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e10720">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>And thears to right our gentle harted kind. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e10750">
          <speaker>York. </speaker>
          <l>Open thy gates of mercie gratious God, </l>
          <l>My soule flies foorth to meet with thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e10790">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>Off with his head and set it on Yorke Gates, </l>
          <l>So Yorke maie ouerlooke the towne of <hi>Yorke. </hi>
          </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e10860">Exeunt omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e10870">
            <pb xml:id="ep000851-013-a"/>Enter Edward and <hi>Richard, </hi>with drum and Souldiers. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e10900">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>After this dangerous fight and haplesse warre, </l>
          <l>How doth my noble brother Richard fare? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e10950">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>I cannot ioy vntil I be resolu'de, </l>
          <l>Where our ●●ght valiant father is become. </l>
          <l>H●● 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 I see him beare himselfe, </l>
          <l>As 〈…〉 didst a heard of neat, </l>
          <l>So 〈…〉 our valiant father, </l>
          <l>Me thinkes tis 〈◊〉 enough to be his sonne. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e11030">Three 〈…〉 in the aire. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e11040">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>〈…〉 the 〈◊〉 opes her golden gates, </l>
          <l>And takes her farewell of the glorious sun, </l>
          <l>dames 〈…〉 doe I see three suns? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e11090">
          <speaker>Rich </speaker>
          <l>Three glorious suns, 〈◊〉 seperated by a racking </l>
          <l>Cloud, but 〈◊〉 in a pale cleere shining skie. </l>
          <l>〈…〉 they ioine, embrace, and seeme to kisse. </l>
          <l>〈…〉 vowde some league inuiolate: </l>
          <l>〈…〉 are they but one lampe, one light, one sun, </l>
          <l>In this the heauens doth figure some euent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e11170">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>I thinke it cites vs brother to the field, </l>
          <l>That we the sonnes of braue <hi>Plantagenet, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Alreadie each one shining by his meed, </l>
          <l>May ioine in one and ouerpeere the world, </l>
          <l>As this the earth, and therefore hence forward, </l>
          <l>Ile beare vpon my Target, three faire shining suns. </l>
          <l>But what art thou? that lookest so heauilie? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e11280">
          <speaker>Mes. </speaker>
          <l>Oh one that was a wofull looker on, </l>
          <l>When as the noble Duke of Yorke was slaine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e11330">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>O speake no more, for I can heare no more. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e11360">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Tell on thy tale, for I will heare it all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e11400">
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-013-b"/>
          <speaker>Mes. </speaker>
          <l>When as the noble Duke was put to slight, </l>
          <l>And then pursu'de by Clifford and the <hi>Queene, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And manie souldiers m●●:, who all at once </l>
          <l>Let driue at him and forst the Duke to yeeld: </l>
          <l>And then they set him on a molehill there, </l>
          <l>And crownd the gratious Duke in high despite, </l>
          <l>Who then with teares began to waile his fall. </l>
          <l>The 〈◊〉 Queene beleeuing he did weepe, </l>
          <l>Gaue him a handkercher to wipe his eies, </l>
          <l>D●pt in the bloud of sweet young Rutland </l>
          <l>By rough Clifford slaine: who weeping tooke it vp. </l>
          <l>Then through his brest they thrust their bloudy swordes, </l>
          <l>Who like a lambe fell at the butchers feete. </l>
          <l>Then on the gates of Yorke they set his head, </l>
          <l>And there it doth remaine the piteous spectacle </l>
          <l>That ere mine eies beheld. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e11640">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Sweet Duke of Yorke our prop to leane vpon, </l>
          <l>Now thou art gone there is no hope for vs: </l>
          <l>Now my soules pallace is become a prison. </l>
          <l>Oh would she breake from compasse of my breast, </l>
          <l>For neuer shall I haue more ioie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e11720">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>I cannot weepe, for all my breasts moisture </l>
          <l>Scarse serues to quench my furnace burning hart: </l>
          <l>I cannot ioie till this white rose be dide, </l>
          <l>Euen in the hart bloud of the house of <hi>Lancaster. </hi>
          </l>
          <l>
            <hi>Richard▪ </hi>I bare thy name, and Ile reuenge thy death, </l>
          <l>Or die my selfe in seeking of reuenge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e11820">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>His name that valiant Duke hath left with thee, </l>
          <l>His chaire and Dukedome that remaines for me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e11860">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Nay, if thou be that princely Eagles bird, </l>
          <l>Shew thy descent by gazing gainst the sunne. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-014-a"/>
          <l>For chaire, and dukedome, Throne and kingdome saie: </l>
          <l>For either that is thine, or else thou wert not his? </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e11920">Enter the Earle of <hi>Warwike, Montague, </hi>with drum, ancient, and souldiers. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e11940">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>How now faire Lords: what sare? what newes abroad? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e11970">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Ah <hi>Warwike? </hi>should we report the balefull </l>
          <l>N●●●●, 〈◊〉 at each words deliuerance stab poinyardes </l>
          <l>In our flesh till all were told, the words would adde </l>
          <l>More 〈◊〉 then the wounds, </l>
          <l>Ah valiant Lord the Duke of Yorke is slaine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e12060">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Ah <hi>Warwike Warwike, </hi>that <hi>Plantagenet, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Which held thee deere: I, euen an his soules redemption, </l>
          <l>Is by the ●●●●ne <hi>L. Clifford, </hi>done to death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e12140">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Ten daies a go I drownd those newes in teares. </l>
          <l>And now to adde more measure to your woes, </l>
          <l>I come to tell you things since then befalne. </l>
          <l>After the bloudie fraie at Wakefield fought, </l>
          <l>Where your braue father breath'd his latest gaspe, </l>
          <l>Tidings as swiflie as the post could runne, </l>
          <l>Was brought me of your losse, and his departure. </l>
          <l>I then in London keeper of the <hi>King, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Mustred my souldiers, gathered flockes of friends, </l>
          <l>And verie well appointed as I thought, </l>
          <l>Marcht to saint Albons to entercept the <hi>Queene, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Bearing the King in my behalfe along, </l>
          <l>For by my scoutes I was aduertised, </l>
          <l>That she was comming, with a full intent </l>
          <l>To dash your late decree in parliament, </l>
          <l>Touching king Henries heires and your succession. </l>
          <l>Short tale to make, we at Saint Albons met, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-014-b"/>
          <l>Our battels ioinde, and both sides fiercelie fought. </l>
          <l>But whether twas the coldnesse of the king, </l>
          <l>He lookt full gentlie on his warlike <hi>Queene, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>That robde my souldiers of their heated spleene. </l>
          <l>Or whether twas report of his successe, </l>
          <l>Or more then common feare of Cliffords rigor, </l>
          <l>Who thunders to his captaines bloud and death, </l>
          <l>I cannot tell. But to conclude with truth, </l>
          <l>Their weapons like to lightnings went and came. </l>
          <l>Our souldiers like the might Owles lasie flight, </l>
          <l>Or like an idle thresher with a flaile, </l>
          <l>Fel gentlie downe as if they smote their friends. </l>
          <l>I cheerd them vp with iustice of the cause, </l>
          <l>With promise of hie paie and great rewardes, </l>
          <l>But all in vaine, they had no harts to fight, </l>
          <l>Nor we in them no hope to win the daie, </l>
          <l>So that We fled. The king vnto the <hi>Queene, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Lord George your brother, <hi>Norffolke, </hi>and my selfe, </l>
          <l>In hast, post hast, are come to ioine with you, </l>
          <l>For in the marches here we heard you were, </l>
          <l>Making another head to fight againe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e12660">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Thankes gentle <hi>Warwike. </hi>
          </l>
          <l>How farre hence is the Duke with his power? </l>
          <l>And when came George from Burgundie to <hi>England? </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e12750">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Some fiue miles off the Duke is with his power, </l>
          <l>But as for your brother he was latelie sent </l>
          <l>From your kind Aunt, Duches of <hi>Burgundie, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>With aide of souldiers gainst this needfull warre. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e12820">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Twas ods belike, when valiant Warwike fled. </l>
          <l>Oft haue I heard thy praises in pursute, </l>
          <l>But nere till now thy scandall of retire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e12880">
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-015-a"/>
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Nor now my scandall Richard dost thou heare, </l>
          <l>For thou shalt know that this right hand of mine, </l>
          <l>Can plucke the Diadem from Saint Henries head, </l>
          <l>And wring the awefull scepter from his fist: </l>
          <l>Were he as famous and as bold in warre, </l>
          <l>As he is famde for mildnesse, peace and praier. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e12980">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>I know it well Lord Warwike blame me not, </l>
          <l>Twas loue I bare thy glories made me speake. </l>
          <l>But in this troublous time, whats to be done? </l>
          <l>Shall we gothrow away our coates of steele, </l>
          <l>And clad our bodies in blacke mourning gownes, </l>
          <l>Numbring our Auemaries with our beades? </l>
          <l>Or shall we on the helmets of our foes, </l>
          <l>Tell our deuotion with reuengefull armes? </l>
          <l>If for the last saie I▪ and to it Lords. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e13120">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Why therefore Warwike came to find ● you out, </l>
          <l>And therefore comes my brother <hi>Montague. </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Attend me Lords, the proud insulting Queene, </l>
          <l>With Clifford and the haught <hi>Northumberland, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And of their feather manie mo proud birdes, </l>
          <l>Haue wrought the easie melting king like waxe. </l>
          <l>He sware consent to your succession, </l>
          <l>His oath inrolled in the Parliament. </l>
          <l>But now to London all the crew are gone, </l>
          <l>To frustrate his oath or what besides </l>
          <l>May make against the house of <hi>Lancaster. </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Their power I gesse them fifty thousand strong. </l>
          <l>Now if the helpe of Norffolke and my selfe, </l>
          <l>Can but amount to 48. thousand, </l>
          <l>With all the friendes that thou braue earle of <hi>March, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Among the louing Welshmen canst procure, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-015-b"/>
          <l>Why via, To London will we march amaine, </l>
          <l>And once againe betraide our foming steedes, </l>
          <l>And once againe crie charge vpon the foe, </l>
          <l>But neuer once againe turne backe and flee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e13420">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>I, now me thinkes I heare great Warwike speake: </l>
          <l>Nere maie he liue to see a sunshine daie, </l>
          <l>That cries retire, when Warwike bids him stay. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e13490">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Lord <hi>Warwike, </hi>on thy shoulder will I leane, </l>
          <l>And when thou faints, must Edward fall: </l>
          <l>Which perill heauen forefend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e13560">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>No longer Earle of <hi>March, </hi>but Duke of <hi>Yorke, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>The next degree, is Englands royall king: </l>
          <l>And king of England and shalt thou be proclaimde, </l>
          <l>In euery burrough as we passe along: </l>
          <l>And he that casts not vp his cap for ioie, </l>
          <l>Shall for the offence make forfeit of his head. </l>
          <l>King <hi>Edward, </hi>valiant <hi>Richard, Montague, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Stay we no longer dreaming of renowne, </l>
          <l>But forward to effect these resolutions. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e13710">Enter a Messenger. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e13720">
          <speaker>Mes. </speaker>
          <l>The Duke of Norffolke sends you word by me, </l>
          <l>The Queene is comming with a puissant power, </l>
          <l>And craues your companie for speedie councell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e13790">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Why then it sorts braue Lordes. Lets march away. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e13820">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e13830">Enter the King and <hi>Queene, </hi>Prince <hi>Edward, </hi>and the Northerne Earles, with drum and Souldiers. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e13870">
          <speaker>Quee. </speaker>
          <l>Welcome my Lord to this braue town of <hi>York, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Yonders the head of that ambitious enemie, </l>
          <l>That sought to be impaled with your crowne. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-016-a"/>
          <l>Doth not the obiect please your eie my Lord? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e13940">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Euen as the rockes please them that feare their wracke. </l>
          <l>Withhold reuenge deare God tis not my fault, </l>
          <l>Nor wittinglie haue I infringde my vow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e13990">
          <speaker>Clif </speaker>
          <l>My gratious Lord, this too much lenitie, </l>
          <l>And harmefull pittie must be laid aside, </l>
          <l>To whom do Lyons cast their gentle lookes? </l>
          <l>Not to the beast that would vsurpe his den. </l>
          <l>Whose hand is that the sauage Beare doth licke? </l>
          <l>Not his that spoiles his young before his face. </l>
          <l>Whose scapes the lurking serpentes mortall sting? </l>
          <l>Not he that sets his foot vpon her backe. </l>
          <l>The smallest worme will turne being troden on, </l>
          <l>And Doues will pecke, in rescue of their broode. </l>
          <l>Ambitious Yorke did leuell at thy Crowne, </l>
          <l>Thou smiling, while he knit his angrie browes. </l>
          <l>He but a Duke, would haue his sonne a king, </l>
          <l>And raise his issue like a louing sire. </l>
          <l>Thou being a king blest with a goodlie sonne, </l>
          <l>Didst giue consent to disinherit him, </l>
          <l>Which argude thee a most vnnaturall father. </l>
          <l>Vnreasonable creatures feed their yong. </l>
          <l>And though mans face be fearefull to their eies, </l>
          <l>Yet in protect on of their tender ones, </l>
          <l>Who hath not seene them euen with those same wings </l>
          <l>Which they haue sometime vsde in fearefull flight, </l>
          <l>Make warre with him, that climes vnto their nest, </l>
          <l>Offring their owne liues in their yongs defence? </l>
          <l>For shame my Lord, make them your president, </l>
          <l>Were it not pittie that this goodlie boy, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-016-b"/>
          <l>should lose his birth right through his fathers fault? </l>
          <l>And long hereafter saie vnto his child, </l>
          <l>What my great grandfather and grandfire got, </l>
          <l>My carelesse father fondlie gaue awaie? </l>
          <l>Looke on the boy and let his manlie face, </l>
          <l>Which promiseth successefull fortune to vs all, </l>
          <l>Steele thy melting thoughtes, </l>
          <l>To keepe thine owne, and leaue thine owne with him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e14360">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Full wel hath Clifford plaid the Orator, </l>
          <l>Inferring, arguments of mighty force. </l>
          <l>But tell me, didst thou neuer yet heare tell. </l>
          <l>That things euill got had euer bad successe, </l>
          <l>And happie euer was it for that sonne, </l>
          <l>Whose father for his hoording went to hell? </l>
          <l>I leaue my sonne my vertuous deedes behind, </l>
          <l>And would my father had left me no more, </l>
          <l>For all the rest is held at such a rate, </l>
          <l>As askes a thousand times more care to keepe, </l>
          <l>Then maie the present profit counteruaile. </l>
          <l>Ah cosen <hi>Yorke, </hi>would thy best friendes did know, </l>
          <l>How it doth greeue me that thy head stands there. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e14530">
          <speaker>Quee. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord this harmefull pittie makes your followers faint. </l>
          <l>You promisde knighthood to your princelie sonne. </l>
          <l>Vnsheath your sword and straight doe dub him knight. </l>
          <l>Kneele downe <hi>Edward. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e14600">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Edward Plantagenet <hi>〈…〉 knight, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And learne this lesson boy▪ draw ●●y sword in right </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e14650">
          <speaker>Prince. </speaker>
          <l>My gratious father by your kingly leaue, </l>
          <l>Ile draw it as apparant to the crowne, </l>
          <l>And in that 〈…〉 to the death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e14700">
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-017-a"/>
          <speaker>Northum. </speaker>
          <l>Why that is spoken like a toward prince. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e14730">Enter a Messenger. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e14740">
          <speaker>Mes. </speaker>
          <l>Royall commaunders be in readinesse, </l>
          <l>For with a band of fiftie thousand men, </l>
          <l>Comes Warwike backing of the Duke of <hi>Yorke. </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And in the townes whereas they passe along, </l>
          <l>Proclaimes him king, and manie flies to him, </l>
          <l>Prepare your battels, for they be at hand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e14840">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>I would your highnesse would depart the field, </l>
          <l>The Queene hath best successe when you are absent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e14890">
          <speaker>Quee. </speaker>
          <l>Do good my Lord, and leaue vs to our fortunes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e14920">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Why thats my fortune, therefore Ile stay still. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e14950">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>Be it with resolution then to fight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e14980">
          <speaker>Prince. </speaker>
          <l>Good father cheere these noble Lords, </l>
          <l>Vnsheath your sword, sweet father crie Saint <hi>George. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e15030">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>Pitch we our battell heere, for hence wee will not moue. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e15060">Enter the house of <hi>Yorke. </hi>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e15080">
          <speaker>Edward </speaker>
          <l>Now periurie Henrie wilt thou yeelde thy crowne, </l>
          <l>And kneele for mercie at thy soueraignes feete? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e15130">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>Go rate thy minions proud insulting boy, </l>
          <l>Becomes it thee to be thus malepert, </l>
          <l>Before thy king and lawfull soueraigne? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e15180">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>I am his king and he should bend his knee, </l>
          <l>I was adopted heare by his consent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e15230">
          <speaker>George. </speaker>
          <l>Since when he hath broke his oath. </l>
          <l>For as we heare you that are king </l>
          <l>Though he doe weare the Crowne, </l>
          <l>Haue causde him by new act of Parlement </l>
          <l>To blot our brother out, and put his owne son in. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e15300">
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-017-b"/>
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>And reason <hi>George. </hi>Who should succeede the father but the son? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e15340">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Are you their butcher? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e15370">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>
            <hi>I Crookbacke, </hi>here I stand to answere thee, or any of your sort. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e15410">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Twas you that kild yong <hi>Rutland, </hi>was it not? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e15450">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>Yes, and old Yorke too, and yet not satisfide. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e15490">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>For Gods sake Lords giue synald to the fight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e15520">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>What saiest thou <hi>Henry? </hi>wilt thou yeelde thy crowne? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e15560">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>What, long tongde <hi>War, </hi>dare you speake? </l>
          <l>When you and I met at saint Albones last, </l>
          <l>Your legs did better seruice than your hands. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e15640">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>I, then twas my turne to flee, but now tis thine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e15670">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>You said so much before, and yet you fled. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e15700">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Twas not your valour <hi>Clifford, </hi>that droue mee thence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e15740">
          <speaker>Northum. </speaker>
          <l>No nor your manhood <hi>Warwike, </hi>that could make you staie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e15780">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Northumberland Northumberland, <hi>wee holde </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Thee reuerentlie Breake off the partie, for scarse </l>
          <l>I can refraine the execution of my big swolne </l>
          <l>Hart, against that Clifford there, that </l>
          <l>Cruell child-killer. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e15870">
          <speaker>Clif </speaker>
          <l>Why I kild thy father, calst thou him a child? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e15900">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>I like a villaine, and a trecherous coward, </l>
          <l>As thou didst kill our tender brother <hi>Rutland. </hi>
          </l>
          <l>But ere sunne set Ile make thee curse the deed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e15960">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Haue doone with wordes great Lordes, and Hear me speake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e15990">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>Defie them then, or else hold close thy lips. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e16020">
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-018-a"/>
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>I prethe giue no limits to my tongue, </l>
          <l>I am a king and priuiledge to speake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e16060">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord the wound that bred this meeting here </l>
          <l>Cannot be cru'd with words, therefore be still. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e16100">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Then executioner vnsheath thy sword, </l>
          <l>By him that made vs all I am resolu'de, </l>
          <l>That Cliffords manhood hangs vpon his tongue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e16160">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>What saist thou <hi>Henry, </hi>shall I haue my right or no? </l>
          <l>A thousand men haue broke their fast to daie, </l>
          <l>That nere shall dine, vnlesse thou yeeld the crowne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e16230">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>If thou denie their blouds be on thy head, </l>
          <l>For Yorke in iustice puts his armour on. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e16280">
          <speaker>Prin. </speaker>
          <l>If all be right that Warwike saies is right, </l>
          <l>There is no wrong but all things must be right. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e16330">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Whosoeuer got thee, there thy mother stands, </l>
          <l>For well I wot thou hast thy mothers tongue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e16370">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>But thou art neither like thy sire nor dam, </l>
          <l>But like a soule mishapen stygmaticke </l>
          <l>Markt by the destinies to be auoided, </l>
          <l>As venome Todes, or Lizards fainting lookes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e16430">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Iron of <hi>Naples, </hi>hid with English gilt, </l>
          <l>Thy father beares the title of a king. </l>
          <l>As if a channell should be calde the Sea; </l>
          <l>Shames thou not, knowing from whence thou art deRiu'de, </l>
          <l>to parlie thus with Englands lawfull heires? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e16510">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>A wispe of straw were worth a thousand crowns, </l>
          <l>To make that shamelesse callet know her selfe, </l>
          <l>Thy husbands father reueld in the hart of <hi>France, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And tam'de the French, and made the Doiphin stoope: </l>
          <l>And had he macht according to his state, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-018-b"/>
          <l>He might haue kept that glorie till this daie. </l>
          <l>But when he tooke a begger to his bed, </l>
          <l>And gracst thy poore sire with his bridall daie, </l>
          <l>Then that sun-shine bred a showre for him </l>
          <l>Which washt his fathers fortunes out of France, </l>
          <l>And heapt seditions on his crowne at home. </l>
          <l>For what hath mou'd these tumults but thy pride? </l>
          <l>Hadst thou beene meeke, our title yet had slept? </l>
          <l>And we in pittie of the gentle king, </l>
          <l>Had slipt our claime vntill an other age. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e16690">
          <speaker>George. </speaker>
          <l>But when we saw our summer brought the gaine, </l>
          <l>And that the haruest brought vs no increase, </l>
          <l>We set the axe to thy vsurping root, </l>
          <l>And though the edge haue something hit our selues, </l>
          <l>Yet know thou we will neuer cease to strike, </l>
          <l>Till we haue hewne thee downe, </l>
          <l>Or bath'd thy growing with our heated blouds. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e16780">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>And in this resolution, I defie thee, </l>
          <l>Not willing anie longer conference, </l>
          <l>Since thou deniest the gentle king to speake. </l>
          <l>Sound trumpets, let our bloudie colours waue, </l>
          <l>And either victorie or else a graue, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e16850">
          <speaker>Quee. </speaker>
          <l>Staie Edward staie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e16890">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Hence wrangling woman, Ile no longer staie, </l>
          <l>Thy words will cost ten thousand liues to daie. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e16930">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e16940">Alarmes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e16950">Enter <hi>Warwike. </hi>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e16970">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Sore spent with toile as runners with the race, </l>
          <l>I laie me downe a little while to breath, </l>
          <l>For strokes receiude, and manie blowes repaide, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-019-a"/>
          <l>Hath robd my strong knit sinnews of their strength, </l>
          <l>And force perforce needes must I rest my selfe. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e17050">Enter <hi>Edward. </hi>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e17070">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Smile gentle heauens or strike vngentle death, </l>
          <l>That we maie die vnlesse we gaine the daie: </l>
          <l>What fatall starre malignant frownes from heauen </l>
          <l>Vpon the harmelesse line of Yorkes TRUE house? </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e17140">Enter <hi>George. </hi>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e17160">
          <speaker>George. </speaker>
          <l>Come brother, come, lets to the field againe, </l>
          <l>For yet theres hope inough to win the daie: </l>
          <l>Then let vs backe to cheere our fainting Troupes, </l>
          <l>Lest they retire now we haue left the field. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e17220">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>How now my lords: what hap, what hope of good▪ </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e17250">Enter Richard running. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e17270">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Ah <hi>Warwike, </hi>why haste thou withdrawne thy selfe? </l>
          <l>Thy noble father in the thickest thronges, </l>
          <l>Cride still for Warwike his thrise valiant son, </l>
          <l>Vntill with thousand swords he was beset, </l>
          <l>And manie wounds made in his aged brest, </l>
          <l>And as he tottering sate vpon his sleede, </l>
          <l>He wa●t his hand to me and cride aloud▪ </l>
          <l>
            <hi>Richard, </hi>commend me to my valiant sonne, </l>
          <l>And still he cride Warwike reuenge my death, </l>
          <l>And with those words he tumbled off his horse, </l>
          <l>And so the noble Salsbury gaue vp the ghost. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e17440">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Then let the earth be drunken with his bloud, </l>
          <l>Ile kill my horse because I will not she: </l>
          <l>And here to God of heauen I make a vow, </l>
          <l>Neuer to passe from forth this bloudy field </l>
          <l>Till I am full reuenged for his death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e17510">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Lord <hi>Warwike, </hi>Id●e bend my knees with thine, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-019-b"/>
          <l>And in that vow now ioine my soule to thee, </l>
          <l>Thou setter vp and puller downe of kings, </l>
          <l>vouchsafe a gentle victorie to vs, </l>
          <l>Or let vs die before we loose the daie: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e17590">
          <speaker>George. </speaker>
          <l>Then let vs haste to cheere the souldiers harts, </l>
          <l>And call them pillers that will stand to vs, </l>
          <l>And hiely promise to remunerate </l>
          <l>Their trustie seruice, in these dangerous warres. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e17650">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Come, come awaie, and stand not to debate, </l>
          <l>For yet is hope of fortune good enough. </l>
          <l>Brothers, giue me your hands, and let vs part </l>
          <l>And take our leaues vntill we meet againe, </l>
          <l>Where ere it be in heauen or in earth. </l>
          <l>Now I that neuer wept, now melt in wo, </l>
          <l>To see these dire mishaps continue so. </l>
          <l>Warwike farewel. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e17760">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Awaie awaie, once more sweet Lords farewell. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e17790">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e17800">Alarmes, and then enter Richard at one dore and Clifford at the other. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e17830">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>A Clifford a <hi>Clifford. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e17880">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>
            <hi>A Richard </hi>a <hi>Richard. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e17930">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Now <hi>Clifford, </hi>for Yorke &amp; young Rutlands death, </l>
          <l>This thirsty sword that longs to drinke thy bloud, </l>
          <l>Shall lop thy limmes, and slise thy cursed hart, </l>
          <l>For to reuenge the murders thou hast made. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e18020">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>Now <hi>Richard, </hi>I am with thee here alone, </l>
          <l>This is the hand that stabd thy father <hi>Yorke▪ </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And this the hand that slew thy brother <hi>Rutland, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And heres the heart that triumphs in there deathes, </l>
          <l>And cheeres these hands that slew thy 〈◊〉 and brother, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-020-a"/>
          <l>To execute the like vpon thy selfe, </l>
          <l>And so haue at thee. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e18140">Alarmes. They fight, and then enters Warwike and rescues <hi>Richard, </hi>&amp; then <foreign xml:lang="lat">exeunt omnes. </foreign>
          </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e18180">Alarmes still, and then enter <hi>Henry solus. </hi>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e18200">
          <speaker>Hen. </speaker>
          <l>Oh gratious God of heauen looke downe on vs, </l>
          <l>And set some endes to these incessant griefes, </l>
          <l>How like a mastlesse ship vpon the seas, </l>
          <l>This woful battaile doth continue still, </l>
          <l>Now leaning this way, now to that side driue, </l>
          <l>And none doth know to whom the daie will fall. </l>
          <l>O would my death might staie these ciuilliars! </l>
          <l>Would I had neuer raind, nor nere bin king. </l>
          <l>Margret and <hi>Clifford, </hi>chide me from the fielde, </l>
          <l>Swearing they had best successe when I was thence. </l>
          <l>Would God that I were dead so all were well, </l>
          <l>Or would my crowne suffice, I were content </l>
          <l>To yeeld it them and liue a priuate life. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e18380">Enter a souldier with a dead man in his armes. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e18390">
          <speaker>Sould </speaker>
          <l>Il blowes the wind that profits no bodie, </l>
          <l>This man that I haue slaine in fight to daie, </l>
          <l>Maie be possessed of some store of crownes, </l>
          <l>And I will search to find them if I can, </l>
          <l>But stay. Me thinkes it is my fathers face, </l>
          <l>Oh I tis he whom I haue slaine in fight, </l>
          <l>From London was I prest out by the king, </l>
          <l>My father he came on the part of <hi>Yorke, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And in this conflict I haue slaine my father: </l>
          <l>Oh pardon God, I knew not what I did, </l>
          <l>And pardon father, for I knew thee not. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e18530">Enter▪ an other souldier with a dead man. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e18540">
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-020-b"/>
          <speaker>2. Soul. </speaker>
          <l>Lie there thou that foughtst with me so stoutly, </l>
          <l>Now let me see what store of gold thou haste, </l>
          <l>But staie, me thinkes this is no famous face: </l>
          <l>Oh no it is my sonne that I haue slaine in sight, </l>
          <l>O monstrous times begetting such euents, </l>
          <l>How cruel bloudy, and ironious, </l>
          <l>This deadlie quarrell dailie doth beget, </l>
          <l>Poore boy thy father gaue thee lif too late, </l>
          <l>And hath b●reau'de thee of thy life too sone. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e18660">
          <speaker>King </speaker>
          <l>Wo aboue wo, griefe more then common griese, </l>
          <l>Whilst Lyons warre and battaile for their dens, </l>
          <l>Poore lambs do feele the rigor of their wraths: </l>
          <l>The red rose and the white are on his face, </l>
          <l>The fatall colours of our striuing houses, </l>
          <l>Wither one rose, and let the other flourish, </l>
          <l>For if you striue, ten thousand liues must perish. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e18750">
          <speaker>1. Sould. </speaker>
          <l>How will my mother for my fathers death, </l>
          <l>Take on with me and nere be satisfide? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e18790">
          <speaker>2. Sol. </speaker>
          <l>How will my wife for slaughter of my son, </l>
          <l>Take on with me and nere be satisfide? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e18830">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>How will the people now misdeeme their king, </l>
          <l>Oh would my death their mindes could satisfie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e18870">
          <speaker>1. Sould. </speaker>
          <l>Was euer son so rude his fathers bloud to spil? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e18900">
          <speaker>2, Soul. </speaker>
          <l>Was euer father so vnnaturall his son to kill? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e18930">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Was euer king thus greeud and vexed still? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e18960">
          <speaker>1. Sould. </speaker>
          <l>Ile beare thee hence from this accursed place, </l>
          <l>For wo is me to see my fathers face. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e19000">Exit with his father. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e19020">
          <speaker>2. Soul. </speaker>
          <l>Ile beare thee hence &amp; let them fight that wil, </l>
          <l>For I haue murdered where I should not kill. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e19070">Exit with his sonne. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e19090">
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-021-a"/>
          <speaker>K. Hen. </speaker>
          <l>Weepe wretched man, Ile lay thee teare for tear, </l>
          <l>Here sits a king as woe begone as thee. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e19130">Alarmes and enter the <hi>Queene. </hi>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e19150">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>Awaie my Lord to Barwicke presentlie, </l>
          <l>The daie 〈…〉, our friends are murdered, </l>
          <l>No hope is left for vs, therefore awaie▪ </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e19210">Enter prince <hi>Edward. </hi>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e19230">
          <speaker>Prince. </speaker>
          <l>Oh father flie, our men haue left the field, </l>
          <l>Take horse sweet father, let vs saue our selues. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e19270">Enter <hi>Exeter. </hi>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e19290">
          <speaker>Exet. </speaker>
          <l>Awaie my Lord for vengance comes along with him: </l>
          <l>Nay stand not to expostulate make hast, </l>
          <l>Or else come after, Ile awaie before. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e19340">
          <speaker>K Hen. </speaker>
          <l>Naie staie good <hi>Exeter, </hi>for Ile along with thee. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e19380">Enter Clissord wounded, with an arrow in his necke. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e19400">
          <speaker>Clif. </speaker>
          <l>Heere burnes my candell out, </l>
          <l>That whilst it lasted gaue king Henry light▪ </l>
          <l>Ah <hi>Lancaster, </hi>I feare thine ouerthrow, </l>
          <l>More then my bodies parting from my soule. </l>
          <l>My loue and feare glude manie friendes to thee, </l>
          <l>And now I die, that tough commixture melts. </l>
          <l>Impairing Henry strengthened misproud <hi>Yorke, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>The common people swarme like summer flies, </l>
          <l>And whither flies the Gnats but to the sun? </l>
          <l>And who shines now but Henries enemie? </l>
          <l>Oh Phoebus hadst thou neuer giuen consent, </l>
          <l>That Phaeton should checke thy fierie steedes, </l>
          <l>Thy burning carre had neuer scorcht the earth. </l>
          <l>And Henry hadst thou liu'd as kings should doe, </l>
          <l>And as thy father and his father did, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-021-b"/>
          <l>Giuing no foot vnto the house of <hi>Yorke, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>I and ten thousand in this wofull land, </l>
          <l>Had left no mourning Widdowes for our deathes, </l>
          <l>And thou this daie hadst kept thy throne in peace. </l>
          <l>For what doth cherish weedes but gentle aire? </l>
          <l>And what makes robbers bold but lenitie? </l>
          <l>Bootlesse are plaintes, and curelesse are my woundes, </l>
          <l>No waie to flie, no strength to hold our flight, </l>
          <l>The foe is mercilesse and will not pittie me, </l>
          <l>And at their hands I haue deserude no pittie. </l>
          <l>The aire is got into my bleeding wounds, </l>
          <l>And much effuse of bloud doth make me faint, </l>
          <l>Come Yorke and <hi>Richard, Warwike </hi>and the rest, </l>
          <l>I stabde your fathers, now come split my brest. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e19850">Enter <hi>Edward, Richard </hi>and <hi>Warwike, </hi>and Souldiers. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e19880">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Thus farre our fortunes keepes an vpward </l>
          <l>Course, and we are grast with wreathes of victorie. </l>
          <l>Some troopes pursue the bloudie minded Queene, </l>
          <l>That now towards Barwike 〈…〉 amaine, </l>
          <l>But thinke you that Clifford is sled awaie with them? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e19970">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>No, tis impossible he should escape, </l>
          <l>For though before his face I speake the words, </l>
          <l>Your brother Richard markt him for the graue. </l>
          <l>And where so ere he be I warrant him dead. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e20030">Clifford grones and then dies. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e20050">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Harke what soule is this that takes his heauy leaue? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e20080">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>A deadlie grone, like life and deaths departure. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e20110">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>See who it is, and now the battailes ended, </l>
          <l>Friend or foe, let him be friendlie vsed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e20150">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Reuerse that doome of mercie, for tis <hi>Clifford. </hi>
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-022-a"/>
          <l>Who kild our tender brother <hi>Rutland, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And stabd our princelie father Duke of <hi>Yorke. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e20230">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>From off the gates of Yorke fetch downe the </l>
          <l>Head, Your fathers head which Clifford placed there, </l>
          <l>Insteed of that, let his supplie the roome. </l>
          <l>Measure for measure must be answered. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e20310">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Bring forth that fatall skrichowle to our house, </l>
          <l>That nothing sung to vs but bloud and death, </l>
          <l>Now his euill boding tongue no more shall speake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e20360">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>I thinke his vnderstanding is berest. </l>
          <l>Say Clifford doest thou know who speakes to thee? </l>
          <l>Darke cloudie death oreshades his beames of life, </l>
          <l>And he nor sees nor heares vs what we saie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e20430">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Oh would he did, and so perhaps he doth, </l>
          <l>And tis his policie that in the time of death, </l>
          <l>He might auoid such bitter stormes as he </l>
          <l>In his houre of death did giue vnto our father. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e20490">
          <speaker>George. </speaker>
          <l>Richard if thou thinkest so, vex him with eager words. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e20530">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>
            <hi>Clifford, </hi>aske mercie and obtaine no grace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e20570">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>
            <hi>Clifford, </hi>repent in bootlesse penitence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e20610">
          <speaker>War </speaker>
          <l>Clifford deuise excuses for thy fault. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e20650">
          <speaker>George. </speaker>
          <l>Whilst we deuise fell tortures for thy fault. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e20680">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Thou pittiedst <hi>Yorke, </hi>and I am sonne to <hi>Yorke. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e20730">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Thou pittiedst <hi>Rutland, </hi>and I will pittie thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e20770">
          <speaker>George. </speaker>
          <l>Wheres captaine Margaret to hence you now? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e20810">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>They mocke thee <hi>Clifford, </hi>sweare as thou wast wont. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e20850">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>What not an oth? Nay, then I know hees dead. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-022-b"/>
          <l>Tis hard, when Clifford cannot foord his friend an oath. </l>
          <l>By this I know hees dead, and by my soule, </l>
          <l>Would this right hand buy but an howres life, </l>
          <l>That I in all contempt might raile at him. </l>
          <l>Ide cut it off and with the issuing bloud, </l>
          <l>Stifle the villaine whose inst inched thirst, </l>
          <l>Yorke and young Rutland could not satisfie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e20990">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>
            <hi>I, </hi>but he is dead, off with the traitors head, </l>
          <l>And reare it in the place your fathers stands. </l>
          <l>And now to London with triumphant march, </l>
          <l>There to be crowned Englands lawfull king. </l>
          <l>From thence shall Warwike crosse the seas to <hi>France, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And aske the ladie Bona for thy <hi>Queene, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>So shalt thou sinew both these landes togither, </l>
          <l>And hauing France thy friend thou needst not dread, </l>
          <l>The scattered foe that hopes to rise againe. </l>
          <l>And though they cannot greatly sting to hurt, </l>
          <l>Yet looke to haue them busie to offend thine eares. </l>
          <l>First Ile see the coronation done, </l>
          <l>And afterward Ile crosse the seas to <hi>France, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>To effect this marriage if it please my Lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e21230">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Euen as thou wilt good Warwike let it be. </l>
          <l>But first before we goe, George kneele downe. </l>
          <l>We here create thee Duke of <hi>Clarence, </hi>and girt thee with the sword. </l>
          <l>Our younger brother Richard Duke of <hi>Glocester. </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Warwike as my selfe shal do &amp; vndo as him pleaseth best. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e21360">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Let me be Duke of <hi>Clarenco, George </hi>of <hi>Gloster, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>For Glosters Duke dome is too ominous. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e21430">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Tush thats a childish obseruation. </l>
          <l>Richard be Duke of <hi>Gloster. </hi>Now to London. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-023-a"/>
          <l>To see these honors in possession. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e21500">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e21510">Enter two keepers with bow and arrowes. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e21520">
          <speaker>Keeper. </speaker>
          <l>Come lets take our stands vpon this hill, </l>
          <l>And by and by the deere will come this waie. </l>
          <l>But staie, heere comes a man, lets listen him a while. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e21570">Enter king Henrie disguisde. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e21590">
          <speaker>Hen. </speaker>
          <l>From Scotland am I stolne euen of pure loue, </l>
          <l>And thus disguisde to greet my natiue land. </l>
          <l>No, Henrie no It is no land of thine, </l>
          <l>No bending knee will call thee Caesar now, </l>
          <l>No humble suters sues to thee for right, </l>
          <l>For how canst thou helpe them and not thy selfe? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e21700">
          <speaker>Keeper. </speaker>
          <l>I marrie sir, here is a deere, his skin is a </l>
          <l>Keepers fee▪ Sirra stand close, for as I thinke, </l>
          <l>This is the king, king Edward hath deposde. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e21760">
          <speaker>Hen. </speaker>
          <l>My Queene and sonne poore soules are gone to </l>
          <l>
            <hi>France, </hi>and as I heare the great commanding <hi>Warwike, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>To intreat a marriage with the ladie <hi>Bona, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>If this be true, poore Queene and sonne, </l>
          <l>Your labour is but spent in vaine, </l>
          <l>For Lewis is a prince soone wun with words, </l>
          <l>And Warwike is a subtill Orator. </l>
          <l>He laughes and saies, his Edward is instalde, </l>
          <l>She weepes, and saies her Henry is deposde, </l>
          <l>He on his right hand asking a wise for <hi>Edward, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>She on his left side crauing aide for <hi>Henry. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e21990">
          <speaker>Keeper. </speaker>
          <l>What art thou that talkes of kings and queens? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e22020">
          <speaker>Hen. </speaker>
          <l>More then I seeme, for lesse I should not be. </l>
          <l>A man at least, and more I cannot be, </l>
          <l>And men maie talke of kings, and why not I? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e22070">
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-023-b"/>
          <speaker>Keeper. </speaker>
          <l>I but thou talkest as if thou wert a king thy selfe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e22100">
          <speaker>Hen. </speaker>
          <l>Why so I am in mind though not in shew. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e22130">
          <speaker>Keeper. </speaker>
          <l>And if thou be a king where is thy crowne? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e22160">
          <speaker>Hen. </speaker>
          <l>My crowne is in my hart, not on my head. </l>
          <l>My crowne is calde content, a crowne that </l>
          <l>Kings doe seldome times enioy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e22210">
          <speaker>Keeper. </speaker>
          <l>And if thou be a king crownd with content, </l>
          <l>Your crowne content and you, must be content </l>
          <l>To go with vs vnto the officer, for as we thinke </l>
          <l>You are our quondam king, <hi>K. Edward </hi>hath deposde, </l>
          <l>And therefore we charge you in Gods name &amp; the kings </l>
          <l>To go along with vs vnto the officers. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e22300">
          <speaker>Hen. </speaker>
          <l>Gods name be fulfild, your kings name be </l>
          <l>Obaide, and be you kings, command and Ile obay. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e22340">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e22350">Enter king <hi>Edward, Clarence, </hi>and <hi>Gloster, Montague, Hastings, </hi>and the Lady <hi>Gray. </hi>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e22390">
          <speaker>K Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Brothers of <hi>Clarence, </hi>and of <hi>Glocester, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>This ladies husband heere sir <hi>Richard Gray, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>At the battaile of saint Alkones did lose his life, </l>
          <l>His lands then were seazed on by the conqueror. </l>
          <l>Her sute is now to repossesse those lands, </l>
          <l>And sith in quarrell of the house of <hi>Yorke, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>The noble gentleman did lose his life, </l>
          <l>In honor we cannot denie her ●●te. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e22540">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>Your highnesse shall doe well to grant it then. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e22570">
          <speaker>K Edw </speaker>
          <l>I, so I will, but yet Ile make a pause. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e22610">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>I is the wind in that doore? </l>
          <l>
            <hi>Clarence, </hi>I see the Lady hath some thing to grant, </l>
          <l>Before the king will grant her humble lute. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e22670">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>He knows the game, how well he keepes the wind. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e22700">
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-024-a"/>
          <speaker>K Ed. </speaker>
          <l>Widow come some other time to know our mind. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e22730">
          <speaker>La. </speaker>
          <l>May it please your grace I cannot brooke delaies, </l>
          <l>I beseech your highnesse to dispatch me now. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e22780">
          <speaker>K Ed. </speaker>
          <l>Lords giue vs leaue, wee meane to trie this widowes wit. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e22810">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>I, good leaue haue you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e22840">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>For you will haue leaue till youth take leaue, </l>
          <l>And leaue you to your crouch. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e22880">
          <speaker>K Ed. </speaker>
          <l>Come hither widdow, howe many children haste thou? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e22910">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>I thinke he meanes to begge a child on her. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e22940">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>Nay whip me then, heele rather giue hir two. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e22970">
          <speaker>La. </speaker>
          <l>Three my most gratious Lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23000">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>You shall haue foure and you wil be rulde by him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23030">
          <speaker>K Ed. </speaker>
          <l>Were it not pittie they shoulde loose their fathers lands? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23060">
          <speaker>La. </speaker>
          <l>Be pittifull then dread L. and grant it them. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23090">
          <speaker>K Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Ile tell thee how these lands are to be got. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23120">
          <speaker>La. </speaker>
          <l>So shall you bind me to your highnesse seruice. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23150">
          <speaker>K Ed </speaker>
          <l>What seruice wilt thou doe me if I grant it them? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23180">
          <speaker>La. </speaker>
          <l>Euen what your highnesse shall command. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23210">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>Naic then widow Ile warrant you all your </l>
          <l>Husbands lands, if you grant to do what he </l>
          <l>Commands, Fight close or in good faith </l>
          <l>You catch a clap. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23270">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>Naie I seare her not vnlesse she fall. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23300">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>Marie godsforbot man, for heele take vantage then. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23330">
          <speaker>La. </speaker>
          <l>Why stops my Lord, shall I not know my taske? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23360">
          <speaker>K Ed. </speaker>
          <l>An easie taske, tis but to loue a king. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23390">
          <speaker>La. </speaker>
          <l>Thats soone perfounde, because I am a subiect. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23420">
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-024-b"/>
          <speaker>K Ed. </speaker>
          <l>Why then thy hushandes landes I freelie giue thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23460">
          <speaker>La. </speaker>
          <l>I take my leaue with manie thousand thankes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23490">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>The match is made, shee seales it with a cursie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23520">
          <speaker>K Ed </speaker>
          <l>Staie widdow stare, what loue dost thou thinke </l>
          <l>I sue so much to get? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23560">
          <speaker>La. </speaker>
          <l>My humble seruice, such as subiects owes and the lawes commands. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23590">
          <speaker>K Ed. </speaker>
          <l>No by my troth, I meant no such loue, </l>
          <l>But to tell thee the troth, I aime to lie with thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23630">
          <speaker>La. </speaker>
          <l>To tell you plaine my Lord, I had rather lie in prison. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23660">
          <speaker>K Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Why then thou canst not get thy husbandes lands. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23690">
          <speaker>La. </speaker>
          <l>Then mine honestie shall be my dower, </l>
          <l>For by that losse I will not purchase them. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23730">
          <speaker>K Ed. </speaker>
          <l>Herein thou wrongst thy children mightilie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23760">
          <speaker>La. </speaker>
          <l>Heerein your highnesse wrongs both them and </l>
          <l>Me, but mightie Lord this merrie inclination </l>
          <l>Agrees not with the sadnesse of my sute. </l>
          <l>Please it your highnes to dismisse me either with I or no. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23830">
          <speaker>K Ed </speaker>
          <l>
            <hi>I, </hi>if thou saie I to my request, </l>
          <l>No, if thousaie no to my demand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23890">
          <speaker>La. </speaker>
          <l>Then no my Lord, my sute is at an end. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23920">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>The widdow likes him not, shee bends the brow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23950">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>Why he is the bluntest woer in christendome. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e23980">
          <speaker>K Ed </speaker>
          <l>Her lookes are all repleat with maiestie, </l>
          <l>One waie or other she is for a king, </l>
          <l>And she shall be my loue or else my <hi>Queene. </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Saie that king Edward tooke thee for his <hi>Queene. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e24070">
          <speaker>La. </speaker>
          <l>Tis better said then done, my gratious Lord, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-025-a"/>
          <l>I am a subiect sit to iest withall, </l>
          <l>But far vnfit to be a Soueraigne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e24130">
          <speaker>K Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Sweet widdow, by my state I sweare, I speake </l>
          <l>No more then what my hart intends, </l>
          <l>And that is to enioie thee for my loue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e24190">
          <speaker>La. </speaker>
          <l>And that is more then I will yeeld vnto, </l>
          <l>I know I am too bad to be your <hi>Queene, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And yet too good to be your Concubine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e24270">
          <speaker>K Edw. </speaker>
          <l>You cauill widdow, I did meane my <hi>Queene. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e24310">
          <speaker>La. </speaker>
          <l>Your grace would be loath my sonnes should call you father. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e24340">
          <speaker>K Edw. </speaker>
          <l>No more then when my daughters call thee </l>
          <l>Mother. Thou art a widow and thou hast some children, </l>
          <l>And by Gods mother I being but a bacheler </l>
          <l>Haue other some Why tis a happy thing </l>
          <l>To be the father of manie children. </l>
          <l>Argue no more, for thou shalt be my Queene. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e24430">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>The ghostlie father now hath done his shrift. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e24460">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>When he was made a shriuer twas for shift. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e24490">
          <speaker>K Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Brothers you muse what talke the widdow </l>
          <l>And I haue had, you would thinke it strange </l>
          <l>If I should marrie her. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e24560">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>Marrie her my Lord, to whom? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e24590">
          <speaker>K Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Why Clarence to my selfe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e24630">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>That would be ten daies wonder at the least. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e24660">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>Why thats a daie longer then a wonder lastes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e24690">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>And so much more are the wonders in extreames. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e24720">
          <speaker>K Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Well, ieast on brothers, I can tell you, hir </l>
          <l>Sute is granted for her husbands lands. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e24770">Enter a Messenger. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e24780">
          <speaker>Mes. </speaker>
          <l>And it please your grace, Henry your foe is </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-025-b"/>
          <l>Taken, and brought as prisoner to your pallace gates. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e24830">
          <speaker>K Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Awaie with him and send him to the Tower, </l>
          <l>And let vs go question with the man about </l>
          <l>His apprehension. Lords along, and vse this </l>
          <l>Ladie honorablie. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e24890">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e24900">
            <hi>Manet Gloster </hi>and speakes. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e24920">
          <speaker>Glost. </speaker>
          <l>I, Edward will vse women honourablie, </l>
          <l>Would he were wasted marrow, bones and all, </l>
          <l>That from his loines no issue might succeed </l>
          <l>To hinder me from the golden time I looke for, </l>
          <l>For I am not yet lookt on in the world. </l>
          <l>First is there <hi>Edward, Clarence, </hi>and Henry </l>
          <l>And his sonne, and all they lookt for issue </l>
          <l>Of their loines ere I can plant my selfe, </l>
          <l>A cold premeditation for my purpose, </l>
          <l>What other pleasure is there in the world beside? </l>
          <l>I will go clad my bodie in gaie ornaments, </l>
          <l>And lull my selfe within a ladies lap, </l>
          <l>And with sweet Ladies with my words and lookes. </l>
          <l>Oh monstrous man, to harbour such a thought▪ </l>
          <l>Why loue did scorne me in my mothers wombe. </l>
          <l>And for I should not deale in hir astaires, </l>
          <l>Shee did corrupt fraile nature in the flesh, </l>
          <l>And plasle an enuious mountaine on my backe, </l>
          <l>Where sits deformity to mocke my bodie, </l>
          <l>To drie mine arme vp like a withered shrimpe. </l>
          <l>To make my legges of an vnequall size, </l>
          <l>And am I then a man to be belou'd? </l>
          <l>Easier for me to compasse twentie crownes. </l>
          <l>Tut I can smile, and murder when I smile, </l>
          <l>I crie content, to that that greeues me most. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-026-a"/>
          <l>I can adde colours to the Camelion, </l>
          <l>And for a need change shapes with <hi>Protheus, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And set the aspiring Catalin to schoole. </l>
          <l>Can I doe this, and cannot get the crowne? </l>
          <l>Tush were it ten times higher, Ile pull it downe. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e25380">Exit. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e25390">Enter king Lewis and the ladie <hi>Bona, </hi>and <hi>Queene Margaret, Prince Edward, </hi>and Oxford and others. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e25440">
          <speaker>Lewes. </speaker>
          <l>Welcome Queene Margaret to the Court of <hi>France, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>It sits not Lewis to sit while thou dost stand, </l>
          <l>Sit by my side, and here I vow to thee, </l>
          <l>Thou shalt haue aide to repossesse thy right, </l>
          <l>And be at proud Edward from his vsurped seat. </l>
          <l>And place king Henry in his former rule. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e25560">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>I humblie thanke your royall maiestie, </l>
          <l>And pray the God of heauen to blesse thy state, </l>
          <l>Great king of <hi>France, </hi>that thus regards our wrongs. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e25620">Enter <hi>Warwike. </hi>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e25640">
          <speaker>Lew. </speaker>
          <l>How now, who is this? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e25670">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>Our Earle of Warwike Edwardes chiefest friend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e25710">
          <speaker>Lew. </speaker>
          <l>Welcome braue <hi>Warwike, </hi>what brings thee to <hi>France? </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e25760">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>From worthy Edward king of <hi>England, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>My Lord and Soueraigne and thy vowed friend, </l>
          <l>I come in kindnes and vnfained loue, </l>
          <l>First to do greetings to thy royall person, </l>
          <l>And then to craue a league of amitie, </l>
          <l>And lastlie to confirme that amitie </l>
          <l>With nuptiall knot if thou vouchsafe to grant </l>
          <l>That vertuous ladie Bona thy faire sister, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-026-b"/>
          <l>To Englands king in lawfull marriage. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e25890">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>And if this go forward all our hope is done. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e25920">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>And gratious Madam, in our kings behalfe, </l>
          <l>I am commanded with your loue and fauour, </l>
          <l>Humblie to kisse your hand and with my tongue, </l>
          <l>To tell the passions of my soueraines hart, </l>
          <l>Where same late entring at his heedfull cares, </l>
          <l>Hath plast thy glorious image and thy vertues. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e26000">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>King Lewes and Lady Bona heare me speake, </l>
          <l>Before you answere Warwike or his words, </l>
          <l>For hee it is hath done vs all these wrongs. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e26080">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Iniurious <hi>Margaret. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e26120">
          <speaker>Prince Ed. </speaker>
          <l>And why not Queene? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e26150">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Because thy father Henry did vsurpe, </l>
          <l>And thou no more art Prince then shee is Queene. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e26200">
          <speaker>Ox. </speaker>
          <l>Then Warwike disanuls great Ioha of <hi>Gaunt, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>That did subdue the greatest part of <hi>Spaine, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And after Iohn of Gaunt wise Henry the fourth, </l>
          <l>Whose wisedome was a mirrour to the world. </l>
          <l>And after this wise prince Henry the fift, </l>
          <l>Who with his prowesse conquered all <hi>France, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>From these our Henries lincallie discent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e26390">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>
            <hi>Oxford, </hi>how haps that in this smooth discourse </l>
          <l>You told not how Henry the sixt had lost </l>
          <l>All that Henry the fift had gotten. </l>
          <l>Me thinkes these peeres of France should smile at that, </l>
          <l>But for the rest you tell a pettigree </l>
          <l>Of three score and two yeares a sillie time, </l>
          <l>To make prescription for a kingdomes worth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e26520">
          <speaker>Oxf. </speaker>
          <l>Why <hi>Warwike, </hi>canst thou denie thy king, </l>
          <l>Whom thou obeyedst thirtie and eight yeeres, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-027-a"/>
          <l>And bewray thy treasons with a blush? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e26580">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Can Oxford that did euer fence the right, </l>
          <l>Now buckler falshood with a pettigree? </l>
          <l>For shame leaue Henry and call Edward king. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e26660">
          <speaker>Oxf. </speaker>
          <l>Call him my king by whom mine elder </l>
          <l>Brother the Lord <hi>Aubray Vere </hi>was done to death, </l>
          <l>And more than so, my father euen in the </l>
          <l>Downefall of his mellowed yeares, </l>
          <l>When age did call him to the dore of death? </l>
          <l>No Warwike no, whilst life vpholds this arme, </l>
          <l>This arme vpholds the house of <hi>Lancaster. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e26780">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>And I the house of <hi>Yorke. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e26820">
          <speaker>K Lewes. </speaker>
          <l>Queene <hi>Margaret, </hi>prince Edward and </l>
          <l>
            <hi>Oxford, </hi>vouchsafe to forbeare a while, </l>
          <l>Till I doe talke a word with <hi>Warwike. </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Now Warwike euen vpon thy honor tell me true; </l>
          <l>
            <hi>Is Edward </hi>lawfull king or no? </l>
          <l>For I were loath to linke with him, that is not lawful heir. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e26960">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Thereon I pawne mine honour and my credit. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e27000">
          <speaker>Lew. </speaker>
          <l>What is he gratious in the peoples eies? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e27030">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>The more, that Henry is vnfortunate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e27070">
          <speaker>Lew. </speaker>
          <l>What is his loue to our sister <hi>Buna? </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e27110">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Such it seemes </l>
          <l>As maie beseeme a monarke like himselfe. </l>
          <l>My selfe haue often heard him s●●e and sweare, </l>
          <l>That this his loue was an eternall plant, </l>
          <l>The root whereof was fixt in vertues ground, </l>
          <l>The leaues and fruite maintainde with beauties sun, </l>
          <l>Exempt from enuie, but not from disdaine, </l>
          <l>Vnlesse the ladie Bona quite his paine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e27220">
          <speaker>Lew. </speaker>
          <l>Then sister let vs heare your firme resolue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e27250">
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-027-b"/>
          <speaker>Bona. </speaker>
          <l>Your grant or your denial shall be mine, </l>
          <l>But ere this daie I must confesse, when I </l>
          <l>Haue heard your kings deserts recounted, </l>
          <l>Mine eares haue tempted iudgement to desire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e27320">
          <speaker>Lew. </speaker>
          <l>Then draw neere Queene Margaret and be a </l>
          <l>Witnesse, that Bona shall be wife to the English king. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e27380">
          <speaker>Prince Edw. </speaker>
          <l>To Edward but not the English king. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e27420">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Henry now liues in Scotland at his ease, </l>
          <l>Where hauing nothing nothing can be lose, </l>
          <l>And as for you your seife our quondun Queene, </l>
          <l>You haue a father able to mainetaine your state, </l>
          <l>And better twere to trouble him them <hi>France. </hi>
          </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e27530">Sound for a post within. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e27540">
          <speaker>Lew. </speaker>
          <l>Here comes some post Warwike to thee orvs, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e27580">
          <speaker>Post. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord ambassador this letter is for you, </l>
          <l>Sent from your brother Marquis <hi>Montague. </hi>
          </l>
          <l>This from our king vnto your Maiestie. </l>
          <l>And these to you Madam, from whom I know not. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e27650">
          <speaker>Oxf. </speaker>
          <l>I like it well that our saire Queene and mistresse, </l>
          <l>Smiles at her newes when Warwike frets as his. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e27700">
          <speaker>P. Ed. </speaker>
          <l>And marke how Lewes stamps as he were nettled. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e27740">
          <speaker>Lew. </speaker>
          <l>Now Margaret &amp; <hi>Warwike, </hi>what are your news? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e27790">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>Mine such as fils my hart full of ioie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e27820">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Mine full of sorrow and harts discontent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e27850">
          <speaker>Lew. </speaker>
          <l>What hath your king married the Ladie <hi>Gray, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And now to excuse himselfe sends vs a post of papers? </l>
          <l>How dares he presume to vse vs thus? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e27910">
          <speaker>Quee. </speaker>
          <l>This proueth Edwards loue, &amp; Warwiks honesty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e27960">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>King <hi>Lewis, </hi>I here protest in sight of heauen, </l>
          <l>And by the hope I haue of heauenlie blisle, </l>
          <l>That I am cleare from this misdeed of <hi>Edwards. </hi>
          </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-028-a"/>
          <l>No more my king, for he dishonours me, </l>
          <l>And most himselfe▪ if he could see his shame. </l>
          <l>Did I forget that by the house of <hi>Yorke. </hi>
          </l>
          <l>My father came vntimelie to his death? </l>
          <l>Did I let passe the abuse done to my neece? </l>
          <l>Did I impale him with the regall Crowne, </l>
          <l>And thrust king Henry from his natiue home, </l>
          <l>And most vngratefull doth he vse me thus? </l>
          <l>My gratious Queene pardon what is past, </l>
          <l>And henceforth I am thy true seruitour. </l>
          <l>I will reuenge the wrongs done to ladie <hi>Bona, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And replant Henry in his former state. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e28220">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>Yes Warwike I doe quite forget thy former </l>
          <l>Faults, if now thou wilt become king Henries friend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e28280">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>So much his friend, I his vnfained friend, </l>
          <l>That if king Lewes vouchsafe to furnish vs </l>
          <l>With some few bands of chosen souldiers, </l>
          <l>Ile vndertake to land them on our coast, </l>
          <l>And force the Tyrant from his seate by warre, </l>
          <l>Tis not his new made bride shall succour him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e28370">
          <speaker>Lew. </speaker>
          <l>Then at the last I firmelie am resolu'd, </l>
          <l>You shall haue aide: and English messenger returne </l>
          <l>In post, and tell false Edward thy supposed king, </l>
          <l>That Lewis of France is sending ouer Maskers </l>
          <l>To reuell it with him and his new bride. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e28460">
          <speaker>Bona </speaker>
          <l>Tell him in hope heele be a Widower shortlie, </l>
          <l>Ile weare the willow garland for his sake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e28500">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>Tell him my mourning weedes be laidle aside, </l>
          <l>And I am readie to put armour on. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e28540">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Tell him from me, that he hath done me wrong, </l>
          <l>And therefore Ile vncrowne him er'e be long. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-028-b"/>
          <l>Thears thy reward, begone. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e28590">
          <speaker>Lew. </speaker>
          <l>But now tell me <hi>Warwike, </hi>what assurance </l>
          <l>I shall haue of thy true loyaltie? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e28640">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>This shall assure my constant loyaltie, </l>
          <l>If that our Queene and this young prince agree, </l>
          <l>Ile ioine mine eldest daughter and my ioie </l>
          <l>To him forthwith in holie wedlockes bandes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e28700">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>Withall my hart, that match I like full wel, </l>
          <l>Loue her sonne <hi>Edward, </hi>shee is faite and yong, </l>
          <l>And giue thy hand to Warwike for thy loue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e28780">
          <speaker>Lew. </speaker>
          <l>It is enough, and now we will prepare, </l>
          <l>To leuie 〈…〉 for to go with you. </l>
          <l>And you Lord Bourbon our high Admirall, </l>
          <l>Shall waft them safelie to the English coast, </l>
          <l>And chase proud Edward from his slumbring trance, </l>
          <l>For mocking marriage with the name of <hi>France. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e28890">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>I came from Edward as Imbassadour </l>
          <l>But I returne his sworne and mortall foe: </l>
          <l>Matter of marriage was the charge he gaue me, </l>
          <l>But dreadfull warre shall answere his demand. </l>
          <l>Had he none else to make a stale but me? </l>
          <l>Then none but I shall turne his iest to sorrow. </l>
          <l>I was the chiefe that raisde him to the crowne, </l>
          <l>And Ile be chiefe to bring him downe againe, </l>
          <l>Not that I pittie Henries miserie, </l>
          <l>But seeke reuenge on Edwards mockerie. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e29060">Exit. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e29070">Enter king <hi>Edward, </hi>the Queene and <hi>Clarence, </hi>and Gloster and Montague and <hi>Hastings, </hi>and <hi>Penbrooke, </hi>with souldiers. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e29150">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Brothers of Clarence and of <hi>Glocester. </hi>
          </l>
          <l>What thinke you of our marriage with the ladie <hi>Gray? </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e29220">
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-029-a"/>
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord, we thinke as Warwike and Lewes </l>
          <l>That are so slacke in iudgement▪ that theile take </l>
          <l>No offence at this suddaine marriage. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e29290">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Suppose they doe, they are but Lewes and </l>
          <l>
            <hi>Warwike, </hi>and I am your king and <hi>Warwikes, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And will be obaied. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e29370">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>And shall, because our king but yet such </l>
          <l>Sudden marriages seldome proueth well. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e29410">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Yea brother Richard are you against vs too? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e29450">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>Not I my Lord, no, God forefend that I should </l>
          <l>Once gaine s●●e your highnesse pleasure, </l>
          <l>● &amp; twere a pittie to sunder them that yoake so wel togither. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e29500">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>〈◊〉 your skornes and your dislikes aside, </l>
          <l>Shew me some reasons why the Ladie <hi>Gray, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Mare not be my loue and Englands <hi>Queene? </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Speake freelie <hi>Clarence, Gloster, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Montague and <hi>Hastings. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e29620">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord then this is my opinion, </l>
          <l>That Warwike beeing dishonored in his embassage, </l>
          <l>Doth seeke reuenge to quite his iniuries. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e29680">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>And Lewes in regard of his sisters wrongs, </l>
          <l>Doth ioine with Warwike to supplant your state. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e29740">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Suppose that Lewis and Warwike be appeas●, </l>
          <l>By such meanes as I can best deuise. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e29800">
          <speaker>Mont. </speaker>
          <l>But yet to haue ioind with France in this </l>
          <l>Alliance, would more haue strengthened this out </l>
          <l>Common wealth, gainst forwarde stormes, </l>
          <l>Then anie home bred marriage. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e29860">
          <speaker>Hast. </speaker>
          <l>Let England be true within it selfe, </l>
          <l>We need not France not any alliance with them. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e29900">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>For this 〈◊〉 speech the Lord Hastings wel deserues, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-029-b"/>
          <l>To haue the daughter and heire of the Lord <hi>Hungerford. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e29960">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>And what then? It was our will it should be so? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e29990">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>I, and for such a thing too the Lord Scales </l>
          <l>Did well deserue at your hands, to haue the </l>
          <l>Daughter of the Lord Bonsield and left your </l>
          <l>Brothers to go seeke elsewhere, but in </l>
          <l>Your madnes, you butie brotherhood. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e30080">
          <speaker>Edw </speaker>
          <l>Alasse poore <hi>Clarence, </hi>is it for a wife, </l>
          <l>That thou art mal-content, </l>
          <l>Why man be of good cheere, I will prouide thee one. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e30140">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>Naie you plaide the broker soull for your selfe, </l>
          <l>That you shall giue me leaue to make my </l>
          <l>Choise as I thinke good, and to that intent, </l>
          <l>I shortlie meane to leaue you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e30200">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Leaue me or tarrie I am full resolu'd. </l>
          <l>Edward will not be tied to his brothers wils. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e30250">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>My Lords doe 〈◊〉 but right and you must </l>
          <l>Confesse, before it pleasd his highnesse to aduance </l>
          <l>My state to title of a Queene, </l>
          <l>That I was not ignoble in my birth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e30310">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Forthcare my loue to ●iwne vpon their frownes, </l>
          <l>For thee they must obay, 〈◊〉 shall obeie, </l>
          <l>And if they looke for fauour at my hands. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e30360">
          <speaker>Mont. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord, heere is the messenger return'd from France. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e30390">Enter a Messenger. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e30400">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Now s●●a, What letters or what new●●● </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e30430">
          <speaker>Mes. </speaker>
          <l>No letters my Lord, and such 〈…〉 without your highnesse speciall pardon I dare not dilate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e30460">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>We pardon thee, and as neere as thou canst </l>
          <l>Tell me, What said Lewis to our letters? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e30510">
          <speaker>Mes. </speaker>
          <l>At my departure these were his vetie words. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-030-a"/>
          <l>Go tell false Edward thy supposed king, </l>
          <l>That Lewis of France is sending ouer Maskers, </l>
          <l>To reuill it with him and his new bride. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e30590">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>
            <hi>Is Lewis </hi>so braue, belike he thinkes me <hi>Henry. </hi>
          </l>
          <l>But what said Lady Bona to these wrongs? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e30660">
          <speaker>Mes. </speaker>
          <l>Tel him quoth she, in hope heele proue a widdower shortly, Ile weare the willow garland for his sake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e30690">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>She had the wrong, indeed she could saie </l>
          <l>Little lesse. But what saide Henries Queene, for as </l>
          <l>I heare, she was then in place? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e30760">
          <speaker>Mes. </speaker>
          <l>Tell him quoth shee my mourning weeds be </l>
          <l>Doone, and I am readie to put armour on. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e30800">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Then be like she meanes to pla●e the <hi>Amazon. </hi>
          </l>
          <l>But what said Warwike to these iniuries? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e30860">
          <speaker>Mes. </speaker>
          <l>He more incensed then the rest my Lord, </l>
          <l>Tell him quoth he, that he hath done me wrong, </l>
          <l>And therefore Ile vncrowne him er'e be long. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e30910">
          <speaker>Ed </speaker>
          <l>Ha, Durst the traytor breath out such proude words? </l>
          <l>But I will arme me to preuent the worst. </l>
          <l>But what is Warwike friendes with <hi>Margaret? </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e30980">
          <speaker>Mes. </speaker>
          <l>I my good Lord▪ theare so 〈◊〉 in friendship, </l>
          <l>That young Prince Edward marries Warwikes daughter. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e31050">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>The elder, belike Clarence shall haue the </l>
          <l>Yonger. All you that loue me and Warwike </l>
          <l>Follo v me. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e31120">Exit Clarence and Summerset. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e31140">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Clarence and Summerset fled to <hi>Warwike. </hi>
          </l>
          <l>What saie you brother <hi>Richard, </hi>will you stand to vs? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e31220">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>I my Lord in despight of all that shall </l>
          <l>Withstand you For why hath Nature </l>
          <l>Made me halt downe right, but that I </l>
          <l>Should be valiant and stand to it, for if </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-030-b"/>
          <l>I would, I cannot runne awaie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e31310">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>` <hi>Penbrooke, </hi>go raise an armie presentlie, </l>
          <l>Pitch vp my tent, for in the field this night </l>
          <l>I meane to rest, and on the morrow morne, </l>
          <l>Ile march to meet proud Warwike ere he land </l>
          <l>Those stragling troopes which he hath got in France. </l>
          <l>But ere I goe Montague and <hi>Hastings, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>You of all the rest are neerest allied </l>
          <l>In bloud to <hi>Warwike, </hi>therefore tell me, if </l>
          <l>You fauour him more then me or not: </l>
          <l>Speake truelie, for I had rather haue you open </l>
          <l>Enemies, then hollow friends. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e31490">
          <speaker>Monta. </speaker>
          <l>So God helpe Montague as he proues true. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e31530">
          <speaker>Hast. </speaker>
          <l>And Hastings as hee fauours Edwards cause. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e31580">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>It shall suffice, come then lets march awaie. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e31610">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e31620">Enter Warwike and <hi>Oxford, </hi>with souldiers. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e31650">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Trust me my Lords all hitherto goes well, </l>
          <l>The common people by numbers swarme to vs, </l>
          <l>But see where Sommerset and Clarence comes, </l>
          <l>Speake suddenlie my Lords, are we all friends? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e31730">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>Feare not that my Lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e31760">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Then gentle Clarence welcome vnto <hi>Warwike. </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And welcome <hi>Summerset, </hi>I hold it cowardise, </l>
          <l>To rest mistrustfull where a noble hart, </l>
          <l>Hath pawnde an open hand in signe of loue, </l>
          <l>Else might I thinke that <hi>Clarence▪ Edwards </hi>brother, </l>
          <l>Were but a fained friend to our proceedings, </l>
          <l>But welcome sweet Clarence my daughter shal be thine. </l>
          <l>And now what rests but in nights couerture, </l>
          <l>Thy brother being careleslie encampt, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-031-a"/>
          <l>His souldiers lurking in the towne about, </l>
          <l>And but attended by a simple guarde, </l>
          <l>We maie surprise and take him at our pleasure, </l>
          <l>Our skouts haue found the aduenture verie easie, </l>
          <l>Then crie king Henry with resolued nundes, </l>
          <l>And breake we presentlie into his tent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e31990">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>Why then lets on our waie in silent sort, </l>
          <l>
            <hi>For Warwike </hi>and his friends God and saint <hi>George. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e32050">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>This is his tent, and see where his guard doth </l>
          <l>Stand, Courage my souldiers, now or neuer, </l>
          <l>But follow me now, and Edward shall be ours. </l>
          <l>All▪ A Warwike, a Warwike </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e32140">Alarmes, and Gloster and Hastings shes. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e32170">
          <speaker>Oxf▪ </speaker>
          <l>Who goes there? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e32200">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Richard and Hastings let them go, heere is the Duke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e32250">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>The Duke, why Warwike when we parted </l>
          <l>Last, thou caldst me king? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e32300">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>I, but the case is altred now. </l>
          <l>When you disgraste me in my embassage, </l>
          <l>Then I disgraste you from being king, </l>
          <l>And now am come to create you Duke of <hi>Yorke, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Alasse how should you gouerne anie kingdome, </l>
          <l>That knowes not how to vse embassadors, </l>
          <l>Nor how to vse your brothers brotherlie, </l>
          <l>No●how to shrowd your selfe from enimies. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e32420">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Well <hi>Warwike, </hi>let fortune doe her worst, </l>
          <l>Edward in mind will beare himselfe a king. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e32480">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Then for his minde be Edward Englands king, </l>
          <l>But Henry now shall weare the English crowne. </l>
          <l>Go conuaie him to our brother archbishop of <hi>Yorke, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And when I haue fought with Penbrooke &amp; his followers, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-031-b"/>
          <l>Ile come and tell thee what the ladie Bona saies, </l>
          <l>And so for a while farewell good Duke of <hi>Yorke. </hi>
          </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e32620">Exeunt some with <hi>Edward. </hi>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e32650">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>What followes now, all hithertoo goes well, </l>
          <l>But we must dispatch some letters to <hi>France, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>To tell the Queene of our happy fortune, </l>
          <l>And bid hir come with speed to ioine with vs. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e32730">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>I thats the first thing that we haue to doe, </l>
          <l>And free king Henry from imprisonment, </l>
          <l>And see him seated in his regall throne, </l>
          <l>Come let vs haste awaie, and hauing past these cares, </l>
          <l>Ile post to <hi>Yorke, </hi>and see how Edward fares. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e32840">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e32850">Enter Gloster, Hastings, <hi>and sir </hi>William Stanly. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e32880">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>Lord <hi>Hastings▪ </hi>and 〈◊〉 <hi>William Stanly, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Know that the cause I sent for you is this. </l>
          <l>I looke my brother with a slender traine, </l>
          <l>Should come a hunting in this forrest heere. </l>
          <l>The Bishop of Yorke be friends him much, </l>
          <l>And lets him vse his pleasure in the chase, </l>
          <l>Now I haue priuilie sent him word, </l>
          <l>How I am come with you to rescue him. </l>
          <l>And see where the huntsman and he doth come. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e33050">Enter Edward and a Huntsman. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e33070">
          <speaker>Hunts </speaker>
          <l>This waie my Lord the deere is gone. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e33100">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>No this waie huntsman, see where the </l>
          <l>Keepers stand. Now brother and the rest, </l>
          <l>What, are you prouided to depart? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e33150">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>
            <hi>I, I▪ </hi>the horse stands at the parke corner, </l>
          <l>Come, to Linne▪ and so take shipping into <hi>Flanders▪ </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e33210">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Come then: <hi>Hastings, </hi>and <hi>Stanlie, I </hi>will </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-032-a"/>
          <l>Requite your loues. Bishop farewell, </l>
          <l>Sheeld thee from Warwikes frowne, </l>
          <l>And praie that I maie repossesse the crowne. </l>
          <l>Now huntsman what will you doe? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e33310">
          <speaker>Hunts </speaker>
          <l>Marrie my Lord, I thinke I had as good </l>
          <l>Goe with you, as tarrie heere to be hangde. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e33360">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Come then lets awaie with speed. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e33390">Exeunt Omnes, </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e33400">Enter the Queene and the Lord <hi>Riuers. </hi>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e33430">
          <speaker>Riuers. </speaker>
          <l>Tel me good maddam, why is your grace </l>
          <l>So passionate of late? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e33470">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>Why brother <hi>Riuers, </hi>heare you not the newes, </l>
          <l>Of that successe king Edward had of late? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e33530">
          <speaker>Riu. </speaker>
          <l>What● losse of some pitcht battaile against <hi>Warwike, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Tush, feare not faire <hi>Queen, </hi>but cast those cares aside. </l>
          <l>King Edwards noble mind his honours doth display▪ </l>
          <l>And Warwike maie loose, though then he got the day. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e33630">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>If that were all, my griefes were at an end: </l>
          <l>But greater troubles will I feare befall. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e33670">
          <speaker>Riu </speaker>
          <l>What, is he taken prisoner? by the foe, </l>
          <l>To the danger of his royall person then: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e33710">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>I, thears my griefe, king Edward is surprisde, </l>
          <l>And led awaie, as prisoner vnto <hi>Yorke. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e33770">
          <speaker>Riu. </speaker>
          <l>The newes is passing strange. I must confesse: </l>
          <l>Yet comfort your selfe, for Edward hath more friends, </l>
          <l>Then Lancaster at this time must perceiue, </l>
          <l>That some will set him in his throne againe▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e33850">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>God grant they maie, but gentle brother come, </l>
          <l>And let me leane vpon thine arme a while, </l>
          <l>Vntill I come vnto the sanctuarie, </l>
          <l>There to preserue the fault within my wombe, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-032-b"/>
          <l>K. Edwards seed true heire to Englands crowne. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e33940">Exit. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e33950">Enter Edward and <hi>Richard, </hi>and Hastings with a troope of Hollanders. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e33990">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Thus far from Belgia haue we past the seas, </l>
          <l>And marcht from Raunspur hauen vnto <hi>Yorke: </hi>
          </l>
          <l>But soft the gates are shut, I like not this. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e34080">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Sound vp the drum and call them to the wals. </l>
          <l>Enter the Lord Maire of Yorke vpon the wals. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e34130">
          <speaker>Mair. </speaker>
          <l>My Lords we had notice of your comming, </l>
          <l>And thats the cause we stand vpon our garde, </l>
          <l>An I shut the gates for to preserue the towne. </l>
          <l>Henry now is king, and we are sworne to him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e34200">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Why my Lord Maire, if Henry be your king, </l>
          <l>Edward I am sure at least, is Duke of <hi>Yorke. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e34270">
          <speaker>Mair. </speaker>
          <l>Truth my Lord, we know you for no lesse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e34300">
          <speaker>Edw▪ </speaker>
          <l>I craue nothing but my Dukedome. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e34330">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>But when the Fox hath gotten in his head, </l>
          <l>Heele quicklie make the bodie follow after. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e34370">
          <speaker>Hast. </speaker>
          <l>Why my Lord Maire, what stand you vpon points? </l>
          <l>Open the gates, we are king Henries friends. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e34420">
          <speaker>Mair. </speaker>
          <l>Saie you so, then Ile open them presentlie. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e34450">Exit Maire. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e34470">Ri. By my faith, a wise stout captain &amp; soone perswaded. The Maire opens the dore, and brings the keies in his hand. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e34490">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>So my Lord Maire, these gates must not be shut, </l>
          <l>But in the time of warre, giue me the keies: </l>
          <l>What, feare not man for Edward will defend </l>
          <l>the towne and you, despight of all your foes. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e34560">Enter sir <hi>Iohn Mountgommery </hi>with drumme and souldiers. </stage>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-033-a"/>
          <l>How now <hi>Richard, </hi>who is this? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e34600">
          <speaker>Rich. </speaker>
          <l>Brother, this is sir Iohn <hi>Mountgommery, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>A trustie friend vnlesse I be deceiude. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e34660">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Welcome sir Iohn▪ Wherfore come you in armes? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e34690">
          <speaker>Sir Iohn. </speaker>
          <l>To helpe king Edward in this time of stormes, </l>
          <l>As euerie loyall subiect ought to doe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e34740">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Thankes braue <hi>Mountgommery, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>But I onlie claime my Dukedom, </l>
          <l>Vntil it please God to send the rest. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e34800">
          <speaker>Sir Iohn. </speaker>
          <l>Then sa●e you wel▪ Drum strike vp and let vs </l>
          <l>March away, I came to serue a king and not a Duke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e34840">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Nay sta●e sir Iohn, and let vs first debate, </l>
          <l>With what security we maie doe this thing. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e34880">
          <speaker>Sir Iohn. </speaker>
          <l>What stand you on debating to be briefe, </l>
          <l>Except you presently proclaime your selfe our king, </l>
          <l>Ile hence againe, and keepe them backe that come to </l>
          <l>Succour you, why should we fight when </l>
          <l>You pretend no title? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e34950">
          <speaker>Rich </speaker>
          <l>Fie brother, fie, stand you vpon tearmes? </l>
          <l>Resolue your selfe, and let vs claime the crowne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e34990">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>I am resolude once more to claime the crowne, </l>
          <l>And win it too▪ or else to loose my life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e35040">
          <speaker>Sir Iohn. </speaker>
          <l>I now my soueraigne speaketh like himselfe, </l>
          <l>And now will I be Edwards Champion, </l>
          <l>Sound Trumpets, for Edward shall be proclaimd. </l>
          <l>Edward the fourth by the grace of God, king of England and France, and Lord of Ireland, and whosoeuer gainsa●es king Edwards Might: by this I challenge him to single sight, long liue Edward the fourth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e35160">
          <speaker>All. </speaker>
          <l>Long liue Edward the fourth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e35200">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>We thanke you all. Lord Maire leade on the waie. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-033-b"/>
          <l>For this night weele harbour here in <hi>Yorke, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And then is earlie as the morning sunne, </l>
          <l>Liftes vp his beames aboue this horison </l>
          <l>Weele march to London, to meete with <hi>Warwike: </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And pull sal●e Henry from the Regall throne. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e35310">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e35320">Enter Warwike and <hi>Clarence, </hi>with the Crowne, and then king <hi>Henry, </hi>and <hi>Oxford, </hi>and <hi>Summerset, </hi>and the yong Earle of <hi>Richmond. </hi>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e35390">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Thus from the prison to this prince lie seat, </l>
          <l>By Gods great mercies am I brought </l>
          <l>Againe, Clarence and Warwike doe you </l>
          <l>Keepe the crowne, and gouerue and protect </l>
          <l>My realme in peace, and I will spend the </l>
          <l>Remnant of my daies, to sinnes rebuke </l>
          <l>And my Creators praise. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e35510">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>What answeres Clarence to his soueraignes will? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e35550">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>Clarence agrees to what king Henry likes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e35600">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord of <hi>Summerset, </hi>what prettie </l>
          <l>Boie is that you seeme to be so carefull of? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e35650">
          <speaker>Sum </speaker>
          <l>And it please your grace, it is youg <hi>Henry, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Earle of <hi>Richmond. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e35710">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Henry of <hi>Richmond, </hi>Come hither pretie Ladde. </l>
          <l>If heauenlie powers doe aime aright </l>
          <l>To my diuining thoughts, thou pretie boy, </l>
          <l>Shalt proue this Countries blisse, </l>
          <l>Thy head is made to weare a princelie crowne, </l>
          <l>Thy lookes are all repleat with Maiestie, </l>
          <l>Make much of him my Lords, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-034-a"/>
          <l>For this is he shall helpe you more, </l>
          <l>Then you are hurt by me. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e35840">Enter one with a letter to <hi>Warwike. </hi>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e35860">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>What Counsell Lords, Edward from <hi>Belgia, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>With hastie Germaines and blunt <hi>Hollanders, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Is past in safetie through the narrow seas, </l>
          <l>And with his troopes doe march amaine towardes London, </l>
          <l>And manie giddie people follow him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e35960">
          <speaker>Oxf. </speaker>
          <l>Tis best to looke to this betimes, </l>
          <l>For if this ●ue doe kindle any further, </l>
          <l>It will be hard for vs to quench it out. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e36010">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>In Warwike shire I haue true harted friends, </l>
          <l>Not mutinous in peace, yet bold in warre, </l>
          <l>Them will I muster vp, and thou sonne Clarence shalt </l>
          <l>In <hi>Essex, Suffolke, Norfolke, </hi>and in <hi>Kent, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Stir vp the knights and gentlemen to come with thee▪ </l>
          <l>And thou brother <hi>Montague, </hi>in Leister shire, </l>
          <l>Buckingham and Northampton shire shalt finde, </l>
          <l>Men well inclinde to doe what thou commands, </l>
          <l>And thou braue Oxford wondrous well belou'd, </l>
          <l>Shalt in thy countries muster vp thy friends. </l>
          <l>My soueraigne with his louing Citizens, </l>
          <l>Shall rest in London till we come to him. </l>
          <l>Faire Lords take leaue and stand not to replie, </l>
          <l>Farewell my soueraigne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e36280">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Farewel my <hi>Hector, </hi>my Troyes true hope, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e36330">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Farewell sweet Lords, lets meet at Couentrie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e36360">
          <speaker>All. </speaker>
          <l>Agreed. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e36390">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e36400">Enter Edward and his traine. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e36420">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Sease on the shamefast <hi>Henry, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And once againe conuaie him to the Tower, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-034-b"/>
          <l>Awaie with him, I will not heare him speake. </l>
          <l>And now towards Couentrie let vs bend our course </l>
          <l>To meet with Warwike and his confederates. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e36520">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e36530">Enter Warwike on the walles. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e36550">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Where is the post that came from valiant <hi>Oxford? </hi>
          </l>
          <l>How farre hence is thy Lord my honest fellow? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e36600">
          <speaker>Oxf post. </speaker>
          <l>By this at Daintrie marching hitherward. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e36640">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Where is our brother <hi>Montague? </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Where is the post that came from <hi>Montague? </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e36700">
          <speaker>Post. </speaker>
          <l>I left him at Donsmore with his troopes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e36740">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Say Summerfield where is my louing son? </l>
          <l>And by thy gesse, how farre is Clarence hence? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e36800">
          <speaker>Sommer. </speaker>
          <l>At Southham my Lord I left him with </l>
          <l>His force, and doe expect him two houres hence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e36850">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Then Oxford is at hand, I heare his drum. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e36880">Enter Edward and his power. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e36900">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>See brother, where the surlv Warwike mans the wal. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e36940">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>O vnbid spight, is spotfull Edward come! </l>
          <l>Where slept our scouts or how are they sedus●e, </l>
          <l>That we could haue no newes of their repaire? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e37000">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Now Warwike wilt thou be sorrie for thy faults, </l>
          <l>And call Edward king and he will pardon thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e37060">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Naie rather wilt thou draw thy forces backe? </l>
          <l>Confesse who set thee vp and puld thee downe? </l>
          <l>Call Warwike patron and be penitent, </l>
          <l>And thou shalt still remaine the Duke of <hi>Yorke. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e37140">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>I had thought at least be would haue said the king. </l>
          <l>Or did he make the best against his will. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e37180">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Twas Warwike gaue the kingdome to thy brother. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e37220">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Why then tis mine, if but by Warwikes gift. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e37260">
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-035-a"/>
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>I but thou art no Atlas for so great a waight, </l>
          <l>And weakling, Warwike takes his gift againe, </l>
          <l>Henry is my king, Warwike his subiect▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e37350">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>I prethe gallant Warwike tell me this, </l>
          <l>What is the bodie when the head is off? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e37400">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>Alasse that Warwike had no more foresight, </l>
          <l>But whilst he sought to steale the single ten, </l>
          <l>The king was finelie fingerd from the decke? </l>
          <l>You left poore Henry in the Bishops pallace, </l>
          <l>And ten to one you'le meet him in the Tower. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e37490">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Tis euen so, and yet you are olde Warwike still. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e37530">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>O cheerefull colours, see where Oxford comes. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e37560">Enter Oxford with drum and souldiers &amp; al crie, </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e37580">
          <speaker>Oxf. </speaker>
          <l>Oxford, Oxford, for <hi>Lancaster. Exit. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e37620">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>The Gates are open, see they enter in, </l>
          <l>Lets follow them and bid them battaile in the streetes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e37660">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>No, so some other might set vpon our backes, </l>
          <l>Weele staie till all be entered, and then follow them. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e37700">Enter <hi>Summerset▪ </hi>with drum and souldiers. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e37720">
          <speaker>Sum. </speaker>
          <l>Summerset, Summerset for Lancaster. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e37760">Exit. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e37770">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>Two of thy name both Dukes of Summerset, </l>
          <l>Haue solde their liues vnto the house of <hi>Yorke, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And thou shalt be the third and my sword hold. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e37830">Enter Montague with drum and souldiers. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e37850">
          <speaker>Mont. </speaker>
          <l>
            <hi>Montague, Montague, </hi>for Lancaster. <hi>Exit. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e37900">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Traitorous <hi>Montague, </hi>thou and thy brother </l>
          <l>Shall deerelie abie this rebellious act. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e37950">Enter Clarence with drum and souldiers. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e37970">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>And loe where George of Clarence sweepes </l>
          <l>Along, of power enough to bid his brother battell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e38030">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>Clarence, Clarence, for <hi>Lancaster. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e38070">
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-035-b"/>
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Et tu Brute, wilt thou stab Caesar too? </l>
          <l>A parlie sirra to George of Clarence. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e38130">Sound a Parlie, and Richard and Clarence whispers togither, and then Clarence takes his red Rose out of his hat, and throwes it at <hi>Warwike. </hi>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e38170">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>C●m Clarence come, thou wilt if Warwike call. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e38210">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>Father of <hi>Warwike, </hi>know you what this meanes▪ </l>
          <l>● throw mine infamie at thee, </l>
          <l>I will not ruinate my fathers house, </l>
          <l>Who gaue his bloud to lime the stones togither, </l>
          <l>And set vp <hi>Lancaster. </hi>Thinkest thou </l>
          <l>That Clarence is so harsh vnnaturall, </l>
          <l>To lift his sword against his brothers life, </l>
          <l>And so proud harted Warwike I defie thee, </l>
          <l>And to my brothers turne my blushing cheekes? </l>
          <l>Pardon me <hi>Edward, </hi>for I haue done amisse, </l>
          <l>And Richard doe not frowne vpon me, </l>
          <l>For hence forth I will proue no more vnconstant. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e38420">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Welcome <hi>Clarence, </hi>and ten times more welcome, </l>
          <l>Then if thou neuer hadst deserud out hate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e38470">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>Welcome good <hi>Clarence, </hi>this is bretherlie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e38510">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Oh passing traytor, periurd and vniust. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e38540">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Now <hi>Warwike, </hi>wilt thou leaue </l>
          <l>The towne and fight? or shall we beate the </l>
          <l>Stones about thine eares? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e38600">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Why I am not coopt vppe heere for defence, </l>
          <l>I will awaie to Barnet presently, </l>
          <l>And bid thee battaile Edward it thou darest. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e38670">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Yes Warwike he dares, and leades the waie, </l>
          <l>Lords to the field, saint George and victorie. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e38730">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-036-a"/>
          <l>Alarmes, and then enter Warwike wounded. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e38760">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Ah, who is ●? Come to m● friend or foe, </l>
          <l>And tell me who is victor Yorke or <hi>Warwike? </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Why aske I that? my ma glad bodie shewes, </l>
          <l>That I must yeeld my bodie to the earth. </l>
          <l>And by my fall the conquest to my foes, </l>
          <l>Thus yeelds the Cedar to the axes edge. </l>
          <l>Whose armes giue shelter to the princelie eagle, </l>
          <l>Vnder whose 〈◊〉 ad● the ramping Lion slept, </l>
          <l>Whose top branch ouerpeerd Ioues sreading tree. </l>
          <l>The wrinkles in my browes now fild with bloud, </l>
          <l>Were likened oft to kinglie sepulchers. </l>
          <l>For who liu'd king, but I could dig his graue? </l>
          <l>And who durst smile, when Warwike bent his brow? </l>
          <l>Lo now my glorie smeerd in dust and bloud, </l>
          <l>My parkes my walkes, my mannors that I had, </l>
          <l>Euen now forsake me and of all my lands, </l>
          <l>Is nothing left me but my bodies length. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e39000">Enter Oxford and <hi>Summerset. </hi>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e39030">
          <speaker>Oxf. </speaker>
          <l>Ah <hi>Warwike, Warwike, </hi>cheere vp thy selfe and li●e, </l>
          <l>For yet thears hope enough to win the daie. </l>
          <l>Our warlike Queene with troopes is come from <hi>France, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And at South●h●mpton landed all hi● traine, </l>
          <l>And mightst thou l●ue then would we neuer flie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e39140">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>Which then I would not flie nor haue I now, </l>
          <l>But Hercules himselfe must yeeld to ods, </l>
          <l>For m●●e wounds receiu'd, and manie moe repaid, </l>
          <l>Hath robd my strong knit ●●news of their strength, </l>
          <l>And spite of sp●tes needes must I yeeld to death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e39220">
          <speaker>Sum. </speaker>
          <l>Thy brother Montague hath breathd his last, </l>
          <l>And at the pangs of death I heard him crie </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-036-b"/>
          <l>And saie, commend me to my valiant brother, </l>
          <l>And more he would haue spoke and 〈◊〉 he said, </l>
          <l>Which sounded like a 〈…〉 a vault, </l>
          <l>That could not be distinguisht for the sound, </l>
          <l>And so the valiant Montague gaue vp the ghost. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e39330">
          <speaker>War. </speaker>
          <l>What is pompe, rule, raigne, but earth and dust▪ </l>
          <l>And liue we how we can, yet the w● m●st. </l>
          <l>Sweet rest his soule, she Lords and 〈◊〉 your selues, </l>
          <l>For Warwike bids you all farewell to mee●●n Heauen. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e39400">He dies. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e39410">
          <speaker>Oxf▪ </speaker>
          <l>Come noble <hi>Summerset, </hi>lets take our horse, </l>
          <l>And cause retrait be sounded through the campe, </l>
          <l>That all our friends that yet remaine aliue▪, </l>
          <l>Maie be awarn'd and ●aue themselues by flight. </l>
          <l>That done, with them weele post vnto the <hi>Queene, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And once mo●eui● our fortune in the field </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e39510">Ex ambo. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e39520">Enter <hi>Edward Clarence, Gloster, </hi>with souldiers. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e39540">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Thus still our fortune 〈◊〉 vs victorie, </l>
          <l>And g●●ts our temples with triumphant ioies </l>
          <l>The bigboond traytor Warwike hath breathde his last, </l>
          <l>An I heauen this daie hath sm●●de vpon v●●all, </l>
          <l>But in this cleere and brightsome ●a●e, </l>
          <l>I see a blacke suspitious cloud appeare </l>
          <l>That will enc●unter with our glorious sunne </l>
          <l>Before he gaine his ●asefull w● ste●e be ●●es, </l>
          <l>I mean those powers which the Queen hath got in France </l>
          <l>Are landed, and meane once more to menace vs. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e39700">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>Oxford and Summerset are sled to hi●, </l>
          <l>And 〈◊〉 likelie if she haue time to breath, </l>
          <l>Her fact on will be full as strong as ours. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e39770">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>We are aduertisde by our louing friends, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-037-a"/>
          <l>That they doe hold their course towards <hi>Tow●burie. </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Th●ther will we 〈◊〉 for willingnes rids waie, </l>
          <l>And in euerie countie as we passe along, </l>
          <l>O●● str engthes shall be augmented. </l>
          <l>Come lets goe, for if we slacke this faire </l>
          <l>B●●ght Summers daie, sharpe winters </l>
          <l>Sho●ers will make our hope for haie. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e39880">Ex▪ Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e39890">Enter the <hi>Queene, Prince Edward Oxford </hi>and <hi>Summerset, </hi>with drum and souldiers. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e39920">
          <speaker>Quee. </speaker>
          <l>Welcome to <hi>England, </hi>my louing friends of <hi>France, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And welcome <hi>Summerset, </hi>and Oxford too. </l>
          <l>Once more haue we spread our sailes abroad, </l>
          <l>And though our tackling be almost consumde, </l>
          <l>And Warwike as our maine mast ouerthrowne, </l>
          <l>Yet warlike Lords raise you that sturdie post, </l>
          <l>That beares the sailes to bring vs vnto rest, </l>
          <l>And Ned and I as willing P●lots should </l>
          <l>For once with carefull mindes guide on the sterne, </l>
          <l>To beare vs through that dangerous gulfe </l>
          <l>That heretofore hath swallowed vp our friends. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e40120">
          <speaker>Prince. </speaker>
          <l>And if there be, as God forbid there should, </l>
          <l>Amongst vs a timorous or fearefull man, </l>
          <l>Let him depart before the battels ioine, </l>
          <l>●east he in time of need intise another, </l>
          <l>And so withdraw the souldiers harts from vs. </l>
          <l>I will not stand aloofe and bid you fight, </l>
          <l>But with my sword presse in the thickest thronges, </l>
          <l>And single Edward from his strongest guard, </l>
          <l>And hand to hand enforce him for to yeeld, </l>
          <l>Or leaue my bodie as witnesse of my thoughts. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e40250">
          <speaker>Oxf. </speaker>
          <l>Women and children of so high resolue, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-037-b"/>
          <l>And Warriors faint, why twere perpetuall </l>
          <l>Shame? Oh braue yong Prince, thy </l>
          <l>Noble grandfather doth liue againe in thee, </l>
          <l>Long maiest thou liue to beare his image, </l>
          <l>And to renew his glories. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e40330">
          <speaker>Sum. </speaker>
          <l>And he that turnes and flies when such do fight, </l>
          <l>Let him to bed, and like the Owle by daie </l>
          <l>Be hist, and wondered at if he arise. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e40380">Enter a Messenger. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e40390">
          <speaker>Mes. </speaker>
          <l>My Lords, Duke Edward with a mighty power, </l>
          <l>Is marching hitherwards to fight with you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e40440">
          <speaker>Oxf. </speaker>
          <l>I thought it was his pollicie, to take vs vnprouided, </l>
          <l>But here will we stand and fight it to the death. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e40480">Enter king <hi>Edward, Cla. Glo. Hast. </hi>and Souldiers. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e40500">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>See brothers, yonder stands the thornie wood, </l>
          <l>Which by Gods assistance and your prowesse, </l>
          <l>Shall with our swords yer night be cleane cut downe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e40550">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>Lords, Knights &amp; gentlemen, what I should say, </l>
          <l>My teares gainesaie, for as you see, I drinke </l>
          <l>The water of mine eies. Then no more </l>
          <l>But this. Henry your king is prisoner </l>
          <l>In the tower, his land and all our friends </l>
          <l>Are quite distrest, and yonder standes </l>
          <l>The Wolfe that makes all this, </l>
          <l>Then on Gods name Lords togither cry saint <hi>George. </hi>
          </l>
          <l>All Saint George for Lancaster. </l>
        </sp>
        <p>Alarmes to the battell, Yorke flies, then the chambers be discharged. Then enter the king▪ Cla &amp; Glo. &amp; the rest, &amp; make a great shout, and crie, for <hi>Yorke, </hi>for <hi>Yorke, </hi>and then the Queene is taken, &amp; the prince, &amp; Oxf. &amp; Sum. and then sound and enter all againe. </p>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e40810">
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-038-a"/>
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Lo here a period of tumultuous broiles, </l>
          <l>Awaie with Oxford to Hames castell straight, </l>
          <l>For Summerset off with his guiltie head. </l>
          <l>Awaie I will not heare them speake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e40890">
          <speaker>Oxf. </speaker>
          <l>For my part Ile not trouble thee with words. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e40920">Exit Oxford. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e40940">
          <speaker>Sum. </speaker>
          <l>Not <hi>I, </hi>but stoope with patience to my death. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e40980">Exit Sum. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e40990">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Now Edward what satisfaction canst thou make, </l>
          <l>●or stirring vp my subiects to rebellion? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e41040">
          <speaker>Prin. </speaker>
          <l>Speake like a subiect proud ambitious Yorke, </l>
          <l>Suppose that I am now my fathers mouth, </l>
          <l>Resigne thy chaire▪ and where I stand kneele thou, </l>
          <l>Whilst I propose the selfesame words to thee, </l>
          <l>Which traytor thou woudst haue me answere to. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e41130">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>Oh that thy father had bin so resolu●d▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e41160">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>That you might still haue kept your </l>
          <l>Peticote, and nere haue slolne the </l>
          <l>Breath from <hi>Lancaster. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e41220">
          <speaker>Prince. </speaker>
          <l>Let Aesop fable in a winters night. </l>
          <l>His cuttish Riddles sorts not with this place. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e41270">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>By heauen brat Ile plague you for that word. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e41300">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>I▪ thou wast borne to be a plague to men. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e41330">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>For Gods sake take a waie this captiue scold. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e41360">
          <speaker>Prin </speaker>
          <l>Nay take away this skolding Crooktbacke rather. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e41390">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Peace wilfull boy, or I will tame your tongue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e41430">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>Vntuterd lad thou art too malepert. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e41460">
          <speaker>Prin. </speaker>
          <l>I know my dutie, you are all vndutifull. </l>
          <l>Lasciuious <hi>Edward, </hi>and thou periurd <hi>George, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And thou mishapen Dicke, I tell you all, </l>
          <l>I am your better, traytors as you be. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e41550">
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-038-b"/>
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Take that, the litnes of this railer heere. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e41580">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>Oh kill me too. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e41610">
          <speaker>Glo </speaker>
          <l>Marrie and shall. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e41640">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Hold Richard hold, for we haue doone too much alreadie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e41680">
          <speaker>Glo </speaker>
          <l>Why should she liue to fill the world with words? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e41710">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>What doth she swound: make meanes for Her recouerie? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e41740">
          <speaker>Glo </speaker>
          <l>
            <hi>Clarence, </hi>excuse me to the king my brother, </l>
          <l>I must to London on a serious matter, </l>
          <l>Ere you come there▪ you shall heare more newes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e41810">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>About what, prethe tell me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e41840">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>The Towerman, the Tower, Ile root them out </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e41870">Exit Gloster. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e41880">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>Ah <hi>Ned, </hi>speake to thy mother boy? ah </l>
          <l>Thou canst not speake. </l>
          <l>Traytors, Tyrants, bloudie Homicides, </l>
          <l>They that stabd Caesar shed no bloud at all, </l>
          <l>For he was a man, this in respect a childe, </l>
          <l>And men nere spend then furie on a child, </l>
          <l>Whats worse then tyrant that I maie name, </l>
          <l>You haue no children Deuils, if you had, </l>
          <l>The thought of them would then haue stopt your rage, </l>
          <l>But if you euer hope to haue a sonne, </l>
          <l>Looke in his youth to haue him so cut off, </l>
          <l>As Traitors you haue doone this sweet young prince. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e42050">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Awaie, and beare her hence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e42080">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>Naie nere beare me hence, dispatch </l>
          <l>Me heere, heere sheath thy sword, </l>
          <l>Ile pardon thee my death. Wilt thou not? </l>
          <l>Then <hi>Clarence, </hi>doe thou doe it? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e42150">
          <speaker>Cla </speaker>
          <l>By Heauen I would not doe thee so much ease. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e42180">
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-039-a"/>
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>Good Clarence doe, sweet Clarence kill me too. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e42220">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>Didst thou not heare me sweare I would not do it? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e42260">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>I, but thou vsest to forsweare thy selfe, </l>
          <l>Twas sinne before, but now tis charitie. </l>
          <l>Whea●s the Diuels butcher, hardfauored <hi>Richard, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Richard where art thou? He is not heere, </l>
          <l>Murder is his almes deed, petitioners </l>
          <l>For bloud he nere put backe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e42350">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Awaie I saie, and take her hence perforce. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e42380">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>So come to you and yours, as to this prince. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e42410">Ex. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e42420">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>
            <hi>Clarence, </hi>whithers Gloster gone? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e42470">
          <speaker>Cla </speaker>
          <l>Marrie my Lord to London, and as I gesse, to </l>
          <l>Make a bloudie supper in the Tower. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e42510">
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>He is sudden if a thing come in his head. </l>
          <l>Well, discharge the common souldiers with paie </l>
          <l>And thankes, and now let vs towards London, </l>
          <l>To see our gentle Queene how shee doth fare, </l>
          <l>For by this I hope shee hath a sonne for vs. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e42590">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="ep000851-e42600">Enter Gloster to king Henry in the Tower. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e42630">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>Good day my Lord. What at your booke so hard? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e42660">
          <speaker>Hen. </speaker>
          <l>I my good Lord. Lord I should saie rather, </l>
          <l>Tis sinne to flatter, good was little better, </l>
          <l>Good <hi>Gloster, </hi>and good Diuell, were all alike, </l>
          <l>What scene of Death hath Rosius now to act? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e42750">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>Suspition alwaies haunts a guiltie mind. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e42780">
          <speaker>Hen. </speaker>
          <l>The birde once limde doth feare the fatall bush, </l>
          <l>And I the haplesse maile to one poore birde, </l>
          <l>Haue now the fatall obiect in mine eie, </l>
          <l>Where my poore young was limde, was caught &amp; kild. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e42840">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>Why, what a foole was that of Cree●e? </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-039-b"/>
          <l>That taught his sonne the office </l>
          <l>Of a birde, and yet for all that the poore </l>
          <l>Fowle was drownde. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e42900">
          <speaker>Hen. </speaker>
          <l>
            <hi>I Dedalus, </hi>my poore sonne <hi>Icarus, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Thy father Minos that denide our course, </l>
          <l>Thy brother <hi>Edward, </hi>the sunne that ●earde his wings, </l>
          <l>And thou the enuious gulfe that swallowed him. </l>
          <l>Oh better can my brest abide thy daggers point, </l>
          <l>Then can mine cares that tragike historie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e43020">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>Why dost thou thinke I am an executioner? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e43060">
          <speaker>Hen. </speaker>
          <l>A persecutor I am sure thou art, </l>
          <l>And if murdering innocents be executions, </l>
          <l>Then I know thou art an executioner. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e43110">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>Thy sonne I kild for his presumption. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e43140">
          <speaker>Hen. </speaker>
          <l>Hadst thou bin kild when first thou didst presume, </l>
          <l>Thou hadst not liude to kill a sonne of mine, </l>
          <l>And thus I prophesie of theo. </l>
          <l>That manie a Widdow for her husbands death, </l>
          <l>And many an infants water standing eie, </l>
          <l>Widowes for their husbands, children for their fathers, </l>
          <l>Shall curse the time that euer thou wert borne. </l>
          <l>The owle s●●ikt at thy birth, an euill signe, </l>
          <l>The night Crow cride, aboding lucklesse tune, </l>
          <l>Dogs howld and hideous tempests shooke down trees, </l>
          <l>The Rauen rookt her on the Chimnies top, </l>
          <l>And chattering Pi●s in dismall discord sung, </l>
          <l>Thy mother felt more then a mothers paine, </l>
          <l>And yet brought ●orth lesse then a mothers hope, </l>
          <l>To wit▪ an vndigest created lumpe. </l>
          <l>Not like the fruit of such a goodly tree, </l>
          <l>Teeth hadst thou in thy head when thou wast borne, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-040-a"/>
          <l>Thus haue we swept suspition from our seat, </l>
          <l>And made our footstoole of securitie. </l>
          <l>Come hither <hi>Besse, </hi>and let me kisse my boie, </l>
          <l>Young <hi>Ned, </hi>for thee, thine Vncles and my selfe, </l>
          <l>Haue in our armors watcht the Winters night, </l>
          <l>Marcht all a foote in summers skalding heat, </l>
          <l>That thou mightst repossesse the crowne in peace, </l>
          <l>And of out labours thou shalt reape the gaine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e43440">
          <speaker>Glo. </speaker>
          <l>Ile blast his haruest and your head were laid, </l>
          <l>For yet I am not lookt on in the world. </l>
          <l>This shoulder was ordaind so thicke to heaue, </l>
          <l>And heaue it shall some waight or breake my backe, </l>
          <l>Worke thou the waie, and thou shalt execute. </l>
          <l>
            <hi>Edward, Clarence </hi>and <hi>Gloster, </hi>loue my louelie Queene, </l>
          <l>And kisse your princely nephew brothers both. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e43550">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>The dutie that I owe vnto your, Maiestie, </l>
          <l>I seale vpon the rosiate lips of this sweet babe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e43600">
          <speaker>Queen. </speaker>
          <l>Thankes noble Clarence worthie brother thankes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e43640">
          <speaker>Gloster. </speaker>
          <l>And that I loue the fruit from whence thou </l>
          <l>Sprangst, witnesse the louing kisse I giue the child. </l>
          <l>To saie the truth so Iudas kist his maister, </l>
          <l>And so he cride all haile▪ and meant all ha●●e. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e43710">
          <speaker>Edward. </speaker>
          <l>Nowe am I seated as my soule delights, </l>
          <l>Hauing my countries peace, and brothers loues. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e43760">
          <speaker>Cla. </speaker>
          <l>What will your grace haue done with <hi>Margaret▪ </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Ranard her father to the king of <hi>France, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>Hath pawnd the Cyssels and <hi>Ierusalem, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And hither haue they sent it for her ransome. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000851-e43870">
          <pb xml:id="ep000851-040-b"/>
          <speaker>Edw. </speaker>
          <l>Awaie with her, and wa●te hir hence to <hi>France, </hi>
          </l>
          <l>And now what rests but that we spend the time, </l>
          <l>With stately Triumphs and mirthfull comick● shewes, </l>
          <l>Such as befits the pleasures of the Court. </l>
          <l>Sound drums and Trumpets, farewell to sower annoy, </l>
          <l>For heere I hope begins our lasting ioie. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000851-e43970">Exeunt Omnes. </stage>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
