<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000838" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The most excellent historie of the merchant of Venice VVith the extreame crueltie of Shylocke the Iewe towards the sayd merchant, in cutting a iust pound of his flesh: and the obtayning of Portia by the choyse of three chests. As it hath beene diuers times acted by the Lord Chamberlaine his Seruants. Written by William Shakespeare.</title>
        <title>Merchant of Venice</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>William</forename>
            <surname>Shakespeare</surname>
          </persName>
          <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q692</idno>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A68727.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <p>
            This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is available for reuse, according to the terms of
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>
            . The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
          </p>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull>
              <titleStmt>
                <title>The most excellent historie of the merchant of Venice VVith the extreame crueltie of Shylocke the Iewe towards the sayd merchant, in cutting a iust pound of his flesh: and the obtayning of Portia by the choyse of three chests. As it hath beene diuers times acted by the Lord Chamberlaine his Seruants. Written by William Shakespeare.</title>
                <title>Merchant of Venice</title>
                <author>Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[76] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Printed by I[ames] R[oberts] for Thomas Heyes, and are to be sold in Paules Church-yard, at the signe of the Greene Dragon,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                <date>1600.</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>Mostly in verse.</note>
                <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                <note>Signatures: A-I⁴ K² .</note>
                <note>Running title reads: The comicall historie of the merchant of Venice.</note>
                <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                <note>Appears at reel 340 (Huntington copy 59956) and at reel 538 (copy 59553).</note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc/>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000838-e10">
        <pb xml:id="ep000838-001-a"/>
        <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000838-001-b"/>
        <p>The most excellent Historie of the <hi>Merchant of Venice</hi>. </p>
        <p>With the extreame crueltie of Shylocke the Iewe towards the sayd Merchant, in cutting a iust pound of his flesh: and the obtayning of Portia by the choyse of three chests. </p>
        <p>As it hath beene diuers times acted by the Lord Chamberlaine his Seruants. </p>
        <p>Written by William Shakespeare. </p>
        <p>AT LONDON, Printed by <hi>I. R. </hi>for Thomas Heyes, and are to be sold in Paules Church-yard, at the signe of the Greene Dragon. 1600. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="play" xml:id="ep000838-e120">
        <pb xml:id="ep000838-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000838-002-b"/>
        <head>The comicall History of the Merchant of Venice. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e140">Enter Anthonio, Salaryno, and Salanio. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e170">
          <speaker>An. </speaker>
          <l>IN sooth I know not why I am so sad, </l>
          <l>It wearies me, you say it wearies you; </l>
          <l>But how I caught it, found it, or came by it, </l>
          <l>What stuffe tis made of, whereof it is borne, </l>
          <l>I am to learne: and such a want-wit sadnes makes of mee, </l>
          <l>That I haue much adoe to know my selfe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e250">
          <speaker>Salarino. </speaker>
          <l>Your minde is tossing on the Ocean, </l>
          <l>There where your Argosies with portlie sayle </l>
          <l>Like Signiors and rich Burgars on the flood, </l>
          <l>Or as it were the Pageants of the sea, </l>
          <l>Doc ouer-peere the petty traffiquers </l>
          <l>That cursie to them do them reuerence </l>
          <l>As they flie by them with theyr wouen wings. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e340">
          <speaker>Salanio. </speaker>
          <l>Beleeue mee sir, had I such venture forth, </l>
          <l>The better part of my affections would </l>
          <l>Be with my hopes abroade. I should be still </l>
          <l>Plucking the grasse to know where sits the wind, </l>
          <l>Piring in Maps for ports, and peers and rodes: </l>
          <l>And euery obiect that might make me feare </l>
          <l>Mis-fortune to my ventures, out of doubt </l>
          <l>Would make me sad. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e440">
          <speaker>Salar. </speaker>
          <l>My wind cooling my broth, </l>
          <l>Would blow me to an ague when I thought </l>
          <l>What harme a winde too great might doe at sea. </l>
          <l>I should not see the sandie howre-glasse runne </l>
          <l>But I should thinke of shallowes and of flatts, </l>
          <l>And see my wealthy Andrew docks in sand </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-003-a"/>
          <l>For saying nothing; when I am very sure </l>
          <l>If they should speake, would almost dam those eares </l>
          <l>which hearing them would call their brothers fooles, </l>
          <l>Ile tell thee more of this another time. </l>
          <l>But fish not with this melancholy baite </l>
          <l>For this foole gudgin, this opinion: </l>
          <l>Come good Lorenso, faryewell a while, </l>
          <l>Ile end my exhortation after dinner. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e620">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>Well, we will leaue you then till dinner time. </l>
          <l>I must be one of these same dumbe wise men, </l>
          <l>For Gratiano neuer lets me speake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e680">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>Well keepe me company but two yeeres moe </l>
          <l>Thou shalt not know the sound of thine owne tongue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e720">
          <speaker>An. </speaker>
          <l>Far you well, Ile grow a talker for this geare. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e750">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>Thanks yfaith, for silence is onely commendable </l>
          <l>In a neates togue dried, and a mayde not vendable. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e790">Exeunt. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e800">
          <speaker>An. </speaker>
          <l>It is that any thing now. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e830">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <p>Gratiano speakes an infinite deale of nothing more then any man in all Venice; his reasons are as two graines of wheate hid in two bushels of chaffe: you shall seeke all day ere you finde them, and when you haue them, they are not worth the search. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e870">
          <speaker>An. </speaker>
          <l>Well, tell me now what Lady is the same </l>
          <l>To whom you swore a secrete pilgrimage </l>
          <l>That you to day promisd to tell me of. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e920">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Tis not vnknowne to you Anthonio </l>
          <l>How much I haue disabled mine estate, </l>
          <l>By something showing a more swelling port </l>
          <l>Then my faint meanes would graunt continuance: </l>
          <l>Nor doe I now make mone to be abridg'd </l>
          <l>From such a noble rate, but my cheefe care </l>
          <l>Is to come fairely of from the great debts </l>
          <l>wherein my time something too prodigall </l>
          <l>Hath left me gagd: to you Anthonio </l>
          <l>I owe the most in money and in loue, </l>
          <l>And from your loue I haue a warrantie </l>
          <l>To vnburthen all my plots and purposes </l>
          <l>How to get cleere of all the debts I owe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e1090">
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-003-b"/>
          <speaker>An. </speaker>
          <l>I pray you good Bassanio let me know it, </l>
          <l>And if it stand as you your selfe still doe, </l>
          <l>within the eye of honour, be assurd </l>
          <l>My purse, my person, my extreamest meanes </l>
          <l>Lie all vnlockt to your occasions. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e1170">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>In my schoole dayes, when I had lost one shaft, </l>
          <l>I shot his fellow of the selfe same flight </l>
          <l>The selfe same way, with more aduised watch </l>
          <l>To finde the other forth, and by aduenturing both, </l>
          <l>I oft found both: I vrge this child-hood proofe </l>
          <l>Because what followes is pure innocence. </l>
          <l>I owe you much, and like a wilfull youth </l>
          <l>That which I owe is lost, but if you please </l>
          <l>To shoote another arrow that selfe way </l>
          <l>which you did shoote the first, I doe not doubt, </l>
          <l>As I will watch the ayme or to find both, </l>
          <l>Or bring your latter hazzard bake againe, </l>
          <l>And thankfully rest debter for the first. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e1320">
          <speaker>An. </speaker>
          <l>You know me well, and heerein spend but time </l>
          <l>To wind about my loue with circumstance, </l>
          <l>And out of doubt you doe me now more wrong </l>
          <l>In making question of my vttermost </l>
          <l>Then if you had made wast of all I haue: </l>
          <l>Then doe but say to me what I should doe </l>
          <l>That in your knowledge may by me be done, </l>
          <l>And I am prest vnto it: therefore speake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e1420">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>In Belmont is a Lady richly left, </l>
          <l>And she is faire, and fairer then that word, </l>
          <l>Of wondrous vertues, sometimes from her eyes </l>
          <l>I did receaue faire speechlesse messages: </l>
          <l>Her name is Portia, nothing vndervallewd </l>
          <l>To Catos daughter, <hi>Brutus Portia</hi>, </l>
          <l>Nor is the wide world ignorant of her worth, </l>
          <l>For the foure winds blow in from euery coast </l>
          <l>Renowned sutors, and her sunny locks </l>
          <l>Hang on her temples like a golden fleece, </l>
          <l>which makes her seat of <hi>Belmont Cholchos </hi>strond, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-004-a"/>
          <l>And many Iasons come in quest of her. </l>
          <l>O my Anthonio, had I but the meanes </l>
          <l>To hold a riuall place with one of them, </l>
          <l>I haue a minde presages me such thrift </l>
          <l>That I should questionlesse be fortunate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e1670">
          <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
          <l>Thou knowst that all my fortunes are at sea, </l>
          <l>Neither haue I money, nor commoditie </l>
          <l>To raise a present summe, therefore goe forth </l>
          <l>Try what my credite can in Venice doe, </l>
          <l>That shall be rackt euen to the vttermost </l>
          <l>To furnish thee to Belmont to faire Portia. </l>
          <l>Goe presently enquire and so will I </l>
          <l>where money is, and I no question make </l>
          <l>To haue it of my trust, or for my sake. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e1800">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e1810">Enter Portia with her wayting woman Nerrissa. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e1840">
          <speaker>Portia. </speaker>
          <p>By my troth Nerrissa, my little body is awearie of this great world. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e1880">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <p>You would be sweet Madam, if your miseries were in the same aboundance as your good fortunes are: and yet for ought I see, they are as sicke that surfeite with too much, as they that starue with nothing; it is no meane happines therfore to be seated in the meane, superfluitie comes sooner by white haires, but competencie liues longer. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e1910">
          <speaker>Portia. </speaker>
          <p>Good sentences, and well pronounc'd. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e1940">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <p>They would be better if well followed. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e1970">
          <speaker>Portia. </speaker>
          <p>If to do were as easie as to know what were good to do, Chappels had beene Churches, and poore mens cottages Princes Pallaces, it is a good diuine that followes his owne instructions, I can easier teach twentie what were good to be done, then to be one of the twentie to follow mine owne teaching: the braine may deuise lawes for the blood, but a hote temper leapes ore a colde decree, such a hare is madnes the youth, to skippe ore the meshes of good counsaile the cripple; but this reasoning is not in the fashion to choose mee a husband, ô mee the word choose, I may neyther choose who I would, nor refuse who I dislike, so is the will of a lyuing daughter curbd by the will of a deade father: is it not harde <pb xml:id="ep000838-004-b"/>Nerrissa, that I cannot choose one, nor refuse none. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2010">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <p>Your Father was euer vertuous, and holy men at theyr death haue good inspirations, therefore the lottrie that he hath deuised in these three chests of gold, siluer, and leade, whereof who chooses his meaning chooses you, will no doubt neuer be chosen by any rightlie, but one who you shall rightly loue: But what warmth is there in your affection towardes any of these Princelie suters that are already come? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2040">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <p>I pray thee ouer-name them, and as thou namest them, I will describe them, and according to my description leuell at my affection. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2070">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <p>First there is the Neopolitane Prince. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2100">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <p>I thats a colt indeede, for he doth nothing but talke of his horse, &amp; he makes it a great appropriation to his owne good parts that he can shoo him himselfe: I am much afeard my Ladie his mother plaid false with a Smyth. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2130">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <p>Than is there the Countie Palentine. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2160">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <p>Hee doth nothing but frowne (as who should say, &amp; you will not haue me, choose, he heares merry tales and smiles not, I feare hee will prooue the weeping Phylosopher when hee growes old, beeing so full of vnmannerly sadnes in his youth,) I had rather be married to a deaths head with a bone in his mouth, then to eyther of these: God defend me from these two. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2190">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <p>How say you by the French Lord, Mounsier <hi>Le Boune</hi>? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2230">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <p>God made him, and therefore let him passe for a man, in truth I knowe it is a sinne to be a mocker, but hee, why hee hath a horse better then the Neopolitans, a better bad habite of frowning then the Count Palentine, he is euery man in no man, if a Trassell sing, he falls straght a capring, he will fence with his owne shadow. If I should marry him, I should marry twenty husbands: if hee would despise me, I would forgiue him, for if he loue me to madnes, I shall neuer requite him. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2280">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <p>What say you then to Fauconbridge, the young Barron of England? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2310">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <p>You know I say nothing to him, for hee vnderstands not me, nor I him: he hath neither Latine, French, nor Italian, &amp; you will come into the Court and sweare that I haue a poore pennie-worth <pb xml:id="ep000838-005-a"/>in the English: hee is a proper mans picture, but alas who can conuerse with a dumbe show? how odly hee is suted, I thinke he bought his doublet in Italie, his round hose in Fraunce, his bonnet in Germanie, and his behauiour euery where. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2380">
          <speaker>Nerrissa </speaker>
          <p>What thinke you of the Scottish Lorde his neighbour: </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2410">
          <speaker>Portia. </speaker>
          <p>That hee hath a neyghbourlie charitie in him, for hee borrowed a boxe of the eare of the Englishman, and swore hee would pay him againe when he was able: I think the Frenchman became his suretie, and seald vnder for another. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2450">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <p>How like you the young Germaine, the Duke of Saxonies nephew? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2480">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <p>Very vildlie in the morning when hee is sober, and most vildly in the afternoone when he is drunke: when he is best, he is a little worse then a man, &amp; when he is worst he is little better then a beast, and the worst fall that euer fell, I hope I shall make shift to goe without him. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2510">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <p>Yf hee shoulde offer to choose, and choose the right Casket, you should refuse to performe your Fathers will, if you should refuse to accept him. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2540">
          <speaker>Portia. </speaker>
          <p>Therefore for feare of the worst, I pray thee set a deepe glasse of Reynishe wine on the contrarie Casket, for if the deuill be within, and that temptation without, I knowe hee will choose it. I will doe any thing Nerrissa ere I will be married to a spunge. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2600">
          <speaker>Nerrissa. </speaker>
          <p>You neede not feare Ladie the hauing anie of these Lords, they haue acquainted me with theyr determinations, which is indeede to returne to theyr home, and to trouble you with no more sute, vnlesse you may be wonne by some other sort than your Fathers imposition, depending on the Caskets. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2630">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <p>Yf I liue to be as old as Sibilla, I will die as chast as Diana, vnlesse I be obtained by the maner of my Fathers will: I am glad this parcell of wooers are so reasonable, for there is not one among them but I doate on his very absence: &amp; I pray God graunt them a faire departure. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2690">
          <speaker>Nerrissa </speaker>
          <p>Doc you not remember Lady in your Fathers time, a Venecian a Scholler &amp; a Souldiour that came hether in companie of the Marquesse of Mountferrat? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2720">
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-005-b"/>
          <speaker>Portia. </speaker>
          <p>Yes, yes, it was Bassanio, as I thinke so was he calld. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2760">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <p>True maddam, hee of all the men that euer my foolish eyes look'd vpon, was the best deseruing a faire Ladie. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2790">
          <speaker>Portia. </speaker>
          <p>I remember him well, and I remember him worthie of thy prayse. </p>
          <p>How nowe, what newes? </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e2850">Enter a Seruingman. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2860">
          <speaker>Ser. </speaker>
          <p>The foure strangers seeke for you maddam to take theyr leaue: and there is a fore-runner come from a fift, the Prince of Moroco, who brings word the Prince his Maister will be heere to night. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e2900">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <p>Yf I could bid the fift welcome with so good hart as I can bid the other foure farewell, I should bee glad of his approch: if he haue the condition of a Saint, and the complexion of a deuill, I had rather he should shriue mee then wiue mee. Come Nerrissa, sirra goe before: whiles we shut the gate vpon one wooer, another knocks at the doore. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e2970">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e2980">Enter Bassanio with Shylocke the Iew. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e3010">
          <speaker>Shy </speaker>
          <p>Three thousand ducates, well. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e3040">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <p>I sir, for three months. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e3080">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <p>For three months, well. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e3110">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <p>For the which as I told you, Anthonio shalbe bound. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e3150">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <p>Anthonio shall become bound, well. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e3190">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <p>May you sted me? Will you pleasure me? Shall I know your aunswere. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e3230">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <p>Three thousand ducats for three months, and Anthonio bound. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e3270">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <p>Your aunswere to that. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e3300">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <p>Anthonio is a good man. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e3340">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <p>Haue you heard any imputation to the contrary. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e3370">
          <speaker>Shylocke. </speaker>
          <p>Ho no, no, no, no: my meaning in saying hee is a good man, is to haue you vnderstand mee that hee is sufficient, yet his meanes are in supposition: hee hath an Argosie bound to Tripolis, another to the Indies, I vnderstand moreouer vpon the Ryalta, ●ee hath a third at Mexico, a fourth for England, <pb xml:id="ep000838-006-a"/>and other ventures he hath squandred abroade, but ships are but boordes, Saylers but men, there be land rats, and water rats, water theeues, and land theeues, I meane Pyrats, and then there is the perrill of waters; windes, and rockes: the man is notwithstanding sufficient, three thousand ducats, I thinke I may take his bond. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e3430">
          <speaker>Bas. </speaker>
          <p>Be assurd you may. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e3460">
          <speaker>Iew. </speaker>
          <p>I will be assurd I may: and that I may bee assured, I will bethinke mee, may I speake with Anthonio? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e3550">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <p>Yf it please you to dine with vs. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e3580">
          <speaker>Iew. </speaker>
          <p>Yes, to smell porke, to eate of the habitation which your Prophet the Nazarit coniured the deuill into: I wil buy with you, sell with you, talke with you, walke with you, and so following: but I will not eate with you, drinke with you, nor pray with you. What newes on the Ryalto, who is he comes heere? </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e3630">Enter Anthonio. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e3650">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>This is signior Anthonio. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e3690">
          <speaker>Jew. </speaker>
          <l>How like a fawning publican he lookes. </l>
          <l>I hate him for he is a Christian: </l>
          <l>But more, for that in low simplicitie </l>
          <l>He lends out money gratis, and brings downe </l>
          <l>The rate of vsance heere with vs in Venice. </l>
          <l>Yf I can catch him once vpon the hip, </l>
          <l>I will feede fat the auncient grudge I beare him. </l>
          <l>He hates our sacred Nation, and he rayles </l>
          <l>Euen there where Merchants most doe congregate </l>
          <l>On me, my bargaines, and my well-wone thrift, </l>
          <l>which hee calls interrest: Cursed be my Trybe </l>
          <l>if I forgiue him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e3880">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Shyloch, doe you heare. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e3920">
          <speaker>Shyl. </speaker>
          <l>I am debating of my present store, </l>
          <l>And by the neere gesse of my memorie </l>
          <l>I cannot instantly raise vp the grosse </l>
          <l>Of full three thousand ducats: what of that, </l>
          <l>Tuball a wealthy Hebrew of my Tribe </l>
          <l>Will furnish me; but soft, how many months </l>
          <l>Doe you desire? Rest you faire good signior, </l>
          <l>Your worship was the last man in our mouthes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e4050">
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-006-b"/>
          <speaker>An. </speaker>
          <l>Shylocke, albeit I neither lend nor borrow </l>
          <l>By taking nor by giuing of excesse, </l>
          <l>Yet to supply the ripe wants of my friend, </l>
          <l>Ile breake a custome: is hee yet possest </l>
          <l>How much ye would? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e4140">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <l>
            <hi>I, I</hi>, three thousand ducats. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e4180">
          <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
          <l>And for three months. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e4210">
          <speaker>Shyl. </speaker>
          <l>I had forgot, three months, you told me so. </l>
          <l>Well then, your bond: and let me see, but heare you, </l>
          <l>Me thoughts you said, you neither lend nor borrow </l>
          <l>Vpon aduantage. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e4280">
          <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
          <l>I doe neuer vse it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e4320">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <l>When Iacob grazd his Vncle Labans Sheepe, </l>
          <l>This Iacob from our holy Abram was </l>
          <l>(As his wise mother wrought in his behalfe) </l>
          <l>The third possesser; I, he was the third. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e4430">
          <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
          <l>And what of him, did he take interrest? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e4460">
          <speaker>Shyl. </speaker>
          <l>No, not take interest, not as you would say </l>
          <l>Directly intrest, marke what Iacob did, </l>
          <l>When Laban and himselfe were compremyzd </l>
          <l>That all the canelings which were streakt and pied </l>
          <l>Should fall as Iacobs hier, the Ewes being ranck </l>
          <l>In end of Autume turned to the Rammes, </l>
          <l>And when the worke of generation was </l>
          <l>Betweene these wolly breeders in the act, </l>
          <l>The skilful sheepheard pyld me certaine wands, </l>
          <l>And in the dooing of the deede of kind </l>
          <l>He stuck them vp before the fulsome Ewes, </l>
          <l>Who then conceauing, did in eaning time </l>
          <l>Fall party-colourd lambs, and those were Iacobs. </l>
          <l>This was a way to thriue, and he was blest: </l>
          <l>And thrift is blessing if men steale it not. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e4670">
          <speaker>An. </speaker>
          <l>This was a venture sir that Jacob serud for, </l>
          <l>A thing not in his power to bring to passe, </l>
          <l>But swayd and fashiond by the hand of heauen. </l>
          <l>Was this inserted to make interrest good? </l>
          <l>Or is your gold and siluer ewes and rammes? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e4750">
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-007-a"/>
          <speaker>Shyl. </speaker>
          <p>I cannot tell, I make it breede at fast, but note me signior. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e4780">
          <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
          <l>Marke you this Bassanio, </l>
          <l>The deuill can cite Scripture for his purpose, </l>
          <l>An euill soule producing holy witnes </l>
          <l>Is like a villaine with a smiling cheeke, </l>
          <l>A goodly apple rotten at the hart. </l>
          <l>O what a goodly out-side falshood hath. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e4870">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <l>Three thousand ducats, tis a good round summe. </l>
          <l>Three months from twelue, then let me see the rate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e4910">
          <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
          <l>Well Shylocke, shall we be beholding to you? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e4950">
          <speaker>Shyl. </speaker>
          <l>Signior Anthonio, manie a time and oft </l>
          <l>In the Ryalto you haue rated me </l>
          <l>About my moneyes and my vsances: </l>
          <l>Still haue I borne it with a patient shrug, </l>
          <l>(For suffrance is the badge of all our Trybe) </l>
          <l>You call me misbeleeuer, cut-throate dog, </l>
          <l>And spet vpon my Iewish gaberdine, </l>
          <l>And all for vse of that which is mine owne. </l>
          <l>Well then, it now appeares you neede my helpe: </l>
          <l>Goe to then, you come to me, and you say, </l>
          <l>Shylocke, we would haue moneyes▪ you say so: </l>
          <l>You that did voyde your ruine vpon my beard, </l>
          <l>And soote me as you spurne a stranger curre </l>
          <l>Ouer your threshold, moneyes is your sute. </l>
          <l>What should I say to you? Should I not say </l>
          <l>Hath a dog money? is it possible </l>
          <l>A curre can lend three thousand ducats? or </l>
          <l>Shall I bend low, and in a bond-mans key </l>
          <l>With bated breath, and whispring humblenes </l>
          <l>Say this: Faire sir, you spet on me on Wednesday last, </l>
          <l>You spurnd me such a day another time, </l>
          <l>You calld me dogge: and for these curtesies </l>
          <l>Ile lend you thus much moneyes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e5220">
          <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
          <l>I am as like to call thee so againe, </l>
          <l>To spet on thee againe, to spurne thee to. </l>
          <l>Yf thou wilt lend this money, lend it not </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-007-b"/>
          <l>As to thy friends, for when did friendship take </l>
          <l>A breede for barraine mettaile of his friend? </l>
          <l>But lend it rather to thine enemie, </l>
          <l>Who if he breake, thou maist with better face </l>
          <l>Exact the penaltie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e5330">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <l>Why looke you how you storme, </l>
          <l>I would be friends with you, and haue your loue, </l>
          <l>Forget the shames that you haue staind me with, </l>
          <l>Supply your present wants, and take no doyte </l>
          <l>Of vsance for my moneyes, and youle not heare mee, this is kinde I offer. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e5400">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>This were kindnesse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e5430">
          <speaker>Shyl. </speaker>
          <p>This kindnesse will I showe, Goe with me to a Notarie, seale me there Your single bond, and in a merrie sport if you repay me not on such a day in such a place, such summe or summes as are exprest in the condition, let the forfaite be nominated for an equall pound of your faire flesh, to be cut off and taken in what part of your bodie pleaseth me. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e5460">
          <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
          <p>Content infaith, Ile seale to such a bond, and say there is much kindnes in the Iew. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e5490">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <p>You shall not seale to such a bond for me, ●e rather dwell in my, necessitie. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e5520">
          <speaker>An. </speaker>
          <p>Why feare not man, I will not forfaite it, within these two months, thats a month before this bond expires, I doe expect returne of thrice three times the valew of this bond. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e5550">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <p>O father Abram, what these Christians are, Whose owne hard dealings teaches them suspect the thoughts of others: Pray you tell me this, if he should breake his day what should I gaine by the exaction of the forfeyture? A pound of mans flesh taken from a man, is not so estimable, profitable neither as flesh of Muttons, Beefes, or Goates, I say <pb xml:id="ep000838-008-a"/>To buy his fauour, I extend this friendship, Yf he wil take it, so, if not adiew, And for my loue I pray you wrong me not. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e5580">
          <speaker>An. </speaker>
          <p>Yes Shylocke, I will seale vnto this bond. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e5620">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <l>Then meete me forthwith at the Noteries, </l>
          <l>Giue him direction for this merry bond </l>
          <l>And I will goe and purse the ducats straite, </l>
          <l>See to my house left in the fearefull gard </l>
          <l>Of an vnthriftie knaue: and presently </l>
          <l>Ile be with you. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e5700">Exit. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e5710">
          <speaker>An. </speaker>
          <l>Hie thee gentle Iewe. The Hebrew will turne </l>
          <l>Christian, he growes kinde. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e5750">
          <speaker>Bassa. </speaker>
          <l>I like not faire termes, and a villaines minde. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e5780">
          <speaker>An. </speaker>
          <l>Come on, in this there can be no dismay, </l>
          <l>My ships come home a month before the day. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e5820">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e5830">Enter Morochus a tawnie Moore all in white, and three or foure followers accordingly, with <hi>Portia, Nerrissa</hi>, and their traine. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e5860">
          <speaker>Morocho. </speaker>
          <l>Mislike me not for my complexion, </l>
          <l>The shadowed liuerie of the burnisht sunne, </l>
          <l>To whom I am a neighbour, and neere bred. </l>
          <l>Bring me the favrest creature North-ward borne, </l>
          <l>Where Phaebus sire scarce thawes the ysicles, </l>
          <l>And let vs make incyzion for your loue, </l>
          <l>To proue whose blood is reddest, his or mine. </l>
          <l>I tell thee Lady this aspect of mine </l>
          <l>Hath feard the valiant, (by my loue I sweare) </l>
          <l>The best regarded Virgins of our Clyme </l>
          <l>Haue lou'd it to: I would not change this hue, </l>
          <l>Except to steale your thoughts my gentle Queene. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e6010">
          <speaker>Portia. </speaker>
          <l>In termes of choyse I am not soly led </l>
          <l>By nice direction of a maydens eyes: </l>
          <l>Besides, the lottrie of my destenie </l>
          <l>Barrs me the right of voluntary choosing: </l>
          <l>But if my Father had not scanted me, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-008-b"/>
          <l>And hedgd me by his wit to yeeld my selfe </l>
          <l>His wife, who winnes me by that meanes I told you, </l>
          <l>Your selfe (renowned Prince) than stoode as faire </l>
          <l>As any commer I haue look'd on yet </l>
          <l>For my affection. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e6130">
          <speaker>Mor. </speaker>
          <l>Euen for that I thanke you, </l>
          <l>Therefore I pray you leade me to the Caskets </l>
          <l>To try my fortune: By this Symitare </l>
          <l>That slewe the Sophy, and a Persian Prince </l>
          <l>That wone three fields of Sultan Solyman, </l>
          <l>I would ore-stare the sternest eyes that looke: </l>
          <l>Out-braue the hart most daring on the earth: </l>
          <l>Pluck the young sucking Cubs from the she Beare, </l>
          <l>Yea, mock the Lyon when a rores for pray </l>
          <l>To win the Lady. But alas, the while </l>
          <l>If Hercules and Lychas play at dice </l>
          <l>Which is the better man, the greater throw </l>
          <l>May turne by fortune from the weaker hand: </l>
          <l>So is Alcides beaten by his rage, </l>
          <l>And so may I, blind Fortune leading me </l>
          <l>Misse that which one vnworthier may attaine, </l>
          <l>And die with greeuing. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e6350">
          <speaker>Portia. </speaker>
          <l>You must take your chaunce, </l>
          <l>And eyther not attempt to choose at all, </l>
          <l>Or sweare before you choose, if you choose wrong </l>
          <l>Neuer to speake to Lady afterward </l>
          <l>In way of marriage, therefore be aduis'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e6420">
          <speaker>Mor. </speaker>
          <l>Nor will not, come bring me vnto my chaunce. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e6450">
          <speaker>Portia. </speaker>
          <l>First forward to the temple, after dinner </l>
          <l>Your hazard shall be made. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e6490">
          <speaker>Mor. </speaker>
          <l>Good fortune then, </l>
          <l>To make me blest or cursed'st among men. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e6530">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e6540">Enter the Clowne alone. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e6550">
          <speaker>Clowne. </speaker>
          <p>Certainely, my conscience will serue me to runne from this Iewe my Maister: the fiend is at mine elbow, and tempts me, saying to me, <hi>Iobbe, Launcelet Jobbe</hi>, good Launcelet, or good Iobbe, <pb xml:id="ep000838-009-a"/>or good <hi>Launcelet Iobbe</hi>, vse your legges, take the start, runne away, my conscience sayes no; take heede honest Launcelet, take heede honest Iobbe, or as afore-saide honest <hi>Launcelet Iobbe</hi>, doe not runne, scorne running with thy heeles; well, the most coragious fiend bids me packe, sia sayes the fiend, away sayes the fiend, for the heauens rouse vp a braue minde sayes the fiend, and runne; well, my conscience hanging about the necke of my heart, sayes very wisely to mee: my honest friend Launcelet beeing an honest mans sonne, or rather an honest womans sonne, for indeede my Father did something smacke, something grow to; he had a kinde of tast; well, my conscience sayes Launcelet bouge not, bouge sayes the fiend, bouge not sayes my conscience, conscience say I you counsaile wel, fiend say I you counsaile well, to be ruld by my conscience, I should stay with the Iewe my Maister, (who God blesse the marke) is a kinde of deuill; and to runne away from the Iewe I should be ruled by the fiend, who sauing your reuerence is the deuill himselfe: certainely the Iewe is the very deuill incarnation, and in my conscience, my conscience is but a kinde of hard conscience, to offer to counsaile mee to stay with the Iewe; the fiend giues the more friendly counsaile: I will runne fiend, my heeles are at your commaundement, I will runne. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e6680">Enter old Gobbo with a basket. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e6690">
          <speaker>Gobbo. </speaker>
          <p>Maister young-man, you I pray you, which is the way to Maister Iewes? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e6720">
          <speaker>Launcelet. </speaker>
          <p>O heauens, this is my true begotten Father, who being more then sand blinde, high grauell blinde, knowes me not, I will try confusions with him. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e6750">
          <speaker>Gobbo. </speaker>
          <p>Maister young Gentleman, I pray you which is the way to Maister Iewes. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e6780">
          <speaker>Launcelet. </speaker>
          <p>Turne vp on your right hand at the next turning, but at the next turning of all on your left; marry at the very next turning turne of no hand, but turne downe indirectly to the Iewes house. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e6810">
          <speaker>Gobbo. </speaker>
          <p>Be Gods sonties twill be a hard way to hit, can you tell <pb xml:id="ep000838-009-b"/>mee whether one Launcelet that dwels with him, dwell with him or no. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e6850">
          <speaker>Launcelet. </speaker>
          <p>Talke you of young Maister Launcelet, marke mee nowe, nowe will I raise the waters; talke you of young Maister Launcelet. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e6900">
          <speaker>Gobbo. </speaker>
          <p>No Maister sir, but a poore mans Sonne, his Father though I say't is an honest exceeding poore man, and God bee thanked well to liue. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e6930">
          <speaker>Launce. </speaker>
          <p>Well, let his Father be what a will, wee talke of young Maister Launcelet. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e6970">
          <speaker>Gob. </speaker>
          <p>Your worships friend and Launcelet sir. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7010">
          <speaker>Launce. </speaker>
          <p>But I pray you ergo olde man, ergo I beseech you, talke you of young Maister Launcelet. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7070">
          <speaker>Gob. </speaker>
          <p>Of Launcelet ant please your maistership. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7110">
          <speaker>Launce. </speaker>
          <p>Ergo Maister Launcelet, talke not of maister Launcelet Father, for the young Gentleman according to fates and destenies, and such odd sayings, the sisters three, and such braunches of learning, is indeede deceased, or as you would say in plaine termes, gone to heauen. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7170">
          <speaker>Gobbo. </speaker>
          <p>Marry God forbid, the boy was the very staffe of my age, my very prop. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7200">
          <speaker>Launcelet. </speaker>
          <p>Doe I looke like a cudgell or a houell post, a staffe, or a prop: doe you know me Father. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7230">
          <speaker>Gobbo. </speaker>
          <p>Alacke the day, I knowe you not young Gentleman, but I pray you tell mee, is my boy GOD rest his soule aliue or dead. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7260">
          <speaker>Launcelet. </speaker>
          <p>Doe you not know me Father. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7290">
          <speaker>Gobbo. </speaker>
          <p>Alack sir I am sand blind, I know you not. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7320">
          <speaker>Launcelet. </speaker>
          <p>Nay, in deede if you had your eyes you might fayle of the knowing mee: it is a wise Father that knowes his owne childe. Well, olde man, I will tell you newes of your sonne, giue mee your blessing, trueth will come to light, muder cannot bee hidde long, a mannes Sonne may, but in the ende trueth will out. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7350">
          <speaker>Gobbo. </speaker>
          <p>Pray you sir stand vp, I am sure you are not Launcelet my boy. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7390">
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-010-a"/>
          <speaker>Launce. </speaker>
          <p>Pray you let's haue no more fooling, about it, but giue mee your blessing: I am Launcelet your boy that was, your sonne that is, your child that shall be. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7430">
          <speaker>Gob. </speaker>
          <p>I cannot thinke you are my sonne. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7460">
          <speaker>Launc. </speaker>
          <p>I know not what I shall think of that: but I am Launcelet the Iewes man, and I am sure Margerie your wife is my mother. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7510">
          <speaker>Gob. </speaker>
          <p>Her name is Margerie in deede, ile be sworne if thou bee Launcelet, thou art mine owne flesh and blood: Lord worshipt might he be, what a beard hast thou got; thou hast got more haire on thy chinne, then Dobbin my philhorse hase on his taile. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7560">
          <speaker>Launce. </speaker>
          <p>It should seeme then that Dobbins taile growes backward. I am sure hee had more haire of his taile then I haue of my face when I lost saw him. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7590">
          <speaker>Gob. </speaker>
          <p>Lord how art thou changd: how doost thou and thy Master agree, I haue brought him a present; how gree you now? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7620">
          <speaker>Launce. </speaker>
          <p>Well, well, but for mine owne part, as I haue set vp my rest to runne away, so I will not rest till I haue runne some ground; my Maister's a very Iewe, giue him a present, giue him a halter, I am famisht in his seruice. You may tell euery finger I haue with my ribs: Father I am glad you are come, giue me your present to one Maister Bassanio, who in deede giues rare newe Lyuories, if I serue not him, I will runne as farre as God has any ground. O rare fortune, heere comes the man, to him Father, for I am a Iewe if I serue the Iewe any longer. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e7660">Enter Bassanio with a follower or two. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7680">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <p>You may doe so, but let it be so hasted that supper be ready at the farthest by fiue of the clocke: see these Letters deliuered, put the Lyueries to making, and desire Gratiano to come anone to my lodging. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7720">
          <speaker>Launce. </speaker>
          <p>To him Father. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7750">
          <speaker>Gob. </speaker>
          <p>God blesse your worship. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7780">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <p>Gramercie, wouldst thou ought with me. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7810">
          <speaker>Gobbe. </speaker>
          <p>Heere's my sonne sir, a poore boy. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7840">
          <speaker>Launce. </speaker>
          <p>Not a poore boy sir, but the rich Iewes man that would sir as my Father shall specifie. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7870">
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-010-b"/>
          <speaker>Gob. </speaker>
          <p>He hath a great infection sir, as one would say to serue. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7900">
          <speaker>Lau. </speaker>
          <p>Indeede the short and the long is, I serue the Iewe, &amp; haue a desire as my Father shall specifie. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7940">
          <speaker>Gob. </speaker>
          <p>His Maister and he (sauing your worships reuerence) are scarce catercosins, </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e7970">
          <speaker>Lau. </speaker>
          <p>To be briefe, the very truth is, that the Iewe hauing done me wrong, dooth cause me as my Father being I hope an old man shall frutifie vnto you. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e8000">
          <speaker>Gob. </speaker>
          <p>I haue heere a dish of Doues that I would bestow vppon your worship, and my sute is. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e8030">
          <speaker>Lau. </speaker>
          <p>In very briefe, the sute is impertinent to myselfe, as your worship shall knowe by this honest old man, and though I say it, though old man, yet poore man my Father. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e8060">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <p>One speake for both, what would you? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e8090">
          <speaker>Laun. </speaker>
          <p>Serue you sir. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e8120">
          <speaker>Gob. </speaker>
          <p>That is the very defect of the matter sir. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e8150">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>I know thee well, thou hast obtaind thy sute, </l>
          <l>Shylocke thy Maister spoke with me this day, </l>
          <l>And hath preferd thee, if it be preferment </l>
          <l>To leaue a rich Iewes seruice, to become </l>
          <l>The follower of so poore a Gentleman. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e8230">
          <speaker>Clowne. </speaker>
          <p>The old prouerb is very well parted betweene my Maister Shylocke and you sir, you haue the grace of God sir, and hee hath enough. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e8270">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Thou speakst it well; goe Father with thy Sonne </l>
          <l>Take leaue of thy old Maister, and enquire </l>
          <l>My lodging out, giue him a Lyuerie </l>
          <l>More garded then his fellowes: see it done. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e8330">
          <speaker>Clowne. </speaker>
          <p>Father in, I cannot get a seruice, no, I haue nere a tong in my head, wel: if any man in Italy haue a fayrer table which dooth offer to sweare vpon a booke, I shall haue good fortune; goe too, heere's a simple lyne of life, heeres a small tryfle of wiues, alas, fifteene wiues is nothing, a leuen widdowes and nine maydes is a simple comming in for one man, and then to scape drowning thrice, and to be in perrill of my life with the edge of a featherbed, heere are simple scapes: well, if Fortune be a woman she's a good wench for this gere: Father come, ile take my leaue of the Iewe in <pb xml:id="ep000838-011-a"/>the twinkling. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e8360">Exit Clowne. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e8370">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>I pray thee good Leonardo thinke on this, </l>
          <l>These things being bought and orderly bestowed </l>
          <l>Returne in hast, for I doe feast to night </l>
          <l>My best esteemd acquaintance, hie thee goe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e8440">
          <speaker>Leon. </speaker>
          <l>My best endeuours shall be done heerein. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000838-e8470">Exit Leonardo. </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e8480">Enter Gratiano. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e8490">
          <speaker>Grati. </speaker>
          <l>Where's your Maister. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e8520">
          <speaker>Leonar. </speaker>
          <l>Yonder sir he walkes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e8550">
          <speaker>Grati. </speaker>
          <l>Signior Bassanio. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e8590">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Gratiano. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e8620">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>I haue sute to you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e8650">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>You haue obtaind it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e8680">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>You must not deny me, I must goe with you to Belmont. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e8710">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Why then you must but heare thee Gratiano, </l>
          <l>Thou art to wild, to rude, and bold of voyce, </l>
          <l>Parts that become thee happily enough, </l>
          <l>And in such eyes as ours appeare not faults </l>
          <l>But where thou art not knowne; why there they show </l>
          <l>Somthing too liberall, pray thee take paine </l>
          <l>To allay with some cold drops of modestie </l>
          <l>Thy skipping spirit, least through thy wild behauiour </l>
          <l>I be misconstred in the place I goe to, </l>
          <l>And loose my hopes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e8850">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>Signor Bassanio, heare me, </l>
          <l>Yf I doe not put on a sober habite, </l>
          <l>Talke with respect, and sweare but now and than, </l>
          <l>Weare prayer bookes in my pocket, looke demurely, </l>
          <l>Nay more, while grace is saying hood mine eyes </l>
          <l>Thus with my hat, and sigh and say amen: </l>
          <l>Vse all the obseruance of ciuillity </l>
          <l>Like one well studied in a sad ostent </l>
          <l>To please his Grandam, neuer trust me more. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e8970">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Well, we shall see your bearing. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e9000">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>Nay but I barre to night, you shall not gage me </l>
          <l>By what we doe to night. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e9040">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>No that were pitty, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-011-b"/>
          <l>I would intreate you rather to put on </l>
          <l>Your boldest sute of mirth, for we haue friends </l>
          <l>That purpose merriment: but far you well, </l>
          <l>I haue some busines. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e9120">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>And I must to Lorenso and the rest, </l>
          <l>But we will visite you at supper time. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e9170">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e9180">Enter Iessica and the Clowne. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e9200">
          <speaker>Jessica. </speaker>
          <l>I am sorry thou wilt leaue my Father so, </l>
          <l>Our house is hell, and thou a merry deuill </l>
          <l>Didst rob it of some tast of tediousnes, </l>
          <l>But far thee well, there is a ducat for thee, </l>
          <l>And Launcelet, soone at supper shalt thou see </l>
          <l>Lorenso, who is thy new Maisters guest, </l>
          <l>Giue him this Letter, doe it secretly, </l>
          <l>And so farwell: I would not haue my Father </l>
          <l>See me in talke with thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e9340">
          <speaker>Clowne. </speaker>
          <p>Adiew, teares exhibit my tongue, most beautifull Pagan, most sweete Iewe, if a Christian doe not play the knaue and get thee, I am much deceaued; but adiew, these foolish drops doe somthing drowne my manly spirit: adiew. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e9380">
          <speaker>Jessica. </speaker>
          <l>Farwell good Launcelet. </l>
          <l>Alack, what heynous sinne is it in me </l>
          <l>To be ashamed to be my Fathers child, </l>
          <l>But though I am a daughter to his blood </l>
          <l>I am not to his manners: ô Lorenso </l>
          <l>Yf thou keepe promise I shall end this strife, </l>
          <l>Become a Christian and thy louing wife. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e9510">Exit. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e9520">Enter Gratiano, Lorenso, Salaryno, and Salanio. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e9530">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>Nay, we will slinke away in supper time, </l>
          <l>Disguise vs at my lodging, and returne all in an houre. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e9570">
          <speaker>Gratia. </speaker>
          <l>We haue not made good preparation. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e9600">
          <speaker>Salari. </speaker>
          <l>We haue not spoke vs yet of Torch-bearers, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e9630">
          <speaker>Solanio. </speaker>
          <l>Tis vile vnlesse it may be quaintly ordered, </l>
          <l>And better in my minde not vndertooke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e9670">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>Tis now but foure of clocke, we haue two houres <pb xml:id="ep000838-012-a"/>To furnish vs; friend Launcelet whats the newes. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e9710">Enter Launcelet. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e9720">
          <speaker>Launcelet. </speaker>
          <p>And it shal please you to breake vp this, it shal seeme to signifie. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e9750">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>I know the hand, in faith tis a faire hand, </l>
          <l>And whiter then the paper it writ on </l>
          <l>Is the faire hand that writ. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e9800">
          <speaker>Gratia. </speaker>
          <l>Loue, newes in faith. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e9830">
          <speaker>Launce. </speaker>
          <l>By your leaue sir. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e9860">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>Whither goest thou. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e9890">
          <speaker>Launc. </speaker>
          <p>Marry sir to bid my old Maister the Iewe to sup to night with my new Maister the Christian. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e9920">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>Hold heere take this, tell gentle Iessica </l>
          <l>I will not faile her, speake it priuatly, </l>
          <l>Goe Gentlemen, will you prepare you for this maske to night, </l>
          <l>I am prouided of a Torch-bearer. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e10010">Exit Clowne. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e10020">
          <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
          <l>I marry, ile be gone about it straite. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e10060">
          <speaker>Sol. </speaker>
          <l>And so will I. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e10100">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>Meete me and Gratiano at Gratianos lodging </l>
          <l>Some houre hence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e10160">
          <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
          <l>Tis good we doe so. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e10190">Exit. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e10200">
          <speaker>Gratia. </speaker>
          <l>Was not that Letter from faire Iessica. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e10240">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>I must needes tell thee all, she hath directed </l>
          <l>How I shall take her from her Fathers house, </l>
          <l>What gold and iewels she is furnisht with, </l>
          <l>What Pages sute she hath in readines, </l>
          <l>Yf ere the Iewe her Father come to heauen, </l>
          <l>Yt will be for his gentle daughters sake, </l>
          <l>And neuer dare misfortune crosse her foote, </l>
          <l>Vnlesse she doe it vnder this excuse, </l>
          <l>That she is issue to a faithlesse Iewe: </l>
          <l>Come goe with me, pervse this as thou goest, </l>
          <l>Faire Jessica shall be my Torch-bearer. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e10380">Exit. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e10390">Enter Iewe and his man that was the Clowne. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e10400">
          <speaker>Iewe. </speaker>
          <l>Well, thou shalt see, thy eyes shall be thy iudge, </l>
          <l>The difference of old Shylocke and Bassanio; </l>
          <l>What Iessica, thou shalt not gurmandize </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-012-b"/>
          <l>As thou hast done with mee: what Iessica, </l>
          <l>and sleepe, and snore, and rend apparraile out. </l>
          <l>Why Iessica I say. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e10530">
          <speaker>Clowne. </speaker>
          <l>Why Iessica. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e10570">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <l>Who bids thee call? I doe not bid thee call. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e10600">
          <speaker>Clow. </speaker>
          <l>Your worship was wont to tell me, </l>
          <l>I could doe nothing without bidding. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e10640">Enter Iessica. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e10660">
          <speaker>Iessica. </speaker>
          <l>Call you? what is your will? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e10690">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <l>I am bid forth to supper Iessica, </l>
          <l>There are my keyes: but wherefore should I goe? </l>
          <l>I am not bid for loue, they flatter me, </l>
          <l>But yet Ile goe in hate, to feede vpon </l>
          <l>The prodigall Christian. Iessica my girle, </l>
          <l>looke to my house, I am right loth to goe, </l>
          <l>There is some ill a bruing towards my rest, </l>
          <l>For I did dreame of money baggs to night. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e10820">
          <speaker>Clowne. </speaker>
          <p>I beseech you sir goe, my young Maister doth expect your reproch. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e10850">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <p>So doe I his. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e10890">
          <speaker>Clowne. </speaker>
          <p>And they haue conspired together, I will not say you shall see a Maske, but if you doe, then it was not for nothing that my nose fell a bleeding on black monday last, at sixe a clocke ith morning, falling out that yeere on ashwensday was foure yeere in thafternoone. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e10930">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <p>What are there maskes? heare you me Iessica, lock vp my doores, and when you heare the drumme and the vile squealing of the wry-neckt Fiffe clamber not you vp to the casements then Nor thrust your head into the publique streete To gaze on Christian fooles with varnisht faces: But stop my houses eares, I meane my casements, let not the sound of shallow fopprie enter my sober house. By Iacobs staffe I sweare I haue no minde of feasting forth to night: but I will goe: goe you before me sirra, say I will come. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11020">
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-013-a"/>
          <speaker>Clowne. </speaker>
          <p>I will goe before sir. Mistres looke out at window for all this, there will come a Christian by will be worth a Iewes eye. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11050">
          <speaker>Shyl. </speaker>
          <p>What sayes that foole of Hagars ofspring? ha. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11090">
          <speaker>Iessica. </speaker>
          <p>His words were farewell mistris, nothing els. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11120">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <p>The patch is kinde enough, but a huge feeder, Snaile slow in profit, and he sleepes by day more then the wild-cat: drones hiue not with me, therefore I part with him and part with him to one that I would haue him helpe to wast his borrowed purse. Well Iessica goe in, perhaps I will return immediathe, do as I bid you, shut dores after you, fast bind, fast find. a prouerbe neuer stale in thriftie minde. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e11180">Exit. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11190">
          <speaker>Ies. </speaker>
          <l>Farewell, and if my fortune be not crost, </l>
          <l>I haue a Father, you a daughter lost. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e11230">Exit. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e11240">Enter the maskers, Gratiano and Salerino. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11270">
          <speaker>Grat. </speaker>
          <p>This is the penthouse vnder which Lorenzo desired vs to make stand. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11310">
          <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
          <p>His howre is almost past. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11340">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <p>And it is meruaile he out-dwells his howre, for louers euer runne before the clocke. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11370">
          <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
          <p>O tenne times faster Venus pidgions flie to seale loues bonds new made, then they are wont to keepe obliged faith vnforfaited. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11410">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <p>That euer holds: who riseth from a feast with that keene appetite that he sits downe? where is the horse that doth vntread againe his tedious measures with the vnbated fire that he did pace them first: all things that are are withmore spirit chased then enioyd. How like a younger or a prodigall the skarfed barke puts from her natiue bay hugd and embraced by the strumpet wind, how like the prodigall doth she returne <pb xml:id="ep000838-013-b"/>with ouer-wetherd ribbs and ragged sailes leane, rent, and beggerd by the strumpet wind? </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e11440">Enter Lorenzo. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11460">
          <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
          <p>Heere comes Lorenzo, more of this hereafter. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11500">
          <speaker>Lor. </speaker>
          <p>Sweet freends, your patience for my long abode not I but my affaires haue made you waite: when you shall please to play the theeues for wiues Ile watch as long for you then: approch here dwels my father Iew. Howe whos's within? </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e11530">Iessica aboue. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11550">
          <speaker>Iess. </speaker>
          <l>Who are you? tell me for more certainty, </l>
          <l>Albeit Ile sweare that I doe know your tongue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11590">
          <speaker>Lor. </speaker>
          <l>Lorenzo and thy loue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11630">
          <speaker>Iessica. </speaker>
          <p>Lorenzo certaine, and my loue indeed, for who loue I so much? and now who knowes but you Lorenzo whether I am yours? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11680">
          <speaker>Lor. </speaker>
          <p>Heauen &amp; thy thoughts are witnes that thou art. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11710">
          <speaker>Ies. </speaker>
          <p>Heere catch this casket, it is worth the paines, I am glad us night you doe not looke on me, for I am much ashamde of my exchange: But loue is blinde, and louers cannot see The prerty follies that themselues commit, for if they could. Cupid himselfe would blush to see me thus transformed to a boy. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11750">
          <speaker>Lor. </speaker>
          <p>Descend, for you must be my torch-bearer. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11780">
          <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
          <p>What, must I hold a candle to my shames, they in themselues goodsooth are too too light. Why, tis an office of discouery loue, and I should be obscurd. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11810">
          <speaker>Lor. </speaker>
          <p>So are you sweet euen in the louely garnish of a boy, but come at once, for the close night doth play the runaway, and we are staid for at Bassanios feast. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11850">
          <speaker>Ios. </speaker>
          <p>I will make fast the doores &amp; guild my selfe with some mo ducats, and be with you straight. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11880">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <p>Now by my hoode a gentle, and no Iew. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11910">
          <speaker>Lor. </speaker>
          <p>Beshrow me but I loue her hartilie, <pb xml:id="ep000838-014-a"/>A coyne that beares the figure of an Angell stampt in gold, but thats insculpt vpon: But heere an Angell in a golden bed lies all within. Deliuer me the key: heere doe I choose, and thriue I as I may. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11940">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <p>There take it Prince, and if my forme lie there then I am yours? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e11970">
          <speaker>Mor. </speaker>
          <p>O hell! what haue wee heare, a carrion death, within whose emptie eye there is a written scroule, Ile reade the writing. </p>
          <q>
            <l>All that glisters is not gold, </l>
            <l>Often haue you heard that told, </l>
            <l>Many a man his life hath sold </l>
            <l>But my outside to behold, </l>
            <l>Guilded timber doe wormes infold: </l>
            <l>Had you beene as wise as bold, </l>
            <l>Young in limbs, in iudgement old, </l>
            <l>Your aunswere had not beene inscrold, </l>
            <l>Fareyouwell, your sute is cold. </l>
          </q>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e12100">
          <speaker>Mor. </speaker>
          <l>Cold indeede and labour lost, </l>
          <l>Then farewell heate, and welcome frost: </l>
          <l>Portia adiew, I haue too greeu'd a hart </l>
          <l>To take a tedious leaue: thus loosers part. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e12170">Exit. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e12180">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>A gentle riddance, draw the curtaines, go, </l>
          <l>Let all of his complexion choose me so. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e12220">Exeum. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e12230">Enter Salarino and Solanio. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e12260">
          <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
          <p>Why man I saw Bassanio vnder sayle, with him is Gratiano gone along; and in theyr ship I am sure Lorenzo is not. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e12320">
          <speaker>Sola. </speaker>
          <p>The villaine Iew with outcries raisd the Duke, who went with him to search Bassanio; ship. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e12360">
          <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
          <p>He came too late, the ship was vndersaile, But there the Duke was giuen to vnderstand that in a Gondylo were seene together Lorenzo and his amorous Iessica. Besides, Anthonio certified the Duke they were not with Bassanio in his ship. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e12430">
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-014-b"/>
          <speaker>Sol. </speaker>
          <p>I neuer heard a passion so confusd, So strange, outragious, and so variable as the dogge Iew did vtter in the streets, My daughter, ô my ducats, ô my daughter, Fled with a Christian, ô my Christian ducats, Iustice, the law my ducats, and my daughter, A sealed bag, two sealed bags of ducats of double ducats, stolne from me by my daughter, and Iewels, two stones, two rich and precious stones, Stolne by my daughter: iustice; find the girle, shee hath the stones vpon her, and the ducats. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e12460">
          <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
          <p>Why all the boyes in Venice follow him, crying his stones, his daughter and his ducats. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e12490">
          <speaker>Sola. </speaker>
          <p>Let good Anthonio looke he keepe his day or he shall pay for this. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e12530">
          <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
          <p>Marry well remembred, I reasond with a Frenchman yesterday, who told me, in the narrow seas that part the French and English, there miscaried a vessell of our country richly fraught: I thought vpon Anthonio when he told me, and wisht in silence that it were not his. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e12570">
          <speaker>Sol. </speaker>
          <p>You were best to tell Anthonio what you heare, Yet doe not suddainely, for it may greeue him. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e12610">
          <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
          <p>A kinder gentleman treades not the earth, I saw Bassanio and Anthonio part, Bassanio told him he would make some speede of his returne: he aunswered, doe not so, slumber not busines for my sake Bassanio, but stay the very riping of the time, and for the Iewes bond which he hath of me let it not enter in your minde of loue: be merry, and imploy your cheefest thoughts to courtship, and such faire ostents of loue as shall conueniently become you there, And euen there his eye being big with teares, turning his face, he put his hand behind him, and with affection wondrous sencible <pb xml:id="ep000838-015-a"/>He wrung Bassanios hand, and so they parted. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e12690">
          <speaker>Sol. </speaker>
          <p>I thinke hee onely loues the world for him, I pray thee let vs goe and finde him out and quicken his embraced heauines with some delight or other. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e12730">
          <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
          <p>Doe we so. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e12760">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e12770">Enter Nerrissa and a Seruiture. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e12790">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <p>Quick, quick I pray thee, draw the curtain strait, The Prince of Arragon hath tane his oath, and comes to his election presently. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e12830">Enter Arrogon, his trayne, and Portia. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e12860">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <p>Behold, there stand the caskets noble Prince, yf you choose that wherein I am containd straight shall our nuptiall rights be solemniz'd: but if you faile, without more speech my Lord you must be gone from hence immediatly. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e12890">
          <speaker>Arra. </speaker>
          <p>I am enioynd by oath to obserue three things, First, neuer to vnfold to any one which casket twas I chose; next, if I faile of the right casket, neuer in my life to wooe a maide in way of marriage: lastly, if I doe faile in fortune of my choyse, immediatly to leaue you, and be gone. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e12940">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <p>To these iniunctions euery one doth sweare that comes to hazard for my worthlesse selfe. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e12970">
          <speaker>Arr. </speaker>
          <l>And so haue I addrest me, fortune now </l>
          <l>To my harts hope: gold, siluer, and base lead. </l>
          <l>Who chooseth me, must giue and hazard all he hath. </l>
          <l>You shall looke fairer ere I giue or hazard. </l>
          <l>What saies the golden chest, ha, let me see, </l>
          <l>Who chooseth me, shall gaine what many men desire, </l>
          <l>What many men desire, that many may be meant </l>
          <l>by the foole multitude that choose by show, </l>
          <l>not learning more then the fond eye doth teach, </l>
          <l>which pries not to thinteriour, but like the Martlet </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-015-b"/>
          <l>Builds in the weather on the outward wall, </l>
          <l>Euen in the force and rode of casualty. </l>
          <l>I will not choose what many men desire, </l>
          <l>Because I will not iumpe with common spirits, </l>
          <l>And ranke me with the barbarous multitudes. </l>
          <l>Why then to thee thou siluer treasure house, </l>
          <l>Tell me once more what title thou doost beare; </l>
          <l>Who chooseth me shall get as much as he deserues, </l>
          <l>And well sayde to; for who shall goe about </l>
          <l>To cosen Fortune, and be honourable </l>
          <l>without the stampe of merrit, let none presume </l>
          <l>To weare an vndeserued dignity: </l>
          <l>O that estates, degrees, and offices, </l>
          <l>were not deriu'd corruptly, and that cleare honour </l>
          <l>were purchast by the merrit of the wearer, </l>
          <l>How many then should couer that stand bare? </l>
          <l>How many be commaunded that commaund? </l>
          <l>How much low peasantry would then be gleaned </l>
          <l>From the true seede of honour? and how much honour </l>
          <l>Pickt from the chaft and ruin of the times, </l>
          <l>To be new varnist; well but to my choise. </l>
          <l>Who chooseth me shall get as much as he deserues, </l>
          <l>I will assume desert; giue me a key for this, </l>
          <l>And instantly vnlocke my fortunes heere. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e13340">
          <speaker>Portia. </speaker>
          <l>Too long a pause for that which you finde there. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e13370">
          <speaker>Arrag. </speaker>
          <l>What's heere, the pourtrait of a blinking idiot </l>
          <l>Presenting me a shedule, I will reade it: </l>
          <l>How much vnlike art thou to Portia? </l>
          <l>How much vnlike my hopes and my deseruings. </l>
          <l>Who chooseth me, shall haue as much as he deserues? </l>
          <l>Did I deserue no more then a fooles head, </l>
          <l>Is that my prize, are my deserts no better? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e13470">
          <speaker>Portia. </speaker>
          <l>To offend and iudge are distinct offices, </l>
          <l>And of opposed natures. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e13510">
          <speaker>Arrag. </speaker>
          <l>What is heere? </l>
          <q>
            <l>The fier seauen times tried this, </l>
            <l>Seauen times tried that iudement is, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000838-016-a"/>
            <l>That did neuer choose amis, </l>
            <l>Some there be that shadowes kis. </l>
            <l>Such haue but a shadowes blis: </l>
            <l>There be fooles aliue Iwis </l>
            <l>Siluerd o're, and so was this. </l>
            <l>Take what wife you will to bed, </l>
            <l>I will euer be your head: </l>
            <l>So be gone, you are sped. </l>
          </q>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e13650">
          <speaker>Arrag. </speaker>
          <l>Still more foole I shall appeare </l>
          <l>By the time I linger heere, </l>
          <l>With one fooles head I came to woo, </l>
          <l>But I goe away with two. </l>
          <l>Sweet adiew, ile keepe my oath, </l>
          <l>Paciently to beare my wroath. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e13740">
          <speaker>Portia. </speaker>
          <l>Thus hath the candle singd the moath: </l>
          <l>O these deliberate fooles when they doe choose, </l>
          <l>They haue the wisedome by their wit to loose. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e13790">
          <speaker>Nerriss. </speaker>
          <l>The auncient saying is no herisie, </l>
          <l>Hanging and wiuing goes by destinie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e13830">
          <speaker>Portia. </speaker>
          <l>Come draw the curtaine Nerrissa. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e13870">Enter Messenger. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e13880">
          <speaker>Mess. </speaker>
          <l>Where is my Lady. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e13910">
          <speaker>Portia. </speaker>
          <l>Heere, what would my Lord? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e13940">
          <speaker>Mess. </speaker>
          <l>Madame, there is a-lighted at your gate </l>
          <l>A young Venetian, one that comes before </l>
          <l>To signifie th'approaching of his Lord, </l>
          <l>From whom he bringeth sensible regreets; </l>
          <l>To wit, (besides commends and curtious breath) </l>
          <l>Gifts of rich valiew; yet I haue not seene </l>
          <l>So likely an Embassador of loue. </l>
          <l>A day in Aprill neuer came so sweete </l>
          <l>To show how costly Sommer was at hand, </l>
          <l>As this fore-spurrer comes before his Lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e14060">
          <speaker>Portia. </speaker>
          <l>No more I pray thee, I am halfe a-feard </l>
          <l>Thou wilt say anone he is some kin to thee, </l>
          <l>Thou spendst such high day wit in praysing him: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-016-b"/>
          <l>Come come Nerryssa, for I long to see </l>
          <l>Quick Cupids Post that comes so mannerly. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e14160">
          <speaker>Nerryss. </speaker>
          <l>Bessanio Lord, loue if thy will it be. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e14200">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e14210">Solanio and Salarino. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e14220">
          <speaker>Solanio. </speaker>
          <p>Now what newes on the Ryalto? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e14250">
          <speaker>Salari. </speaker>
          <p>Why yet it liues there vncheckt, that Anthonio hath a ship of rich lading wrackt on the narrow Seas; the Goodwins I thinke they call the place, a very dangerous flat, and fatall, where the carcasses of many a tall ship lie buried, as they say, if my gossip report be an honest woman of her word. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e14290">
          <speaker>Solanio. </speaker>
          <p>I would she were as lying a gossip in that, as euer knapt Ginger, or made her neighbours beleeue she wept for the death of a third husband: but it is true, without any slips of prolixity, or crossing the plaine high way of talke, that the good Anthonio, the honest Anthonio; ô that I had a tytle good enough to keepe his name company. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e14350">
          <speaker>Salari. </speaker>
          <p>Come, the full stop. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e14380">
          <speaker>Solanio. </speaker>
          <p>Ha, what sayest thou, why the end is, he hath lost a ship. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e14410">
          <speaker>Salari. </speaker>
          <p>I would it might proue the end of his losses. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e14440">
          <speaker>Solanio. </speaker>
          <p>Let me say amen betimes, least the deuil crosse my praier, for heere he comes in the likenes of a Iewe. How now Shylocke, what newes among the Merchants? </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e14480">Enter Shylocke. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e14490">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <p>You knew, none so well, none so well as you, of my daughters flight. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e14520">
          <speaker>Salari. </speaker>
          <p>Thats certaine, I for my part knew the Taylor that made the wings she flew withall. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e14560">
          <speaker>Solan. </speaker>
          <p>And Shylocke for his own part knew the bird was flidge, and then it is the complexion of them all to leaue the dam. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e14600">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <p>She is damnd for it. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e14630">
          <speaker>Salari. </speaker>
          <p>Thats certaine, if the deuill may be her Iudge. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e14660">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <p>My owne flesh and blood to rebell. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e14690">
          <speaker>Sola. </speaker>
          <p>Out vpon it old carrion, rebels it at these yeeres. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e14720">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <p>I say my daughter is my flesh and my blood. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e14750">
          <speaker>Salari. </speaker>
          <p>There is more difference betweene thy flesh and hers, then betweene Iet and Iuori, more betweene your bloods, then there is betweene red wine and rennish: but tell vs, doe you heare whether Anthonio haue had any losse at sea or no? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e14790">
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-017-a"/>
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <p>There I haue another bad match, a bankrout, a prodigall, who dare scarce shewe his head on the Ryalto, a begger that was vsd to come so smug vpon the Mart: let him looke to his bond, he was wont to call me vsurer, let him looke to his bond, hee was wont to lende money for a Christian cursie, let him looke to his bond. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e14820">
          <speaker>Salari. </speaker>
          <p>Why I am sure if he forfaite, thou wilt not take his flesh, what's that good for? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e14850">
          <speaker>Shyl. </speaker>
          <p>To baite fish with all, if it will feede nothing else, it will feede my reuenge; hee hath disgrac'd me, and hindred me halfe a million, laught at my losses, mockt at my gaines, scorned my Nation, thwarted my bargaines, cooled my friends, heated mine enemies, and whats his reason, I am a Iewe: Hath not a Iewe eyes, hath not a Iewe hands, organs, dementions, sences, affections, passions, fed with the same foode, hurt with the same weapons, subiect to the same diseases, healed by the same meanes, warmed and cooled by the same Winter and Sommer as a Christian is: if you pricke vs doe we not bleede, if you tickle vs doe wee not laugh, if you poyson vs doe wee not die, and if you wrong vs shall wee not reuenge, if we are like you in the rest, we will resemble you in that. If a Iewe wrong a Christian, what is his humillity, reuenge? If a Christian wrong a Iewe, what should his sufferance be by Christian example, why reuenge? The villanie you teach me I will execute, and it shall goe hard but I will better the instruction. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e14880">Enter a man from Anthonio. </stage>
        <p>Gentlemen, my maister Anthonio is at his house, and desires to speake with you both. </p>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e14920">
          <speaker>Saleri. </speaker>
          <p>We haue beene vp and downe to seeke him. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e14950">Enter Tuball. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e14970">
          <speaker>Solanio. </speaker>
          <p>Heere comes another of the Tribe, a third cannot bee matcht, vnlesse the deuill himselfe turne Iewe. <hi>Exeunt Gentlemen</hi>. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e15010">Enter Tuball. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e15030">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <p>How now Tuball, what newes from Genowa, hast thou found my daughter? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e15070">
          <speaker>Tuball. </speaker>
          <p>I often came where I did heare of her, but cannot finde her. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e15100">
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-017-b"/>
          <speaker>Shylocke. </speaker>
          <p>Why there, there, there, there, a diamond gone cost me two thousand ducats in Franckford, the curse neuer fell vpon our Nation till now, I neuer felt it till nowe, two thousand ducats in that, &amp; other precious precious iewels; I would my daughter were dead at my foote, and the iewels in her eare: would she were hearst at my foote, and the ducats in her coffin: no newes of them, why so? and I know not whats spent in the search: why thou losse vpon losse, the theefe gone with so much, and so much to finde the theefe, and no satisfaction, no reuenge, nor no ill lucke stirring but what lights a my shoulders, no sighs but a my breathing, no teares but a my shedding. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e15130">
          <speaker>Tuball. </speaker>
          <p>Yes, other men haue ill lucke to, Anthonio as I heard in Genowa? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e15170">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <p>What, what, what, ill lucke, ill lucke. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e15200">
          <speaker>Tuball. </speaker>
          <p>Hath an Argosie cast away comming from Tripolis. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e15230">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <p>I thank God, I thank God, is it true, is it true. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e15270">
          <speaker>Tuball. </speaker>
          <p>I spoke with some of the Saylers that escaped the wrack. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e15310">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <p>I thank thee good Tuball, good newes, good newes: ha ha, heere in Genowa. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e15350">
          <speaker>Tuball. </speaker>
          <p>Your daughter spent in Genowa, as I heard, one night fourescore ducats. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e15380">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <p>Thou stickst a dagger in me, I shall neuer see my gold againe, foure score ducats at a sitting, foure score ducats </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e15410">
          <speaker>Tuball. </speaker>
          <p>There came diuers of Anthonios creditors in my company to Ven●●●●hat sweare he cannot choose but breake. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e15450">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <p>I am very glad of it, ile plague him, ile torture him, I am glad of it. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e15490">
          <speaker>Tuball. </speaker>
          <p>One of them shewed mee a ring that hee had of your daughter for a Monky. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e15520">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <p>Out vpon her, thou torturest mee Tuball, it was my Turkies, I had it of Leah when I was a Batcheler: I would not haue giuen it for a Wildernes of Monkies. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e15570">
          <speaker>Tuball. </speaker>
          <p>But Anthonio is certainly vndone. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e15610">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <p>Nay, that's true, that's very true, goe Tuball fee me an Officer, bespeake him a fortnight before, I will haue the hart of him if he forfeite, for were he out of Venice I can make what merchandize I will: goe Tuball, and meete me at our Smagogue, goe good <pb xml:id="ep000838-018-a"/>Tuball, at our Sinagogue Tuball. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e15680">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e15690">Enter Bassanio, Portia, Gratiano, and all their traynes. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e15700">
          <speaker>Portia. </speaker>
          <l>I pray you tarry, pause a day or two </l>
          <l>Before you hazard, for in choosing wrong </l>
          <l>I loose your companie; therefore forbeare a while, </l>
          <l>Theres something tells me (but it is not loue) </l>
          <l>I would not loose you, and you know your selfe, </l>
          <l>Hate counsailes not in such a quallity; </l>
          <l>But least you should not vnderstand me well, </l>
          <l>And yet a mayden hath no tongue, but thought, </l>
          <l>I would detaine you heere some moneth or two </l>
          <l>before you venture for me. I could teach you </l>
          <l>how to choose right, but then I am forsworne, </l>
          <l>So will I neuer be, so may you misse me, </l>
          <l>But if you doe, youle make me wish a sinne, </l>
          <l>That I had beene forsworne: Beshrow your eyes, </l>
          <l>They haue ore-lookt me and deuided me, </l>
          <l>One halfe of me is yours, the other halfe yours, </l>
          <l>Mine owne I would say: but if mine then yours, </l>
          <l>And so all yours; ô these naughty times </l>
          <l>puts barres betweene the owners and their rights, </l>
          <l>And so though yours, not yours, (proue it so) </l>
          <l>Let Fortune goe to hell for it, not I. </l>
          <l>I speake too long, but tis to peize the time, </l>
          <l>To ech it, and to draw it out in length, </l>
          <l>To stay you from election. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e16010">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Let me choose, </l>
          <l>For as I am, I hue vpon the racke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e16070">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Vpon the racke Bassanio, then confesse what treason there is mingled with your loue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e16110">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>None but that vgly treason of mistrust, </l>
          <l>which makes me feare th'inioying of my Loue, </l>
          <l>There may as well be amity and life </l>
          <l>Tweene snow and fire, as treason and my loue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e16170">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>I but I feare you speake vpon the racke </l>
          <l>where men enforced doe speake any thing. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e16210">
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-018-b"/>
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Promise me life, and ile confesse the truth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e16240">
          <speaker>Portia. </speaker>
          <l>Well then, confesse and liue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e16270">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Confesse and loue </l>
          <l>had beene the very sum of my confession: </l>
          <l>O happy torment, when my torturer </l>
          <l>doth teach me aunsweres for deliuerance: </l>
          <l>But let me to my fortune and the caskets. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e16340">
          <speaker>Portia. </speaker>
          <l>Away then, I am locktin one of them, </l>
          <l>If you doe loue me, you will finde me out. </l>
          <l>Nerryssa and the rest, stand all aloofe, </l>
          <l>Let musique sound while he doth make his choyse, </l>
          <l>Then if he loose he makes a Swan-like end, </l>
          <l>Fading in musique. That the comparison </l>
          <l>may stand more proper, my eye shall be the streame </l>
          <l>and watry death-bed for him: he may win, </l>
          <l>And what is musique than? Than musique is </l>
          <l>euen as the flourish, when true subiects bowe </l>
          <l>to a new crowned Monarch: Such it is, </l>
          <l>As are those dulcet sounds in breake of day, </l>
          <l>That creepe into the dreaming bride-groomes eare, </l>
          <l>And summon him to marriage. Now he goes </l>
          <l>with no lesse presence, but with much more loue </l>
          <l>Then young Alcides, when he did redeeme </l>
          <l>The virgine tribute, payed by howling Troy </l>
          <l>To the Sea-monster: I stand for sacrifice, </l>
          <l>The rest alo●●● are the Dardanian wiues: </l>
          <l>With bleared visages come forth to view </l>
          <l>The issue of th'exploit: Goe Hercules, </l>
          <l>Liue thou, I liue with much much more dismay, </l>
          <l>I view the fight, then thou that mak'st the fray. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000838-e16600">A Song the whilst Bassanio comments on the caskets to himselfe. </stage>
          <l>Tell me where is fancie bred, </l>
          <l>Or in the hart, or in the head, </l>
          <l>How beget, how nourished? Replie, replie. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-019-a"/>
          <l>It is engendred in the eye, </l>
          <l>With gazing fed, and Fancie dies: </l>
          <l>In the cradle where it lies </l>
          <l>I et vs all ring Fancies knell. </l>
          <l>Ile begin it. </l>
          <l>Ding, dong, bell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e16700">
          <speaker>All. </speaker>
          <l>Ding, dong, bell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e16730">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>So may the outward showes be least themselues, </l>
          <l>The world is still deceau'd with ornament </l>
          <l>In Law, what plea so tainted and corrupt, </l>
          <l>But being season'd with a gracious voyce, </l>
          <l>Obscures the show of euill. In religion </l>
          <l>What damned error but some sober brow </l>
          <l>will blesse it, and approue it with a text, </l>
          <l>Hiding the grosnes with faire ornament: </l>
          <l>There is no voyce so simple, but assumes </l>
          <l>Some marke of vertue on his outward parts; </l>
          <l>How many cowards whose harts are all as false </l>
          <l>As stayers of sand, weare yet vpon their chins </l>
          <l>The beards of Hercules and frowning Mars, </l>
          <l>who inward searcht, haue lyuers white as milke, </l>
          <l>And these assume but valours excrement </l>
          <l>To render them redoubted. Looke on beauty, </l>
          <l>And you shall see tis purchast by the weight, </l>
          <l>which therein works a miracle in nature, </l>
          <l>Making them lightest that weare most of it: </l>
          <l>So are those crisped snaky golden locks </l>
          <l>which maketh such wanton gambols with the wind </l>
          <l>Vpon supposed fairenes, often knowne </l>
          <l>To be the dowry of a second head, </l>
          <l>The scull that bred them in the Sepulcher. </l>
          <l>Thus ornament is but the guiled shore </l>
          <l>To a most dangerous sea: the beautious scarfe </l>
          <l>vailing an Indian beauty; In a word, </l>
          <l>The seeming truth which cunning times put on </l>
          <l>To intrap the wisest. Therefore then thou gāudy gold, </l>
          <l>Hard food for Midas, I will none of thee, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-019-b"/>
          <l>Nor none of thee thou pale and common drudge </l>
          <l>tweene man and man: but thou, thou meager lead </l>
          <l>which rather threatenst then dost promise ought, </l>
          <l>thy palenes moues me more then eloquence, </l>
          <l>and heere choose I, ioy be the consequence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e17130">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>How all the other passions fleet to ayre, </l>
          <l>As doubtfull thoughts, and rash imbrac'd despaire▪ </l>
          <l>And shyddring feare, and greene-eyed iealousie. </l>
          <l>O loue be moderate, allay thy extasie, </l>
          <l>In measure raine thy ioy, scant this excosse, </l>
          <l>I feele too much thy blessing, make it lesse </l>
          <l>for feare I surfeit. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e17230">
          <speaker>Bas. </speaker>
          <l>What finde I heere? </l>
          <l>Faire Portias counterfeit. What demy God </l>
          <l>hath come so neere creation? moue these eyes? </l>
          <l>Or whither riding on the balls of mine </l>
          <l>seeme they in motion? Heere are seuerd lips </l>
          <l>parted with suger breath, so sweet a barre </l>
          <l>should sunder such sweet friends: heere in her haires </l>
          <l>the Paynter playes the Spyder, and hath wouen </l>
          <l>a golden mesh tyntrap the harts of men </l>
          <l>faster then gnats in cobwebs, but her eyes </l>
          <l>how could he see to doe them? hauing made one, </l>
          <l>me thinkes it should haue power to steale both his </l>
          <l>and leaue it selfe vnfurnisht: Yet looke how farre </l>
          <l>the substance of my praise doth wrong this shadow </l>
          <l>in vnderprysing it, so farre this shadow </l>
          <l>doth limpe behind the substance. Heeres the scroule, </l>
          <l>the continent and summarie of my fortune. </l>
          <q>
            <l>You that choose not by the view </l>
            <l>Chaunce as faire, and choose as true; </l>
            <l>Since this fortune falls to you, </l>
            <l>Be content, and seeke no new. </l>
            <l>If you be well pleasd with this, </l>
            <l>and hold your fortune for your blisse, </l>
            <l>Turne you where your Lady is, </l>
            <l>And claims her with a loving kis. </l>
          </q>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-020-a"/>
          <l>A gentle scroule: Faire Lady, by your leaue, </l>
          <l>I come by note to giue, and to receaue, </l>
          <l>Like one of two contending in a prize </l>
          <l>That thinks he hath done well in peoples eyes: </l>
          <l>Hearing applause and vniuersall shoute, </l>
          <l>Giddy in spirit, still gazing in a doubt </l>
          <l>whether those peales of praise be his or no, </l>
          <l>So thrice faire Lady stand I euen so, </l>
          <l>As doubtfull whether what I see be true, </l>
          <l>Vntill confirmd, signd, ratified by you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e17620">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>You see me Lord Bassamo where I stand, </l>
          <l>such as I am; though for my selfe alone </l>
          <l>I would not be ambitious in my wish </l>
          <l>to wish my selfe much better, yet for you, </l>
          <l>I would be trebled twentie times my selfe, </l>
          <l>a thousand times more faire, tenne, thousand times </l>
          <l>more rich, that onely to stand high in your account, </l>
          <l>I might in vertues, beauties, liuings, friends </l>
          <l>exceede account: but the full summe of me </l>
          <l>is sume of something: which to terme in grosse, </l>
          <l>is an vnlessond girle, vnschoold, vnpractized, </l>
          <l>happy in this, she is not yet so old </l>
          <l>but she may learne: happier then this, </l>
          <l>shee is not bred so dull but she can learne; </l>
          <l>happiest of all, is that her gentle spirit </l>
          <l>commits it selfe to yours to be directed, </l>
          <l>as from her Lord, her gouernour, her King. </l>
          <l>My selfe, and what is mine, to you and yours </l>
          <l>is now conuerted. But now I was the Lord </l>
          <l>of this faire mansion, maister of my seruants, </l>
          <l>Queene ore my selfe: and euen now, but now, </l>
          <l>this house, these seruants, and this same my selfe </l>
          <l>are yours, my Lords, I giue them with this ring, </l>
          <l>which when you part from, loose, or giue away, </l>
          <l>let it presage the ruine of your loue, </l>
          <l>and be my vantage to exclaime on you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e17910">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Maddam, you haue beteft me of all words, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-020-b"/>
          <l>onely my blood speakes to you in my vaines, </l>
          <l>and there is such confusion in my powers, </l>
          <l>as after some oration fairely spoke </l>
          <l>by a beloued Prince, there doth appeare </l>
          <l>among the buzzing pleased multitude. </l>
          <l>Where euery somthing beeing blent together, </l>
          <l>turnes to a wild of nothing, saue of ioy </l>
          <l>exprest, and not exprest: but when this ring </l>
          <l>parts from this finger, then parts life from hence, </l>
          <l>ô then be bold to say Bassanios dead. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e18050">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord and Lady, it is now our time </l>
          <l>that haue stoode by and seene our wishes prosper, </l>
          <l>to cry good ioy, good ioy my Lord and Lady. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e18100">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord Bassanio, and my gentle Lady, </l>
          <l>I wish you all the ioy that you can wish: </l>
          <l>for I am sure you can wish none from me: </l>
          <l>and when your honours meane to solemnize </l>
          <l>the bargaine of your fayth: I doe beseech you </l>
          <l>euen at that time I may be married to. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e18200">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>With all my hart, so thou canst get a wife. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e18230">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>I thanke your Lordship, you haue got m●… </l>
          <l>My eyes my Lord can looke as swift as yours: </l>
          <l>you saw the mistres, I beheld the mayd: </l>
          <l>You lou'd, I lou'd for intermission, </l>
          <l>No more pertaines to me my lord then you; </l>
          <l>your fortune stood vpon the caskets there, </l>
          <l>and so did mine to as the matter falls: </l>
          <l>for wooing heere vntill I swet againe, </l>
          <l>and swearing till my very rough was dry </l>
          <l>with oathes of loue, at last, if promise last </l>
          <l>I got a promise of this faire one heere </l>
          <l>to haue her loue: prouided that your fortune </l>
          <l>atchiu'd her mistres. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e18400">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Is this true Nerrissa? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e18440">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <l>Maddam it is, so you stand pleasd withall. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e18470">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>And doe you Gratiano meane good fayth? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e18510">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>Yes faith my Lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e18540">
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-021-a"/>
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Our feast shalbe much honored in your mariage. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e18570">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>Wele play with them the first boy for a thousand ducats. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e18600">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <l>What and stake downe? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e18630">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>No, we shall nere win at that sport and stake downe. </l>
          <l>But who comes heere? Lorenzo and his infidell? </l>
          <l>what, and my old Venecian friend Salerio? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e18700">Enter <hi>Lorenzo, Iessica</hi>, and Salerio a messenger from Venice. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e18730">
          <speaker>Bassa. </speaker>
          <l>Lorenzo and Salerio, welcome hether, </l>
          <l>if that the youth of my newe intrest heere </l>
          <l>haue power to bid you welcome: by your leaue </l>
          <l>I bid my very friends and countrymen </l>
          <l>sweet Portia welcome. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e18830">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>So doe I my Lord, they are intirely welcome. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e18860">
          <speaker>Lor. </speaker>
          <l>I thanke your honour, for my part my Lord </l>
          <l>my purpose was not to haue seene you heere, </l>
          <l>but meeting with Salerio by the way </l>
          <l>he did entreate me past all saying nay </l>
          <l>to come with him along. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e18940">
          <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
          <l>I did my Lord, </l>
          <l>and I haue reason for it, Signior Anthonio </l>
          <l>commends him to you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e19000">
          <speaker>Bassa. </speaker>
          <l>Ere I ope his Letter </l>
          <l>I pray you tell me how my good friend doth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e19040">
          <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
          <l>Not sicke my Lord, vnlesse it be in mind, </l>
          <l>nor well, vnlesse in mind: his letter there </l>
          <l>will shew you his estate. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e19090">open the letter. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e19100">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>Nerrissa, cheere yond stranger, bid her welcom. </l>
          <l>Your hand Salerio, what's the newes from Venice? </l>
          <l>how doth that royall Merchant good Anthonio? </l>
          <l>I know he will be glad of our successe, </l>
          <l>we are the Iasons, we haue wone the fleece. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e19210">
          <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
          <l>I would you had won the fleece that he hath lost. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e19240">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>There are some shrowd contents in yond same paper </l>
          <l>that steales the colour from Bassanios cheeke, </l>
          <l>some deere friend dead, else nothing in the world </l>
          <l>could turne so much the constitution </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-021-b"/>
          <l>of any constant man: what worse and worse? </l>
          <l>With leaue Bassanio I am halfe your selfe, </l>
          <l>and I must freely haue the halfe of any thing </l>
          <l>that this same paper brings you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e19360">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>O sweete Portia, </l>
          <l>heere are a few of the vnpleasant'st words </l>
          <l>that euer blotted paper. Gentle Lady </l>
          <l>when I did first impart my loue to you, </l>
          <l>I freely told you all the wealth I had </l>
          <l>ranne in my vaines, I was a gentleman, </l>
          <l>and then I told you true: and yet deere Lady </l>
          <l>rating my selfe at nothing, you shall see </l>
          <l>how much I was a Braggart, when I told you </l>
          <l>my state was nothing, I should then haue told you </l>
          <l>that I was worse then nothing; for indeede </l>
          <l>I haue ingag'd my selfe to a deere friend, </l>
          <l>ingag'd my friend to his meere enemie </l>
          <l>to feede my meanes. Heere is a letter Lady, </l>
          <l>the paper as the body of my friend, </l>
          <l>and euery word in it a gaping wound </l>
          <l>issuing life blood. But is it true Salerio </l>
          <l>hath all his ventures faild, what not one hit, </l>
          <l>from Tripolis, from Mexico and England, </l>
          <l>from Lisbon, Barbary, and India, </l>
          <l>and not one vessell scape the dreadfull touch </l>
          <l>of Merchant-marring rocks? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e19650">
          <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
          <l>Not one my Lord. </l>
          <l>Besides, it should appeare, that if he had </l>
          <l>the present money to discharge the Iew, </l>
          <l>hee would not take it: neuer did I know </l>
          <l>a creature that did beare the shape of man </l>
          <l>so keene and greedie to confound a man. </l>
          <l>He plyes the Duke at morning and at night, </l>
          <l>and doth impeach the freedome of the state </l>
          <l>if they deny him iustice. Twentie Merchants, </l>
          <l>the Duke himselfe, and the Magnificoes </l>
          <l>of greatest port haue all perswaded with him, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-022-a"/>
          <l>but none can driue him from the enuious plea </l>
          <l>of forfaiture, of iustice, and his bond. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e19810">
          <speaker>Jessi. </speaker>
          <l>When I was with him, I haue heard him sweare </l>
          <l>to Tuball and to Chus, his country-men, </l>
          <l>that he would rather haue Anthonios flesh </l>
          <l>then twentie times the value of the summe </l>
          <l>that he did owe him: and I know my lord, </l>
          <l>if law, authoritie, and power denie not, </l>
          <l>it will goe hard with poore Anthonio. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e19940">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Is it your decre friend that is thus in trouble? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e19970">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>The deerest friend to me, the kindest man, </l>
          <l>the best conditiond and vnwearied spirit </l>
          <l>in dooing curtesies: and one in whom </l>
          <l>the auncient Romaine honour more appeares </l>
          <l>then any that drawes breath in Italie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e20040">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>What summe owes he the Iew? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e20070">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>For me three thousand ducats. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e20100">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>What no more, pay him six thousand, &amp; deface the bond: </l>
          <l>double sixe thousand and then treble that, </l>
          <l>before a friend of this discription </l>
          <l>shall lose a haire through Bassanios fault. </l>
          <l>First goe with me to Church, and call me wife, </l>
          <l>and then away to Venice to your friend: </l>
          <l>for neuer shall you lie by Portias side </l>
          <l>with an vnquiet soule. You shall haue gold </l>
          <l>to pay the petty debt twenty times ouer. </l>
          <l>When it is payd, bring your true friend along, </l>
          <l>my mayd Nerrissa, and my selfe meane time </l>
          <l>will liue as maydes and widdowes; come away, </l>
          <l>for you shall hence vpon your wedding day: </l>
          <l>bid your freends welcome, show a merry cheere, </l>
          <l>since you are deere bought, I will loue you decre. </l>
          <l>But let me heare the letter of your friend. </l>
          <p>Sweet Bassanio, my ships haue all miscaried, my Creditors growe cruell, my estate is very low, my bond to the Iewe is forfaite, and since in paying it, it is impossible I should liue, all debts are cleerd betweene you <pb xml:id="ep000838-022-b"/>and I if I might but see you at my death: notwithstanding, vse your pleasure, if your loue do not perswade you to come, let not my letter. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e20330">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>O loue! dispatch all busines and be gone. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e20360">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Since I haue your good leaue to goe away, </l>
          <l>I will make hast; but till I come againe, </l>
          <l>no bed shall ere be guiltie of my stay, </l>
          <l>nor rest be interposer twixt vs twaine. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e20430">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e20440">Enter the Iew, and Salerio, and Anthonio, and the Iaylor. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e20480">
          <speaker>Iew. </speaker>
          <l>Iaylor, looke to him, tell not me of mercie, </l>
          <l>this is the foole that lent out money gratis. </l>
          <l>Iaylor, looke to him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e20530">
          <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
          <l>Heare me yet good Shylock. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e20570">
          <speaker>Iew. </speaker>
          <l>Ile haue my bond, speake not against my bond, </l>
          <l>I haue sworne an oath, that I will haue my bond: </l>
          <l>thou call'dst me dogge before thou hadst a cause, </l>
          <l>but since I am a dog, beware my phanges, </l>
          <l>the Duke shall graunt me iustice, I do wonder </l>
          <l>thou naughtie Iaylor that thou art so fond </l>
          <l>to come abroade with him at his request. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e20670">
          <speaker>An. </speaker>
          <l>I pray thee heare me speake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e20700">
          <speaker>Iew. </speaker>
          <l>Ile haue my bond. I will not heare thee speake, </l>
          <l>Ile haue my bond, and therefore speake no more. </l>
          <l>Ile not be made a soft and dull eyde foole, </l>
          <l>to shake the head, relent, and sigh, and yeeld </l>
          <l>to christian intercessers: follow not, </l>
          <l>Ile haue no speaking, I will haue my bond. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e20790">Exit Iew. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e20800">
          <speaker>Sol. </speaker>
          <l>It is the most impenitrable curre </l>
          <l>that euer kept with men. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e20840">
          <speaker>An. </speaker>
          <l>Let him alone, </l>
          <l>Ile follow him no more with bootlesse prayers. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-023-a"/>
          <l>hee seekes my life, his reason well I know; </l>
          <l>I oft deliuerd from his forfeytures </l>
          <l>many that haue at times made mone to me, </l>
          <l>therefore he hates me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e20930">
          <speaker>Sal. </speaker>
          <l>I am sure the Duke will neuer grant </l>
          <l>this forfaiture to hold. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e20970">
          <speaker>An. </speaker>
          <l>The Duke cannot denie the course of law: </l>
          <l>for the commoditie that strangers haue </l>
          <l>with vs in Venice, if it be denyed, </l>
          <l>will much impeach the iustice of the state, </l>
          <l>since that the trade and profit of the citty </l>
          <l>consisteth of all Nations. Therefore goe, </l>
          <l>these griefes and losses haue so bated me </l>
          <l>that I shall hardly spare a pound of flesh </l>
          <l>to morrow, to my bloody Creditor. </l>
          <l>Well Iaylor on, pray God Bassanio come </l>
          <l>to see me pay his debt, and then I care not. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e21130">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e21140">Enter <hi>Portia, Nerrissa, Lorenzo, Iessica, </hi>and a man of Portias. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e21170">
          <speaker>Lor. </speaker>
          <l>Maddam, although I speake it in your presence, </l>
          <l>you haue a noble and a true conceite </l>
          <l>of god-like amitie, which appeares most strongly </l>
          <l>in bearing thus the absence of your Lord. </l>
          <l>But if you knew to whom you show this honour, </l>
          <l>how true a gentleman you send releefe, </l>
          <l>how decre a louer of my Lord your husband, </l>
          <l>I know you would be prouder of the worke </l>
          <l>then customarie bountie can enforce you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e21280">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>I neuer did repent for dooing good, </l>
          <l>nor shall not now: for in companions </l>
          <l>that doe conuerse and wast the time together, </l>
          <l>whose soules doe beare an egall yoke of loue, </l>
          <l>there must be needes a like proportion </l>
          <l>of lyniaments, of manners, and of spirit; </l>
          <l>which makes me thinke that this Anthonio </l>
          <l>beeing the bosome louer of my Lord, </l>
          <l>must needes be like my Lord. If it be so, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-023-b"/>
          <l>How little is the cost I haue bestowed </l>
          <l>in purchasing the semblance of my soule; </l>
          <l>From out the state of hellish cruelty, </l>
          <l>This comes too neere the praising of my selfe, </l>
          <l>Therefore no more of it: heere other things </l>
          <l>Lorenso I commit into your hands, </l>
          <l>The husbandry and mannage of my house, </l>
          <l>Vntill my Lords returne: for mine owne part </l>
          <l>I haue toward heauen breath'd a secret vowe, </l>
          <l>To liue in prayer and contemplation, </l>
          <l>Onely attended by Nerrissa heere, </l>
          <l>Vntill her husband and my Lords returne, </l>
          <l>There is a Monastry two miles off, </l>
          <l>And there we will abide. I doe desire you </l>
          <l>not to denie this imposition, </l>
          <l>the which my loue and some necessity </l>
          <l>now layes vpon you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e21590">
          <speaker>Lorens. </speaker>
          <l>Madame, with all my hart, </l>
          <l>I shall obey you in all faire commaunds. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e21630">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>My people doe already know my mind, </l>
          <l>And will acknowledge you and Jessica </l>
          <l>in place of Lord Bassanio and my selfe. </l>
          <l>So far you well till we shall meete againe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e21710">
          <speaker>Lor. </speaker>
          <l>Faire thoughts and happy houres attend on you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e21740">
          <speaker>Iessi. </speaker>
          <l>I wish your Ladiship all harts content. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e21780">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>I thank you for your wish, and am well pleasd </l>
          <l>to wish it back on you: far you well Jessica. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000838-e21830">Exeunt. </stage>
          <l>Now Balthaser, as I haue euer found thee honest true, </l>
          <l>So let me find thee still: take this same letter, </l>
          <l>and vse thou all th'indeuour of a man, </l>
          <l>In speede to Mantua see thou render this </l>
          <l>into my cosin hands Doctor Belario, </l>
          <l>And looke what notes and garments he doth giue thee, </l>
          <l>bring them I pray thee with imagin'd speede </l>
          <l>vnto the Tranect, to the common Ferrie </l>
          <l>which trades to Venice; wast no time in words </l>
          <l>but get thee gone, I shall be there before thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e21970">
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-024-a"/>
          <speaker>Baltha. </speaker>
          <l>Madam, I goe with all conuenient speede. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e22000">
          <speaker>Portia </speaker>
          <l>Come on Nerrissa, I haue worke in hand </l>
          <l>That you yet know not of; weele see our husbands </l>
          <l>before they thinke of vs? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e22060">
          <speaker>Nerrissa. </speaker>
          <l>Shall they see vs? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e22090">
          <speaker>Portia. </speaker>
          <l>They shall Nerrissa: but in such a habite, </l>
          <l>that they shall thinke we are accomplished </l>
          <l>with that we lacke; Ile hold thee any wager </l>
          <l>when we are both accoutered like young men, </l>
          <l>ile proue the prettier fellow of the two, </l>
          <l>and weare my dagger with the brauer grace, </l>
          <l>and speake betweene the change of man and boy, </l>
          <l>wi'h a reede voyce, and turne two minsing steps </l>
          <l>into a manly stride; and speake of frayes </l>
          <l>like a fine bragging youth: and tell quaint lyes </l>
          <l>how honorable Ladies sought my loue, </l>
          <l>which I denying, they fell sicke and dyed. </l>
          <l>I could not doe withall: then ile repent, </l>
          <l>and wish for all that, that I had not killd them; </l>
          <l>And twenty of these punie lies ile tell, </l>
          <l>that men shall sweare I haue discontinued schoole </l>
          <l>aboue a twelue-moneth: I haue within my minde </l>
          <l>a thousand raw tricks of these bragging lacks, </l>
          <l>which I will practise. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e22310">
          <speaker>Nerriss. </speaker>
          <l>Why, shall we turne to men? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e22340">
          <speaker>Portia. </speaker>
          <l>Fie, what a question's that, </l>
          <l>if thou wert nere a lewd interpreter: </l>
          <l>But come, ile tell thee all my my whole deuice </l>
          <l>when I am in my coach, which stayes for vs </l>
          <l>at the Parke gate; and therefore hast away, </l>
          <l>for we must measure twenty miles to day </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e22420">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e22430">Enter Clowne and Jessica. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e22440">
          <speaker>Clowne. </speaker>
          <p>Yes truly, for looke you, the sinnes of the Father are to be laid vpon the children, therefore I promise you, I feare you, I was alwaies plaine with you, and so now I speake my agitation of the matter: therefore be a good chere, for truly I thinke you are damnd, there is but one hope in it that can doe you any good, and <pb xml:id="ep000838-024-b"/>that is but a kinde of bastard hope neither. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e22470">
          <speaker>Iessica. </speaker>
          <p>And what hope is that I pray thee? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e22500">
          <speaker>Clowne. </speaker>
          <p>Marry you may partly hope that your Father got you not, that you are not the Iewes daughter. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e22530">
          <speaker>Jessica. </speaker>
          <p>That were a kind of bastard hope in deede, so the sinnes of my mother should be visited vpon me. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e22560">
          <speaker>Clowne. </speaker>
          <p>Truly then I feare you are damnd both by father and mother: thus when I shun Scilla your father, I fall into Caribdis your mother; well, you are gone both wayes. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e22610">
          <speaker>Iessica. </speaker>
          <p>I shall be sau'd by my husband, he hath made me a Christian? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e22640">
          <speaker>Clowne. </speaker>
          <p>Truly the more to blame he, we were Christians enow before, in as many as could well liue one by another: this making of Christians will raise the price of Hogs, if we grow all to be pork eaters, we shall not shortly haue a rasher on the coles for mony. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e22670">Enter Lorenzo. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e22680">
          <speaker>Iessi. </speaker>
          <p>Ile tell my husband Launcelet what you say, here he come? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e22720">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <p>I shall grow iealious of you shortly Launcelet, if you thus get my wife into corners? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e22760">
          <speaker>Jessica. </speaker>
          <p>Nay, you neede not feare vs <hi>Lorenzo, Launcelet </hi>and I are out, he tells me flatly there's no mercy for mee in heauen, because I am a Iewes daughter: and he sayes you are no good member of the common-wealth, for in conuerting Iewes to Christians, you raise the price of porke. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e22800">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <p>I shall aunswere that better to the common-wealth than you can the getting vp of the Negroes belly: the Moore is with child by you Launcelet? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e22840">
          <speaker>Clowne. </speaker>
          <p>It is much that the Moore should be more then reason: but if she be lesse then an honest woman, she is indeede more then I tooke her for. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e22870">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <p>How euery foole can play vpon the word, I thinke the best grace of wit will shortly turne into silence, and discourse grow commendable in none onely but Parrats: goe in sirra, bid them prepare for dinner? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e22900">
          <speaker>Clowne. </speaker>
          <p>That is done sir, they haue all stomacks? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e22930">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <p>Goodly Lord what a wit snapper are you, than bid them prepare dinner? </p>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-025-a"/>
          <l>to offices of tender curtesie: </l>
          <l>We all expect a gentle aunswere Iewe? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e22980">
          <speaker>Iewe. </speaker>
          <l>I haue possest your grace of what I purpose, </l>
          <l>and by our holy Sabaoth haue I sworne </l>
          <l>to haue the due and forfet of my bond, </l>
          <l>if you deny it, let the danger light </l>
          <l>vpon your charter and your Citties freedome? </l>
          <l>Youle aske me why I rather choose to haue </l>
          <l>a weight of carrion flesh, then to receaue </l>
          <l>three thousand ducats: Ile not aunswer that? </l>
          <l>But say it is my humour, is it aunswerd? </l>
          <l>What if my house be troubled with a Rat, </l>
          <l>and I be pleasd to giue ten thousand ducats </l>
          <l>to haue it baind? what, are you aunswerd yet? </l>
          <l>Some men there are loue not a gaping pigge? </l>
          <l>Some that are mad if they behold a Cat? </l>
          <l>And others when the bagpipe sings ith nose, </l>
          <l>cannot containe their vrine for affection. </l>
          <l>Maisters of passion swayes it to the moode </l>
          <l>of what it likes or loathes, now for your aunswer: </l>
          <l>As there is no firme reason to be rendred </l>
          <l>why he cannot abide a gaping pigge? </l>
          <l>why he a harmelesse necessarie Cat? </l>
          <l>why he a woollen bagpipe: but of force </l>
          <l>must yeeld to such in euitable shame, </l>
          <l>as to offend himselfe being offended: </l>
          <l>So can I giue no reason, nor I will not, </l>
          <l>more then a lodgd hate, and a certaine loathing </l>
          <l>I beare Anthonio, that I follow thus </l>
          <l>a loosing sute against him? are you aunswered? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e23300">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>This is no aunswer thou vnfeeling man, </l>
          <l>to excuse the currant of thy cruelty? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e23340">
          <speaker>Iewe. </speaker>
          <l>I am not bound to please thee with my answers? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e23380">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Doe all men kill the things they doe not loue? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e23410">
          <speaker>Iewe. </speaker>
          <l>Hates any man the thing he would not kill? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e23440">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Euery offence is not a hate at first? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e23470">
          <speaker>Iewe. </speaker>
          <l>What wouldst thou haue a serpent sting thee twice? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e23500">
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-025-b"/>
          <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
          <l>I pray you think you question with the Iewe, </l>
          <l>you may as well goe stand vpon the Beach </l>
          <l>and bid the maine flood bate his vsuall height, </l>
          <l>well vse question with the Woolfe, </l>
          <l>the Ewe bleake for the Lambe: </l>
          <l>You may as well forbid the mountaine of Pines </l>
          <l>to wag their high tops, and to make no noise </l>
          <l>when they are fretten with the gusts of heauen: </l>
          <l>You may as well doe any thing most hard </l>
          <l>as seeke to soften that then which what's harder: </l>
          <l>his Iewish hart? therefore I doe beseech you </l>
          <l>make no moe offers, vse no farther meanes, </l>
          <l>but will all briefe and plaine conueniencie </l>
          <l>let me haue iudgement, and the Iewe his will? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e23680">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>For thy three thousand ducats heere is sixe? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e23710">
          <speaker>Iewe. </speaker>
          <l>If euery ducat in sixe thousand ducats </l>
          <l>were in sixe parts, and euery part a ducat, </l>
          <l>I would not draw them, I would haue my bond? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e23780">
          <speaker>Duk. </speaker>
          <l>How shalt thou hope for mercy rendring none? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e23810">
          <speaker>Jewe. </speaker>
          <l>What iudgment shall I dread doing no wrong? </l>
          <l>you haue among you many a purchast slaue, </l>
          <l>which like your Asses, and your Dogs and Mules </l>
          <l>you vse in abiect and in slauish parts, </l>
          <l>because you bought them, shall I say to you, </l>
          <l>let them be free, marry them to your heires? </l>
          <l>why sweat they vnder burthens, let their beds </l>
          <l>be made as soft as yours, and let their pallats </l>
          <l>be seasond with such viands, you will aunswer </l>
          <l>the slaues are ours, so doe I aunswer you: </l>
          <l>The pound of flesh which I demaund of him </l>
          <l>is deerely bought, as mine and I will haue it: </l>
          <l>if you deny me, fie vpon your Law, </l>
          <l>there is no force in the decrees of Venice: </l>
          <l>I stand for iudgement, aunswer, shall I haue it? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e24040">
          <speaker>Duke. </speaker>
          <l>Vpon my power I may dismisse this Court, </l>
          <l>vnlesse Bellario a learned Doctor, </l>
          <l>whom I haue sent for to determine this </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-026-a"/>
          <l>Come heere to day? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e24130">
          <speaker>Salerio. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord, heere stayes without </l>
          <l>a messenger with letters from the Doctor, </l>
          <l>new come from Padua? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e24180">
          <speaker>Duke. </speaker>
          <l>Bring vs the letters? call the Messenger? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e24210">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Good cheere Anthonio? what man, courage yet: </l>
          <l>The Iew shall haue my flesh, blood, bones and all, </l>
          <l>ere thou shalt loose for me one drop of blood? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e24270">
          <speaker>Antho. </speaker>
          <l>I am a tainted weather of the flocke, </l>
          <l>meetest for death, the weakest kind of fruite </l>
          <l>drops earliest to the ground, and so let me; </l>
          <l>You cannot better be imployd Bassanio, </l>
          <l>then to liue still and write mine Epitaph? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e24360">Enter Nerrissa. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e24370">
          <speaker>Duke. </speaker>
          <l>Came you from Padua from Bellario? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e24410">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <l>From both? my L. Bellario greetes your grace? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e24450">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Why doost thou whet thy knife so earnestly? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e24480">
          <speaker>Iewe. </speaker>
          <l>To cut the forfaiture from that bankrout there? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e24510">
          <speaker>Gratia. </speaker>
          <l>Not on thy soule: but on thy soule harsh Iew </l>
          <l>thou makst thy knife keene: but no mettell can, </l>
          <l>no, not the hangmans axe beare halfe the keenenesse </l>
          <l>of thy sharpe enuie: can no prayers pearce thee? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e24570">
          <speaker>Iewe. </speaker>
          <l>No, none that thou hast wit enough to make▪ </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e24600">
          <speaker>Gratia. </speaker>
          <l>O be thou damnd, inexecrable dogge, </l>
          <l>And for thy life let iustice be accusd; </l>
          <l>Thou almost mak'st me wauer in my faith, </l>
          <l>to hold opinion with Pythagoras, </l>
          <l>that soules of Animalls infuse themselues </l>
          <l>into the trunks of men: Thy currish spirit </l>
          <l>gouernd a Woolfe, who hangd for humaine slaughter </l>
          <l>euen from the gallowes did his fell soule fleete, </l>
          <l>and whilest thou layest in thy vnhallowed dam; </l>
          <l>infusd it selfe in thee: for thy desires </l>
          <l>are woluish, bloody, staru'd, and rauenous. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e24740">
          <speaker>Iewe. </speaker>
          <l>Till thou canst raile the seale from off my bond, </l>
          <l>Thou but offendst thy lungs to speake so loud: </l>
          <l>Repaire thy wit good youth, or it will fall </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-026-b"/>
          <l>to curelesse ruine. I stand heere for law. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e24800">
          <speaker>Duke. </speaker>
          <l>This letter from Bellario doth commend </l>
          <l>a young and learned Doctor to our Court: </l>
          <l>Where is he? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e24860">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <l>He attendeth here hard by </l>
          <l>to know your aunswer whether youle admit him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e24900">
          <speaker>Duke. </speaker>
          <l>With all my hart: some three or foure of you </l>
          <l>goe giue him curteous conduct to this place, </l>
          <l>meane time the Court shall heare Bellarios letter. </l>
          <p>Your Grace shall vnderstand, that at the receit of your letter I am very sicke, but in the instant that your messenger came, in louing visitation was with me a young Doctor of Rome, his name is <hi>Balthazer: I </hi>acquainted him with the cause in controuersie between the Iew and Anthonio the Merchant, wee turnd ore many bookes together, hee is furnished with my opinion, which bettered with his owne learning, the greatnes whereof I cannot enough commend, comes with him at my importunitie, to fill vp your graces request in my stead. I beseech you let his lacke of yeeres be no impediment to let him lacke a reuerend estimation, for I neuer knew so young a body with so olde a head: I leaue him to your gracious acceptance, whose tryall shall better publish his commendation. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e25010">Enter Portia for Balthazer. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e25040">
          <speaker>Duke. </speaker>
          <l>You heare the learnd Bellario what he writes, </l>
          <l>and heere I take it is the doctor come. </l>
          <l>Giue me your hand, come you from old Bellario? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e25110">
          <speaker>Portia. </speaker>
          <l>I did my Lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e25150">
          <speaker>Duke. </speaker>
          <l>You are welcome, take your place: </l>
          <l>are you acquainted with the difference </l>
          <l>that holds this present question in the Court. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e25200">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>I am enformed throughly of the cause, </l>
          <l>which is the Merchant here? and which the Iew? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e25250">
          <speaker>Duke. </speaker>
          <l>Anthonio and old Shylocke, both stand forth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e25300">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Is your name Shylocke? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e25340">
          <speaker>Iew. </speaker>
          <l>Shylocke is my name. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e25380">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Of a strange nature is the sute you follow, </l>
          <l>yet in such rule, that the Venetian law </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-027-a"/>
          <l>cannot impugne you as you doe proceed. </l>
          <l>You stand within his danger, doe you not. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e25440">
          <speaker>An. </speaker>
          <l>I, so he sayes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e25470">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Doe you confesse the bond? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e25500">
          <speaker>An. </speaker>
          <l>I doe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e25530">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Then must the Iew be mercifull. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e25560">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <l>On what compulsion must I, tell me that. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e25590">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>The qualitie of mercie is not straind, </l>
          <l>it droppeth as the gentle raine from heauen </l>
          <l>vpon the place beneath: it is twise blest, </l>
          <l>it blesseth him that giues, and him that takes, </l>
          <l>tis mightiest in the mightiest, it becomes </l>
          <l>the throned Monarch better then his crowne. </l>
          <l>His scepter showes the force of temporall power, </l>
          <l>the attribut to awe and maiestie, </l>
          <l>wherein doth sit the dread and feare of Kings: </l>
          <l>but mercie is aboue this sceptred sway, </l>
          <l>it is enthroned in the harts of Kings, </l>
          <l>it is an attribut to God himselfe; </l>
          <l>and earthly power doth then show likest gods </l>
          <l>when mercie seasons iustice: therefore Jew, </l>
          <l>though iustice be thy plea, consider this, </l>
          <l>that in the course of iustice, none of vs </l>
          <l>should see saluation: we doe pray for mercy, </l>
          <l>and that same prayer, doth teach vs all to render </l>
          <l>the deedes of mercie. I haue spoke thus much </l>
          <l>to mittigate the iustice of thy plea, </l>
          <l>which if thou follow, this strict Court of Venice </l>
          <l>must needes giue sentence gainst the Merchant there. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e25830">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <l>My deeds vpon my head, I craue the law, </l>
          <l>the penalty and forfaite of my bond. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e25870">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Is he not able to discharge the money? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e25900">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Yes, heere I tender it for him in the Court, </l>
          <l>yea, twise the summe, if that will not suffise, </l>
          <l>I will be bound to pay it ten times ore </l>
          <l>on forfait of my hands, my head, my hart, </l>
          <l>if this will not suffise, it must appeare </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-027-b"/>
          <l>that malice beares downe truth. And I beseech you </l>
          <l>wrest once the law to your authoritie, </l>
          <l>to doe a great right, doe a little wrong, </l>
          <l>and curbe this cruell deuill of his will. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e26020">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>It must not be, there is no power in Venice </l>
          <l>can altar a decree established: </l>
          <l>twill be recorded for a precedent, </l>
          <l>and many an errour by the same example </l>
          <l>will rush into the state, it cannot be. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e26090">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <l>A Daniell come to iudgement: yea a Daniell. </l>
          <l>O wise young Iudge how I doe honour thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e26140">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>I pray you let me looke vpon the bond. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e26170">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <l>Heere tis most reuerend doctor, here it is. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e26200">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Shylocke theres thrice thy money offred thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e26240">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <l>An oath, an oath, I haue an oath in heauen, </l>
          <l>shall I lay periurie vpon my soule? </l>
          <l>Not not for Venice. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e26290">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Why this bond is forfait, </l>
          <l>and lawfully by this the Iew may claime </l>
          <l>a pound of flesh, to be by him cut off </l>
          <l>neerest the Merchants hart: be mercifull, </l>
          <l>take thrice thy money, bid me teare the bond. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e26360">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <l>When it is payd, according to the tenure. </l>
          <l>It doth appeare you are a worthy iudge, </l>
          <l>you know the law, your exposition </l>
          <l>hath beene most sound: I charge you by the law, </l>
          <l>whereof you are a well deseruing piller, </l>
          <l>proceede to iudgement: by my soule I sweare, </l>
          <l>there is no power in the tongue of man </l>
          <l>to alter me, I stay here on my Bond, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e26480">
          <speaker>An. </speaker>
          <l>Most hartelie I doe beseech the Court </l>
          <l>to giue the iudgement. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e26530">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Why than thus it is, </l>
          <l>you must prepare your bosome▪ for his knife. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e26570">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <l>O noble Iudge, ô excellent young man. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e26600">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>For the intent and purpose of the law </l>
          <l>hath full relation to the penaltie, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-028-a"/>
          <l>which heere appeareth due vpon the bond. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e26650">
          <speaker>Iew. </speaker>
          <l>Tis very true: o wise and vpright Iudge, </l>
          <l>how much more elder art thou then thy lookes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e26690">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Therefore lay bare your bosome. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e26720">
          <speaker>Jew. </speaker>
          <l>I, his breast, </l>
          <l>so sayes the bond, doth it not noble Iudge? </l>
          <l>Neerest his hart, those are the very words. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e26770">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>It is so, are there ballance here to weigh the flesh? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e26800">
          <speaker>Iew. </speaker>
          <l>I haue them ready. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e26830">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Haue by some Surgion Shylocke on your charge, </l>
          <l>to stop his wounds, least he doe bleede to death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e26880">
          <speaker>Iew. </speaker>
          <l>Is it so nominated in the bond? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e26910">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>It is not so exprest, but what of that? </l>
          <l>Twere good you doe so much for charitie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e26950">
          <speaker>Iew. </speaker>
          <l>I cannot finde it, tis not in the bond. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e26980">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>You Merchant, haue you any thing to say? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e27010">
          <speaker>Ant. </speaker>
          <l>But little; I am armd and well prepard, </l>
          <l>giue me your hand Bassanio, far you well, </l>
          <l>greeue not that I am falne to this for you: </l>
          <l>for heerein Fortune showes her selfe more kind </l>
          <l>then is her custome: it is still her vse </l>
          <l>to let the wretched man out-liue his wealth, </l>
          <l>to view with hollow eye and wrinckled brow </l>
          <l>an age of pouertie: from which lingring pennance </l>
          <l>of such misery doth she cut me of. </l>
          <l>Commend me to your honourable wife, </l>
          <l>tell her the processe of Anthonios end, </l>
          <l>say how I lou'd you, speake me faire in death: </l>
          <l>and when the tale is told, bid her be iudge </l>
          <l>whether Bassanio had not once a loue: </l>
          <l>Repent but you that you shall loose your friend </l>
          <l>and he repents not that he payes your debt. </l>
          <l>For if the Iew doe cut but deepe enough, </l>
          <l>Ile pay it instantly with all my hart. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e27260">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>
            <hi>Anthonio, I </hi>am married to a wife </l>
          <l>which is as deere to me as life it selfe, </l>
          <l>but life it selfe, my wife, and all the world, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-028-b"/>
          <l>are not with m●●●steemd aboue thy life. </l>
          <l>I would loose all I sacrifize them all </l>
          <l>heere to this deuill, to deliuer you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e27350">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Your wife would giue you little thankes for that </l>
          <l>if she were by to heare you make the offer. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e27390">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>I haue a wife who I protest I loue, </l>
          <l>I would she were in heauen, so she could </l>
          <l>intreate some power to change this currish Iew. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e27470">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <l>Tis well you offer it behind her back, </l>
          <l>the wish would make else an vnquiet house. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e27510">
          <speaker>Iew. </speaker>
          <l>These be the christian husbands, I haue a daughter </l>
          <l>would any of the stocke of Barrabas </l>
          <l>had beene her husband, rather then a Christian. </l>
          <l>We trifle time, I pray thee pursue sentence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e27590">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>A pound of that same Merchants flesh is thine, </l>
          <l>the Court awards it, and the law doth giue it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e27630">
          <speaker>Jew. </speaker>
          <l>Most rightfull Iudge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e27660">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>And you must cut this flesh from off his breast, </l>
          <l>the law alowes it, and the court awards it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e27700">
          <speaker>Jew. </speaker>
          <l>Most learned Iudge, a sentence, come prepare. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e27730">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Tarry a little, there is some thing else, </l>
          <l>this bond doth giue thee heere no iote of blood, </l>
          <l>the words expresly are a pound of flesh: </l>
          <l>take then thy bond, take thou thy pound of flesh, </l>
          <l>but in the cutting it, if thou doost shed </l>
          <l>one drop of Christian blood, thy lands and goods </l>
          <l>are by the lawes of Venice confiscate </l>
          <l>vnto the state of Venice. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e27830">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>O vpright Iudge, </l>
          <l>Marke Iew, ô learned Iudge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e27870">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <l>Is that the law? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e27900">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Thy selfe shalt see the Act: </l>
          <l>for as thou vrgest iustice, be assurd </l>
          <l>thou shalt haue iustice more then thou desirst. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e27950">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>O learned iudge, mark Iew, a learned iudge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e27980">
          <speaker>Iew. </speaker>
          <l>I take this offer then, pay the bond thrice </l>
          <l>and let the Christian goe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e28020">
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-029-a"/>
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Heere is the money. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e28050">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Soft, the Iew shal haue all iustice, soft no hast, </l>
          <l>he shall haue nothing but the penalty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e28090">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>O Iew, an vpright Iudge, a learned Iudge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e28120">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Therefore prepare thee to cut of the flesh, </l>
          <l>Shed thou no blood, nor cut thou lesse nor more </l>
          <l>but iust a pound of flesh: if thou tak'st more </l>
          <l>or lesse then a iust pound, be it but so much </l>
          <l>as makes it light of heauy in the substance, </l>
          <l>or the deuision of the twentith part </l>
          <l>of one poore scruple, nay if the scale doe turne </l>
          <l>but in the estimation of a hayre, </l>
          <l>thou dyest, and all thy goods are confiscate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e28230">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>A second Daniell, a Daniell Iew, </l>
          <l>now infidell I haue you on the hip. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e28280">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Why doth the Iew pause, take thy forfaiture. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e28310">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <l>Giue me my principall, and let me goe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e28340">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>I haue it ready for thee, here it is. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e28370">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Hee hath refusd it in the open Court, </l>
          <l>hee shall haue meerely iustice and his bond. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e28410">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>A Daniell still say I, a second Daniell, </l>
          <l>I thanke thee Iew for teaching me that word. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e28470">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <l>Shall I not haue barely my principall? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e28510">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Thou shalt haue nothing but the forfaiture </l>
          <l>to be so taken at thy perrill Iew. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e28550">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <l>Why then the deuill giue him good of it: </l>
          <l>Ile stay no longer question. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e28590">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Tarry Iew, </l>
          <l>the law hath yet another hold on you. </l>
          <l>It is enacted in the lawes of Venice, </l>
          <l>if it be proued against an alien, </l>
          <l>that by direct, or indirect attempts </l>
          <l>he seeke the life of any Citizen, </l>
          <l>the party gainst the which he doth contriue, </l>
          <l>shall seaze one halfe his goods, the other halfe </l>
          <l>comes to the priuie cofler of the State, </l>
          <l>and the offenders life lies in the mercy </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-029-b"/>
          <l>of the Duke onely, gainst all other voyce. </l>
          <l>In which predicament I say thou standst: </l>
          <l>for it appeares by manifest proceeding, </l>
          <l>that indirectly, and directly to </l>
          <l>thou hast contriued against the very life </l>
          <l>of the defendant: and thou hast incurd </l>
          <l>the danger formorly by me rehearst. </l>
          <l>Downe therefore, and beg mercie of the Duke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e28790">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>Beg that thou maist haue leaue to hang thy selfe, </l>
          <l>and yet thy wealth beeing forfait to the state, </l>
          <l>thou hast not left the value of a cord, </l>
          <l>therefore thou must be hangd at the states charge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e28850">
          <speaker>Duke. </speaker>
          <l>That thou shalt see the difference of our spirit </l>
          <l>I pardon thee thy life before thou aske it: </l>
          <l>for halfe thy wealth, it is Anthonios, </l>
          <l>the other halfe comes to the generall state, </l>
          <l>which humblenes may driue vnto a fine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e28930">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>I for the state, not for Anthonio. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e28970">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <l>Nay, take my life and all, pardon not that, </l>
          <l>you take my house, when you doe take the prop </l>
          <l>that doth sustaine my house: you take my life </l>
          <l>when you doe take the meanes whereby I liue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e29040">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>What mercy can you render him Anthonio? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e29080">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>A halter gratis, nothing else for Godsake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e29110">
          <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
          <l>So please my Lord the Duke, &amp; all the Court </l>
          <l>to quit the fine for one halfe of his goods, </l>
          <l>I am content: so he will let me haue </l>
          <l>the other halfe in vse, to render it </l>
          <l>vpon his death vnto the Gentleman </l>
          <l>that lately stole his daughter. </l>
          <l>Two things prouided more, that for this fauour </l>
          <l>he presently become a Christian: </l>
          <l>the other, that he doe record a gift </l>
          <l>heere in the Court of all he dies possest </l>
          <l>vnto his sonne Lorenzo and his daughter. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e29250">
          <speaker>Duke. </speaker>
          <l>He shall doe this, or else I doe recant </l>
          <l>the pardon that I late pronounced heere. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e29290">
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-030-a"/>
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Art thou contented Iew? what dost thou say? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e29320">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <l>I am content. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e29350">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Clarke, draw a deede of gift. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e29380">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <l>I pray you giue me leaue to goe from hence, </l>
          <l>I am not well, send the deede after me, </l>
          <l>and I will signe it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e29430">
          <speaker>Duke. </speaker>
          <l>Get thee gone, but doe it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e29460">
          <speaker>Shy. </speaker>
          <l>In christning shalt thou haue two Godfathers, </l>
          <l>had I beene iudge, thou shouldst haue had ten more, </l>
          <l>to bring thee to the gallowes, not to the font. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e29510">Exit. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e29520">
          <speaker>Duke. </speaker>
          <l>Sir I entreate you home with me to dinner. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e29550">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>I humbly doe desire your Grace of pardon, </l>
          <l>I must away this night toward Padua, </l>
          <l>and it is meete I presently set forth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e29610">
          <speaker>Duke. </speaker>
          <l>I am sorry that your leysure serues you not. </l>
          <l>Anthonio, gratifie this gentleman, </l>
          <l>for in my mind you are much bound to him. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e29670">Exit Duke and his traine. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e29680">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Most worthy gentleman, I and my friend </l>
          <l>haue by your wisedome been this day aquitted </l>
          <l>of greeuous penalties, in Iewe whereof, </l>
          <l>three thousand ducats due vnto the Iew </l>
          <l>wee freely cope your curtious paines withall. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e29750">
          <speaker>An. </speaker>
          <l>And stand indebted ouer and aboue </l>
          <l>in loue and seruice to you euer-more. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e29790">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Hee is well payd that is well satisfied, </l>
          <l>and I deliuering you, am satisfied, </l>
          <l>and therein doe account my selfe well payd, </l>
          <l>my minde was neuer yet more mercinarie. </l>
          <l>I pray you know me when we meete againe, </l>
          <l>I wish you well, and so I take my leaue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e29870">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Deere sir, of force I must attempt you further, </l>
          <l>take some remembrance of vs as a tribute, </l>
          <l>not as fee: graunt me two things I pray you, </l>
          <l>not to deny me, and to pardon me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e29940">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>You presse me farre, and therefore I wil yeeld, </l>
          <l>giue mee your gloues, Ile weare them for your sake, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-030-b"/>
          <l>and for your loue ile take this ring from you, </l>
          <l>doe not draw back your hand, ile take no more, </l>
          <l>and you in loue shall not denie me this? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e30020">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>This ring good sir, alas it is a trifle, </l>
          <l>I will not shame my selfe to giue you this? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e30060">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>I will haue nothing else but onely this, </l>
          <l>and now me thinks I haue a minde to it? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e30100">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>There's more depends on this then on the valew, </l>
          <l>the dearest ring in Venice will I giue you, </l>
          <l>and finde it out by proclamation, </l>
          <l>onely for this I pray you pardon me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e30160">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>I see sir you are liberall in offers, </l>
          <l>you taught me first to beg, and now me thinks </l>
          <l>you teach me how a begger should be aunswerd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e30210">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Good sir, this ring was giuen me by my wife, </l>
          <l>and when she put it on, she made me vowe </l>
          <l>that I should neither sell, nor giue, nor loose it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e30260">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>That scuse serues many men to saue their gifts, </l>
          <l>and if your wife be not a mad woman, </l>
          <l>and know how well I haue deseru'd this ring, </l>
          <l>she would not hold out enemy for euer </l>
          <l>for giuing it to me: well, peace be with you. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e30330">Exeunt. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e30340">
          <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
          <l>My L. Bassanio, let him haue the ring, </l>
          <l>let his deseruings and my loue withall </l>
          <l>be valued gainst your wiues commaundement. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e30400">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Goe Gratiano, runne and ouer-take him, </l>
          <l>giue him the ring, and bring him if thou canst </l>
          <l>vnto Anthonios house, away, make hast. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000838-e30470">Exit Gratiano. </stage>
          <l>Come, you and I will thither presently, </l>
          <l>and in the morning early will we both </l>
          <l>flie toward Belmont, come Anthonio. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e30520">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e30530">Enter Nerrissa. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e30540">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Enquire the Iewes house out, giue him this deed, </l>
          <l>and let him signe it, weele away to night, </l>
          <l>and be a day before our husbands home: </l>
          <l>this deede will be well welcome to Lorenzo? </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-031-a"/>
          <stage xml:id="ep000838-e30610">Enter Gratiano. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e30620">
          <speaker>Grati. </speaker>
          <l>Faire sir, you are well ore-tane: </l>
          <l>My L. Bassanio vpon more aduice, </l>
          <l>hath sent you heere this ring, and doth intreate </l>
          <l>your company at dinner. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e30690">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>That cannot be; </l>
          <l>his ring I doe accept most thankfully, </l>
          <l>and so I pray you tell him: furthermore, </l>
          <l>I pray you shew my youth old Shylockes house. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e30760">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>That will I doe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e30790">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <l>Sir, I would speake with you: </l>
          <l>Ile see if I can get my husbands ring </l>
          <l>which I did make him sweare to keepe for euer. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e30860">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Thou maist I warrant, we shal haue old swearing </l>
          <l>that they did giue the rings away to men; </l>
          <l>but wele out-face them, and out-sweare them to: </l>
          <l>away, make hast, thou knowst where I will tarry. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e30920">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <l>Come good sir, will yov shew me to this house. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e30950">Enter Lorenzo and Iessica. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e30960">
          <speaker>Lor. </speaker>
          <l>The moone shines bright. In such a night as this, </l>
          <l>when the sweet winde did gently kisse the trees, </l>
          <l>and they did make no noyse, in such a night </l>
          <l>Troylus me thinks mounted the Troian walls, </l>
          <l>and sigh'd his soule toward the Grecian tents </l>
          <l>where Cressed lay that night. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e31060">
          <speaker>Jessi. </speaker>
          <l>In such a night </l>
          <l>did Thisbie fearefully ore-trip the dewe, </l>
          <l>and saw the Lyons shadow ere him selfe, </l>
          <l>and ranne dismayed away. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e31130">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>In such a night </l>
          <l>stoode Dido with a willow in her hand </l>
          <l>vpon the wilde sea banks, and waft her Loue </l>
          <l>to come againe to Carthage. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e31200">
          <speaker>Iessi. </speaker>
          <l>In such a night </l>
          <l>Medea gathered the inchanted hearbs </l>
          <l>that did renew old Eson. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e31270">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>In such a night </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-031-b"/>
          <l>did Iessica steale from the wealthy Iewe, </l>
          <l>and with an vnthrift loue did runne from Venice, </l>
          <l>as farre as Belmont. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e31340">
          <speaker>Iessi. </speaker>
          <l>In such a night </l>
          <l>did young Lorenzo sweare he loued her well, </l>
          <l>stealing her soule with many vowes of faith, </l>
          <l>and nere a true one. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e31410">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>In such a night </l>
          <l>did pretty Iessica (like a little shrow) </l>
          <l>slaunder her Loue, and he forgaue it her. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e31470">
          <speaker>Iessi. </speaker>
          <l>I would out-night you did no body come: </l>
          <l>But harke, I heare the footing of a man. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e31510">Enter a Messenger. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e31520">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>Who comes so fast in silence of the night? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e31550">
          <speaker>Messen. </speaker>
          <l>A friend? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e31580">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>A friend, what friend, your name I pray you friend? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e31610">
          <speaker>Mess. </speaker>
          <l>Stephano is my name, and I bring word </l>
          <l>my Mistres will before the breake of day </l>
          <l>be heere at Belmont, she doth stray about </l>
          <l>by holy crosses where she kneeles and prayes </l>
          <l>for happy wedlock houres. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e31690">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>Who comes with her? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e31720">
          <speaker>Mess. </speaker>
          <l>None but a holy Hermit and her mayd: </l>
          <l>I pray you is my Maister yet returnd? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e31760">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>He is not, nor we haue not heard from him, </l>
          <l>But goe we in I pray thee Iessica, </l>
          <l>and ceremoniously let vs prepare </l>
          <l>some welcome for the Mistres of the house. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e31830">Enter Clowne. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e31840">
          <speaker>Clowne. </speaker>
          <l>Sola, sola: wo ha, ho sola, sola. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e31870">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>Who calls? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e31900">
          <speaker>Clo. </speaker>
          <l>Sola, did you see M. Lorenzo, &amp; M. Lorenzo sola, sola. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e31950">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>Leaue hollowing man, heere. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e31980">
          <speaker>Clowne. </speaker>
          <l>Sola, where, where? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e32010">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>Heere? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e32040">
          <speaker>Clow. </speaker>
          <p>Tell him there's a Post come from my Maister, with his horne full of good newes, my Maister will be heere ere morning sweete soule. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e32070">
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-032-a"/>
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>Let's in, and there expect their comming. </l>
          <l>And yet no matter: why should we goe in. </l>
          <l>My friend Stephen, signifie pray you </l>
          <l>within the house, your mistres is at hand, </l>
          <l>and bring your musique foorth into the ayre. </l>
          <l>How sweet the moone-light sleepes vpon this banke, </l>
          <l>heere will we sit, and let the sounds of musique </l>
          <l>creepe in our eares soft stilnes, and the night </l>
          <l>become the tutches of sweet harmonie: </l>
          <l>sit Iessica, looke how the floore of heauen </l>
          <l>is thick inlayed with pattens of bright gold, </l>
          <l>there's not the smallest orbe which thou beholdst </l>
          <l>but in his motion like an Angell sings, </l>
          <l>still quiring to the young eyde Cherubins; </l>
          <l>such harmonie is in immortall soules, </l>
          <l>but whilst this muddy vesture of decay </l>
          <l>dooth grosly close it in, we cannot heare it: </l>
          <l>Come hoe, and wake Diana with a himne, </l>
          <l>with sweetest tutches pearce your mistres eare, </l>
          <l>and draw her home with musique. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e32320">play Musique. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e32330">
          <speaker>Iessi. </speaker>
          <l>I am neuer merry when I heare sweet musique. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e32360">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>The reason is▪ your spirits are attentiue: </l>
          <l>for doe but note a wild and wanton heard </l>
          <l>or race of youthfull and vnhandled colts </l>
          <l>fetching mad bounds, bellowing and neghing loude, </l>
          <l>which is the hote condition of their blood, </l>
          <l>if they but heare perchance a trumpet sound, </l>
          <l>or any ayre of musique touch their eares, </l>
          <l>you shall perceaue them make a mutuall stand, </l>
          <l>their sauage eyes turn'd to a modest gaze, </l>
          <l>by the sweet power of musique: therefore the Poet </l>
          <l>did faine that Orpheus drew trees, stones, and floods. </l>
          <l>Since naught so stockish hard and full of rage, </l>
          <l>but musique for the time doth change his nature, </l>
          <l>the man that hath no musique in himselfe, </l>
          <l>nor is not moued with concord of sweet sounds, </l>
          <l>is fit for treasons, stratagems, and spoiles, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-032-b"/>
          <l>the motions of his spirit are dull as night, </l>
          <l>and his affections darke as Terebus: </l>
          <l>let no such man be trusted: marke the musique. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e32580">Enter Portia and Nerrissa. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e32590">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>That light we see is burning in my hall: </l>
          <l>how farre that little candell throwes his beames, </l>
          <l>so shines a good deede in a naughty world. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e32640">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <l>When the moone shone we did not see the candle? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e32670">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>So dooth the greater glory dim the lesse, </l>
          <l>a substitute shines brightly as a King </l>
          <l>vntill a King be by, and then his state </l>
          <l>empties it selfe, as doth an inland brooke </l>
          <l>into the maine of waters: musique harke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e32740">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <l>It is your musique Madame of the house? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e32770">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Nothing is good I see without respect, </l>
          <l>me thinks it sounds much sweeter then by day? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e32810">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <l>Silence bestowes that vertue on it Madam? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e32840">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>The Crow doth sing as sweetly as the Larke </l>
          <l>when neither is attended: and I thinke </l>
          <l>the Nightingale if she should sing by day </l>
          <l>when euery Goose is cackling, would be thought </l>
          <l>no better a Musition then the Renne? </l>
          <l>How many things by season, seasond are </l>
          <l>to their right prayse, and true perfection: </l>
          <l>Peace, how the moone sleepes with Endimion, </l>
          <l>and would not be awak'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e32950">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>That is the voyce, </l>
          <l>or I am much deceau'd of Portia. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e33010">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>He knowes me as the blind man knowes the Cuckoe </l>
          <l>by the bad voyce? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e33050">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>Deere Lady welcome home? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e33080">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>We haue bin praying for our husbands welfare, </l>
          <l>which speed we hope the better for our words: </l>
          <l>are they return'd? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e33130">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>Madam, they are not yet: </l>
          <l>but there is come a Messenger before </l>
          <l>to signifie their comming? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e33180">
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-033-a"/>
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Goe in Nerrissa. </l>
          <l>Giue order to my seruants, that they take </l>
          <l>no note at all of our being absent hence, </l>
          <l>nor you <hi>Lorenzo, Jessica </hi>nor you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e33260">
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>Your husband is at hand, I heare his trumpet, </l>
          <l>we are no tell-tales Madame, feare you not. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e33300">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>This night me thinks is but the day light sicke, </l>
          <l>it lookes a little paler, tis a day, </l>
          <l>such as the day is when the sunne is hid. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e33350">Enter Bassanio, Anthonio, Gratiano, and their followers. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e33360">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>We should hold day with the Antipodes, </l>
          <l>if you would walke in absence of the sunne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e33400">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Let me giue light, but let me not be light, </l>
          <l>for a light wife doth make a heauie husband, </l>
          <l>and neuer be Bassanio so for me, </l>
          <l>but God sort all: you are welcome home my Lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e33470">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>I thank you Madam, giue welcome to my friend, </l>
          <l>this is the man, this is Anthonio, </l>
          <l>to whom I am so infinitely bound. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e33530">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>You should in all sence be much bound to him, </l>
          <l>for as I heare he was much bound for you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e33570">
          <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
          <l>No more then I am well acquitted of. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e33600">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Sir, you are very welcome to our house: </l>
          <l>it must appeare in other wayes then words, </l>
          <l>therefore I scant this breathing curtesie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e33650">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>By yonder moone I sweare you doe me wrong, </l>
          <l>infaith I gaue it to the Iudges Clarke, </l>
          <l>would he were gelt that had it for my part, </l>
          <l>since you doe take it Loue so much at hart. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e33710">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>A quarrell hoe already, what's the matter? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e33740">
          <speaker>Grati. </speaker>
          <l>About a hoope of gold, a paltry ring </l>
          <l>that she did giue me, whose posie was </l>
          <l>for all the world like Cutlers poetry </l>
          <l>vpon a knife, <hi>Loue me, and leaue me not. </hi>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e33810">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <l>What talke you of the posie or the valew: </l>
          <l>You swore to me when I did giue you, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-033-b"/>
          <l>that you would weare it till your houre of death, </l>
          <l>and that it should lie with you in your graue, </l>
          <l>though not for me, yet for your vehement oathes, </l>
          <l>you should haue beene respectiue and haue kept it. </l>
          <l>Gaue it a Iudges Clarke: no Gods my Iudge </l>
          <l>the Clarke will nere weare haire ons face that had it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e33910">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>He will, and if he liue to be a man. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e33940">
          <speaker>Nerrissa. </speaker>
          <l>I, if a woman liue to be a man. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e33970">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>Now by this hand I gaue it to a youth, </l>
          <l>a kind of boy, a little scrubbed boy, </l>
          <l>no higher then thy selfe, the Iudges Clarke, </l>
          <l>a prating boy that begd it as a fee, </l>
          <l>I could not for my hart deny it him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e34040">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>You were to blame, I must be plaine with you, </l>
          <l>to part so slightly with your wiues first gift, </l>
          <l>a thing stuck on with oaths vpon your finger, </l>
          <l>and so riueted with faith vnto your flesh. </l>
          <l>I gaue my Loue a ring, and made him sweare </l>
          <l>neuer to part with it, and heere he stands: </l>
          <l>I dare be sworne for him he would not leaue it, </l>
          <l>nor pluck it from his finger, for the wealth </l>
          <l>that the world maisters. Now in faith Gratiano </l>
          <l>you giue your wife too vnkind a cause of griefe, </l>
          <l>and twere to me I should be mad at it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e34180">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Why I were best to cut my left hand off, </l>
          <l>and sweare I lost the ring defending it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e34220">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord Bassanio gaue his ring away </l>
          <l>vnto the Iudge that begd it, and indeede </l>
          <l>deseru'd it to? and then the boy his Clarke </l>
          <l>that tooke some paines in writing, he begd mine, </l>
          <l>and neither man nor maister would take ought </l>
          <l>but the two rings. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e34310">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>What ring gaue you my Lord? </l>
          <l>Not that I hope which you receau'd of me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e34350">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>If I could add a lie vnto a fault, </l>
          <l>I would deny it: but you see my finger </l>
          <l>hath not the ring vpon it, it is gone. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e34400">
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-034-a"/>
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Euen so voyd is your false hart of truth. </l>
          <l>By heauen I will nere come in your bed </l>
          <l>vntill I see the ring? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e34460">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <l>Nor I in yours </l>
          <l>till I againe see mine? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e34500">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Sweet Portia, </l>
          <l>if you did know to whom I gaue the ring, </l>
          <l>if you did know for whom I gaue the ring, </l>
          <l>and would conceaue for what I gaue the ring, </l>
          <l>and how vnwillingly I left the ring, </l>
          <l>when naught would be accepted but the ring, </l>
          <l>you would abate the strength of your displeasure? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e34620">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>If you had knowne the vertue of the ring, </l>
          <l>or halfe her worthines that gaue the ring, </l>
          <l>or your owne honour to containe the ring, </l>
          <l>you would not then haue parted with the ring: </l>
          <l>what man is there so much vnreasonable </l>
          <l>if you had pleasd to haue defended it </l>
          <l>with any termes of zeale: wanted the modesty </l>
          <l>to vrge the thing held as a ceremonie: </l>
          <l>Nerrissa teaches me what to beleeue, </l>
          <l>ile die for't, but some woman had the ring? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e34750">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>No by my honour Madam, by my soule </l>
          <l>no woman had it, but a ciuill Doctor, </l>
          <l>which did refuse three thousand ducats of me, </l>
          <l>and begd the ring, the which I did denie him, </l>
          <l>and sufferd him to goe displeasd away, </l>
          <l>euen he that had held vp the very life </l>
          <l>of my deere friend. What should I say sweet Lady, </l>
          <l>I was inforc'd to send it after him, </l>
          <l>I was beset with shame and curtesie, </l>
          <l>my honour would not let ingratitude </l>
          <l>so much besmere it: pardon me good Lady, </l>
          <l>for by these blessed candels of the night, </l>
          <l>had you been there, I think you would haue begd </l>
          <l>the ring of me to giue the worthy Doctor? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e34920">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Let not that Doctor ere come neere my house </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-034-b"/>
          <l>since he hath got the iewell that I loued, </l>
          <l>and that which you did sweare to keepe for me, </l>
          <l>I will become as liberall as you, </l>
          <l>Ile not deny him any thing I haue, </l>
          <l>no, not my body, nor my husbands bed: </l>
          <l>Know him I shall, I am well sure of it. </l>
          <l>Lie not a night from home. Watch me like Argos, </l>
          <l>if you doe not, if I be left alone, </l>
          <l>now by mine honour which is yet mine owne. </l>
          <l>ile haue that Doctor for mine bedfellow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e35050">
          <speaker>Nerrissa. </speaker>
          <l>And I his Clark: therefore be well aduisd </l>
          <l>how you doe leaue me to mine owne protection. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e35090">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>Well doe you so: let not me take him then, </l>
          <l>for if I doe, ile mar the young Clarks pen. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e35130">
          <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
          <l>I am th'vnhappy subiect of these quarrells. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e35160">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Sir, greeue not you, you are welcome notwithstanding. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e35190">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Portia, forgiue me this enforced wrong, </l>
          <l>and in the hearing of these many friends </l>
          <l>I sweare to thee, euen by thine owne faire eyes </l>
          <l>wherein I see my selfe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e35260">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Marke you but that? </l>
          <l>In both my eyes he doubly sees himselfe: </l>
          <l>In each eye one, sweare by your double selfe, </l>
          <l>and there's an oath of credite. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e35320">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Nay, but heare me. </l>
          <l>Pardon this fault, and by my soule I sweare </l>
          <l>I neuer more will breake an oath with thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e35370">
          <speaker>Anth. </speaker>
          <l>I once did lend my body for his wealth, </l>
          <l>which but for him that had your husbands ring </l>
          <l>had quite miscaried. I dare be bound againe, </l>
          <l>my soule vpon the forfet, that your Lord </l>
          <l>will neuer more breake faith aduisedly. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e35450">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Then you shall be his surety: giue him this, </l>
          <l>and bid him keepe it better then the other. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e35490">
          <speaker>Antho. </speaker>
          <l>Here Lord Bassanio, sweare to keepe this ring. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e35530">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>By heauen it is the same I gaue the Doctor. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e35560">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>I had it of him: pardon me Bassanio, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-035-a"/>
          <l>for by this ring the Doctor lay with me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e35610">
          <speaker>Nerrissa. </speaker>
          <l>And pardon me my gentle Gratiano, </l>
          <l>for that same scrubbed boy the Doctors Clarke </l>
          <l>in liew of this, last night did he with me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e35670">
          <speaker>Grati. </speaker>
          <l>Why this is like the mending of high wayes </l>
          <l>in Sommer where the wayes are faire enough? </l>
          <l>What, are we cuckolds ere we haue deseru'd it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e35720">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>Speake not so grosly, you are all amaz'd; </l>
          <l>Heere is a letter, reade it at your leasure, </l>
          <l>It comes from Padua from Bellario, </l>
          <l>there you shall finde that Portia was the Doctor, </l>
          <l>Nerrissa there her Clarke. Lorenzo heere </l>
          <l>shall witnes I set foorth as soone as you, </l>
          <l>and euen but now returnd: I haue not yet </l>
          <l>enterd my house. Anthonio you are welcome, </l>
          <l>and I haue better newes in store for you </l>
          <l>than you exspect: vnseale this letter soone, </l>
          <l>there you shall finde three of your Argosies </l>
          <l>are richly come to harbour sodainly. </l>
          <l>You shall not know by what strange accident </l>
          <l>I chaunced on this letter. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e35950">
          <speaker>Antho. </speaker>
          <l>I am dumb? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e35990">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>Were you the Doctor, and I knew you not? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e36030">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>Were you the Clark that is to make me cuckold. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e36060">
          <speaker>Ner. </speaker>
          <l>I but the Clarke that neuer meanes to doe it, </l>
          <l>vnlesse he liue vntill he be a man. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e36110">
          <speaker>Bass. </speaker>
          <l>(Sweet Doctor) you shall be my bedfellow, </l>
          <l>when I am absent then lie with my wife. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e36160">
          <speaker>An. </speaker>
          <l>(Sweet Lady) you haue giuen me life and lyuing; </l>
          <l>for heere I reade for certaine that my ships </l>
          <l>are safely come to Rode. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e36220">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>How now Lorenzo? </l>
          <l>my Clarke hath some good comforts to for you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e36270">
          <speaker>Ner </speaker>
          <l>I, and ile giue them him without a fee. </l>
          <l>There doe I giue to you and Iessica </l>
          <l>from the rich Iewe, a speciall deede of gift </l>
          <l>after his death, of all he dies possest of. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e36360">
          <pb xml:id="ep000838-035-b"/>
          <speaker>Loren. </speaker>
          <l>Faire Ladies, you drop Manna in the way </l>
          <l>of starued people. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e36400">
          <speaker>Por. </speaker>
          <l>It is almost morning, </l>
          <l>and yet I am sure you are not satisfied </l>
          <l>of these euents at full. Let vs goe in, </l>
          <l>and charge vs there vpon intergotories, </l>
          <l>and we will aunswer all things faithfully. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="ep000838-e36480">
          <speaker>Gra. </speaker>
          <l>Let it be so, the first intergory </l>
          <l>that my Nerrissa shall be sworne on, is, </l>
          <l>whether till the next night she had rather stay, </l>
          <l>or goe to bed now being two houres to day: </l>
          <l>But were the day come, I should wish it darke </l>
          <l>till I were couching with the Doctors Clarke. </l>
          <l>Well, while I liue, ile feare no other thing </l>
          <l>so sore, as keeping safe Nerrissas ring. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000838-e36630">Exeunt. </stage>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
