<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The rape of Lucrece, committed by Tarquin the sixt; and the remarkable judgments that befel him for it. / By the incomparable master of our English poetry, Will: Shakespeare gent. Whereunto is annexed, The banishment of Tarquin: or, the reward of lust. By J. Quarles.</title>
        <author>
<!--Shakespeare, William,-->
          <persName>
            <forename>William</forename>
            <surname>Shakespeare</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <idno type="dracor" xml:base="https://dracor.org/id/">ep000845</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://earlyprint.org</idno>
          <availability>
            <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this EEBO-TCP Phase II text, in whole or in part.</p>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull>
              <titleStmt>
                <title>The rape of Lucrece, committed by Tarquin the sixt; and the remarkable judgments that befel him for it. / By the incomparable master of our English poetry, Will: Shakespeare gent. Whereunto is annexed, The banishment of Tarquin: or, the reward of lust. By J. Quarles.</title>
                <author>Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616.</author>
                <author>Quarles, John, 1624-1665. Tarquin banished: or, The reward of lust.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[6], 71, [5], 12 p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Printed by J.G. for John Stafford in George-yard neer Fleet-bridge, and Will: Gilbertson at the Bible in Giltspur-street,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London. :</pubPlace>
                <date>1655.</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>"Tarquin banished: or, The revvard of lust" has separate dated title page; identified as E.1672[4] on Thomason Tracts.</note>
                <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 31".</note>
                <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library.</note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000845-e10030">
        <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000845-001-a"/>
        <p>TARQVIN BANISHED: OR, THE REWARD Of LUST. </p>
        <p>Written by <hi>J. Q.</hi>
        </p>
        <q cert="high" xml:lang="lat">Quicquid boni cum discretione feceris, virtus est; quicquid sine discretione gesseris, vitium est: virtus enim indiscreta pro vitio deputatur. </q>
        <p>LONDON. Printed by <hi>J. G. </hi>for <hi>John Stafford </hi>at Fleet-bridge, and <hi>Will: Gilbertson </hi>in Giltspur-street. 1655. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="to_the_reader" xml:id="ep000845-e10140">
        <pb xml:id="ep000845-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000845-002-b"/>
        <head>To the READER. </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Kinde Reader, </salute>
        </opener>
        <p>I Am confident when thou doest seriously consider the unworthinesse of the Action, thou wilt not approve of the Actor; for, after he had received those many civilities which the house of chast Lucretia could afford, he with an unheard-of violence, requited her with a most barbarous rape, which cause not only his banishment, but likewise cost the lives of many of the Nobility; nay, and the King himself in defence of his son, the Ravisher, <pb xml:id="ep000845-003-a"/>lost his life; and that which wa● more than all, was the losse of Lucretia's life: for the sense of the fact, made her stab her self; so died poor Lucretia, blameable in nothing but that she was the Author of her own death: So Reader, as thou hast before read Tarqiun ●s offence, thou mayst now read his punishment. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute>And so farewell. </salute>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000845-e10270">
        <pb n="1" xml:id="ep000845-003-b"/>
        <head>TARQVIN <hi>Banished: OR</hi>, The reward of Lust. </head>
        <lg>
          <l>TIs seldome known that good effects attend </l>
          <l>Upon bad causes; Tarquin, to befriend </l>
          <l>His own desires, contaminates his will, </l>
          <l>And blasts that vertue, which before did fill </l>
          <l>The ears of Rome, and made it to proclame </l>
          <l>The future hopes of his encreasing name. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>May we not judge him wise that loves to spend </l>
          <l>Ere he begins, some thoughts upon the end </l>
          <l>Of his designe, had Pha'ton done the same </l>
          <l>He had not turn'd the world into a flame. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>The acts of Catiline, were noble deeds </l>
          <l>Compar'd to this, this horrid act exceeds </l>
          <l>Horror it self; Oh what obdurate breast </l>
          <l>Can read this story, and not be opprest, </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>If ever mischief practis'd to excell </l>
          <l>It was in this, this Master-piece of Hell. </l>
          <pb n="2" xml:id="ep000845-004-a"/>
          <l>Had chast Lucretia follow'd the advice </l>
          <l>Of lustfull Tarquin, what a lavish price </l>
          <l>Had she layd out for sin, and yet the shame </l>
          <l>Had been far greater, and her death the same </l>
          <l>If not much worse, for had she not reveal'd it, </l>
          <l>T' had prov'd her death to think she had conceal'd it. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Ah poor Lucretia! what a fatall guest </l>
          <l>Didst thou receive, how was thy roof unblest </l>
          <l>And thou mistook, how sadly did it prove </l>
          <l>Thy table fed a Serpent, not a Dove: </l>
          <l>It was thy face, Lucretia, that was spread </l>
          <l>With lavish beauty, and there Tarquin fed. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>'Twas not to take repose, he made such speed, </l>
          <l>Nor was't the arrant of his minde to feed </l>
          <l>Upon such Cates, his eye had chose a dish </l>
          <l>Which pleas'd him, and awhile he fed by wish: </l>
          <l>And then by force, Lucretia, thou didst finde </l>
          <l>The raging stomach of his lustfull minde. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>But ah! the sad effect records the crime, </l>
          <l>Unparalleld in any Age, or time; </l>
          <l>For weeping Lucrece had no other shield </l>
          <l>Than virtue, which deny'd her heart to yield: </l>
          <l>And this all can be deduc'd from hence </l>
          <l>That virtue was opprest by violence. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <pb n="3" xml:id="ep000845-004-b"/>
          <l>But at the last, when violence had gain'd </l>
          <l>The upper-hand, vile Tarquin was constrain'd </l>
          <l>To flie, and leave Lucretia to lament, </l>
          <l>Though not conceal her wofull banishment: </l>
          <l>Judge Ladies her distresse, poor heart, her grief </l>
          <l>Inclin'd her more to death, than to relief. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>She wisht to see her Lord, yet knew not how </l>
          <l>To look upon him with a stedfast brow; </l>
          <l>But when she thought on his abused bed, </l>
          <l>Ah then! ah then! her much dejected head: </l>
          <l>Out stream'd a fountain, nothing could prevent </l>
          <l>The nimble current of her discontent. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>At last he comes, and with a fearfull hast </l>
          <l>In his expatiated arms imbrac'd </l>
          <l>His Lucrece, who being tutor'd by here fears, </l>
          <l>●ke all in sighs, and answer'd him in tears: </l>
          <l>Whilst gazing Colatine with raging speed, </l>
          <l>Stampt out these words, <hi>I will revenge the deed</hi>. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>So out he runs, but hark, a groan recalls </l>
          <l>His hasty feet, for his Lucretia's fall, </l>
          <l>Wounded by her own hand, whilst he in vain, </l>
          <l>Lifts up her corps, and layes it down again: </l>
          <l>At last poor soul, she mov'd her dying head </l>
          <l>And cry'd revenge, for thy Lucretia's dead. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <pb n="4" xml:id="ep000845-005-a"/>
          <l>Ah! who can grieve with Collatine, whose grief </l>
          <l>Admits no equall, but transcends belief, </l>
          <l>He now is fled, and ransacks all about, </l>
          <l>Contrives and plots to finde young Tarquin out; </l>
          <l>At last arriving where the Army stay'd, </l>
          <l>The colours of his grief he thus display'd. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Dear friends, the liberality of my speech </l>
          <l>Is humbly free, and fluent to beseech </l>
          <l>Your joynt assistance, to revenge a wrong </l>
          <l>Whose intricacy neither pen, nor tongue </l>
          <l>Is able to expresse: Alas! and I </l>
          <l>Can only shaddow forth my misery. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>My dear Lucretia, In whose brest did lie </l>
          <l>My life, is fled unto eternity; </l>
          <l>She's dead my Lords, and ah! if that were all </l>
          <l>In time I might endevour to recall </l>
          <l>My grief, she is (my Lords) I speak what's true, </l>
          <l>Ravish'd by death, nay, and by Tarquin too. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>And if a worser fate than this can be, </l>
          <l>Ile swear there is no grief, no misery; </l>
          <l>But to be short dear friends, I cannot now </l>
          <l>Dispose of so much time, as to utter how: </l>
          <l>But the last sound of my Lucretia's breath </l>
          <l>Was this, <hi>Revenge my rape, condole my death. </hi>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <pb n="5" xml:id="ep000845-005-b"/>
          <l>The frightned aire had hardly cool'd his words, </l>
          <l>Before the Nobles with their soon-drawn swords </l>
          <l>Vow'd a compleat revenge, and to effect </l>
          <l>Their vow'd designs, they suffer'd no neglect </l>
          <l>To harbour in their breasts, but with a speed </l>
          <l>Wing'd with affection they perform'd the deed. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>If I should lavish time, and here relate </l>
          <l>Their sev'rall battels, and their sev'rall fate, </l>
          <l>I might perplex my Reader with a story </l>
          <l>Of this mans ruine, and of that mans glory: </l>
          <l>But at my period, I should only say, </l>
          <l>Tarquins bad cause, not valour lost the day. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>But let me say that in this fatall cloud </l>
          <l>Of ruine, Tarquins father that did croud </l>
          <l>Into the arms of danger to maintain </l>
          <l>His sons vile cause, deservedly was slain: </l>
          <l>And when young Tarquin heard his fathers fall, </l>
          <l>He grew more desperate, lost himself and all. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Thus captive to his foes, his sullen breast </l>
          <l>Swell'd more with malice, than it seem'd opprest; </l>
          <l>For like a base Usurper, having thrust </l>
          <l>Himself in power, his actions must be just: </l>
          <l>Nay, though the sword decline him, yet would he </l>
          <l>Make all Authentick by obduracie. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <pb n="6" xml:id="ep000845-006-a"/>
          <l>A brazen conscience findes a brazen face, </l>
          <l>Tarquin, because he knew his foul disgrace </l>
          <l>Could not receive addition, grew so bold, </l>
          <l>So peremptory, that what others told </l>
          <l>To him in grief, he in disdain, reply'd, </l>
          <l>Lucretia's rape, is Tarquins onely pride. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Since she is dead, the thing that grieves me most </l>
          <l>Is this, to think my spirits cannot boast </l>
          <l>Of more enjoyments; but Ile cease to crave, </l>
          <l>For I am well content with what I have; </l>
          <l>And if I die, I charge thee grief, forbear, </l>
          <l>I am a Roman, and I scorn to fear. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Oh how Ile vex my foes! for when as I </l>
          <l>Am brought to death, they shall not know I die; </l>
          <l>He steal into a slumber, none shall say </l>
          <l>They saw me die, although perhaps they may </l>
          <l>Report they saw me dead; and Rome shall crie, </l>
          <l>Tarquin hath taught us how to scorn, and die. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Well then, where's their revenge? for I am sure </l>
          <l>A Roman spirit never can endure </l>
          <l>To triumph ore a corps; when smiling death </l>
          <l>Shall put a period to my yielding breath; </l>
          <l>What then? Alas! they only can concur </l>
          <l>In this one sense, he dy'd a Ravisher. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <pb n="7" xml:id="ep000845-006-b"/>
          <l>Thus, thus insentiate Tarquin seems to show </l>
          <l>More raging courage, than repentant woe; </l>
          <l>His inconsiderate thoughts think all things good, </l>
          <l>And slightly wade through poor Lucretia's blood: </l>
          <l>Go forward Reader, and thou'lt quickly finde </l>
          <l>An alter'd Tarquin, and a changed minde. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>The Consuls after serious debate </l>
          <l>Concerning Tarquin, did agree, his fate </l>
          <l>Should not be speedy death, but should be sent </l>
          <l>Into a sad and lasting banishment, </l>
          <l>That so his more deliberate thoughts might finde </l>
          <l>A way to call his villany to minde. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>This news arriving unto Tarquins ears, </l>
          <l>He soon begins to argue with his fears: </l>
          <l>Must I be sent, cryes he, into a place </l>
          <l>Of no society, and there imbrace </l>
          <l>Perpetual woe? Oh! how could Hell contrive </l>
          <l>So great a plague to keep me still alive? </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>What shall I doe in this extreme abysse </l>
          <l>Of woe and torments? Death had been a blisse </l>
          <l>Beyond expression; Ah! must wretched I </l>
          <l>Be so accurst t' offend, and yet not die? </l>
          <l>Oh most prodigious fate! vile Ixions wheel </l>
          <l>Had been a paradise to what I feel. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <pb n="8" xml:id="ep000845-007-a"/>
          <l>Methinks I feel a sudden fire that burns </l>
          <l>My very soul, my former comfort turns </l>
          <l>To present woe; methinks I grow, and swell </l>
          <l>Into a larger Continent, sure Hell </l>
          <l>Hath chang'd his mansion, and intends to make </l>
          <l>My troubled Tenement his fiery lake. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Since so it is, Ile labour to prevent </l>
          <l>Their swelling laughter with a forc'd content. </l>
          <l>Ile hide my sorrows from their gazing eyes, </l>
          <l>Ile seem to slight their malice, and despise </l>
          <l>Their scornful mocks, but yet my heart will tell </l>
          <l>My heart, that all within me, is not well. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>But stay, shall I forget my self, was I not born </l>
          <l>A noble Roman, and shall I not scorn </l>
          <l>Their impositions; shall I now relent </l>
          <l>And prove a willing slave to discontent? </l>
          <l>Fie Tarquin, fie; but hark, I hear the summe </l>
          <l>Of my destruction, now my foes are come. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Courage my heart, be bold, and let them finde, </l>
          <l>Thou hast an Army in thy strength'ned minde, </l>
          <l>And if a pressing sigh should chance to fly </l>
          <l>Our of the prison of thy minde, deny </l>
          <l>It to be thine, so shall thy prying eyes </l>
          <l>See thou disown'st their lavish tyrannies. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <pb n="9" xml:id="ep000845-007-b"/>
          <l>Even as the boysterous Ocean, if deny'd </l>
          <l>A present passage for her swelling tyde </l>
          <l>Swells and looks big, and with insulting waves </l>
          <l>Assaults th' immoving shore which stoutly staves </l>
          <l>Its fury off; but if it proudly swell </l>
          <l>Above the banks, 'tis time to bid farewell. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Even so our Tarquins passion, for a time </l>
          <l>Found opposition, but at last did clime </l>
          <l>Above his strength, and when it was too late, </l>
          <l>He soon deplor'd his miserable state, </l>
          <l>And being cast into a remote place, </l>
          <l>He thus bewails his lamentable case. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Ah! what a sad Companion is a heart, </l>
          <l>Burthen'd with guilt; Alas! I can impart </l>
          <l>No comfort to my self, all things declare </l>
          <l>My ruine, that's attended with despair: </l>
          <l>Methinks I have a still continued flood </l>
          <l>Before my eyes, of chast Lucretia's blood. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Nor is my eye disturbed, but my ear </l>
          <l>Is grown of late accustomed to hear </l>
          <l>Strange dialects, methinks Lucretia cryes, </l>
          <l>Revenge, revenge my wofull injuries: </l>
          <l>And thus my eyes, my ears sadly portend </l>
          <l>A present woe, a miserable end. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <pb n="10" xml:id="ep000845-008-a"/>
          <l>Thus in a sad discourse vile Tarquin goes </l>
          <l>He knows not where, being usher'd by his woes; </l>
          <l>At last arriving at a shadie grove, </l>
          <l>Close by a wanton stream he sadly strove </l>
          <l>To mitigate his sorrow, but his fire </l>
          <l>Encreas'd above the reach of his desire. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>I am enflam'd, he cryes, could I devise </l>
          <l>A way to quench my sorrows with my eyes; </l>
          <l>My eye enflam'd my heart, my heart combin'd </l>
          <l>With my affections to corrupt my minde; </l>
          <l>Thus minde, thus heart, obey'd a lustful call; </l>
          <l>Thus lust procur'd my hate, and hate my fall. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Ah! how these silent fishes seem to sport, </l>
          <l>And revel in their cool aquarian Court! </l>
          <l>Ah! how they bathe themselves in their own flood, </l>
          <l>Whilst I am parboyl'd in a sea of blood! </l>
          <l>Lucretia, ah Lucretia! thou didst finde </l>
          <l>A raped body, I a raped minde. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>At last the Sylvane Choristers begun </l>
          <l>Their warbling notes to the departing Sun, </l>
          <l>Which Tarquin hearing with a deep-fetch'd groan </l>
          <l>He cry'd, How more than happy's every one </l>
          <l>Of these care-wanting creatures! they are free </l>
          <l>From the rude hand of griping tyrannie. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <pb n="11" xml:id="ep000845-008-b"/>
          <l>And now deploring Philomel begins </l>
          <l>Her sad, and melancholy notes, and spins </l>
          <l>Her tedious notes unto the smallest thred </l>
          <l>As if she meant to strike poor Tarquin dead; </l>
          <l>For he no sooner heard her, but he cries, </l>
          <l>Sweet Philomel forbear thy tyrannies. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Tell me thou woful wretch, doe not deny </l>
          <l>Who was most villain <ref target="A93033-e13650-b">* </ref>
            <note corresp="A93033-e13650-a" n="*" place="margin">* The Poets fain, that Philomel was a Lady of an incomparable beauty, and being ravished by one Tereus, she importuned the Gods that she might be turned into a Bird; since which time she sadly deplored her misfortune, and is vulgarly called a Nightingale. </note>Tereus, or I; </l>
          <l>Was it not he did perpetrate thy rape, </l>
          <l>And made thee wish thy self into this shape? </l>
          <l>Since which sad time having banisht all delight, </l>
          <l>Thy sham'd-fac'd sorrow shroud themselves in night. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Let me conjure thee Philomel to cease </l>
          <l>Thy high strain'd notes, for they doe much encrease </l>
          <l>My raging grief; and now, ah now! I finde </l>
          <l>Horrour in sweetnesse, why art thou unkinde, </l>
          <l>And wilt not cease? thou shalt not ring my knell, </l>
          <l>For Ile be gon, so Philomel, farewell. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Away goes <hi>Tarquin, Philomel </hi>pursues; </l>
          <l>The more he flyes, she more and more renewes </l>
          <l>Her ecchoing notes, he swears, she chants and rears </l>
          <l>Her shriller accents to his tortur'd ears, </l>
          <l>Enrag'd he cryes, the Gods did doe thee wrong </l>
          <l>To take thy womans shape, yet leave her tongue. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <pb n="12" xml:id="ep000845-009-a"/>
          <l>Will not entreaties move thee? wilt thou still </l>
          <l>Send arrowes to my soul, and be thus shrill? </l>
          <l>Peace witch thou tempt'st my patience, every note </l>
          <l>Derived from the Magick of thy throat </l>
          <l>Strikes me to death, but ah, I will not hear; </l>
          <l>For if thou find'st a tongue, Ile want an ear. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>With that he stops his ears, but all in vaine, </l>
          <l>His fancy turnes all Philomels, and straine </l>
          <l>Far higher notes; so he, at length let fly </l>
          <l>The portalls of his eares, and by and by </l>
          <l>More then a flock of Nightingalls, being met, </l>
          <l>They thus contriv'd to pay Lucretia's debt. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>First, they encampe about his eares, and send </l>
          <l>A party out of notes, which recommend </l>
          <l>Themselves unto him, whil'st affrightn'd he </l>
          <l>Decayes, and reels into an extasie. </l>
          <l>Then they assault him with full bodied notes </l>
          <l>Discharged from the Engins of their throats. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>But Tarquin, not encourag'd to abide </l>
          <l>So hot a Charge, falls down, and falling dy'd. </l>
          <l>Which they perceiving presently arise </l>
          <l>And flockt about him, and pickt out his eyes; </l>
          <l>From which sad story we may well infer, </l>
          <l>That Philomel abhors a Ravisher. </l>
        </lg>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
