<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000284" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Hector of Germany, or The Palsgrave, Prime Elector</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Wentworth</forename>
            <surname>Smith</surname>
          </persName>
          <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q522771</idno>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>William</forename>
            <surname>Smith</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A12548.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence>
          </availability>
        </bibl>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The Hector of Germany. Or The Palsgraue, prime Elector. A new play, an honourable history. As it hath beene publickly acted at the Red-Bull, and at the Curtayne, by a company of young-men of this citie. Made by W. Smith: with new additions.</title>
            <author>Smith, Wentworth, fl. 1601-1623.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>34 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2005 March (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99852846</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 22871.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 329.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">18198</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12548</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUESTGOID">2240887975</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The Hector of Germany. Or The Palsgraue, prime Elector. A new play, an honourable history. As it hath beene publickly acted at the Red-Bull, and at the Curtayne, by a company of young-men of this citie. Made by W. Smith: with new additions.</title>
            <title type="alt">Hector of Germany</title>
            <title type="alt">Palsgraue.</title>
            <title type="alt">Hector of Germany. Or The Palsgrave, prime Elector.</title>
            <title type="alt">Palsgraue, prime Elector.</title>
            <author>Smith, Wentworth, fl. 1601-1623.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[66] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>By Thomas Creede, for Iosias Harrison, and are to be solde in Pater-Noster-Row, at the signe of the Golden Anker,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
            <date type="publication_date">1615.</date>
            <date type="creation_date">1614</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-H4 I2 (-I2).</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Running title reads: The Palsgraue.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>I2 is the cancel title used in STC 22871a.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-palsgrave">
            <persName>Palsgrave</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-savoy">
            <persName>Savoy</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-bohemia">
            <persName>Bohemia</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-marquis">
            <persName>Marquis</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-cullen">
            <persName>Cullen</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-bastard">
            <persName>Bastard</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-saxony">
            <persName>Saxony</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-mentz">
            <persName>Mentz</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-trier">
            <persName>Trier</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-peter">
            <persName>Peter</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-old_fitzwater">
            <persName>Old Fitzwater</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-steward">
            <persName>Steward</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-page">
            <persName>Page</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-young_fitzwater">
            <persName>Young Fitzwater</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-floramell">
            <persName>Floramell</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-clinton">
            <persName>Clinton</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-bishop">
            <persName>Bishop</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-king">
            <persName>King</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-lord">
            <persName>Lord</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-fitzwater">
            <persName>Fitzwater</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-messenger">
            <persName>Messenger</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-palantine">
            <persName>Palantine</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-mendoza">
            <persName>Mendoza</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-vandome">
            <persName>Vandome</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-french_king">
            <persName>French King</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-poitiers">
            <persName>Poitiers</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-queen">
            <persName>Queen</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-multiple">
            <persName>Multiple</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-artois">
            <persName>Artois</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-servant">
            <persName>Servant</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-herald">
            <persName>Herald</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-unassigned">
            <persName>Unassigned</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-french_queen">
            <persName>French Queen</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-frenchman">
            <persName>Frenchman</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-englishman">
            <persName>Englishman</persName>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="ep000284-brandenburgh">
            <persName>Brandenburgh</persName>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
      <textClass>
        <classCode scheme="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/">Q80930</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1614">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000284-e100030">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000284-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-001-b"/>
        <p>THE HECTOR OF GERMANY. OR The Palsgraue, Prime Elector. </p>
        <p>A New Play, an Honourable History. </p>
        <p>As it hath beene publickly Acted at the Red-Bull, and as the Curtayne, by a Company of Youngmen of this Citie. </p>
        <p>¶ Made by W. SMITH: with new Additions. </p>
        <p>Historia vita temporis. </p>
        <p>Printed at London by Thomas Creede, for Iosias Harrison, and are to be solde in Pater-Noster-Row, at the Signe of the Golden Anker. 1615. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000284-e100100">
        <pb type="blank" xml:id="ep000284-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-002-b"/>
        <head>TO THE RIGHT WORshipfull, the great Fauourer of the Muses, Syr Iohn Swinnerton Knight, sometimes Lord Mayor of this honourable Cittie of London. </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>SYR </salute>
        </opener>
        <p>Poesie is a diuine gifte, borne with many, without which donation no man can be a Poet, though he be Princeps doctorum; and haue all the Languages (ad vnguem.) Ouid found this inclination in himselfe, and that was the reason hee saide, Quicquid conabor dicere versus erit; where Nature speakes so forceablie in any, there is no suppressing it: For, Naturam expellas furca licet vsque recurrit, your Wor: is so farre from offering such violence, that you are known to be a great cherisher of the Muses. And I hauing receiued some fauours from you, for priuate things, thought it might be acceptable, to giue you some Honor in Print; So that this Play, intuled The Palsgraue, beeing made for Citizens, who acted it well; I deemde it fitte to bee Patronizde by a Citizen. And not knowing any so worthy thereof as your selfe, I made choyce of your Wor: to be my Mecoenas: The kinde acceptance whereof, will make me proceede farther in your praise. And as I haue begun in a former Play, called the Freemans Honour, acted by the Now-seruants of the Kings Maiestie, to degnifie the worthy Companie of the Marchantaylors, wherof you are a principall Ornament, I shall ere long, make choyce of some subiect to equall it. In the meane time, I leaue the Palsgraue in your hand, as a pledge of my good meaning, &amp; will rest▪ </p>
        <closer>
          <signed>Your Wor: most dutious, W. Smith </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="prologue" xml:id="ep000284-e100170">
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-003-a"/>
        <head>The Prologue. </head>
        <l>OUr Authour for himselfe, this bad me say, </l>
        <l>Although the Palsgraue be the name of th' Play, </l>
        <l>Tis not that Prince, which in this Kingdome late, </l>
        <l>Marryed the Mayden-glory of our state: </l>
        <l>What Pen dares be so bold in this strict age, </l>
        <l>To bring him while he liues vpon the Stage? </l>
        <l>And though he would, Authorities sterne brow </l>
        <l>Such a presumptuous deede will not allow: </l>
        <l>And he must not offend Authoritie, </l>
        <l>Tis of a Palsgraue generous and high, </l>
        <l>Of an vndaunted heart, an Hectors spirit, </l>
        <l>For his great valour, worthy royall merite; </l>
        <l>Whose fayre achieuements, and victorious glory, </l>
        <l>Is the mayne subiect of our warlike Story. </l>
        <l>Mars gouerns here, his influence rules the day, </l>
        <l>And should by right be Prologue to the Play: </l>
        <l>But that besides the subiect, Mercury </l>
        <l>Sent me to excuse our insufficiencie. </l>
        <l>If you should aske vs, being men of Trade, </l>
        <l>Wherefore the Players facultie we inuade? </l>
        <l>Our answere is, No ambition to compare </l>
        <l>With any, in that qualitie held are; </l>
        <l>Nor with a thought for any grace you giue </l>
        <l>To our weake action, by their course to liue: </l>
        <l>But as in Camps, and Nurseries of Art, </l>
        <l>Learning and valour haue assum'd a part, </l>
        <l>In a Cathurnall Sceane their wits to try, </l>
        <l>Such is our purpose in this History. </l>
        <l>Emperours haue playd, and their Associates to, </l>
        <l>Souldiers and Schollers; tis to speake and do. </l>
        <l>If Citizens come short of their high fame, </l>
        <l>Let Citizens beare with vs for the name. </l>
        <l>And Gentlemen, we hope what is well ment, </l>
        <l>Will grace the weake deede for the good intent. </l>
        <l>Our best we promise with a dauntlesse cheeke; </l>
        <l>And so we gayne your loue, tis all we seeke. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e100540">Exit. </stage>
        </l>
      </div>
      <div type="play" xml:id="ep000284-e100550">
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-003-b"/>
        <head>Palsgraue. </head>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e100560">A Bed thrust out, the Palsgraue lying sicke in it, the King of Bohemia, the Duke of Sauoy, the Marquesse Brandenburgh, entring with him. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e100570">A Letter. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e100580">
          <speaker>Palsgraue. </speaker>
          <l>Sicke at this instant now to be infirme, </l>
          <l>When the English King hath his kinde Letter sent: </l>
          <l>For mee to place this honourable prince, </l>
          <l>The Duke of Sauoy in the Empires rule: </l>
          <l>That Nation my great Grandfather did loue. </l>
          <l>And since I came to vnderstand their valour, </l>
          <l>I held them the Prime Souldiers of the world: </l>
          <l>And thinke no Martiall Tutor fittes a prince, </l>
          <l>But hee that is a true borne Englishman. </l>
          <l>Ill comes this Letter, and your Grace at once, </l>
          <l>A worser time then this you could not choose. </l>
          <l>Though I am chiefe Elector of the seuen, </l>
          <l>And a meere Caesar now the Chayre is voyde: </l>
          <l>Sicknesse hath weakened all my powers so much, </l>
          <l>I shalbe slighted as a worthlesse thing. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-savoy" xml:id="ep000284-e100740">
          <speaker>Sauoy. </speaker>
          <l>Why should the Palsgraue so mistrust his Friends? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e100760">
          <speaker>Palgr: </speaker>
          <l>Sauoy, because I know them factious. </l>
          <l>And though Bohemia loue me as his life, </l>
          <l>And Vmpeare-like, should pacifie our iars, </l>
          <l>What is his voyce when Saxon drawes his sword? </l>
          <l>Mentz of a Cleargie-man is stout and prowde, </l>
          <l>Trier his like, in nature and in vice. </l>
          <l>And the bold Bastard, late expulst from Spayne, </l>
          <l>Has a blood-thirsty hart, a vengefull spleene. </l>
          <l>Misfortune cannot daunt him though he fled </l>
          <l>Out of his owne Realme, and has lost his Crowne. </l>
          <l>His impudencie yet aymes at Caesars Throne, </l>
          <l>Ide freely part with mine inheritance, </l>
          <l>If it could purchase health to tame his pride, </l>
          <l>But in you onely I repose my trust. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-004-a"/>
          <l>Reserue your voyces for this Noble Duke, </l>
          <l>Who were I well should bee an Emperour: </l>
          <l>Sicknesse will be obeyde, I must decline, </l>
          <l>For my speech failes mee to vrge more discourse, </l>
          <l>Pray for mee all, if that they chaunce to win, </l>
          <l>And I recouer Ile helpe all by Warre. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e100970">The Bedde drawne in. Exit Palsgraue. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bohemia" xml:id="ep000284-e100980">
          <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
          <l>The strength of Germanie is sicke in him, </l>
          <l>And should hee die now in his prime of life, </l>
          <l>Like Troy wee loose the Hector of our Age: </l>
          <l>For hee alone, when he was strong and well, </l>
          <l>Curb'd all their pride, and kept the worst in awe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-marquis" xml:id="ep000284-e101040">
          <speaker>Marqu: </speaker>
          <l>We must expect warre: &amp; prepare our selues </l>
          <l>With expedition to resist their force: </l>
          <l>For a more dangerous Foe for Treachery, </l>
          <l>Then is the Bastard, liues not in these parts. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-savoy" xml:id="ep000284-e101090">
          <speaker>Sauoy. </speaker>
          <l>I am sorie, that presuming on the health </l>
          <l>Of the most valiant Palsgraue now falne sicke, </l>
          <l>I came so ill prouided for the Warres. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bohemia" xml:id="ep000284-e101130">
          <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
          <l>We are strong enough to meet them in the field </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e101150">Enter the Byshop of Cullen. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-cullen" xml:id="ep000284-e101160">
          <speaker>Cullen. </speaker>
          <l>Prepare for Warre, the Bastard is in armes, </l>
          <l>With him the fiery Saxon, Mentz, and Trier: </l>
          <l>And they'le besiege this Castle, to constraine </l>
          <l>The Palsgraue, to elect him Emperour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-marquis" xml:id="ep000284-e101210">
          <speaker>Marq: </speaker>
          <l>Shame to vs all, if we giue ayme to that. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-savoy" xml:id="ep000284-e101230">
          <speaker>Sauoy. </speaker>
          <l>Begyrt this Castle, and disturbe the health </l>
          <l>Of our deare friends, it is insufferable. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bohemia" xml:id="ep000284-e101260">
          <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
          <l>Let vs conuey him lower downe the riuer, </l>
          <l>Vnto a stronger Castle of his owne: </l>
          <l>And with such Forces as we haue prepar'd, </l>
          <l>Giue battell to the Bastard and his crue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-savoy" xml:id="ep000284-e101310">
          <speaker>Sauoy. </speaker>
          <l>You haue a Caesar of your owne Election, </l>
          <l>To leade the Vangard, doe but follow mee, </l>
          <l>Ile guide you where the greatest danger dwells: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-004-b"/>
          <l>And like an Emperour fright it from the field: </l>
          <l>The Bastards but a Coward; and a Spanyard, </l>
          <l>Coward and Spanyard oft-times goe together. </l>
          <l>Their greatest valour does consist in Braues, </l>
          <l>And once repulst, theyl run away like Slaues. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e101400">Enter Prince Henry, the Bastard, the Duke of Saxon, The Bishop of Mentz, Drum, Cullors, &amp; Soldiours. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e101410">
          <speaker>Bastard. </speaker>
          <l>This Land of Germanie yeelds valiant men, </l>
          <l>Haughty in heart as they in stature are: </l>
          <l>Ten thousand such had I bene Leader of </l>
          <l>When the Blacke-Prince, lately my greatest Foe, </l>
          <l>Opposde me at Mazieres, and wonne the day, </l>
          <l>I had bene Lord of that most noble Fielde, </l>
          <l>And where an Hermit now tells ore his Beades, </l>
          <l>Had sat a Souldier and a Conquerour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e101500">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>That Hermit is too bookish to raigne long. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e101520">
          <speaker>Bastard. </speaker>
          <l>When th'Imperiall Scepter fills my hand, </l>
          <l>And I haue Caesars wreath vpon my brow, </l>
          <l>As had my Grandsire, and his royall Father, </l>
          <l>Ile make Iberia wreake with my foes blood, </l>
          <l>And force the Dotard to his Hermitage. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mentz" xml:id="ep000284-e101580">
          <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
          <l>Such thoughts becomes the Germaine Emperour, </l>
          <l>Has courage to wage Warre with all the world. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e101610">
          <speaker>Saxon: </speaker>
          <l>Harry, a word in priuate in your eare, </l>
          <l>When you are Emperour, as in time you shall, </l>
          <l>I must rule all, although you weare the Crowne: </l>
          <l>The Edicts I propose you must enact, </l>
          <l>And call them your owne Lawes, not being vext </l>
          <l>At what I doe, although I mince your honour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e101680">
          <speaker>Bastard. </speaker>
          <l>How Saxon? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e101700">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>Harry, Darst' thou wreath thy brow, </l>
          <l>In any contumelious forme gainst mee? </l>
          <l>T'is by my fauour that thou art aliue. </l>
          <l>My greater greatnes has repaird thy fame, </l>
          <l>And being but my creature, it is fitte </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-005-a"/>
          <l>I should bee knowne to be the worthier man. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e101770">
          <speaker>Bastard. </speaker>
          <l>Betweene our selues in priuate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e101790">
          <speaker>Sax: </speaker>
          <l>Publikely, and in the view of all, youle sweare. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e101810">
          <speaker>Bastard. </speaker>
          <l>I must. </l>
          <l>But being installed in the dignitie, </l>
          <l>Ile alter what I sweare. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e101850">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>Come, Come, your Oath, </l>
          <l>Being an Elector, I am bard the onely Throane, </l>
          <l>And therefore will rule by a Deputy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mentz" xml:id="ep000284-e101890">
          <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
          <l>This is the Castle, shall wee sommon it? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e101910">Enter Trier, another Bishop. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-trier" xml:id="ep000284-e101920">
          <speaker>Trier. </speaker>
          <l>Emperour elect, and princes of the State, </l>
          <l>In vaine you labour to begyrt this hold </l>
          <l>With hostile Armes, for Sauoy is yth field, </l>
          <l>The Bishop of Cullen, and stoute Brandenburgh, </l>
          <l>With the Bohemian King, are already prest, </l>
          <l>To giue you battell ere you stirre your foote. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e101990">
          <speaker>Bast. </speaker>
          <l>Are they so braue, so hote, &amp; full of courage? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e102010">
          <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
          <l>The Palsgraue has breath'd spirit into them all. </l>
          <l>Thogh sicknes make him droop, weel meet them straight </l>
          <l>Battells are gouernd by the will of Fate. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e102050">An Allarum. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e102060">Enter to them Sauoy, Bohem, Marquesse, and Cullen, They are beaten off by the Bastards side, &amp; exeunt. A Flourish, enter in triumph, Bastard, Saxon, Trier, Mentz, leading the king of Bohemia, Brandenburgh, and Sauoy, Prisoners. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e102070">
          <speaker>Bast. </speaker>
          <l>So moues the Sunne in glory through the skie, </l>
          <l>Hauing outpast the clowdes that shadow him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e102100">
          <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
          <l>Now Spanish Henry, thou hast prou'd thy selfe </l>
          <l>Worthy the Germane scepter, by thy valour, </l>
          <l>And hee that sayes not Aue Caesar, dyes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bohemia" xml:id="ep000284-e102140">
          <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
          <l>Swell not too high thou bubble, least thou </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e102160">
          <speaker>Bastard. </speaker>
          <l>Ile breake thy heart first. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-savoy" xml:id="ep000284-e102180">
          <speaker>Sauoy. </speaker>
          <l>Ere my tongue pronounce </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-005-b"/>
          <l>Aue to any that's my enemie; </l>
          <l>Ile bare my brest to meete thy conquering sword, </l>
          <l>And make it crimson with an Emperours blood. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e102230">
          <speaker>Bast: </speaker>
          <l>There must be but one Emperour, thats our selfe, </l>
          <l>Therefore to prison with the counterfeit, </l>
          <l>Whence neither County Pallatine, nor King, </l>
          <l>Shall with theyr Forces if they were conioynd, </l>
          <l>Haue power to set thee free. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e102290">
          <speaker>Saxon: </speaker>
          <l>For you my Lords, that are Electors like vnto my selfe, </l>
          <l>Giue but your free consents that hee shall gouerne, </l>
          <l>And that shall serue as ransome for you all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-marquis" xml:id="ep000284-e102330">
          <speaker>Marq: </speaker>
          <l>Neuer while life lastes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bohemia" xml:id="ep000284-e102350">
          <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
          <l>Or I breath this ayre. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mentz" xml:id="ep000284-e102370">
          <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
          <l>Then let them share like fortune in his doom </l>
          <l>As they haue done this happy day ith field. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e102400">
          <speaker>Bastard. </speaker>
          <l>To prison with them all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e102420">
          <speaker>Saxon: </speaker>
          <l>Not till you are Crownde. </l>
          <l>That sight shall serue in steed of a Tormentor, </l>
          <l>And I reioyce to vexe mine enemie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e102460">
          <speaker>Bastard. </speaker>
          <l>Giue vs our rights. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e102480">The two Bishops, Ments, &amp; Trier, Crowne the Bastard. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mentz" xml:id="ep000284-e102490">
          <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
          <l>Rex Romanorum, &amp; magnus Imperator GerViue Caesar. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e102510">
          <speaker>Saxon: </speaker>
          <l>Viue Caesar. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e102530">
          <speaker>Bastard. </speaker>
          <l>Enough those Viues, take away my life, </l>
          <l>In the delitious wrapture of my soule, </l>
          <l>For theres no heauen me thinkes like royall thoughts, </l>
          <l>The Palsgraues Castles raste vnto the ground, </l>
          <l>And peace establisht, we meane once againe </l>
          <l>To trye our Fortune for the Realme of Spayne. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e102600">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e102610">Enter Peter the Hermit, King of Spaine in a disguise. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-peter" xml:id="ep000284-e102620">
          <speaker>Peter. </speaker>
          <l>Since the decease of Englands royall Sonne, </l>
          <l>That plac't me lately in Spaynes gouernment, </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-006-a"/>
        <l>Those that did feare me for his valor sake, </l>
        <l>Are by the traynes and falshood of my brother, </l>
        <l>Reuolted from mee, and to saue my life </l>
        <l>I was constrained put on this disguise, </l>
        <l>To goe to England for a newe supplie </l>
        <l>Of men and Soldiours would but weary them. </l>
        <l>I haue therefore bene in France, and failing there, </l>
        <l>Am come to Germanie, to implore the ayde </l>
        <l>Of the Electors, but by ill successe, </l>
        <l>Bohemia, Brandenburgh, and Sauoyes tane: </l>
        <l>The Bastard has bewitcht the other Peeres. </l>
        <l>So that my Foe is now an Emperour, </l>
        <l>And all the hope I haue to get mine owne </l>
        <l>Lyes in the Palsgraue sicke I heare to death, </l>
        <l>Heare I expect his answere to my Letter. </l>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e102800">Enter the Palsgraue, led in by Cullen, and others. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e102810">
          <speaker>Palsgr. </speaker>
          <p>Are you the Hermit that did bring this letter? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-peter" xml:id="ep000284-e102830">
          <speaker>Peter. </speaker>
          <p>And personate him that sent it. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e102850">
          <speaker>Palsgraue. </speaker>
          <l>What Spaynes King? </l>
          <l>Oh that I were as I was wont to bee, </l>
          <l>Before this dangerous sicknesse was my Foe, </l>
          <l>No Christian King that came to mee for ayde </l>
          <l>But hee should speed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-peter" xml:id="ep000284-e102910">
          <speaker>Peter. </speaker>
          <p>In time you may recouer. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e102930">
          <speaker>Palsgr. </speaker>
          <l>Meane time be welcom, sit, &amp; take your rest, </l>
          <l>And now my Lord of Cullen I me preparde, </l>
          <l>To heare the woefull tydings you haue brought. </l>
          <l>Comes noble Sauoy, and Bohemias King, </l>
          <l>With the stoute Marquesse Brandenburgh in triumph </l>
          <l>And is proude Saxon taken, with the Bastard, </l>
          <l>Trier and Mentz made subiect to your sword? </l>
          <l>Oh if they beespeake it, and make me well. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-cullen" xml:id="ep000284-e103020">
          <speaker>Cullen. </speaker>
          <l>Alls lost, We are conquered, Sauoy is surprizde, </l>
          <l>And our best Friends in bondage to our Foes: </l>
          <l>Heauen has forgot the Iustice of our cause. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-006-b"/>
          <l>And onely I escapt to tell the newes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e103070">
          <speaker>Palsg: </speaker>
          <l>This were enough to kill some man in health, </l>
          <l>But in me the effect is contrary. </l>
          <l>All lost, all conquerd, Sauoy made a Slaue: </l>
          <l>My Friends in prison, and none escapt but you, </l>
          <l>Hee that can heare such ill newes and be sicke, </l>
          <l>Deserues nere to recouer, in my blood, </l>
          <l>I feele an inflammation of reuenge: </l>
          <l>Theres greater strength gathered into my nerues, </l>
          <l>Then ere before, since that I grewe infirme: </l>
          <l>They will not rest thus, and stay onely there, </l>
          <l>But hauing conquered them, assume the Crowne, </l>
          <l>And make the Bastard Emperour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-cullen" xml:id="ep000284-e103200">
          <speaker>Cullen. </speaker>
          <p>Hee is Crownd. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e103220">
          <speaker>Palsg. </speaker>
          <l>More blood increases, &amp; some more ill newes </l>
          <l>Would make me cast my Night-cap on the ground, </l>
          <l>And call my Groome to fetch mee a Warre-horse, </l>
          <l>That I may ride before an Army royall, </l>
          <l>And plucke the Crowne from off the Bastards head, </l>
          <l>That is anothers right. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-cullen" xml:id="ep000284-e103290">
          <speaker>Cullen. </speaker>
          <l>Tis thought my Lord, </l>
          <l>Your Castle which you left to saue your life </l>
          <l>Is beaten to the ground, and your goods theirs: </l>
          <l>And further, that they will pursue you hither, </l>
          <l>As if you fled before their conquering swords. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e103350">
          <speaker>Palsgr. </speaker>
          <l>Be sicke who will, mine Ague does retire. </l>
          <l>And Cullen thou hast cur'd me with ill newes. </l>
          <l>Come valiant Soldiours shew your selues like men, </l>
          <l>And be assur'd weele winne the victory. </l>
          <l>Harke how they shout as they applauded mee: </l>
          <l>And see how brauely euery Leader rides, </l>
          <l>Plum'd from the Beauer to the Saddle bowe, </l>
          <l>Whilst the bold Souldier makes his lofty pike </l>
          <l>Stretch in the Ayre with tossing it aloft. </l>
          <l>Brauely done fellow: that tricke once againe, </l>
          <l>And there's gold for thy paines, hee fights like Hector. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-007-a"/>
          <l>Whilst at his feete th'amazed Grecians fall, </l>
          <l>And though Achilles would renew the Field, </l>
          <l>Hee dares not doo't, the enemies so strong, </l>
          <l>Me thinks I heare a peale of Ordinance play, </l>
          <l>They are the Bastards Cannons, planted high, </l>
          <l>To ouerthrow my Castle to the ground. </l>
          <l>Now they shoote off, Death, all my foes are come. </l>
          <l>Marshall my Troups, and let Drum answere Drum. </l>
          <l>My selfe in person will be generall. </l>
          <l>But I fainte, and am not what I would be. </l>
          <l>My spirit is stronger then my feeble lyms, </l>
          <l>Leade me once more with griefe vnto my bed, </l>
          <l>Fewe know the sorrowes of a troubled head. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e103600">Manent Cullen, &amp; Peter. Exit Palsgraue led in. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-cullen" xml:id="ep000284-e103610">
          <speaker>Cullen. </speaker>
          <l>How faine would valour sickness ouercom? </l>
          <l>But his infirmity denyes such power. </l>
          <l>And I am more grieued for his weake estate, </l>
          <l>Then for our late great losse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-peter" xml:id="ep000284-e103660">
          <speaker>Peter. </speaker>
          <p>Palsgraue may helpe him. </p>
          <l>And as I liu'de a fellow amongst Hermits, </l>
          <l>I learnt some skill that has curde many a Prince. </l>
          <l>See him safe guarded from his enemies. </l>
          <l>And on my life I will recouer him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-cullen" xml:id="ep000284-e103720">
          <speaker>Cullen. </speaker>
          <l>Wee are strong enough to waste him to his Fleete, </l>
          <l>And when the Enemy shall misse him here, </l>
          <l>Theyle turne their conquering Force another way, </l>
          <l>And goe for Spayne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-peter" xml:id="ep000284-e103770">
          <speaker>Peter. </speaker>
          <p>My Kingdome. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-cullen" xml:id="ep000284-e103790">
          <speaker>Cullen. </speaker>
          <p>To subdue it. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-peter" xml:id="ep000284-e103810">
          <speaker>Peter. </speaker>
          <p>Let them proceed, but when hee has got his strength, theyle rue their boldnesse; Meane time trust to mee. For next to Heauen Ile cure his maladie. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e103830">Enter olde Fitzwaters, and his Steward. Exeunt. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e103840">
          <speaker>Old Fitz: </speaker>
          <l>Thou art his hand, the agent of his thoughts, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-007-b"/>
          <l>And onely enginor, by which he works </l>
          <l>Some dangerous plot to blow his Honour vp: </l>
          <l>Is't possible my Sonne should be from Court </l>
          <l>So often, and the cause vnknowne to thee, </l>
          <l>That art his bosome-friend, his Counseller? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-steward" xml:id="ep000284-e103910">
          <speaker>Stew. </speaker>
          <p>I know no cause except to take the ayre. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e103930">
          <speaker>Old Fyth. </speaker>
          <l>My wrath shall finde another in thy brest. </l>
          <l>Know that thou tread'st on thy last foote of earth, </l>
          <l>From whence is no remooue, but to the graue: </l>
          <l>Flye me thou canst not, and to make resistance, </l>
          <l>Will draw vpon thee for one Lyons rage, </l>
          <l>All the whole denne. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e104000">Offers to kill him. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-steward" xml:id="ep000284-e104010">
          <speaker>Stew. </speaker>
          <l>Hold, and Ile tell your Honour. </l>
          <l>Know that his vsuall haunt is to the house </l>
          <l>Of the Lord Clynton, whither he is gone </l>
          <l>To see his Daughter, whom he does affect. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e104060">
          <speaker>Old. </speaker>
          <l>Doats he on my betrothed, my Loue, my wife? </l>
          <l>Had he the liues of many hopefull sonnes </l>
          <l>Incorporate with his owne, my rate is such </l>
          <l>I should destroy them all, ere lose my Loue. </l>
          <l>But how does she affect him? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-steward" xml:id="ep000284-e104120">
          <speaker>Stew. </speaker>
          <l>As her life: </l>
          <l>Alleadging, that the Contract made to you, </l>
          <l>Was by constraint to please her honour'd Father: </l>
          <l>But he was precontracted, first made sure. </l>
          <l>And this I heard her speake, with pearled teares; </l>
          <l>Then Loue, no passion ought to be more free, </l>
          <l>Nor any agreement like that sympathie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e104200">
          <speaker>Old Fyth. </speaker>
          <l>I haue put on Dianiras poysoned shirt </l>
          <l>In the discourse, and euery word cleaues to me </l>
          <l>As deadly in the apprehension, </l>
          <l>As that which kill'd the Iew-borne Hercules. </l>
          <l>But wherefore doe I combat with my selfe, </l>
          <l>That haue a greater enemie to curbe? </l>
          <l>Oh, but he is my sonne! What is a sonne? </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-008-a"/>
          <l>The effect of a sweete minute, he shall dye, </l>
          <l>Being my pleasure to effect my pleasure: </l>
          <l>Attend me where he is, I may destroy him. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e104310">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e104320">Enter a Page. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-page" xml:id="ep000284-e104330">
          <speaker>Page. </speaker>
          <p>I haue a sweete Office, to be Gentleman Porter to a backe dore; but tis for a Lady, the best beauty in England: and if there be any Pandering in the businesse, though I am accessary i'the fee, because I liue by it, I haue no knowledge in the fault. Many a Courtier would be glad of my place, yet I hold it not by pattent, for terme of life, nor for yeeres: but as young Gentlemen get Venison vpon sufferance or by stealth. If the Lord Clynton should haue notice of this Key or euidence, by which the young Lord Fythwaters is conueyed to his Daughter against his will, though shee be his Wife by a precontract, I might bee conueyed to the porters-lodge. But if all Court-secrets come to light, what will become of the Farthingales thinke you that couer them? No, since Ladies weare Whale-bones, many haue beene swallowed, and so may this. Heere comes the Young Lord. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e104350">Enter Young Fythwaters. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e104360">
          <speaker>Y. Fyt. </speaker>
          <p>Alwaies at hand, thy carefulnesse is great: Where is thy Lady? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-page" xml:id="ep000284-e104380">
          <speaker>Pag. </speaker>
          <p>Walking in the Garden. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e104400">
          <speaker>Y. Fyt. </speaker>
          <l>So early, then I see loues the best larke; </l>
          <l>For the Corne builder has not warbled yet </l>
          <l>His mornings Carroll to the rising Sunne. </l>
          <l>There's for thy paines. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-page" xml:id="ep000284-e104450">
          <speaker>Page. </speaker>
          <p>I thanke your Lordship. And now like the Keeper of a prison, hauing my fee, tis fit I should turne the Key. You know the way to my Ladies chamber. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e104470">
          <speaker>Y. Fyth. </speaker>
          <p>I doe. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e104490">Exit Young Fythwaters. </stage>
          </p>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-008-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000284-page" xml:id="ep000284-e104500">
          <speaker>Page. </speaker>
          <p>Sure liberallitie was a louer, or he would nere be so bountifull: some thinke it a chargeable thing to keepe a Woman of any eminent fashion, and so tis, but to keepe them as I doe vnder locke and key, and suffer none to enter but such liberall Gentlemen, is the onely way to make a rich Keeper. I must walke still to watch his comming foorth. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e104520">Enter old Fythwaters and Steward. </stage>
          </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e104530">
          <speaker>O. Fyth. </speaker>
          <p>You haue beene with the Lord Clynton? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-steward" xml:id="ep000284-e104550">
          <speaker>Stew. </speaker>
          <p>And he promist to meete you in the Garden couertly. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e104570">
          <speaker>O. Fyth. </speaker>
          <p>Is this the place? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-steward" xml:id="ep000284-e104590">
          <speaker>Stew. </speaker>
          <p>And this is the Ladyes Page that lets him in. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-page" xml:id="ep000284-e104610">
          <speaker>Page. </speaker>
          <p>Helpe, helpe. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e104630">Stop his mouth. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e104640">
          <speaker>O. Fyt. </speaker>
          <l>If you bellow here, you breath your last; by waies, </l>
          <l>Backe dores, come sir along with me. </l>
          <l>If that her father meete, as I desire, </l>
          <l>Whats but a sparke, will prooue a mount of fire. </l>
          <l>Locke the dore after vs. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-steward" xml:id="ep000284-e104700">
          <speaker>Steward. </speaker>
          <p>My Lord I will. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e104720">Exeunt all. </stage>
          </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e104730">Enter in the Garden, Floramell the Lord Clyntons Daughter, and Young Fythwaters. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e104740">They sit on a banke. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e104750">
          <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
          <l>The delian Lute is not more Musicall </l>
          <l>Then thy sweete voyce, Oh my Apollo speake, </l>
          <l>That with the wrapture of thy words, my soule </l>
          <l>May be intranst, and wish no other ioyes: </l>
          <l>That by the discord of two Broken harps, </l>
          <l>(Old and vnfit for Louers harmony) </l>
          <l>Our ioyes should suffer a distate of feare; </l>
          <l>And in our most delights a qualme of griefe </l>
          <l>Runne like a vayne of Lead through a Gold-mine. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e104850">Olde Fyth-waters and the Lord Clynton some behinde, and ouer-heare them. </stage>
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-009-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e104860">
          <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
          <l>We grow too iealous of our prosperous daies, </l>
          <l>Making an euill, where no ill is meant: </l>
          <l>Like hallowed ground, loue sanctifies this place, </l>
          <l>And will not suffer danger to intrude. </l>
          <l>Here we are ringd in earthly Paradise, </l>
          <l>And may haue all the heauen to our selues: </l>
          <l>Be then Mistrust an exile from my brest, </l>
          <l>Where liues no iealousie, dwells present rest. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e104950">
          <speaker>Clyn. </speaker>
          <p>But wee'l disturbe it, &amp; your amorous ioyes. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e104970">
          <speaker>Y. Fyt. </speaker>
          <p>Our Fathers present; Sweet, we are betraid. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e104990">
          <speaker>O. Fyt. </speaker>
          <l>Betrayd to death: why doe you hold my Sword? </l>
          <l>There's greater fury kindled in my brest, </l>
          <l>Then can be quencht by any thing but blood: </l>
          <l>I shall turne frantique if you brand the Sea </l>
          <l>Of my displeasure in such narrow bounds, </l>
          <l>And with a Deluge, equall to the first, </l>
          <l>That ouer-spred the world, swell vp so high, </l>
          <l>Till not a Mountaine ouer-looke the streame, </l>
          <l>Nor heauen be seene for Riuers of the Land. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e105090">
          <speaker>Y. Fyt. </speaker>
          <l>If I could feare the wauing of a Sword, </l>
          <l>Mine enemies had frighted me ere now; </l>
          <l>But I'me invaluable, like my minde, </l>
          <l>Not to be wounded but with darts of loue; </l>
          <l>And I as little estimate a Father </l>
          <l>In these Pathaires, as he esteemes my griefe. </l>
          <l>There's no preoritie in loues high Court </l>
          <l>Graunted vnto the Fathers 'fore the Sonne; </l>
          <l>But like the purest gouernment of all, </l>
          <l>Euery mans minde is his owne Monarchy: </l>
          <l>Where reason nere set foote to make a law, </l>
          <l>Shall common sense keepe one, that were absurd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e105220">
          <speaker>O. Fyt. </speaker>
          <p>Wouldst fight with me? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e105240">
          <speaker>Y. Fyt. </speaker>
          <l>Not if you will forbeare me; </l>
          <l>But in a warre defensiue I will stand </l>
          <l>Against an Army of my Auncestors, </l>
          <l>Did their enfranchiz'd soules break ope their tombes, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-009-b"/>
          <l>And reassum'd their bodyes as they liu'd, </l>
          <l>In their full pride and youthfull iollity. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e105310">
          <speaker>O. Fy. </speaker>
          <l>Let Rauens perch vpon these blossomd trees, </l>
          <l>Night Owles their stations in this Garden keepe, </l>
          <l>And euery ominous portence draw neere: </l>
          <l>For here Ile offer vnto Hecate, </l>
          <l>A hellish sacrifice in a sonnes blood. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e105370">
          <speaker>Clyn. </speaker>
          <l>I feele an Earth-quake in my trembling flesh, </l>
          <l>And my well boding Gemms bids me draw </l>
          <l>A sword of vengeance on this hastie Lord, </l>
          <l>Ere suffer him to be a pariside. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e105420">
          <speaker>O. Fyth. </speaker>
          <p>Will the Lord Clynton buckler out my foe? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e105440">
          <speaker>Clyn. </speaker>
          <p>No, but restraine you from a wilfull murther. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e105460">
          <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
          <l>And like the best oblation for your wrath, </l>
          <l>Loe, I the subiect of this variance fall </l>
          <l>prostrate on my knee, to suffer death, </l>
          <l>Ere such a rude act, most vnfather-like, </l>
          <l>Be put in practice on so good a sonne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e105520">
          <speaker>O. Fyth. </speaker>
          <p>Good to deceiue me. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e105540">
          <speaker>Y. Eyth. </speaker>
          <p>The deceit is yours. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e105560">
          <speaker>O. Fyth. </speaker>
          <p>Forsweare him, and I shall rest satisfied. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e105580">
          <speaker>Flora. </speaker>
          <p>Neuer. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e105600">
          <speaker>Y. Fyth. </speaker>
          <p>Nor I. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e105620">
          <speaker>O. Fyth. </speaker>
          <p>Giue way. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e105640">
          <speaker>Y. Fyth. </speaker>
          <p>I neede no buckler. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e105660">
          <speaker>Clyn. </speaker>
          <l>I stand not here to offend, but to defend </l>
          <l>Your liues and honour gainst so vile and act </l>
          <l>Would blurre the Conquerors fame perpetually, </l>
          <l>Making your swords the furies fire-brands, </l>
          <l>Bath'd so vnnaturally in others blood. </l>
          <l>Where neither Honour, nor Religion springs, </l>
          <l>Tis better farre such combats be vnsought: </l>
          <l>I know your pleas, her father has my graunt, </l>
          <l>You her affection got against my will: </l>
          <l>The place whereon you stand is our owne ground, </l>
          <l>And here tis fit I arbitrate the cause. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-010-a"/>
          <l>Mongst reasonable men peace is held good: </l>
          <l>None loue dissention, but they thirst for blood. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e105800">
          <speaker>O. Fyt. </speaker>
          <p>Counsel preuailes, I am glad he is not slaine. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e105820">
          <speaker>Y. Fyt. </speaker>
          <p>I liue with ioy, that I'me no Father-killer. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e105840">
          <speaker>Clyn. </speaker>
          <p>Will you subscribe to what we shall inioyne? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater #ep000284-young_fitzwater"
                 xml:id="ep000284-e105860">
          <speaker>Old Fyth. &amp; Y. Fyt. </speaker>
          <p>We doe. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e105880">
          <speaker>Clyn. </speaker>
          <l>In briefe tis this. You must forbeare my house, </l>
          <l>And neuer more be seene within my gates. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e105910">
          <speaker>Y. Fyt. </speaker>
          <p>This is extreame. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e105930">
          <speaker>O. Fyt. </speaker>
          <l>I haue a heauier doome, </l>
          <l>Which on my curse I charge thee to obserue: </l>
          <l>Which is, That instantly thou leaue the Land, </l>
          <l>And trouble me no more to get her loue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e105980">
          <speaker>Y. Fyt. </speaker>
          <p>How am I crost! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e106000">
          <speaker>Flor. </speaker>
          <p>How is my heart tormented! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e106020">
          <speaker>Y. Fyt. </speaker>
          <l>Yet I haue all the world to trafique in, </l>
          <l>Except in England, and your Honoures house: </l>
          <l>But as the dissolution of the soule </l>
          <l>From such a body as desires to loue, </l>
          <l>Is burthensome and grieuous to the man; </l>
          <l>Such is my heart disseuered from my Loue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e106090">
          <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
          <p>And such is mine to lose thy company. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e106110">
          <speaker>Y. Fyt </speaker>
          <l>You are cruell to impose a curse vpon me, </l>
          <l>That sentence is extreame, I feele it worke. </l>
          <l>More deadly on my grieued faculties, </l>
          <l>Then to haue dyed vpon my fathers sword: </l>
          <l>For now mine owne woes must destroy my selfe. </l>
          <l>And thats a murther worse then paracide. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e106180">Exit Y. Fyt. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e106190">
          <speaker>Flora. </speaker>
          <p>My knife shall end me. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e106210">
          <speaker>Old Fyth. </speaker>
          <l>Hold thy desperate hand, </l>
          <l>Would'st make our Nuptialls proue a Tragedy? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e106240">
          <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
          <l>I would, and be inhum'd within the ground, </l>
          <l>Rather then measure out a hated bed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e106270">
          <speaker>Clyn. </speaker>
          <l>Neuer regard the passions of a woman, </l>
          <l>They are wily creatures, and haue learnt this wit, </l>
          <l>Where they loue most, best to dissemble it. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-010-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e106310">
          <speaker>O. Fyt. </speaker>
          <p>If that proue so, my heart wil be the lighter. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e106330">Manet Steward. Exeunt. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-steward" xml:id="ep000284-e106340">
          <speaker>Stew. </speaker>
          <l>I haue done an act will make me odious </l>
          <l>To all succeeding times, betrayde my friend: </l>
          <l>But here he comes, Ile stay and speake with him. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e106380">Enter young Fytzwaters. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e106390">
          <speaker>Y. Fyt. </speaker>
          <l>Carelesse of foes, of father, or his curse, </l>
          <l>Come I againe to challenge Floramell, </l>
          <l>Which I suspect the Steward has betrayde. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-steward" xml:id="ep000284-e106430">
          <speaker>Stew. </speaker>
          <l>Within my brest bathe a reuengefull sword, </l>
          <l>Loe, I oppose it to your greatest wrath: </l>
          <l>Yet if you saw the counsells of my heart, </l>
          <l>There you may reade, twas not I but feare </l>
          <l>That was the Authour of your loues betraying; </l>
          <l>Your angry father threatned me with death, </l>
          <l>And I had no euasion but to tell it: </l>
          <l>But if your Lordship please to pardon me, </l>
          <l>Ile lay a plot to helpe you to your Loue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e106530">
          <speaker>Y. Fyt. </speaker>
          <p>He that is once false, will be neuer true. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-steward" xml:id="ep000284-e106550">
          <speaker>Stew. </speaker>
          <p>Then wherefore serues repentance? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e106570">
          <speaker>Y. Fyt. </speaker>
          <p>Well, proecede. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-steward" xml:id="ep000284-e106590">
          <speaker>Stew. </speaker>
          <l>Set downe the place where I shall finde your Honour, </l>
          <l>And if I bring not thither Floramell, </l>
          <l>At our next meeting take away my life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e106630">
          <speaker>Y. Fyt. </speaker>
          <p>Meete me at Yorke house. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-steward" xml:id="ep000284-e106650">
          <speaker>Stew. </speaker>
          <l>Ile be there ere long. </l>
          <l>I haue done amisse, and will amend the wrong. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e106680">Exeunt. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e106690">Enter old Fythwaters, Clynton, and a Bishoppe. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e106700">
          <speaker>Clyn. </speaker>
          <l>The Bride not vp, and the Archbishop come, </l>
          <l>Some call her downe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e106730">
          <speaker>O. Fyt. </speaker>
          <l>Welcome my reuerend Lord. </l>
          <l>Doe not you Bishops vse sometimes to dreame? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bishop" xml:id="ep000284-e106760">
          <speaker>Bish. </speaker>
          <l>We haue the same incitements of the blood </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-011-a"/>
          <l>That others haue, and in our phantasies </l>
          <l>We see strange shapes, and diuers things to follow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e106800">
          <speaker>Clyn. </speaker>
          <l>What was your dreame to night? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bishop" xml:id="ep000284-e106820">
          <speaker>Bish. </speaker>
          <l>As I remember, </l>
          <l>Himen was turn'd into a Mercury, </l>
          <l>And hee's the Patron of all slye deceits. </l>
          <l>But whats my dreame to your affayres my Lord? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e106870">
          <speaker>O. Fyt. </speaker>
          <l>That such another dreame I had last night: </l>
          <l>And if I should be cheated of my Bride, </l>
          <l>Twere a strange premonition. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e106910">
          <speaker>Clyn. </speaker>
          <l>Feare it not, see where shee comes. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e106930">Enter the Page, drest in one of Floramells Gownes, wearing a Maske. Floramell and the Steward aboue. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e106940">
          <speaker>O. Fyth. </speaker>
          <l>March forwarde to the Church. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e106960">Exeunt Lords and Page. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-steward" xml:id="ep000284-e106970">
          <speaker>Ste. </speaker>
          <l>So, whilst he takes your place, we are for York-house. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e106990">
          <speaker>Flora. </speaker>
          <l>I come Fythwaters flying. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-steward" xml:id="ep000284-e107010">
          <speaker>Stew. </speaker>
          <l>Let's away. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e107030">Enter young Fythwaters. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e107040">
          <speaker>Y. Fy. </speaker>
          <l>The stay of my faire Mistris makes me wilde, </l>
          <l>Sure I shall neuer more behold her face; </l>
          <l>The Stewards false, and Floramell may change. </l>
          <l>Ile therefore giue a period to my griefe, </l>
          <l>And in dispayre finish what life denyes: </l>
          <l>Yet ere I dye, let all the World this know, </l>
          <l>A Womans loue procur'd my ouerthrow. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e107120">Enter the Steward and Floramell. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e107130">
          <speaker>Y. Fith. </speaker>
          <l>My Floramell, to Sea. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e107150">Exeunt. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e107160">Enter from Church, old Fythwaters, Clynton, Bishop, and the Page discouered. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e107170">
          <speaker>O. Fyth. </speaker>
          <l>Oh my distracted soule, this is extreame, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-011-b"/>
          <l>Gull'd with a Boy, drest in your Daughters gowne: </l>
          <l>This is a crosse that patience cannot beare. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e107210">
          <speaker>Clynton. </speaker>
          <l>Who was the cause of this, speake; </l>
          <l>Wheres my Daughter? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-page" xml:id="ep000284-e107240">
          <speaker>Pvge </speaker>
          <l>Fledde to your Sonne. </l>
          <l>The Steward layd the plot; What I haue done </l>
          <l>Was for my Ladies sake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e107280">
          <speaker>Old Fitzw: </speaker>
          <l>That Steward is a Villaine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e107300">
          <speaker>Clinton. </speaker>
          <l>Lets goe seeke him. </l>
          <l>Take seuerall streetes, but let your meeting be </l>
          <l>At the Water-side, least they should flee to Sea. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e107340">
          <speaker>Old Fi. </speaker>
          <l>To the water side; Lord Bishop keep the boy. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e107360">Exeunt Old Fitzwater and Clynton. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bishop" xml:id="ep000284-e107370">
          <speaker>Bishop. </speaker>
          <l>I will. </l>
          <l>My Dreame is falne out right, Hymen is chang'd </l>
          <l>Into a slye deceyuing Mercurie: </l>
          <l>But tis most requisite, they that doe wrong </l>
          <l>Should feele the penaltie by suffering it. </l>
          <l>I witnesse can the Young Lordes precontract, </l>
          <l>Bad Fathers that infringe a holy act. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e107450">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e107460">Enter King Edward disguised like a priuate man, a Lord with him. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e107470">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>This day I thinke I promised the Lord Clinton </l>
          <l>To be his Guest. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-lord" xml:id="ep000284-e107500">
          <speaker>Lord. </speaker>
          <l>It was my Liege this Day. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e107520">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>I haue dismist my Traine to steale vpon him, </l>
          <l>But whats the season all things are so quiet? </l>
          <l>A Lordes house at so great a Cerimonie </l>
          <l>As is a Marriage, should be like a Court: </l>
          <l>Multitudes thronging vp and downe like waues; </l>
          <l>And the Gate kept with an Officious porter, </l>
          <l>To giue kinde entertainment to all Commers; </l>
          <l>Heres no such a matter. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-lord" xml:id="ep000284-e107610">
          <speaker>Lord. </speaker>
          <l>Here Olde Fitzwater: comes. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e107630">Enter Olde Fitzwaters. </stage>
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-012-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e107640">
          <speaker>O. Fyt. </speaker>
          <l>Some Pegasus has borne her from my sight </l>
          <l>For nere a horse I keepe can ouertake them: </l>
          <l>By all coniectures they are gone to Sea, </l>
          <l>And Shipt by this. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e107690">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>His Bride. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-lord" xml:id="ep000284-e107710">
          <speaker>Lord. </speaker>
          <l>Belike tis so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e107730">
          <speaker>O. Fyt. </speaker>
          <l>Some whirle-winde follow them; </l>
          <l>And making the Ocean rougher then my brow, </l>
          <l>Yee dauncing Porpusses caper aloft, </l>
          <l>And mud the white foame with your ietty backs; </l>
          <l>A perfect signe a tempest is at hand. </l>
          <l>Rise from the bottome of the deepe ye Whales, </l>
          <l>And ouerturne the Shippe that carryes them: </l>
          <l>But let a Dolphin saue my Floramell, </l>
          <l>And backe vnto the hauen guide her safe. </l>
          <l>As for the boy, make him your watry pray, </l>
          <l>Eate him aliue, that he may heare his bones </l>
          <l>Crash in the iawes of the Leuiathan: </l>
          <l>But saue his head for me to know him by, </l>
          <l>Authour of all my griefe and misery. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e107880">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Ile interrupt his passion. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-lord" xml:id="ep000284-e107900">
          <speaker>Lord. </speaker>
          <l>Stay my Liege. </l>
          <l>You shall heare more, here comes the other Father. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e107930">Enter Clynton. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e107940">
          <speaker>Clyn. </speaker>
          <l>How now my Lord, haue you surprizd your Bride? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e107960">
          <speaker>Old. </speaker>
          <l>I thinke thy trechery conueyd her hence, </l>
          <l>And by thy meanes another was attyr'd </l>
          <l>In her habilaments to vexe me thus. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e108000">
          <speaker>Clyn. </speaker>
          <l>You highly wrong me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e108020">
          <speaker>Old. </speaker>
          <l>I would right you better, </l>
          <l>Were I assur'd of your close tretchery. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e108050">
          <speaker>Clyn. </speaker>
          <l>Threaten me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e108070">
          <speaker>Old. </speaker>
          <l>With no more then Ile performe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e108090">
          <speaker>Clyn. </speaker>
          <l>Not in cold blood. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e108110">
          <speaker>Old. </speaker>
          <l>No, but in blood like fire. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-012-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e108130">
          <speaker>Clinton. </speaker>
          <l>In choller, passion and a crazed braine, </l>
          <l>But when you haue slept vpon your menaces, </l>
          <l>You will not then make good a noble challenge, </l>
          <l>And enter single combate like a Lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e108180">
          <speaker>Old Fitz. </speaker>
          <l>There lie my gage I dare thee to the field, </l>
          <l>And will auer without the aduice of sleepe, </l>
          <l>That thou wert priuy to the Stewards blot. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e108220">
          <speaker>Clint. </speaker>
          <l>Ile take your gage, and meet you when you dare. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e108240">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>But we'le not suffer it, that loue the liues </l>
          <l>Of euery subiect, much more of our Peeres: </l>
          <l>And as for you Fitz-waters, that are growne </l>
          <l>Hotter then I exspected from your age, </l>
          <l>Except you can produce good witnesses, </l>
          <l>That Clinton has deceiu'd you of your Bride, </l>
          <l>Ile stay the combate or imprison you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e108320">
          <speaker>Fitz. </speaker>
          <l>I cannot prooue it, but I thinke tis so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e108340">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Correct such thoughts, and giue him back his gage. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e108360">
          <speaker>Fitz. </speaker>
          <l>With all my heart. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e108380">(giues bake the gage. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e108390">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Clinton I am satisfied. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e108410">Enter a Messenger with a Letter whith he offers to the King. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e108420">
          <speaker>King </speaker>
          <l>How now, what newes bring you? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-messenger" xml:id="ep000284-e108440">
          <speaker>Messenger </speaker>
          <l>Letters my Liege from the Count Palatine </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e108460">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Our noble friend Bauaria's valiant Duke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-messenger" xml:id="ep000284-e108480">
          <speaker>Messenger. </speaker>
          <l>From him my Leige. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e108500">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Weele read them instantly. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e108520">The Contents of the Letter. <p>Alls lost, our elected friend Sauoy taken prisoner, with him Bohemia, and Brandenburgh; sickenesse would not suffer mee to weare Armour, but by the helpe of the Royall Hermit, Peter the King of Spayne your friend and Beadesman I am recouered. The Bastard is made Emperour, and has shipt himselfe for Spaine, whither I purpose to saile to hinder <pb xml:id="ep000284-013-a"/>His intendements, If I suruiue the Battell, and be conquerour. Ile vnfitte you in England, except the Sea be my Sepulcher. </p>
        </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e108540">Your Friend in Armes, ROBERT the Palsgraue. </stage>
        <l>Ill newes, not suddenly to be amended, </l>
        <l>The Palsgraues sicknesse was the greatest losse. </l>
        <l>The Bastard Crownd, vncrowne him if thou canst, </l>
        <l>Thou that art matchlesse for thy Chiualrie. </l>
        <l>Send but his head from Spayne, to tread vpon, </l>
        <l>And I should count it an vnvalued gift. </l>
        <l>As for good Sauoy, and his Germaine Friends, </l>
        <l>Ere long Ile set them free, or make the soyle </l>
        <l>That holds them prisoners a Marsh-ground for blood, </l>
        <l>Till I heare newes from Spayne of good successe. </l>
        <l>Each day I liue will be a yeare of griefe. </l>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e108660">
          <speaker>Clynton. </speaker>
          <l>Pleaseth my Liege to lay aside your sorrow, </l>
          <l>And with your Royall person grace my house, </l>
          <l>Clynton will holde it an exceeding fauour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e108700">
          <speaker>Old Fitzw. </speaker>
          <l>So will Fitzwaters gratious soueraigne. </l>
          <l>And though this day looke blacke with my disgrace, </l>
          <l>Your Royall presence whites an Aethyops face. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e108740">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>I accept your kindnesse, &amp; wilbe your Guest. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e108760">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e108770">Enter the Palsgraue; Cullen: and Peter the King of Spayne, Drum, Cullors, and Soldiors. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e108780">
          <speaker>Palsg. </speaker>
          <l>Next vnto heauen to you, we giue the praise, </l>
          <l>Most zealous King for our recouery, </l>
          <l>And now my Lord of Cullen shew your selfe, </l>
          <l>As good a Souldier as a Cleargie man. </l>
          <l>In stead of Beades now vse a Martiall sword. </l>
          <l>For here in Spayne where the Blacke Prince incampte, </l>
          <l>And made the Bastard flie, our Tents are pitcht, </l>
          <l>And the prowde Foe comes with a Spleene inrag'de, </l>
          <l>To driue vs from Mazieres; Harry shall know, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-013-b"/>
          <l>As hee has Kingly blood within his veynes, </l>
          <l>And is a Caesar, hee shall meete with Caesars. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-cullen" xml:id="ep000284-e108900">
          <speaker>Cullen. </speaker>
          <l>I heare their Drummes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-peter" xml:id="ep000284-e108920">
          <speaker>Peter. </speaker>
          <l>And I reioyce to heare them, </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e108940">Enter to them the Bastard, Saxon, Mentz, and Trier. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e108950">
          <speaker>Bastard. </speaker>
          <l>The Palsgraue heere, now wee shall haue </l>
          <l>Your voyce to our Election, or for that your life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e108980">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>You were sicke in Germanie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e109000">
          <speaker>Palsgraue. </speaker>
          <l>But now recouered. </l>
          <l>And hither come to beate you out of Spaine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-trier" xml:id="ep000284-e109030">
          <speaker>Trier. </speaker>
          <l>He beares himself, as he were sure to conquer. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mentz" xml:id="ep000284-e109050">
          <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
          <l>And looks more like a Ioue then like a man. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e109070">
          <speaker>Palsgraue. </speaker>
          <l>I hold my thunder here, &amp; my right arme </l>
          <l>Has vigor in it, when you feele my blowes </l>
          <l>To giue you cause to call them Thunderboltes, </l>
          <l>If there be any in this Martiall Troope </l>
          <l>That with a Soldiours face, has a bold heart, </l>
          <l>And dares auerre that this religious prince </l>
          <l>Is not the lawfull and true King of Spaine, </l>
          <l>I will make good his Title by the sword, </l>
          <l>And against that prowde combattant oppose </l>
          <l>My selfe as challenger to fight for him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e109180">
          <speaker>Bastard. </speaker>
          <l>I dare take vp your gage, and answere you. </l>
          <l>But that I should impaire this dayes renowne, </l>
          <l>By giuing desperate men such meanes to dye, </l>
          <l>Who for you know your Armie weake, and fewe </l>
          <l>Would hazard that vpon a single fight. </l>
          <l>Which in the Battell you are sure to loose, </l>
          <l>No Foxlike pollicie shall blind my sight, </l>
          <l>But that Ile see the ruine of you all. </l>
          <l>This day ith Field, thine Palsgraue and the rest, </l>
          <l>He combats well rips vp an Armyes brest. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e109290">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>Ile answer his prowd challenge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e109310">
          <speaker>Bast. </speaker>
          <l>We forbid it, that are your Emperor, both in stile </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e109330">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>In stile, but not in power, that strength is mine, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-014-a"/>
          <l>Except youle be forsworne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e109360">
          <speaker>Bastard. </speaker>
          <l>This for an Oath, </l>
          <l>Th'art but the step by which I did ascend, </l>
          <l>And being vp, rest there till I descend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e109400">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>Youle answere this anon. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e109420">
          <speaker>Bastard. </speaker>
          <l>Here, or else-where. </l>
          <l>Didst euer know a Caesar that could feare. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e109450">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>Ile stabbe the Bastard. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-trier" xml:id="ep000284-e109470">
          <speaker>Trier. </speaker>
          <l>Worthy Duke desist. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e109490">Stayes him. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e109500">
          <speaker>Palsg: </speaker>
          <l>No Combat then will be accepted of. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e109520">
          <speaker>Bastard. </speaker>
          <l>In general, with our powers in the open field, </l>
          <l>But not betwixt the Generalls priuately. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e109550">
          <speaker>Palsgr: </speaker>
          <l>Then you are Cowardes all. </l>
          <l>Ile so proclaime you in my thundring Drums, </l>
          <l>And by the gloryes that I hope to win, </l>
          <l>Proue it this day to thy perpetuall shame: </l>
          <l>But to a hartlesse foe words are but vaine. </l>
          <l>Alarum Drum, that showres of blood may raigne. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e109620">Exeunt omnes. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e109630">Alarum, The Bastards side beaten off. Enter in an excursion Bastard, Saxon, Mentz, and Trier. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e109640">
          <speaker>Bastard. </speaker>
          <l>It shall be treason to my Fame to day, </l>
          <l>If I encounter any Foe ith field, </l>
          <l>Till I haue combatted this drunken Saxon. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e109680">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>How Bastard, how? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e109700">
          <speaker>Bast. </speaker>
          <l>Bastard! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e109720">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>What else? </l>
          <l>Thou wert twice misbegotten, once in Nature, </l>
          <l>And secondly, in being any prides defalt, </l>
          <l>By which thou art a Bastard Emperour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e109770">
          <speaker>Bastard. </speaker>
          <l>Stand from about me, or Ile strike you dead </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mentz" xml:id="ep000284-e109790">
          <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
          <l>Remember where you are amongst your foes </l>
          <l>Who by your discord may destroy vs all. </l>
          <l>And this aduantage of your variance </l>
          <l>Giues them the victorie with easinesse. </l>
          <l>If not for your owne Honours and your liues, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-014-b"/>
          <l>Forbeare for ours. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-trier" xml:id="ep000284-e109860">
          <speaker>Trier. </speaker>
          <l>They shal not combat here: </l>
          <l>Ile make my Rotchet crimson like your Colours, </l>
          <l>Ere I stand by and suffer such a wrong. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e109900">
          <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
          <l>How these braue Churchmen talke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e109920">
          <speaker>Bast. </speaker>
          <l>Are you in your Pulpits? <stage xml:id="ep000284-e109940">Strikes the Bishops on their Targets, and fights with Saxon. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e109950">Enter Palsgraue, Peter, and Cullen, with Souldiers. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-trier" xml:id="ep000284-e109960">
          <speaker>Trier. </speaker>
          <l>Here's those will strike you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e109980">
          <speaker>Bast. </speaker>
          <l>What, the Palsgraue come? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e110000">
          <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
          <l>Emperour be wise, &amp; ioyne thy force to mine, </l>
          <l>Till we haue driuen away the enemy, </l>
          <l>And then returne to our old variance. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e110040">
          <speaker>Ba. </speaker>
          <l>I am Saxons till the Palsgraue dye or fly. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palantine" xml:id="ep000284-e110060">
          <speaker>Pa. </speaker>
          <l>You should haue fought stil, twould haue bin my glory, </l>
          <l>To haue giuen ayme, &amp; then the conqueror conquerd: </l>
          <l>But what your variance leaues vnfinish here, </l>
          <l>Ile end with the destruction of you both. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e110110">
          <speaker>Bast. </speaker>
          <l>We feare you not. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e110130">
          <speaker>Pals. </speaker>
          <l>Vpon them valiant friends. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000284-e110150">Charge vpon them, and the Bastard taken Prisoner on the Stage, Saxon and the Bishops beaten off. </stage>
          <l>Saxon is fled, Caesar my captiue is, </l>
          <l>I must not lose him; guard the Emperour sure, </l>
          <l>Whilst I pursue the Duke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-peter" xml:id="ep000284-e110190">
          <speaker>Peter. </speaker>
          <l>We will. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e110210">
          <speaker>Bast. </speaker>
          <l>Am I your prisoner? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-peter" xml:id="ep000284-e110230">
          <speaker>Peter. </speaker>
          <l>Not so good, my slaue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-cullen" xml:id="ep000284-e110250">
          <speaker>Cullen. </speaker>
          <l>To trample on, or vse as he likes best. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e110270">
          <speaker>Bast. </speaker>
          <l>We are Brothers. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-peter" xml:id="ep000284-e110290">
          <speaker>Peter. </speaker>
          <l>Now: but in your high estate, </l>
          <l>No greater enemy then you had I. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-cullen" xml:id="ep000284-e110320">
          <speaker>Cul. </speaker>
          <l>Best that we guide him to the Palsgraues. Tent. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e110340">Enter Saxon with two swords, and meetes them. </stage>
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-015-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e110350">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>Although he be Ambitious, and my Foe, </l>
          <l>Honour commaunds mee that I reskew him. </l>
          <l>That I may haue the honour of his death. </l>
          <l>When we 〈◊〉 Maisteries in a single fight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-peter" xml:id="ep000284-e110400">
          <speaker>Peter. </speaker>
          <l>Tis Saxon, Guarde him sure. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-cullen" xml:id="ep000284-e110420">
          <speaker>Cullen. </speaker>
          <l>To our best power. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e110440">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>No further, if you meane to saue your liues. </l>
          <l>The Palsgraues slaine, his blood wreakes on my sword, </l>
          <l>And I aduise you for your owne discharge, </l>
          <l>To giue this valiant Emperour libertie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-peter" xml:id="ep000284-e110490">
          <speaker>Peter. </speaker>
          <l>Not whilst wee liue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e110510">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>Helpe to release your selfe. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e110530">Saxon giues him a sworde. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e110540">
          <speaker>Bastard. </speaker>
          <l>Most willingly. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000284-e110560">They beats of Cullen the King of Spayne, </stage>
          <l>Thanks for your paines, but yet we will be Foes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e110580">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>To horse, to horse, and talke of that elswhere. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e110600">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e110610">Enter againe Cullen and Peter. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-peter" xml:id="ep000284-e110620">
          <speaker>Peter. </speaker>
          <l>This was the most ill chance that euer hapned. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-cullen" xml:id="ep000284-e110640">
          <speaker>Cullen. </speaker>
          <l>He saide he had slaine the Palsgraue, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-peter" xml:id="ep000284-e110660">
          <speaker>Peter. </speaker>
          <l>Twas his cunning to astonish vs with feare, but </l>
          <l>If he liue, how shall we answer him for this mischance. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-cullen" xml:id="ep000284-e110690">
          <speaker>Cullen. </speaker>
          <l>See where he comes, I would the storm were past. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e110710">Enter Palsgraue. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e110720">
          <speaker>Palsgraue. </speaker>
          <l>I lost him in the preasse, his snowy steed </l>
          <l>Was crimsond ouer with the blood of men, </l>
          <l>And Lyon-like he fought with all his strength, </l>
          <l>But since the Emperour is my prisoner, </l>
          <l>I shall die lesse regard the Dukes escape. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-peter" xml:id="ep000284-e110780">
          <speaker>Peter. </speaker>
          <l>Oh Noble Syr, we haue deceiued your trust, </l>
          <l>And lost the Jewell you had vs keepe. </l>
          <l>Caesar by Saxon is redeemd and fleed, </l>
          <l>And wee 〈…〉 for his escape. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e110830">
          <speaker>Palsgraue. </speaker>
          <l>When fortune is dispos'd? 〈…〉 a man. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-015-b"/>
          <l>Valour and foresight are of no effect: </l>
          <l>Releast by Saxon, and his Keepers liue; </l>
          <l>You are not as I thought you, valiant men; </l>
          <l>But worse then these that runne away for feare. </l>
          <l>He should haue made passage through my heart, </l>
          <l>Ere scapt from me by Saxon or his plots: </l>
          <l>But now it is too late to follow him; </l>
          <l>And the whole Field is made a liquid Sea, </l>
          <l>Sinke may they both into the crimson fenne. </l>
          <l>But why should they sinke, you deserue it best: </l>
          <l>From hencefoorth Ile nere take a Spaniards part, </l>
          <l>Except he had a farre more valiant heart, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-peter" xml:id="ep000284-e110970">
          <speaker>Peter. </speaker>
          <l>Let my blood speake for me; faire words displease. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e110990">
          <speaker>Palsg. </speaker>
          <l>Well, since I thinke twas weaknes and not will, </l>
          <l>By which they are escapt, I calme my spleene, </l>
          <l>And rest content that we haue woon the field. </l>
          <l>After you are establish in your Throne, </l>
          <l>Ile sayle to England to regreete the King: </l>
          <l>And then to Germany, where if we meete </l>
          <l>Bauaria's, ayre shall be his winding sheete. </l>
          <l>Retreat, retreat, and thanke heauen for the day. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e111080">Enter Bastard, Saxon, Mentz, and Trier. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e111090">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>At your requests my Lords, I am contented </l>
          <l>To receiue this Emperour into grace and fauour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e111120">
          <speaker>Bast. </speaker>
          <l>He flouts me, would you haue me suffer this? </l>
          <l>At their requests they haue requested me </l>
          <l>To allay my spleene, and take thee into fauour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mentz" xml:id="ep000284-e111160">
          <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
          <l>Theyle nere be friends. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-trier" xml:id="ep000284-e111180">
          <speaker>Trier. </speaker>
          <l>Lets leaue them both to fight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e111200">
          <speaker>Bastard. </speaker>
          <l>Away. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e111220">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>Weele force you else. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mentz" xml:id="ep000284-e111240">
          <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
          <l>We are a going. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e111260">Exeunt Bishops. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e111270">
          <speaker>Bast. </speaker>
          <l>So, now I will imagine that this ground </l>
          <l>Is all the Empire that my greatnesse swayes: </l>
          <l>And that the heads of many rebell Subiects </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-016-a"/>
          <l>Are plaste on thee; that striking off thy head, </l>
          <l>I cut off halfe a Nation at a blow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e111330">
          <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
          <p>And I the Emperours of a Nation. </p>
          <stage xml:id="ep000284-e111350">Fight, and Saxon is downe. </stage>
          <l>Why dost not kill me, since tis in thy power? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e111370">
          <speaker>Bast. </speaker>
          <p>Thou sau'dst my life, for that Ile set the free. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e111390">
          <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
          <l>Caesar, thou art a Noble enemie; </l>
          <l>Hencefoorth I vow to relinquish euery ill </l>
          <l>That may displease thee, and obey thy will. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e111430">
          <speaker>Bast. </speaker>
          <p>Such be my conquests ouer those I loue. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e111450">As they embrace, </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e111460">Enter Trier and Cullen. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mentz" xml:id="ep000284-e111470">
          <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
          <p>So, they are friends, they haue fought away their anger. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e111490">
          <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
          <p>Has conquer'd me with courtesie and valour. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mendoza" xml:id="ep000284-e111510">
          <speaker>Men. </speaker>
          <l>Then now to counsel how we shall proceede </l>
          <l>In this most dangerous warre against the Palsgraue, </l>
          <l>Who as I heare by firme intelligence. </l>
          <l>Meanes with his Fleete to touch the English Shore, </l>
          <l>And draw the valiant Edward to his part. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e111570">
          <speaker>Bast. </speaker>
          <l>If such a day come, twill be blacke to vs: </l>
          <l>For of all Nations in the world, I hate </l>
          <l>To deale with Englishmen they conquer so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e111610">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>Follow his example and lets get a King </l>
          <l>To take our part, as well as they haue done: </l>
          <l>France has beene wasted by their crueltie, </l>
          <l>And cannot but in spleene desire reuenge, </l>
          <l>Were he sollicited to be our friend, </l>
          <l>We should with the more ease be conquerers. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mentz" xml:id="ep000284-e111680">
          <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
          <p>Send thither. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-trier" xml:id="ep000284-e111700">
          <speaker>Trier. </speaker>
          <p>Or fayle thither. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e111720">
          <speaker>Bast. </speaker>
          <l>Thats the best: </l>
          <l>But shall we onely build our hopes on strength; </l>
          <l>I thinke twere good to peece the Lyons skinne </l>
          <l>Where it too short falls, with the Foxes skinne, </l>
          <l>A couple of Protean villaines I haue ready, </l>
          <l>For any dangerous attempt in peace, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-016-b"/>
          <l>And they can poyson, stab, and lye in wayte </l>
          <l>Like Serpents, to intrappe and cease their prey, </l>
          <l>Mendoza and Vandome, those are the men: </l>
          <l>Let them be call'd in. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mentz" xml:id="ep000284-e111830">
          <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
          <p>They are heare, great Caesar. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e111850">Enter Vandome and Mendoza. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-vandome" xml:id="ep000284-e111860">
          <speaker>Van. </speaker>
          <p>Most mightie Emperour, whats your Highnes will? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e111880">
          <speaker>Bast. </speaker>
          <l>That vnto England presently you sayle, </l>
          <l>And there consort you with the Earle of Artoyes, </l>
          <l>A Frenchman borne, but one that loues vs well; </l>
          <l>Let him and you send vs intelligence </l>
          <l>Of the proceedings of the English King, </l>
          <l>With the haughty Palsgraue, giue the Earle this Letter, </l>
          <l>By which yee may winne credit in his trust: </l>
          <l>And er't be long I will deuise a plot, </l>
          <l>Which you shall mannage, for the generall good. </l>
          <l>Be carefull; as you doe respect our loue, </l>
          <l>And hope for gold in showres, meane time take this. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mendoza" xml:id="ep000284-e112000">
          <speaker>Mend. </speaker>
          <p>Your will shall be obey'd. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-vandome" xml:id="ep000284-e112020">
          <speaker>Vand. </speaker>
          <p>It shall be done. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e112040">
          <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
          <l>Great Ioue can say no more: </l>
          <l>That State thriues best that has such Slaues in store. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e112070">
          <speaker>Bast. </speaker>
          <l>See our Fleet ready: and yee swelling gales, </l>
          <l>That blow the good houres, fill our empty sayles. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e112100">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e112110">Enter the King the Queene, and Poytieres. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e112120">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord of Poytieres, as you are inform'd, </l>
          <l>Where meanes the Emperour and his trayne to land? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-poitiers" xml:id="ep000284-e112150">
          <speaker>Poyt. </speaker>
          <p>Here at this 〈◊〉 of Bolleigne, &amp; the newes </p>
          <l>Is certaine that his Mightinesse is neere. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e112180">
          <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
          <l>How angry has the heauens as bin with the sea, </l>
          <l>That it hath boyld so much, and cast the sands </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-017-a"/>
          <l>Into such mountaines that they ouer-looke </l>
          <l>The bounds that held them in. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e112230">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <l>Well may our friends </l>
          <l>Escape the danger of this heauy storme: </l>
          <l>Small gusts at Land, sinke a whole Fleete at sea; </l>
          <l>And whilst our Cities keepe vs from their rage, </l>
          <l>The Rocks beare them, as Tennis-Courts doe balles. </l>
          <l>Ide haue an Atheist trauell through the deepe, </l>
          <l>And he shall see such wonders, that his soule </l>
          <l>Would make him soone beleeue there is a God. </l>
          <l>But what fayre Gentle woman haue we here, </l>
          <l>Which is a Ship-wrackt creature, comes a shore? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e112340">Enter Floramell. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e112350">
          <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
          <l>All wet and weary with a boysterous storme, </l>
          <l>At last I haue set my foote vpon the Land; </l>
          <l>I tremble as a Feauer shooke my ioynts, </l>
          <l>But tis the Ocean that has frozen me: </l>
          <l>Drop there thou moysture of a swelling Flood. </l>
          <l>And let me see, no Fisher-man at hand, </l>
          <l>To tell me in what Coast I am arriu'd: </l>
          <l>Alas I see none, I shall dye with cold. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-multiple" xml:id="ep000284-e112440">
          <speaker>Q. Poytiers. </speaker>
          <p>Speake to her, giue the woman comfort. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-poitiers" xml:id="ep000284-e112460">
          <speaker>Poyt. </speaker>
          <p>How is it with pretty Gentlewoman? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e112480">
          <speaker>Flor. </speaker>
          <l>Sir, I am very cold, and wet, and ill, </l>
          <l>Would you could helpe me to a little fire </l>
          <l>To dry my selfe, and I would pray for you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-poitiers" xml:id="ep000284-e112520">
          <speaker>Poyt. </speaker>
          <l>Tis now no time to reason of your state: </l>
          <l>Here take my Cloake. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e112550">A taffata Cloake. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e112560">
          <speaker>Flora. </speaker>
          <l>Alasse Sir, tis but thinne, </l>
          <l>And makes 〈◊〉 the more to 〈…〉 </l>
          <l>I would be shifted into warmer Roades, </l>
          <l>If I could meete with some kind Gentlewoman. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e112610">
          <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
          <p>Make vse of me, you shall not want for helpe. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e112630">
          <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
          <l>You seeme to be of a Maiestique state, </l>
          <l>What should a poore distressed Gentlewoman, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-017-b"/>
          <l>Trouble a person of such eminence? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e112670">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <p>Thy state wants present pitty, women take it </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e112690">
          <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
          <l>I haue seene a King ere now, </l>
          <l>And by your Diadem you should be one: </l>
          <l>Pray, rather let me dye then trouble you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e112730">
          <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
          <l>Tis perfect charitie to helpe the poore: </l>
          <l>Yet by these Iewels, you should beare a place, </l>
          <l>If not amongst the Royall, with the Noble. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e112770">
          <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
          <l>Indeede I am but a poore Gentlewoman, </l>
          <l>Punisht for wearing Iewels in a storme: </l>
          <l>But I haue lost a husband whom I lou'd, </l>
          <l>For marying whom, I haue endur'd this crosse; </l>
          <l>And now his friends, if they should finde me out, </l>
          <l>Would finish what the storme has left vndone. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e112840">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <p>His name? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e112860">
          <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
          <l>Twas Infortunio, as mine is, </l>
          <l>With the alteration of a letter onely. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e112890">
          <speaker>Quee. </speaker>
          <l>Good Infortuna goe along with me, </l>
          <l>Ile finde some helpe for this thy misery. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e112920">
          <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
          <l>May the Sea neuer vse you of this fashion; </l>
          <l>I take your courtesie, and will attend. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e112950">Exeunt Queene and Floramell. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e112960">
          <speaker>F.K. </speaker>
          <p>Young, fayre, and louely, is she not Poytiers? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-poitiers" xml:id="ep000284-e112980">
          <speaker>Poyt. </speaker>
          <p>She is a comely, and a sweet Gentlewoman. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e113000">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <l>In my opinion shee's the fayrest creature </l>
          <l>Nature ere made. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-poitiers" xml:id="ep000284-e113030">
          <speaker>Poyt. </speaker>
          <p>In loue my gracious Liege? </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e113050">(strange. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e113060">
          <speaker>F.K. </speaker>
          <p>What and my Queen aliue, that would seeme strange. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-poitiers" xml:id="ep000284-e113080">
          <speaker>Poyt. </speaker>
          <p>Loue does regard no person, nor the time. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e113100">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <p>Loue is a power will ouer-rule a King. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-poitiers" xml:id="ep000284-e113120">
          <speaker>Poyt. </speaker>
          <l>Finding her honest, though of meane estate, </l>
          <l>You may doe well to rayse poore vertue vp, </l>
          <l>And marry her to some great Nobleman. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e113160">
          <speaker>F. K. </speaker>
          <p>Ile thinke of that hereafter: now, the newes? </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e113180">Enter Queene. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e113190">
          <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
          <p>The Emperour and the Electors are arriu'd. </p>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-018-a"/>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e113210">Enter Bast ard, Saxon, Mentz, and Trier. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e113220">
          <speaker>Bast. </speaker>
          <p>Health to the Maiestie and Seate of France. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e113240">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <l>As welcome hither is your Mightinesse, </l>
          <l>As if you were arriu'd in Germany. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e113270">
          <speaker>Bast. </speaker>
          <p>I thanke King Iohn. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e113290">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <p>Saxon, with Mentz, and Trier. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e113310">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <p>We rest your louing friend for Warre. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-trier" xml:id="ep000284-e113330">
          <speaker>Trier. </speaker>
          <p>For Counsell. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e113350">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <p>And Counsell is as great a friend as War. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mentz" xml:id="ep000284-e113370">
          <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
          <p>It hath preuaild as much. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e113390">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <p>Thrice welcome all. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e113410">
          <speaker>Bast. </speaker>
          <l>The storme has kept vs ouerlong at Sea: </l>
          <l>But Mighty King of France, worse stormes then these </l>
          <l>Haue and will shake vs, if you helpe vs not: </l>
          <l>All things goe Backwards, that should bode vs good; </l>
          <l>And he that is Conqueror already, </l>
          <l>The haughty palsgraue, is to England sayld, </l>
          <l>To ioyne with Edward in our ouerthrow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e113490">
          <speaker>F.K. </speaker>
          <l>We haue felt the valour of the English King, </l>
          <l>And of his sonne, the Blacke Prince now deceased: </l>
          <l>Witnes Poytiers and Cressey, where our blood </l>
          <l>Royall, although it be sau'd to make clay </l>
          <l>Moyst with the showers, and temper the dry earth: </l>
          <l>When I and all my sonnes were prisoners tane, </l>
          <l>And had to England to be wondred at: </l>
          <l>Ransom'd although I was, it grieues me much </l>
          <l>I cannot doe the like vnto my foe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-savoy" xml:id="ep000284-e113590">
          <speaker>Sa. </speaker>
          <l>Let your French Souldiers ioyne themselues with ours, </l>
          <l>And weele inuade his Kingdome. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e113620">
          <speaker>Bast. </speaker>
          <p>And constraine him &amp; the Palsgraue to the like disgrace. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mendoza" xml:id="ep000284-e113640">
          <speaker>Me. </speaker>
          <l>Fortune was neuer stedfast vnto any. </l>
          <l>But like the Ocean that bounds in the Land, </l>
          <l>Both ebbs and flowes according to the Moone. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e113680">
          <speaker>Quee. </speaker>
          <l>But if I might aduise your Maiestie, </l>
          <l>By former losses you should be more wise, </l>
          <l>Then hazzard France againe to the like snoyle: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-018-b"/>
          <l>Edward is fortunate in all his warres; </l>
          <l>And wise men will not striue against the streames </l>
          <l>Therefore be circumspect, and keepe your owne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e113750">
          <speaker>F.K. </speaker>
          <l>This theame our counsel shal at large discusse, </l>
          <l>Till when, to England weele Ambassage send, </l>
          <l>To aduise King Edward not to be our foe, </l>
          <l>Left it offend vs, that are friends to both: </l>
          <l>If thé Doue speede not, weele the Serpent proue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e113810">
          <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
          <l>And winne by craft, what may not be by loue. </l>
          <l>Who shall haue that imployment? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e113840">
          <speaker>Bast. </speaker>
          <p>Not your Honor, because your spirit is rough and turbulent. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e113860">
          <speaker>F.K. </speaker>
          <l>No, if I might intreat these reuerend Bishops, </l>
          <l>By them I would direct this Embassie: </l>
          <l>Since it concernes them, it behooues they stirre, </l>
          <l>Who know the sweetes, will cause no warre. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-trier" xml:id="ep000284-e113910">
          <speaker>Trier. </speaker>
          <p>Weele vndertake it, if the Emperour please. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e113930">
          <speaker>Bast. </speaker>
          <l>When I send thither, it shall be in thunder: </l>
          <l>Yet as the French King orders it proceede. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e113960">
          <speaker>F. K. </speaker>
          <l>You know your charge, be milde, but yet not base, </l>
          <l>Though we giue ground, we will not lose our place. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e113990">Manet Saxon. Exeunt. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e114000">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>Euen now a bold conceit hath entered me, </l>
          <l>And thats to visit England in disguise: </l>
          <l>As well to further our conspiracie </l>
          <l>Against the Palsgraue and King Edwards life, </l>
          <l>As to surueigh the Countrey, and obserue </l>
          <l>What Hauens best to entertaine a Fleete: </l>
          <l>The English Nation with my soule I hate, </l>
          <l>And would doe any thing to winne the State. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e114090">Exit. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e114100">Enter Edward, Clynton, olde Fytzwaters, the Palsgraue, Cullen, and others. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e114110">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Not possible my Lords to finde those men? </l>
          <l>Are they so wily to deceiue vs all? </l>
          <l>Sure they are harboured by some neere about, </l>
          <l>That does affect the English Diadem: </l>
          <l>He's worse then mad would ayme at Englands Crowne, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-019-a"/>
          <l>Though the Blacke Prince be dead, so many sonnes </l>
          <l>I haue left to gouerne, which marres their rule. </l>
          <l>Edward himselfe has left a hopefull heyre, </l>
          <l>The Princely Richard to inherit it. </l>
          <l>Plots yet, tricks yet, well we must hope the best. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e114220">
          <speaker>Pals. </speaker>
          <l>I rather thinke the ill was aymd at me, </l>
          <l>Because I came to mooue your Maiestie. </l>
          <l>For the deposing of the Emperour: </l>
          <l>And it is knowne the Bastard is my foe, </l>
          <l>Witnesse the Warres in Germany and Spayne: </l>
          <l>Treason by him is euermore in act, </l>
          <l>His brayne coynes faster then the English Mynt; </l>
          <l>Tretcherous proceedings, gold has many friends: </l>
          <l>And he must be a man of excellent vertue </l>
          <l>Whom it corrupts not. Howsoere, I am sorry </l>
          <l>The Saylors did escape. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e114340">
          <speaker>Clyn. </speaker>
          <l>Here are their cases. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e114360">2. Saylors canuas Suits. </stage>
          </l>
          <l>Vnder the which I thinke were better cloathes, </l>
          <l>And for their Steedes, thought could not be more quicke, </l>
          <l>Or we had tooke them. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e114400">
          <speaker>O. Fytz. </speaker>
          <l>They were swift indeed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e114420">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>As swiftly with their flight vanish our feares. </l>
          <l>And now most Noble Palsgraue of the Rheine, </l>
          <l>Thinke your selfe welcome to the English Court: </l>
          <l>And reuerend Cullen. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-cullen" xml:id="ep000284-e114470">
          <speaker>Cullen. </speaker>
          <p>I doe thanke your Grace. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e114490">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Your Father lou'd me well, and for his sake, </l>
          <l>As well as for your owne, Ile honour you: </l>
          <l>And after feasting we will try your force </l>
          <l>In friendly manner at a Tournament, </l>
          <l>Which as I thinke, you haue prepard my Lords. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e114550">
          <speaker>O. F. </speaker>
          <l>We haue my Liege, &amp; the most youthful blood </l>
          <l>That the Court yeelds will shew their Chiualdry, </l>
          <l>In honour of Bauaria's Royall Duke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e114590">
          <speaker>Palsg. </speaker>
          <l>Let him sit fast that shall contend with me, </l>
          <l>Or I shall shake him, be he nere so Royall: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-019-b"/>
          <l>I shew no fauour when I am in Armes, </l>
          <l>Nor looke for any from my Opposites. </l>
          <l>But Turnaments are reuels made for sport, </l>
          <l>And hee runnes well, that gets a good report. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e114660">
          <speaker>King: </speaker>
          <l>Weele trie your valour, &amp; perchance run with you. </l>
          <l>Leade on. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e114690">Exeunt. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e114700">Enter the Earle of Artoise. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-artois" xml:id="ep000284-e114710">
          <speaker>Artoise. </speaker>
          <l>The discontented English like to mee, </l>
          <l>Hates all delight, I and the Court it selfe: </l>
          <l>To lead a priuate life, where they may plot </l>
          <l>Reuenge on those that are theyr opposites; </l>
          <l>Not many yeares past, who but I esteem'd, </l>
          <l>King Edward has vpon my shoulder leand, </l>
          <l>And thankt mee in mine eare many a time, </l>
          <l>For making Fraunce his, I betraid Valoys </l>
          <l>My soueraigne King, in England to get grace: </l>
          <l>And now I lookte to be a Duke at least: </l>
          <l>Artoise is sleighted as a thing forgot, </l>
          <l>But I haue sent my Attendant to the Court, </l>
          <l>And if he speed not, I shall proue as false </l>
          <l>Edward to thee, as to my Natiue French. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e114860">Enter a Seruant. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-servant" xml:id="ep000284-e114870">
          <speaker>Seruant. </speaker>
          <l>The King is not at leysure </l>
          <l>To listen to your sute; All his thoughts now </l>
          <l>Are taken vp to giue the Palsgraue grace, </l>
          <l>Who is come to Court, and meanes to Turney there </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-artois" xml:id="ep000284-e114920">
          <speaker>Art. </speaker>
          <l>Treason run with them, or som dángerous plot, </l>
          <l>Take life and being to destroy them both; </l>
          <l>Must my affaires giue place vnto a Palgraue? </l>
          <l>T'was I that quartered with the English Lyons, </l>
          <l>The Armes of France, in opening Edwards Title, </l>
          <l>Which but for mee had in obliuion slept, </l>
          <l>Then I was as the Palsgraue in his brest, </l>
          <l>My sight his foode, my saying his harts rest. </l>
          <l>Who's that, that knock's look forth, &amp; bring vs word? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-servant" xml:id="ep000284-e115020">
          <speaker>Seru. </speaker>
          <p>A couple of Gentleme would speak with you. </p>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-020-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000284-artois" xml:id="ep000284-e115040">
          <speaker>Arto. </speaker>
          <l>Let them com in, were they a pair of mischiefs, </l>
          <l>They are welcome now. For I haue thoughts like Held, </l>
          <l>Blacke and confusde. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e115080">Enter Vandome and Mendozze. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-servant" xml:id="ep000284-e115090">
          <speaker>Seru. </speaker>
          <p>These are the Gentlemen. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-vandome" xml:id="ep000284-e115110">
          <speaker>Vandome. </speaker>
          <l>Our busines is to you most noble Artoise, </l>
          <l>The Emperour does salute you in this Letter, </l>
          <l>And prayes you by the Honour of an Earle, </l>
          <l>You faile not to conioyne your ayde with ours, </l>
          <l>About some plot against his Enemies. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-artois" xml:id="ep000284-e115170">
          <speaker>Artoise. </speaker>
          <l>The Letter speaks the words, but names no plot. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mendoza" xml:id="ep000284-e115190">
          <speaker>Mendo: </speaker>
          <l>Tis not deuisd as yet, but ere lóg great Caesar. </l>
          <l>Will set it downe, and send it to vs all. </l>
          <l>Now as his Mightinesse desires is this, </l>
          <l>That you giue shelter to vs while wee stay </l>
          <l>For his Affaires in England, and your pénsion </l>
          <l>Which euery yeare you haue receiued from him, </l>
          <l>Shall from henceforth be doubled with his loue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-artois" xml:id="ep000284-e115270">
          <speaker>Artoise. </speaker>
          <l>Caesar is gracious, and has my hart: </l>
          <l>But were not you the Seruants that attended </l>
          <l>On the last Emperour that was made away, </l>
          <l>And helpt to send him to a timelesse graue? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-vandome" xml:id="ep000284-e115320">
          <speaker>Vandome. </speaker>
          <p>We were my Lord. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-artois" xml:id="ep000284-e115340">
          <speaker>Artoise. </speaker>
          <p>Let me embrace you in mine armes for that. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mendoza" xml:id="ep000284-e115360">
          <speaker>Mendo: </speaker>
          <l>But that ill speed followed our hopes to day, </l>
          <l>We had giuen a period to King Edwards life, </l>
          <l>And to the Palsgraues. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-vandome" xml:id="ep000284-e115400">
          <speaker>Vandome: </speaker>
          <l>Wee attempted it. </l>
          <l>Habited like Saylers, but our pistolls failde, </l>
          <l>And after long pursute, our Roabes throwne off, </l>
          <l>We escapte with life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mendoza" xml:id="ep000284-e115450">
          <speaker>Mendozze. </speaker>
          <p>And come to liue with you. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-artois" xml:id="ep000284-e115470">
          <speaker>Artoise. </speaker>
          <l>Liue here as safe as in a Fort of brasse. </l>
          <l>Such men I wisht for to a fit my spleene, </l>
          <l>Vnto one marke all our affections tend. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-020-b"/>
          <l>And they both dye if that the Emperour send. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e115520">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e115530">The Trumpets sound within as at a Tournament: A great shoute. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e115540">Enter old Fytzwaters and Clynton. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e115550">
          <speaker>O. Fytz. </speaker>
          <l>Did you ere see a better Tournament, </l>
          <l>Or brauer Runners then this day appear'd </l>
          <l>In the Tilt-yard? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e115590">
          <speaker>Clyn. </speaker>
          <l>The best that ere I saw. </l>
          <l>What a braue Horse the Palsgraue rid vpon, </l>
          <l>And with what courage, nimblenesse, and strength, </l>
          <l>Did he vnhorse his valiant opposites? </l>
          <l>Speares flew in splinters, halfe the way to heauen, </l>
          <l>And none that ranne against him kept this saddle, </l>
          <l>Except the King, and he demeand him well: </l>
          <l>It ioyes my soule, that he has yet in store </l>
          <l>Such manly vigor; and the peoples hearts </l>
          <l>Were not a little glad. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e115700">
          <speaker>O. Fytz. </speaker>
          <p>Here they come all. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e115720">Enter King Edward, Palsgraue, Cullen, and others. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e115730">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>I feare you are ouer-wearied with our sports, </l>
          <l>To speake the truth. I feele them troublesome, </l>
          <l>Whether it be by discontinuancce or age, I know not, </l>
          <l>But my breath growes short. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e115780">
          <speaker>Pals. </speaker>
          <l>What Oke is euer strong? age makes Ioues tree, </l>
          <l>The fayrest King, and Emperour of the wood, </l>
          <l>To bend it selfe, and bow his lofty armes </l>
          <l>Downewards vnto the earth that softned it. </l>
          <l>No Caeder growes straight till his latest day: </l>
          <l>As there's a weaknesse in their springing vp, </l>
          <l>So is there in their declination. </l>
          <l>The middle age the luffy does expresse, </l>
          <l>And there flowes vigor, like a sea of strength, </l>
          <l>Able to beare downe what doth stand the streame: </l>
          <l>Such is mine now, but as my yeers doe flow, </l>
          <l>Like Okes and Caeders they must straight bow low. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-021-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e115910">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Sit by our side, and weare a Caesars wreath. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e115930">A Wreath of Laurell. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e115940">
          <speaker>Palsgr. </speaker>
          <l>Victorious Edward keepe it as your right, </l>
          <l>And let it mingle with your Royall Crowne, </l>
          <l>That haue deseru'd it in a field of warre, </l>
          <l>Not as tis mine, giuen for a Turnament. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e115990">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>It is our gifte, and you shall weare it still, </l>
          <l>Bring forth the other honour wee intend </l>
          <l>Vnto this thrice renowned Gentleman. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e116030">Enter an Herauld, with a faire Cushion, and the Garter vppon it. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-herald" xml:id="ep000284-e116040">
          <speaker>Herald. </speaker>
          <l>My gratious Liege here is the Garter ready. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e116060">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Which to the Palsgraue we command you beare, </l>
          <l>Garter and Herald heere presents your Honour </l>
          <l>With the Order of the Garter, whence he takes </l>
          <l>His Office and his Name, by our Decree: </l>
          <l>This is a fauour which no Forraine Prince </l>
          <l>Euer enioyd yet, but the time may come </l>
          <l>When Kings in seeking it may be instald, </l>
          <l>It was my Institution, and is worne </l>
          <l>By none but the most Noble, and those fewe </l>
          <l>Hereafter I will tell your Excellence </l>
          <l>The Motiue why the Order was deuisd': </l>
          <l>Meane time his hand shall claspe it to your Legge, </l>
          <l>For tis a custome which you must not breake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e116200">
          <speaker>Palsgr: </speaker>
          <l>Your Highnes honours mee exceedingly. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e116220">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>You are now my Fellow-Knight, and you must sweare, </l>
          <l>To fight for Ladies, &amp; their Fames preserue, </l>
          <l>But that wee leaue to Deputation, </l>
          <l>It shall suffice now, say on, passe your word. </l>
          <l>My Word and Oath, so please your Maiestie, </l>
          <l>The Motto, as I red it was in French, </l>
          <l>Honny, soit qui Mal y: </l>
          <l>Ill be his meede makes goodnesse an offence: </l>
          <l>Or, Euill bee to him that euill thinkes. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-021-b"/>
          <l>I haue learnt the sence, the Order I will keepe </l>
          <l>Inuiolate, by Hand and by my Sword; </l>
          <l>And hope in time it shall as famous prooue, </l>
          <l>As that of Malta or Ierusalems. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e116360">
          <speaker>Clinton. </speaker>
          <l>The Bishops, Mentz, &amp; Trier, sent from France, </l>
          <l>By the French King desire to be admitted. </l>
          <l>With them associate comes the bold Poytiers, </l>
          <l>But as I thinke hee's no Embassadour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e116410">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Giue them admittance. </l>
          <l>We could not wish for a more braue assemblie, </l>
          <l>Then at this instant to giue Audience. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e116450">Enter Mentz and Trier, and Saxon disguised like a Frenchman. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mentz" xml:id="ep000284-e116460">
          <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
          <l>Because the matter does concerne our selues </l>
          <l>Most mighty King of England, we haue taken </l>
          <l>This Embassie in hand, not sent by Caesar, </l>
          <l>But from your Neighbour, the great King of France: </l>
          <l>Who by vs first intreates, after enioynes </l>
          <l>You take good heede how you the Palsgraue aide, </l>
          <l>For that he sayes, and will maintaine asmuch, </l>
          <l>It were vniust now Caesar to depose, </l>
          <l>Who by his valour, if all Titles faile, </l>
          <l>Merits the honour of an Emperour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-trier" xml:id="ep000284-e116570">
          <speaker>Trier. </speaker>
          <l>And that he is peerlesse for his minde, </l>
          <l>And haughty resolution through the world, </l>
          <l>That none so well as hee deserues the stile, </l>
          <l>And being inuested in the dignitie, </l>
          <l>Twere a dishonour great and Capitall, </l>
          <l>Now to constraine him to a lower place: </l>
          <l>Which if you seeke, heele shield from such disgrace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e116650">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Has France forgot our former victories, </l>
          <l>That his Commission is so peremptorie? </l>
          <l>Or is it but the Stratageme of Caesar. </l>
          <l>To blinde vs with the Name of the French King? </l>
          <l>And Iohn of France be ignorant of this, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-022-a"/>
          <l>Before we answere your prowde Embassie, </l>
          <l>Weel send Embassadours to know the truth: </l>
          <l>And if we be deceiu'd by a tricke, </l>
          <l>Caesar shall know he has dishonourd vs. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e116750">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>I am a Frenchman, and a Peere of France, </l>
          <l>My name Poyctiers, but no Ambassadour. </l>
          <l>Yet by the Honours that my sword hath wonne, </l>
          <l>King Iohn of France deliuered what they spake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e116800">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Being no Embassadour, why came you hither </l>
          <l>To be a Spye, and to surueigh my Land? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e116830">
          <speaker>Saxon </speaker>
          <l>A Spye, one of my blood without disguise, </l>
          <l>Being the first Reuealer of my selfe, </l>
          <l>How can this hold King Edward to be true? </l>
          <l>I vse no Intelligence but with my sword: </l>
          <l>Nor seeke for other corners then deepe wounds. </l>
          <l>So if I come by any great mans hart </l>
          <l>In honourable difference I surueigh it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e116910">
          <speaker>Palsgraue. </speaker>
          <l>At whose hart aime you now, that you are come? </l>
          <l>To iustifie an Embassage against mee? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e116940">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>I say who weares the Germaine Diadem </l>
          <l>Deserues it better then the best that's here; </l>
          <l>Or any whom the English King, or thou </l>
          <l>For priuate reasons wouldst preferre to weare it, </l>
          <l>And that it is not honour prompts you to it; </l>
          <l>But secret pride, to haue a person gouerne, </l>
          <l>Which Palsgraue, thou mightst rule ambitiously. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e117020">
          <speaker>Palsgr: </speaker>
          <l>Thou fowl-mouth'd slanderer eat thy prowd words vp, </l>
          <l>Wherwith thou hast asperst me; or my furie </l>
          <l>Shall make thee curse this bold-fac'te impudence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e117060">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>Come, Come, you cannot doe it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e117080">
          <speaker>Palsgraue. </speaker>
          <l>Cannot. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e117100">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>Nor dare. Ile stand the furie of thy prowdest shocke, </l>
          <l>Not fearing danger in so sleight a Foe: </l>
          <l>Should I put off these Masks, my wounds would fright, </l>
          <l>And these wide mouthes which I haue got in warre </l>
          <l>Not halfe heald vp, pronounce it in thy blood. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-022-b"/>
          <l>Thou art too weake to enter Armes with mee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e117170">
          <speaker>Palsgraue. </speaker>
          <l>Since mildnesse cannot temper your stern wrath, </l>
          <l>But that your splene must vomit vpon mee. </l>
          <l>Ile teach you Syr to haue your tongue lockt vp. </l>
          <l>By taking off your locke. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e117220">Pulls off his locke. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e117230">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>My haire torne off. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e117250">They part them. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e117260">
          <speaker>Palsgr. </speaker>
          <l>Who haue we here? This is the hauty Saxon. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e117280">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>Grant me the combat Edward, of this Palsgraue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e117300">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>He is a prince himselfe, &amp; knowes his power. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e117320">
          <speaker>Palsgraue. </speaker>
          <l>Now by the honour of my Fathers house, </l>
          <l>Saxon Ile meete thee in the Realme of France, </l>
          <l>In the Kings Court, or place where thou wert borne, </l>
          <l>So I may haue good Hostage, and faire play. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e117370">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>Now by my gage thou shalt. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e117390">(His gloue. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e117400">
          <speaker>Palsgr: </speaker>
          <l>This shall suffise. </l>
          <l>I haue your locke to mee a better pledge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e117430">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>I would I had thy head to counteruayle it. </l>
          <l>A whyrl-winde be thy guide, and a rough Sea </l>
          <l>Plague thee before thou comst for my haires losse, </l>
          <l>Hel &amp; som Diuell was author of this crosse Exit Saxon. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e117480">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>You haue payd him soundly and deseruedly. </l>
          <l>But now to answere you in briefe, tis thus, </l>
          <l>The Palsgraue and our selfe will see the King </l>
          <l>With expedition, where (if hee make good </l>
          <l>The prowd Iniunction you haue chargde vs with, </l>
          <l>We will lay wast his Countrey, and once more </l>
          <l>Put France in hazard of a sound losse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e117560">
          <speaker>Palsgraue. </speaker>
          <l>This Saxons braue, giues courage to vs all. </l>
          <l>But Ile requite it with a Germaine braule. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e117590">Enter Saxon, Artoise, Vandome, and Mendoza, Trier, and Cullen. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e117600">
          <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
          <l>You are the cause next to disgrace the Palsgraue </l>
          <l>For which I came. The Emperour greetes you well, </l>
          <l>And would haue noble Artoise lend his hand, </l>
          <l>Both to cut off Bauaria and the King. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-023-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000284-artois" xml:id="ep000284-e117650">
          <speaker>Artoise. </speaker>
          <l>Where? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mentz" xml:id="ep000284-e117670">
          <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
          <l>Here in England. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-trier" xml:id="ep000284-e117690">
          <speaker>Trier. </speaker>
          <l>Or what place you will. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-vandome" xml:id="ep000284-e117710">
          <speaker>Vandome. </speaker>
          <l>France is the safer for the Stratagem. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mendoza" xml:id="ep000284-e117730">
          <speaker>Mendoz. </speaker>
          <l>And Edward is determined to saile thither. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e117750">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>In Frauce then giue it birth. </l>
          <l>Where if it sayle Ile be the Palsgraues death. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e117780">Exeunt. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e117790">Enter French King solus. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e117800">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <l>The care of Kingdomes is a weighty charge </l>
          <l>So is the care of children. But Loues care </l>
          <l>Exceeds them all: That dryes the blood of life </l>
          <l>More then the Feauer, though they burne like Fire: </l>
          <l>And to submit it to the law of reason, </l>
          <l>Makes reason follie, and discourse a Foole. </l>
          <l>Then irresistable all ruling power </l>
          <l>Reuell in young mens hearts, and leaue the olde, </l>
          <l>Or meddle with inferiours, not with Kings; </l>
          <l>We should be priuiledged, because most high, </l>
          <l>But what's a King vnto a Deitie? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e117920">Enter Floramell, with a Napkin, and a cup of Wine. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e117930">
          <speaker>Floramell. </speaker>
          <l>Your Maiestie call'd for a cup of wine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e117950">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <l>I did faire creature, &amp; I thank your paines. </l>
          <l>But when I view the colour of your lippe. </l>
          <l>And looke on this, the wine me thinks lookes pale: </l>
          <l>You haue a better luster in your eye, </l>
          <l>Then any sparkel that can rise from hence: </l>
          <l>The siluer whitenesse that adornes thy necke, </l>
          <l>Sullyes the plate, and makes the Napkin blacke. </l>
          <l>Thy looking well, makes all things else looke fowle, </l>
          <l>Being so faire in bodie, what's thy soule? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e118050">
          <speaker>Floram. </speaker>
          <l>My soule and body are the gift of heauen, </l>
          <l>And I will vse them to my Makers praise: </l>
          <l>If other seruice (great King) you require, </l>
          <l>I am ready, attend your hearts desire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e118100">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <l>I think sweet creature, what thy tongue has vtterd </l>
          <l>Is distant many paces from thy heart. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-023-b"/>
          <l>My hearts desire, tis not in bending low, </l>
          <l>After the afficious custome of a Court: </l>
          <l>Nor lyes it in the vse of common things, </l>
          <l>To bring and take away; my hearts desire </l>
          <l>Is to enioy thee in another sort, </l>
          <l>Which if thou yeeld vnto, thou shalt be great, </l>
          <l>Greatest in France, next, nay before my Queene: </l>
          <l>For Ile finde meanes to to take away her life, </l>
          <l>So I may haue thee as a second wife. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e118220">
          <speaker>Flora. </speaker>
          <l>The Saint of France forbid it, &amp; all powers, </l>
          <l>That haue continued both so long together </l>
          <l>In sacred rites of Mariage, heauen deny </l>
          <l>I should be Authour of her Tragedy: </l>
          <l>Or giue content where murther is oppos'd. </l>
          <l>If I should yeeld, and your Queene made away, </l>
          <l>Might you not vse me so another day? </l>
          <l>Tis fearefull building vpon any sinne, </l>
          <l>One mischiefe entred, brings another in: </l>
          <l>The second pulls a third, the third drawes more, </l>
          <l>And they for all the rest set ope the dore: </l>
          <l>Till custome take away the iudging sence, </l>
          <l>That to offend we thinke it no offence. </l>
          <l>Wherefore my Lord, kill mischiefe while tis small, </l>
          <l>So by degrees you may destroy it all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e118380">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <l>Diuine is thy discourse, like to thy beauty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e118400">
          <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
          <l>Does not Idolatrize, beauties a flowre, </l>
          <l>Which springs and withers almost in an houre: </l>
          <l>Sicknesse impayres it, but death kills it quite, </l>
          <l>It vades as fast as shaddowes in the night. </l>
          <l>Why should your Grace call it Diuinitie? </l>
          <l>There's nought diuine, but that which cannot dye. </l>
          <l>Least I offend by staying here too long, </l>
          <l>Ile take my leaue, and so curbe in my tongue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e118490">
          <speaker>F. King </speaker>
          <l>Speake still, Ile heare thee. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e118510">(Exit Floramell. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e118520">
          <speaker>Flor. </speaker>
          <l>To our Sex tis bard, </l>
          <l>We should be twice seene, ere we be once heard. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-024-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e118550">
          <speaker>F. K. </speaker>
          <l>Shee'll neuer yeeld! why do I woo her then? </l>
          <l>Because I cannot bridle my desires, </l>
          <l>Nor sleepe, nor eate, but as I dreame of her: </l>
          <l>Shee's to me as my Genius, or my soule, </l>
          <l>And more then they, because she gouernes them. </l>
          <l>Some way Ile take, my freedome to recouer: </l>
          <l>That there's no physicke made to cure a Louer! </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e118630">Enter the French Queene. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e118640">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>My Lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e118660">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <l>My Loue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e118680">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>Yes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e118700">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <l>Infortuna. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e118720">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>How! Infortuna? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e118740">
          <speaker>F. K. </speaker>
          <l>I mistooke thy name: </l>
          <l>Yet now I thinke on't, I had busie thoughts </l>
          <l>How I might raise that Virgin to some Honour, </l>
          <l>And match her with some worthy Peere of France. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e118790">
          <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
          <l>Your selfe my Lord in some Adulterate kinde. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e118810">
          <speaker>F. K. </speaker>
          <l>Nay then you wrong me, I meant vertuously; </l>
          <l>Beleeue me Sweet I did, I loue thee so, </l>
          <l>No euill thought should make me wrong thy bed, </l>
          <l>By this it shall not, this, and this, my Loue. Kisses her. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e118860">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>You flatter me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e118880">
          <speaker>F. K. </speaker>
          <l>I loue thee as I should: </l>
          <l>What, we haue liu'd together twenty yeeres, </l>
          <l>And neuer wrongd each other, should I now </l>
          <l>Be the first causer of the marriage breach? </l>
          <l>Banish such thoughts, let all mistrust begon. </l>
          <l>If she grow iealous, I am twice vndone. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e118950">Exit. F. King. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e118960">
          <speaker>Quee. </speaker>
          <l>Ile haue about with her, to finde out all. </l>
          <l>Within there. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e118990">Enter Floramell. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e119000">
          <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
          <l>Madame. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e119020">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>What Medea was't, </l>
          <l>Of whom you learnt the Art of Sorcery, </l>
          <l>To inchaunt a King, and draw him to your bed? </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-024-b"/>
          <l>Thinke you, because you are my Mayd of Honour, </l>
          <l>Ile honour you so farre, to haue my Lord, </l>
          <l>Thou shamelesse Callet? tis ingratitude, </l>
          <l>Into my Husbands heart so to intrude. </l>
          <l>I could haue helpt thee to a wealthy choyce, </l>
          <l>Had you spar'd mine; but now it cannot be, </l>
          <l>For I must hate thee for thy tretchery. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e119130">
          <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
          <l>I am accus'd, that ought to be excus'd, </l>
          <l>And blam'd as one vnchaste, for being chaste. </l>
          <l>I Inchaunt the King, and vse Medeas Art? </l>
          <l>Witch-craft I haue alwaies hated with my heart: </l>
          <l>And except Modestie a Circe be, </l>
          <l>I know no other kinde of Sorcery. </l>
          <l>Your Highnesse sent me with a Cup of Wine </l>
          <l>Vnto the King, the occasion of his wooing; </l>
          <l>Was it my fault to doe your Highnesse will? </l>
          <l>Iudge gracious Maiestie but as you ought, </l>
          <l>And doe not blame me for a Virgins tryall: </l>
          <l>His loue was answered with a strong denyall; </l>
          <l>And so deny'd for euer shall he be, </l>
          <l>That seekes by such meanes to dishonour me. </l>
          <l>Before I wrong a Queene so truely kinde, </l>
          <l>Ile marre my face, and make my sad eyes blinde. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e119300">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>In. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e119320">Exit Floramell. </stage>
          </l>
          <l>Weele consider farther of your teares: </l>
          <l>Ile haue her watcht, if she prooues false, she dyes; </l>
          <l>But if continue constant to the end, </l>
          <l>Neuer had Lady a more Royall friend. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e119370">Exit. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e119380">Enter young Fitzwaters aloft. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e119390">
          <speaker>Y. Fytz. </speaker>
          <l>Since I was cast vpon this fatall Rocke, </l>
          <l>And saw my Loue disseuered by the waues, </l>
          <l>And my kinde Steward in the Ocean drownd, </l>
          <l>Here I haue liu'd, fed onely with raw Fish, </l>
          <l>Such as the Sea yeelds: and each Shippe I see, </l>
          <l>(As dayly there are some furrow this way) </l>
          <l>I call vnto for ayde, but nere the neere. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-025-a"/>
          <l>Once ask't me, What I was? I answer'd him, </l>
          <l>An Englishman. Quoth he, Stay there and starue. </l>
          <l>To the next that past, I sayd I was a French-borne. </l>
          <l>Ile ayde no French quoth he. Vnto a third, </l>
          <l>That I a Spaniard was. He bad me hang: </l>
          <l>So that I know not what I ought to say, </l>
          <l>Nor whom to speake to: but in happy time, </l>
          <l>From this high Rocke, I see a tall Shippe come, </l>
          <l>Furnisht with all his Sayles; and as it ploughes </l>
          <l>The Ocean vp, it rayses hills of snow, </l>
          <l>That fly on both sides as they did giue way, </l>
          <l>To make a valley for the Shippe to passe. </l>
          <l>Their Captaine as I thinke lookes vpon me, </l>
          <l>And has tooke notice of my wauing hand. </l>
          <l>Now the Ship turnes and this way ploughes amaine, </l>
          <l>As if it meant to runne it selfe aground: </l>
          <l>In happy time, now I shall be relieu'd. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e119640">Enter Saxon, Artoise, Mentz, Vandome, and Mendoza. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e119650">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>Twas heere abouts the Gallant beckned me, </l>
          <l>He seemes a person of some eminence, </l>
          <l>By the glittering of his Suite against the Sunne, </l>
          <l>Cast Anker here, and let vs question him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mendoza" xml:id="ep000284-e119700">
          <speaker>Men. </speaker>
          <l>Yonder he stands, mounted vpon the rocke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e119720">
          <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
          <l>The very same. What art thou, whats they name? </l>
          <l>Thy place of birth, fortune, and parentage, </l>
          <l>That thou art left vpon this desolate shore? </l>
          <l>And what requirest thou stranger at our hands? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e119770">
          <speaker>Y. Eytz. </speaker>
          <l>As you are men, and therefore may be crost, </l>
          <l>Be fauourable to a wretched man: </l>
          <l>Know, that the Sea has cast me on this place, </l>
          <l>Where I haue led a discontented life, </l>
          <l>Ere since the last storme, and no passenger </l>
          <l>Has taken pitty to remooue me hence. </l>
          <l>Though food I want not, cause the sea yeelds fish, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-025-b"/>
          <l>I woul'd be shifted to a better place. </l>
          <l>My name's Fitzwaters, by my byrth a Lord: </l>
          <l>My naturall residence in England was, </l>
          <l>Some of your company I haue often seene, </l>
          <l>Set me aland where dwell inhabitants, </l>
          <l>And thankfully I will require your loue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-artois" xml:id="ep000284-e119910">
          <speaker>Artoy. </speaker>
          <l>Tis young Fytzwaters, pray sir take him in. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e119930">
          <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
          <l>You know my li●●● 〈◊〉 all Englishmen. </l>
          <l>Since my disgrace, and shall I pitty him? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mentz" xml:id="ep000284-e119960">
          <speaker>Ment. </speaker>
          <l>But he's descended of a Noble house. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e119980">
          <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
          <l>The more should I reioyce to see him dye. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-trier" xml:id="ep000284-e120000">
          <speaker>Trier. </speaker>
          <l>Has valour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e120020">
          <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
          <l>Let him vse it on the Rocks. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-vandome" xml:id="ep000284-e120040">
          <speaker>Vand. </speaker>
          <l>But euery enemie beares not your minde, </l>
          <l>Some haue beene fauourable to their foes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mendoza" xml:id="ep000284-e120070">
          <speaker>Mend. </speaker>
          <l>And tis an honour in an enemie </l>
          <l>To saue where he may kill. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e120100">
          <speaker>Y. Fytz. </speaker>
          <l>Your answere there? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e120120">
          <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
          <l>You speake as you'd compell it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e120140">
          <speaker>Y. Fytz. </speaker>
          <l>In the honourable entercourse of men </l>
          <l>I should doe so, and were you in my case, </l>
          <l>You would inforce your owne necessitie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-savoy" xml:id="ep000284-e120180">
          <speaker>Sa. </speaker>
          <l>What wold this Stranger be in prosperous state, </l>
          <l>That beares so high a minde in his distresse? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e120210">
          <speaker>Y. Fytz. </speaker>
          <l>I would be as thou art, proud of nothing. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e120230">
          <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
          <l>Is a Shippe nothing? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e120250">
          <speaker>Y. Fytz. </speaker>
          <l>As it ankers here </l>
          <l>It beares a goodly show; but launcht againe, </l>
          <l>And a storme rise, it may be cast aland </l>
          <l>As I haue beene: nay worse, it may may be sunke, </l>
          <l>And then what is't, but a fayre something, nothing? </l>
          <l>What is, and now is not; mans life, or a dreame, </l>
          <l>Now swimming, and then swallowed in the streame. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e120330">
          <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
          <l>His words are piercing, some go take him in: </l>
          <l>Come downe, and be receiued into our Boate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-artois" xml:id="ep000284-e120360">
          <speaker>Art. </speaker>
          <l>That shall be my charge. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e120380">Exit Artoise. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-026-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e120390">
          <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
          <l>Could wee draw this spirit </l>
          <l>Into our plot, hee'd helpe to manage it </l>
          <l>Vnto the life, and I should take it better </l>
          <l>Then yet I doe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-vandome" xml:id="ep000284-e120440">
          <speaker>Vand. </speaker>
          <p>Perswasion may corrupt. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mentz" xml:id="ep000284-e120460">
          <speaker>Ment. </speaker>
          <p>But be adjust'd how you perswade him to it. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-trier" xml:id="ep000284-e120480">
          <speaker>Trier. </speaker>
          <l>And take his Oath at first for sacrifice, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-vandome" xml:id="ep000284-e120500">
          <speaker>Vand. </speaker>
          <l>We are no puny Pollititians, </l>
          <l>To be instructed in the rules of euill; </l>
          <l>Here comes Fitzwaters. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e120540">Enter young Fytzwaters and Artoise. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e120550">
          <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
          <l>Your hand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e120570">
          <speaker>Y. Fytz. </speaker>
          <l>And sword but that the Sea deuour'd it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e120590">
          <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
          <l>Know sir, we haue businesse of import in hand, </l>
          <l>Wherein our purpose is to craue your ayde, </l>
          <l>And as we sayle to France weele open it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e120630">
          <speaker>Y. Fyt. </speaker>
          <l>I am yours in all things that are honourable. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e120650">
          <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
          <l>Honourable be not, your shall do what we list. </l>
          <l>Launch foorth into the deepe. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e120680">Exeunt. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e120690">Enter King Edward, Palsgraue, old Fytzwaters, Clynton and Cullen, Drummes, Colours, and Souldiers. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e120700">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>We did not thinke to haue footed the French ground </l>
          <l>A second time in such Hostilitie; </l>
          <l>But when the conquered beares so proud a head, </l>
          <l>Tis fit we make him stoope: yet least, the King </l>
          <l>Be not himselfe, or be abus'd by any, </l>
          <l>My Lord of Cullen, we intreat your paynes </l>
          <l>To enquire it out by our Ambassadour, </l>
          <l>as Mentz and Trier his assay that our force </l>
          <l>Might spoyle his countrey, and make waste his land; </l>
          <l>But that with French blood we haue surfetted, </l>
          <l>And therefore care not greatly to shed more. </l>
          <l>Say, We will meete him at an enterview, </l>
          <l>There to discourse our griefes before we fight, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-026-b"/>
          <l>Where if he haue wrongd me, he shall doe me right. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-cullen" xml:id="ep000284-e120850">
          <speaker>Cullen. </speaker>
          <l>I shall delate your Highnesse Embassie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palantine" xml:id="ep000284-e120870">
          <speaker>Pal. </speaker>
          <l>But say from me my sword nere drunke French </l>
          <l>And therefore it is thirstie for their liues: </l>
          <l>That are I leaue the Continent of France, </l>
          <l>Without good satisfaction from the King, </l>
          <l>None of his Caualieres shall were a locke, </l>
          <l>Ile haue them all cut off, and euery yeere </l>
          <l>Be payd in such a tribute for my wrongs. </l>
          <l>As for proud Saxon, Say my word is kept, </l>
          <l>And bid him warily respect his owne: </l>
          <l>The French Kings Palace shall not saue his life, </l>
          <l>Nor the best rampierd Bulwarke in the Land, </l>
          <l>Except he answere me as fits a Peere. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-cullen" xml:id="ep000284-e121000">
          <speaker>Cul. </speaker>
          <l>But to the Emperour, whats your will to him? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e121020">
          <speaker>Pals. </speaker>
          <l>That as he run from Spayne, he shall run hence, </l>
          <l>Or I shall make him a poore Emperour. </l>
          <l>His Bastard brauery tell him must goe downe, </l>
          <l>And the legitimate weare Caesars Crowne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e121070">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Fayle not to vtter euery sillable </l>
          <l>Both of the Palsgraues sending and our owne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-cullen" xml:id="ep000284-e121100">
          <speaker>Cul. </speaker>
          <l>I shall deliuer both. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e121120">
          <speaker>Pals. </speaker>
          <l>Tak't how they please, </l>
          <l>If they fly hence, weele follow through the Seas. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-cullen" xml:id="ep000284-e121150">
          <speaker>Cullen. </speaker>
          <l>I goe. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e121170">Exit Cullen. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e121180">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>High is this Embassy, like to your valour, </l>
          <l>Which I admire, and loue ardently; </l>
          <l>That I could wish your presence all my dayes, </l>
          <l>And thinke your company to me more sweete </l>
          <l>Then mine owne Kingdome, or my Crowne besides. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e121240">
          <speaker>Pals. </speaker>
          <l>Your loue and Royall presence I desire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-unassigned" xml:id="ep000284-e121260">
          <speaker>K. Clynton, </speaker>
          <l>and bold Fytzwaters, be it your charge, </l>
          <l>Prouided well of our best ships and Souldiers, </l>
          <l>To sayle to Germanie, and free our friends, </l>
          <l>Kept as we heare there with a slender guard, </l>
          <l>In a weake Castle. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-027-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e121320">
          <speaker>Old Fitz. </speaker>
          <l>Which weele soone beats downe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e121340">
          <speaker>Passgr. </speaker>
          <l>And bring them hither. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e121360">
          <speaker>Clinton. </speaker>
          <p>Or returne no more. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e121380">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>March forwards to the place where weel encampe </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e121400">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e121410">Enter Fitz-waters, Artoyse, Vandome, and Mendoza. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-vandome" xml:id="ep000284-e121420">
          <speaker>Vand. </speaker>
          <l>What should the reason be of this dissention </l>
          <l>And why is young Fitz-waters froward thus? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-artois" xml:id="ep000284-e121450">
          <speaker>Artoyse. </speaker>
          <l>His arguments are strong and forcible. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mendoza" xml:id="ep000284-e121470">
          <speaker>Mendoz. </speaker>
          <l>Single vs hither to the forrest side, </l>
          <l>Vnder pretense to plot more priuately, </l>
          <l>And now not onely to mislike! our drifts, </l>
          <l>But call vs punies, and vnskilfull men, </l>
          <l>If showes a spleenefull hatred to vs all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e121530">
          <speaker>Y. Frytz. </speaker>
          <l>Not vnto all, but only to you two: </l>
          <l>Why should the Earle and I borne a Lords sonne, </l>
          <l>Ioine with a paire of base companions, </l>
          <l>In such a waighty cause as a Kings death: </l>
          <l>I know youle say you haue beene physitians, </l>
          <l>Sailer, and Soldiers, and in such disguise, </l>
          <l>Done some exploit that haue deserv'd respect, </l>
          <l>I graunt as much, but yet your birthes are meane. </l>
          <l>No gentry in your blood was ever knowne </l>
          <l>By naturall Heraldry, your low discents </l>
          <l>Disables vs, and we must seeke to rise, </l>
          <l>With others of our own condition. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mendoza" xml:id="ep000284-e121660">
          <speaker>Men. </speaker>
          <l>Come Vandome, of our selues weele do the deed </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e121680">
          <speaker>Y. Fitz. </speaker>
          <l>That were the ingrossing of the same from vs </l>
          <l>And so you would haue all the thankes your selues: </l>
          <l>Neither commixt with vs, nor yet alone, </l>
          <l>Shall it be acted, but as we are the best </l>
          <l>In brith, and ability to doe it, </l>
          <l>Weele haue the priuiledge of doing it: </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-vandome" xml:id="ep000284-e121750">
          <speaker>Vandome. </speaker>
          <l>And we should giue it ouer. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e121770">
          <speaker>Y. Fitz. </speaker>
          <l>To your betters. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-027-b"/>
          <l>Or having fit place, Artoise and my selfe, </l>
          <l>Will kill you first, then cast you in the River. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-artois" xml:id="ep000284-e121810">
          <speaker>Artoise. </speaker>
          <l>Hee speakes what wee intend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mendoza" xml:id="ep000284-e121830">
          <speaker>Mendozze. </speaker>
          <l>Intend your worse? </l>
          <l>Caesar has promisde him the Palsgraues place, </l>
          <l>And I shall be the Marquesse Brandenburgh: </l>
          <l>Thinke you such Titles shalbe lost by feare. </l>
          <l>Our valour has bene tryde with worthy men, </l>
          <l>And ere we loose the glorie of the Act, </l>
          <l>Vandome and I doe meane to vse you so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e121910">
          <speaker>Y. Fyth. </speaker>
          <l>Theyle nere be honest. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-vandome" xml:id="ep000284-e121930">
          <speaker>Vandome. </speaker>
          <l>Come Syr, are you ready? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-artois" xml:id="ep000284-e121950">
          <speaker>Artoise. </speaker>
          <l>Most resolute villains, how they would out-braue vs? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e121970">
          <speaker>Y. Fyth. </speaker>
          <l>But noble Artoise, now the fire is giuen </l>
          <l>The Cannon must goe off. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-artois" xml:id="ep000284-e122000">
          <speaker>Artoise. </speaker>
          <l>Vnto theyr deaths. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000284-e122020">Fight. Y. Fyth and Artoise kill Vandoume, and Mendozza. </stage>
          <l>So they are dead, and now the Fame remaines </l>
          <l>Onely to vs, that will accomplish it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e122050">
          <speaker>Y. Ftyh. </speaker>
          <l>Onely to mee, that will perform't alone. </l>
          <l>Thinkes Artoise those were slaine cause they are base? </l>
          <l>Or that I wrought you to assist my plot, </l>
          <l>Because you are of the Nobilitie? </l>
          <l>No, I haue still this Maxime in my thoughts, </l>
          <l>That a Competitor, though nere so Noble, </l>
          <l>Takes away halfe the same in euery thing: </l>
          <l>I could haue opend this vnto you all, </l>
          <l>But that I thought my selfe too weake for three: </l>
          <l>And therefore prouidently vsde thy strength, </l>
          <l>To kill them first, that I might slay thee after. </l>
          <l>Now they are dead, thy life must follow theirs, </l>
          <l>And so I share the honour to my selfe: </l>
          <l>I will be Palsgraue, Marquesse Brandenburgh, </l>
          <l>And the Bohemian King in mee alone, </l>
          <l>Caesar shall write himselfe three Friends in one. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-028-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000284-artois" xml:id="ep000284-e122220">
          <speaker>Artoise. </speaker>
          <l>I doe not think thou meanst to be a traitor. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e122240">
          <speaker>Y. Fitz. </speaker>
          <l>Now you come neer me, but that secrets mine, </l>
          <l>And seeking it you must digge through my heart, </l>
          <l>Or it will nere be found, it lyes so close. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-artois" xml:id="ep000284-e122280">
          <speaker>Art: </speaker>
          <l>Ile know it, or a reason in your blood. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e122300">
          <speaker>Y. Fytz: </speaker>
          <l>Wilt thou turne honest? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-artois" xml:id="ep000284-e122320">
          <speaker>Artoise. </speaker>
          <l>Doe not torture mee, </l>
          <l>With repetition of that Beggars name: </l>
          <l>Whome none but Idiots, Innocents, or blockes </l>
          <l>Will entertaine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e122370">
          <speaker>Y. Fytz. </speaker>
          <l>I would change your minde </l>
          <l>From this erronious and ill boding thought, </l>
          <l>Because of late you freed me from the rocke, </l>
          <l>But if it be so hurtfull to your sight </l>
          <l>Be your own death, Ile not reueale my minde. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-artois" xml:id="ep000284-e122430">
          <speaker>Arto. </speaker>
          <l>If that I cannot force it with my sworde, </l>
          <l>Ile let it alone. </l>
          <stage xml:id="ep000284-e122460">Fight, and kills Artoise. </stage>
          <l>So lye together, three a paire Royall makes, </l>
          <l>And heres a paire Royall of excellent Villaines; </l>
          <l>These haue slaine princes by their owne confession, </l>
          <l>These made a Nation swimme in her owne blood, </l>
          <l>The streame is turnde with you, t'is now high flood: </l>
          <l>But I must cast you all into the Riuer. </l>
          <l>Yea, swords and all, to cleare mee from suspect; </l>
          <l>Suspect? by whome this place yeelds no such eye, </l>
          <l>Tis well the worlds rid of their villanie. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e122560">Exit. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e122570">Enter seuerally, the French king and Floramell. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e122580">
          <speaker>Floram. </speaker>
          <l>His Highnes here, then Floramell giue back. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e122600">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <l>Tis shee, a word; theres no retiring hence. </l>
          <l>In vaine you striue, my force opposde against yours, </l>
          <l>Will easily subdue your womans strength, </l>
          <l>But theres a power included in your eye </l>
          <l>That conquers Kings, subdues a Deitie. </l>
          <l>And he that had the strength to rule those graces, </l>
          <l>Might nere be caught, yet view the brightest faces: </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-028-b"/>
          <l>One kisse, and Ile no more importune you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e122690">
          <speaker>Floram. </speaker>
          <p>On that condition, I will graunt you one. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e122710">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <p>But you must giue it mee. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e122730">
          <speaker>Floram. </speaker>
          <p>Dian forbid, that were immodestie. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e122750">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <p>It must be so. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e122770">
          <speaker>Floram. </speaker>
          <l>Vpon your Kingly Oath, </l>
          <l>Neuer hereafter to renew your sute. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e122800">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <p>Now by my crowne I sweare. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e122820">
          <speaker>Floram. </speaker>
          <p>Take it. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e122840">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <l>Tis done: </l>
          <l>And with this kisse, a second Fire begun, </l>
          <l>More ardent are my thoughts now then before: </l>
          <l>I lou'd thee well, but now I loue thee more. </l>
          <l>Thou shalt not leaue me, but for euer dwell, </l>
          <l>Where I abide, thy absence is my hell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e122910">
          <speaker>Floram. </speaker>
          <p>Thinke on your Oath. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e122930">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <l>At Louers periurie, the Gods themselues doe winke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e122950">
          <speaker>Flo. </speaker>
          <l>A king say so, pardon me sir, your wil Ile not obey. </l>
          <l>But your oth broken mainely run a away. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e122980">Exit Floram. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e122990">Enter the Queene, hauing heard their conference. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e123000">
          <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
          <l>So, so, so: This is the affection that you beare to me? </l>
          <l>Thinkes the French King Ile not reuenge this wrong? </l>
          <l>As I am Queene of France, Ile make her know, </l>
          <l>What tis to be corriuall in my Loue: </l>
          <l>Shee dyes by Heauen. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e123060">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <l>If thou but spoyle a haire, </l>
          <l>Or shed one drop of her celestiall blood </l>
          <l>For any courtesie I haue offered her, </l>
          <l>My wrath shall: as a furie haunt the deed. </l>
          <l>And Ile torment thee for such crueltie, </l>
          <l>Worse then the damned in the world below. </l>
          <l>I seldome threaten, but I doe it straight, </l>
          <l>Her death thy Hell, looke too't, tis a shrewd fate. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e123150">Exit King. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_queen" xml:id="ep000284-e123160">
          <speaker>F. Queene. </speaker>
          <l>Hee euer yet was soueraigne of his word, </l>
          <l>What shall I doe, brooke this corriualship? </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-029-a"/>
          <l>No, since I cannot in the Realme of France, </l>
          <l>Haue the reuenge my longing heart desires, </l>
          <l>Else-where Ile seeke it, I of late behold </l>
          <l>An English Lord in fauour at the Court, </l>
          <l>His Name Fitzwaters, and I loue him well: </l>
          <l>By his procurement I will lay a plot, </l>
          <l>To yeeld King Iohn vnto his enemies, </l>
          <l>So to obtaine my purpose, if it take </l>
          <l>How euer Fooles may thinke to proiect ill, </l>
          <l>It likes mee well, because I haue my will. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e123290">Exit. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e123300">Enter a Frenchman and an Englishman. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-frenchman" xml:id="ep000284-e123310">
          <speaker>Frenchman. </speaker>
          <p>What are you? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-englishman" xml:id="ep000284-e123330">
          <speaker>English: </speaker>
          <p>An Englishman &amp; a traueller; what are you? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-frenchman" xml:id="ep000284-e123350">
          <speaker>French: </speaker>
          <p>A Frenchman, and no traueller. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-englishman" xml:id="ep000284-e123370">
          <speaker>English: </speaker>
          <p>Then giue way; For I am the better man. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-frenchman" xml:id="ep000284-e123390">
          <speaker>French: </speaker>
          <p>The better man? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-englishman" xml:id="ep000284-e123410">
          <speaker>English: </speaker>
          <p>I, the better man, by the porambulation of 2. or 3. thousand miles, I haue seene the great Turke borrow Money, and neuer minde the repayment ont. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-frenchman" xml:id="ep000284-e123430">
          <speaker>French: </speaker>
          <p>Peuh, is that all? we haue a number of great Christians that will doe so, and when a man comes to demaund his owne somewhat boldly, hee shalbe committed to prison, or made a Foole, to stand wayting at the foredore where the Coach stands, whiles the Lord steales out at the backe-dore by water. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-englishman" xml:id="ep000284-e123450">
          <speaker>English: </speaker>
          <p>Ist possible? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-frenchman" xml:id="ep000284-e123470">
          <speaker>French: </speaker>
          <p>That our Tradesmen can tell, to their great hindrance, &amp; I my selfe know this, that being in pouertie, a Lord calld me by my name thrice, but hee would not remember it once, when hee came to his Lands. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-englishman" xml:id="ep000284-e123490">
          <speaker>Englishman. </speaker>
          <p>The reason is, least thou shouldst begge some of his New-liuing. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-frenchman" xml:id="ep000284-e123510">
          <speaker>French: </speaker>
          <p>Nay rather for feare of paying the old score. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-englishman" xml:id="ep000284-e123530">
          <speaker>English: </speaker>
          <p>Sure thou art some Noblemans bastard, thou canst tell their tricks so right. </p>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-029-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000284-frenchman" xml:id="ep000284-e123550">
          <speaker>French. </speaker>
          <p>And by some great woman: For I can tell you their trickes too. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-englishman" xml:id="ep000284-e123570">
          <speaker>English. </speaker>
          <p>As how? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-frenchman" xml:id="ep000284-e123590">
          <speaker>French. </speaker>
          <p>Your only fine Lady is wantonnesse, &amp; new Fashions, your Cittizens wife gallops after. But shee is not so well horste to ouertake her. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-englishman" xml:id="ep000284-e123610">
          <speaker>English: </speaker>
          <p>Now wee are in the discourse of women, What Countrey-women doest thou loue best? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-frenchman" xml:id="ep000284-e123630">
          <speaker>French: </speaker>
          <p>I loue none. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-englishman" xml:id="ep000284-e123650">
          <speaker>English: </speaker>
          <p>I loue all, and to kisse them after the fashion of all Nations. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-frenchman" xml:id="ep000284-e123670">
          <speaker>Frenchm. </speaker>
          <p>Why I pray sir, doe not all Nations kisse alike? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-englishman" xml:id="ep000284-e123690">
          <speaker>English: </speaker>
          <p>You are no Traueller, and therfore Ile beare with your ignorance: but know this, your Spanyard, as hee is prowde, hee kisses prowdly, as if hee scornde the touch of a Ladies lippe; marry you Frenchmen draw it in, as if hee would swallow her aliue: Now the Italian has soone done with the vpper parts, to be tickling of the lower: and we Englishmen can neuer take enough at both endes. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-frenchman" xml:id="ep000284-e123710">
          <speaker>Frenchm: </speaker>
          <p>Is not your name Maister doe much? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-englishman" xml:id="ep000284-e123730">
          <speaker>English: </speaker>
          <p>It is, and yours (I thinke should be Monsieur doe litle. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-frenchman" xml:id="ep000284-e123750">
          <speaker>Frenchman. </speaker>
          <p>Wee ere somewhat a kinne in the first part of our names, and I pray heartily let vs be better acquainted together. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-englishman" xml:id="ep000284-e123770">
          <speaker>English: </speaker>
          <p>You must doe as I doe then, and since we were both appointed, to wayte heere for the French Queenes comming, lets take her golde, and forsweare our selues. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-frenchman" xml:id="ep000284-e123790">
          <speaker>French: </speaker>
          <p>Heere comes her Maiestie. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e123810">Enter the Queene. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e123820">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <p>Are you resolu'de to vndergoe this charge? Tis but an Oath, which I will guild with Crownes, <pb xml:id="ep000284-030-a"/>And beare you out against the Law. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-frenchman" xml:id="ep000284-e123840">
          <speaker>Frenchm. </speaker>
          <p>I can doe little beeing so animated, if I should not forsweare my selfe, for so fayre a Queene. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-englishman" xml:id="ep000284-e123860">
          <speaker>Englishm: </speaker>
          <p>And Ile doe as much as your Maiestie will haue me doe. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e123880">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <p>Take this in earnest, and when tis done, you shall haue more. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-frenchman" xml:id="ep000284-e123900">
          <speaker>Frenchman. </speaker>
          <p>Wee will. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-englishman" xml:id="ep000284-e123920">
          <speaker>Englishman. </speaker>
          <p>And from this time forwards, let vs bee forsworne brothers. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-frenchman" xml:id="ep000284-e123940">
          <speaker>Frenchman. </speaker>
          <l>Content. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e123960">Exeunt French. &amp; English. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e123970">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>Ile instruct you: Here comes Fitzwaters. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e123990">Enter Young Fytzwaters. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e124000">
          <speaker>Y. Fytz. </speaker>
          <l>According to your Maiesties commaund, </l>
          <l>I come to know your pleasure for the Letter </l>
          <l>I should deliuer to the English King, </l>
          <l>With that base strumpet that has Iniur'd you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e124050">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <p>There is the Letter, which I charge you beare vnto King Edward, and assure his Grace I will performe what I haue promis'de in't, Ile send the strumpet to you instantly. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e124070">Exit Queene. </stage>
          </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e124080">
          <speaker>Y. Fyth. </speaker>
          <l>I knowe not by what influence I am falne </l>
          <l>Into the affection of this potent Queene: </l>
          <l>But shee has sworne shee loues me as her soule: </l>
          <l>And to enioy me in her amorous Bed, </l>
          <l>Would spend the reuenues of the Crowne of France </l>
          <l>Were it her owne: Ile temporize with her, </l>
          <l>To effect some plot vpon my Soueraignes foes, </l>
          <l>But shee shall know, Although shee loue me well, </l>
          <l>My hearts desires were drownd with Floramell. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e124180">Enter Floramell. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e124190">
          <speaker>Floramell. </speaker>
          <l>By all descriptions this should be the man, </l>
          <l>To whome I am directed by the Queene; </l>
          <l>But whome doe I beholde the young Fytzwaters? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e124230">
          <speaker>Y. Fyth. </speaker>
          <l>Tis she, Oh no, shees in the Ocean drownd, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-030-b"/>
          <l>No; Shee escapt it seemes as well as I. </l>
          <l>But I will take no acquaintance of my Loue, </l>
          <l>Till shee has cleerd her from the Queenes suspect. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e124280">
          <speaker>Floramell. </speaker>
          <l>It is not meete I take acquaintance first, </l>
          <l>Nor will I till I know a iust cause why, </l>
          <l>Of his Familiar dealings with the Queene, </l>
          <l>Here is the key her Highnes promiz'd you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e124330">
          <speaker>Y. Fytz. </speaker>
          <l>And you the prisoner to be safe lockt vp, </l>
          <l>For your incontinence and wanton life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e124360">
          <speaker>Floramell. </speaker>
          <l>You doe me wrong, I hate incontinence, </l>
          <l>Nor did I euer loue a wanton life: </l>
          <l>I am a desolate Ladie, shipwrackt here, </l>
          <l>And had a Husband once, too like thy lookes, </l>
          <l>But not of such a rude condition. </l>
          <l>Oh were hee present, and should heare thee speake </l>
          <l>Such boystrous termes against his honourd wife, </l>
          <l>He would out of the vertue of his minde </l>
          <l>Knowing my conuersation to be good, </l>
          <l>Write this base slander in thy villaines blood. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e124470">
          <speaker>Y. Fytz. </speaker>
          <l>So confident, her innocence is great, </l>
          <l>That can doe this sincerely without trickes: </l>
          <l>But if you be the same that you would seeme, </l>
          <l>How comes that your reputations growne, </l>
          <l>Into such scandall, and your name the theame, </l>
          <l>Of euery idle fellow in the Court? </l>
          <l>That Groomes report, faire Infortunate is: </l>
          <l>The French Kings loue; Nay worse his concubine. </l>
          <l>The voyce of men is held the voyce of God: </l>
          <l>And where an euill is so farre proclaimde, </l>
          <l>The generality approues the guilt, </l>
          <l>And shees vnworthy to surviue a minute, </l>
          <l>To be the separation of two hearts, </l>
          <l>Made one by Marriage. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e124620">
          <speaker>Floramell. </speaker>
          <l>Kill me, kill me then. </l>
          <l>Hauing my sentence, wherfore am I sparde? </l>
          <l>Or doe you take delight to torture mee? </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-031-a"/>
          <l>Before you serue the Executione </l>
          <l>The Law requires no more but death for Lust. </l>
          <l>The lingring is a note of Tyrannie. </l>
          <l>It is sufficient that the wretch must die, </l>
          <l>The sooner done, the lesser crueltie. </l>
          <l>But if your conscience vrge you to forbeare, </l>
          <l>I shall confute your worthlesse Arguments, </l>
          <l>And tell you in the purenesse of my soule, </l>
          <l>Report's a lyar, common talke a Foole. </l>
          <l>Wayters &amp; Groomes, light-headed like theyr plumes, </l>
          <l>And those that doe attend in Princes Courtes, </l>
          <l>Too actiue and quicke-witted to depraue </l>
          <l>A Courting they proclaime for a consent, </l>
          <l>A fauour for the deede, belieue them not: </l>
          <l>It is too common, this they hourely doe, </l>
          <l>And thinke none chast, but her whom none did wooe, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e124820">
          <speaker>Y. Fytz. </speaker>
          <l>But you did kisse the King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e124840">
          <speaker>Floramell. </speaker>
          <l>The Queene did see it, </l>
          <l>Vrg'de by constraint, and Kingly violence. </l>
          <l>Vpon condition hee should wooe no more: </l>
          <l>And for that kisse I am esteemd a whore: </l>
          <l>If you beleeue I am, I pray proceede, </l>
          <l>I kist the King, doe you a murderous deede. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e124910">
          <speaker>Y. Fytz. </speaker>
          <l>Rise, rise, hereafter the discourse Ile tell, </l>
          <l>Meane time Fytzwaters welcomes Floramell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e124940">
          <speaker>Floramell. </speaker>
          <l>So then I am honest by your owne confession, </l>
          <l>But ere I entertaine you as a Husband, </l>
          <l>Ile be resolu'd what Loue has past betweene </l>
          <l>The Queene and you, that you her Agent are, </l>
          <l>In such a weighty cause as is my life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e125000">
          <speaker>Y. Fytz. </speaker>
          <l>Runs the stream this way, is the wind turnd thus? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e125020">
          <speaker>Floramell. </speaker>
          <l>I must know all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e125040">
          <speaker>Y. Fytz. </speaker>
          <l>In sight of Heauen I vowe </l>
          <l>Shee is as chaste for any lust from mee, </l>
          <l>As vnborne Infants, and I vse her loue, </l>
          <l>But to aduance my soueraigne and his Realme. </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-031-b"/>
          <l>No other case by honour I protest, </l>
          <l>In signe whereof I oppose an innocent breast </l>
          <l>Against the sword: if you beleeue not, kill, </l>
          <l>But neuer man died for a lesser ill. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e125130">
          <speaker>Floramel. </speaker>
          <l>I am satisfied, rise loue, and let vs goe, </l>
          <l>Theres no true ioy without some taste of woe. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e125160">Exeunt. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e125170">Enter French King, Bastard, Saxon, Trier, and Mentz, Queene. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e125180">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <l>Prosperity I thinke was borne in France, </l>
          <l>Tis so obsequious vnto all our acts; </l>
          <l>And like a subiect waites vpon our will: </l>
          <l>To morrow is this happy enterview, </l>
          <l>In which Fitz-waters and the Earle of Artoise, </l>
          <l>Haue promisde to surprise the English King, </l>
          <l>And the ambitious Palsgraue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e125260">
          <speaker>Bastard. </speaker>
          <l>If it take, </l>
          <l>We shall haue cause to praise our happinesse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e125290">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>Take, out of all surmise: and in my thoughts </l>
          <l>It is as good already as perform'de. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-trier" xml:id="ep000284-e125320">
          <speaker>Trier. </speaker>
          <l>I thinke no lesse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mentz" xml:id="ep000284-e125340">
          <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
          <l>It is most probable. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e125360">
          <speaker>F. K. </speaker>
          <l>Where is the Queen she promisde vs a maske? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e125380">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>The Palsgrave. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e125400">
          <speaker>F. K. </speaker>
          <l>Be Iouiall Caesar: mirth began the night: </l>
          <l>And we will end it with the like delight. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e125430">Enter King Edward, the Palsgraue and Y. Fitz, Floramell, Cullen, &amp; diuers Lords in the Maske, they daunce there. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e125440">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <l>We are beholding to you Gentlemen, </l>
          <l>For this your Court-ship, pray discouer now. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e125470">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <l>We will, and make you all die prisoners. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e125490">
          <speaker>F.K. </speaker>
          <l>King Edward heere? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e125510">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>The Palsgraue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e125530">
          <speaker>Bastard. </speaker>
          <l>All our foes. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-032-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mentz" xml:id="ep000284-e125550">
          <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
          <l>Whose plot was this? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-trier" xml:id="ep000284-e125570">
          <speaker>Trier. </speaker>
          <l>Or is it not a Dreame? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e125590">
          <speaker>Palsgraue. </speaker>
          <l>Tis such a Dreame youl neuer waken from? </l>
          <l>To talke of this strange admiration, </l>
          <l>Which like the night houers on euery eye: </l>
          <l>Know that I haue deluded you with hopes </l>
          <l>Vaine, like those villaines, which my sword did kill, </l>
          <l>And by a Letter to the King deliuered, </l>
          <l>Sent by your Queene, to be reueng'd for lust, </l>
          <l>I causde his Maiestie to enter thus. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e125680">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>I receiued them in at the backe Gate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e125700">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Wheres the Lady that has wrongd the Queen? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e125720">
          <speaker>Y. Fytzw: </speaker>
          <l>Heere is my trosh-plight wife, </l>
          <l>Freer from that soule imputation, </l>
          <l>Then is her Maiestie from iealousie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e125760">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Is shee then chaste? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e125780">
          <speaker>French King: </speaker>
          <l>Ile answere for the Virgin, </l>
          <l>By my good Fortunes once, now by my beard, </l>
          <l>She is as nobly vertuous of a stranger, </l>
          <l>As ere I knew, and though I sought her loue, </l>
          <l>I nere obtaind it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e125840">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>No, where is my witnesse? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e125860">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Sonne, call them in. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e125880">Enter 〈…〉. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e125890">
          <speaker>Palsgraue. </speaker>
          <l>What can you sweare? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-frenchman" xml:id="ep000284-e125910">
          <speaker>French: </speaker>
          <l>What must hee sweare? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-englishman" xml:id="ep000284-e125930">
          <speaker>English: </speaker>
          <l>Ile sweare that the Lady is a good Ladie, </l>
          <l>The Queen a good Queen, ther's an end of swearing. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e125960">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Is this all? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-englishman" xml:id="ep000284-e125980">
          <speaker>English. </speaker>
          <p>And more then you should get of mee, but that the Queene gaue vs golde to say something: but who haue we here sirrah? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-frenchman" xml:id="ep000284-e126000">
          <speaker>Frenchm. </speaker>
          <p>Players, by this light players: Oh I loue a play with all my heart. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-englishman" xml:id="ep000284-e126020">
          <speaker>English. </speaker>
          <l>Begin, begin, we are set. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e126040">Sits on the Railes. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-frenchman" xml:id="ep000284-e126050">
          <speaker>French: </speaker>
          <l>That's a braue King. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-032-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000284-englishman" xml:id="ep000284-e126070">
          <speaker>English: </speaker>
          <l>Thats a braue boy that playes the Queenes part. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-frenchman" xml:id="ep000284-e126090">
          <speaker>French: </speaker>
          <l>He shalbe my Iuggler. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-englishman" xml:id="ep000284-e126110">
          <speaker>English: </speaker>
          <l>And when the play's don, Ile be at charges </l>
          <l>To bid them all to supper. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e126140">
          <speaker>Palsgraue. </speaker>
          <l>Away with them. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-frenchman" xml:id="ep000284-e126160">
          <speaker>French: </speaker>
          <l>I am very sleepy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-englishman" xml:id="ep000284-e126180">
          <speaker>English: </speaker>
          <l>Would I were a bed, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e126200">
          <speaker>Y. Fitz. </speaker>
          <l>Ile leade you thither. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-englishman" xml:id="ep000284-e126220">
          <speaker>English. </speaker>
          <l>God a mercy good Chamberlaine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-frenchman" xml:id="ep000284-e126240">
          <speaker>French. </speaker>
          <p>The play's done, and now we must go home. Farewell. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e126260">Exeunt Fooles. </stage>
          </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-queen" xml:id="ep000284-e126270">
          <speaker>Queene. </speaker>
          <l>But shal the stream turne, this way is my plot </l>
          <l>Become so weake? you will beleeue a Subiect </l>
          <l>Before a Queene? I haue out-shot my selfe, </l>
          <l>In seeking Iustice at an enemies hand: </l>
          <l>This is a crosse beyond the strength of brayne; </l>
          <l>Sure I shall end my dayes in Lunacy, </l>
          <l>Like one to whom due vengeance is denide, </l>
          <l>Because of weaknesse, on my selfe Ile turne </l>
          <l>The fury that should light vpon my foe, </l>
          <l>Scatter my hayre, like chaffe before the winde, </l>
          <l>Hell in this world dwells in a iealous minde, <stage xml:id="ep000284-e126390">Exit. Q. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e126400">
          <speaker>Pals. </speaker>
          <l>Our reuelling has strucke day out of night, </l>
          <l>And bright Aurora vshers foorth the Sunne </l>
          <l>To his diurnall course; yet neyther night, </l>
          <l>Day, nor the morning, with her flaring beames, </l>
          <l>Can stirre vp valour in this Saxons brest: </l>
          <l>What, is thy minde made captiue with thy body? </l>
          <l>Or thinkst thou that I take aduantages </l>
          <l>Where honour should be shewd, Ime still my selfe </l>
          <l>Ready to giue an answere to thy challenge </l>
          <l>As at the first, and if thou conquerst me, </l>
          <l>By my Atchiuements I will set thee free. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e126520">
          <speaker>Sax. </speaker>
          <l>You shew your selfe in this a Noble foe, </l>
          <l>And I receiue more honour then I hop't: </l>
          <l>I thought, because I was your prisoner, </l>
          <pb xml:id="ep000284-033-a"/>
          <l>You had esteemd captiuitie a conquest. </l>
          <l>But since you haue awaked sleeping valour, </l>
          <l>And giuen your Captiue such a priuiledge? </l>
          <l>I am the same bolde combattant to dare, </l>
          <l>And doe asmuch as erst I did intend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e126610">
          <speaker>Palsgraue. </speaker>
          <p>Choose your owne Weapons, and Ile meete you streight. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e126630">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>My Armour there. <stage xml:id="ep000284-e126650">Exeunt. </stage>
          </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e126660">Enter Cullen. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-cullen" xml:id="ep000284-e126670">
          <speaker>Cullen. </speaker>
          <l>Clinton and bold Fitzwaters are arriu'de, </l>
          <l>And bring with them releast from seruitude </l>
          <l>Brandenberg, Sauoy, and Bohemia. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e126710">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Guide them in. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e126730">Enter Old Fytzwaters, Clinton, Drum, and Cullens with Sauoy, Brandenberg, and Bishops, with Soldiers. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e126740">
          <speaker>Old Fytzw: </speaker>
          <p>Those with our selues, we humbly doe present vnto your Maiestie. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e126760">
          <speaker>Clinton. </speaker>
          <p>Such as our Swordes by a glorious victorie set free. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e126780">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <p>When Heauen is pleasde to giue prosperitie, How it flowes in: welcome my honord Friends: I am glad your thraldomes proue your libertie. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-savoy" xml:id="ep000284-e126800">
          <speaker>Sauoy. </speaker>
          <l>The King of England has bene alwayes kinde. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bohemia" xml:id="ep000284-e126820">
          <speaker>Bohem. </speaker>
          <l>I haue euer found it so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-brandenburgh" xml:id="ep000284-e126840">
          <speaker>Brandenb: </speaker>
          <l>And so haue I. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e126860">
          <speaker>Old Fytzw: </speaker>
          <p>Whom doe I fee? my Sonne that stole my Bride? As you respect my seruice (gracious King) Let me haue Iustice. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e126880">
          <speaker>Clint: </speaker>
          <l>Clinton kneeles with him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e126900">
          <speaker>Y. Fytz. </speaker>
          <l>To their great seruice, greater I oppose, </l>
          <l>And doe beseech your Highnes wrong me not. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e126930">
          <speaker>Old-Fyztw: </speaker>
          <l>Wrong thee? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e126950">
          <speaker>Y. Fytzw: </speaker>
          <p>I wrong mee, may not Kings doe wrong? Or dare you thinke because you are my Father, Ile loose my wife. </p>
        </sp>
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-033-b"/>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e126970">
          <speaker>Clinton. </speaker>
          <l>Daughter come from him, least I force you hither. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e126990">
          <speaker>Floramell. </speaker>
          <l>Father I may not. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e127010">
          <speaker>Y. Fytz. </speaker>
          <l>Fathers both shee shall not. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e127030">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Weele heare no more of these bold menaces </l>
          <l>On paine of death I charge you both forbeare: </l>
          <l>And let my censure sway this difference. </l>
          <l>In England as your house the Byshop tolde mee </l>
          <l>That Clintons Daughter by a precontract, </l>
          <l>Was young Fytzwaters wife, and that some tricke </l>
          <l>Betwixt the Fathers to preserue theyr wealth, </l>
          <l>Broke off the match, to haue him wedde the olde. </l>
          <l>This being true; I charge you on your liues </l>
          <l>Vrge him no further in his lawfull choyce, </l>
          <l>But as twas wrong enough to hinder it, </l>
          <l>Make him amends, by being reconcilde, </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e127160">
          <speaker>Y. Fytzw. </speaker>
          <l>Which I intreat vpon a dutious knee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-floramell" xml:id="ep000284-e127180">
          <speaker>Floramell. </speaker>
          <l>And so doe I. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-old_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e127200">
          <speaker>Old Fytzw. </speaker>
          <l>Rise, rise, I am frends with you both, and </l>
          <l>When my Anger's ouer you shall find me a kind Father. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-clinton" xml:id="ep000284-e127230">
          <speaker>Clinton. </speaker>
          <l>So shall you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-young_fitzwater" xml:id="ep000284-e127250">
          <speaker>Y. Fytz. </speaker>
          <l>All lets are now remou'd, I am truly happy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-cullen" xml:id="ep000284-e127270">
          <speaker>Cullen. </speaker>
          <l>The Combattants are ready. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e127290">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Guide them in. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e127310">Enter seuerally Saxon and the Palsgraue Armd, and in theyr shyrts, Drum &amp; Culiors. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e127320">
          <speaker>Palsgr. </speaker>
          <l>Idle are words where we must vse our swords, </l>
          <l>Yet that it may appeare what mindes we beare, </l>
          <l>Now we are marcht into this dreadfull Lists, </l>
          <l>Know that this day my Honour shall exceede. </l>
          <l>Or I lye breathlesse where I set my foote. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-saxony" xml:id="ep000284-e127380">
          <speaker>Saxon. </speaker>
          <l>Were thy brest Marble, &amp; thy ribbs of brasse, </l>
          <l>Saxon will haue the superioritie, </l>
          <l>Or in this dreadfull place, his life expires. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e127420">
          <speaker>Palsgraue. </speaker>
          <l>Sound trumpets, &amp; the destinies guide all. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e127440">Fight, and kills Saxon. </stage>
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-034-a"/>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e127450">
          <speaker>Bastard. </speaker>
          <l>The Palsgraue is invincible I thinke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e127470">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <l>Not to be ouercome. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-mentz" xml:id="ep000284-e127490">
          <speaker>Mentz. </speaker>
          <l>Nor to be tam'de by any. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e127510">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <p>Matchlesse, and farre beyond the praise of words, are all thy actions, let me honour thee. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e127530">
          <speaker>Palsgraue. </speaker>
          <l>Our Friends returnd in safety cheers more </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-french_king" xml:id="ep000284-e127550">
          <speaker>F. King. </speaker>
          <p>Caesar resigne your Title vnto Sauoy, and Sauoy, fit you vp, whilst the doctors heare ioyn all their hands to make thee Emperour. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e127570">
          <speaker>Palsgr: </speaker>
          <l>〈◊〉 as the first. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e127590">Bohem. </stage>
        <sp who="#ep000284-trier" xml:id="ep000284-e127600">
          <speaker>Trier. </speaker>
          <l>And to get your loue, </l>
          <l>We will disgrace our selues to honour him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-bastard" xml:id="ep000284-e127630">
          <speaker>Bastard. </speaker>
          <p>Receiue the Crowne, but as hee weares the same may it crush out his braines. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e127650">
          <speaker>Palsgr. </speaker>
          <l>Long liue and happily the 〈◊〉 Caesar. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-savoy" xml:id="ep000284-e127670">
          <speaker>Sauoy. </speaker>
          <l>As happily as your kinded loues haue made me. </l>
          <l>And long as please the Heauens. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e127700">
          <speaker>Palsgraue. </speaker>
          <l>Your fare●●● rights shall be perfect ●● with State in Germanie, whither I make the Maiestie of England, and all our Friends. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-king" xml:id="ep000284-e127720">
          <speaker>King. </speaker>
          <l>Ile beare you companie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#ep000284-palsgrave" xml:id="ep000284-e127740">
          <speaker>Palsgr: </speaker>
          <l>Faire windes and prosperous to our several </l>
          <l>Realmes, wee wish and pray for, tis not our least good </l>
          <l>To be the Fauorites of the waning Flood. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="ep000284-e127780">Exeunt. </stage>
        <closer>
          <signed>W. Smyth. </signed>
        </closer>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
        <pb xml:id="ep000284-034-b"/>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back></back>
  </text>
</TEI>
