<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000770" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The loyal general a tragedy : acted at the Duke's Theatre / written by N. Tate.</title>
        <author>
<!--Tate, Nahum-->
          <persName>
            <forename>Nahum</forename>
            <surname>Tate</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A62967.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <p>
            This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is available for reuse, according to the terms of
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>
            . The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
          </p>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull>
              <titleStmt>
                <title>The loyal general a tragedy : acted at the Duke's Theatre / written by N. Tate.</title>
                <author>Tate, Nahum, 1652-1715.</author>
                <author>Dryden, John, 1631-1700.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[12], 59, [1] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Printed for Henry Bonwicke ...,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                <date>1680.</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>Prologue written by John Dryden.</note>
                <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
      <profileDesc>
        <particDesc>
          <listPerson>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-diphatt">
              <persName>Diph. Att</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-lady">
              <persName>Lady</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-myr">
              <persName>Myr</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-2priest">
              <persName>2. Priest</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-myrr">
              <persName>Myrr</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-esca">
              <persName>Esca</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-3off">
              <persName>3. Off</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-theranddiph">
              <persName>Ther. and Diph</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-king">
              <persName>King</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-myrh">
              <persName>Myrh</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-arvandedr">
              <persName>Arv and Edr</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-escalus">
              <persName>Escalus</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-arv">
              <persName>Arv</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-att">
              <persName>Att</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-4off">
              <persName>4. Off</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-theoc">
              <persName>Theoc</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-ab">
              <persName>Ab</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-ther">
              <persName>Ther</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-qu">
              <persName>Qu</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-the">
              <persName>The</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-theo">
              <persName>Theo</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-all">
              <persName>All</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-esc">
              <persName>Esc</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-dam">
              <persName>Dam</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-ar">
              <persName>Ar</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-1priest">
              <persName>1. Priest</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-diph">
              <persName>Diph</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-soss">
              <persName>Soss</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-priest">
              <persName>Priest</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-1herm">
              <persName>1. Herm</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-edr">
              <persName>Edr</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-pis">
              <persName>Pis</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-her">
              <persName>Her</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-mess">
              <persName>Mess</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-2off">
              <persName>2. Off</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep000770-1off">
              <persName>1. Off</persName>
            </person>
          </listPerson>
        </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000770-e10">
        <pb xml:id="ep000770-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000770-001-b"/>
        <p>THE LOYAL GENERAL, A TRAGEDY. </p>
        <p>ACTED at the Duke's Theatre </p>
        <p>WRITTEN By <hi>N. TATE</hi>. </p>
        <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Henry Bonwicke</hi>, at the <hi>Red Lion </hi>in St. <hi>Paul's Church-yard</hi>. M. DC. LXXX. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000770-e110">
        <pb xml:id="ep000770-002-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000770-002-b"/>
        <head>TO Edward Tayler ESQ </head>
        <p>THAT I interrupt your Retirement with such a trifling Present (for even your Retirement is Busie) wou'd need an Appology with a Friend of more Ceremony and less good Humour. Your Judgment will set a value on Poetry from any Hand, and your Kindness dispense with the imperfect Essays of a Friend. The general hard Censure of Poetry, and its Professors, has sometimes been the Subject of our Discourse, where amongst other Reflections, we have with some surprize, observ'd that none hold this Art in less esteem than your gravest Pretenders to Learning; but tax it on such an Account, as they, of all Men, should least insist upon. <hi>Its Insignificancy to the World</hi>, What can be easier than to recriminate in this Case? Will not impartial Censure prefer the Author of Chevee-Chase to the nicest Distinguisher in Metaphysicks? What difference (as to publick benefit, between idle Speculations and the slightest Madrigalls, excepting that the former is a more Creditable Impertinence, and the Folly made Reverend with a Gown and Title, </p>
        <p>In the mean time 'tis forgotten what Aristotle <pb xml:id="ep000770-003-a"/>himself (even against his own Profession) has declared in behalf of the Muses? <hi>That Poetry (Tragedy in particular) is more effectual to instruct Mankind than Philosophy. </hi>And ev'n Tully is Poetical in pleading for this Faculty: <foreign xml:lang="lat">Haec Studia Adolescentiam alant, Senectutem oblectant, Secundas Res ornant, Adversis per sugium ac solatium praebent; delectant domi, non impediunt Foris: pernoctunt nobiscum, perigrinantur, rusticantur. </foreign>And a little after, <foreign xml:lang="lat">Caeterarum rerum Studia, &amp; Doctrin&#226; &amp; Praeceptis, &amp; Arte constare, Poetam Natur&#226; ips&#224; valere, mentis Viribus excitari, &amp; quasi Divinoquodam Spiritu asflari. </foreign>
        </p>
        <p>'Tis an Error as groundless as Vulgar, to think that there goes no more to the furnishing a Poet, than a Wind-mill in the Head, a Stream of Tattle, and convenient Confidence; whereas no Exercise of the Soul requires a more compos'd Thought, more sparingness of Words, more Modesty and Caution in the Undertaker. To make an accomplisht Poet, Nature, in the first place must do her best; she must give him the Faculties of Soul in Perfection, a Copious Invention, a Comprehensive Memory, a Nimble Wit to repair to this Store-house for Materials on all occasions, a Strict Discerning Judgment to censure this Choice, to give it just Expression, and in short, to square and finish what was wrought off in the Heat of Fancy. Nor is even this enough to constitute a Poet. Nature will not do his Business, he must have the Addition of Arts and Learning, be familiar with the Sciences, acquainted with the Intrigues of Courts, the <pb xml:id="ep000770-003-b"/>Customs and Constitutions of Nations, vers'd in their Languages, and read in the Histories of all Ages. His Knowledge must reach to the Policies of State, and descend even to Mechachanism; have insight into the meanest Mysteries and Trades, because 'tis uncertain whither his Subject will lead him; and he is to speak properly on all Occasions: nor are these Accomplishments above Humane Capacity, for they are every where conspicuous in the Iliad and the AEneid. </p>
        <p>I am apt to think, that Expression of your beloved Horace, the <foreign xml:lang="lat">Potestas quidlibet Audendi</foreign>, which he allows to Poets and Painters, was rather a Proverb of his time than a Notion of his own; for he immediately lays this restraint upon't, </p>
        <q>
          <l>Sed non ut placidis coeant immitia, non ut </l>
          <l>Serpentes Avibus geminentur, Tigribus Agni. </l>
        </q>
        <p>There are some Beauties common to Poems of all sorts, and there are besides select Graces peculiar to every Species of Poesie; and these so distinct among themselves, that 'tis a question whether there ever was an Universal Poet. Many believe there can be no such, the various Temperament and Passion of the Poems (which must be as different in the mind of the Writer) being <hi>inconsistent. Virgil </hi>may be urg'd on this Occasion, there being nothing softer than his Ecclogues, his Tytirus, his Alexis, his Gallus; nothing loftier than his AEneid: yet even in these Pastorals you <pb xml:id="ep000770-004-a"/>will find the Heroick turn of his Verse, and the Air of a Muse, too Majestick to be diguis'd amongst the Nymphs of the Plain. </p>
        <q>
          <l>&#8212; Illa Pharetram </l>
          <l>Fert humero, gradiensque Deas Supereminet Omnes. </l>
        </q>
        <p>The greatest Labour of the Muses is by some thought a Task of Ease, whereas there is no Poem of the lowest Degree, that is perfect in kind, but must have such a Symetry in the whole, and so many Proprieties beside, which the Author must have regard to; the <foreign xml:lang="lat">Lucidus, Ordo, Series &amp; Junctura, </foreign>and the <foreign xml:lang="lat">Felix Operis Summa</foreign>, exacted by Horace, that the Undertaker will find even a good Eligy or Epigram, a Work of weight. What more difficult than to steer amongst such Shelves, where the avoiding an Error is a ready way to commit one. </p>
        <l>In vitium ducit Culpae fuga. </l>
        <p>This great Poet and Critique will have even the <foreign xml:lang="lat">Debentia dici</foreign>, sometimes omitted, to secure the justness of the Poem; and yet he will tell ye that </p>
        <l>Non satis est Pulchra esse Poemata, dulcia sunto. </l>
        <p>Where by Pulchra I suppose he means Exact, and by Dulcia, Diverting and Aery. As in good Painting, where the Colours must be neither Dead nor Gawdy. </p>
        <p>For distinction of Characters he has given us Rule and Examples in the same Verses, and drawn in little, what can never be more fully exprest in large. </p>
        <q>
          <pb xml:id="ep000770-004-b"/>
          <l>Intererit Multum, Davusne loquatur, an Eros </l>
          <l>Maturusne senex, an adhuc florente juventa </l>
          <l>Fervidus, an Matrona potens, an sedula Nutrix. </l>
        </q>
        <p>Where every single Epithite distinguishes the Person and makes it a Character. </p>
        <p>You have sometimes ask'd my Opinion to what sort of Poetry I would give the Preheminence? And will possibly expect some account at this time. I suppose the Question can be only betwixt the Epic and Tragedy. The end that is pursu'd by both, I conceive to be the same (for the later Designs the Instruction even of Princes, as well as the former; (and no Monarch was ever too great to be represented on the Stage) but I will not take upon me to determine which is most effectual for that end. If you will have my imperfect thoughts, I conceive 'em too nearly related to make different Species; and find our learned Laureat content to have one of his <ref target="A62967-e720-b">* </ref>
          <note corresp="A62967-e720-a" n="*" place="margin">* Praef. <hi>to the </hi>Conqu. of Granada. </note>Sprightliest Tragedies, call'd an <hi>Epic Poem</hi>. </p>
        <p>I cannot forget the strong desire I have heard you express to see the Common Places of our Shakespear, compar'd with the most famous of the Ancients. This indeed were a Task worthy the greatest Critique. Our Learned Hales was wont to assert, That since the time of Orpheus and the Oldest Poets, no Common Place has been touch'd upon, where our Author has not perform'd as well. Our Laureat has <pb xml:id="ep000770-005-a"/>thrown in his Testimony, and declar'd, <ref target="A62967-e820-b">* </ref>
          <note corresp="A62967-e820-a" n="*" place="margin">* Essay on Dram. Poe. </note>That Shakespear was a Man that of all Men had the largest and most comprehensive Soul. </p>
        <p>What I have already asserted concerning the necessity of Learning to make a compleat Poet, may seem inconsistent with my Reverence for our Shakespear. </p>
        <l>&#8212; Cujus amor semper mihi crescit in Horas. </l>
        <p>I confess I cou'd never yet get a true account of his Learning, and am apt to think it more than Common Report allows him. I am sure he never touches on a Roman Story, but the Persons, the Passages, the Manners, the Circumstances, the Ceremonies, all are Roman. And what Relishes yet of a more exact Knowledge, you do not only see a Roman in his Heroe, but the particular Genius of the Man, without the least mistake of his Character, given him by their best Historians. You find his Anthony in all the Defects and Excellencies of his Mind, a Souldier, a Reveller, Amorous, sometimes Rash, sometimes Considerate, with all thevarious Emotions of his Mind. His Brutus agen has all the Constancy, Gravity, Morality, Generosity, Imaginable, without the least Mixture of private Interest or Irregular Passion. He is true to him, even in the imitation of his Oratory, the famous Speech which he makes him deliver, being exactly agreeable to his manner of expressing himself; of which we have this account, <foreign xml:lang="lat">Facultas ejus <pb xml:id="ep000770-005-b"/>erat Militaris &amp; Bellicis accommodata Tumultubus. </foreign>
        </p>
        <p>But however it far'd with our Author for Book-Learning, 'tis evident that no man was better studied in Men and Things, the most useful Knowledge for a Dramatic Writer. He was a most diligent Spie upon Nature, trac'd her through her darkest Recesses, pictur'd her in her just Proportion and Colours; in which Variety 'tis impossible that all shou'd be equally pleasant, 'tis sufficient that all be proper. </p>
        <p>Of his absolute Command of the Passions, and Mastery in distinguishing of Characters, you have a perfect Account in that most excellent Criticism before, Troylus and Cressida: If any Man be a lover of Shakespear and covet his Picture, there you have him drawn to the Life; but for the Eternal Plenty of his Wit on the same Theam, I will only detain you with a few instances of his Reflections on the Person, and Cruel Practices of Richard the Third. First of all Henry the Sixth bespeaks him in these words: </p>
        <q>
          <l>The Owl shriekt at thy Birth, an evil sign, </l>
          <l>Dogs howl'd and hideous Tempests shook down Trees, </l>
          <l>The Raven rookt her on the Chymneys Topp, </l>
          <l>And chatt'ring Pies in dismal Discords sung; </l>
          <l>Thy Mother felt more than a Mothers Pain, </l>
          <l>And yet brought forth less than a Mothers hope; </l>
          <l>An indigested Lump, &amp;c. </l>
        </q>
        <p>Richard afterwards makes as bold with himself, where this is part of his Soliloque. </p>
        <q>
          <pb xml:id="ep000770-006-a"/>
          <l>Cheated of Fevture by dissembling Nature, </l>
          <l>Deform'd, unfinish'd, sent before my time </l>
          <l>Into this breathing World, scarce half made up, </l>
          <l>And that so lamely and unfashionable, </l>
          <l>That Dogs bark at me as I halt by them. </l>
          <l>I that in this weak piping time of Peace, </l>
          <l>Have no delight to pass away the time, </l>
          <l>Unless to view my Shadow in the Sun, </l>
          <l>And descant on my own Deformity. </l>
        </q>
        <p>Queen Margaret cannot hear him mention'd without a new stream of Satyr. </p>
        <q>
          <l>A Hell-hound that doth Hunt us all to Death, </l>
          <l>That Dog that had his Teeth before his Eyes, </l>
          <l>To worry Lambs and lap their gentle Blood, &amp;c. </l>
        </q>
        <p>And never meets him but she presents him with his Picture; </p>
        <q>
          <l>Hells black Intelligencer, </l>
          <l>Their Factour to buy Souls and send 'em thither. </l>
        </q>
        <p>And again, </p>
        <q>
          <l>Thon elfish markt abortive Monster, </l>
          <l>Thou that wast seal'd in thy Nativity, </l>
          <l>The Slave of Nature and the Son of Hell. </l>
          <l>Thou slander of thy heavy Mothers Womb. </l>
        </q>
        <p>With very many other Taunts to the same purpose. </p>
        <p>It cannot be deny'd but he is often insipid where he is careless, many Things he wrote in hurry; but for his more elaborate Scenes, what Cicero spoke of the Writings of Archias, will hold good. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Quae ver&#242; accurat&#232; Cogitat&#233;que scripsisset, ad veterum Scriptorrm Laudem pervenerunt. </foreign>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="prologue" xml:id="ep000770-e1440">
        <pb xml:id="ep000770-006-b"/>
        <head>PROLOGUE WRITTEN BY Mr. DRYDEN. </head>
        <l>IF yet there be a few that take delight </l>
        <l>In that which reasonable Men should write; </l>
        <l>To them Alone we Dedicate this Night. </l>
        <l>The Rest may satisfie their curious. Itch </l>
        <l>With City Gazets or some Factious Speech, </l>
        <l>Or what-ere Libel for the Publick Good, </l>
        <l>Stirs up the Shrove-tide Crew to Fire and Blood! </l>
        <l>Remove your Benches you apostate Pit, </l>
        <l>And take Above, twelve penny-worth of Wit; </l>
        <l>Go back to your dear Dancing on the Rope, </l>
        <l>Or see what's worse the Devil and the Pope! </l>
        <l>The Plays that take on our Corrupted Stage, </l>
        <l>Methinks resemble the distracted Age; </l>
        <l>Noise, Madness, all unreasonable Things, </l>
        <l>That strike at Sense as Rebels do at Kings! </l>
        <l>The stile of Forty One our Poets write, </l>
        <l>And you are grown to judge like Forty Eight. </l>
        <l>Such Censures our mistaking Audience make, </l>
        <l>That 'tis almost grown Scandalous to Take! </l>
        <l>They talk of Feavours that infect the Brains, </l>
        <l>But Non-sence is the new Disease that reigns. </l>
        <l>Weak Stomacks with a long Disease opprest, </l>
        <l>Cannot the Cordials of strong Wit digest: </l>
        <l>Therfore thin Nourishment of Farce ye choose, </l>
        <l>Decoctions of a Barly-water Muse: </l>
        <l>A Meal of Tragedy wou'd make ye Sick, </l>
        <l>Unless it were a very tender Chick. </l>
        <l>Some Scenes in Sippets wou'd be worth our time, </l>
        <l>Those wou'd go down; some Love that's poach'd in Rime; </l>
        <l>If these shou'd fail&#8212; </l>
        <l>We must lie down, and after all our cost, </l>
        <l>Keep Holy-day, like Water-men in Frost, </l>
        <l>Whil'st you turn Players on the Worlds great Stage, </l>
        <l>And Act your selves the Farce of your own Age. </l>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="ep000770-e1800">
        <pb xml:id="ep000770-007-a"/>
        <head>The Persons. </head>
        <list>
          <label>King </label>
          <item>Mr. Harris. </item>
          <label>Theocrin </label>
          <item>Mr. Betterton. </item>
          <label>Theron </label>
          <item>Mr. Norris. </item>
          <label>Diphilus </label>
          <item>Mr. Gillo. </item>
          <label>Escalus </label>
          <item>Mr. Jevan. </item>
          <label>Pisander </label>
          <item>Mr. Bowman. </item>
          <label>Abardanes </label>
          <item>Mr. Jo. Williams. </item>
          <label>Sossacles </label>
          <item>Mr. Williams. </item>
          <label>Queen </label>
          <item>Mrs. Currer. </item>
          <label>Arviola </label>
          <item>Mrs. Lee. </item>
          <label>Edraste </label>
          <item>Mrs. Price. </item>
          <label>Myrrhoe </label>
          <item/>
        </list>
        <p>Messengers, Priests, &amp;c. </p>
        <p>SCENE GREECE. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="play" xml:id="ep000770-e2230">
        <pb n="1" xml:id="ep000770-007-b"/>
        <head>THE Loyal General, A TRAGEDY. </head>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="ep000770-e2250">
          <head>ACT. I. SCENE <hi>The Palace</hi>. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000770-e2280">Escalus and Pisander. </stage>
          <sp who="ep000770-pis" xml:id="ep000770-e2300">
            <speaker>Pis. </speaker>
            <l>TIs certain then the Armies joyn'd this Morn. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e2330">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>There's no Intelligence from either Camp, </l>
            <l>But by the joynt Report of Cottagers, </l>
            <l>That from the Mountains viewed the distant Fray. </l>
            <l>The Rebels have the Royal Troops in chase, </l>
            <l>Whose broken Squadrons make a Flying ight, </l>
            <l>And much disdaining to the Woods Retr eat. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-pis" xml:id="ep000770-e2410">
            <speaker>Pis. </speaker>
            <l>They were the Kings last stake. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e2440">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>This is the day </l>
            <l>That crowns the hopes of our designing Queen, </l>
            <l>Or sinks her Projects ever; for if now </l>
            <l>The Rebels prove the Masters of the Field, </l>
            <l>Conqu'ring Argaleon strait Usurps the Throne, </l>
            <l>And Weds Edraste Partner of his Pow'r. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-pis" xml:id="ep000770-e2540">
            <speaker>Pis. </speaker>
            <l>The Slaughter of the Field will scarce suffice, </l>
            <l>Or effect an Enterprize so great and dangerous; </l>
            <l>To finish it, the Princes too must Bleed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e2590">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Edraste through their Blood to Empire sails, </l>
            <l>And we the Pilots hir'd to steer her thither. </l>
            <l>The Queen to serve her high Designs preferr'd us </l>
            <l>To the Dignity we hold, and dearly made </l>
            <l>Our Loyalty the Price of our Preferment. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-pis" xml:id="ep000770-e2670">
            <speaker>Pis. </speaker>
            <l>When with bright Honours to her Plots she drew me, </l>
            <pb n="2" xml:id="ep000770-008-a"/>
            <l>I snatcht at the rich Wages, and ne'r weigh'd </l>
            <l>The dangerous Task;&#8212; but I rec &#12296;&#8230;&#12297; te, </l>
            <l>I'm sold to her Commands, and &#12296;&#9674;&#12297; perform. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e2730">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Soft, Theron comes, </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e2770">Enter Theron. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ther" xml:id="ep000770-e2790">
            <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
            <l>Unhappy Greece! Escalus, Pisander! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e2830">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>There's Terror in that Voice; how fares the King? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-pis" xml:id="ep000770-e2860">
            <speaker>Pis. </speaker>
            <l>How brooks he the suppos'd Defeat? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-the" xml:id="ep000770-e2890">
            <speaker>The. </speaker>
            <l>So various are the Transports of his Rage, </l>
            <l>That with each minute his Resolves are chang'd: </l>
            <l>Sometimes desies aloud the Rebel Pow'rs, </l>
            <l>Threatning swift Vengeance; then despairs agen, </l>
            <l>And cries all's lost, the Fates are Factious too! </l>
            <l>Thus tost with Doubts, and starting from his Chair </l>
            <l>He grasps his Scepter, cries I have thee still; </l>
            <l>Nor shall the Furies wrest thee: then o'th' sudden </l>
            <l>Disdaining casts it from him; thou'rt a Serpent, </l>
            <l>Away infectious Rod, thou fir'st my Hand. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e3010">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>The Kings last hopes depend on your Sage Councils, </l>
            <l>Say, what will you advise in these extreams? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-the" xml:id="ep000770-e3050">
            <speaker>The. </speaker>
            <l>The growing ill past Cure he neglected, </l>
            <l>And now blames his Physicians want of Skill; </l>
            <l>Because we cannot from the Dead restore. </l>
            <l>I'll haste, and with dissembled hopes support </l>
            <l>His drooping Spirits, and prevent Despair, </l>
            <l>Which yet in my own Breast I cannot quell. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e3130">[Exit] </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e3140">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>How temperate is this Politician grown! </l>
            <l>The publique Troubles seem t'afflict him now, </l>
            <l>Though most industrious once t' embroil a State </l>
            <l>In Civil Jars; till Ages Winter chill'd </l>
            <l>His Factious Blood, congealed his working Brain; </l>
            <l>And now the Dotard's Loyal for his Ease. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e3220">Enter the Queen with Letters. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e3230">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>See, Lords; th' Intelligence of Conquerors, </l>
            <l>Like Victory comes wing'd: the King as yet </l>
            <l>Has no Particulars o'th' Fight. </l>
            <l>Whil'st from Argaleon's Camp I am inform'd </l>
            <l>That in the general Rout and hot Pursuit </l>
            <l>O'th' Royal Forces, both the Princes fell: </l>
            <l>Now then Arviola alone remains </l>
            <pb n="3" xml:id="ep000770-008-b"/>
            <l>The Obstacle of my Edraste's Glory. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e3360">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>We are your Creatures, Madam, by your Favour </l>
            <l>Possess the height of Dignity we hold. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-pis" xml:id="ep000770-e3400">
            <speaker>Pis. </speaker>
            <l>And shou'd be proud to perish in your Service. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e3430">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>Experience, Escalus, has prov'd your Truth; </l>
            <l>And for Pisander, my new Servant (in </l>
            <l>His sparkling Eyes, his active Zeal I read) </l>
            <l>I dare pronounce him resolute and bold, </l>
            <l>By Nature form'd t' engage in glorious Ills, </l>
            <l>T' embarque in a rough Sea of Court-Designs, </l>
            <l>And share the Fortunes of a Plotting Queen. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e3540">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>New Servant; Hell! New Favourite, she meant. </l>
            <l>Ah Myrrhoc, thy Conjecture's true, I am </l>
            <l>Supplanted by this Partner of my Projects; </l>
            <l>Dull that I was, not to suspect before: </l>
            <l>'Twas not to serve her Pride but Lust, she drew </l>
            <l>This new Confed'rate in; and judg'd his years </l>
            <l>More sit t' advise of such Affairs than mine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e3640">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>Conqu'ring Argaleon now will soon advance </l>
            <l>With all his Pow'r, and close besiege these Walls; </l>
            <l>The Fort is in your hand&#8212; </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e3700">[To Esc.] </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e3710">Enter Edraste. </stage>
            <l>Come near Edraste; </l>
            <l>I travel with thy Fate in greater Pangs </l>
            <l>Than when my Womb unwillingly resign'd </l>
            <l>The Treasure of thy Beauties to the Light. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e3780">
            <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
            <l>The Life you gave, I offer at your Feet. </l>
            <l>By my dear Fathers shade 'tis nobler far </l>
            <l>To die forlorn, than by your Guilt to Reign. </l>
            <l>Your Life, which I, of all things hold most dear, </l>
            <l>You prodigally stake to win for me </l>
            <l>A Crown, which I of all things least esteem. </l>
            <l>My private Cares alass! have too much weight </l>
            <l>For my weak Mind to bear; how can I then </l>
            <l>Sustain the Troubles that infest a Throne. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e3890">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>Cou'd I give Being to a thing so Tame! </l>
            <l>Rouse, rouse, thy self, Edraste, nor permit </l>
            <l>My active Blood to freeze within thy Veins; </l>
            <l>If thou want'st Heat, come, to my Bosom fly, </l>
            <l>For I have yet enough of Warmth to spare. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e3970">
            <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
            <l>The rightful Crown at best uneasie sits, </l>
            <l>But sinks the crusht usurper to the Ground. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e4010">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>These Thoughts wou'd more befit the Cell than court. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e4040">
            <pb n="4" xml:id="ep000770-009-a"/>
            <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
            <l>To me there is no Palace like a Cell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e4070">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>What serves the Cloyster for, but last Retreats </l>
            <l>To such as have without success aspir'd; </l>
            <l>Where having fail'd of glorious Action, they </l>
            <l>Hush froward Age with the dull Joys of Ease. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e4130">
            <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
            <l>Heav'n has been pleas'd t'indulge my humble Thoughts, </l>
            <l>Giv'n Heirs to th' Crown, which you wou'd wrest for me; </l>
            <l>And I must hold it in two Princes Wrongs, </l>
            <l>Both grac'd with Royal Gifts and form'd to Reign. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e4190">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>Suppose these Lets remov'd, the Princes dead? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e4220">
            <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
            <l>Arviola, their Sister then succeds. </l>
            <l>Arviola, to whom I have sworn Friendship. </l>
            <l>Arviola, that loves me as you do. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e4300">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>Fond Girl, 'twas to your Loss you did contract </l>
            <l>That Friendship, and must conceal it or perish. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e4340">
            <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
            <l>I but comply'd, in this, with your Commands, </l>
            <l>You charg'd me love her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e4380">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>To dissemble love, </l>
            <l>As I pretend Affection to the King; </l>
            <l>And counterfeit so well, 'tis real thought. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e4430">
            <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
            <l>O Heav'n! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e4460">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>Arviola comes, prepare, </l>
            <l>And practise Artfully. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e4510">[Ex. Queen, Esc. Pis.] </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e4520">
            <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
            <l>Instruct my Vertue Heav'n in these Extreams, </l>
            <l>I must unnat'ral or disloyal prove! </l>
            <l>Dissemble Friendship! O ye Pow'rs! Dissemble </l>
            <l>With the open-hearted true Arviola, </l>
            <l>That has not for her Foe one thought of Guil; </l>
            <l>Hard Mother! cruel Fate! most cruel Love, </l>
            <l>To watch the hour of my Distress, and then </l>
            <l>To wound a Heart so much opprest before! </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e4630">Enter Arviola, Myrrhoe. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e4650">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Dispise not Myrrhoe, my threat'ning Dream, </l>
            <l>The Scene presented both my Brothers slain; </l>
            <l>I saw their Royal Blood mixt with the stream </l>
            <l>Of Common Gore; then as my Theocrin </l>
            <l>Rusht on to Death; I started from my sleep </l>
            <l>And lost th' unfinisht Vision&#8212; dear Edraste. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e4760">
            <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
            <l>Dearest Arviola! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e4800">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>I sought thee to redress my Griefs, and find theo </l>
            <l>As much opprest as I; 'tis some new Grief </l>
            <l>That now usurps thy Breast, and I suspects </l>
            <l>More Tyranous than ever rag'd before. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e4860">
            <pb n="5" xml:id="ep000770-009-b"/>
            <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
            <l>Ah Princess! in this tempest of Affairs, </l>
            <l>Nothing remains untroubled but our Friendship; </l>
            <l>All other things are from their Channel stray'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e4910">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Yet since our Breasts are open to each other, </l>
            <l>Let the Storm drive, we have one Harbour sure; </l>
            <l>Heav'n so be-friend me as I love Edraste. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e4970">
            <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
            <l>And were Arviola my happy Rival, </l>
            <l>I cou'd (I think) still prize her as I do </l>
            <l>Heav'n knows I flatter not, she is my Rival; </l>
            <l>Yet then my dearest hopes more dear! </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e5040">[Aside.] </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e5050">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Let's stop a while the current of our Tears, </l>
            <l>And piously dissembling our Dispair, </l>
            <l>Divert the pensive King; that Fate shou'd heap </l>
            <l>Upon his feeble Age such weighty Ills </l>
            <l>As Youth cou'd not sustain. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e5120">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Th' event's uncertain; yet, the sudden storm </l>
            <l>As soon may scatter, and the Clouded King, </l>
            <l>Set glorious as the Rose. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e5170">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Ah! Myrrhoe, thy Love wou'd flatter us, </l>
            <l>As ours impose on him. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e5220">[Ex. Arv. Adraste.] </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000770-e5240">
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e5250">Enter Escalus. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e5270">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Stay Myrrhoe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e5310">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Now Brother you are sad. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e5340">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Your late suspicion of the Queen proves true. </l>
            <l>I cease to please, and her regard to me </l>
            <l>Grows hourly Cold, </l>
            <l>Whil'st all her kindness on <hi>Pisander streams</hi>. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e5410">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Despond not Brother, there are Joys in Pow'r </l>
            <l>To Charm dull Age, when Beauty fails to please: </l>
            <l>If Love deserts you, bend henceforth your thoughts </l>
            <l>To Nobler Cares; convert that cunning now </l>
            <l>(That hitherto has so successful prov'd, </l>
            <l>I'th Queens designs) to your own Int'rest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e5490">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Good! </l>
            <l>Wee'll watch the Fate of this tempestuous Realm, </l>
            <l>And make our Fortunes of the gen'ral wreck. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e5540">[Exeunt.] </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000770-e5550">
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e5560">[Scene drawn, discovers the King sitting discontented; <hi>Theron, Diphilus </hi>on each side of the Chair. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e5590">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Why was my Life stretcht out to this black day? </l>
            <l>Death might have come long since, and sound me ripe </l>
            <pb n="6" xml:id="ep000770-010-a"/>
            <l>With all my Honours flourishing round my Head: </l>
            <l>But now to Winter blasts I'm left expos'd, </l>
            <l>Stript of my Leaves, and with'ring on the Bough. </l>
            <l>Argaleon come, and press thy Conquest home. </l>
            <l>This is our last Retreat, besiege us here, </l>
            <l>Sack, Burn, Destroy, and finish my Disgrace. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ther" xml:id="ep000770-e5700">
            <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
            <l>Your suffering, Royal Sir, this Glory brings, </l>
            <l>That from your goodness, your distresses sprang. </l>
            <l>For having Conquer'd i'th pitcht Field (ensnar'd </l>
            <l>By your own Vertue; which refus'd to spill </l>
            <l>Your Subjects Blood) you treated with the Rebels, </l>
            <l>Who su'd for Peace to keep your Forces husht, </l>
            <l>Till with recruited Pow'r they might oppress you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-diph" xml:id="ep000770-e5790">
            <speaker>Diph. </speaker>
            <l>Argaleon rais'd by your too liberal Favour, </l>
            <l>Seem'd ev'n to cope with you on even Ground; </l>
            <l>And wanted but the Crown to match your Height. </l>
            <l>Were you as quick to punish a Delinquent </l>
            <l>As to reward the smallest Worth, your Throne </l>
            <l>Had still been fixt, </l>
            <l>And proud Argaleon's Blood. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e5900">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Hold preaching Fool, </l>
            <l>Too late your tedious Lectures you begin: </l>
            <l>Where slept your Counsels whil'st these Mischiefs grew </l>
            <l>And might be ravisht by the tender Root; </l>
            <l>Then you indulg'd my Ease, beheld my State </l>
            <l>Float loose, whil'st I in soft Retirement slept; </l>
            <l>Now rak'd me to the Helm, till the Storm fell. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e5990">Enter Arv. Edraste. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arvandedr" xml:id="ep000770-e6010">
            <speaker>Arv and Edr. </speaker>
            <l>Live Royal Sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e6040">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Look, I have Homage paid me! <hi>Theron, Diphilus</hi>. </l>
            <l>Behold, two Princesses kneel at my Feet: </l>
            <l>Ha! ha! speak Sirs, am I not yet a King? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theranddiph" xml:id="ep000770-e6100">
            <speaker>Ther. and Diph. </speaker>
            <l>Most Sacred Sir&#8212; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e6130">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>'Tis false, ye Sycophants, I was a King, </l>
            <l>A prosperous Majesty; </l>
            <l>But now my Empire shakes, </l>
            <l>Opprest with its own weight. </l>
            <l>Th' unwieldy State falls on the Founders Head. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e6200">[Enter the Queen.] </stage>
            <l>The Queen! must She be conscious too of my Disgrace! </l>
            <l>O Aribell, How is my Fate relaps'd </l>
            <l>Since first we met? Those Lawrels now are blasted </l>
            <pb n="7" xml:id="ep000770-010-b"/>
            <l>Which in my Myrile Wreath I did &#9679;&#9679;&#9679;sert. </l>
            <l>When I espoused thee, Triumphs grac'd our Hymen, </l>
            <l>And Captive Princes at our Nuptials serv'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e6290">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>Nay Sir, be just still, tho' unfortunate; </l>
            <l>Nor think the transitory Charms of Pow'r </l>
            <l>Endear'd you to this Breast; this is a season </l>
            <l>To excuse such active Love as mine, </l>
            <l>That like the Dolphin shews it self in Storms. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e6370">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>What Trumpet's that? </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e6400">[Trumpet sounds.] </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ther" xml:id="ep000770-e6410">
            <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
            <l>Att. A Souldier from the Camp. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e6450">Enter Messenger. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e6460">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>I read thy Message in thy drooping Brow, </l>
            <l>Thou bend'st beneath my Fate, hurl it on me, </l>
            <l>And crush me with the Burden; Thou hast Wounds, </l>
            <l>And may'st with Honour speak of Vanquishment. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-mess" xml:id="ep000770-e6520">
            <speaker>Mess. </speaker>
            <l>Fly, Royal Sir, all's lost, O fly and save </l>
            <l>Our Empires dearer half, your Sacred Life: </l>
            <l>Nor think these Walls secure against the Shock </l>
            <l>Of Rebels, with Infernal Rage possest: </l>
            <l>Your strongest Fence, your Loyal Old Battalions, </l>
            <l>Taught by your self to Conquer, in Pitcht Field </l>
            <l>Are by these Troops of Furies driv'n and scatter'd; </l>
            <l>And what I fear will shake your Temper most, </l>
            <l>Your Royal Sons, by whom our Wings were led, </l>
            <l>Turn'd in the Chase t' oppose th' unequal Foe </l>
            <l>Till spent; on Heaps of slaughter'd Files they fell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e6650">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>My Sons both slain, my Legions too o'rthrown; </l>
            <l>My Sons, my flourishing Branches both lopt off, </l>
            <l>And I the useless Trunk left standing yet </l>
            <l>For Passengers to descant on my shame: </l>
            <l>Rend me consuming Lightnings Earth divide, </l>
            <l>Till thy unfathom'd Centre be my Grave; </l>
            <l>Nature her self should Shake when Princes Fall. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ther" xml:id="ep000770-e6740">
            <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
            <l>Dread Sir, restrain this Transport, and resume </l>
            <l>Your Reason now in your extreamest Need. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-mess" xml:id="ep000770-e6780">
            <speaker>Mess. </speaker>
            <l>Lord Theocrin, who in the Fight perform'd </l>
            <l>What the Beholders scarce believed (and must </l>
            <l>Despair of Credit when they shall relate) </l>
            <l>Gather'd our scattered Stray, a poor Remain, </l>
            <l>That scarce a Limb of the Old Body seem; </l>
            <l>Which in the Clifts he posted, where they hold </l>
            <l>Spight of the Foe, that scale the Rock in vain. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e6880">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>'Twas well perform'd, we'll march to their Relief; </l>
            <pb n="8" xml:id="ep000770-011-a"/>
            <l>Get me new Forces rais'd, a sudden Host, </l>
            <l>Like that which sprung from the dire Serpents Teeth: </l>
            <l>Arm'd with Necessity and steel'd with Wrongs, </l>
            <l>We'll rush at once on these fierce Savages, </l>
            <l>And ravish from their Mouths the panting Prey. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-diph" xml:id="ep000770-e6960">
            <speaker>Diph. </speaker>
            <l>Forgive me, Sacred Sir, that I disswade </l>
            <l>Your Fury from unfeazable Designs. </l>
            <l>You must create the Forces you wou'd levy. </l>
            <l>Your Loyal Cities, your thin Fields to fill, </l>
            <l>Long since were glean'd, the rigid Press scarce spar'd </l>
            <l>Decrepid Age, and weeping Infancy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e7040">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Peace Dotard, hast thou worn thy Sable Locks, </l>
            <l>To wither'd Gray, and even that Gray to Baldness. </l>
            <l>And art thou still contriving to Inch out </l>
            <l>Insipid Life? the gen'ral fright shou'd cure </l>
            <l>Your Agues, and ferment your freezing Bloods: </l>
            <l>Hast and Proclaim our Will, lest all our Males, </l>
            <l>From lisping Infancy, to Bed-rid Age. </l>
            <l>Set free th'imprison'd, bid the Sick discharge </l>
            <l>Their Maladies; the Storm comes thundring on, </l>
            <l>And in our sinking State all hands must work. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e7160">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>The Good Old Man, that like an Infant slept </l>
            <l>Till now, at last wakes froward; let him Brawl, </l>
            <l>He'll quickly Rage himself asleep agen. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e7210">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Be it further publisht, to enstame our Youth, </l>
            <l>That yet survive from the Consuming War. </l>
            <l>If any dare so far tempt glorious danger, </l>
            <l>To force the Enemies Ward, and bear away </l>
            <l>Th' Arch Rebels Head by our last hopes I swear; </l>
            <l>My Crown, and fair Arviola are his: </l>
            <l>Empire and Beauty, Valour's Noblest Prize. </l>
            <l>Our self in Person will Command and Dazle </l>
            <l>The factious Host with full-beam'd Majesty: </l>
            <l>Thus your Ag'd Monarch draws his Vengeful Sword. </l>
            <l>Our Flame shall snatch the Foe that thinks us Cold, </l>
            <l>There's none destroys like Time, and none so Old. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e7360">[Exeunt.] </stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="ep000770-e7370">
          <pb n="9" xml:id="ep000770-011-b"/>
          <head>ACT. II. SCENE, <hi>A Pleasant Grotto</hi>. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000770-e7400">Pisander brought in by an Attendant. </stage>
          <sp who="ep000770-att" xml:id="ep000770-e7420">
            <speaker>Att. </speaker>
            <l>HIther the Queen injoyn'd me to Conduct you, </l>
            <l>And you must wait her here: </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-pis" xml:id="ep000770-e7460">
            <speaker>Pis. </speaker>
            <l>On What Concern? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-att" xml:id="ep000770-e7490">
            <speaker>Att. </speaker>
            <l>My Charge was only to admit you hither, </l>
            <l>Where none approach without her special Orders; </l>
            <l>And We, Th' Attendants on her Private Hours, </l>
            <l>Are sworn to strictest Secrecy. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e7560">[Exit.] </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-pis" xml:id="ep000770-e7570">
            <speaker>Pis. </speaker>
            <l>Sure I am charm'n into an Extasie, </l>
            <l>And this a scene by Fancy's cunning form'd; </l>
            <l>Pictures of Nature drawn beyond the Life. </l>
            <l>Remove from hence, and the declining Year </l>
            <l>Looks sickly and deform'd; the wither'd Leaves </l>
            <l>In Search of the retreated Sap fall down, </l>
            <l>And from the Root seek what the Bough deny'd: </l>
            <l>But here the Summer blooms, in all its Pride, </l>
            <l>The Sun darts in with kindlier Warmth, the Winds </l>
            <l>Breath softer, and the Brook complains less loud. </l>
            <l>Hail blest Retreat of Nature happy Shade; </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e7700">Soft Musick. [Bower Opening discovers the Queen Splendid and youthfully Altir'd.] </stage>
            <l>My senses fail, this is some sacred Grove: </l>
            <l>And that the bright Divinity o'th' Place! </l>
            <l>Where are the Cupids that shou'd hover round, </l>
            <l>I Feel'um here! th' are div'd into my Brest! </l>
            <l>Forgive me Goddess&#8212; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e7770">
            <pb n="10" xml:id="ep000770-012-a"/>
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>You mistake, Pisander. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-pis" xml:id="ep000770-e7810">
            <speaker>Pis. </speaker>
            <l>The Queen! forgive my dazled Eyes their Error! </l>
            <l>I come by your Command to know your Pleasure, </l>
            <l>And trust you judge so truly of my Zeal, </l>
            <l>To ' think me worth some Enterprize of danger. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e7870">
            <speaker>Qu </speaker>
            <l>Yes, you shall find how I esteem your Zeal, </l>
            <l>By the important service I enjoyn, </l>
            <l>Indeed 'tis an Affair of so much weight, </l>
            <l>I know not how to word it&#8212; You must Guess. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-pis" xml:id="ep000770-e7930">
            <speaker>Pis. </speaker>
            <l>Instruct me what I am to undertake, </l>
            <l>And if I fail t' attempt&#8212; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e7970">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>Alas! </l>
            <l>So bold t' engage, and slow to apprehend? </l>
            <l>How like Conspirators at their first. Meeting, </l>
            <l>With caution we gaze silent on each other, </l>
            <l>Expecting who shall start the Business first! </l>
            <l>Since then I must speak first in the Design, </l>
            <l>Draw near and on my Hand swear Secrecy. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e8060">[Pisander Bows and Kisses her Hand] </stage>
            <l>Repeat your Vow&#8212; Oh Love! the quickning Touch, </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e8090">[Aside.] </stage>
            <l>Through my pleas'd Veins, runs tingling to my Heart. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-pis" xml:id="ep000770-e8110">
            <speaker>Pis. </speaker>
            <l>My Warmth is fled, I've sworn my Life away! </l>
            <l>My Soul cleaves to that Hand&#8212; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e8150">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>How soft is Youth! </l>
            <l>How soon dissolv'd into an Extasie! </l>
            <l>Pisander Rise&#8212; now sure you well can guess, </l>
            <l>For what I summon'd you to this Retirement? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-pis" xml:id="ep000770-e8220">
            <speaker>Pis. </speaker>
            <l>I know it; you'd engage me to perform </l>
            <l>A dangerous Task, to blast the Kings Succession, </l>
            <l>And settle your Edraste in the Throne; </l>
            <l>I'll do't. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e8290">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>Still you are wide of my Design, </l>
            <l>I'll Plot at leisure hours for my Ambition, </l>
            <l>But Love's my great Affair, th' important Business. </l>
            <l>Come, speak boldly Youth, </l>
            <l>Thy free Conjecture of these private Bowers, </l>
            <l>Where I so oft retire, while all is husht, </l>
            <l>Silent and close, as Ceres's awful Fane? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-pis" xml:id="ep000770-e8390">
            <speaker>Pis. </speaker>
            <l>Tis said, that for Devotion you repair </l>
            <l>From the Court's Crow'd to these secluded Shades, </l>
            <l>Where you consume successive Nights and Days, </l>
            <l>In Abstinence and Penitential Tears. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e8450">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>Ha! ha! the World retains its old perversness still, </l>
            <pb n="11" xml:id="ep000770-012-b"/>
            <l>To scandalize the Vertuous, and to Saint </l>
            <l>The Libertine; but 'tis no fault of mine, </l>
            <l>If Rumour will lay Vertue to my Charge! </l>
            <l>What, mar these Eyes with Penitential Tears, </l>
            <l>Fond Youth? They have too much of fire to weep. </l>
            <l>Their glances cou'd Create a Day in Cells, </l>
            <l>And kindle freezing Hermites into Dalliance. </l>
            <l>Why this Reserv'dness Sir? Has Majesty </l>
            <l>So little Charmes? Or do's its Splendour dazle? </l>
            <l>Then I'll divest me of my Royalty, </l>
            <l>And love upon the Square. Still fixt and senseless? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-pis" xml:id="ep000770-e8590">
            <speaker>Pis. </speaker>
            <l>Think not I have no sense of such full Bliss, </l>
            <l>But like Young Prophets from thei: Visions Waking; </l>
            <l>I fear to stir and loose the Charming Dream. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e8640">[Shouts and Trumpets from without.] </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e8650">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>What means those Shouts? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-pis" xml:id="ep000770-e8680">
            <speaker>Pis. </speaker>
            <l>Th' are Sounds of Triumph not of Terrot. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e8710">Enter Attendant hastily. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-att" xml:id="ep000770-e8730">
            <speaker>Att. </speaker>
            <l>Lord Escalus in haste desires Admittance. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e8770">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>He comes unseasonably, but let him Enter. </l>
            <l>Pisander hide a while within that Bower. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e8820">Enter Escalus. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e8840">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Forgive me Madam, that with so much haste, </l>
            <l>I bring unwelcome Newe, our Plot's Defeated. </l>
            <l>The Subtle Web which with such Toil we wrought, </l>
            <l>Is quite unravell'd to the very Loom. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e8900">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>Dispatch, cut short the Story of my Fate. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e8930">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Argaleon's Faction which with so much Cost </l>
            <l>And Secrecy, you nourisht to that Growth. </l>
            <l>That they cou'd grap le with the Kings whole Forces, </l>
            <l>Ev'n they, so late the Masters of the Field, </l>
            <l>Are now in shameful Rout disperst and broken, </l>
            <l>And their bold Leader, on whose daring Vertue, </l>
            <l>Our Hopes depended, shares the Vulgar Fate, </l>
            <l>And Headless Bleeds amongst the Common Slain. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e9040">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>'Tis false and shall not be. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e9070">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>'Tis past already, </l>
            <pb n="12" xml:id="ep000770-013-a"/>
            <l>The Gods have your Resolves fore-stall'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e9110">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>Did they from Heav'n war with my Officer? </l>
            <l>The Loyal Forces were cut off intire, </l>
            <l>Except a Despicable Remnant posted </l>
            <l>I'th' Clifts by Theocrin. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e9180">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>From thence broke forth </l>
            <l>The flame that thus laid waste Argaleon's Trenches. </l>
            <l>For Theocrin by night forsook the Clifts, </l>
            <l>With his small Train, and Coasting wide Attaqu'd </l>
            <l>Argaleon's Camp, with Shouts as of full Legions, </l>
            <l>And Num'rous Trumpets to increase the Terror, </l>
            <l>Which so prevail'd on the surprized Host, </l>
            <l>(Confus'd, twixt Wine and Slumber) that at last </l>
            <l>Half-arm'd they took themselves to general Flight, </l>
            <l>And more opprest by their own Numbers fell </l>
            <l>Than the Pursuers Swords. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e9340">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>Enough, Enough, </l>
            <l>'Tis but an Army and a Project lost. </l>
            <l>And Wee'll contrive anew, </l>
            <l>Anon Expect my Orders to await me. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e9400">[Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e9410">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>So unconcern'd, so fill'd with her new Love, </l>
            <l>T'Exclude the Darling of Her Brest Ambition? </l>
            <l>Methought Pisander glanc'd by as I enter'd; </l>
            <l>For his delight she's deckt as she was wont, </l>
            <l>When loose she wanton'd with my Vig'rous years; </l>
            <l>On her young Paramour she shows her Favour, </l>
            <l>Whil'st a Sapless Trunk neglected fades! </l>
            <l>But Age that lessens me in her Esteem, </l>
            <l>Has taught me Cunning timely to provide, </l>
            <l>And seek elsewhere the Favour she denies. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e9550">[Exit.] </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e9560">[Scene changes to the Palace.] [<hi>Shouts again</hi>.] </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000770-e9580">
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e9590">
              <hi>Enter King attended with </hi>Theron, Diphilus, Arviola, Edraste, Myrrhoe, &amp;c. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e9620">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>The Gods, the Gods at last, have own'd the Cause, </l>
            <l>Of injur'd Majesty; We have o'recome! </l>
            <l>Summon the Priests to speedy Sacrifice, </l>
            <l>Crown every Altar, heap the Spicy Piles, </l>
            <l>Till the vast Fanes be hid in Smoaking Gums; </l>
            <l>No Pensive Look prosane the Gen'ral Joy, </l>
            <l>Not Orphan'd Matrons be allow'd to Mourn: </l>
            <pb n="13" xml:id="ep000770-013-b"/>
            <l>Nor Virgins Widdow'd on their Brldal Day! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-the" xml:id="ep000770-e9720">
            <speaker>The. </speaker>
            <l>When Young in the Rang'd Field you first appear'd, </l>
            <l>You Charm'd Success, nor had She now forsook you, </l>
            <l>But, like a Mistress with Discretion kind, </l>
            <l>Withdrew a while till absence made her priz'd; </l>
            <l>Then with Surprizing Kindness met your Passion. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000770-e9790">
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e9800">Enter Theocrin, with Argaleon's Head, Chief Officers of the Army following. [<hi>Shout again</hi>.] </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-the" xml:id="ep000770-e9840">
            <speaker>The. </speaker>
            <l>Hail best of Kings! Fall ev'ry Traytors Head, </l>
            <l>Like this, and Flourish all Crown'd Brows like yours. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e9880">[Kneels and lays the Head at the Kings Feet.] </stage>
            <l>The Savage that so long had Lawless Rang'd, </l>
            <l>That slew our Youth, and laid our Vineyards Waste, </l>
            <l>Lies Bloodless, now by this Successful Hand. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e9920">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Rise Theocrin, Cast not to Ground, those Limbs, </l>
            <l>That Cou'd support a Sinking Monarchy. </l>
            <l>Now I am King indeed, my Shaken Throne </l>
            <l>Again takes Root, and my Decaying Scepter </l>
            <l>Buds in my Hand anew. </l>
            <l>
              <hi>Arviola, Edraste</hi>, both draw near; </l>
            <l>And pay him with your own the Publick Thanks. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e10040">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>My Dearest Theocrin, how greedily </l>
            <l>Do's my impatient Love snatch this Occasion </l>
            <l>T'unlaid it self unseen into your Brest! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-the" xml:id="ep000770-e10100">
            <speaker>The. </speaker>
            <l>O my Arviola, I'm Lost in Joy! </l>
            <l>I am too Blest! Indulgent Pow'rs rest rain </l>
            <l>The Flowing Bliss, or I shall Die of Rapture! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e10160">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Arviola was proclaim'd the Prize o'th Valour </l>
            <l>That brought Argaleon's Head: 'Tis Theocrin's, </l>
            <l>Brave Youth, my Crown is Hers, and She is Thine; </l>
            <l>Thou merrit'st Both: Though not from Kings descended, </l>
            <l>Thou art by Vertue to the Gods Ally'd! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-the" xml:id="ep000770-e10260">
            <speaker>The. </speaker>
            <l>Your Goodness, Royal Sir, o're rates my Service; </l>
            <l>What I perform'd, was but a Subjects, Duty. </l>
            <l>But Oh! I feel a warmth t'attempt such things, </l>
            <l>As shall (is merrit sound not too prophane) </l>
            <l>Deserve a Princess, and Oblige a King. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e10330">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>By all the Powers that sped thee in the Fight, </l>
            <l>Thou art our Son, and this thy Nuptial Day. </l>
            <pb n="14" xml:id="ep000770-014-a"/>
            <l>Lo there thy Royal Bride, and too compleat </l>
            <l>Thy Happy Fortunes, Thou shalt Tryumph too. </l>
            <l>Bellona once shall be with Myrtle Crown'd, </l>
            <l>And War's loud Voice in Rev'ling Musique drown'd. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e10420">[<hi>Exeunt All but </hi>Edraste.] </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e10440">
            <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
            <l>Fortunate Princess, Happy Arviola, </l>
            <l>Forgive me if I Envy now ev'n Thee! </l>
            <l>How long have I been tost in Storms of Fate, </l>
            <l>And still the Tempest darkens round my Head. </l>
            <l>The restless Queen's Ambition still projects </l>
            <l>To Load my Temples with a Hated Crown. </l>
            <l>And to effect her Plot, Aviola </l>
            <l>Must bleed, and Theocrin be lost; to Him </l>
            <l>My seoret Love long since I have devoted. </l>
            <l>To her long since my open Friendship sworn: </l>
            <l>Something I will perform in their behalf, </l>
            <l>Worthy the Chastest Love and Noblest Friendship; </l>
            <l>For from the Court I'll wander in disguise, </l>
            <l>No matter where; for one distrest like me, </l>
            <l>Can no where loose her way: When I'm remov'd, </l>
            <l>The Queen's Designs will rest, and Theocrin </l>
            <l>Possets Arviola, and the Crown in Peace: </l>
            <l>And I my self have all the sad Relief </l>
            <l>That my Forlorn Condition will admit; </l>
            <l>To Mourn retir'd in Caves and Glut of Sorrow. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e10710">Enter Myrrhoe. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myrh" xml:id="ep000770-e10730">
            <speaker>Myrh </speaker>
            <l>Madam the Princess beggs your Presence: </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e10760">
            <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
            <l>No. </l>
            <l>My Griefs will make me rude, and check her Mirth: </l>
            <l>Thou Myrrhoe ever lov'dst me, </l>
            <l>Now like a Dying Miser I'll reveal </l>
            <l>A Secret, the dear Treasure of my Soul! </l>
            <l>I love this Theocrin ev'n to Distraction: </l>
            <l>And for his Quiet, and more private Reasons, </l>
            <l>I will for ever hide me from the Court: </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e10880">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Oh Heav'n th' Eternal Powers! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e10910">
            <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
            <l>Make no Reply, </l>
            <l>But Treasure still this Secret in thy Brest: </l>
            <l>For by th' Eternal Pow'rs you meant t' invoke, </l>
            <l>I am resolv'd, and if prevented, swear </l>
            <pb n="15" xml:id="ep000770-014-b"/>
            <l>To act a speedy Violence on my Life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e10980">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Your dire Resolve alas! Has Charm'd my Tongue; </l>
            <l>But my Swoln Eyes will take their Liberty. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e11020">[Weept (Gives her Letters.] </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e11030">
            <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
            <l>When I am gone, give these to Theocrin, </l>
            <l>The short sad Accents of my Dying Passion. </l>
            <l>He may afford my Memory a Tear: </l>
            <l>Nor ev'n Arviola her self Repine. </l>
            <l>And so Fare-well to Hope and Thee for ever. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e11120">[Exeunt. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000770-e11130">
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e11140">[Warlike Musique, Theocrin in Triumph, Argaleon's Head born before him on a Spear. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-the" xml:id="ep000770-e11170">
            <speaker>The. </speaker>
            <l>Enough my Dear Companions of the War; </l>
            <l>Nor think these Honors all addrest to me: </l>
            <l>But hold your selves large Sharers in these Tryumphs. </l>
            <l>My Courage was more fortunate then vours, </l>
            <l>Not greater: Trust me then I Triumph most, </l>
            <l>When I the Honour had to Lead such Worthies </l>
            <l>To Reap an Host, not now I Head this Pomp. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e11260">[Soft Musique. Arviola in her Nuptial Dress, with a Train of Ladies Splendidly Attir'd. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e11280">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Myrrhoe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e11310">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Madam, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e11340">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Edraste was unkind </l>
            <l>Not to Accompany our Nuptial Rites. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-the" xml:id="ep000770-e11390">
            <speaker>The. </speaker>
            <l>Behold the Silver Moon shot from her Sphere, </l>
            <l>With all her Starry Train! Divine Arviola, </l>
            <l>Not Victory her self can Charm like Thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e11450">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Ah! Theocrin, my old Griefs still pursue </l>
            <l>And haunt me, even upon my Nuptial Day! </l>
            <l>A Sumptuous Feast of Joy is spread before us, </l>
            <l>But I suspect it as a Poyson'd Treat, </l>
            <l>And fear to taste; I see you, hear you talk, </l>
            <l>Clasp fast your Hand; and yet methinks w'are still </l>
            <l>As far divided as the distant Poles, </l>
            <l>And shall unite as soon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theoc" xml:id="ep000770-e11560">
            <speaker>Theoc. </speaker>
            <l>Our Joy's a Feast of the Gods own preparing; </l>
            <l>Permit not then imaginary Fears </l>
            <l>To poyson your Delights; suspect no Storm </l>
            <l>In such a Halcyon Skie, our tender Love </l>
            <l>Long nourisht covertly, till grown to an Head, </l>
            <l>Is now expos'd to th' Air, and dares the Weather, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000770-e11640">
            <pb n="16" xml:id="ep000770-015-a"/>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e11650">Enter King attended, Escalus speaking to him. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e11680">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Dread Sir, the Queen desires you to excuse </l>
            <l>Her Absence from the Pomp; she's indispos'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e11720">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>It was a rude Distemper to intrude </l>
            <l>At such a season&#8212; Bid the Masque begin; </l>
            <l>Come to your Monarchs Arms, ye happy Pair, </l>
            <l>Supporters of my Age: Thus let me joyn you; </l>
            <l>This Knot I have begun, the Priest shall finish. </l>
            <l>Look down ye Spirits of my slaughter'd Sons; </l>
            <l>Behold the Avenger of your Royal Blood; </l>
            <l>Behold our gen'ral Mirth; then summon all </l>
            <l>Your Brother Stars and Revel in your Spheros. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e11830">
              <hi>[King, Arv. Theoc. </hi>take their Seats; A Martial Dance, After which a Priest in his Habits Enters. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-priest" xml:id="ep000770-e11850">
            <speaker>Priest. </speaker>
            <l>The Flamen waits, and the preparing Rites </l>
            <l>Are finishe; thrice has Hymen been invok'd, </l>
            <l>And Iuno's Altar thrice perfum'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e11920">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>We come. </l>
            <l>Move on, lead to the Temple. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e11960">Enter a Messenger hastily. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-mess" xml:id="ep000770-e11970">
            <speaker>Mess. </speaker>
            <l>To Arms, to Arms! a Forreign Fleet invades </l>
            <l>Our frighted Coast, and brings a floating War: </l>
            <l>They spread their Streamers as secure of Conquest; </l>
            <l>With Shouts and louder Trumpets rend the Air, </l>
            <l>And seem to Triumphe'r the Fight begin. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e12040">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>A Forreign Naw! What new Turn of Fate? </l>
            <l>Must then our dear-bought Peace so soon be ravisht, </l>
            <l>And Wars green Wounds be launc'd and bleed anew? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theoc" xml:id="ep000770-e12090">
            <speaker>Theoc. </speaker>
            <l>I thank ye Gods, I have not yet deserv'd </l>
            <l>This charming Princess, am too poor in Fame, </l>
            <l>And kindly you provide for my Renown. </l>
            <l>Permit me, Royal Sir, forthwith to head </l>
            <l>Your Troops, whil'st their last Lawrels still are green, </l>
            <l>T' engage Breast-deep this bold invading Foe: </l>
            <l>Our Blood shall snatch their Legions, nor permit </l>
            <l>Their Corosea once to touch our threatn'd Soil. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e12190">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Fly swift as Light'ning, and destroy more sure. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theoc" xml:id="ep000770-e12220">
            <speaker>Theoc. </speaker>
            <l>Weep not Arviola, but bade me Conquest; </l>
            <pb n="17" xml:id="ep000770-015-b"/>
            <l>I go to bring thee Honours from the Flood, </l>
            <l>Richer than all the Gems the Deep contains; </l>
            <l>From Conquest late we mov'd to Triumph, now </l>
            <l>From Triumph to new Conquest, to return </l>
            <l>Triumphant, in an endless Round of Glory. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e12310">[Ex. with his Officers. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e12320">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>'Tis so! our Halcyon Day is overcast, </l>
            <l>And all the smiling Prospect snatch'd already: </l>
            <l>My troubled Heart presag'd its own Distress: </l>
            <l>And gave dark symptoms of the rising Storm, </l>
            <l>That parts, I fear, my Theocrin and me, </l>
            <l>To meet no more but on the Coast of Souls. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e12410">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Canst thou inform us nothing more particular? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-mess" xml:id="ep000770-e12440">
            <speaker>Mess. </speaker>
            <l>A Barge before the Fleet arriv'd the Bay, </l>
            <l>As I presume, with speedy Embassie </l>
            <l>And full Intelligence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-att" xml:id="ep000770-e12490">
            <speaker>Att. </speaker>
            <l>A Herauld Sir, </l>
            <l>Sent from the newly arriv'd Fleet. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e12530">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Admit him. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e12560">[Herauld Enters.] </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-her" xml:id="ep000770-e12570">
            <speaker>Her. </speaker>
            <l>Health to the Sacred Majesty of Greece; </l>
            <l>Prince Abardanes from the Thracian Coast, </l>
            <l>By free Commission from his Royal Father, </l>
            <l>With Seven Arm'd Legions, and full Fifty Sail </l>
            <l>Now Anchors in your Port, t' assist your Cause, </l>
            <l>And quell the Rebels that imbroil your State: </l>
            <l>Partly our Old Alliance to this Crown, </l>
            <l>Oblig'd our King t' engage in your Relief; </l>
            <l>But most t' uphold the Rights of Majesty, </l>
            <l>Whose Dignity's the Common Cause of Kings. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e12720">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Our Cause already has restor'd itself; </l>
            <l>Bear to your gen'rous Prince a Monarchs Thanks: </l>
            <l>And in our Name invite him to our Court; </l>
            <l>Our Self will meet our Royal Guest half way, </l>
            <l>Doubling our Pomp with his illustrious Train, </l>
            <l>Whil'st spight of blazing Noon, the waken'd Stars </l>
            <l>Start from their Cells, our Triumphs to survey, </l>
            <l>And joyn their Glories to this wond'rous day. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="ep000770-e12820">
          <pb n="18" xml:id="ep000770-016-a"/>
          <head>ACT. III. SCENE, <hi>The Palace</hi>. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000770-e12850">Myrrhoe with Letters. </stage>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e12870">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e12890">reads. </stage>
            <p>IAm now on my Pilgrimage, when the Nuptial Ceremonies are over, at your leisure give the Inclosed to Theocrin, from Yours Edraste. </p>
            <l>These Letters speak this Princess ignorant </l>
            <l>O' th' sudden turn in Theocrin's Affairs: </l>
            <l>A queint Device was forming in my Thought </l>
            <l>And these come seas'nably t' assist the Project. </l>
            <l>Lord Theocrin your pardon&#8212; <stage xml:id="ep000770-e13000">(<hi>opens and reads</hi>)</stage>&#8212; 'Tis right. </l>
            <l>Penn'd to my wish; a hopeful Policy, </l>
            <l>But time must ripen it. Edraste drew not </l>
            <l>From me her Ruin, nor am I unjust </l>
            <l>To play the Game which she gave o'r for lost, </l>
            <l>And sweep the Stakes. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e13080">Enter Escalus. </stage>
            <l>Brother you'r-are well return'd, and as I wisht </l>
            <l>With busie Brow; How went the Salutation? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e13120">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>The King and Prince, like Old Familiars, met, </l>
            <l>And having thrice in close Imbraces joyn'd, </l>
            <l>Admitted to their Hand each others Nobles. </l>
            <l>Th' Officious Flamen at our Western Gate, </l>
            <l>Perform'd short Sacrifice; mean while the King </l>
            <l>And Abardanes joyn'd in solemn League </l>
            <l>Of Friendship, and before their Entrance hail'd </l>
            <l>The Genius of the Place. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e13240">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>On what Design </l>
            <l>Shou'd Abardanes with such costly Forces </l>
            <l>Arrive our Shore? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e13300">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>T' assist the King to o'rthrow </l>
            <pb n="19" xml:id="ep000770-016-b"/>
            <l>The Rebels, was the plausible Pretence. </l>
            <l>A slight disguise&#8212; but hark! they come. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e13350">[King <hi>Arviola, Abardanes</hi>, with their Courtiers and Attendance, pass over the Stage. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e13370">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>The Pomp seems clouded with a sullen gloom, </l>
            <l>The King looks sad, Arviola's Cheek's are flusht </l>
            <l>With such disdainful Rage; her flashing Eyes </l>
            <l>Struck bold Argaleon at the Treaty dumb. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e13450">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Dissention, wrecking Discord is broken loose, </l>
            <l>And we must cast our Net i'th' troubled Tide; </l>
            <l>It must succeed&#8212; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e13500">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Speak, feast my greedy Ear, </l>
            <l>That wou'd devour at once the charming Tale. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e13540">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>This Prince with Passion has beheld Arviola, </l>
            <l>Which yet his haughty Mind seem'd to disdain, </l>
            <l>And with a Lions Fury shook the Toil: </l>
            <l>At last to th' King, his Grief he did unfold, </l>
            <l>And with a haughty meen (befitting more </l>
            <l>A Conqueror than Suiter) mustring up </l>
            <l>His Titles, he demanded her in Marriage: </l>
            <l>The King reply'd, 'twas an Affair of weight, </l>
            <l>And in regard of Theocrin's just claim </l>
            <l>Of fatal consequence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myrr" xml:id="ep000770-e13680">
            <speaker>Myrr. </speaker>
            <l>And this Reply </l>
            <l>Th' impatient Prince took for Consent. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esca" xml:id="ep000770-e13720">
            <speaker>Esca. </speaker>
            <l>His Pride resented it as flat denial, </l>
            <l>And scarce contain'd its Swellings within bounds. </l>
            <l>And now near Hella's Grove, Lord Theocrin, </l>
            <l>Attended with light Horseman, met the Pomp, </l>
            <l>Forward we mov'd, when in a sudden Feud; </l>
            <l>The fiery Rivals drew; but first the Prince: </l>
            <l>Both mad as Winds contesting for the Main, </l>
            <l>And scarce the thund'ring King their Fury quell'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myrr" xml:id="ep000770-e13840">
            <speaker>Myrr. </speaker>
            <l>A promising Disaster! What ensu'd? </l>
            <l>And why return'd not Theocrin? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e13890">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Scarce was the Fray compos'd, when there arriv'd </l>
            <l>Intelligence that the Disperst remains </l>
            <l>O'th' Rebel Troops, had gather'd since the Rout, </l>
            <l>And garison'd within Eipercte's Towers: </l>
            <l>The King seiz'd this occasion to dismiss </l>
            <l>Chaft Theocrin to th' Army, with strict charge </l>
            <l>To block Eipercte's Walls with speedy Siege: </l>
            <l>An exquisite Device of State, at once </l>
            <l>To keep the fiery Rivals at just distance, </l>
            <pb n="20" xml:id="ep000770-017-a"/>
            <l>And compass leisure for the best Resolves. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e14040">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Soft, he returns with pensive Diphilus </l>
            <l>And thoughtful Theocrin. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e14100">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>My Design's a-float! </l>
            <l>Pisander in the Queens esteem supplants me; </l>
            <l>What then remains but that I shift my Sails, </l>
            <l>And seek some richer Port: the King's Esteem, </l>
            <l>And Wind and Tide conspire to waft me in! </l>
            <l>The Tempest is on Wing, sink Theocrin, </l>
            <l>'Tis on thy Ruins I must build my Hopes, </l>
            <l>And mounted on thy Ship-wrack make to shore. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e14220">[Exeunt.] </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e14230">Re-enter King, Theron, Diph. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e14250">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Now Lords as you do prize your Countreys Peace, </l>
            <l>Your Ages ease, your Wives and Childrens Safety; </l>
            <l>Ply your best Skill and Bank against the Deluge! </l>
            <l>Methinks I see our Greece again embroil'd </l>
            <l>And Slaughter's bloody Sluces drawn anew; </l>
            <l>Our Laws disarm'd, and holiest Rites profan'd, </l>
            <l>Our Streets alarm'd with Tumults, Rapes and Fire, </l>
            <l>And all the Terrors of Argaleon's War. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ther" xml:id="ep000770-e14370">
            <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
            <l>Whence can you fear, dread Sir, Events so fatal? </l>
            <l>Not from the Prince, he is your Friend in League. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e14410">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>My Friend in League! Friendship's the priviledge </l>
            <l>Of private Men, for wretched Greatness knows </l>
            <l>No Blessing so substantial. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-diph" xml:id="ep000770-e14460">
            <speaker>Diph. </speaker>
            <l>Sacred Sir; </l>
            <l>I see not why your Maiesty shou'd take </l>
            <l>An anxious Thought! What can the Scruple be? </l>
            <l>What better can secure the Peace of Greece, </l>
            <l>Then that Prince Abardanes Wed Arviola? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e14560">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>And my late Vows to Theocrin be revok&#9679;&#9679;&#9679; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ther" xml:id="ep000770-e14600">
            <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
            <l>Your Int'rest, and the present Exigence </l>
            <l>Of your Affairs require it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e14640">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Then blush Hell! </l>
            <l>For Earth's more false, and Fiends to Men are Angels; </l>
            <l>O hard Estate of Empire! wretched Kings; </l>
            <l>How are we snar'd in Errors not our own, </l>
            <l>And hood-winkled to th' Crimes we most wou'd shun? </l>
            <l>Hence 'tis our Names stand Black in Chronicle, </l>
            <l>When impious Councellors betray our Reason; </l>
            <pb n="21" xml:id="ep000770-017-b"/>
            <l>With Eloquence and Sophistry ensnare us, </l>
            <l>And make Injustice necessary! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-diph" xml:id="ep000770-e14750">
            <speaker>Diph. </speaker>
            <l>Prince Abardanes aws us from the Bay, </l>
            <l>Threatens to pour his Legions on our Coast, </l>
            <l>If fair Arviola refuse his Love. </l>
            <l>His Rival Theocrin's grown Popular, </l>
            <l>And Heads our Army; what if he resent </l>
            <l>His Disappointment, seek by Force his Claim? </l>
            <l>Shall we permit him take by Arms his Right, </l>
            <l>And to a Subjects Tyranny submit? </l>
            <l>Or call the Princes Forces to our Aid, </l>
            <l>And trust the Courtesie of Forreign Pow'rs? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e14900">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>The Siege will hold him for a while employ'd; </l>
            <l>The Prince and he, fierce as they are, may yet </l>
            <l>Burn harmless as dire Planets do; whil'st distant: </l>
            <l>But meeting hurl swist ruin on our State. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e14960">Enter Escalus. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e14980">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>My Business Royal Sir, will justifie </l>
            <l>My bold Intrusion; give me leave t' impeach </l>
            <l>Your Favourite of Guilt, which true as 'tis, </l>
            <l>Will scarce meet your Belief; of Treason. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e15040">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Ha! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e15070">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Lord Theocrin, he Courts the Popular Fame, </l>
            <l>And forms Designs against your Life and Empire. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e15120">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Say, speak'st thou this on thy own Knowledge or </l>
            <l>Conjecture? If no more, on what Presumption? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e15160">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>The cause, his jealousie of Abardanes, </l>
            <l>And your deferring his expected Nuptials: </l>
            <l>With blood shot Eyes I view'd him in the Pomp, </l>
            <l>Whil'st diving low from his Triumphant Chair, </l>
            <l>The Rabble at each Hault he did salute, </l>
            <l>Then eagerly inclin'd his Lawrell'd Head, </l>
            <l>To catch the buzzing Praises of the Crow'd; </l>
            <l>Whil'st on his Youth (his Active Youth they call'd it) </l>
            <l>And (as they term'd it) your neglectful Age </l>
            <l>They descanted, wounding each Loyal Ear! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e15290">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>I must have Evidence more positive, </l>
            <l>Till then suspend my Judgment, make it clear, </l>
            <l>And know that on the Proof depends thy Life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e15340">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Good Gods, that I were Earth! forgotten Dust; </l>
            <l>Th'oblit'rate Marble mouldring o'r my Ashes, </l>
            <l>And this Black Charge a Slander: Heaven! My Life! </l>
            <pb n="22" xml:id="ep000770-018-a"/>
            <l>Your Empire's Life depends on your Belief. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e15400">[Exit King, Theron, Diph.] </stage>
            <l>So now I'm Plung'd, and must dash through or Perish: </l>
            <l>Three Factious Stout Repiners at the State </l>
            <l>(Of Bank'rupt Fortunes) I have Brib'd already. </l>
            <l>To swear this Charge, a Circumstance or two, </l>
            <l>Neatly devis'd and plausibly alledg'd, </l>
            <l>Will make th' Impeachment pass. </l>
            <l>Now to my She consed'rate to confer </l>
            <l>Of my Designs: She's a Projecter too, </l>
            <l>Lur'd on by Interests resistless Charms; </l>
            <l>The vig'rous Spring that sets all Plots adrist, </l>
            <l>From Womens Projects to th' Intrigues of State. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e15530">[Exit.] </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e15540">Enter Arviola, Myrrhoe. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e15560">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Ha! Visit you disguis'd, too Night? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e15590">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>He comes: </l>
            <l>My Theocrin, I but ev'n now discharg'd </l>
            <l>The welcome Messenger he sent to inform me. </l>
            <l>No tidings of my dear Edraste yet? </l>
            <l>'Twas sure no small Resentment that cou'd move </l>
            <l>Her temp'rate Breast to such a rash Resolve! </l>
            <l>My Fate in all its past Severities, </l>
            <l>Allow'd me that dear Partner of my Cares; </l>
            <l>But now the Charmer of my Griess is gone. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e15720">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Your sorrow never shall complain alone, </l>
            <l>Whil'st I have Breath to eccho to your Sighs. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e15760">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Myrrhoe, thy Truth deserves a better Fate, </l>
            <l>Then waits thy wretched Princess! O my Heart&#8212; </l>
            <l>My Theorcrin!&#8212; but that's too harsh a string </l>
            <l>And I forbear to touch&#8212; Say Myrrhoe, </l>
            <l>How does the Queen resent Edraste's Absence? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myrr" xml:id="ep000770-e15870">
            <speaker>Myrr. </speaker>
            <l>Her Women fear'd t' inform her of the Truth, </l>
            <l>And forg'd a formal Tale&#8212; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000770-e15910">
            <pb n="23" xml:id="ep000770-018-b"/>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e15920">Enter a Lady with a Ring. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-lady" xml:id="ep000770-e15940">
            <speaker>Lady. </speaker>
            <l>A Stranger, Madam, </l>
            <l>Desires Admittance; when I crav'd his Business, </l>
            <l>He enjoyn'd me to deliver you this Ring. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ar" xml:id="ep000770-e15990">
            <speaker>Ar. </speaker>
            <l>See Myrrhoe. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e16030">[Gives her the Ring.] </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myrr" xml:id="ep000770-e16040">
            <speaker>Myrr. </speaker>
            <l>Lord Theocrin's Signet Madam. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e16080">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Conduct him privately to my Apartment. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e16110">[Ex. the Lady.] </stage>
            <l>You Myrrhoe wait here, and on your Life, </l>
            <l>Permit none t' approach us. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e16150">[Exit.] </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e16160">Enter Escalus. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e16180">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>I'm wing'd with Transport, and I tread on Air, </l>
            <l>Ha Myrrhoe, what's thero? Lord Theocrin in's Seal? </l>
            <l>A prize by Mercury! the Luckiest hit. </l>
            <l>Ev'n fortune's self is my Confedrate now, </l>
            <l>And Aids me in my jugling: Sister stay, </l>
            <l>This Ring must do me present service, but </l>
            <l>I'll instantly restore it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myrr" xml:id="ep000770-e16290">
            <speaker>Myrr. </speaker>
            <l>Stay Escalus. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e16330">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>My business is most pressing. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myrr" xml:id="ep000770-e16360">
            <speaker>Myrr. </speaker>
            <l>So is mine. </l>
            <l>Did not the Queen too night send to invite you </l>
            <l>To banquet with her in the Grotto. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e16430">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Yes, </l>
            <l>Pisander too is summon'd thither; </l>
            <l>Some new adventure that requires our Counsel. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e16490">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Know then you are invited to your death, </l>
            <l>The banquet's Poysoned. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-escalus" xml:id="ep000770-e16530">
            <speaker>Escalus </speaker>
            <l>Ha! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e16560">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>The Queen perceives you are jealous of Pisander, </l>
            <l>And to prevent your just revenge, conspires </l>
            <l>With her Young Paramour to take your life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e16640">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Whence your Intelligence? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e16670">
            <pb n="24" xml:id="ep000770-019-a"/>
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>From Bromian, </l>
            <l>Attendant on the Queen in her Retirement, </l>
            <l>Who persecutes me with his whining Passion, </l>
            <l>And to oblige me made this dear Discovery. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e16740">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Ev'n this shall give a Lift to my Designs, </l>
            <l>For Fencer like I'll Ward and Strike together. </l>
            <l>The Queen and I too Night draw Stakes for Life; </l>
            <l>The Lots are hid, now for a flight of hand, </l>
            <l>To pick the Prize and shift the blank to Her. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e16810">[Exeunt severally.] </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000770-e16820">
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e16830">Scene draws, Arviola and Theocrin. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e16860">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>So hasty were my Orders for the Siege, </l>
            <l>That I was forc'd Disguis'd to make this Visit </l>
            <l>Arviola! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e16920">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e16950">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>The last days Sun </l>
            <l>Was to have seen our Nuptials celebrated: </l>
            <l>The busie Priests for us prepar'd their Temple; </l>
            <l>Nor cou'd attend the Morning Sacrifice! </l>
            <l>The pompous Streets with Bays and Palm were strew'd, </l>
            <l>And Legions blest us as we past along, </l>
            <l>Hail Conqu'ring Bridegroom, Royal Bride all Hail, </l>
            <l>Enrich our Empire with a glorious Race. </l>
            <l>Die Ag'd and Happy! Thus our Loves were greeted: </l>
            <l>And now we meet, we meet (Oh Gods!) by stealth! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e17070">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Dear Theocrin, believe me still your Bride, </l>
            <l>For Souls can wed without the Formal Priest: </l>
            <l>Why are our Loves, that prosper'd when conceal'd, </l>
            <l>Like Faiery-Wealth, curst since they came to light? </l>
            <l>Ah! had you ne'r aspir'd at fatal Glory, </l>
            <l>We might at least have given the Night to Love, </l>
            <l>Tho we, like Glow-worms, hid by Day our Fires. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e17170">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>Divinest of thy Sex, ' its past the powr </l>
            <l>Of Thought to rate my Love!&#8212; Arviola! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e17220">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>What wou'd my Theocrin? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e17260">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>Dismiss me to my Grave, whilst thou art kind; </l>
            <l>And hurry from the World this useless Life, </l>
            <l>Which if prolong'd, must prove to Thee most fatal. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e17310">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Alas, my Lord, your Griefs talk wildly now. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e17340">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>The haughty Prince his Rival once remov'd, </l>
            <l>Will prove more mild, nor longer threaten War; </l>
            <l>With thousand more Conveniences of thine! </l>
            <pb n="25" xml:id="ep000770-019-b"/>
            <l>The King will ne'r chide with you for my sake, </l>
            <l>Nor trembling Mothers curse your Constancy! </l>
            <l>Fate wills, and 'tis expedient that I die! </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e17420">Enter Myrrhoe with a Ring. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e17440">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Prince Abardanes, Madam, waits your leisure; </l>
            <l>My Lord, your Signet. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e17490">[Gives him the Ring.] </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e17500">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>The Prince demand Admittance?, </l>
            <l>Sure he is well improv'd in his Acquaintance </l>
            <l>To seek Admittance here!&#8212; Go Myrrhoe </l>
            <l>Inform the Stranger better. He mistakes, </l>
            <l>These are the Apartments of Arviola </l>
            <l>The Princess; Privacy. Haste, tell him so. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myrr" xml:id="ep000770-e17600">
            <speaker>Myrr. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord 'tis, with the Princess he wou'd speak; </l>
            <l>He comes to Visit&#8212; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e17640">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>Visit? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e17670">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Good: He's jealous. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e17700">[Aside.] </stage>
            <l>The Furies send the Princess half so apt </l>
            <l>To take th' Infection and my Project's made. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e17730">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Retire my Theocrin. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e17770">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>How my Arviola? </l>
            <l>Retire?&#8212; by Love I will not understand thee, </l>
            <l>Nor wou'dst thou sure be understood&#8212; and yet </l>
            <l>That angry Brow recalls my Charity! </l>
            <l>Is't possible? bid Theocrin retire? </l>
            <l>Remove, and give a new Pretender room? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e17870">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Thank your Distresses that disarm my Rage, </l>
            <l>Or my resenting Honour shou'd chastise </l>
            <l>This Jealousie; it shou'd rash Man: but now </l>
            <l>(Since Fortune treats you ill) I am content </l>
            <l>To weigh your Griefs and wink at your Offence. </l>
            <l>Once more I do entreat you to with draw, </l>
            <l>And humour the perversness of our Fate; </l>
            <l>A little Patience will restore our Wishes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e17970">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>I find my Error, and am dash'd with shame! </l>
            <l>Excuse the Ravings of a feav'rish mind; </l>
            <l>Nor rate by common Rules immod'rate Love. </l>
            <l>Ah Princess, could'st thou dive into my Heart, </l>
            <l>And see how absolute thy Form reigns there, </l>
            <l>How much I prize the Treasure of thy Love, </l>
            <l>Thou would'st at least forgive my wakeful care; </l>
            <l>That miser-like I wear a watchful Eye, </l>
            <l>And weigh each Grain of the hard purchast Store. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e18080">
            <pb n="26" xml:id="ep000770-020-a"/>
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Now by a Virgins Truth, I swear (stand still </l>
            <l>Ye flying Minutes, and attend my Vow;) </l>
            <l>Whil'st Nature holds her Course and Time runs on, </l>
            <l>Whil'st Night and Day the Night and Day succeed, </l>
            <l>Whil'st Rivers pay their Tribute to the Sea: </l>
            <l>And Seas with fresh recruits the Streams supply, </l>
            <l>Whil'st Winter strews Hoar-Frost and Summer Dew; </l>
            <l>I'm Theocrin's&#8212; So Theocrin prove True. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e18200">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>What pittying God, toucht with the sad Estate </l>
            <l>Of fall'n Mankind, sent from their bright Abodes, </l>
            <l>This Vertue to reform the Savage World! </l>
            <l>Bright Excellence, Imperial Maid, farwel; </l>
            <l>I go to glean the last Remains o'th' War; </l>
            <l>And like Argaleon let me fall accurst, </l>
            <l>If once these weary Lids be clos'd in sleep; </l>
            <l>Or these devoted Limbs uncas'd from Steell, </l>
            <l>Till I've compleated well my task of Honour, </l>
            <l>And brought thee Conquest perfect as my Love. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e18330">[Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000770-e18340">
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e18350">Enter <hi>Abardanes, Sossacles </hi>at distance. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e18370">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>A Lover's Visit if it fail to meet </l>
            <l>The best Reception, most unwelcome proves: </l>
            <l>But Madam, if my Passion's troublesome, </l>
            <l>Accuse the fatal Power of your own Charms; </l>
            <l>Unwillingly I put your Fetters on. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e18440">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>With what an Arrogance his Passion sues. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e18470">[Aside. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e18480">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>I know I Court on Disadvantages, </l>
            <l>And my rough Passion can have little Charms; </l>
            <l>But Love dissolves and Moulds me o'r anew: </l>
            <l>My Temper gives beneath each Glance you dart. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e18540">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>None sure can be to your vast Merits blind, </l>
            <l>But Prince your Court-ship's to a Bride addrest, </l>
            <l>And Brides in Heav'ns account are wed already. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e18590">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>It was my Rivall's Fortune, not desert, </l>
            <l>T'have first beheld your Charms; which having seen, </l>
            <l>He Lov'd of necessary Consequence: </l>
            <l>Chance laid the dazzling Treasure in his way, </l>
            <l>Too vast to be by any Subject held; </l>
            <l>And into Royal Hands must be resign'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e18670">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Now Prince you press too far your Priviledge, </l>
            <l>Allow his Worth, as I Dispute not Yours; </l>
            <pb n="27" xml:id="ep000770-020-b"/>
            <l>Which weigh'd, perhaps wou'd make the lighter Scale. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e18720">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>I'm pleas'd to find his Merit swell so high! </l>
            <l>Your Praise has made him Worthy of my Sword: </l>
            <l>If wanting Royal Bloud, it prove his Fate </l>
            <l>To enrich himself with mine, you are his Prize: </l>
            <l>But first we'll try the Forune of the Field. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e18790">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Ah me! He is rash, and Theocrin all Fire; </l>
            <l>What Ruin must attend such meeting Hames. </l>
            <l>My Lord, the Prince, Return&#8212; Cou'd you Pretend </l>
            <l>To Love, and in neglectful Rage withdraw? </l>
            <l>Permit my Grief to reason calmly with you, </l>
            <l>For you are generous and will be just! </l>
            <l>This Love that has surpriz'd your noble Mind, </l>
            <l>Is but a vicious and irregular Heat&#8212; </l>
            <l>Which your severer Prudence will Correct. </l>
            <l>You'll be advis'd my Lord, I know you will; </l>
            <l>You ought not, must not&#8212; and you will not Love. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e18930">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>O my divided Soul! her painted Grief </l>
            <l>Darts through my stubborn Bosom to my Heart. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e18970">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>What Triumph is there in a Virgins Tears? </l>
            <l>What Conquest to pursue her to her Grave? </l>
            <l>I'm sworn to be Lord Theocrin's or die; </l>
            <l>And if from his Embrace I am Divorc'd; </l>
            <l>Who Courts me after, is my Murderer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e19050">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>Rise Princess, witness these prodigious Tears, </l>
            <l>How much I'm touch'd with your Distress; how much </l>
            <l>My lab'ring Heart resists the pow'rful Charm. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e19100">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>So may you speed in War and thrive in Glory, </l>
            <l>Nor of your Crowns and Trophies know the Tale; </l>
            <l>And if agen you condescend to Love, </l>
            <l>With all the soft Returns of Kindness meet, </l>
            <l>Which tender Maids, that pine with secret Flame, </l>
            <l>Wish, when retir'd, they tell the Groves their Pain! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e19180">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>I yield! you have prevail'd against your self, </l>
            <l>Your Tears have quencht the Fire your Glances gave; </l>
            <l>I'll force a Conquest on my Heart, I will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e19230">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Then Blessings Crown&#8212; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e19260">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>O take your Charms away, </l>
            <l>I cannot look and with such Treasure part, </l>
            <l>But when remov'd, I'll try to represent </l>
            <l>Your Form less Glorious, and resign you then. </l>
            <l>This Pang, and I'm at ease!&#8212; O Sossacles, </l>
            <l>I have o'rcome!&#8212; 'Tis false, I'm still her Slave, </l>
            <l>I long, and 'tis methinks an Age already </l>
            <l>Since I beheld her! How shall I sustain </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e19370">[Exit Arviola. </stage>
            <pb n="28" xml:id="ep000770-021-a"/>
            <l>Eternal Absence? It can never be, </l>
            <l>My Fancy forms her fairer now than ever; </l>
            <l>As Colours take in Christal brighter Die. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-soss" xml:id="ep000770-e19420">
            <speaker>Soss. </speaker>
            <l>Your Highness better knows to War than Love; </l>
            <l>Presume not Sir to force a Victory </l>
            <l>By furious onset here, as in the Field; </l>
            <l>'Tis, Patience and a formal Siege must win, </l>
            <l>The Fort which you in vain attempt to storm: </l>
            <l>Bribes must Corrupt, where Force and Valour fail. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e19500">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>Speak plain, my Oracle, thy Conduct here </l>
            <l>May speed my Love, as it has done my Arms. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-soss" xml:id="ep000770-e19540">
            <speaker>Soss. </speaker>
            <l>The Princess Heart's already taken up </l>
            <l>With Theocrin, and if you press for Entrance, </l>
            <l>Must sink all Three: Plot first to dispossess </l>
            <l>Your Rival. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e19610">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>'Tis a Task for Hercules. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-soss" xml:id="ep000770-e19650">
            <speaker>Soss. </speaker>
            <l>I'll work the self-same Engine to dislodge </l>
            <l>Your Rival, and to fix you in his room. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e19690">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>'Tis past the pow'r of Wit; but I can trust </l>
            <l>Thy Cunning for Impossibilities. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e19730">[Exeunt. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000770-e19740">
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e19750">Enter King, Escalus, Theron, Diph. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e19770">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>The Queen Confed'rate too with Theocrin? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e19810">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Your Queen, your pensive, solitary Queen, </l>
            <l>Conspires with Theocrin against your Life; </l>
            <l>Her Cell, her sacred Grotto, is the Nest </l>
            <l>To hatch their Treason; haste and trust your Eyes, </l>
            <l>Ev'n now th'are brooding there together. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e19890">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>On </l>
            <l>And force our Entrance. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e19930">[Exeunt. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000770-e19940">
            <pb n="29" xml:id="ep000770-021-b"/>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e19950">Scene drawing, discovers the <hi>Grotto. Queen </hi>and Pisander amorously seated in a Bowr. </stage>
            <lg>
              <head>Song. </head>
              <lg n="1">
                <head>1. </head>
                <l>TELL my Strephon that I die, </l>
                <l>Let th' Ecchoes to each other tell, </l>
                <l>Till the mournful Accent fly </l>
                <l>To Strephon's Ear and all is well. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg n="2">
                <head>2. </head>
                <l>But gently break the fatal Truth, </l>
                <l>Sweeten ev'ry sadder sound; </l>
                <l>For Strephon's such a tender Youth, </l>
                <l>The gentlest words too deep will wound. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg n="3">
                <head>3. </head>
                <l>No! Fountains, Eccho's, all be dumb; </l>
                <l>For shou'd I cost my Swain a Tear, </l>
                <l>I shou'd repent me in the Tomb, </l>
                <l>And grieve t' have bought my Rest so dear. </l>
              </lg>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000770-e20210">
            <pb n="30" xml:id="ep000770-022-a"/>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e20220">
              <hi>After which Enter </hi>King, Esc. The. Diph. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e20240">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>My Eyes have surfeited upon their shame; </l>
            <l>Guards seize 'em both: </l>
            <l>Dissembling Aribell! false Theocrin! </l>
            <l>Why that's Pisander. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e20330">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Ha! Pisander?&#8212; Gods! </l>
            <l>Then there's a new Discov'ry&#8212; who'd ha' thought </l>
            <l>Pisander were a Villain. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-pis" xml:id="ep000770-e20400">
            <speaker>Pis. </speaker>
            <l>Perjur'd Slave! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e20430">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>I blush for thee Pisander! cou'd even weep </l>
            <l>To see such hopeful Vertue fall'n away. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-pis" xml:id="ep000770-e20480">
            <speaker>Pis. </speaker>
            <l>I know vour Majesty decrees my Death; </l>
            <l>And with my latest Breath I will pronounce </l>
            <l>That Escalus a Traytor. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e20540">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>Treach'rous Fiend! </l>
            <l>I'll Perish, and involve Thee in my Ruin! </l>
            <l>My Lord, the King, I own foul practices </l>
            <l>Against your Crown, but was in all seduc'd </l>
            <l>By that Arch-Devil. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e20610">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Hear me Sacred Sir? </l>
            <l>To clear my Loyalty, I but demand </l>
            <l>Your Majesty compel 'em taste these Bowls. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e20660">[A Goblet is given to Pisander] </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e20680">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Drink Slave or Perish. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e20710">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>Hell 'tis Drink and Perish. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e20740">[Aside Pisander's Dead] </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e20760">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Unfold this Riddle. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e20790">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Know my Royal Master </l>
            <l>The Queen her self broke with me of this Plot; </l>
            <l>But having found me firm of Loyalty, </l>
            <l>Resolv'd to silence me with Death for ever. </l>
            <l>On that Design invited me too Night, </l>
            <l>To Banquet with her here i'th Grotto, where </l>
            <l>These Poyson'd Goblets were to have giv'n me Welcome. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e20890">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Guards, bear the Empress to the Cittadel, </l>
            <l>Till we resolve the manner of her Death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e20930">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>Death, doting Monarch, must that witherd Brow </l>
            <l>Give Sentence on this Bloom, this Spring of Beauty, </l>
            <l>That has preserv'd thy friezing Bloud in Motion, </l>
            <l>Cous'ning the Grave of her long due; the Grave </l>
            <l>That rivall'd me, and for thy Lumber waited, </l>
            <l>When I received it to my Youthful Bed. </l>
            <l>Have I sustain'd thy sinking Royalty, </l>
            <l>And stufft thy hollow Robes to fill the Throne; </l>
            <pb n="31" xml:id="ep000770-022-b"/>
            <l>And talk'st Thou of my Death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e21040">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Away with her, </l>
            <l>Let darkest Mansions hide her from the Day, </l>
            <l>That Sickens at her Insolence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-qu" xml:id="ep000770-e21090">
            <speaker>Qu. </speaker>
            <l>Be't so. </l>
            <l>I'll make those Mansions fairer that those Bow'rs, </l>
            <l>And in a Scene of thought repeat these Joys, </l>
            <l>So oft within these rev'ling Shades Possest. </l>
            <l>See there thy Rival, King, how lovelier far </l>
            <l>In Death than thou art Breathing? Fear him still, </l>
            <l>Be jealous of his Memory, and live </l>
            <l>Till ev'ry Subject scorns thee as I do, </l>
            <l>And Vermine like o'r-leap their Wooden King. </l>
            <l>State, Tempests, shake thee into Dust&#8212; Fates catch </l>
            <l>My Curse, and stamp it in their brazen Volumns. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e21220">[Exit Queen Guarded </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e21230">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>This jumps not with my Wish, Tame, Suff'ring King! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e21260">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>But Theocrin&#8212; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e21300">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Is to his Charge return'd, </l>
            <l>Too late we enter'd to surprize him here; </l>
            <l>These Letters I intended t'have produc'd, </l>
            <l>And charg'd him with his Treason to his Face. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e21360">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>To the Rebels? and with Theocrin's Signet seal'd? </l>
            <l>See <hi>Theron, Diphilus</hi>. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ther" xml:id="ep000770-e21420">
            <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
            <l>With what Contents. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e21450">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>He taxes me with Breach of Faith, repents </l>
            <l>His Service, and solicites them t'espouse </l>
            <l>His Cause, and ioyn their Out-law'd Troops with his; </l>
            <l>Which will secure at once their forfeit Heads; </l>
            <l>And vindicate his Claim t' Arviola. </l>
            <l>My Lords your speedy and most safe Resolves. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-diph" xml:id="ep000770-e21540">
            <speaker>Diph. </speaker>
            <l>'Twere safest to discover no distrust, </l>
            <l>But summon him to Court with speed, </l>
            <l>As to some sudden Council, then </l>
            <l>Surprize and sentence him to present Death. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e21600">[Ex. King, Ther. Diph. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e21620">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Mid'st all my busie Zeal, this stupid King, </l>
            <l>As yet no mention of Reward has made! </l>
            <l>And rates my Service as a Subjects Duty: </l>
            <l>Had I imploy'd but half the expence of Wit </l>
            <l>To serve the Prince, my Pains had past for Merit: </l>
            <pb n="32" xml:id="ep000770-023-a"/>
            <l>He claims no Soveraign Right in my Endeavours, </l>
            <l>And will with Honours crown my Industry. </l>
            <l>The time presents, his Agent Sossacles </l>
            <l>With Myrrhoe has been tamp'ring; I'll strike in </l>
            <l>And share in the Design; 'twere plausible, </l>
            <l>And of good credit, to perswade this Prince, </l>
            <l>That for his Interest I have undermin'd </l>
            <l>Lord Theocron, his dangerous Rival. Good! </l>
            <l>Thus tacking oft to catch the veering Winds, </l>
            <l>The skilful Pilot works into the Bay. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e21820">[Exit. </stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="ep000770-e21830">
          <head>ACT. IV. SCENE, <hi>The Palace</hi>. </head>
          <stage xml:id="ep000770-e21860">King, Escalus, Theron, Diph. </stage>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e21870">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>TIs odds, but he'll suspect the sudden Summons </l>
            <l>(As Guilt is ever jealous) and decline </l>
            <l>Our Orders. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e21920">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Doubt not, Sir, but he'll appear, </l>
            <l>And with as bold a meen as ever. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e21960">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Thus forward Spirits, howe'r by Heav'n design'd </l>
            <l>For State-Defenders, prove their Countries Bane; </l>
            <l>For when their active Courage has redrest </l>
            <l>The Publique Wrongs; the proud Restorer's self </l>
            <l>Next Tyrant proves, and for Reward Usurps </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e22030">To them Abardanes and Sossacles. </stage>
            <l>Now Prince to your Desires I can be just; </l>
            <l>Your Rival has by Treason forseited </l>
            <l>His Right to Arviola and our Favour, </l>
            <l>And naught remains that can resist your claim. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e22110">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>Not ev'n Arviola's Divinest Charms </l>
            <l>Are more desirable, than to be stil'd </l>
            <pb n="33" xml:id="ep000770-023-b"/>
            <l>Your Son, not Glory cou'd have charm'd me more; </l>
            <l>Glory that drew me forth to share your War. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e22180">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Free I receiv'd this Crown from Heav'n, and leave </l>
            <l>Arviola her freedom to confer </l>
            <l>The fortune of her Greece, where she bestows </l>
            <l>Her Love; and Abardanes is secure </l>
            <l>Of our best Aid t'endear him to her Breast. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e22280">[Ex. King, Esc. Ther. Diph. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e22300">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>Come near, my Sossacles, thou art surpriz'd </l>
            <l>To find this Cheek turn'd pale, and see this Breast </l>
            <l>Heav'd with unwonted Sighs; I know 'tis mean, </l>
            <l>And blush at this Disorder, but bear with me, </l>
            <l>Thou only conscious art to my Complaint, </l>
            <l>And even to thee I tell but half my Pain. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-soss" xml:id="ep000770-e22390">
            <speaker>Soss. </speaker>
            <l>To me you gave the Conduct of your Love, </l>
            <l>And with successful Industry I've won </l>
            <l>(What most I doubted) Myrrhoe to our side) </l>
            <l>The Princess's confident. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e22460">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>Is't possible? </l>
            <l>'Twas by her Art that Theocrin prevail'd, </l>
            <l>And work'd into Arviola's esteem. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-soss" xml:id="ep000770-e22530">
            <speaker>Soss. </speaker>
            <l>The fittest Engine therefore to dislodge </l>
            <l>And work him out agen: She knew t' extol </l>
            <l>And dazzle the Young Princess with his Praise; </l>
            <l>And doubtless can with equal Art accuse. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e22590">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>By what strange Wiles, my subtle Mercury, </l>
            <l>Could'st thou prevail on this demure Deceiver? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-soss" xml:id="ep000770-e22640">
            <speaker>Soss. </speaker>
            <l>With well couch'd Flattery, and pretended Love; </l>
            <l>Besides with Gemms and Gold I brib'd her Favour, </l>
            <l>Yet with such difficulty, that t' have viewed </l>
            <l>The winding Scene, had prov'd no small Diversion. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e22700">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>Methinks I see my Engineer at work. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-soss" xml:id="ep000770-e22730">
            <speaker>Soss. </speaker>
            <l>At first, with such disdain, as wou'd ha' past </l>
            <l>For real, with the unskill'd in Womens Wiles, </l>
            <l>The Present she refus'd; in passion told me </l>
            <l>That she had much projected for your sake, </l>
            <l>And by degrees intended to encline </l>
            <l>The Princess to accept of your Address, </l>
            <l>But was prevented by those hated Gifts, </l>
            <l>That rendered her free Service Mercinary. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e22830">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>Then flung away? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-soss" xml:id="ep000770-e22860">
            <speaker>Soss. </speaker>
            <l>No! paus'd, and with a sigh </l>
            <l>Confest, though you had justly disoblig'd her, </l>
            <pb n="34" xml:id="ep000770-024-a"/>
            <l>Yet since it was the Princess Interest </l>
            <l>T'slight fall'n Theocrin, and approve your Suit, </l>
            <l>She'd still proceed to serve you, and engag'd </l>
            <l>(By wha&#772;t Device I know not) instantly </l>
            <l>To render her Averse to Theocrin, </l>
            <l>And then of course you seize her vacant Breast. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e22980">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>Thou shalt have Altars rais'd thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-soss" xml:id="ep000770-e23010">
            <speaker>Soss. </speaker>
            <l>See, she comes. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e23040">Enter Myrrhoe. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e23060">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord, I come to check your lavish Bounty, </l>
            <l>That leaves no place, for gen'rous and free Service, </l>
            <l>But turns my best Endeavours into Hire. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e23110">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>Think not those trivial Presents were design'd </l>
            <l>For more than Earnests of Rewards to come; </l>
            <l>'Tis in your pow'r to enrich me with a Treasure, </l>
            <l>Beyond the Wealth of my expected Empire; </l>
            <l>Arviola's Love. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e23190">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Know my Designs on that account were ripe, </l>
            <l>Before you shar'd your Bounty: a few hours </l>
            <l>Is all I crave to perfect your Request. </l>
            <l>Arviola comes, with-draw Sir, and expect </l>
            <l>My Promise. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e23270">[Ex. Abard. Soss. </stage>
            <l>Now Edraste's Letter </l>
            <l>To Theocrin, comes in play; now all the Fraud </l>
            <l>That injur d Lovers charge upon our Sex </l>
            <l>Inspire me; Tears, Oaths, Swoonings, changing Blood; </l>
            <l>And all the seeming Pangs of wildest Rage, </l>
            <l>Assist my Cous'nage. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e23370">Enter <hi>Arviola. [Myrhoe </hi>falls prostrate, as going to stab her self. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e23390">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Ha! the Gods forbid! </l>
            <l>Stop thy rash Arm, or turn thy Steel on me, </l>
            <l>Distracted Myrrhoe; speak what means this Fury. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e23450">
            <pb n="35" xml:id="ep000770-024-b"/>
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Where am I? What unkind Hand has disarm'd me! </l>
            <l>O my asslicted Heart! Arviola? </l>
            <l>Fly Princess, for I have resolved on Death, </l>
            <l>And shall depart in Pain if you are by. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e23520">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Speak, I conjure thee, and unfold thy Grief; </l>
            <l>Or by our dearest Friendship I'll bleed first. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e23560">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>As you regard your Peace, permit me die </l>
            <l>In silence, nor reveal a fatal Truth, </l>
            <l>Which you of all the World shou'd last discover. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e23610">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Thy tender Bosom takes too quick a sense </l>
            <l>Of my Distresses; but of me learn temper, </l>
            <l>That can survive at once Edraste's Absence </l>
            <l>And Theocrin's Disgrace. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e23690">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>I Theocrin! </l>
            <l>Was it not I that kindled first your Breast </l>
            <l>With Love of Theocrin, and fann'd the Flame </l>
            <l>With hourly Praise? Unfortunate Zeal. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e23770">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Thou did'st, </l>
            <l>And I adore thee for't. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e23810">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>I did, </l>
            <l>And with that Ponyard meant to act </l>
            <l>A Justice on my self for doing it; </l>
            <l>Tho to the expecting Fates I will appeal </l>
            <l>I was abus'd, and more deceiv'd than you! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e23880">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Wreck me no longer with tormenting doubt; </l>
            <l>If my full Griefs can yet be capable </l>
            <l>Of fresh Disasters, let me know the worst. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e23930">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Swear then to bear it as a Princess shou'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e23960">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Perish my dearest hopes, but I will do </l>
            <l>As shall become my Sex and Royal Blood. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e24000">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Peruse that Letter then. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e24030">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>To Theocrin? </l>
            <l>And in Edrastes Hand? Her N&#224;me subscrib'd? </l>
            <l>Most strange Contents!&#8212; Yet she concludes more strangely! </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e24100">
              <hi>[Reads.</hi>]&#8212; Forgive my Griefs this Trespass; they shall never offend you more; for I have not the heart to complain of you, tho the Author of my Ruin. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e24120">Edraste. </stage>
            <l>The Author of her Ruin! Theocrin </l>
            <l>The Author of Edraste's Ruin! Speak! </l>
            <l>Confess, or dear as 'tis, I will rip up </l>
            <l>That reverend Breast, and tear the Secret forth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e24190">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Take then the fatal Story (Sighs be husht </l>
            <pb n="36" xml:id="ep000770-025-a"/>
            <l>And give me Breath)&#8212; th' unfortunate Edraste </l>
            <l>(As I have ever been her Confident) </l>
            <l>Inform'd me of the Cause why she with-drew; </l>
            <l>You thought her Absence unaccountable; </l>
            <l>So little you surmis'd that she retir'd </l>
            <l>To hide her growing shame! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e24290">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Her growing shame! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e24320">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>With Cheeks now pale, now blushing, she confest </l>
            <l>She had resign'd her sacred Virgins Treasure, </l>
            <l>And in close dalliance wanton'd, till at last, </l>
            <l>Her amorous Theft no longer wou'd be hid, </l>
            <l>But forc'd her to retire. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e24390">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>I'll mourn for thee Edraste, and lament </l>
            <l>In thy Offence, the Fall of Womankind!&#8212; </l>
            <l>But&#8212; Myrhoe&#8212; Thou seem'st not yet discharg'd </l>
            <l>Of half thy Tragick Tale&#8212; Thou fear'st to say </l>
            <l>With whom she did offend; and I to enquire! </l>
            <l>Why art thou rackt my Heart with fond mistrust; </l>
            <l>For 'tis impossible that Theocrin </l>
            <l>Shou'd prove so false&#8212; and as impossible </l>
            <l>That any other Tempter shou'd prevail! </l>
            <l>I dare not&#8212; will not&#8212; yet I must suspect </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e24540">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Now Princess call to mind your solemn Vow, </l>
            <l>You swore to act as Honour shou'd advise, </l>
            <l>And Honour will inspire you with disdain, </l>
            <l>For this ingrateful, most forsworn of Men. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e24600">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Sink me to Death! Plunge me in streaming Fire, </l>
            <l>Heap Mountains on my Head, </l>
            <l>And bury my Disgrace, </l>
            <l>Abus'd <hi>Arviola.</hi>! </l>
            <l>Deluded, credulous Maid!&#8212; Oh Perjury! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e24680">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Rise Princess and compose this dang'rous Passion. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e24710">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>No! to this Earth I'll grow, </l>
            <l>Out-rave the Winter Sea, </l>
            <l>Out-rage the Northern Wind, </l>
            <l>And with my loud Complaints alarm the Gods, </l>
            <l>Till they resent the Wrongs </l>
            <l>Of flatter'd Virgins, and confound Mankind. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e24790">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Then curse thy self rash Tongue for thy discovery! </l>
            <l>Perish these idle Hands, that had not first </l>
            <l>Sheath'd this preventing Ponyard in my Heart; </l>
            <l>But 'tis not yet too late&#8212; </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e24850">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Hold Myrrhoe! </l>
            <l>Thou art more rash than I; </l>
            <l>Think, think how much I lov'd! </l>
            <pb n="37" xml:id="ep000770-025-b"/>
            <l>How much I was abus'd! </l>
            <l>And thou wilt say I have a Turtles tameness! </l>
            <l>False! perjur'd Theocrin! </l>
            <l>I can almost excuse thee Lost Edraste, </l>
            <l>When I recall the smooth Deceivers Charms; </l>
            <l>He'd sigh his Passion in such soft Complaints; </l>
            <l>Courted with such a winning Modesty, </l>
            <l>Even in his Silence reloquent, his words </l>
            <l>So Artfully disorde'd, as might move, </l>
            <l>Devoted Vestals to a living Grave! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e25030">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Your Anger do's him too much Grace; forget him, </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e25060">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Where then is my Revenge? I hear he's charg'd </l>
            <l>With Treason too, and I believe him guilty; </l>
            <l>For false in Love, and false in ev'ry Trust: </l>
            <l>Yet once agen I will repeat my Vow, </l>
            <l>And Heav'n and Earth refuse me if I fail </l>
            <l>To execute the strictest Laws of Honour. </l>
            <l>I'll meet him in spight of my relenting Heart, </l>
            <l>(For inwardly I fear I shall relent) </l>
            <l>Yet I will meet him with a scornful Brow, </l>
            <l>And to his Face disdain him, though I die. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e25180">[Exit. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e25190">Enter Escalus. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e25210">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Hist. Sister. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e25240">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Now, what fresh Discovery, whence those Letters, and </l>
            <l>Of what Concern? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e25280">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>From our imprison'd, discontented Queen; </l>
            <l>Here she solicites me to close afresh </l>
            <l>With her Design; already she has urg'd </l>
            <l>Her Brother of Epirus to revenge </l>
            <l>Th' affront of her Confinement on the King. </l>
            <l>These are t' oblige me to betray the Fort </l>
            <l>Into his Hand, when he by Night arrives, </l>
            <l>And my Reward the Crown. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e25390">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Be not too credulous, </l>
            <l>Nor trust offended Majesty too far. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e25430">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>With caution I'll resolve, in the mean time </l>
            <l>Seem to comply; I'll shun no path to Greatness, </l>
            <l>But wou'd seek it in the Jaws of Death. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e25480">[Exit severally. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000770-e25490">
            <pb n="38" xml:id="ep000770-026-a"/>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e25500">Scene draws. Theocrin with Four or Five Officers from the Siege. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ther" xml:id="ep000770-e25520">
            <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
            <l>Leave me my Friends, and of your Jealousies </l>
            <l>Take leave; the gen'rous King </l>
            <l>Has no dishon'rable Design upon me: </l>
            <l>Some sudden Council of the State requires me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-1off" xml:id="ep000770-e25580">
            <speaker>1. Off. </speaker>
            <l>There is no trust in States-men, and in Courts </l>
            <l>'Tis dang'rous to excell allow our fears, </l>
            <l>We know your worth, and wou'd not see you fall. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e25630">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>Meet I the Death of Cowards, the Renown </l>
            <l>Of my fam'd Ancestors expire in me, </l>
            <l>E'r I grow vain, and trumpet my own Deeds; </l>
            <l>Yet must this King confess, </l>
            <l>That what I have for him perform'd, </l>
            <l>Within the Sylvan Courts of Savage Moors, </l>
            <l>At least wou'd have procur'd me my Lifes safety: </l>
            <l>I've seen a Lion from the Toil set free, </l>
            <l>Yet famisht, as he was, spare his Deliverer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-2off" xml:id="ep000770-e25750">
            <speaker>2. Off. </speaker>
            <l>Shou'd the ungrateful Senate dare to call </l>
            <l>Your Worth in question; we that know how deep </l>
            <l>Your Merit's rooted in your Armies Hearts, </l>
            <l>Shall soon reform the Abuses of the Bench, </l>
            <l>And teach the ermin'd Doatards Justice. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e25820">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>Ha! </l>
            <l>Degen'rate Damocles, how art thou fall'n, </l>
            <l>That Breath has blasted all thy early Glories! </l>
            <l>Beware, brave Youth, the least disloyal thought, </l>
            <l>That like a Canker will destroy thy Lawrel. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-3off" xml:id="ep000770-e25900">
            <speaker>3. Off. </speaker>
            <l>Be not betray'd by your Credulity; </l>
            <l>Your midnight Summons brings no small suspicion! </l>
            <l>The Prince makes open Love to Arviola; </l>
            <l>You know his Fleet rides still within our Bay, </l>
            <l>And on his least Resentment can pour forth </l>
            <l>Their Legions on our Shore; consider then </l>
            <l>How this may work on the defenceless King, </l>
            <l>To sacrifice you to your Rivals Rage. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e26010">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>My safety's grounded on the Eternal Truth </l>
            <l>Of my Arviola; may she desert me, </l>
            <l>When once I prove so mean to fear she will; </l>
            <l>She's constant as the Diamonds standing Light: </l>
            <l>Once more, my Friends, I beg you wou'd retire, </l>
            <pb n="39" xml:id="ep000770-026-b"/>
            <l>And will not be deny'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-4off" xml:id="ep000770-e26100">
            <speaker>4. Off. </speaker>
            <l>We go, but shall be near to watch your Danger. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e26130">[Ex. the Officers. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e26140">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>Spight of my forc'd neglect, a sullen fear </l>
            <l>Intrudes it's terror on me; first it seiz'd </l>
            <l>My Slumber, since pursues my waking Thoughts; </l>
            <l>A mourning Venus stript my verdant Bayes, </l>
            <l>And on my Temples dropt a Cypress Wreath, </l>
            <l>Whil'st weeping Cupids lean'd on slacken'd Bows, </l>
            <l>Shrouding their Faces in their sable Wings. </l>
            <l>Dreams I regard not, but this Vision leaves me </l>
            <l>Gloomy and Dull, as sated Ravishers. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e26270">
              <hi>Theron, Diphilus</hi>, passover the Stage. </stage>
            <l>These Lords once knew me, fawn'd and kiss'd my Knees, </l>
            <l>When from Argaleon's Conquest I return'd, </l>
            <l>And now the Doatards pass neglectfully by! </l>
            <l>But change in States-men is most natural: </l>
            <l>Th'are Weather-cocks of time, and face about </l>
            <l>To ev'ry veering Wind! </l>
            <l>But here comes Myrrhoe, and her I'll seize. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e26380">Enter Myrrhoc. </stage>
            <l>Tell me kind Patroness of all my hopes, </l>
            <l>Thou that hast known my Passions secret growth, </l>
            <l>Brought'st kindly warmth, and hatcht it with thy Beams &#167;. </l>
            <l>How fares my bright Arviola? </l>
            <l>How mindful of her Pining Theocrin? </l>
            <l>How many Sighs has scapt her balmy Lipp? </l>
            <l>(For Myrrhoe I will know Particulars.) </l>
            <l>How many Tears?&#8212; Reserv'd, and silent Ha! </l>
            <l>What means that wrinkled Brow? Dishonour blast me, </l>
            <l>But thou hast struck a Chilness to my Heart, </l>
            <l>A Death-like Cold. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e26540">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Your Pardon Lord, </l>
            <l>I am in haste, on Business to the Prince. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e26580">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>The Prince! Confusion! Business to the Prince? </l>
            <l>What Business bear'st thou to the Prince? Whose Business? </l>
            <l>I know thou wilt not say Arviola's. </l>
            <l>Thou wilt not let me know that killing secret, </l>
            <pb n="40" xml:id="ep000770-027-a"/>
            <l>Tho it were true. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e26660">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>My Lord; I'm no Dissembler, </l>
            <l>When I inform'd you that the Princess lov'd you, </l>
            <l>'Twas true!&#8212; she did&#8212; at present I affirm </l>
            <l>She thinks of you no more. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e26720">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>And that true too! </l>
            <l>Wer't thou an Oracle to tell me this, </l>
            <l>Id slight it as a black malicious lie, </l>
            <l>Tho thunder struck me for the misbelief. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e26780">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Your Lordship's discompos'd, I take my leave. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e26810">[Exit </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e26820">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>Go then, and like a Sorc'ress blast thy Walk, </l>
            <l>How have I prun'd my Fortunes till they bleed, </l>
            <l>To fill this Mercenary's Coffers: </l>
            <l>But this rich Prince's weightier Gold, I find </l>
            <l>Has turn'd the Scale against me; be it so, </l>
            <l>I'll give the World the lie, e'r I supect: </l>
            <l>None but Arviola her self shall e'r </l>
            <l>Perswade me that Arviola is chang'd: </l>
            <l>Here comes this Pageant Prince! Down swelling Blood, </l>
            <l>I must speak to him, and wou'd do't in temper. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e26960">Enter Abardanes, Sossacles. </stage>
            <l>Prince, by your Favour, turn; a Souldier calls. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e26990">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>Ha; who art, that with so bold a freedom </l>
            <l>Retards my haste? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e27030">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>I am one whom thou hast wrong'd, </l>
            <l>Demand'st thou further?&#8212; One whom thou must right; </l>
            <l>Forbear that frown, I wou'd not move thy Passion, </l>
            <l>And wou'd much less that thou should'st wake my Rage: </l>
            <l>As therefore calmly I my Grievance tell, </l>
            <l>Do thou as calmly promise to redress: </l>
            <l>Thou seek'st to rob me of my Valour's Prize, </l>
            <l>My Right by chance of War and Royal Grant, </l>
            <l>My Mistress&#8212; more&#8212; my Bride Arviola. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e27150">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>Ha! Theocrin? stand forth, let me survey thee; </l>
            <l>Dar'st thou, poor Sprout of obscure Growth, presume </l>
            <l>To be ingrafted to the Royal Stock, </l>
            <l>And stain with Peazant Blood the Race of Kings? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e27220">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>Thus far I bear with thee thou barbarous Prince, </l>
            <l>Less disciplin'd then those rough Winter-gusts, </l>
            <pb n="14" xml:id="ep000770-027-b"/>
            <l>That scourge thy barren Clime. This is the Palace, </l>
            <l>The Mansion of the King; the Place protects thee, </l>
            <l>Thou art too vile a Sacrifice to fall </l>
            <l>On Sacred Ground. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e27300">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>Unhand me Sossacles; </l>
            <l>Now thank the Gods that thou art rankt beneath </l>
            <l>A Prince's Vengeance; I forbear thy Life, </l>
            <l>And will not stoop to take the worthless forfeit: </l>
            <l>Thou art hedg'd in with double Infamy; </l>
            <l>For as a Subject I disdain thee much, </l>
            <l>But as a Traytor more. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e27400">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>Blasphemer die. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e27430">[Draws. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000770-e27440">
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e27450">Enter King, <hi>with Guard.</hi>
            </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e27480">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>This Insolence within our Palace Walls? </l>
            <l>Guards seize the Tyger. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e27520">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>O my Lord the King, </l>
            <l>To Heav'n and you I will appeal. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e27560">
            <speaker>King. </speaker>
            <l>Be dumb, </l>
            <l>I'll hear thee nothing till the Bench is sate, </l>
            <l>And then thy Practices shall have fair Tryal. </l>
            <l>Guards he's your Charge. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e27620">[Ex. King and Abard. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e27650">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>Are these then the Rewards of Loyalty? </l>
            <l>To bind these Arms &#12296;&#9674;&#12297; set their Countrey free? </l>
            <l>My Vertue shot too &#12296;&#9674;&#12297;, and shaded all </l>
            <l>The Bramble Courtiers; therefore I must fall </l>
            <l>As one that rob'd 'em of the Royal Beams! </l>
            <l>But Winter Storms will fall again, and then </l>
            <l>They'll wish their Shelter standing&#8212; O my Heart! </l>
            <l>Those Beauties must belong to Arviola! </l>
            <l>Arviola! Hast thou forgot me too. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e27780">Enter Arviola reading. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e27810">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Nor am to blame, </l>
            <l>Y'are so much alter'd now from what you were; </l>
            <l>An Angel fall'n cou'd take no change so fowl. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e27860">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>Yes&#8212; I am fall'n indeed! most strangely alter'd! </l>
            <l>A few days since I triumpht, was proclaim'd </l>
            <l>The States Deliverer; Virgins wreath'd in Flowr's, </l>
            <l>Sung Hymns of Conquest, Insants lisp'd my Praise; </l>
            <pb n="42" xml:id="ep000770-028-a"/>
            <l>The King, the King, smil'd on me, Fortune smil'd, </l>
            <l>Arviola smil'd&#8212; Where's now the dazling Pomp? </l>
            <l>The bright Scene's chang'd, the Heav'nly Dream with-drawn; </l>
            <l>My Flags disperst, and all my Streamers drown'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e27970">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Dispense with me thou nice and rig'rous Honour, </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e28000">[Aside. </stage>
            <l>This Penance is too much for Flesh to bear! </l>
            <l>False as he is, I cannot see his Pain,! </l>
            <l>Yet am condemned to be his Torturer! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e28040">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>Fickle Maid, </l>
            <l>Like Venus thou wer't wont to scatter Joys; </l>
            <l>But now those Eyes have lost their healing Pow'r, </l>
            <l>Shoot Pains, and like Malignant Planets strike! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e28110">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Take on your self the Blame, if I disturb you; </l>
            <l>I wou'd have past in Silence by. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e28150">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>Thou woudl'st not! </l>
            <l>I'll justifie thee, ev'n against thy Self! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e28190">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>To prove what I affirm, I'll leave you now. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e28220">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>Then fickle Maid, thy Love was all a Mock! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e28250">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>The Gods will be my Witnesses, how much </l>
            <l>I priz'd the brave, the valiant Theocrin; </l>
            <l>The Conscious Gods will be my Witnesses, </l>
            <l>How much the Traytor Theocrin I scorn. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e28330">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>Forbear, my Fame, rash Beauty! O take heed </l>
            <l>How thou revild'st a Souldiers Loyalty! </l>
            <l>Least Light'nings fall and singe thee Black as Moors. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e28380">
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>This Conference is our last, and our Discourse </l>
            <l>Has shot too far already&#8212; I have done. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e28420">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>What mute? This silence tortures me beyond </l>
            <l>The sting of Slander; speak, though it be to curse me, </l>
            <l>
              <hi>Arviola! Arviola! Arviola</hi>! </l>
            <l>O deaf as storms, to sinking Mariners! </l>
            <l>Speak, I conjure thee by the spotless Joys </l>
            <l>Of our stol'n Visits! by the friendly Bow'r, </l>
            <l>Whose Shade was conscious to our mid-night Meeting. </l>
            <l>Whil'st from the Jess'mine Roof the Dew distill'd, </l>
            <l>And trickling from thy Brow perfum'd thy Tears! </l>
            <l>Whil'st to correct the Vapours of the Night, </l>
            <l>Officious Loves Celestial Perfumes breath'd, </l>
            <l>And fann'd the Moon-beams, with more shining Wings: </l>
            <l>By all those Nights! and that most friendly Night, </l>
            <l>When to my ravisht Ear you first confest </l>
            <l>Your Love, and shot me through with trembling Joy! </l>
            <l>The Stars flam'd brighter, and the Flow'rs breath'd forth </l>
            <l>A warmer Fragrancy; the gloomy Grove </l>
            <l>Approv'd our Vows, and at our Contract smill'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e28630">
            <pb n="43" xml:id="ep000770-028-b"/>
            <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
            <l>Oh! O! O! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e28660">
            <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
            <l>Relentless still? What shall I say? </l>
            <l>What sad Complaint assume t'extort thy Pity? </l>
            <l>This posture can re-call the offended Gods! </l>
            <l>Hear cruel Princess; 'tis not yet too late! </l>
            <l>One balmy Tear and I am whole!&#8212; </l>
            <l>With-drawing?- Can it be? </l>
            <l>Ha! Wilt thou, can'st thou part and leave me thus </l>
            <l>Grov'ling in Agony!- Turn, turn, at least </l>
            <l>To view my dying Pangs, and glut thy Sight </l>
            <l>With the last Pantings of a broken Heart. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e28780">[Here Arviola seems much discompos'd, but stiffling her Disorder. </stage>
            <l>Ev'n yet thou art not quite with-drawn! turn yet, </l>
            <l>And leave with bleeding Love, the Charity </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e28820">[Ex. Arviola] </stage>
            <l>Of one relenting Sigh!- She's gone! retir'd, </l>
            <l>Vanisht for ever from these closing Eves. </l>
            <l>Come Chaos now! Resume thy horrid Reign; </l>
            <l>Blend Earth with Heav'n, the Elements confound, </l>
            <l>And quench in Seas the fall'n Etherial Fires! </l>
            <l>When Vertu's dead, 'tis time that Nature die; </l>
            <l>Wake Theocrin! forsaken as thou art </l>
            <l>Of all; thy Innocence stays with thee still! </l>
            <l>Guards, to your Office, wreath me o'r in Chains, </l>
            <l>And in the gloomiest Dungeon shroud me fast; </l>
            <l>When this is done, if my escape you fear, </l>
            <l>The Grave's the safest Prison, lodge me there. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e28970">Enter Abardanes, Myrrhoe. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e28990">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>Scarce can I credit what I've heard and seen; </l>
            <l>Approach thou subtl'st of the subtle Sex: </l>
            <l>Say, what Return, what Off'ring shall I make </l>
            <l>To thy immortal Wit&#8212; Sossacles. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e29060">Enter Sossacles with Aribert. </stage>
            <l>The change is wrought, a change more wonderful </l>
            <l>Than of black Chaos into smiling Day. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-soss" xml:id="ep000770-e29110">
            <pb n="44" xml:id="ep000770-029-a"/>
            <speaker>Soss. </speaker>
            <l>Your Servant Aribert, from Thrace arriv'd </l>
            <l>With Letters of Importance. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e29170">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>Souldier welcome! </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e29200">[Opens the Letter and reads. </stage>
            <l>Fly Myrrhoe, foment the Princess rage, </l>
            <l>That no relenting Thought for Theocrin </l>
            <l>Surprize her Breast, and mar the noble Project. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e29260">[Ex. Myrrh. </stage>
            <l>Confusion! Torture! all my hopes are dash'd. </l>
            <l>Read Sossacles, my Royal Father's sick, </l>
            <l>And I am summon'd home to Thrace with speed: </l>
            <l>Aspiring Sythrax waits the Kings last hour, </l>
            <l>To seize the vacant Throne; and they inform me </l>
            <l>Our speediest return can scarce prevent him: </l>
            <l>What shall I do? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-soss" xml:id="ep000770-e29380">
            <speaker>Soss. </speaker>
            <l>Your danger Sir instructs you; </l>
            <l>Your Fleet's in readiness, we'll sail to night. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e29420">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>And leave Arviola?&#8212; </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e29460">Enter Escalus. </stage>
            <l>Now Escalus, </l>
            <l>If thou hast Policy produce it now, </l>
            <l>And make a Prince thy Friend; my Father dies </l>
            <l>And warns me hence, my Brother Sythrax takes </l>
            <l>Advantage of my Absence to Usurp, </l>
            <l>Shall I secure my Crown or Love? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e29560">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Both Sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e29590">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>How my Apollo? O my panting Heart! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e29630">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>The means are obvious; bear Arviola </l>
            <l>By force aboard your Fleet, then sail for Thrace: </l>
            <l>The season gives you opportunity, </l>
            <l>Too morrow she attends the Sacred Rites, </l>
            <l>And Sacrifices at Diana's Grove. </l>
            <l>The Princess early with her Virgin Train, </l>
            <l>Sets forth to finish the preparing Ceremonics, </l>
            <l>Before the Court Arives; then you may seize her, </l>
            <l>For Myrrhoe shall seduce her through the Groves, </l>
            <l>Where you shall plant your Servants to surprize her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e29790">
            <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
            <l>Most exquisite contrivance! </l>
            <l>We'll send immediate notice to our Fleet. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e29830">[Ex. Ab. and Soss. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="ep000770-e29860">
            <pb n="45" xml:id="ep000770-029-b"/>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e29870">Enter Myrrhoe hastily. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e29890">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Where thus confusedly Sister? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myrr" xml:id="ep000770-e29920">
            <speaker>Myrr. </speaker>
            <l>Where's the Prince? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e29950">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>What new Disaster? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e29980">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Theocrin's escap'd. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e30020">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Escap'd! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e30050">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>Rescu'd from the Guards, </l>
            <l>And born with violence from the Town. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e30090">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>By whom? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e30120">
            <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
            <l>'Tis guest by the Offiers, that from the Camp </l>
            <l>Attended him to the Court, for all were Masqu'd, </l>
            <l>Nor trusted to the Evenings Dusk. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e30170">
            <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
            <l>Perdition; </l>
            <l>This happens ill; but Fortune do thy worst, </l>
            <l>My ripe Designs are past the blasting now; </l>
            <l>Sister one day, one busie morrow more </l>
            <l>Crowns out Desires: Retire, and I'll inform you. </l>
            <l>I toil for Empire, now at Scepters fly, </l>
            <l>Resolv'd to force'em or expire; </l>
            <l>And tho I perish in th' attempt, </l>
            <l>Even in the Grave, my Pomp, my Court I'll keep, </l>
            <l>And dream of Crowns in Deaths Eternal Sleep. </l>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e30290">[Ex. </stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="ep000770-e30300">
          <head>ACT. V. </head>
          <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000770-e30320">
            <head>SCENE, <hi>A Desart</hi>. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e30350">Thunder. Enter Theocrin in the Tempest. </stage>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e30370">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>THe Storm is husht, the Winds breath out their last; </l>
              <l>The Thunders too in feebler Volleys die; </l>
              <l>All Night they humour'd my Complaints; but now </l>
              <l>The Day intrudes, the dear Confusion's vanisht, </l>
              <l>And all the ruffled Elements return </l>
              <pb n="46" xml:id="ep000770-030-a"/>
              <l>To their dull Order. Shroud thy hated Light, </l>
              <l>Thou rising Sun, nor summon with such speed, </l>
              <l>Th' o'rlabour'd World to th' Toils of a new day! </l>
              <l>Why flatter'd Mortals, will ye wake to Cares, </l>
              <l>When Sleep in kind Delusion may divert </l>
              <l>Your pensive Minds with pleasing Images. </l>
              <l>A Dream sets free the Captive, can restore </l>
              <l>Lost Fields to Souldiers, and wreckt Merchants Wealth; </l>
              <l>In Dreams the Exile Visits his dear home, </l>
              <l>And o'r the sparkling Bowl relates at large </l>
              <l>His past Distresses to his wond'ring Friends! </l>
              <l>The lover too the sad forsaken Lover, </l>
              <l>May dream and feign the falsest Mistriss true. </l>
              <l>O for a gentle Slumber, that wou'd thus </l>
              <l>Delude my Griefs, and shew my Perjur'd Fair </l>
              <l>Constant as once I thought her&#8212; Oh I rave, </l>
              <l>For Sleep no more must seal these Lids; this Sun </l>
              <l>May set and rise agen to his dull Round, </l>
              <l>But see me tread Life's giddy Maze no more; </l>
              <l>Perform thy work thou deadly Juice&#8212; 'Tis off. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e30640">[Drinks a Viol of Poison. </stage>
              <l>That Death (by Nature so abhor'd) shou'd be </l>
              <l>As easily into our Vitals drawn, </l>
              <l>As th' Air by which we live. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e30680">Enter Four or Five of the Officers. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-1off" xml:id="ep000770-e30690">
              <speaker>1. Off. </speaker>
              <l>I fear his discontent has made him stay, </l>
              <l>Regardless of the Storm that rag'd too Night. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-2off" xml:id="ep000770-e30730">
              <speaker>2 Off. </speaker>
              <l>We left him near these Clifts. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-3off" xml:id="ep000770-e30760">
              <speaker>3. Off. </speaker>
              <l>'Twas </l>
              <l>Rash to trust him with his Griefs alone. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-4off" xml:id="ep000770-e30800">
              <speaker>4. Off. </speaker>
              <l>It was his own Resolve, which we </l>
              <l>Obey'd with much Reluctance&#8212; O ye Gods! </l>
              <l>See where he prostrate lies in the cold Dew, </l>
              <l>With his bare Head expos'd to th' troubled Air. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e30860">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>Tyrant of Nature, I wou'd view thee near, </l>
              <l>Thou Chief of Terrots, Death! a Form so horrid, </l>
              <l>As even the Wretched shun: This brittle Glass </l>
              <l>Contain'd that awful thing; the fatal Juice, </l>
              <l>That turns my working Organs into Clay; </l>
              <l>I' cou'd even now have dasht it on the Ground; </l>
              <l>But let that pass. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-1off" xml:id="ep000770-e30950">
              <speaker>1. Off. </speaker>
              <l>Rise Noble General; </l>
              <l>We cometo seek you in the Armies Name. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e30990">
              <pb n="47" xml:id="ep000770-030-b"/>
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>Nay, now my Friends you are too officious! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-2off" xml:id="ep000770-e31020">
              <speaker>2. Off. </speaker>
              <l>O my dear Lord, I grieve to have found now! </l>
              <l>Why wou'd you dare the Terrors of this Night? </l>
              <l>Such Lightnings, Wind and Rain&#8212; </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e31070">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>Ha Damocles. </l>
              <l>Was't not a merry Night, thou know'st I shou'd </l>
              <l>Have been a Bridgroom now, and therefore 'twas </l>
              <l>The rev'ling Storm struck up to make me Musick; </l>
              <l>The Lightnings danc'd to entertaine me&#8212; True, </l>
              <l>The Bride was absent, and the Bed was cold! </l>
              <l>But 'twas of Natures making, honest Rock, </l>
              <l>O'r-spread with Moss. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-3off" xml:id="ep000770-e31180">
              <speaker>3. Off. </speaker>
              <l>His Griefs I fear distract him. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e31210">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>Hark Damocles, a Secret, O my Boy, </l>
              <l>When I am Earth, remember thou wert warn'd </l>
              <l>To trust no Woman when she smiles, and when </l>
              <l>She weeps believe her less, least when she swears; </l>
              <l>But if she swear thee Love&#8212; Oh Wracks and Pangs! </l>
              <l>Why Sirs d'ye gaze so wildly on me?&#8212; Ha! </l>
              <l>The Poison I perceive has touch'd my Brain! </l>
              <l>Come Damocles, let's talk no more of Women; </l>
              <l>Arms be our Theam, bright Arms&#8212; Arviola! </l>
              <l>Tell me of Arms, my Boy&#8212; Arviola! </l>
              <l>Of Battles, tatter'd Ensigns, bloody Bayes; </l>
              <l>Trophies and Triumphs&#8212; Oh Arviola! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-4off" xml:id="ep000770-e31400">
              <speaker>4. Off. </speaker>
              <l>We must divert this Frensie. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e31430">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>Still they gaze! </l>
              <l>My Senses then are going, let e'm go. </l>
              <l>O that my working Thoughts were once at rest, </l>
              <l>Still as fall'n Stars, or Streams bound up in Frost. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-1off" xml:id="ep000770-e31490">
              <speaker>1. Off. </speaker>
              <l>Your Griefs shall be redrest; the Army waits </l>
              <l>For your Return, resolv'd to force your Right, </l>
              <l>And place you in the Imperial Bed and Throne. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e31540">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>Then you have weighed my Wrongs. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-1off" xml:id="ep000770-e31570">
              <speaker>1. Off. </speaker>
              <l>We have, my Lord, </l>
              <l>And must resent your Suffring as our own. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e31610">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>Swear then to work the Army to my Will. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-1off" xml:id="ep000770-e31640">
              <speaker>1. Off. </speaker>
              <l>We swear. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e31670">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis well; </l>
              <l>Know then 'twill most conduce to my Content, </l>
              <l>That you forget my Abuses from the Court, </l>
              <l>And spight of all my Wrongs be Loyal still! </l>
              <l>Nay Sirs, seem not dissatisfi'd, you've sworn, </l>
              <l>Perform my last Request, for 'tis my last; </l>
              <l>I've taken Poison. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-3off" xml:id="ep000770-e31760">
              <pb n="48" xml:id="ep000770-031-a"/>
              <speaker>3. Off. </speaker>
              <l>Horror! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e31800">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>Infamy! </l>
              <l>What Souldiers Tears, a few hours will reduce </l>
              <l>This shaken Frame to its first Elements; </l>
              <l>Part we like Soldiers without Ceremony: </l>
              <l>I must devote my short remains of Life </l>
              <l>To private Thoughts, and you must leave me all. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-1off" xml:id="ep000770-e31880">
              <speaker>1. Off. </speaker>
              <l>At least permit us wait you to the Grave. </l>
              <l>To sling our pining Lawrels on your Earth, </l>
              <l>And give the Warriour's Volley o'r your Tomb. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e31940">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>I have my self to took care for my Enterment. </l>
              <l>The Hermite's Cave is near, where I'll unload me </l>
              <l>Of this dull Earth; they'll decently bestow </l>
              <l>This Lumber in some Vault by Nature fram'd; </l>
              <l>Wrapt in no Sables, but of deepest Night; </l>
              <l>No Pageantry, or more superfluous Trains </l>
              <l>Of such as mourn for Hire, no Funeral Dirge, </l>
              <l>But what the widdow'd Turtle shall afford me. </l>
              <l>The Pomp that I despis'd in Life, in Death </l>
              <l>I hold most vain; nor care to rot in State. </l>
              <l>Farewel, commend me to our Valiant Troops, </l>
              <l>And as ye wish my Ashes rest, be Loyal. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e32080">[Ex. severally. </stage>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000770-e32090">
            <head>SCENE, <hi>The Hermites Cell</hi>. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e32120">A Tomb discovered, the Hermite's Consecrating it. Edraste in Youths Apparel. </stage>
            <sp who="ep000770-1herm" xml:id="ep000770-e32140">
              <speaker>1. Herm. </speaker>
              <l>Enough, the Tomb is hallow'd; all retire </l>
              <l>To your respective Tasks, your chosen Toil; </l>
              <l>Behold my Son this rude unpolisht Marble, <stage xml:id="ep000770-e32200">(To Edraste. </stage>
              </l>
              <l>The common Receptacle of our Dust, </l>
              <l>When Fate shall summon our Obedient Spirits. </l>
              <l>What Follows Death, the Dead alone can tell; </l>
              <l>But to our Life of Rule and Discipline. </l>
              <l>We owe at least, this certain Priviledge, </l>
              <l>Calmly to wait the change, nor fear to die. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e32280">
              <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
              <l>O peaceful Solituds! </l>
              <l>Here all things smile, and in sweet Consort joyn. </l>
              <pb n="49" xml:id="ep000770-031-b"/>
              <l>All but my Thoughts, that still are out of tune, </l>
              <l>And break, like jarring Strings, the Harmony. </l>
              <l>Why, cruel Theocrin, do'st thou pursue me </l>
              <l>To these Retreats? For still thy Image wounds. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e32370">Enter Theocrin. </stage>
              <l>My panting Breast, and robs me of Repose, </l>
              <l>Tho lodg'd on Poppies by the murmuring Stream. </l>
              <l>Ha! is't the raving of my feaverish Thought </l>
              <l>Or Theocrin's appears! Defend my Heart, </l>
              <l>Some kinder Pow'r, or undeceive my Eyes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e32450">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>I feel the trusty Person by degrees, </l>
              <l>Spread through my yielding Veins, my circling Blood, </l>
              <l>At length, will bear the Cordial to my Heart; </l>
              <l>As nearer to Eternity I coast, </l>
              <l>The Prospect grows more lovely&#8212; Here's the Cave, </l>
              <l>And I descry the Hermites working near; </l>
              <l>The neighb'ring Vale shall be my Walk, </l>
              <l>Till the prevailing Poison summon me </l>
              <l>To turn and yield this Earth to their disposal. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e32560">[Exit. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e32570">
              <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis he! the Royal Bridegroom wand'ring here </l>
              <l>Alone, Bare-headed, and with sorrowful Brow; </l>
              <l>Fortune, I fear, has wrought some dreadful change! </l>
              <l>I'll trust to my Disguise, and follow him; </l>
              <l>My Heart is on the Rack till I'm inform'd. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e32640">[Exit. </stage>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000770-e32650">
            <head>WOOD SCENE agen. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e32680">Arviola, Myrrhoe: Arviola <hi>drest as for the Sacrifice</hi>. </stage>
            <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e32700">
              <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
              <l>Where Myrrhoe, wilt thou and Sorrow lead me? </l>
              <l>This Shade is dark, and silent to my wish, </l>
              <l>Here let me sit and breath my last complaints! </l>
              <l>He was the falsest of the treach'rous Sex; </l>
              <l>The falsest, and as such, my just Revenge </l>
              <l>Disdain'd his Pangs, when groveling at my Feet. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e32790">
              <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
              <l>His Love was feign'd, and so was his Remorse. </l>
              <l>Where are these Ravishers, this was the time </l>
              <l>Design'd for the Adventure, this the place. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e32840">[Aside. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000770-e32850">
              <pb n="50" xml:id="ep000770-032-a"/>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e32860">Enter two Priests in Habits. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e32870">
              <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
              <l>Rise, we are summoned to attend the Altar; </l>
              <l>Speak, have ye sung your Mattins, hail'd the Grove, </l>
              <l>And with the Victim trod the Sacred Round? </l>
              <l>Why stand ye thus fixt on each others Look, </l>
              <l>As ye had some dire Message to deliver, </l>
              <l>Whil'st each declines th' ungrateful Tale; speak forth. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-1priest" xml:id="ep000770-e32950">
              <speaker>1. Priest. </speaker>
              <l>A better Fate attend our Greece, then what </l>
              <l>The Omens of this Morning Rites presage; </l>
              <l>Which of us, has with guilty hands approach'd </l>
              <l>The awful Ceremonies, is unknown; </l>
              <l>But our dread Goddess is displeas'd, </l>
              <l>And thwarts our Work with boding Prodigies. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-myrr" xml:id="ep000770-e33040">
              <speaker>Myrr. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis but the Old Mans Fear, the hallow'd Wine </l>
              <l>Has touch'd his feeble Brain, and makes him rave. </l>
              <l>Shall we retire, yet farther, Madam? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-1priest" xml:id="ep000770-e33090">
              <speaker>1. Priest. </speaker>
              <l>The Virgin Taper thrice I did apply, </l>
              <l>Before the Flame wou'd taste the melting Gums, </l>
              <l>Nor then blaz'd prosperously, erect to Heav'n, </l>
              <l>But scatt'ring, turn'd his conscious folds to Earth, </l>
              <l>And rol'd his smoaky Globes along the Ground. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e33160">
              <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
              <l>These Wizzards will mar all; to lose her thus, </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e33190">[Aside. </stage>
              <l>When I've decoy'd her to the very Ginn. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-2priest" xml:id="ep000770-e33210">
              <speaker>2. Priest. </speaker>
              <l>The destin'd Bull in Garlands wreath'd, stood bound, </l>
              <l>And turn'd his lowring Eyes upon the Attendants; </l>
              <l>Nor sooner had the blushing Wine distain'd </l>
              <l>His snowy Brow, but rearing high in Air, </l>
              <l>He shook the yielding Cords from his curl'd Front, </l>
              <l>O'r-threw the Altar, tost the Golden Pile, </l>
              <l>And forcing through the scatter'd Priests his way, </l>
              <l>Ran with high Nostrils, Bellowing through the Grove. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e33310">
              <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
              <l>Return, and Consecrate the Place anew, </l>
              <l>With mournful Cypress bind your Pensive Brows, </l>
              <l>And prostrate falling on the Sacred Ground, </l>
              <l>Each Vow his Innocence before the Altar; </l>
              <l>Then cast the Lots to find the Osfender out. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e33380">[Ex. Priest. </stage>
              <l>O Virgin Goddess, if this Breast indulge </l>
              <l>One secret Guilt, turn all thy Rage on me, </l>
              <l>And let thy Priestess bleed thy Sacrifice! </l>
              <l>Else let me live with fall'n Edraste's shame; </l>
              <l>My sond Heart, be agen seduc'd to Love. </l>
              <l>Deceiv'd agen&#8212; Assassins, Treason! Help. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000770-e33460">
              <pb n="51" xml:id="ep000770-032-b"/>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e33470">Enter Escalus Masqu'd, with others. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e33490">
              <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
              <l>Seize her, Confederates, seize your Royal Prize. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e33520">
              <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
              <l>Help Heav'n, Rocks, Groves, Diana help! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e33560">
              <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
              <l>Soft, Madam, we are Friends, design no Wrong, </l>
              <l>But come to bear you to a Lover's Arms. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e33600">
              <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
              <l>Off Traytor! Light'ning blast </l>
              <l>Thy Sacrilegious Hands. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e33640">
              <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
              <l>Quick Sirs, convey her to the Prince's Chariot, </l>
              <l>That waits without the Grove, thence to the Fleet; </l>
              <l>And in the Court of Thrace expect her Thanks. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e33700">Enter from the other side Theocrin's Officers. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-4off" xml:id="ep000770-e33720">
              <speaker>4. Off. </speaker>
              <l>The Cry came this way&#8212; See! The Princess seiz'd </l>
              <l>By Ravishers, ev'n in her sacred Robes. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e33760">[Fight. Whil'st they are engag'd, <hi>Arv. Myrrh</hi>. run off, Myrrh. Wounded; the Officers beat the others off. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-2off" xml:id="ep000770-e33790">
              <speaker>2. Off. </speaker>
              <l>The Fiends are Vanisht; where's the Princess? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-3off" xml:id="ep000770-e33820">
              <speaker>3. Off. </speaker>
              <l>Fled off in Fight. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-2off" xml:id="ep000770-e33850">
              <speaker>2. Off. </speaker>
              <l>Disperse we strait; you Damocles return </l>
              <l>To the General, and inform him what has happened; </l>
              <l>You Phorbus to the King, the rest search for the Princess: </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e33920">[Ex. </stage>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e33930">Re-enter Escalus unmasqu'd. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e33950">
              <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
              <l>Curse on the Coward Slaves, they fought like Women; </l>
              <l>Not Wolves more tamely wou'd resign their Prey </l>
              <l>To Lion: How shall I excuse </l>
              <l>This soul Defeat, to the expecting Prince? </l>
              <l>The Prince? Hell! that's the least Difficulty: </l>
              <l>How shall I answer to the King this Treason? </l>
              <l>Hard-hunted, as I am, I've one shift yet, </l>
              <l>And that a sure one: I'll with speed inform </l>
              <l>The King, of this Design to seize Arviola: </l>
              <l>Charge all the Guilt upon the Prince, pretend </l>
              <l>The Plot was frustrated by my Contrivance; </l>
              <l>Then when the Intelligence comes, the King </l>
              <l>Shall thank me for my Villany, perhaps </l>
              <pb n="52" xml:id="ep000770-033-a"/>
              <l>Reward me too; thus cautious Sailers quit </l>
              <l>The sinking Ship, and rowing off to shore, </l>
              <l>Enrich themselves with the wreck'd Merchants Wealth. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e34140">[Exit </stage>
            </sp>
            <list>
              <item>Theocrin and Edraste. </item>
            </list>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e34180">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>Leave me fond Youth, why wilt thou follow me? </l>
              <l>I'm Savage as a Sylvan, and unfit </l>
              <l>For thy soft Conversation; prethee leave me! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e34240">
              <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
              <l>Forgive a Strangers Rudeness, Sir, excuse </l>
              <l>A charitable Crime; say you are happy, </l>
              <l>And for some pleasing Contemplation seek </l>
              <l>This Solitude; convince me with a smile </l>
              <l>And I'll retire. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e34310">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>Believe me happy then </l>
              <l>And leave me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e34350">
              <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
              <l>Wherefore then that troubled Sigh? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e34380">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>Pretty Impertinence, no more Inquiries; </l>
              <l>But since thy Curiosity is such, </l>
              <l>Know I am wretched to that sad degree, </l>
              <l>That Fiends might pitty me, and therefore leave me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e34440">
              <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
              <l>'Tis therefore I woud follow. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e34470">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>Thou are Young, </l>
              <l>And Grief's infectious; get thee to Court, and revel out thy Youth; Sorrow will come </l>
              <l>Unsought, and poyson thy Delights too soon. </l>
              <l>Besides, thou'rt Beautiful and form'd for Dalliance, </l>
              <l>Therefore to Court, there practice ev'ry Wile </l>
              <l>To charm the Fair; none scape thy Flattery; </l>
              <l>But Youth take heed that it be Flattery. </l>
              <l>For should'st thou be sincere in thy Addresses, </l>
              <l>Give up thy Heart, and trust thy Happiness </l>
              <l>To a Woman's Mercy, thou'rt lost for ever. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e34590">
              <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
              <l>Then all all my Fears are just, and Destiny </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e34620">[Aside. </stage>
              <l>Has play'd most fowl; </l>
              <l>Arviola is chang'd, or he abus'd. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e34660">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>Thou weep'd! What mean those Tears, I did but speak. </l>
              <l>Of disappointed Love, and thou art touch'd! </l>
              <l>Is't possible that thy soft Innocence, </l>
              <l>So early, shou'd be Martyr'd by the scorn </l>
              <l>Of any cruel she! </l>
              <l>Then I am still to learn in Woman's Falshood; </l>
              <l>And my fair Cous'ner yet may be a Saint, </l>
              <pb n="53" xml:id="ep000770-033-b"/>
              <l>Compar'd to the rest of her deluded Sex. </l>
              <l>Yes, false Arviola, when I descend, </l>
              <l>And to the lower World report my Love, </l>
              <l>I'll do thy Fame the Right, to say, </l>
              <l>There was one more inhumane Maid than thou! </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e34810">Enter Damocles. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-dam" xml:id="ep000770-e34830">
              <speaker>Dam. </speaker>
              <l>Your Pardon, my best Lord, that I trangress </l>
              <l>Your last Commands, the occasion is surprizing; </l>
              <l>Your fair Arviola, with her Maiden Train, </l>
              <l>This Morning came to attend the Annual Rites </l>
              <l>Of Great Diana's Altar in the Grove: </l>
              <l>On our Return we found the Princess seiz'd </l>
              <l>By Rusfians, whom we soon o'rcome, </l>
              <l>But lost her in the hurry of the Fight&#8212; </l>
              <l>Behold, my Lord, three of their scatter'd Crew </l>
              <l>Flying this way. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e34970">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>False, tho she be, yet some Revenge is due </l>
              <l>To injur'd Beauty and a Princess Name. </l>
              <l>Stand Traytors. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e35020">[Fight. The Assassins are Slain, Edraste Wounded. </stage>
              <l>How fares my gentle Boy. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e35060">
              <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
              <l>The friendly Steel </l>
              <l>Has pierc'd my aking Heart, and giv'n me ease. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e35100">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>Ha! Wounded! We have bought the Villains Lives </l>
              <l>Too dear; help Damocles </l>
              <l>Yo bear him to the Cell. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e35160">[Ex. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000770-e35170">
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e35180">Enter King Attended, <hi>Esc. Ther. Diph. </hi>Priests brought in by the Guards. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e35210">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Disperse and search each Thicket of the Forrest; </l>
              <l>And as your for feit Heads shall answer for't, </l>
              <l>Return not to our Presence till y'ave found her. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e35260">[Ex. Attend, </stage>
              <l>Stand forth, ye reverend Hypocrites, confess </l>
              <l>When, where, for what you barter'd, to betray </l>
              <l>Your Monarch's Daughter? Hell! I am too cold! </l>
              <l>Produce her Traytors, set her in my Sight, </l>
              <l>Restore her to my Arms this minute, or </l>
              <l>Your pamper'd Flesh shall on the Rack be torn, </l>
              <pb n="54" xml:id="ep000770-034-a"/>
              <l>And scatter'd piece-meal on this hallow'd Ground. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e35340">
              <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
              <l>This is the Musick that I long'd to hear; </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e35370">[Aside. </stage>
              <l>King, y'are too tame, rage louder yet; Ha! Ha! </l>
              <l>How vain a Creature were the plotting Knave, </l>
              <l>But for the credulous Fool? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e35410">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Slaves, must I twice command, e'r I am answer'd? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-2priest" xml:id="ep000770-e35440">
              <speaker>2. Priest. </speaker>
              <l>By all the Pow'rs, by Great Diana's Self, </l>
              <l>And your own Sacred Head, we are innocent. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e35490">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>They sport with my Revenge, quick, drag'em hence </l>
              <l>To present Death; nor shall th' ingrateful Prince </l>
              <l>Our Vengeance shun: he comes, make ready Guards </l>
              <l>To seize him, he shall bleed. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-ther" xml:id="ep000770-e35550">
              <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
              <l>Dread Sir, consider. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e35580">Enter Abardanes, speaking to his Attendants. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e35600">
              <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
              <l>O'r-powr'd? Excuse it not, 'twas Cowardise; </l>
              <l>Retire, I must to the King, least he suspect. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e35640">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Disarm him. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e35670">
              <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
              <l>I am betray'd, </l>
              <l>Basely you have surpriz'd us; give me room, </l>
              <l>Slaves know the Prince, nor with your Vassal Hands </l>
              <l>Profane my Royalty&#8212; What! Servile Chains! </l>
              <l>I'll not endur't. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e35740">
              <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
              <l>Now the Chast Lion foams. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e35770">
              <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
              <l>I charge thee King release me, by thy Sceptre, </l>
              <l>Thy Head, thy Empire, which my Thracian Troops </l>
              <l>Shall drown in Blood, and waste with Vengeful Fire. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e35830">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>We dare thy worst, ingrateful, barb'rous Prince, </l>
              <l>That could'st abuse our Hospitality, </l>
              <l>And plot a Rape upon a Royal Maid. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-ab" xml:id="ep000770-e35880">
              <speaker>Ab. </speaker>
              <l>Why then did she not Love? What I design'd </l>
              <l>Was gen'rous all; and thou should'st thank me, King, </l>
              <l>That of thy Dignity I took such care, </l>
              <l>Fo force thy Daughter to my Princely Arms, </l>
              <l>That on a Vassal else, a Subject Slave, </l>
              <l>Had lost her Crown and Beauty; and corrupted </l>
              <l>Th' untainted Blood of Monarchs! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e35970">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Bear him off; </l>
              <l>Come to my Heart, thou faithful Escaellus; </l>
              <l>With what Return shall I reward thy Vertue! </l>
              <l>Our Army we commit to thy Command, </l>
              <l>Be thou our Gen'ral in false Theocrin's stead, </l>
              <l>And meet the shock of War, this Prince has threaten'd. </l>
              <pb n="55" xml:id="ep000770-034-b"/>
              <l>Whom bring ye there? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-diphatt" xml:id="ep000770-e36080">
              <speaker>Diph. Att. </speaker>
              <l>Dread Sir, A Forrester, </l>
              <l>That says, he saw but now a Lady fly </l>
              <l>In fright to the Hermite's Cave. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e36130">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>'Twas my Arviola, lead thither. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e36170">[Ex. All. </stage>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div type="scene" xml:id="ep000770-e36180">
            <head>The CAVE. </head>
            <stage xml:id="ep000770-e36210">Theocrin and Damocles <hi>bearing in </hi>Edraste. </stage>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e36240">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>Now Damocles Fly and call the Hermites in, </l>
              <l>Their Art will bring Relief; take Heart, my Boy. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e36290">
              <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
              <l>I Die, my Lord, and with my latest Breath </l>
              <l>Will speak of Wonders; now my Stars are kind, </l>
              <l>And for my past Griefs make too large Amends, </l>
              <l>Since in your dear Embrace I do expire; </l>
              <l>I am Edraste. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e36370">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>This indeed is wond'rous. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-edr" xml:id="ep000770-e36400">
              <speaker>Edr. </speaker>
              <l>Deaths Paleness will forbid my Blushes now; </l>
              <l>If I confess that I have lov'd you long, </l>
              <l>But with a Flame as Chaste as Vestal Fire; </l>
              <l>Or may no Pious Garland crown my Tomb, </l>
              <l>But Virgins shun it as unhallow'd Ground. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e36470">Enter Arviola in Fright. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e36490">
              <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
              <l>Where shall I hide? O for an Earthquake now </l>
              <l>To sink me from these Ravishers&#8212; Whos's there? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e36530">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>Speak my Edraste, end thy charming Tale, </l>
              <l>For I wou'd Die convinc'd, there can be Truth </l>
              <l>In Woman's Love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e36590">
              <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
              <l>Edraste in Disguise with Theocrin, </l>
              <l>In close Embraces joyn'd! My Eyes too long </l>
              <l>Are guilty, but the sacred Ponyard thus </l>
              <l>Shall expiate the Offence; Eternal Night </l>
              <l>Remove the hated Object from my view. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e36680">[Stabs her self. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e36690">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>She's gone, and in her Cheeks </l>
              <l>A scatter'd Purple smi'es, </l>
              <l>Like streaks of Sun-shine from a Setting Day: </l>
              <l>My Fate comes next, the sure-slow Poison now </l>
              <l>Preys on my Vitals- Ha! what Heavenly Form </l>
              <l>Sits there? Bright Vision turn&#8212; Arviola! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e36780">
              <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
              <l>O Gods, those ruffled Locks, and that wan Look, </l>
              <pb n="56" xml:id="ep000770-035-a"/>
              <l>Against my Honour plead in his behalf; </l>
              <l>But 'tis a Woman's Weakness, and I'll crush it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e36830">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>It cannot be! Not Woman's Cruelty </l>
              <l>Can swell to that Excess, to persecute </l>
              <l>Her poor forsaken Lover to his Cave; </l>
              <l>To tear his closing Wounds, and wake </l>
              <l>His slumb'ring Griefs into a fresh Despair. </l>
              <l>Is this the tenderness of Beauty, this </l>
              <l>The Weeping Sexe's Mercy? Oh! Arviola! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e36930">
              <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
              <l>With what divided Passions am I torn! </l>
              <l>Stream faster sluggish Blood and give me ease! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e36970">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>That so contemn'd a Thing as I, shou'd e'r </l>
              <l>Create your Highness Trouble, were unjust; </l>
              <l>But Princess you'll excuse me: that I lov'd you, </l>
              <l>I do confess, but wore my Flames conceal'd </l>
              <l>And silent, as the Lamps that burn in Tombs, </l>
              <l>Sigh'd only to my self and to the Winds, </l>
              <l>Gaz'd on your Beauties with the distant Crowd: </l>
              <l>Your self at last perceiv'd my drooping care, </l>
              <l>And forc'd the trembling Secret from my Breast, </l>
              <l>Which with my Life I render'd at your Feet: </l>
              <l>Then&#8212; I remember&#8212; Oh! the panting Minute&#8212; </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e37100">
              <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
              <l>That panting Minute I remember too! </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e37130">[Aside. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e37140">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>You rais'd me by the bloodless Hand from Ground, </l>
              <l>With such obliging Tenderness, secur'd </l>
              <l>My trembling Hopes, that next I sunk with joy! </l>
              <l>But (Oh the Torture!) this transporting Scene </l>
              <l>Was but a gawdy Dream, and wak'd with Storms, </l>
              <l>Here on cold Earth the flatter'd Dreamer lies. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e37220">
              <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
              <l>Tempt not the Gods too far, those Gods that know </l>
              <l>The Falseness of your Love: yet O thrice Happy, </l>
              <l>If here your Crimes had fixt, but to Corrupt </l>
              <l>A Royal Maid&#8212; The fowl Thought strikes me Dumb, </l>
              <l>I leave your Guilt t' interpret&#8212; Oh Edraste! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e37300">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>Take heed, Licencious Fair! Thy perjur'd Love </l>
              <l>Was but thy Sexe's Sin, a Crime of Nature, </l>
              <l>But to Blaspheme the Vertue of the Dead, </l>
              <l>Will wrest from the forbearing Gods their Thunder. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e37360">
              <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
              <l>Ha! Dead! Each Minute draws fresh Wonders on. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e37390">Enter Myrrhoc Bloody. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e37410">
              <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
              <l>The Princess must perceive that I betray'd her, </l>
              <l>Perhaps this Cave will hide me from the Search. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e37450">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>Hast Thou too brought thy Raven's Note t'afflict me? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e37480">
              <pb n="57" xml:id="ep000770-035-b"/>
              <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
              <l>Gods! Theocrin Pale! Arviola Bloody, and Edraste Dead; </l>
              <l>Then Furies lash me with your Scorpion Whips; </l>
              <l>Give me the Torments of th' Etornal Damn'd, </l>
              <l>
                <hi>Prometheus, Vulture</hi>, and Ixion's Wheel. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e37590">
              <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
              <l>Alas, what mean those dreadful Execrations? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e37620">
              <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
              <l>My Breath grows short, but shall suffice t' unfold </l>
              <l>Such Treasons, as will fright the Dephts of Hell, </l>
              <l>For whil'st the Plotting Escalus accus'd </l>
              <l>This gen'rous Lord of Treason to the King, </l>
              <l>As falsely I abus'd his Love to you; </l>
              <l>Taxt him of wanton Dalliance with Edraste, </l>
              <l>Who from the Court retreated, to divert </l>
              <l>Th' Ambitious Queens Designs on both your Lives: </l>
              <l>Thus were you wrought to treat him with Disdain, </l>
              <l>At his return from Field. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e37760">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>The Truth, the Truth as thou shalt meet the Gods. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e37790">
              <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
              <l>For thy Souls sake, the Truth and I forgive thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-myr" xml:id="ep000770-e37820">
              <speaker>Myr. </speaker>
              <l>At fast, Brib d by the Prince, I undertook </l>
              <l>To tempt you through the Groves, till the Assassins </l>
              <l>Might seize and bear you to the Thracian Fleet; </l>
              <l>But (unexpectedly engag'd) i'th' Fight </l>
              <l>I met th' unluckly Wound that gives me Death, </l>
              <l>By the dar Pow'rs that wait for my Descent. </l>
              <l>This is most true, as true as I was false, </l>
              <l>Or let my Pains, through circling Ages last, </l>
              <l>Nor Time expiring, see my Torments done. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e37950">[Dies. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000770-e37960">
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e37970">Theo. and Arv. attempt to Rise, but (wanting Strength) on their Hands and Knees, get to each other. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e38000">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>O bounteous Pow'rs! O balmy healing Joy! </l>
              <l>Pride of thy Sex, Imperial Excellence, </l>
              <l>My still Beloved, still Loving, True Arviola. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e38060">
              <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
              <l>Can you forgive my Lord my rash Disdain? </l>
              <l>You must, for I was punish'd in the Crime, </l>
              <l>Ev'n then (cou'd you have seen my Heart) </l>
              <l>You wou'd confess that your Arviola </l>
              <l>Was ne'r so passionate kind. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e38140">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>Let me in haste&#8212; </l>
              <l>Devour those Sweets, and load me with thy Bloom, </l>
              <l>A Stock to feed on in Eternity. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e38190">
              <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
              <l>O that some pittying God wou'd six us thus </l>
              <l>(To solid Marble turn'd) Eternal Statues, </l>
              <l>Whil'st Pious Lovers flock from farthest Lands, </l>
              <l>To hear the wond'rous Chances of our Loves, </l>
              <l>And thence be taught whate'r Disasters fall, </l>
              <pb n="58" xml:id="ep000770-036-a"/>
              <l>Ne'r to despair of Passion that is true. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e38270">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>My Feeling fails, but ah what purple Dew </l>
              <l>Distains this Hand that prest thy panting Heart? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e38310">
              <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
              <l>Thank the Good Gods, 'tis my Life-Blood, my Lord, </l>
              <l>I saint; my Theocrin, but one thing more </l>
              <l>Tell me, if we shall love i'th' other World? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e38370">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>'Twill be our Business, 'tis the Land of Love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e38400">
              <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
              <l>And without Jealousie. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e38430">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>Their Paradise knows no such poisonous Weed; </l>
              <l>Their Loves are as their Streams, full, calm, and clear! </l>
              <l>Secure and free they pass their harmless hours, </l>
              <l>Gay as the Birds that revel in the Groves, </l>
              <l>And sing the Morning up. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-arv" xml:id="ep000770-e38500">
              <speaker>Arv. </speaker>
              <l>Farewel. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-theo" xml:id="ep000770-e38530">
              <speaker>Theo. </speaker>
              <l>She's gone! </l>
              <l>And charms me after. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e38570">[Dies Both. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000770-e38580">
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e38590">Enter <hi>Theron, Diphilus</hi>, Guards, Attendants, Hermite, King and Escalus, in the middle of Train. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-ther" xml:id="ep000770-e38630">
              <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
              <l>Confusion! Diphilus see the Princess slain in Theocrin's Arms, more bloodless Corpses too, </l>
              <l>To fill the ghastly Scene&#8212; Dread Sir, Retire; </l>
              <l>Such Horror fills this Cave, as will congeal </l>
              <l>Your Aged Blood, and blast your Royal Sight. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e38710">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Why do your Knees prevent me; sink in Earth </l>
              <l>And give Passage: Where's the Goblin now </l>
              <l>That should appall me? Ha! My Arviola dead. </l>
              <l>And in the Traytor's Arms! </l>
              <l>Fate thou hast struck me home, but struck thy last. </l>
              <l>Here fell my only Comfort, only Care. </l>
              <l>Haste, set the Prince at large. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e38810">
              <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
              <l>'Twas my sole fear, least Myrrhoe should discover, </l>
              <l>And Death has ty'd her Tongue; there's that breach stopt. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e38860">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Rob'd of my Heirs; be all my Witnesses </l>
              <l>How timely for my Empire I provide; </l>
              <l>Behold this Man of Worth, and know him all </l>
              <l>For our Adopted Son and Heir of Greece; </l>
              <l>Bow all to Earth and do him present Homage. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e38940">[Presenting Escalus. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e38960">
              <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
              <l>Thus, gracious Sir, thus prostrate at your Feet, </l>
              <l>Your Vassal begs you to revoke your Favour; </l>
              <l>I am th' unworthiest&#8212; </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e39010">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>Rise, our Pleasure's sixt, Slaves is our Will disputed. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-all" xml:id="ep000770-e39040">
              <speaker>All. </speaker>
              <l>Hail Heir of Greece, Hail Royal Escalus. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e39090">[Enter Messenger with Letters. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-diph" xml:id="ep000770-e39100">
              <speaker>Diph. </speaker>
              <l>Way there, a Message to the King. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e39130">
              <pb n="59" xml:id="ep000770-036-b"/>
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>What bring'st thou? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-mess" xml:id="ep000770-e39160">
              <speaker>Mess. </speaker>
              <l>Great Sir, your Queen disdaining her Confinement, </l>
              <l>Took Poison, but enjoyn'd me e'r she dy'd, </l>
              <l>To bear these Papers to your Royal Hand. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e39210">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>O Dephs of Villany! Guards seize that Fiend. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e39240">[Pointing to Esc. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e39260">
              <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
              <l>What means my gracious Lord. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e39290">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>See here, my Lords, what will amaze you too! </l>
              <l>Our Empress, by that Escalus detected, </l>
              <l>Liv'd but to take Revenge on the Discoverer; </l>
              <l>And to effect it, made pretence of Forces, </l>
              <l>Rais'd by her Brother to invade this Empire, </l>
              <l>Which this Designing Lord was to command, </l>
              <l>And these his Letters in Return; where he </l>
              <l>Accepts her Terms! To Death with the Impostor. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-esc" xml:id="ep000770-e39400">
              <speaker>Esc. </speaker>
              <l>That Breath that doom'd me be thy last, weak Monarch; </l>
              <l>But King, know thou, and these (but now) my Slaves, </l>
              <l>That for that minutes Pride, that single Taste </l>
              <l>Of Royal Pow'r, for that one Hail, I'd meet </l>
              <l>The worst of Deaths thy feeble Rage can form. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e39470">[Ex. Born off by the Guards. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e39480">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>My Lord, I trust your Care to see just Rites </l>
              <l>Perform'd to these dead Bodies; my next charge </l>
              <l>(And that my last) is, that you summon streight </l>
              <l>Our Senate, and by fair Election crown </l>
              <l>Our Successor; for my own private part </l>
              <l>I have determin'd what the Gods inspire: </l>
              <l>Reach me a Hermite's Habit. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-ther" xml:id="ep000770-e39570">
              <speaker>Ther. </speaker>
              <l>Now I find </l>
              <l>His rash Resolve, but durst not interpose. </l>
              <stage xml:id="ep000770-e39610">[King kneeling, takes a Hermites Vestment in his hand kisses, then shifting his Robes of State, puts it on. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp who="ep000770-king" xml:id="ep000770-e39620">
              <speaker>King. </speaker>
              <l>How light sits this! And thus have I put off, </l>
              <l>With the Imperial Robes, Imperial Cares. </l>
              <l>Thus after all my Storms of Court, I make </l>
              <l>My last Retreat to the Gods and Poverty. </l>
              <l>Here as the Sanctions of this Cell, shall bind </l>
              <l>By turns, I'll wait, and in my Course be King. </l>
              <l>Here Lust wants Fewel, and Ambition starves, </l>
              <l>My temper'd Appetites shall here be taught, </l>
              <l>T'ask Council of my Reason e'r they crave: </l>
              <l>Here just but temperate Meals, short Sleeps and sound, </l>
              <l>Shall cheer me for the Labours of the Day: </l>
              <l>Thus Life's well manag'd Remant will I spend, </l>
              <l>And when the Gods shall lease, resign my Breath </l>
              <l>Calmly, as Infants sleep, and smile on Death. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="epilogue" xml:id="ep000770-e39800">
        <pb xml:id="ep000770-037-a"/>
        <head>EPILOGUE, Spoken by Mrs. Currer. </head>
        <l>YOUR humble Servant Gentlemen&#8212; How d'ye, </l>
        <l>I' faith I've broke my Prison Walls to see ye; </l>
        <l>Must I he cloyster'd up? Dull Poet stay, </l>
        <l>I hate Consinement tho' but in a Play. </l>
        <l>Doom me to a Nun's Life?&#8212; A Nun! Oh Heart! </l>
        <l>The Name's so dreadful, that it makes me start! </l>
        <l>No! Tell the Scribbling Fool I'm just as sit </l>
        <l>To make a Nun as he to make a Wit. </l>
        <l>What? A-la-mort Messieurs? Nay then I'll sit ye </l>
        <l>Adieu! I' faith no Epilogue for Betty! </l>
        <l>And yet, shame on my Foolish Womans Heart, </l>
        <l>I fain wou'd see ye smile before we part. </l>
        <l>You know how oft, like preaching Sisters, we </l>
        <l>Have from the Stage Lectur'd your Vanity; </l>
        <l>Yet like those Sisters, out o' th' Preaching Mood, </l>
        <l>You have surpriz'd and found us Flesh and Blood! </l>
        <l>Well, if your stubborn Hearts will not dissolve, </l>
        <l>Prepare to hear our fatal last Resolve; </l>
        <l>Since Sense has broke us, henceforth shall be shown </l>
        <l>The Feats of <hi>Robbin Hood </hi>and <hi>Little John</hi>, </l>
        <l>With the thrice fam'd Exploits of Whittington! </l>
        <l>&#12296;&#9674;&#12297; Vergers then in your lewd steads shall sit, </l>
        <l>A &#12296;&#9674;&#12297; and Scarlet Audience crowd our Pit. </l>
        <l>&#12296;&#9674;&#12297; like your Misses, we are forc'd to quit ye, </l>
        <l>And make our last Dependance on the City. </l>
        <pb xml:id="ep000770-037-b"/>
      </div>
      <div type="supplied_by_editor">
        <head>Notes, typically marginal, from the original text</head>
        <div corresp="A62967-e110" xml:id="ep000770-e110-n">
          <head>Notes for div A62967-e110</head>
        </div>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
