<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000824" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The fancies theater· By Iohn Tatham Gent</title>
        <author>
<!--Tatham, John-->
          <persName>
            <forename>John</forename>
            <surname>Tatham</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A13393.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <p>
            This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is available for reuse, according to the terms of
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>
            . The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
          </p>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull>
              <titleStmt>
                <title>The fancies theater· By Iohn Tatham Gent</title>
                <author>Tatham, John, fl. 1632-1664.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[162] p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Printed by Iohn Norton, for Richard Best, and are to be sold at his shop neere Grayes-Inne-gate in Holborne,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                <date>1640.</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>In verse.</note>
                <note>Signatures: * (-*1) A⁴ B-E F⁴ G-K L² .</note>
                <note>"Love crownes the end" has separate dated title page; register is continuous.</note>
                <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc/>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="1640">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <group>
      <text>
        <front>
          <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000824-e30">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-001-a"/>
            <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000824-001-b"/>
            <p>THE FANCIES THEATER. </p>
            <p>BY IOHN TATHAM Gent. </p>
            <q>
              <bibl>HORAT </bibl>
              <l>Quòd si me Lyricis vatibus inseris, </l>
              <l>Sublimi feriam sidera vertice. </l>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by IOHN NORTON, for RICHARD BEST, and are to be sold at his Shop neere Grayes-Inne-gate in Holborne. 1640. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000824-e140">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-002-a"/>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-002-b"/>
            <head>TO THE HONORABLE AND THE MOST WORTHY MECAENAS, SIR John Winter Knight, Secretary of State, and Master of Requests to the Queenes most excellent Majestie. </head>
            <opener>
              <salute>HONOR'D SIR, </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe confidence I have of your Native goodnesse (of which the World is sufficient Dilater) has prompt mee to this audacious presumption, which with <pb xml:id="ep000824-003-a"/>some would have beene held a crime insufferable. But I know your Honor is so farre from a Censurer, that you had rather cherish endeavours then destroy 'em: Besides, there's a certaine Sect of selfe-affecters, that will (unlesse some judicious Patron be fixt to the fronts-peece, as the beames of the Sunne, to correct their sawsie peering, with blindnesse) not only disgorge their Envie, but wrest the sense to be succinct; I (knowing your Name to be such, as amongst the discerning Spirits deserves the highest Attributes of worth; and of such singular power, 'twill extirp the Malevolent thoughts that raigne in the vulgar and most infectious Traducers) tender this, as my first Sacrifice, at the Altar <pb xml:id="ep000824-003-b"/>of your mercy. And if it may obtaine the reflection of your acceptance, 'twill so much encourage your poore Admirer, that I shall be Ambitious in the continuance of your favours: These are the Mayden-blosomes of my Muse, which (without your protection) may (in their infancie) be destroyed by the breath of Zoïlus; but shelter'd by your Honor, they shall live, and dare the Criticks rancour, retorting to their owne shame. Sir, the fostering this Orphan will make you famous for Charity, and impose an obligation beyond expression, upon </p>
            <closer>
              <signed>Your Honors truly devoted, JO. TATHAM. </signed>
            </closer>
          </div>
          <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000824-e220">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-004-a"/>
            <head>To the honor'd Patron of his Book. </head>
            <opener>
              <salute>SIR, </salute>
            </opener>
            <l>AS my service binds me and my love, </l>
            <l>(May your faire selfe so of the same approve) </l>
            <l>As your deservings, I have plac'd you here </l>
            <l>Equall with Phoebus in his Hemisphere, </l>
            <l>Where your refulgent brightnesse cast's a light </l>
            <l>Into these twinkling Lamps, and give's them sight. </l>
            <l>Minerva bad me tell you she is proud </l>
            <l>Of those deserts which in your brest doe crowd </l>
            <l>As in a throng, which our capacity </l>
            <l>Not able to finde out, leave's to her eye. </l>
            <l>Thrice worthy Hero, may your Halcion dayes </l>
            <l>Be ne're extinct till crazie Time decayes. </l>
            <closer>
              <signed>Jo. Tatham. </signed>
            </closer>
          </div>
          <div type="to_the_reader" xml:id="ep000824-e440">
            <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000824-004-b"/>
            <head>Fancie, to the Reader. </head>
            <l>REaders of all sorts, when you have survai'd </l>
            <l>Each roome within this Theater, and paid </l>
            <l>Sufficient for admittance, you'l allow </l>
            <l>To render me account of all, and how </l>
            <l>You like the fabrick, if it be well rear'd; </l>
            <l>The thought of falling is not to be fear'd, </l>
            <l>Though he that did erect it, has not serv'd </l>
            <l>Seaven yeares to the Profession, nor deserv'd </l>
            <l>The Attribute of Architect, yet hee </l>
            <l>Expects by your faire hands to be made free; </l>
            <l>Hee'l then set up in th' Citie, and in spight </l>
            <l>Of Suburb power, or Corporation's might: </l>
            <l>Vse his best skill to please you. Faith, be just, </l>
            <l>Doe not enscale his Freedome with the aust, </l>
            <l>Hee's prest t' obey you howsoe're, and will </l>
            <l>Without a grumble, serve you, and fulfill </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-005-a"/>
            <l>Forsooth, your precepts being prest so lowe, </l>
            <l>I hope you'l raise him, Char'ty teacheth so: </l>
            <l>Yet, hee'l not begge your favours, to assist </l>
            <l>Him, by Certificate, doe what you list; </l>
            <l>He knowes the worst on't, if you doe refuse, </l>
            <l>'Tis but the having (to the Hall) his Muse </l>
            <l>To have the gentle notch; and so to try </l>
            <l>If hee in time can gaine the Mystery; </l>
            <l>Hee sweares he will defie you, when that hee </l>
            <l>Atchives to th' Warden of the Company. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000824-e760">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-005-b"/>
            <head>To his friend the Author on his Fancies Theater. </head>
            <l>FAncie, in all his Colours ne're appear'd </l>
            <l>So variously delightfull, as in this </l>
            <l>Magnificent Theater, which thou hast rear'd </l>
            <l>Out of thy <hi>Genuine braine</hi>, and call'st it His. </l>
            <l>Here does he take all shapes, and act all parts; </l>
            <l>The noble Hero, and the humble Swaine; </l>
            <l>The jocund Lovers, and lamenting hearts. </l>
            <l>As well the Buskind, as the Comick straine. </l>
            <l>Fancie has something here for every one, </l>
            <l>From Reveller to Mourner; still provided, </l>
            <l>Each brings a proper apprehension; </l>
            <l>And one not by anothers humor guided. </l>
            <l>But let all come and welcome: The severe </l>
            <l>Cato himselfe may have free entrance here. </l>
            <closer>
              <signed>R. Broome. </signed>
            </closer>
          </div>
          <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000824-e1040">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-006-a"/>
            <head>To his friend the Author, on his ingenious Theater of Fancies. </head>
            <l>A Theater is built, and every part </l>
            <l>Order'd with various Workmanship and Art, </l>
            <l>The Sceanes with Protean transformation move, </l>
            <l>Presenting Buskins, Socks, and Themes of love: </l>
            <l>A Mourners teares, and joy of a faire Bride; </l>
            <l>Smart Satyre, and a world of change beside. </l>
            <l>'Tis not the Building only Men should see, </l>
            <l>But what's prepar'd for Action in't by thee. </l>
            <l>Upon the outward forme let no Man looke, </l>
            <l>But search the richer inside of thy Booke. </l>
            <l>And if their humors doe not judgement blinde, </l>
            <l>They'l most things pleasing, none offending finde. </l>
            <closer>
              <signed>
                <foreign xml:lang="lat">Sic censet Amicus</foreign>. THO. NABBES. </signed>
            </closer>
          </div>
          <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000824-e1290">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-006-b"/>
            <head>To his loving friend the Author, on his Fancies Theater. </head>
            <l>'TIs worth enough to have so many friends, </l>
            <l>Who doe applaud with judgement thy faire ends▪ </l>
            <l>Which raise thy Towring Fancies to such height, </l>
            <l>That ev'ry line affords us a conceit </l>
            <l>Farre different from the Whimzies of the time, </l>
            <l>Where 'tis their chiefest praise to trot in Rime, </l>
            <l>And thunder out their meaning in a Phrase, </l>
            <l>Wo'd strike a Martiall spirit in a maze: </l>
            <l>But let the world judge if what thou hast done, </l>
            <l>Deserve not good mens approbation? </l>
            <l>For my part, I shall deeme thee worthy praise, </l>
            <l>When such a troope as these extoll thy Bayes. </l>
            <l>When Fancie in thy Theater doth play, </l>
            <l>And wins more credit than a second day; </l>
            <l>When thy pure Helicon so high doth flow, </l>
            <l>It out-braves Iordan or the swelling Poe. </l>
            <l>Let not thy Fancie ebbe, but more and more </l>
            <l>Inlarge it's limits, and encroach the Shoare. </l>
            <l>And let the Sea-borne Goddesse ever be </l>
            <l>Propitious to thy straines of Poesie. </l>
            <l>And may'st thou in thy Verse so happy prove, </l>
            <l>That Cupid may affect thy beauteous Love </l>
            <l>Dearer than Psyche, till thou make her be </l>
            <l>Fairer than thine, lest he shou'd Rivall thee. </l>
            <closer>
              <signed>Thy Friend <hi>C. G.</hi>
              </signed>
            </closer>
          </div>
          <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000824-e1650">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-007-a"/>
            <head>To his Friend the Author, on his Fancies Theater. </head>
            <l>FRiend, since the choise and most Emphatick phrase </l>
            <l>Appeares too slender to enrich thy prayse; </l>
            <l>How shall the discord of my jarring skill </l>
            <l>Ought but detract from th'honor of thy Quill? </l>
            <l>But yet, so just an int'rest in my love </l>
            <l>Thy merits clayme, that should I not approve </l>
            <l>The rich Exchequer of thy pregnant Braine </l>
            <l>To it's true worth, I should appeare a staine. </l>
            <l>Come all you Youths fill'd with Phoebean fire, </l>
            <l>(As tribute to the Musick of his Lyre) </l>
            <l>Bring each with willing Palmes a Daphnean Bough, </l>
            <l>And make a Chaplet to impale his Brow, </l>
            <l>Into whose Brest Apollo's selfe hath ray'd </l>
            <l>Such loftie Raptures, as may well perswade </l>
            <l>The transmigration which Pythagoras </l>
            <l>Maintain'd for truth, may for authentick passe. </l>
            <l>For, when th'inticing pleasure of thy Line, </l>
            <l>And teeming Fancies unexhausted Myne </l>
            <l>I view, me thinks the Genius of those Three </l>
            <l>Admired Laureats are ensphear'd in Thee, </l>
            <l>Smooth Shakespeare, neat Randolph, and wittie Ben, </l>
            <l>Flow in a mutuall sweetnesse from Thy Pen: </l>
            <l>Nature in Thee seemeth Arts parallell, </l>
            <l>For Thou art both her Pride and Miracle. </l>
            <l>May th'Virgin Candor of thy infant Bayes, </l>
            <l>Unravisht, spring, spight of our Critick dayes; </l>
            <l>And from Thee such Nectarean Dew distill, </l>
            <l>As may the world with admiration fill. </l>
            <closer>
              <signed>Geo. Lynn. </signed>
            </closer>
          </div>
          <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000824-e2250">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-007-b"/>
            <head>To his good friend M. <hi>Iohn Tatham </hi>upon his <hi>Fancies Theater</hi>. </head>
            <l>TO see what upstart Scriblers strive in Rime, </l>
            <l>To be the Paper-blu●rers of the time, </l>
            <l>Makes me amaz'd; yet if they wo'd but see </l>
            <l>The flowry Raptures that are done by thee, </l>
            <l>They wo'd no question blush to see the Bulls, </l>
            <l>And rabling Ballads of their windy sculls. </l>
            <l>Here they may see compos'd a spicy-nest </l>
            <l>Of flaming Fancies, all in spangles drest: </l>
            <l>For here each line that to the eye appeares, </l>
            <l>May sing a Lullaby unto the Spheres. </l>
            <l>Poore Fancies marre a Theater, but see </l>
            <l>The <hi>Fancies Theater </hi>is made by thee. </l>
            <closer>
              <signed>Robert Chamberlaine. </signed>
            </closer>
          </div>
          <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000824-e2440">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-008-a"/>
            <head>To his friend M. <hi>Iohn Tatham </hi>on his Fancies Theater. </head>
            <l>TO shew my selfe in Print I ne're had thought, </l>
            <l>But that thy Fancies has my thoughts out-wrought. </l>
            <l>What shall I say? 'tis this I doe admire, </l>
            <l>And think thy wits like to th'aspiring fire, </l>
            <l>Will ne're descend; thy braine from vulgar straines </l>
            <l>Is clarifi'd so neatly, it containes </l>
            <l>Th'Epitome of smooth and well scan'd verse, </l>
            <l>And though in future times thy aged he●se, </l>
            <l>Shall be enthron'd with Lawrell; yet this age </l>
            <l>May blame my zealous friendship, and in rage </l>
            <l>Both carp at thee, and me: But it shall ne're </l>
            <l>Make me strike sayle, but rather make my steere </l>
            <l>Beare stiffe with malice for to think that men </l>
            <l>Would make abortive this thy Infant Pen. </l>
            <l>But yet my hopes are confident, that they </l>
            <l>Cannot but give thy worth a branch of Bay, </l>
            <l>Though not a Lawrell, which slow-paced Time </l>
            <l>Shall bring, and humbly offer at thy Shrine. </l>
            <closer>
              <signed>H. Davison. </signed>
            </closer>
          </div>
          <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000824-e2680">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-008-b"/>
            <head>To his friend <hi>Iohn Tatham </hi>Gent. upon his <hi>Fancies Theater</hi>. </head>
            <l>THou didst not meane thy Theater sho'd be </l>
            <l>Common (though publique) to th'Obliquity </l>
            <l>Of ev'ry duller eye: 'Tis rais'd too neere, </l>
            <l>(Propt by thy Fancies Atlas) to the sphere </l>
            <l>Of purest wit, which the dull sonnes of Earth </l>
            <l>(Sho'd they afflict the Universe with dearth </l>
            <l>Of Ignorance and Envie, pile it up </l>
            <l>In envious heapes for their ascent to crop </l>
            <l>Thy Bayes) can ne're aspire to: Attempt they may, </l>
            <l>And passe our duller ayre; But the cleare Ray </l>
            <l>Of thy bright worth appearing, will deprive </l>
            <l>Their terrified soule of sence; deceive </l>
            <l>Their hopes through their own ruine And what they have </l>
            <l>Now for their steps, anon shall be their grave, </l>
            <l>Prest by the weight of Ignorance: But then </l>
            <l>Their guilty blushing shame shall rise agen </l>
            <l>To scornfull memory, whose black name shall give </l>
            <l>More lustre to thy praises, to survive </l>
            <l>'Till Time hath lost himselfe: And this great All </l>
            <l>Be brought to its confused Funerall. </l>
            <l>Passe not a Zoylists envie, since th'ast knowne </l>
            <l>Thy censure through their breath, whose pleasure none </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-009-a"/>
            <l>Can without sacriledge dispute. But if </l>
            <l>Thy fearefull soule cannot retaine beliefe </l>
            <l>Of safety, Iove shall to secure thy feare, </l>
            <l>Displace his Bird from's bosome-nest, and there </l>
            <l>Harbour thy Muse: But what injustice can </l>
            <l>Refuse the God's, and take the word of Man, </l>
            <l>Th'ast had a Jury of Immor●●lls, that </l>
            <l>Have given their censure: finde not guilty; what </l>
            <l>Bold Heav'n-contemners then dare contradict, </l>
            <l>When the Divine Vote's publish their Edict? </l>
            <l>The Daphnean Bay graspt by the Frosts cold hand, </l>
            <l>Doth grow more freshly greene; thy Muse shall stand </l>
            <l>As firme 'gainst Envies storme, till Fame shall be </l>
            <l>Proud to record thy still greene memory. </l>
            <closer>
              <signed>Iames Iones. </signed>
            </closer>
          </div>
          <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000824-e3150">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-009-b"/>
            <head>Vpon his Dreame and Censure of the Gods. </head>
            <l>ANd canst thou dreame so well? then never wake, </l>
            <l>Unlesse it be that so thou may'st pertake </l>
            <l>The reall substance of thy thoughts, and then </l>
            <l>Thou'lt make a subject for the rarest Pen </l>
            <l>To treat on: But having at a venture </l>
            <l>Invok'd th'th'Immortals for to have their censure </l>
            <l>Upon thy Fate; Sol sooner shall stand still, </l>
            <l>And fire the Orbs, but thou shalt hate thy will. </l>
            <closer>
              <signed>H. Davison. </signed>
            </closer>
          </div>
          <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000824-e3280">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-010-a"/>
            <head>To his friend M. <hi>Io. Tatham </hi>on his Fancies Theater. </head>
            <l>WHen I beheld and view'd each sev'rall line </l>
            <l>Appearing a full fraughted Magazine </l>
            <l>Of choyce conceits; such as our Fancies now </l>
            <l>(Diff'ring from what they were) must needs allow: </l>
            <l>How sweet and how delici'ous to the taste: </l>
            <l>How pleasing to the eye, how trim'd, how chaste; </l>
            <l>And where thy Fancy hits upon a crime, </l>
            <l>Thy Verse doth mask it, suting with the Time; </l>
            <l>How eloquent thou art, how thine owne phrase </l>
            <l>Becomes an Orator, and tells thy praise; </l>
            <l>The faults I found were few, the greatest was </l>
            <l>(And yet for some knowne reasons it may passe) </l>
            <l>Where thou do'st court thy Mistris, and doth wipe </l>
            <l>Each word with gold, enough for to invite </l>
            <l>All eyes, all hearts; our greatest feare was, wee </l>
            <l>Should suffer by th'inchanting Orat'ry. </l>
            <l>I know thy Muse is chaste, and will not strive, </l>
            <l>T'attract all Beauties to her pleasing hive. </l>
            <l>My wishes bid goe on, and may thy Rime </l>
            <l>Flourish beyond the utmost date of Time. </l>
            <closer>
              <signed>William Barnes. </signed>
            </closer>
          </div>
          <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000824-e3530">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-010-b"/>
            <head>On the Author of the Fancies Theater. </head>
            <l>AMongst the rest, Friend, Tatham, I am come, </l>
            <l>To doe thy Fancies right, and quit the summe </l>
            <l>I stand engag'd for: since my forward youth </l>
            <l>Sign'd Love a Bond, for currant Coyne of Truth, </l>
            <l>To pay at severall times▪ the world shall be </l>
            <l>Thy Secretarie; and take this truth from me, </l>
            <l>In all thy Shop of Fancies, not a Line </l>
            <l>(I emulate thee so) but I wish mine; </l>
            <l>'Twill be sufficient portion for thy Name </l>
            <l>To live by; for Times Treasurer, wing'd Fame, </l>
            <l>Shall, as thy worth deserves, speake thee as high </l>
            <l>As any fill'd her Trump with Poesie. </l>
            <closer>
              <signed>Tho. Rawlins. </signed>
            </closer>
          </div>
          <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000824-e3760">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-011-a"/>
            <head>To his friend M. <hi>Iohn Tatham</hi>, upon his <hi>Fancies Theater</hi>. </head>
            <l>MY Muse composed more of love than fire, </l>
            <l>Would spare her Pen, and silently admire </l>
            <l>Thy worth, which her expressions cannot rayse, </l>
            <l>Unlesse she borrow thine owne stile and phrase, </l>
            <l>And from thy proper heapes purloyne a store, </l>
            <l>Which payes one debt to make a thousand more; </l>
            <l>Did not thy friendship and thy sacred merit </l>
            <l>Conjure up flames even in a frozen spirit. </l>
            <l>Though last in number, thinke me not the least, </l>
            <l>I thought as much as all thy Friends exprest; </l>
            <l>But our sincere desires suffer much wrong, </l>
            <l>Since the sad diff'rence 'twixt the heart and tongue; </l>
            <l>My thoughts soare high, though my expression's weake, </l>
            <l>True friends think out their tale, when others speake. </l>
            <l>Yet write I this not for peculiar ends, </l>
            <l>To cast aspersion on your other friends; </l>
            <l>I in that Consort jointly doe preferre </l>
            <l>My off'ring to thy <hi>Fancies Theater</hi>. </l>
            <closer>
              <signed>An. Newport. </signed>
            </closer>
          </div>
          <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000824-e4010">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-011-b"/>
            <head>To his friend the Author, on his Fancies Theater. </head>
            <l>DEare friend, my infant Muse will bee </l>
            <l>Obscur'd, when as the Readers see </l>
            <l>Thy am'rous straines, and thou'lt be found </l>
            <l>To be with greater glory crown'd </l>
            <l>By my weake Lines, which to thy prayse </l>
            <l>Affords a Coronet of Bayes. </l>
            <l>In this I am thy friend, to bee </l>
            <l>Thy foile, that plainely men may see </l>
            <l>Thy greater lustre, and may spend </l>
            <l>Their Censures gently on thy friend. </l>
            <closer>
              <signed>R. Pynder. </signed>
            </closer>
          </div>
          <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000824-e4150">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-012-a"/>
            <head>To his friend the Author. </head>
            <l>HAd I Chapmans Line or Learning, Iohns●ns Art, </l>
            <l>Fletchers more accurate Fancie, or that part </l>
            <l>Of Beaumont that's divine, Dun's profound skill, </l>
            <l>Making good Verses live, and damning ill: </l>
            <l>I then would prayse thy Verses, which sho'd last </l>
            <l>Whil'st Time ha's sands to run, or Fame a blast. </l>
            <l>But I've a Braine so dull, that though I beat </l>
            <l>The Anvill ne're so oft, there's nought but sweat </l>
            <l>And emptie vapours crowne my long lost paine. </l>
            <l>I write, 'tis bad, dislik't, rub't out againe; </l>
            <l>And in this serious folly I abuse </l>
            <l>The patience of my Lamp, my Oyle I loose; </l>
            <l>Nor is it fit, that each unworthy Line </l>
            <l>Sho'd court the light, but onely such as thine. </l>
            <l>Then since I cannot write what I desire, </l>
            <l>May thine for ever live, mine's for the fire. </l>
            <closer>
              <signed>W. Ling. </signed>
            </closer>
          </div>
          <div type="imprimatur" xml:id="ep000824-e4420">
            <opener>
              <dateline>
                <date>21 Aprilis, 1640. </date>
              </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Imprimatur, </p>
            <closer>
              <signed>JOHANNES HANSLEY. </signed>
            </closer>
          </div>
        </front>
        <body>
          <div type="dialogue" xml:id="ep000824-e4520">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-012-b"/>
            <head>A DIALOGVE betweene <hi>Momus, Tyme</hi>, and the Author. </head>
            <sp xml:id="ep000824-e4560">
              <speaker>Momus. </speaker>
              <l>HOw now presumpt'ous Lad, think'st thou that wee </l>
              <l>Will be disturb'd with this thy Infancie </l>
              <l>Of wit:— </l>
              <l>Or doe's thy am'rous thoughts beget a flame </l>
              <l>(Beyond it's merit) for to court the name </l>
              <l>Of Poet; or is't common now adayes </l>
              <l>Such slender wits dare clayme such things as Bayes: </l>
              <l>Or doe's thy sickly Fancie think to get </l>
              <l>Some foole to be enamour'd on thy wit? </l>
              <l>Thy reason, prythee, why, ambitious Boy, </l>
              <l>Thou do'st present the world with such a toy; </l>
              <l>Yet giv'st it such a title, that 'twere sin </l>
              <l>To view the outside, and not looke within; </l>
              <l>The <hi>Fancies Theater</hi>, a Title wee </l>
              <l>Durst ne're assume to reach, much lesse for thee: </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-013-a"/>
              <l>It is the very Prologue, to invite </l>
              <l>A Puritan to covet for it's sight. </l>
              <l>And then agen I wonder, what mad vaine </l>
              <l>Did prompt thy Fancie, to present a straine </l>
              <l>(So farre unworthy) to so bright an eye, </l>
              <l>Where all deserts and true perfections lye. </l>
              <l>When I behold his name, me thinks I see </l>
              <l>Phoebus himselfe, the God of Poesie, </l>
              <l>— By whose judicious eye deserts shall live,— </l>
              <l>And spight of killing Envie, shall survive. </l>
              <l>I should mistrust my selfe, should I but think </l>
              <l>His judgement will at thee connive, or wink; </l>
              <l>To him, forgetfull Lad, durst thou present </l>
              <l>These weak conceits; or was it to prevent </l>
              <l>Our rasher censure; thinking thou might'st sing </l>
              <l>At peace, once shelter'd underneath his wing? </l>
              <l>I laugh to see thy follyes, yet I sweare </l>
              <l>I heartily could wish thy Fancies were </l>
              <l>Such as might well deserve him; for, know, I </l>
              <l>Doe envie at thy blest prosperity. </l>
              <l>Is not the world cram'd full of wits? why then </l>
              <l>Should'st thou be favour'd thus above those men, </l>
              <l>Whose high and rare deserts, doth clayme to be </l>
              <l>The Kingdomes best and richest Treasurie? </l>
              <l>Yet all their fortunes, and their merits, they </l>
              <l>Would levell at his feet; and, well they may. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000824-e5010">
              <speaker>Tyme. </speaker>
              <l>IT is confest, that Tyme's old age could yet </l>
              <l>Ne're glory in a world, so full of wit, </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-013-b"/>
              <l>Nor was his snowy haires crown'd with delight </l>
              <l>Of sweeter choycer Raptures, such as might </l>
              <l>(Like <hi>gold-tongu'd Orpheus</hi>) make stones follow men: </l>
              <l>Their Verse extinct, Stones propagate agen, </l>
              <l>And though the world doth boast of such, yet wee </l>
              <l>Doe finde it stayn'd with base impiety; </l>
              <l>Such as thy selfe proud Momus, that do'st strive </l>
              <l>To damne young wits, to keepe thine owne alive. </l>
              <l>Tyme must amend this fault I say, unlesse </l>
              <l>The world is weary of the bigge swolne Presse, </l>
              <l>And her deliverings; When our Wits are dead, </l>
              <l>Shall only their great Names be registred, </l>
              <l>And not their works; or shall not th'Muses heire● </l>
              <l>Encrease and multiply as Tyme, and Yeares? </l>
              <l>For now adayes our younger wits are quite </l>
              <l>Disheartned by the venome of thy spight; </l>
              <l>Whose base detraction would have none to be </l>
              <l>Inroll'd within the List of Poetry, </l>
              <l>But of thy Sect; whose numbers still encrease, </l>
              <l>Belching out foule-mouth'd words, derision's ease; </l>
              <l>For could your Sect make what you'd mend, 'twere well, </l>
              <l>'Tis better prate than doe: But let me tell </l>
              <l>The world my humour, though I've often bin </l>
              <l>Taxt as being guilty of this Critick sin, </l>
              <l>In giving leave to your prophane intent, </l>
              <l>(A thing Heav'n knows, my judgment never ment) </l>
              <l>I doe pro●est, though Opportunity </l>
              <l>You have engross'd and brib'd, yet, 'twas not I. </l>
              <l>I hate thy doings, so I'le henceforth be </l>
              <l>A scorner of thy base dishonesty. </l>
              <l>Is it not time that Tyme should urge the ayre </l>
              <l>Of such grosse putrefaction; and repaire </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-014-a"/>
              <l>The almost lost deserts of many, which </l>
              <l>Dare not presume their sences to enrich </l>
              <l>With the Divine instinct of Poesie: </l>
              <l>Fearing thy Carping and thy Blasphemy. </l>
              <l>There cannot now a Rapture be put forth; </l>
              <l>But thou detract'st the substance of their worth. </l>
              <l>Is thy wit rare, or dost thou think there's none </l>
              <l>Can equalize thy Fancies, but thine owne? </l>
              <l>Misguided selfe-conceited Idiots, see, </l>
              <l>But your owne ignorance and simplicity; </l>
              <l>And then you'l yeeld 'tis better mend, than make; </l>
              <l>This without Bribe, or favour, I have spake </l>
              <l>For him whose wit's (as yet) but rawe, till Time </l>
              <l>And yeares hath taught him higher for to climbe. </l>
              <l>Then forward (Youth) let not the Criticks eye </l>
              <l>Be th'cause ●o stay thy ingenuity. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000824-e5620">
              <speaker>Author. </speaker>
              <l>LEt me first crave from thee gray-headed Time, </l>
              <l>Thy absolution, e're I put my Rime </l>
              <l>To be a Courtier in the wanton ayre, </l>
              <l>Making their Progresse to each witty faire. </l>
              <l>And courteous Mistris, unto whose white hand </l>
              <l>I wish them happy journey, while I stand </l>
              <l>Devoted for their service: I have beene </l>
              <l>Too, too, too prodigall, and have not seene </l>
              <l>My errors: but have wilfully run on, </l>
              <l>As Steward to some liberall Gentleman? </l>
              <l>Where I have beene too lavish, and have spent </l>
              <l>What was my Masters, freely to me lent. </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-014-b"/>
              <l>And though the Steward hath but little now </l>
              <l>Left for to shew his Master, yet I vow </l>
              <l>I have some remnants left, although they be </l>
              <l>But shreds to what I might have gain'd from thee. </l>
              <l>If I have us'd thee ill. I'le be thy Slave, </l>
              <l>And henceforth dote on nothing but my grave. </l>
              <l>Yet let me thus much tell thee; my desire </l>
              <l>Ne're kindled from a base ambitious fire </l>
              <l>Of an applause, though carping Momus hee </l>
              <l>Murmurs, and bites my Title Page and mee. </l>
              <l>I have observ●d his envie▪ and I say, </l>
              <l>I doe not this in hope to get a pay, </l>
              <l>Reward, or such base mercenary gaine; </l>
              <l>Let them that gape for't, have it for their paine. </l>
              <l>I will not sell that little mite of wit, </l>
              <l>If so (without offence) I dare terme it, </l>
              <l>At any rate; Nor doe I care the while, </l>
              <l>If at the Title they doe lend a smile; </l>
              <l>I willingly would please them, yet if they </l>
              <l>Will not be pleas'd, I weigh not what they say. </l>
              <l>My Title Momus, let me tell thee true, </l>
              <l>Is for to please my selfe, not to please you. </l>
              <l>Nor doe I strive to gaine a Poets name; </l>
              <l>A title my weak soule durst never ayme </l>
              <l>To court at; For, I may as soone aspire, </l>
              <l>To kisse the Sunne, as warme me at that fire. </l>
              <l>To end expostulation, thus much know, </l>
              <l>What my dese●ts can merit, I doe owe </l>
              <l>To him whose kinde acceptance makes me blest, </l>
              <l>Lifting me higher than the Eagles nest. </l>
              <l>And if my wit encrease (as yeares in me) </l>
              <l>I shall aspire no higher than to be </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-015-a"/>
              <l>Accounted as his Servant; and will lay </l>
              <l>My off'rings at his feet as well as they, </l>
              <l>Whom you alledge deserv'd him better; why? </l>
              <l>They can but give their store, and so will I. </l>
              <l>Then why should you as canker'd, so deject </l>
              <l>That, which his wisedome's pleas'd with to protect: </l>
              <l>But I'le not barre your custome, for 'tis knowne </l>
              <l>You will detract all Writings but your owne. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e6200">
            <head>To the truly worthy and his much honoured friend, Sir <hi>Edward Savage</hi>. </head>
            <l>HOw some will erre in making that seeme good, </l>
            <l>Scarce ha's allowance to be understood! </l>
            <l>Honor consists in Vertues, nor is't fit </l>
            <l>Each worthlesse faune should clayme a share in wit. </l>
            <l>It wrongs the Poets Genius, whose pure fire </l>
            <l>Will suffer no privation, when the Quire </l>
            <l>Of Fancy-propping Muses does distill </l>
            <l>The oyly-drops of merit from the hill </l>
            <l>Of Noble-worth, to tell the erring sence </l>
            <l>Of credulous Man, that Truths preheminence </l>
            <l>Keepes no alliance with such motions, tends </l>
            <l>To soothing flattery, the bad Mans friends. </l>
            <l>And to that end sends me Ambassador, </l>
            <l>To make the world acquainted what you are: </l>
            <l>With vowes unfained, Noble Sir, y'are one, </l>
            <l>That shares on Natures distribution. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-015-b"/>
            <l>And I would say, but that your modest eares </l>
            <l>Are wool'd 'gainst your own praises, though't appeares </l>
            <l>Roab'd in reality itselfe, you can </l>
            <l>Distinguish 'twixt the best and worst of Man: </l>
            <l>One who may clayme the Attributes of wise, </l>
            <l>Noble, and courteous, and from these does rise </l>
            <l>The living Emblems, Charity and Love, </l>
            <l>The Orbs by which each faculty doe move, </l>
            <l>That claymes a being in you. You appeare </l>
            <l>The spacious blisse where Vertue keepes her Spheare, </l>
            <l>In a sweet temp'rature; the thought of Pride </l>
            <l>(As Omen to your Vertues) you deride, </l>
            <l>Exiled from that bosome which inherits▪ </l>
            <l>The uncorrupted wishes to your merits. </l>
            <l>May health still crowne you with felicity, </l>
            <l>Till you desire to change Mortality, </l>
            <l>For th'reserved blisse in Elizium, </l>
            <l>When as your Dove-like expirations come. </l>
            <l>And may your better part transferred be </l>
            <l>Into a constellatious Soveraignty: </l>
            <l>While Vertues-Lovers Requiems sing, and I </l>
            <l>Have vitall motion, study for the eye </l>
            <closer>
              <signed>Of your devoted Servant. </signed>
            </closer>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e6680">
            <head>A Newyeares gift to Clarinda. </head>
            <l>FAshions are now a dayes so often us'd, </l>
            <l>That meanest Peasants have the same abus'd. </l>
            <l>Each servile creature can command their Rings, </l>
            <l>Gloves, or the like, (such b●se mechanick things) </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-016-a"/>
            <l>Reason must guide you then; such toyes as those </l>
            <l>Are subject still to losing; Ile repose </l>
            <l>More confidence in you, and will impart </l>
            <l>A farre transcendent Gift, my loyall Heart: </l>
            <l>Embrace it then, and let no envious fate </l>
            <l>Crosse our united loves, nor derogate </l>
            <l>From what you former were; such Gifts as this </l>
            <l>Deserve the keeping, nay, some future blisse. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e6830">
            <head>Vpon an old rich Woman in love with a young Gentleman. </head>
            <lg>
              <l>MOre rich than wise, and yet more wise than faire, </l>
              <l>Yeares adde grey Trophi●s to enrich thy haire; </l>
              <l>Rather than live to love, die with despaire. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>When as sad Comets in the Skies appeare, </l>
              <l>Some strange disaster then approacheth neere, </l>
              <l>Which in our doubtfull Soules begets a feare. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Thy Nose is that disaster; for, in thee, </l>
              <l>No lesse than thousand Comets we may see, </l>
              <l>As symptomes to ensuing miserie. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Below thy Nose, a Hill we may descry, </l>
              <l>Darkning the light appearing from thy eye, </l>
              <l>Within that hollow Concave where they lye. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Eye, Nose, and Chin, since you in darknesse be, </l>
              <l>Premeditate before you visit me, </l>
              <l>And rayse young Cynders to your Venerie. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-016-b"/>
              <l>And in Nights shade meet with your shadow, where </l>
              <l>Some Incubus by chance may get an heire, </l>
              <l>Making the World accurst with such a paire. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Or if thy wither'd Hand (begot by Time) </l>
              <l>Should with thy Eye, Nose, Chin, and Face combine, </l>
              <l>Without discordant, for to make me thine: </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Know gumlesse-wooer that diseases thirst, </l>
              <l>To seize thy hand, where th'Apoplexy must </l>
              <l>Bring thee e're long, unto thy neighbours dust. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Or if thy wither'd thigh desires to know </l>
              <l>The sweet contents that in our Youth doe flow, </l>
              <l>Convert a teare into a flood below. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>So may some Cripple wanting Almes, supply, </l>
              <l>Thy al-most desperate necessity: </l>
              <l>And please both nose, gums, chin, thigh, hands, &amp; eye. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Covet no more when that you are so sped </l>
              <l>Nor dye your cheeks with colour from your bed, </l>
              <l>Since afore th'Ark you lost your Maydenhead. </l>
            </lg>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e7310">
            <head>The Superscription of a Letter sent to Clarinda. </head>
            <l>FRom my Master here I'm come, </l>
            <l>To embrace your Martyrdome▪ </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-017-a"/>
            <l>Let no other hand come neere me, </l>
            <l>You alone have power to teare me. </l>
            <l>If you like not what's within, </l>
            <l>Then your frownes may purge my sin: </l>
            <l>But if he or I can please, </l>
            <l>Friendly let me rest at ease. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e7420">
            <head>The Letter. </head>
            <l>GOe pale-fac't Paper to my Deare, </l>
            <l>And whisper this into her eare: </l>
            <l>Though I absent am, yet shee </l>
            <l>Keeping thee, embraces mee. </l>
            <l>Let no rude hand dare to touch thee, </l>
            <l>Care not though a thousand grutch thee </l>
            <l>Of that blisse which in her Hive </l>
            <l>Thou enjoy'st till I arrive, </l>
            <l>And be sure thou do'st not flye </l>
            <l>From the glances of her eye. </l>
            <l>Where she goes, be thou about her, </l>
            <l>Gad not thou abroad without her; </l>
            <l>Nor let any dare to see </l>
            <l>What's betweene my Love and thee. </l>
            <l>Nay, and when she chance to sleepe, </l>
            <l>Gently to her Bosome creepe, </l>
            <l>Where I charge thee, rest till shee, </l>
            <l>With her kisses waken thee. </l>
            <l>Goe and prosper for a space, </l>
            <l>Till I rob thee of thy place. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e7640">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-017-b"/>
            <head>To Clarinda. </head>
            <l>PRetty Wanton, prythee say, </l>
            <l>Did you see my Heart to day? </l>
            <l>Marks to know it, you shall finde </l>
            <l>Alwayes constant, true, and kinde; </l>
            <l>Wounds about it, it doth beare, </l>
            <l>Drops are trickling here, and there, </l>
            <l>●n which wound you'l finde, a Dart </l>
            <l>Shot by you into my hart, </l>
            <l>●f you saw it; doe not blush, </l>
            <l>Th'wounds are fresh, and blood will gush </l>
            <l>●nto your face, and you be knowne, </l>
            <l>To covet more than is your owne. </l>
            <l>Send it back, but let it bee </l>
            <l>Sound as when it came to thee. </l>
            <l>Doe not think for to deny it; </l>
            <l>These are tokens will discry it. </l>
            <l>How can I subsist and live, </l>
            <l>When my owne you will not give? </l>
            <l>Yet if you will send to me, </l>
            <l>Yours in faire exchange, I'le be </l>
            <l>Mute, and not report that I </l>
            <l>Suffer by your cruelty. </l>
            <l>●hen I prythee let me know, </l>
            <l>If you will exchange, or no. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e7910">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-018-a"/>
            <head>In praise of Sack. </head>
            <l>TO write thy prayse, let ev'ry Poets Quill </l>
            <l>Flow with sweet Dew, suckt from Parnassus Hill. </l>
            <l>Sack, I adore thee; nay, the Muses nine </l>
            <l>Count thee the Fabrick of their heav'nly Chime: </l>
            <l>And in their choice ●nventions strive to gaine </l>
            <l>Thy liking, ere the World peruse a straine. </l>
            <l>Aged thou art, by which thou do'st possesse </l>
            <l>Of Noble Spirits, Poets numberlesse: </l>
            <l>And to thy Cistern's head doe all resort, </l>
            <l>Admire thee, as they doe admire the Court. </l>
            <l>The very Children, ere they scarce can say </l>
            <l>Their Pater-Noster, or their Christ-Crosse A, </l>
            <l>Will to their Parents prattle, and desire </l>
            <l>To tast that Drinke, which Gods doe so admire: </l>
            <l>So by degrees, ere Time can count their yeares, </l>
            <l>Thy strength doth make them Ovids wittie heires. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e8150">
            <head>To Clarinda, walking with her in his Garden. </head>
            <lg>
              <l>SAy, my Clarinda, is the Rose </l>
              <l>Not prowd to have thy sweet repose, </l>
              <l>Since they derive their dye from those, </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Those precious Colours, Red and White, </l>
              <l>Dwell in thy Checkes, may Gods invite </l>
              <l>To feed, not surfet with delight. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-018-b"/>
              <l>Twere sinne, Clarinda, to beleeve, </l>
              <l>From thee they could such harme receive; </l>
              <l>Yet should they, thou canst Cordials give. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>●ay, my Clarinda, why the Aire </l>
              <l>Appeares thus fresh, soft, clearely faire, </l>
              <l>Yet cloudie Vapours yonder are? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Why does the injur'd Philomell </l>
              <l>Hither retire, her moane to tell, </l>
              <l>Yet Wood-men want her dolefull knell? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Why does she alter now her Vote, </l>
              <l>Purging the Quinzie in her throat, </l>
              <l>Payes sorrow with a pleasing note? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Why Violets in Purple drest, </l>
              <l>The Damask thus the Rose invest, </l>
              <l>Whose perfum'd Mantles grace the East? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Why doe the humble Pebbles rise </l>
              <l>Like Opals, to out-brave the Skies, </l>
              <l>And Iris various Clouds despise? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Tell me, Clarinda, why the Sun </l>
              <l>Is set before his course is run, </l>
              <l>Readie to fire his Region? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And why does his beloved Flower </l>
              <l>Forget her Cue, her time and houre, </l>
              <l>And shuts not, when he shewes his power? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-019-a"/>
              <l>Each spicie Child, whose crisped Bed </l>
              <l>Intwines the Earths Spring Maidenhead, </l>
              <l>Are blest, in kissing where you tread. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Or why does every thing beside, </l>
              <l>That's good, in this small place abide, </l>
              <l>When other Gardens want such pride? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>'Tis thou, Clarinda, mak'st this place </l>
              <l>So fertile glorious; when you pace </l>
              <l>This Walke, each Evill shuns your Chase. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>When you appeare, th'amorous Ayre </l>
              <l>With modest breath salutes your hayre, </l>
              <l>And whispers out their zeale in prayer. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>The Nightingale confines her woe, </l>
              <l>And gives mirth libertie to goe, </l>
              <l>As Ecchoes to your Beds of Snow. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>The Violet, Rose, and Pebbles have </l>
              <l>No other Liveries than you gave, </l>
              <l>Yet such as may the World out-brave. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>The Sunne does melt to see thy face, </l>
              <l>The perfect Modell of pure Grace; </l>
              <l>H'ad rather burne than mend his pace. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>The Marigold knowes none but thee, </l>
              <l>To whom she owes observancie, </l>
              <l>Opens and shuts at your bright eye. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-019-b"/>
              <l>Though now this place is trim and fine, </l>
              <l>When you depart, all will decline, </l>
              <l>And others seeme more rich than mine. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Oh then! Clarinda, stay and bring </l>
              <l>Night into Day, the Winter, Spring; </l>
              <l>We need not then a Wintering. </l>
            </lg>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e9060">
            <head>Clarinda describ'd. </head>
            <lg>
              <l>CLarinda! Oh, that very Name </l>
              <l>Includes such worth, that he but dares </l>
              <l>Without a Reverence speake the same, </l>
              <l>Commits a sinne his teares and prayers </l>
              <l>Can ne're wash off: it is so foule, </l>
              <l>'Tis her pure sighs must cleanse his Soule. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Who sayes, that Leda's Swan is white, </l>
              <l>Or sweetnesse dwels in Hybla's Trees, </l>
              <l>Or Roses balmie breath delight </l>
              <l>The Pallats of the active Bees, </l>
              <l>Deceives himselfe; they all appeare </l>
              <l>Not worth our thoughts, Clarinda neere. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Her Haire our Appetites entice, </l>
              <l>Her Front a Mount of bleached Snow, </l>
              <l>Her Eyes are Natures Paradice, </l>
              <l>Her Lips are Mines where Rubies grow: </l>
              <l>Her Breath perfumes the chequer'd fields, </l>
              <l>They have no sweet, but what she yeelds. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-020-a"/>
              <l>Her Neck the polisht Ivorie weares, </l>
              <l>Her Brests the Valleys of Desire. </l>
              <l>When Love cuts through the circled Spheares, </l>
              <l>There lights, to coole the scorching fire </l>
              <l>His Brest receiv'd from her: whose art </l>
              <l>Without his ayd can smite a Hart. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>In every part she is most rare, </l>
              <l>All good in her contracted is, </l>
              <l>Nature's whole stock's envolv'd in her, </l>
              <l>Th'Epitome of heavenly blisse; </l>
              <l>Her Voice can stay the hand of Fate, </l>
              <l>Her Smiles young Cupids can create. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Her ex'lence Metaphysicall, </l>
              <l>Partakes not of old Natures stamps, </l>
              <l>For she is supernaturall, </l>
              <l>Her Luminaries, Heavens Lamps: </l>
              <l>I will conclude, shee's all divine, </l>
              <l>For else I ne're had writ her mine. </l>
            </lg>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e9560">
            <head>On Clarinda smiling. </head>
            <l>HAve you beheld the Orient Sunne appeare, </l>
            <l>Casting his splendour to each neighb'ring Spheare? </l>
            <l>When cold-blood Winter copulated Ice, </l>
            <l>Congeal'd a Frost, cov'ring each Bough with Spice </l>
            <l>As white as Winters hayres; how he displayes </l>
            <l>His youthfull heat, auspicious to his Rayes; </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-020-b"/>
            <l>How each tree melts, or to a jelly turnes; </l>
            <l>Such was Clarinda's smile, that ever burnes, </l>
            <l>And melts my yeelding Heart, that I till now </l>
            <l>Cloyster'd with Ice, could not of heat allow. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e9710">
            <head>A Contemplation of Liberty and Love. </head>
            <l>VVHat is that freedome which men call </l>
            <l>A blessednesse to sport withall: </l>
            <l>Or what those joyes which Lovers deeme, </l>
            <l>To equalize their best esteeme, </l>
            <l>I long to know, that I may see, </l>
            <l>The diff'rence 'twixt those joyes and me. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e9790">
            <head>Responsio. </head>
            <l>THen know, Loves joyes are such as still </l>
            <l>Are subject to Fates supreme will. </l>
            <l>And every howre the Lover findes </l>
            <l>Crosse friends, crosse starres, and crosser windes. </l>
            <l>Till Seas grow calme, and we arrive </l>
            <l>At Loves eternall peacefull Hive. </l>
            <l>If Patience then may bring me ease, </l>
            <l>Swell bigg a while you boyst'rous Seas▪ </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e9890">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-021-a"/>
            <head>Vpon the hinderance of meeting by raine, sent to his friend Mr. W. B. </head>
            <l>WHen last we did encounter with the GLOBE, </l>
            <l>The Heav'ns was pleas'd to grace us with his robe </l>
            <l>Of settled motions; but Aquarius, hee, </l>
            <l>Like an ambitious Churle, disdaines that wee </l>
            <l>Should have another meeting; Bacchus smilde, </l>
            <l>But not prevail'd, because an Infant childe: </l>
            <l>Nor could we get a Venus to embrace, </l>
            <l>Mars strives to keepe them back, and hold them chace. </l>
            <l>Iove stamps, Apollo frownes, th'Heavens all o're, </l>
            <l>Seeme as contentious, and are in uprore. </l>
            <l>Mercury doth seeme to clogg his feather'd h●eles, </l>
            <l>With weighty lead▪ in stead of flying, reeles </l>
            <l>Into great Taurus center, the BULL-HEAD, </l>
            <l>Where, with dull Claret we our sences fed, </l>
            <l>Delaying time, till the roboyst'rous raine </l>
            <l>Ceas'd its unmatched course, then up againe </l>
            <l>To walk; th'Heavens not yet appeas●d, cast downe </l>
            <l>Their urmost Envy in that flood to drowne </l>
            <l>Our then expected hopes, in that poore wee </l>
            <l>Were forc'd to keepe our center, not to flye. </l>
            <l>Great Bishop●gate can witnesse in what houre, </l>
            <l>We did arrive within its haplesse Bowre. </l>
            <l>The Gods did seeme thus angry, thinking wee </l>
            <l>Should by our mirth consume their Treasury. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-021-b"/>
            <l>What's best to doe? wee must not now contend </l>
            <p>Against their power, and so farewell my friend. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e10270">
            <head>Vpon Inconstancie. </head>
            <l>INconstancie, how chance that thou of late, </l>
            <l>Art growne the chiefest Minion to my Kate? </l>
            <l>Could your ambition finde no other roome, </l>
            <l>Or secret place, but make her brest your Tomb </l>
            <l>Of ayrie motions, filling so each veyne </l>
            <l>With swelling pleasures mixt with base disdaine: </l>
            <l>That now there's not a corner scarce left free, </l>
            <l>To lodge a thought of hidden secrecie? </l>
            <l>Hence thou insatiate Monster, Lovers hate. </l>
            <l>The Commons envy, and the scorne of th'State; </l>
            <l>Get thee to Court, use there thy tyranny: </l>
            <l>Let Lovers sports alone; base Infamy, </l>
            <l>Think not to harbour in a brest so faire; </l>
            <l>I banish thee, and doe conjure thee, ne're </l>
            <l>Usurp that center yeelds us such delight: </l>
            <l>But usher thou th' obscure and darkned night </l>
            <l>Of ever gnawing conscience▪ in such soules </l>
            <l>Whose base and impure actions, still controules </l>
            <l>Their pale-check'd Lovers▪ on whose fickle state, </l>
            <l>Dispaire and horror doth attend and wait. </l>
            <l>Goe base Neglect, and scorne, presume no more </l>
            <l>T'assayle those Vertues, that her choycest store </l>
            <l>Shee may impart to me; if thou be thence▪ </l>
            <l>I know I shall not want her excellence▪ </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e10540">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-022-a"/>
            <head>Vpon Clarinda's comming to Towne, and departure. </head>
            <l>NOW comes the pride of Earth, the glorious Spring; </l>
            <l>And Philomel, to welcome her, doth sing. </l>
            <l>The pretty birds doe play, </l>
            <l>And make a Holyday. </l>
            <l>And I with them present my offering: </l>
            <l>Th' Arabian Bird presents to her, her kinde, </l>
            <l>Ne're seene before; on whose sweet face, the winde </l>
            <l>Suckt in his breath </l>
            <l>For feare of death; </l>
            <l>And Phoebus in his Majestie then shinde: </l>
            <l>And on her head cast his perfumes: but they, </l>
            <l>As farre unworthy, to her breath give way. </l>
            <l>The odours which </l>
            <l>The World enrich, </l>
            <l>Did to her breath their choysest sents convey; </l>
            <l>The Queene of Love asham'd, did hide her head, </l>
            <l>And Cynthia in a cloud bemuffeled, </l>
            <l>Did murmur there, </l>
            <l>And in her Spheare </l>
            <l>Waxt pale to see her lips and cheekes so red. </l>
            <l>The humble Pebbles where her feet did lite, </l>
            <l>Were straight made Jacinths, Saphires, Rubies bright, </l>
            <l>Who wantonly did kiste </l>
            <l>At such a change as this. </l>
            <l>And blest the comming of this glorious light. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-022-b"/>
            <l>If any Objects pleas'd her, with a glance </l>
            <l>They should be Mynes of Dyamonds; but Chance </l>
            <l>The fickle Goddesse would not be </l>
            <l>Propitious to our hopes, 'cause wee </l>
            <l>Shee fear'd, with her, might out-vye Spaine and France: </l>
            <l>Nay, both the Indies: None need plough the Seas </l>
            <l>To purchase wealth with toyle; for, here with ease </l>
            <l>They might obtaine </l>
            <l>A world of gaine, </l>
            <l>Had she but writ in smiles to them, <hi>I please</hi>. </l>
            <l>But oh! shee's gone, and ev'ry thing has now </l>
            <l>His courser Nature on; Winters rough brow, </l>
            <l>And Boreas blast </l>
            <l>With envious hast </l>
            <l>Rends ev'ry tree, dis-leaves each twigge and bough; </l>
            <l>The Phoenix too retir'd unto her nest, </l>
            <l>And pining for her absence, pierc't her brest </l>
            <l>With sighes, and di'd, </l>
            <l>Left none beside </l>
            <l>Clarinda, with her worth to be possest. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e11130">
            <head>On the first leafe of a Psalme. Booke presented to Clarinda. </head>
            <l>TO her faire hand I this direct; </l>
            <l>Good Angels guide, and her protect </l>
            <l>That keepes my heart; O, may shee be </l>
            <l>But touch'd with flames of Love, like me! </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e11200">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-023-a"/>
            <head>Another vacant leafe in the same Booke. </head>
            <l>SHine little Booke, more glorious than the Sunne, </l>
            <l>In her faire heart that hath thy Masters wonne: </l>
            <l>May'st thou procure in her relenting teares, </l>
            <l>To pitty him whose thoughts breed naught but feares. </l>
            <l>I know that thou hast power enough, and Art </l>
            <l>To wound, rewound, and cure a wounded hart. </l>
            <l>Thou art her chiefe delight, whose vertuous minde, </l>
            <l>To study thee from childhood hath enclinde: </l>
            <l>Tell her thy Master sent thee, for that shee </l>
            <l>Might think on him, by often reading thee. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e11320">
            <head>To Clarinda, walking with her in the night in a Wood or Grove, she being fearefull. </head>
            <l>FEare not Clarinda, though th'emulous Night, </l>
            <l>Doubting his forked Queene shou'd loose her light, </l>
            <l>Retires behind a Cloud; horne-mad to see, </l>
            <l>Her glorious lamps extinguished by thee. </l>
            <l>Yet did she know the good shee might embrace </l>
            <l>At her full rising, on her mealy face </l>
            <l>(Viewing thy exquisite beauty) wou'd be drawne </l>
            <l>Mantles of crimson blushes, t'grace the lawne </l>
            <l>Of her complexion, till the angry Morne, </l>
            <l>Growne pale with Envy, sues they may adorne </l>
            <l>Her cheekes.— </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-023-b"/>
            <l>But th' pride of Heav'n's ecclips'd, this peacefull Grove </l>
            <l>Enjoyes their Cynthia, ev'ry st●rre does move </l>
            <l>(As your attendants.) Here, what need I crave </l>
            <l>Twy-light from Heav'n, that such a Guider have? </l>
            <l>Doe you not see each harmlesse creature hies </l>
            <l>With early haste to view those Radiant eies, </l>
            <l>As Heav'ns bright Tapers? th'active Fayries doe </l>
            <l>Trip from their Glo-worme, and resort to you: </l>
            <l>But having seene you, vanish, thinking day </l>
            <l>Was sent their tardy errors to betray; </l>
            <l>Repine, and dye for anger. Th' Nai●des </l>
            <l>Seeing themselves surpast in Beauty, please </l>
            <l>Their Fancies with adoring you, desire </l>
            <l>No greater blisse, than warmth from your pure fire. </l>
            <l>Why weepes my deare Clarinda? here is none </l>
            <l>Dare injure thy knowne pur'ty, th'art alone </l>
            <l>In naught but singularity; See, The skyes </l>
            <l>Offer their stock of teares, to save thy eyes. </l>
            <l>Mix not thine, with corruption; they can be </l>
            <l>No lesse (my Faire) 'till puri●'d by thee. </l>
            <l>Each teare that falls from that coelestiall fount▪ </l>
            <l>Is of more price, than Craesus wealth can mount </l>
            <l>To by Arithmetick; 'tis of that store, </l>
            <l>One drop will buy the world when it growes poore. </l>
            <l>See, they have left with thee, ambitious raine, </l>
            <l>To watch thy opportunity to gaine </l>
            <l>Such undeserved happinesse▪ I'le seeke </l>
            <l>Anon for ev'ry pearle upon thy cheeke: </l>
            <l>There shall not one be lost; each tree does shake </l>
            <l>Their sappy heads; drops falling downe doe take </l>
            <l>Hold with thy breath, compounded Nectar's made, </l>
            <l>Which by Favonian winds is straight convey'd </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-024-a"/>
            <l>To Ioves Emperial Palace; to the brink </l>
            <l>They fill their Bowles, and Healths about they drink </l>
            <l>To us, and our successe; the blinking Boy </l>
            <l>Recovering sight by thee, is drunk for joy, </l>
            <l>And vowes unto his Mother, and the rest, </l>
            <l>To build his Paradise upon thy brest; </l>
            <l>So proves my Rivall: but, I know, thy might </l>
            <l>Has power to blinde him; as thou gav'st him sight, </l>
            <l>So drowne his expectation in the flood </l>
            <l>Of the incensed Justice of the good. </l>
            <l>The Graces waite for thee; and Cedars now, </l>
            <l>As you past by, their lofty tops they bow, </l>
            <l>To doe you reverence, while you sooty Hall </l>
            <l>Stayes your approach to guild it, then it shall </l>
            <l>Resemble heaven for brightnesse. Fancie die, </l>
            <l>If what thou speak'st be an Hyperboly. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e12020">
            <head>To Clarinda singing and playing on the Lute, shee being bashfull upon the sight of him. </head>
            <l>BLush not Clarinda, though my sences steale </l>
            <l>Upon thy modesty; I prythee seale </l>
            <l>My welcome with a smile. Oh! stop not Sweet, </l>
            <l>Let once againe thy ayre and singers meet </l>
            <l>In blest contention; I prote it, my eares </l>
            <l>Were rapt into attention, and the Spheares </l>
            <l>Wantonly tript to heare 'em; sure, there lyes </l>
            <l>Some power 'bove Magick in those Star-like eyes; </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-024-b"/>
            <l>Whose swift pursuit gives life unto each string, </l>
            <l>I'obey the touch of thy soft fingering. </l>
            <l>The amorous courdage of thy Lute convayes, </l>
            <l>Unto the Heav'ns such Harmony, that stayes </l>
            <l>The Planets to admire it: But thy breath </l>
            <l>Despight of Nature, can enlive pale death. </l>
            <l>Sing then Clarinda, ravish evry sence, </l>
            <l>With the choyse concord of thy excellence. </l>
            <l>Out-doe the Lybian Harper, touch thy Lute, </l>
            <l>And doome the world to silence, Angels mute, </l>
            <l>While thou chaunt'st Madrigals, whose flight may tell </l>
            <l>The world th'art Heavens only miracle; </l>
            <l>For that the Earth till now has never bin </l>
            <l>Possest of such a glorious Seraphin. </l>
            <l>Oh happy roome that has atchived more </l>
            <l>Grace by her voyce, than e're thou knew'st before, </l>
            <l>Or thy first Master hop'd for; shee has made </l>
            <l>Thee by her presence an Elizian shade. </l>
            <l>The dumb Effigies dance, and th'hangings doe </l>
            <l>Shake off their gravity, and congie to </l>
            <l>The motion of your body (which till now </l>
            <l>Made gray with sorrow, wore a sullen brow) </l>
            <l>And youthfully doe move; my faire One, see, </l>
            <l>Thy Power's above the reach of Poetry, </l>
            <l>Or Art, or Fancie; live to cure the world </l>
            <l>Of Lethargies, and when curst clouds are hurld, </l>
            <l>T'oppres't— </l>
            <l>Send forth thy breath; 'twill purifie the ayre </l>
            <l>From Plagues infection, full, as well as prayer. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e12450">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-025-a"/>
            <head>An excusive Letter made by the Author, for a friend of his ●o his Father. </head>
            <l>AS one who having rob'd, fearing no Law, </l>
            <l>Till hue and cry a●●aults him, and doth draw </l>
            <l>Perforce his body to the Gaole, where long </l>
            <l>Enduring ali extreames, at last is stung </l>
            <l>With some remorce of conscience, doth ●elent </l>
            <l>His wicked life, a reform'd penitent. </l>
            <l>He goeth farre that never back returnes, </l>
            <l>An angry fire 'tis that ever burnes </l>
            <l>Within the heart of man. Oh! then be pleas'd </l>
            <l>To let your anger passe, and be appeas'd, </l>
            <l>Though all this while, my Infant yeares did stray, </l>
            <l>And trod the path of follies baiting way: </l>
            <l>Though all this while I was in blindnesse led, </l>
            <l>And all my sences unto fondnesse wed: </l>
            <l>My unripen'd yeares had not the wit to finde </l>
            <l>The vaine delights that still provokes the minde, </l>
            <l>Till buying wit now at the dearest rate, </l>
            <l>I gain'd experience through my best friends hate: </l>
            <l>Witnesse the daily teares I shed at last, </l>
            <l>In true repentance for my follyes past. </l>
            <l>Then worthy Sir, your pardon let me crave; </l>
            <l>Without your pardon I no life can have: </l>
            <l>For better 'twere that life from body fled, </l>
            <l>Than in your deepe disdaines lie buried. </l>
            <l>Let my repentance plead for mine offence, </l>
            <l>And my reformed life my innocence. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e12730">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-025-b"/>
            <head>To Clarinda upon her absence from her window. </head>
            <lg>
              <l>FAirest, if passions might expresse my love, </l>
              <l>If my unfained sighes might force beliefe: </l>
              <l>If that my nightly watchings could but move </l>
              <l>Your Adamatine heart, and give reliefe; </l>
              <l>Though now I praise your beauty, I should more, </l>
              <l>Make you my Idoll, as my Saint adore. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Oh what unworthy actions have you seene? </l>
              <l>What cause, or why, am I thus sleighted now? </l>
              <l>And held so little in your wont esteeme? </l>
              <l>Has my youth broke a syllable, or vow </l>
              <l>Which once I willing made? speake, and be sure, </l>
              <l>To finde a spotlesse heart, as chaste, as pure. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Why should you now withdraw that heav'nly light, </l>
              <l>Which struck amazement in each living creature? </l>
              <l>The lustre of your beauty from my sight; </l>
              <l>A grace bestow'd on you, by choyce dame Nature. </l>
              <l>You are her only choyce, O prythee why </l>
              <l>Should'st thou thus derogate, to let me dye? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Was it because my longing eyes did still </l>
              <l>Covet to view thy beauty ev'ry day, </l>
              <l>Glutting with surfets, yet had not it's fill, </l>
              <l>But begs a pleasing smile, and then away, </l>
              <l>Leaving behinde a heart so full of woe, </l>
              <l>That I could better stay than thence to goe? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-026-a"/>
              <l>〈◊〉 was't because my love to thee was such, </l>
              <l>That I each minute set thy prayses forth; </l>
              <l>And never thinking that I lov'd too much </l>
              <l>A soule of such rare beautie, and pure worth, </l>
              <l>Hoping at last to purchase such a prize, </l>
              <l>That should Iove see, he might eternalize? </l>
            </lg>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e13120">
            <head>To Clarinda, having had no answer to the former Letter. </head>
            <l>NOt yet an answer! ha's your well-●●n'd Muse </l>
            <l>Forsooke her pleasing Pamphlets, and refuse </l>
            <l>To grace me, as the subject of her Verse? </l>
            <l>Or doe you please to keepe 'em for my Herse; </l>
            <l>Thinking your studies (whil'st living) were ill spent, </l>
            <l>Unlesse in jesting sort and merriment? </l>
            <l>Not as a solid Lover, but as one </l>
            <l>Who ne're fetcht sighs, shed teares, or lent a groane, </l>
            <l>Which I, poore I, have done. Oh, why ha's Heaven </l>
            <l>Grac'd you with such a feature, and not given </l>
            <l>A correspondent heart? or, if it be </l>
            <l>That you retaine your Lyrick Verse for me, </l>
            <l>To grace my sable Herse; I'le pray no more; </l>
            <l>You need not, Lovers shall my case deplore; </l>
            <l>Such as have knowne what 'tis to lose a heart, </l>
            <l>They, they shall pitie me, and beare a part. </l>
            <l>And if thy studies be to such an end, </l>
            <l>Live happy, and embrace another friend, </l>
            <l>Whom you can fancie better, while poore I </l>
            <l>In peace forsake this Earths mortality. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e13360">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-026-b"/>
            <head>To Fortune. </head>
            <l>GReat Queene of Mutabilitie, to thee </l>
            <l>I send my Votes; nor beg I smiles from thee; </l>
            <l>My low and humble thoughts shall ne're aspire </l>
            <l>To climbe unto an Earledome, or Empire; </l>
            <l>Nor are they sweld with strong Ambition so, </l>
            <l>To beg a Lordship, or thy favours: no; </l>
            <l>Since begging is so usefull, I'le forbeare </l>
            <l>To beg, lest whipping fall unto my share. </l>
            <l>I will not aske thee any thing, but what </l>
            <l>Thou canst not give, that onely is my lot. </l>
            <l>First, I wo'd have from thee thy massie store, </l>
            <l>Whereby I may extend it to the poore; </l>
            <l>Nor sho'd it court your fawning Parasite, </l>
            <l>Or kisse rich Dives wealth, that's infinite▪ </l>
            <l>Give me thy eyes, and with thy eyes I'le see, </l>
            <l>To give desert its due, scorne flatterie. </l>
            <l>But thou art blind, they say, and do'st not know </l>
            <l>On what, or whom thou do'st thy wealth bestow. </l>
            <l>Thy judgement rather than thy eyes are blind, </l>
            <l>In my opinion, else thou couldst not find </l>
            <l>Such ominous distinctions 'twixt true worth </l>
            <l>And dunghill Doublets, muskt and sented forth: </l>
            <l>The Gallants Feather, and his tatling Spurre, </l>
            <l>The Citie Miser wrapt in's Neighbours Furre, </l>
            <l>The Countrey-dolthead Mungrell brought to Land, </l>
            <l>Though illegitimate, is by thy hand </l>
            <l>Advanc'd above the ranke of Carters sonne, </l>
            <l>(Reserv'd for laughter till his wealth is done) </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-027-a"/>
            <l>Gulls were ordain'd wits pastime, 'tis their fate </l>
            <l>To be wits slave, though on wits gold they bate. </l>
            <l>How aptly thou hast fan●i'd out their Mates? </l>
            <l>On vitious Gallants still diseases waites, </l>
            <l>Accompanied with pride and infamy, </l>
            <l>Base sonne and daughter to civility. </l>
            <l>On your ingrossing Usurer attends </l>
            <l>Legions of tim'rous heart-quakes, that portends </l>
            <l>Some eminent danger, masqu'd with Vailes of gold, </l>
            <l>Immur'd in dung that doth his conscience hold. </l>
            <l>Your plodding Country-man, whose subtill shift </l>
            <l>Imploy'd to vex his neighbours by his thrift; </l>
            <l>Continuall sutes in Law, a Termes vexation </l>
            <l>Consumes more angels than a long Vacation. </l>
            <l>His misery's in this, his painefull evill </l>
            <l>Can never gaine 'bove factor for the devill. </l>
            <l>Then what are all these blest in, save the Ore </l>
            <l>That guilds their lives, yet leaves their souls most poore? </l>
            <l>Shou'd I with strict severenesse use my skill </l>
            <l>In the deepe search of folly, wade my quill </l>
            <l>Through pitchy Seas of Satyrisme, I might </l>
            <l>Rip up thy parched intrals, and incite </l>
            <l>Each sence we master, to grow fat, and swell </l>
            <l>With uncurb'd laughter; let my whispers tell, </l>
            <l>Thou do'st reside in ignorance, and braggs </l>
            <l>Most in thy gorgeous vestments, when the raggs </l>
            <l>Of poverty's more pretious: what upholds </l>
            <l>Thy pride but indiscretion? Will controules </l>
            <l>The Law of reason, and when these doe reele, </l>
            <l>Thy state is unsupported, and thy wheele </l>
            <l>Broke in despight of frownes; thou canst not see </l>
            <l>(As we doe) into thine owne misery. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-027-b"/>
            <l>Wrack not thy wealth on errors, but require </l>
            <l>More brawny-nerv'd assistance, whose pure fire </l>
            <l>Cohabits with true judgement; wisdome can </l>
            <l>Envolv'd in reason, make the soule of man </l>
            <l>Run up the Pyramids of praise, and shew </l>
            <l>The world new wayes to honor thee. Then know </l>
            <l>Thy choyce of Votaries; the Poet will </l>
            <l>Practise his Arts Encomions, and distill </l>
            <l>His rich harmonious Raptures that shall raise </l>
            <l>A Fabrick to thy name, 'bove th' reach of praise, </l>
            <l>Vertues white essence next in order shall▪ </l>
            <l>Accompani'd with Patience, offer all </l>
            <l>Her stock of goodnesse, and the Scholler turne </l>
            <l>His books to Martyrs, at thy Altar burne. </l>
            <l>Europe must needs adore thee; wonder more </l>
            <l>To see the Scholler rich, the Miser poore. </l>
            <l>Poets shall then disdaine th● thred-bare Bride, </l>
            <l>When silver-fac'd Pecunia is ally'd </l>
            <l>To their ingenious Pockets; Oh 'twould be, </l>
            <l>Me thinks a glorious metamorphosie▪ </l>
            <l>But why am I thus passionate, and speake </l>
            <l>Of such impossibilities, to breake </l>
            <l>My Optick Science? Well, the world may see, </l>
            <l>I wou'd hav't so; though Fortune lowres on mee, </l>
            <l>No matter, use your Envie, thou shalt be </l>
            <l>Enricht with nothing▪ save inconstancie. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e14270">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-028-a"/>
            <head>To Clarinda upon her inconstancie. </head>
            <l>I Finde; you are no Changeling, for indeed </l>
            <l>You can dissemble neatly, and still feed </l>
            <l>My hopelesse comforts with your hearty vowes, </l>
            <l>That neither Faith, nor Constancie allowes: </l>
            <l>I blush to speake thy weaknesse, prythee why </l>
            <l>Do'st thou make black thy tongue with perjury? </l>
            <l>Wantons doe often use it, canst thou be </l>
            <l>A faithlesse Wanton, and so faire a Shee? </l>
            <l>I dare not say you love me, your reply </l>
            <l>Will then ungently give my tongue the lye. </l>
            <l>You are not true as I am, but still prove </l>
            <l>A seeming Saint, in vow'd dissembling love. </l>
            <l>Yet know, I love you, and would have you doe </l>
            <l>A miracle in Woman, to be true. </l>
            <l>What constancie canst thou expect from any, </l>
            <l>That art so fickle, and canst love so many? </l>
            <l>I prythee leave dissembling, doe not gloze, </l>
            <l>Or guild thy words with vowes, make silver dro●●e; </l>
            <l>Thy vowes are farre more pretious; gold to them, </l>
            <l>Is as a Leaden Crowne to a Diadem: </l>
            <l>Which vowes you'l use so often, that they'l be </l>
            <l>The chiefest witnesse 'gainst thy guilt and thee. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e14520">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-028-b"/>
            <head>To his much honoured friend Master Robert Newsteade Gent. </head>
            <l>TO rank thee friend, amongst my best of friends, </l>
            <l>For thy Quotidian favours, makes amends, </l>
            <l>In part, though not in all; and then againe, </l>
            <l>When I conceive the fickle state of men, </l>
            <l>How soone their faith's extinct, how quickly gone, </l>
            <l>Like to a thing but newly thought upon: </l>
            <l>My feare begets a passion, and doth strive </l>
            <l>To hugge my friends, and keepe their names alive. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e14630">
            <head>To his good friend M. <hi>H. D.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>FRiend, I must blame thee, yet I thank thee too: </l>
            <l>Thou hast done that which many would not doe; </l>
            <l>For when my lines lay open to your view, </l>
            <l>Begot by me, yet fetch'd their breath from you, </l>
            <l>Through your perswasions, and entreaty, I </l>
            <l>Have thrust my Rimes into the worlds wide eye, </l>
            <l>Where I expect their censure, yet I sweare, </l>
            <l>Be't good, or bad, thou shalt embrace thy share. </l>
            <l>Thy verse my Verse to th'world doth Usher in; </l>
            <l>Not to requite thee then 'twere held a sin: </l>
            <l>Nor will I be too lavish in thy praise, </l>
            <l>(Thy worth alone may gaine Poetick bayes) </l>
            <l>All that I'le doe, if any count me rude, </l>
            <l>Is to repell the brand, Ingratitude. </l>
            <closer>
              <signed>Io. Tatham. </signed>
            </closer>
          </div>
          <div type="ode" xml:id="ep000824-e14820">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-029-a"/>
            <head>An Ode Acrostick-wise on the Vertuous Gentlewoman, Mistris A. P. </head>
            <lg>
              <l>Amongst so many, whose desire </l>
              <l>Lives fresh thy goodnesse to admire, </l>
              <l>I doe present my Votes, to be </l>
              <l>Crowned with thy Resplendencie. </l>
              <l>Enjoy thou Beautie, whose desarts </l>
              <l>Proclaime thee Mistris of all hearts, </l>
              <l>Vertues blessing, with those Graces </l>
              <l>Raigning in their proper places, </l>
              <l>Dayning now to wait on thee, </l>
              <l>Yeelding to thy Soveraigntie. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And while the starres shall grace the Skyes, </l>
              <l>Like sparkes of light from Cynthia's eyes, </l>
              <l>Imbrace more blessings than can bee </l>
              <l>Cast by Arithmetick on thee, </l>
              <l>Enrich thy Nuptials with a Guest, </l>
              <l>Proud to harbour in thy Brest; </l>
              <l>Vesta with her Virgin Crue, </l>
              <l>Richly deckt, to wait on you, </l>
              <l>Devoted comes, and at your Shrine </l>
              <l>Yssues forth her Offering. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-029-b"/>
              <l>Aurora's sence-delighting Flowers </l>
              <l>Leave to deck her fragrant Bowers, </l>
              <l>Indeared to your ever Spring, </l>
              <l>Courting Philomel to sing </l>
              <l>Encomiasticks, as your due, </l>
              <l>Purchas'd by those gifts which you </l>
              <l>Vouchsaf'd to lend them, to adorne </l>
              <l>Rose-cheek'd and nixious-finger'd Morne; </l>
              <l>Distilled Pearles from your bright eyes, </l>
              <l>Yeelds them their Morning Sacrifice. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And now the Musick of the Spheares </l>
              <l>Lent by you, invites all eares; </l>
              <l>Iuventa 'maz'd from whence it came, </l>
              <l>Comes to meet your Pophian flame, </l>
              <l>Early brings to please your sense, </l>
              <l>Pauch●ian Fumes, rich Frankincense, </l>
              <l>Vestituted with delight, </l>
              <l>Resplendent as the Morning bright, </l>
              <l>Dis-●obes her selfe, and leaves in truth </l>
              <l>You the onely Queene of Youth. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Aglaia, with her Sisters two, </l>
              <l>Likewise comes to wait on you; </l>
              <l>Injur'd Virgins to you flye, </l>
              <l>Craving shelter from your eye, </l>
              <l>Eterniz'd by those Blessings which </l>
              <l>Presag'd their Vertues should enrich, </l>
              <l>Vniting there an ardent Zone, </l>
              <l>Reason tells is you alone; </l>
              <l>Dryades, with all their powers </l>
              <l>You command, and they are yours▪ </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-030-a"/>
              <l>Arabian Phoenix needs must bee </l>
              <l>Lesse rare than Fly, compar'd to thee; </l>
              <l>Iove in revenge, and envying me●, </l>
              <l>Chain'd himselfe, to dote on thee; </l>
              <l>Emperious Love hath lost his heart, </l>
              <l>Pretending thou hast got his Dart; </l>
              <l>Vowes must be onely made to thee, </l>
              <l>Releasing Loves captivitie; </l>
              <l>Denie not your perfections true; </l>
              <l>Youths Queene (and all) doth rest in you. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>All Beauties, Graces, Vertues bee </l>
              <l>Lively pencil'd out in thee: </l>
              <l>In thy haire we may discrie </l>
              <l>Chast Love sit in majestie; </l>
              <l>Eyes thou hast, by which the Sunne </l>
              <l>Plyes his course, ere day be done; </l>
              <l>Voyce? the Nightingales sweet throat, </l>
              <l>Runs hoarsely to thy Dorick note: </l>
              <l>Dance? did the rare Penelope </l>
              <l>Yet live, she needs must yeeld to thee: </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>As in the Spheare of Goodnesse, ev'ry Sence </l>
              <l>Hath by instinct in you their Residence. </l>
            </lg>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e15780">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-030-b"/>
            <head>To Philomel. </head>
            <l>LEave Philomel, to make thy moane, </l>
            <l>'Tis I have cause to grieve alone: </l>
            <l>Thy Woes had periods; mine must be </l>
            <l>Invaded with fresh Crueltie. </l>
            <l>The Joyes I have, are such as may </l>
            <l>Make the greene Spring a Winters day▪ </l>
            <l>Or such as when desir'd, doe take </l>
            <l>A course to kill, for pitty sake. </l>
            <l>Cease then thy noyse of woe, unlesse </l>
            <l>Thou'lt grieve for my unhappinesse. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e15920">
            <head>To Clarinda. </head>
            <l>THat I did love thee, summon up my Vowes, </l>
            <l>As uncorrupted witnesses allowes </l>
            <l>No partialitie; peruse my truth, </l>
            <l>Unspotted, as th'immaculate zeale of youth, </l>
            <l>Unfained, as the Orasons of Saints, </l>
            <l>Expird, as Altars Incense, that acquaints </l>
            <l>Heav'n with sincere devotion; that I did </l>
            <l>Adore each feature, as well seene as hid; </l>
            <l>Examine each particular line and phrase </l>
            <l>My doting fancie offer'd to thy praise; </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-031-a"/>
            <l>That every smile enliven'd my dull sence; </l>
            <l>Search but the custome of thy influence, </l>
            <l>And it appeares in Characters of blisse, </l>
            <l>No Paradise so pleasing as a kisse; </l>
            <l>That I did deeme thy polisht Ivory brow, </l>
            <l>A firmament, wherein twin-starres allow </l>
            <l>A greater lustre than the pride of Heaven, </l>
            <l>Contracted t'a full sky-light, could have given </l>
            <l>Us Mortals Ask the World, and then o're which </l>
            <l>A Mount of Alabaster does enrich </l>
            <l>Thy smooth Ermin-like forehead, to thy cheekes, </l>
            <l>The stock of Flora for a refuge seekes. </l>
            <l>Those Tresses which thou wear'st are golden snares, </l>
            <l>Though falsly some did nominate them haires. </l>
            <l>The Affrick Coralls on thy ruby lips </l>
            <l>Mix their perfections, ●nd in Nupti●ll skips </l>
            <l>Trip to the Spheare-like Musick of thy voyce </l>
            <l>Able to charme a Seraphin; the choyce </l>
            <l>Electrum in your neck; your azure veines </l>
            <l>On snowy beds discypher to the Swaines </l>
            <l>The Tempe of true happinesse, when they </l>
            <l>By my command did to 'em homage pay. </l>
            <l>I set thee forth in Verse, rais'd thee so high, </l>
            <l>All sinn'd, that breath'd thee lesse than Deity. </l>
            <l>My praises out-did Nature, thou wert then </l>
            <l>The only subject for my Muse and Pen. </l>
            <l>The world shall likewise testifie; but here— </l>
            <l>Yet wisedome bids me stop: I will not sweare, </l>
            <l>Though I have cause to execrate thy faith, </l>
            <l>Which is a blessing your sexe seldome hath. </l>
            <l>I will omit all rashnesse, only this, </l>
            <l>Confute thy soule even in its hope of blisse. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-031-b"/>
            <l>False and neglectfull Woman, hadst thou bin </l>
            <l>Deformed in thy person, as thy sin, </l>
            <l>I sho'd have then abhorr'd thee, and my eyes </l>
            <l>Perceiv'd the strong infection in thee lyes. </l>
            <l>Thou art not faire; 'twas only Fancy led </l>
            <l>Me to <hi></hi>Hyperbole's; thy cheeks once red </l>
            <l>Colour'd by me, thy eyes, lips, hands and all, </l>
            <l>In Lethe have deserving Funerall. </l>
            <l>Thy breath infects as-killing pestilence; </l>
            <l>No more Panchayan Gums, choyce Frankincence, </l>
            <l>Shall grace it with resemblance; thou art </l>
            <l>Of an AEthiopian colour ev'ry part; </l>
            <l>Pencil'd by Shame and Infamy: thy name </l>
            <l>Rac'd forth the Role of Constancy and Fame. </l>
            <l>The world only records thy falshood; try </l>
            <l>If thou canst winne me to credulity, </l>
            <l>That thou didst love me once, and check each tong, </l>
            <l>For it's aspertion 'tis no potent wrong, </l>
            <l>Lesse vindicated; but my faculties </l>
            <l>Abjure thee now, though once thy Votaries, </l>
            <l>And cannot retaine beliefe Colusive you </l>
            <l>Were ever reall, but in being untrue; </l>
            <l>That only thou wert made for; else thy brest </l>
            <l>Would ne're have covetted a new imprest: </l>
            <l>But, like the constant Emerauld, have kept </l>
            <l>Its primitive, stamp, and purity; falshood slept </l>
            <l>In ignorance: O yee powers, can there be </l>
            <l>An absolution for impiety? </l>
            <l>If you'l decline from Justice, then you may </l>
            <l>Flatter her erring hopes with a long day </l>
            <l>Of fatall tryall, whose conviction must </l>
            <l>Precipitate her gloryes into dust </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-032-a"/>
            <l>Sure, though prolong'd, the difference then will be; </l>
            <l>Th'insulting freedome chain'd, my bondage free. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e16780">
            <head>The Authors Dreame. </head>
            <l>WHen as my dull and weary'd eyes, had long </l>
            <l>With tedious watchings, 'bout my temples hung; </l>
            <l>The vale of sleepe like a long wasted Lamp, </l>
            <l>Smother'd, went out, and fell into a damp: </l>
            <l>My sences tasting of some happinesse, </l>
            <l>Ambition rose, and strove for further blisse, </l>
            <l>Till that me thought, an Eccho in my eare, </l>
            <l>Bad, rise and follow me, why sleep'st thou here? </l>
            <l>With that a Winter-sweat did over-spread </l>
            <l>My bloodlesse cheekes as in amazement dead; </l>
            <l>Each limb did shake, my panting heart did knell </l>
            <l>Death's sad unwelcome tone, Nights-passing-bell; </l>
            <l>The selfe-same voyce againe did seeme to be </l>
            <l>The comforter of my sad hopes and me. </l>
            <l>Musick possest mine eares, in that I then </l>
            <l>Contemn'd my feares, and seem'd awake agen. </l>
            <l>No sooner had my eares enjoy'd so rare </l>
            <l>Unlook'd for pleasures, but did straight repaire </l>
            <l>A Lady of that beauty (clad in white) </l>
            <l>As seem'd to out-face Day, and conquer Night. </l>
            <l>Her haire dishevel'd hung, about her browes </l>
            <l>A wreath of Lawrell; on her garments, vowes </l>
            <l>Of perjur'd Lovers, mingled with the blood </l>
            <l>Of some poore injur'd creature, that withstood </l>
            <l>No ill-tempestuous storme in hope to gaine </l>
            <l>For her pure constancie th' Elizian Plaine; </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-032-b"/>
            <l>When as their spotted soules as black as hell, </l>
            <l>Shall choake themselves with vows in Pluto's Cell. </l>
            <l>Her brests not bare, but in a modest manner, </l>
            <l>Shew the pure colour of true Lovers Banner. </l>
            <l>Under the which they hold their second faith, </l>
            <l>(Those spungy pearlesse Twins the females hath) </l>
            <l>About which blood a pretious stone was plac'd, </l>
            <l>Such, as had Venus worne, it wo'd have grac'd </l>
            <l>Her wanton beauty, and have forc'd the Boy </l>
            <l>T'a'left his dallying, and the sport enjoy. </l>
            <l>On th'other side whereas black vowes doe make </l>
            <l>A darknesse shadow, brightnesse does pertake </l>
            <l>Of golden Charecters, that who so see, </l>
            <l>Must by those golden letters guided be. </l>
            <l>Rich Sandals fetcht from farre, of purest gold, </l>
            <l>Did her unvalu'd feet in pleasure hold, </l>
            <l>As white as is the purest morning milk, </l>
            <l>And seem'd insnar'd with fine Arabian silk. </l>
            <l>With her two Virgins also clad in white, </l>
            <l>Supporting on each side this Queene of light. </l>
            <l>Upon each garment artificially </l>
            <l>Was interweav'd a pearle distilled eye, </l>
            <l>Sad, discontented, languisht, broken hearts, </l>
            <l>Feares, teares, sighes, sobs, laments, and piercing darts. </l>
            <l>Crosse Fates, friends frownes (in gold) the Parents hate, </l>
            <l>Seem'd their contentions to expostulate, </l>
            <l>With that their soules sweet Organs tun'd. Forbeare; </l>
            <l>Let thy feares vanish, we shall bring thee where </l>
            <l>Death keepes his Court, the sable irksome Cell </l>
            <l>Of murdering soules, where sinnes with Furies dwell: </l>
            <l>There thou shalt see each broken Vow to have </l>
            <l>Deserved punishment: dead, want a Grave. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-033-a"/>
            <l>Yet feare not Youth, for through the ayre wee'l hover, </l>
            <l>And with our robes of truth thy doubts will cover. </l>
            <l>My feares then left me, and we mounted straight </l>
            <l>On a wing'd Chariot they enjoyn'd to waite </l>
            <l>For us, drawne with foure milk-white Doves; </l>
            <l>Such as dame <hi></hi>Venus's pleas'd with, when her Loves </l>
            <l>Shee meanes to visit; through the ayre than wee, </l>
            <l>Swifter than nimble-footed Mercury </l>
            <l>Did fly.— At length </l>
            <l>Such shrill confusions beat into my eares, </l>
            <l>As wo'd have sunk the world, dissolv'd the spheares: </l>
            <l>But Truth my still supporter, bade me be </l>
            <l>No whit yet daunted, for I soone sho'd see </l>
            <l>Horrours of worse affrightments; with that shake </l>
            <l>The lower earth, and from a Sulphurous lake </l>
            <l>Flew flames of quenchlesse fier, with the smoake </l>
            <l>Of loathsome brimstone, eating trees of Oake. </l>
            <l>The dismall noyse of screech-Owles, hissing Snakes, </l>
            <l>To●ds, Adders, Monsters, and what else pertakes </l>
            <l>Of ugly poyson, seem'd a Cavalere, </l>
            <l>And fellow partner with all creatures there: </l>
            <l>In that fal● teares made furrowes in my cheekes, </l>
            <l>And for some reconciliation seekes; </l>
            <l>With that demanding of my guider Truth, </l>
            <l>What place that was? she answer'd, pretty Youth, </l>
            <l>A place where false neglectfull Lovers be; </l>
            <l>Such as have cancell'd faith and loyalty. </l>
            <l>This is the place where thy disdainefull Faire </l>
            <l>Shall be created new; teare her bright haire; </l>
            <l>Rejoyce to have a Serpent to her bed, </l>
            <l>And by deformed monsters ravished. </l>
            <l>My panting soule then sunk, but tender shee </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-033-b"/>
            <l>Rais'd me againe, demanding straight of mee </l>
            <l>The reason of that passion; I reply'd, </l>
            <l>I lov'd her still: though Reason it deny'd: </l>
            <l>Shall she for whom my studies I have spent, </l>
            <l>(Faire Truth) receive this doome and punishment? </l>
            <l>Shall Monsters then enjoy what I before </l>
            <l>Did Idolize, and as my Saint adore? </l>
            <l>Shall they suck hony from so rich a Hive, </l>
            <l>And glut themselves with that each soule alive </l>
            <l>Wo'd humbly kneele for: O, shall they then be </l>
            <l>The only meanes t'enlarge my misery? </l>
            <l>Truth's answer was, wee'l leave this dolefull place; </l>
            <l>Banish distrust, wee'l mend our slow-wing'd pace, </l>
            <l>And drive thee to the Tempe of content, </l>
            <l>Where Love shall laugh at Falshoods banishment, </l>
            <l>And in dispight of Envie, shall obtaine </l>
            <l>The feeling welcome of his heart againe. </l>
            <l>Where Pyramus and Thisbe live in blisse, </l>
            <l>And there enjoy each other with a kisse. </l>
            <l>Then did we drive our Chariot through a Grove </l>
            <l>Of Mayden-flowers, where the Queene of Love </l>
            <l>Met with her Martialist, and present came </l>
            <l>With due salutes, and homage to Truths name. </l>
            <l>The Chariot staid, we lighted, and then went </l>
            <l>Into a place call'd <hi>Loves true ravishment</hi>. </l>
            <l>Where e'ry pretty Bird in warbling notes, </l>
            <l>Did give us entertainement with their Votes. </l>
            <l>Each Lover had his Mate, and on the Greene </l>
            <l>Did sport and play, and blush because o're-seene, </l>
            <l>Exchanging kisses, in so much that I </l>
            <l>Did emulate their candy'd jollity. </l>
            <l>The Virgins that did waite upon our Queene, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-034-a"/>
            <l>Left her with me, and went into a Greene, </l>
            <l>Where two sweet Youths, clad in a crimson dye, </l>
            <l>Did give 'em entertainment to the eye. </l>
            <l>Joyes met with joyes, the Quiristers did sing, </l>
            <l>As welcoming the wanton youthfull Spring, </l>
            <l>Where in an Arbour, crown'd with Violets, </l>
            <l>Each with his Mate new happinesse begets. </l>
            <l>Truth's smiling Aspect with her Affrick gemms, </l>
            <l>Offer'd a whisper to me, and condemnes </l>
            <l>My former incredulity, then gave </l>
            <l>Me her advice to purchase ought they have: </l>
            <l>Opens her richest Caskenet, and shewes </l>
            <l>The bed of Odours, where th' Elizian Rose, </l>
            <l>The sence-delighting Violets, and th'rest </l>
            <l>Of <hi></hi>Flora's pride, are in a Garland drest, </l>
            <l>Compass'd about with little hoops of Glasse, </l>
            <l>Reflecting on each cheeke that by 'em passe. </l>
            <l>The ground-work honey, and the Juice of love, </l>
            <l>The Mornes refreshment. Nectar cast by Iove, </l>
            <l>(Instead of dew) upon their colour'd veynes, </l>
            <l>With oyle of Constancy to keepe from steynes </l>
            <l>Of every ruder hand, and there they lye </l>
            <l>Unpluckt by any, save Maturity. </l>
            <l>No mervaile then Winter cannot afford </l>
            <l>Us such Redolent Miracles, when th'hord </l>
            <l>And Closet that retaynes 'em, is a place </l>
            <l>Impal'd with all contents, and Beauties Chase, </l>
            <l>A Park where Harts keepe their Imperious way </l>
            <l>Without usurping Tyrants, they can pay </l>
            <l>Their Morne-devotion without losse of life, </l>
            <l>Exactions trouble, or a womb of strife: </l>
            <l>Here they like Doves, use Nature in her kinde, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-034-b"/>
            <l>Mutually live each with his Mate, refinde </l>
            <l>From the grosse errors dwell in Mortalls, who </l>
            <l>Think 'tis enough, in that they onely wooe, </l>
            <l>Without a thought of fervency, if one </l>
            <l>(A Woman, for none else wo'd be a stone) </l>
            <l>Finds an incurable folly to invade </l>
            <l>Her Lover, called passion, sh'as a Trade, </l>
            <l>Though 'twill scarce get her living, yet shee'l grow </l>
            <l>Fat with insulting o're her Patients woe, </l>
            <l>Which custome's here a Stranger; here, said Truth, </l>
            <l>Lawes are enacted to entreasure Youth; </l>
            <l>Here Flora's Spring, Autumne, and chequer'd May, </l>
            <l>The pleasing Gales of Zephyres doe convay; </l>
            <l>And this their Winter Mansion: Yet they know </l>
            <l>No frosty finger can assault 'em so. </l>
            <l>Here they inhabit without nipping paine, </l>
            <l>'Till gentle Zephyres post▪ 'em back againe, </l>
            <l>To kisse the worlds knowne Wanton, then ensues </l>
            <l>Th'unused rashnesse that their births abuse; </l>
            <l>Each wilfull finger and depraving hand </l>
            <l>With Insolency robs, uses command </l>
            <l>(Instead of milde entreaties) teares from thence </l>
            <l>The infancy of their sprung influence: </l>
            <l>Crops the sweet Virgin flower before the age </l>
            <l>Makes it compleatly ripe, while the sad Bryer, </l>
            <l>Mother to those rich gemms, embraces fier; </l>
            <l>Or else left destitute: who does become </l>
            <l>Barren in nought but griefe, her martyrdome. </l>
            <l>Oh irreligious Mortalls, see your error: </l>
            <l>Covetous in nothing but in hoording Treasure, </l>
            <l>Which last like Roses, leaving once their Tree, </l>
            <l>Becomes inconstant through inconstancie. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-035-a"/>
            <l>Then know the diff'rence, and invest thy selfe </l>
            <l>With whiter thoughts, banish respect of pelfe, </l>
            <l>That like a hellish Advocate delude </l>
            <l>Mans sence into a glittering servitude: </l>
            <l>Which choakes 'em in disgestion; cut the tye </l>
            <l>Which binds thee to thy ruine, let 'em be </l>
            <l>Disjoyn'd for ever, and deeme constancie </l>
            <l>The only meanes of Fortune, for without </l>
            <l>Such resolutions never goe about </l>
            <l>To stile thy selfe a Lover; 'tis a thing </l>
            <l>Abhorr'd in reall Actions, 'twill not bring </l>
            <l>Mortality to th'pleasure sign'd for thee, </l>
            <l>This sacred <hi></hi>Tempe's true felicity: </l>
            <l>Where no tempestuous storme of Parents hate, </l>
            <l>Shall dare to crosse thy e're propitious Fate. </l>
            <l>Thy Love and thee 'mongst th'rest in sweet content, </l>
            <l>Shall spin your times in endlesse merriment: </l>
            <l>But if that she be obstinate, and still </l>
            <l>Disdaines our dread command and pow'rfull will: </l>
            <l>I'le send a summon by our blindfold Boy, </l>
            <l>That shall convert to terror ev'ry joy. </l>
            <l>Goe tell the lower world what you have seene, </l>
            <l>As you doe honor us a Mayden Queene: </l>
            <l>This have I shewn you, that the world may know, </l>
            <l>What power we have, and what to us they owe. </l>
            <l>Then post you back, you winged Messengers, </l>
            <l>And leave him where we found him; Time refers </l>
            <l>No other conference, for the gladsome Day </l>
            <l>Appeares; then hence, pack on, make hast away, </l>
            <l>For feare our theevish frosty-bearded Time, </l>
            <l>Rushes through th'speares too fast, and Phoebus shine. </l>
            <l>With that they mounted me, and in the space </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-035-b"/>
            <l>Of one poore minute brought me to the place </l>
            <l>Where first they found me, that my giddy braine </l>
            <l>Struck with amaze, knew not from whence I came, </l>
            <l>'Till gentle Morpheus, that did first surprize </l>
            <l>My weaken'd sences had unlock'd mine eyes, </l>
            <l>And gave free passage to each stretching part, </l>
            <l>By the pure skill of his ne're failing Art. </l>
            <l>Then kinde Aurora grac't me with a smile, </l>
            <l>And Phoebus welcom'd me from my exile. </l>
            <l>In that my late dull spirits then were apt </l>
            <l>To entertaine secrets in Riddles wrapt. </l>
            <l>Then did I think upon my former charge, </l>
            <l>Giv'n by my guider Truth to me at large. </l>
            <l>And all those pleasures I that night did see, </l>
            <l>Grew fresh and pleasant in my memory: </l>
            <l>That I not disobeying her command, </l>
            <l>Like a true Subject, in another land </l>
            <l>In trust for her, must let her praises be </l>
            <l>Blazon'd by Fames guilt Trump of Poesie. </l>
            <l>And first unto my Dearest as a friend, </l>
            <l>I did unfold my Dreame, and recommend </l>
            <l>Each passage I had seene, time, place, and where </l>
            <l>Of paine, joy, griefe, or blisse, she might have share. </l>
            <l>But shee not giving credit or beliefe </l>
            <l>To any such weake fictions, nor reliefe </l>
            <l>To me, or any others; but doth still </l>
            <l>Continue in her bad obdurate will. </l>
            <l>Leave her I must; but let her know, that face </l>
            <l>Shall live to be the subject of disgrace. </l>
            <l>Nor shall one teare be shed in pitty; shee </l>
            <l>That liv'd disdainfull, shall disdained be. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e19670">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-036-a"/>
            <head>To Cupid. </head>
            <l>CVpid, I'm inflam'd with feare, </l>
            <l>Lest her beauty bribes thy care; </l>
            <l>Shee's sufficient to intice </l>
            <l>Vertue out of Paradice; </l>
            <l>When her breathings kisse her lips, </l>
            <l>Expired Gums and Odours skips; </l>
            <l>Every Accent is a charme, </l>
            <l>And her circle is her arme, </l>
            <l>In the which shee'l raise or lay, </l>
            <l>Man or spirit, flesh or clay; </l>
            <l>Shee's an Artist that delights </l>
            <l>More in Conquests than in fights, </l>
            <l>'Tis her use to fetter those </l>
            <l>Icy-bodies she has chose </l>
            <l>(In her owne reserv'd intent, </l>
            <l>T'appeare by it more excellent) </l>
            <l>To her bright Phebean haire, </l>
            <l>Where perfum'd M●anders are; </l>
            <l>In such a prison Iove, or thee </l>
            <l>Wo'd descend and Captive bee. </l>
            <l>But, here's the glory crownes her most, </l>
            <l>Shee dissolves those lumps of frost, </l>
            <l>And gives it active blood and fire, </l>
            <l>(Rather wonder, than desire) </l>
            <l>Makes it forme; for, from her eye, </l>
            <l>A hot Promethean flame does flye, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-036-b"/>
            <l>And penetrates so ev'ry brest, </l>
            <l>Th'augmenting flames cann't be exprest. </l>
            <l>In that shee only erres in part, </l>
            <l>'Tis wilfulnesse, not want of Art. </l>
            <l>Shee shoots her scorching beames too fast, </l>
            <l>Piles flame on flame, and blast on blast; </l>
            <l>And then she leaves him in his flame, </l>
            <l>Though one poore teare wo'd quench the sam●▪ </l>
            <l>Her oyl'd expressions shee did gaine, </l>
            <l>From the false Mercurian trayne. </l>
            <l>'Tis a language windes the ●ares </l>
            <l>To admiration, gulls the Spheares; </l>
            <l>Yet all these, rarities are us'd </l>
            <l>To the contrary sence, therefore abus'd. </l>
            <l>Then Cupid, now thou know'st by me, </l>
            <l>How to shunne her flattery: </l>
            <l>Be thy selfe, and let her know, </l>
            <l>Beauty does a reverence owe </l>
            <l>To thy powerfull frowne: goe play </l>
            <l>My part a while, and for me say, </l>
            <l>(If that her smiles don't bribe thy wit) </l>
            <l>Rather for scorne than praise she's fit. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e20240">
            <head>Cupids Summons. </head>
            <l>FAirest Mortall, think not I </l>
            <l>Priviledge a starre-like eye, </l>
            <l>Or the choycest Faire on earth; </l>
            <l>I can blast 'em in their birth: </l>
            <l>Yet that you might feele desires, </l>
            <l>Quenching Loves Idalian fires. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-037-a"/>
            <l>'Mongst a many Beauties more, </l>
            <l>I preserv'd thee to adore </l>
            <l>My Deity: but now I see </l>
            <l>Thou disdain'st my power and me. </l>
            <l>Therefore by my Paphian Bow </l>
            <l>My commands must let you know, </l>
            <l>That a strange complaint of late, </l>
            <l>Beat a parley at my Gate; </l>
            <l>And so entred, that the Gods </l>
            <l>With that uprore grew at odds: </l>
            <l>In so much that they me sent </l>
            <l>Messenger of punishment, </l>
            <l>In my Mothers sacred name, </l>
            <l>You a Traitor to proclame </l>
            <l>'Gainst the Lawes of Love and Beauty. </l>
            <l>And to what you owe by duty </l>
            <l>To th'AEthereall powers and me, </l>
            <l>Cancel'd through Inconstancie. </l>
            <l>By my Bow and flaming Dart, </l>
            <l>By the Lovers bleeding hart, </l>
            <l>By the hand, and by the glove: </l>
            <l>By the eye that captiv'd Iove, </l>
            <l>I command and summon thee, </l>
            <l>At Loves Barre to answer mee, </l>
            <l>To what we shall there object, </l>
            <l>'Gainst thy scorne and base neglect: </l>
            <l>Faile not creature, as you will </l>
            <l>Answer, your ensuing ill. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e20640">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-037-b"/>
            <head>The Oath after appearance. </head>
            <l>PAle-cheek'd Mortall, now your eyes </l>
            <l>Returne their lustre to the skyes: </l>
            <l>No hue of Rosie-red doth guide </l>
            <l>The welcome Lilyes, as a Bride: </l>
            <l>Nor are th'Lilyes fresh, and gay, </l>
            <l>As they were the other day. </l>
            <l>The present guilt doth make it knowne, </l>
            <l>Beautie lent, is not your owne. </l>
            <l>Venus now the Queene of Love, </l>
            <l>Is in presence, and must prove </l>
            <l>You a disobedient heire </l>
            <l>To her glorious Hemisphere. </l>
            <l>Paphos Archer hates to owne </l>
            <l>You a sister to his throne: </l>
            <l>And must here as witnesse be </l>
            <l>To your black-mouth'd perjury; </l>
            <l>Therefore on this gold-leaf'd booke, </l>
            <l>In which Lovers oft doe looke, </l>
            <l>Lay your hands, if you be free </l>
            <l>From usurping Tyranny, </l>
            <l>From the many sighes and teares </l>
            <l>Lovers use, their nightly feares: </l>
            <l>From their passions, folded armes, </l>
            <l>Lull'd asleepe with Syrens charmes, </l>
            <l>From the murdering of a Hart, </l>
            <l>Glorying at th'excessive smart: </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-038-a"/>
            <l>From an angry lowring eye, </l>
            <l>Spying Lovers destiny, </l>
            <l>From a mock or scornefull smile, </l>
            <l>That kills, though pleases for a while. </l>
            <l>From a heart that harbors scorne, </l>
            <l>Leaving witlesse Youths forlorne: </l>
            <l>You may freely sweare, but see, </l>
            <l>The Rose has left his Treasury, </l>
            <l>Your starres are clouded; Rubies to </l>
            <l>Have left th'exchequer'd lips of you, </l>
            <l>And with sweet gales transported thence, </l>
            <l>To seeke a better residence. </l>
            <l>Hence to tryall Themis now </l>
            <l>'Gainst thy guilt doth set her brow </l>
            <l>And Conscience calls; you must appeare </l>
            <l>At Loves Barre, and answer there. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e21110">
            <head>His Allegations against Clarinda. </head>
            <l>TO you faire Cyprian Dame, I doe present, </l>
            <l>A languisht heart bound to imprisonment, </l>
            <l>(Without your faire releasement) to an eye </l>
            <l>Swel'd with Ambition, flat Conspiracie, </l>
            <l>Whose still aspiring soule did think 'twas duty, </l>
            <l>That greatest Mortalls shou'd admire her beauty. </l>
            <l>Nay, to that height Ambition had convey'd </l>
            <l>A strong beliefe, shee was not Earthly made, </l>
            <l>To entertaine a Love that had no power, </l>
            <l>Like Iove t'appeare in an Argolian showre, </l>
            <l>And when bright Sol his glorious Rayes displaide </l>
            <l>To grace the world, Conceit might soone perswade </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-038-b"/>
            <l>He● witlesse-fancie, his all-seeing eye, </l>
            <l>Borrow'd it's lustre from her brighter eye. </l>
            <l>Your selfe whom Paris well did judge to bee </l>
            <l>Heav'ns only peece, the fairer of the three, </l>
            <l>Shee wo'd not blush to say, had the Youth seene </l>
            <l>Her matchlesse Beauty, you had beene no Queene▪ </l>
            <l>And I in ignorance beleev'd the same, </l>
            <l>Blinded with love, so weav'd into a frame </l>
            <l>Of doting passions, having no alliance </l>
            <l>To my owne welfare, or her base defiance. </l>
            <l>For her I wasted all my houres in griefe, </l>
            <l>Expecting comfort, yet found no reliefe; </l>
            <l>Oft have I curst the Boy that first betray'd </l>
            <l>My hearts security, forcing me to wade </l>
            <l>Through th'ever sable streame of curst despaire, </l>
            <l>Or crimson gulfe of horror to the staire </l>
            <l>Of absolute madnesse, still ingendring ill, </l>
            <l>Now sink, then rise, subject to Fates sterne will: </l>
            <l>Not knowing thee to be of sacred line, </l>
            <l>Yet felt thy sting, but knew it not divine, </l>
            <l>As now I doe. But thought some Circes might </l>
            <l>With charmes bereave me of my bodies right, </l>
            <l>Forgive me sacred Deities; no more </l>
            <l>Will I blaspheme your goodnesse as before. </l>
            <l>No oaths or vowes of Hymenean right </l>
            <l>Could move her minde, no liquid teares invite </l>
            <l>Her heart to pitty, no disast'rous fate </l>
            <l>Of future mischiefe could accelerate </l>
            <l>My present death. But in her scornefull looke, </l>
            <l>I read her meaning as in Anger's booke, </l>
            <l>Sometimes with a dissembling smile retaines, </l>
            <l>Me longer to encrease my Love-sick paines. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-039-a"/>
            <l>As doth the cunning Doctor keepe in ure, </l>
            <l>His queasie Patient, and prolongs the Cure; </l>
            <l>Either to make his skill the brighter shine; </l>
            <l>Or else for feare his Patient sho'd combine </l>
            <l>With others, and he lose his Cure; e'ne so </l>
            <l>My cunning faire with smiles wou'd work too; </l>
            <l>Knowing that none but shee had equall power, </l>
            <l>To crowne my hopes, or blast 'em in an houre. </l>
            <l>And thus in endlesse passions did I lye, </l>
            <l>Ling'ring my breath, Deaths bare Epitomy. </l>
            <l>Nor would shee pitty that my spring-like age </l>
            <l>Sho'd dying, live, in Lovers Pilgrimage. </l>
            <l>When as th'impartiall Maids have beene at strife, </l>
            <l>Which first sho'd cut my thred, and end my life, </l>
            <l>Shee'd tyrannize o're my passions; nay, and more, </l>
            <l>Disdain'd your power, whose ayde I did implore; </l>
            <l>Telling me, Beauty had more than Love, </l>
            <l>Beauty was that strong charme enchaunted Iove. </l>
            <l>Then wo'd appeare such lightning from her eye, </l>
            <l>As seem'd to equall Iunos Majesty. </l>
            <l>Here doe I stand for to averre, and prove </l>
            <l>Her base, disloyall, and my constant love. </l>
            <l>Be just you Powers, and let your sentence be </l>
            <l>A punishment too good for perjury; </l>
            <l>That future times perusing of her shame, </l>
            <l>May praise your Justice, and abhorre her name; </l>
            <l>Without your sentence, all will soone aspire, </l>
            <l>Like proud Prometheus for to steale your fire: </l>
            <l>For th'envie of their Sex it is so deepe, </l>
            <l>They'l study nightly, and revenge in sleepe. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e21980">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-039-b"/>
            <head>The Censure of the Gods. <hi rend="stage">Present. <list>
                  <item>Iupiter </item>
                  <item>Sol. </item>
                  <item>Cupid </item>
                  <item>Vulcan </item>
                  <item>Iuno </item>
                  <item>Venus</item>
                </list>
              </hi>..... </head>
            <sp xml:id="ep000824-e22140">
              <speaker>Sol. </speaker>
              <l>WEe will not heare her answer, her reply </l>
              <l>Will but adde torments to her misery. </l>
              <l>Her guilt is too apparant, therefore wee </l>
              <l>For thy aspiring thoughts, doe banish thee </l>
              <l>From that best light, which earthly creatures doe </l>
              <l>Admire, and yearely pay a tribute to. </l>
              <l>Since from thine eye such sparks of lightning came, </l>
              <l>To blast our servant here wee'l vaile the same </l>
              <l>From thenceforth never— </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000824-e22250">
              <speaker>Venus. </speaker>
              <l>Forbeare; indeed you wrong me: her offence </l>
              <l>Requires a censure from our Excellence. </l>
              <l>Was shee not Ours, 'till her presumptuous soule </l>
              <l>(Inflam'd with Treason) sought for to controule </l>
              <l>Our all-commanding power, has shee not bin </l>
              <l>Stain'd with the folly of Narcissus sin? </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-040-a"/>
              <l>Has not her Beauty made the world below </l>
              <l>Forget that duty which to us they owe, </l>
              <l>Deeming our greatnesse but a fallacie, </l>
              <l>Mention'd by children in their infancie? </l>
              <l>Then know, to us, to us shee has done wrong, </l>
              <l>Corrupting Mortalls with her venom'd tongue, </l>
              <l>To cast mists on our greatnesse; since then shee </l>
              <l>Has not yet tasted of those sweets that wee, </l>
              <l>And those that live to love, doe still enjoy, </l>
              <l>All subject to the anger of my Boy: </l>
              <l>Shee shall be barren in that happinesse, </l>
              <l>And ne're embrace what hidden sweets there is </l>
              <l>In Lovers glances; but shall live to be </l>
              <l>The onely scorne to Loves posterity; </l>
              <l>Shee shall love one, and (living) love him so, </l>
              <l>Her love shall gaine his ha●e; his hate, her woe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000824-e22510">
              <speaker>Iupiter. </speaker>
              <l>This must not be, your censure doth appeare, </l>
              <l>Not from desert, but Envie; I dare cleare </l>
              <l>The innocent soule. Why barren? cause, you know </l>
              <l>The sweets already; none can merit so. </l>
              <l>Forsooth a kisse is envi'd, and a glance </l>
              <l>That does unbreath, mans spirits with a trance. </l>
              <l>Deni'd embraces is forbidden: what if I </l>
              <l>Endeavour to salute lip, breast, or— why? </l>
              <l>Wo'd blushes beat me thence? wooe her white hand </l>
              <l>To lead me to the fountaine, where I'le stand </l>
              <l>As cold as Marble, 'till her lips doe seale </l>
              <l>A Patent for my entrance, I'le appeale </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-040-b"/>
              <l>Not to your Will, but Love; ah, 'two'd arise </l>
              <l>Mutually sweet, when both hearts sympathize. </l>
              <l>Come, you forget your selfe; is it not rare, </l>
              <l>To have a woman honest, while she's faire? </l>
              <l>Which by your Sentence must be; 'faith, and then </l>
              <l>Shee'l grow more famous, though lesse lov'd of men. </l>
              <l>Had you beene charie of your Maidenhead, </l>
              <l>As you were of your Beautie, y'might ha' spread </l>
              <l>Your Ivorie Leafes to Sparrows, and they'd peck </l>
              <l>Those Letters out, which doe your Goddesse deck. </l>
              <l>Faire Maid, for that thou hast a stirring thought </l>
              <l>Of Greatnesse, hating all but such as brought </l>
              <l>A Showre like Us, into our Dana's Lap, </l>
              <l>We fancie thee too much, to let a Clap </l>
              <l>Of raging Thunder pierce thee— lend thine eare— </l>
              <l>What, is't a match? No: Why? thinkst thou they heare? </l>
              <l>We will adjourne the Court. Not? prythee say; </l>
              <l>I am incinder'd; kisse me, 'twill allay </l>
              <l>My heat: come, I will have it so; wee'l steale </l>
              <l>Into an obscure cranie, put the eye </l>
              <l>Of Phoebus out; my appetite does frye. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000824-e22880">
              <speaker>Vulcan. </speaker>
              <l>How Iupiter does looke now: 'tis a prey </l>
              <l>Wou'd make all sell their happ'nesse; by my fay </l>
              <l>A plump-cheek'd wench, and does deserve no lesse </l>
              <l>Honour than Venus, were she of her Dresse. </l>
              <l>Ile to her— don't beleeve him Lasse, his Wife </l>
              <l>Will blast thee with her anger, intrap thy life, </l>
              <l>As she did poore Alomena's; leane to mee </l>
              <l>Venus and I are out, Ile none but thee. </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-041-a"/>
              <l>And though I'm rough and sootie, yet I can </l>
              <l>Bestow on thee the pleasures rest in man, </l>
              <l>As well as he; my hoofe shall be set right, </l>
              <l>If thou sweare to let me taste delight; </l>
              <l>Or if thou wilt not sweare, or yeeld, yet bee </l>
              <l>A woman; winke, and let me feed on thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000824-e23080">
              <speaker>Iupiter. </speaker>
              <l>Thou art a sawcie Vulcan; goe about </l>
              <l>To make me thunderbolts for th'Summer rout, </l>
              <l>Use your black-cru●ted hands i'th' Cyclops forge, </l>
              <l>Or dye your Hornes a sable hue; disgorge </l>
              <l>Your juicie stomack where our Horses lyes; </l>
              <l>Your man-like action needs must please their eyes; </l>
              <l>Or make thy Wife turne honest: but I feare </l>
              <l>Mars ha's too late uncharm'd her Hemispheare. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000824-e23210">
              <speaker>Vulcan. </speaker>
              <l>Why in this passion? 'las, I will connive </l>
              <l>At all your doings, provided I may thrive </l>
              <l>As well as you by it. What, not agree? </l>
              <l>Iuno shall know thy folly then— D'ye see </l>
              <l>How brisk he is with th'piece of Venerie? </l>
              <l>The match is made, and he must clip the thred </l>
              <l>That tyes her beautie to her maiden bed. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000824-e23310">
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-041-b"/>
              <speaker>Iuno. </speaker>
              <l>Wee'le make her feele our wrath. Why fall you not </l>
              <l>To Censure? Where's our Iupiter? Absent: What, </l>
              <l>Courting the trash of Beautie? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000824-e23370">
              <speaker>Iupiter. </speaker>
              <l>Yes; but loose </l>
              <l>My labour: shee's growne cunning, to refuse. </l>
              <l>Nay, use your pleasure now; shee'l scarce be made </l>
              <l>Capable of Venus traffique, Wantons Trade. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000824-e23440">
              <speaker>Iuno. </speaker>
              <l>Then, Boy, 'tis thee we stay for; let thy Art </l>
              <l>And tongue agree. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="ep000824-e23480">
              <speaker>Cupid. </speaker>
              <l>Doubt not, I'le find her heart. </l>
              <l>Since I as Vmpire stand; I will, that shee </l>
              <l>A faithlesse Wanton shall from henceforth bee; </l>
              <l>One, whose insatiate Wombe no meane shall know, </l>
              <l>But prostitute her Body, till shee grow </l>
              <l>Unusefull, and that time shall let her see </l>
              <l>A period to her hidden Venerie. </l>
              <l>Her person shall be much desir'd of many, </l>
              <l>Nor chast nor constant shall she prove to any, </l>
              <l>But covet to imbrace new fashions still, </l>
              <l>Whereby to glut her base insatiate will. </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-042-a"/>
              <l>Those that have long been practisers in sin, </l>
              <l>She shall instruct new wayes to wallow in, </l>
              <l>And with her faire illusions shall invite </l>
              <l>All sorts of Nations to her seem'd delight. </l>
              <l>But when her Face with furrowes shall appeare, </l>
              <l>And that her Cheekes no Rosie colour beare, </l>
              <l>When her soft Lip shall want the force to bind </l>
              <l>Thousands by adjuration to her mind; </l>
              <l>When as the youthfull heat hath left to raigne, </l>
              <l>And that her Nerves an Icie cold retaine; </l>
              <l>Where Eyes begin to looke into her Soule, </l>
              <l>Where they espie it spotted, wicked, foule; </l>
              <l>When as her Hands, so much admir'd, shall be </l>
              <l>Wither'd, and like a bare Anatomie; </l>
              <l>Then shall she lingring live without reliefe, </l>
              <l>Nor shall one prove a helper to her griefe. </l>
              <l>Those whom her youth and time she spent withall, </l>
              <l>(When as her Beautie became prodigall) </l>
              <l>Shall loath to heare her nam'd; and more, her fight </l>
              <l>Shall be to 'em as poys'nous Aconite: </l>
              <l>And when that Time shall, with his Neighbour Death, </l>
              <l>Steale unawares, and stop her vitall breath, </l>
              <l>All that she leaves behind, is bu● her Name, </l>
              <l>And that lives onely to enlarge her shame. </l>
              <l>So, while she lives, her life is but a hate, </l>
              <l>And yet her death proves more unfortunate: </l>
              <l>Wretched by birth, and so brought vp to woe, </l>
              <l>In Life accurst, in Death her Soules chiefe foe. </l>
              <l>Then what remaines, but onely this to prove, </l>
              <l>A scorne to Time, a hatred unto Love? </l>
              <l>And on her Grave this Epitaph shall be </l>
              <l>Read, to condemne her vitious memorie. </l>
            </sp>
            <q>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-042-b"/>
              <floatingText>
                <body>
                  <div type="epitaph" xml:id="ep000824-e24030">
                    <head>Her Epitaph. </head>
                    <l>HEre remaines a Piece, that shame </l>
                    <l>Does forbid to owne, or name: </l>
                    <l>She was once, as this, a Stone, </l>
                    <l>'Till Conversion made her none; </l>
                    <l>Then her Beautie stain'd her Soule, </l>
                    <l>Being faire, she was most foule: </l>
                    <l>Lov'd, yet hated all; 'tis crost, </l>
                    <l>Whom she lov'd, she hated most. </l>
                    <l>She was skil'd in Language too, </l>
                    <l>Ev'ry Nation did her woo; </l>
                    <l>She cou'd French interpret well, </l>
                    <l>Till she fashion'd how to spell </l>
                    <l>Through the Nose. If any passe </l>
                    <l>On this tender yeelding Grasse, </l>
                    <l>To view this Piece, doe not weepe, </l>
                    <l>'Tis a passion they may keepe; </l>
                    <l>Onely Charitie bids us say, </l>
                    <l>She is happie now she's Clay. </l>
                  </div>
                </body>
              </floatingText>
            </q>
            <sp xml:id="ep000824-e24240">
              <speaker>Omnes. </speaker>
              <l>We like thy Censure well, and are content </l>
              <l>She shall endure thy Doome and punishment. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div type="epithalamium" xml:id="ep000824-e24280">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-043-a"/>
            <head>An Epithalamium on the two happie Paire, <hi>Thomas B. </hi>Esquire, the younger, and his faire Bride. </head>
            <l>VP lazie Morne, send through th' odorous ayre </l>
            <l>A blush, that may invite the Hemispheare </l>
            <l>To wonder, then looke pale with spleene, denie </l>
            <l>To all, save to this Bride, supremacie. </l>
            <l>Wonder; in that the still usurping Night, </l>
            <l>Fat with the weight of sinnes dismounted, spight </l>
            <l>Of his assistant Horrors, e're his Raigne, </l>
            <l>Fatall to erring Mortals, cou'd obtaine </l>
            <l>Its finall course; and Day appeare, before </l>
            <l>Thy Porter had unhing'd his painted Dore; </l>
            <l>And 'tis confest, that Night two houres ha●s lost, </l>
            <l>Since her bright rising banished his Host; </l>
            <l>Starres hid themselvs in Clouds, no Cynthia seene, </l>
            <l>The petty Lights would all have Cynthias beene, </l>
            <l>Could they have vanquisht Nature; but the height </l>
            <l>Of their Ambition prov'd their Opposite, </l>
            <l>And sunke them in their Errors▪ Oh! to see </l>
            <l>A Heav'n on Earth, yet Heav'n no Heav'n to bee, </l>
            <l>'Lesse by her Light assisted; th' Skie appeare </l>
            <l>In sable dresse, while Day did trip it here, </l>
            <l>A new Aurora brake, whose potent smiles </l>
            <l>Gilded the Easterne Morne, thaw'd Winter Iles </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-043-b"/>
            <l>Tyl'd o're with plates of Ice; shew'd th'Heav'ns grow poor </l>
            <l>In goodnesse, yet from her they may gleane store, </l>
            <l>To furnish 'em for ever,' lesse they be </l>
            <l>Too prodigall of her liberalitie. </l>
            <l>Hamstead was made a Paradise, each Bush </l>
            <l>Retain'd a Spring-like Coat; the chirping Thrush </l>
            <l>Grew proud and wanton, and did use their Note </l>
            <l>In fancying Anthems, which they got by Rote; </l>
            <l>The chanting Philomels mellifluous straine, </l>
            <l>O'th'piked Eglantine reviv'd againe; </l>
            <l>The am'rous Spring and Roses there were blowne, </l>
            <l>That in their Chaos slept, forgot, unshowne; </l>
            <l>The frostie-bearded Winter at her feet </l>
            <l>Dropt into Pearles his substance; and the Sheet </l>
            <l>That Earth of Nature borrowes to lye in, </l>
            <l>Chequer'd with Flòra's beauties, did begin </l>
            <l>To prove abortive, came before their time; </l>
            <l>Yet safe deliver'd of its Spicie slime, </l>
            <l>Forc't by her radiant lustre; ev'ry Tree </l>
            <l>Wore Fruit forbidden, cause her Liverie. </l>
            <l>Can this stirre Wonder in thee? No; for 'tis </l>
            <l>No wonder, didst thou know but what shee is: </l>
            <l>Shee's all divine, whose Virgin influence </l>
            <l>Merits the courtship of the dayes bright Prince, </l>
            <l>By whose amplexures, mixtures, Nuptiall tyes, </l>
            <l>Religious Votes shall from each Soule arise, </l>
            <l>To blesse their bright Conjunction; for the which, </l>
            <l>Hymen, whose care is Vertue to enrich, </l>
            <l>Hath singled out her Consort, brought her one </l>
            <l>That out-rayes P●oebus through his Horizon; </l>
            <l>Adorn'd with Masculine Vertues he can be: </l>
            <l>Should I compare him to th'Heavens; but He, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-044-a"/>
            <l>And in that He, consists such ample worth, </l>
            <l>We want a Homers Pen to set it forth. </l>
            <l>He's exquisitely rare, shou'd I say more, </l>
            <l>'Two'd not enlarge his worth, but make me poore </l>
            <l>In fancie: for alas, what need I tell </l>
            <l>The world a storie, which they know so well? </l>
            <l>I will conclude in prayers, not in prayse, </l>
            <l>Though you deserve them both, while I have dayes </l>
            <l>Or minutes to unburden: may Encrease </l>
            <l>For ever Crowne the Harvest of your Peace; </l>
            <l>May you live like two Angels sent from Heaven, </l>
            <l>To teach the world examples, and run even </l>
            <l>In Vertues progresse, till your sacred Urne </l>
            <l>Claymes its prerogative, your ashes turne </l>
            <l>The Phoenix Exequies to nothing. Why? </l>
            <l>Your lives extinct, Perfections with you dye; </l>
            <l>Nor shall our Ages after mention one, </l>
            <l>Without committing Sacriledge, you gone, </l>
            <l>But your Remembrance, which shall last, and be </l>
            <l>The onely Phoenix to Posteritie. </l>
            <l>Shine like the Twins of Miracle; for it's true, </l>
            <l>Nature comply'd with Wonder, framing you. </l>
            <l>Let your refulgent Beames afford more Light, </l>
            <l>For Turtle loyaltie, than the wisht sight </l>
            <l>Of Phoebus, rouzed from the Ocean, </l>
            <l>Ascends to his full Lines Meridian. </l>
            <l>Flourish in the blest Concords Unitie, </l>
            <l>And spinne your Lives into Eternitie. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="epithalamium" xml:id="ep000824-e25300">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-044-b"/>
            <head>An Epithalamium on the happie Nuptials of his much respected friend Geo. F. Gent. </head>
            <l>RIse wanton Phoebus, leave thy am'rous play, </l>
            <l>And prune thy selfe, to grace this Nuptiall Day; </l>
            <l>Shake off thy drowsie Looks, and let thine Eye </l>
            <l>Appeare in its full height of Majestie. </l>
            <l>Let Hermes in his greatest glory shine, </l>
            <l>And Bacchus drink full Bowles of Helvian Wine: </l>
            <l>Let Iove forget to play with Ganimed, </l>
            <l>And Mars once leave the Cyprian Goddesse Bed; </l>
            <l>Vesta, with all thy Darlings, hither hie, </l>
            <l>And crowne our Wedding with thy companie: </l>
            <l>Bring thou our Bride to Church, but leave her there; </l>
            <l>Nor blush not, if she chance to shed a teare; </l>
            <l>Feares doe possesse the tender yeares of one, </l>
            <l>Unapt to know th'untwining of her Zone. </l>
            <l>Hymen▪ Rites finisht, let your Welcomes be </l>
            <l>To grace our Bridegroome with your Companie. </l>
            <l>And now let chast Desires adorne her Bed, </l>
            <l>Whose Blushes shewes the Dye of Maydenhead; </l>
            <l>Wishes and sweet content may they possesse, </l>
            <l>Each heart bring joy to th'other numberlesse. </l>
            <l>Who bids Good-night unto our Bride, be dumb, </l>
            <l>(And sayes no more) Such as shall hither come, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-045-a"/>
            <l>Must not bring one Nights joy alone, but force </l>
            <l>Their throats to reach with Eccho's, till they hoarse. </l>
            <l>Millions of joyes attend 'em both for ever; </l>
            <l>May they be curst who shall their chast hearts sever. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e25690">
            <head>Acrostick on the well-deserving Gentlewoman, Mistris <hi>Eliz. Hill.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
              <l>Enricht with Natures choisest Excellence, </l>
              <l>Light to thy Sex, thou art rare Quintessence, </l>
              <l>Ioves e're admired Creature, in whose face </l>
              <l>Zeale seemes to keepe account of womans grace; </l>
              <l>A thousand joyes attend thee, and may e're </l>
              <l>Beautie (adorn'd with Vertue) be thy share; </l>
              <l>Exquisite Creature, whose perfections lye </l>
              <l>Transparent to each well-discerning eye, </l>
              <l>Heaven sends you here, to grace Mortalitie. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>How much was Helen counted to be faire, </l>
              <l>In so much more thou art beyond compare; </l>
              <l>Love is thy Mirror; then be not too proud, </l>
              <l>Lest Heaven dims that Beautie with a Cloud; </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And so debarre us Mortals of that blisse, </l>
              <l>Which each deserving Soule desires were his. </l>
            </lg>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e25930">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-045-b"/>
            <head>Acrostick on Mistris <hi>Marie Rashley</hi>, in requitall of her Musicall entertainment. </head>
            <l>Many that knowe you not, may thinke that I </l>
            <l>Am by affection led to flatterie, </l>
            <l>Raising your Vertues to sublimest height, </l>
            <l>In hope to gaine you as my purchas'd right, </l>
            <l>Enflam'd by Love; ah no, my zeale is such, </l>
            <l>Rare Phoenix, that I cannot write too much, </l>
            <l>As prayses due; for shou'd Apollo heare </l>
            <l>Such Dorick Musick, he wou'd leave his Spheare; </l>
            <l>Hymen wou'd boast, if you unto his Shrine </l>
            <l>Love, with your Vertue, bring as Offering; </l>
            <l>Each God wou'd leave his Throne, cou'd Nature frame </l>
            <l>Your equals to embrace their Paphian flame. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e26120">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-046-a"/>
            <head>On his very loving friend, Mistris Bridgett Peck. Acrostick. </head>
            <l>Beautie with Vertues, doth enlarge the store, </l>
            <l>Riches without those Vertues, are but poore; </l>
            <l>In thee both shine, to make thy brightnesse knowne, </l>
            <l>Dame Natures glorious workmanship alone, </l>
            <l>Grac'd with her feature, and so highly priz'd, </l>
            <l>Emaculate, to be eternalliz'd; </l>
            <l>Thou peerelesse piece of Vertue, live to be </l>
            <l>Times wonder, and Mans chiefe felicitie. </l>
            <l>Prudence, the Soule of Wisdome, 's in thy brest, </l>
            <l>Endu'd with all thy Graces, and there rest </l>
            <l>Courted. Vrania in thy Brest doth find </l>
            <l>Kind Zeale, the true Companion to her mind. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e26270">
            <head>To his vertuous Kinswoman, Mistris S. B. </head>
            <l>IF to adore thee, were not held a sinne </l>
            <l>Beyond the reach of mercie, I'd begin </l>
            <l>To render up my Orasons to thee, </l>
            <l>And so by custome, write thee Deitie. </l>
            <l>If to admire thy Beautie, and thy Grace, </l>
            <l>And prayse the Native Liveries of thy Face, </l>
            <l>Tell Stories of the whitenesse of thy Brest, </l>
            <l>Thy Hand, thy Legge, thy Foot, and never rest, </l>
            <l>'Till I had made thee famous with my Pen, </l>
            <l>And rais'd thy Name in great esteeme 'mongst men; </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-046-b"/>
            <l>If with industry I sought to please; </l>
            <l>Yet thou would●st count 'em but Hyperbole's; </l>
            <l>So modest is thy faith; thou canst endure </l>
            <l>No straines of wit, that seemes to be impure, </l>
            <l>Or stuft with needlesse superstition, </l>
            <l>The knowing follies in some wanton one: </l>
            <l>Thou art entirely vertuous; Pardon me </l>
            <l>If I transgresse, speaking Truth's Embassie: </l>
            <l>For he that's zealous, will confirme the same, </l>
            <l>Love blowes the fire, but you can quench the flame. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e26530">
            <head>An Elegie on the vertuous Gentlewoman Frances Dixon. </head>
            <l>WHy smil'd the Heavens? why did Sol display </l>
            <l>His golden beames to grace the slow-foot Day? </l>
            <l>What made th'AEtheriall power to cleare the skies? </l>
            <l>And why did Venus scorne thy Obsequies? </l>
            <l>While Vesta's Darlings wearing black, did shew </l>
            <l>What true devotion to chaste corps they owe, </l>
            <l>Iove did appeare, and court thee e're grim Death </l>
            <l>Had pow'r to stop thy od'rous balmie breath. </l>
            <l>And hadst thou yeelded, then thy yeares had bin </l>
            <l>Enlarg'd to feast the Gods with pleasures sin: </l>
            <l>But making sleight of's gifts, enraged hee </l>
            <l>Leaves thee to what the Destinies decree. </l>
            <l>Then 'tis no mervaile that the Heav'ns did smile, </l>
            <l>To see weake Mortalls can their hopes beguile. </l>
            <l>Thou mirror of true Chastity, let mee </l>
            <l>Pay hourely tribute with my teares for thee. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-047-a"/>
            <l>Nor think pure course as many use to doe. </l>
            <l>I strive with them to mourne in fash'on to. </l>
            <l>Ah no, I hate it: for my inward part </l>
            <l>Shall witnesse that the Mourner is my hart. </l>
            <l>Religion wept, and sung, and Vertues score </l>
            <l>Was paid in teares, and sighes, her only store, </l>
            <l>Sending thy sable Herse homeward to blisse, </l>
            <l>Where Chastity receives it's happinesse. </l>
            <l>And the fresh tincture of thy virgin-Tye </l>
            <l>Shall wreath thy brow with spotlesse memory. </l>
            <l>The Gods did smile for anger, 'cause poore wee </l>
            <l>Enjoy'd on earth so rich a prize as thee; </l>
            <l>And in a rage have t'ane thee from us here, </l>
            <l>To place thee in the Elementall sphere. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="elegy" xml:id="ep000824-e26890">
            <head>On his loving friend M. <hi>John Day </hi>an Elegie. </head>
            <l>
              <hi>DOn Phoebus </hi>now hath lost his light, </l>
            <l>And left his Rule unto the night: </l>
            <l>And Cynthia shee hath overcome </l>
            <l>The day, and darkened the Sunne: </l>
            <l>Whereby we now have lost our hope, </l>
            <l>Of gayning Day in's Horoscope. </l>
            <l>A strange Ecclipse did late arise, </l>
            <l>Where naught but blood did deck the skies; </l>
            <l>And in that fight was ta'ne away, </l>
            <l>Our thrice desir'd refulgent day; </l>
            <l>And only Phoebe does appeare, </l>
            <l>To grace the mournfull Hemisphere▪ </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-047-b"/>
            <l>With her dew-ey'd Hyades, </l>
            <l>Hoping with their lights to please </l>
            <l>The angry world; but 'tis in vaine </l>
            <l>To think their light can longer raine, </l>
            <l>Since their chiefest ayde is gone </l>
            <l>Day: and left his Horizon. </l>
            <l>Yet from th'East we may descry, </l>
            <l>A new Day approaching nigh. </l>
            <l>To whom th'Heavens have given strength, </l>
            <l>And made his houres of equall length; </l>
            <l>Vowing that the Night shall ne're </l>
            <l>Displace him from his golden sphere, </l>
            <l>'Till this Sunne begets a Sunne, </l>
            <l>And his Sonne another Sonne. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e27250">
            <head>Epigram 1. </head>
            <l>WIll the Perfumer, met me in the Street, </l>
            <l>I stood amaz'd, he askt me what I meant. </l>
            <l>In faith, said I, your Gloves are mighty sweet, </l>
            <l>And yet your breath doth cast a stronger scent. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e27330">
            <head>EBRIUS. Epigram 2. </head>
            <l>EBrius had long sick of a Feaver bin, </l>
            <l>And feeling the reward he had for sin, </l>
            <l>Did freely vow unto the powers Divine, </l>
            <l>(But at his meat) not to drink any wine. </l>
            <l>And be'ng recover'd, he began to think </l>
            <l>How he might keepe his vow, and safely drink. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-048-a"/>
            <l>And wheresoe're he came, commanded straight, </l>
            <l>That cloth and meat sho'd on the Table wait. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e27450">
            <head>A BRASIER. Epigram 3. </head>
            <l>IOnas the Brasier and his wife fell out, </l>
            <l>He call'd her Slut, and so it came about. </l>
            <l>Slut Knave shee said, now in good sooth you lye. </l>
            <l>With whom (quoth he?) whereat shee gan to cry, </l>
            <l>Reply'd; Enough; I'le yeeld in such a case, </l>
            <l>When you are still your selfe a Brazen face. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e27550">
            <head>Epigram 4. </head>
            <l>A Youthfull Lad match'd with a wrinkl'd Dame, </l>
            <l>Whose gold did kindle in the Youth a flame; </l>
            <l>And being wedded, shee with teares wo'd say, </l>
            <l>I feare my Heart, that thou wilt gad astray, </l>
            <l>Because my time with age is almost spent, </l>
            <l>And cannot yeeld to Youth its full content. </l>
            <l>Yet prythee Love let me this poore boone crave, </l>
            <l>That you on me a small respect will have. </l>
            <l>Feare you my love, said he? now I protest </l>
            <l>Thy teares have wrought impression in my brest; </l>
            <l>And here I vow, by Heav'n, if thou would </l>
            <l>Desire to eare (thou should'st not want) my gold. </l>
            <l>But this I sweare, if he co'd so provoke her, </l>
            <l>His full intention was for to have choak'd her. </l>
            <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e27730">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-048-b"/>
            <head>LOVE. Epigram 5. </head>
            <l>IF any Soule desires to know </l>
            <l>How Love at first came blinde, </l>
            <l>Before the Poet made him so, </l>
            <l>The Reason now h'shall finde: </l>
            <l>Which here to All I'le willingly impart. </l>
            <l>Love shot his eyes and lost 'em in my heart. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e27860">
            <head>LIPS. Epigram 6. </head>
            <l>I Was in company with two or three </l>
            <l>Dispos'd for Mirth; amongst us was a Lasse </l>
            <l>Handsome enough: her Prodigality </l>
            <l>With frequent kissing on our lips did passe▪ </l>
            <l>To one shee'd say, How do'st thou like that kisse? </l>
            <l>And to another (faith) thine was as sweet? </l>
            <l>Swearing her lips dissolv'd, the juice of blisse, </l>
            <l>Which betweene hers, and ours, did freely meet: </l>
            <l>Whereat, we all did laugh; I sweare (quoth she) </l>
            <l>If you say otherwise, you say not well; </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-049-a"/>
            <l>I will refe●'t to you, Sir, meaning mee: </l>
            <l>Are they not moist, pray taste againe and tell. </l>
            <l>I did so, and reply'd▪ thus much I felt, </l>
            <l>Either thy Lips, or else thy Painting melt. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e28050">
            <head>DAME SULLEN. Epigram 7. </head>
            <l>PUtting some questions to a <hi>Sullen Dame</hi>, </l>
            <l>To each of them her answer still was, Well: </l>
            <l>The more I strove t'divert her from the same, </l>
            <l>The more she plagu'd me with her apish Well. </l>
            <l>Impertinent to my demands; at last </l>
            <l>Finding a way to search her folly out, </l>
            <l>And change her note which formerly had past; </l>
            <l>I us'd my Art to bring the same about, </l>
            <l>Speaking but this, <hi>How doth thy Husband doe</hi>? </l>
            <l>Shee fetcht a sigh, and said, he do's but ill; </l>
            <l>Pardon mee Sir, for I must tell it you, </l>
            <l>The more's my griefe, and much against my will, </l>
            <l>He is so frigid growne: He has not done </l>
            <l>Me right, (I vow) since the last Mornings-Sun. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e28260">
            <head>A Lawyer and his Wife. Epigram 8. </head>
            <l>A Beetle-headed Lawyer, one of those </l>
            <l>That leaves his Conscience in his other hose </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-049-b"/>
            <l>For feare of Bribing, and could never spell </l>
            <l>
              <foreign xml:lang="lat">Vices imo Iacobi </foreign>perfect well, </l>
            <l>Knew no more Latine, than his Clarks afford </l>
            <l>Him to encounter with the Kitchin-boord; </l>
            <l>Some stale unsavory stuffe, at second hand </l>
            <l>Which he will have, to never understand; </l>
            <l>He knowes how many lines there's in a sheer, </l>
            <l>How Fayres are kept, and how his Fees do meet: </l>
            <l>And that's enough for him, the rest must be </l>
            <l>Supply'd by his Clarks best indust'ry. </l>
            <l>I name no man, but there was such a one, </l>
            <l>Liv'd in Tricesimo of good Queene Ioane. </l>
            <l>This man of worth was wedded to a faire </l>
            <l>And comely Creature, born neere th'Northern ayre, </l>
            <l>By whom the Churle got wealth; yet he ne're thought </l>
            <l>On th'richnesse of the Jewell he had bought </l>
            <l>Almost with nothing; and would scarce allow </l>
            <l>Her Buttermilk, or strokins from the Cow: </l>
            <l>Yet the poore thing with patience did endure </l>
            <l>●ll this and more, saying to her selfe, that sure </l>
            <l>H● would one day remember, how he had </l>
            <l>Promis'd her often, the next Fees should clad </l>
            <l>Her pretty body: His Fees still came in, </l>
            <l>But still with his old Note he would begin, </l>
            <l>The next that comes is thine, in Sexto Girle </l>
            <l>Thou shalt walk in, or say I am a Chirle: </l>
            <l>Which the poore soule could have said long agoe: </l>
            <l>But to be briefe, the wooll was yet to grow </l>
            <l>Should make her cloth for Gownes and such like things </l>
            <l>She had occasion of; each day he sings </l>
            <l>One Note, and strives with words to put her by; </l>
            <l>Till need had found her out a remedy. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-050-a"/>
            <l>And of his Clyent newly come to towne </l>
            <l>She took up Fees, and he took up her Gowne. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="encomium" xml:id="ep000824-e28710">
            <head>To his much esteemed friend M. <hi>Iohn Tatham </hi>on his Fancies Theater. </head>
            <l>FRiend, let me honour thee, I did not think </l>
            <l>'Till now, th'adst sipt at Agamppes Brink, </l>
            <l>Though I confesse thy Genious was so free </l>
            <l>At all times, that I fear'd thy Poetry </l>
            <l>Would with conveniencie appeare unto </l>
            <l>The World, and Friends; something I have to doe, </l>
            <l>And this it is; I tell thee Friend, from me </l>
            <l>Thou must expect no straines of flattery </l>
            <l>In too much praising; Thus much I dare say, </l>
            <l>I know thy Fancies each sence ravish may </l>
            <l>As well as th'have done mine, for I ne're knew </l>
            <l>A line, but what was good, proceed from you; </l>
            <l>I've said enough, and though I last am come </l>
            <l>To fill a Page, and take up Paper roome; </l>
            <l>Yet with as free a Heart to these last lines </l>
            <l>Of thine, I offer as to those which shines </l>
            <l>Before, thy Friends have done; and proud am I </l>
            <l>To be a Sp●rke 'mongst starres in such a skie. </l>
            <closer>
              <signed>Geo. Sparke. </signed>
            </closer>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e29050">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-050-b"/>
            <head>To the Honorable Sir <hi>John Wintour </hi>Knight, Secretary of State, and Master of Requests to the Queenes most excellent Majestie, The Honor'd Patron of his Book. </head>
            <l>THe Vine and Figg-tree to the God did bring </l>
            <l>Their Mayden-tributes for their offering, </l>
            <l>In hope to purchase by their blest Decree, </l>
            <l>Favours that should our last Mans memory, </l>
            <l>And to that end, plead Merit, shew that Wine </l>
            <l>(Mans nourishment) without the <hi>Grape-sick vine </hi>
            </l>
            <l>Had ne're beene thought on, nor the dimpled sunne </l>
            <l>Of Semile sit crown'd upon his Tunne </l>
            <l>With the Grapes Chaplet; then the Figg-tree too </l>
            <l>Boasts of her worth, shews what her strength can do </l>
            <l>With forraigne States, how great, how rich, how skil'd </l>
            <l>In Languages: the Merchants Cofers fil'd </l>
            <l>Partly by her large travels; how the sence </l>
            <l>Of man is cherisht by their excellence: </l>
            <l>And both concluded if the Gods did please </l>
            <l>For a set-time to grant 'em Writs of ease </l>
            <l>From future transportation, that they might </l>
            <l>With more security enjoy their right, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-051-a"/>
            <l>And be the select trees of all the rest, </l>
            <l>That by their sacred favours should be blest, </l>
            <l>They'd render duly to their Treasury, </l>
            <l>A full encrease for perpetuity, </l>
            <l>And add unto their titles more than yet </l>
            <l>Was fanci'd in the Poets veine of wit. </l>
            <l>The Lawrell, Pyne, and Poplar that could ne're </l>
            <l>Boast of a happy fruit to crowne the yeare, </l>
            <l>Hearing th'others o●tentation, th●ught </l>
            <l>There was no hopes for them, they had not brought </l>
            <l>Things meritorious; nor could they infer </l>
            <l>Large circumstance, to make the Gods confer </l>
            <l>Their choicest blessings on ●em, all their stor● </l>
            <l>Was in their naked selves, barren and poore. </l>
            <l>These Barren Plants doubting a sad successe, </l>
            <l>By reason of the others happinesse, </l>
            <l>Would have departed; but the pious Gods </l>
            <l>Knowing their faith was sure (how e're the ods </l>
            <l>'Twixt em in riches made the others bee </l>
            <l>In ●ore respect with Worldlings,) did agree </l>
            <l>(For some reserv'd conditions) to supply </l>
            <l>Their poore defects by gracious clemency. </l>
            <l>The Vine and <hi>Fig tree </hi>straightway hereupon </l>
            <l>Stole from the Presence, sham'd at what they'd done; </l>
            <l>Those that were worthlesse trees of late, are now </l>
            <l>By the Gods Patronage and gentle brow, </l>
            <l>Made happy, and the onely trees that be </l>
            <l>Held famous, for their singularity. </l>
            <l>The Moral's mine Sir; great ones favour men </l>
            <l>Of meaner quality, not for deserts that pen </l>
            <l>Them meriting Characters, but in favouring them </l>
            <l>They give them all their worth, esteeme, and jem. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-051-b"/>
            <l>So the reflection from your Honours eye, </l>
            <l>On this weake peece, will awe base Crit●c●e; </l>
            <l>And so secure my freedome, that I may </l>
            <l>(Soaring above their spleene) your Will obey. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e29750">
            <head>To a Gentlewoman having beene scandaliz'd by some. </head>
            <l>GRieve not deare Mistresse; faults that are undone, </l>
            <l>If but suspected, might as well be done </l>
            <l>'Mongst soules of no capacity, that draw </l>
            <l>An envious breath, not rul'd by Reasons law; </l>
            <l>They may more safely tax the Gods of sin, </l>
            <l>Than the composed strictnesse y'ave liv'd in, </l>
            <l>Who rather are the Patronesse of Truth, </l>
            <l>Spending in broken sighs your pretious youth: </l>
            <l>Than one that gives way to those loose desires </l>
            <l>Our giddy Youth are prone to; such quick fires </l>
            <l>Ne're boyl'd your innocent blood, nor in your brest </l>
            <l>Did e're impure thoughts discompose your rest; </l>
            <l>You ne're were drest like th'gaudy Queene of May, </l>
            <l>Swimming through th'streets in Coaches to a play; </l>
            <l>Nor did you ever weare in your faire looks </l>
            <l>Lascivious glances, Lusts intangling hooks: </l>
            <l>You never kept your bed to use your wit, </l>
            <l>To ape a fashion, which to patterne it </l>
            <l>Would puzle all the Taylors save the French. </l>
            <l>O fairest Mistresse, would my teares might quench </l>
            <l>The flavour of your sorrow; I know you ●ree </l>
            <l>From this black, false, unheard of calumny, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-052-a"/>
            <l>Or each particular Page or line that may </l>
            <l>Admit of blurres to wrong thee, or decay </l>
            <l>The least of thy perfections; Think not then </l>
            <l>It lyes in th'malice of the devill or men </l>
            <l>To staine thine Innocence, whose unspotted zeale </l>
            <l>Onely to Heaven, not to the World appeale. </l>
            <l>There you are fixt a Saint already: why </l>
            <l>Then you'd waste your selfe so pensively? </l>
            <l>These scandalls wound you not, they'l heavy fall </l>
            <l>On their owne heads, whose weight will sink 'em all. </l>
            <l>Temper your crosses Mistresse, be more milde </l>
            <l>To your faire selfe, than vainely thus to strive </l>
            <l>Against your Natures sweetnesse, and impose </l>
            <l>Such cruelty on your selfe. Malice that throwes </l>
            <l>Her venome at you, if I doe not erre, </l>
            <l>Shall with't be her owne executioner: </l>
            <l>So did the spotlesse Damsell suffer wrong, </l>
            <l>By the sinne-plotting Elders; but e're long </l>
            <l>Heaven did acquit her: And so Heaven pure Maid </l>
            <l>Doth acquit thee from this aspertion laid▪ </l>
            <l>So have I seene a fierce-opposing cloud, </l>
            <l>With an intent bright Cynthias light to shroud </l>
            <l>Under its sable wings, in triumph stay </l>
            <l>For a set space, then dully move away, </l>
            <l>When with a sudden motion shee'd appeare </l>
            <l>Bright as her selfe, yet to our eyes more cleare </l>
            <l>Then formerly shee was: so is't with thee </l>
            <l>Whom Envie left in deepe obscurity. </l>
            <l>But now shine forth, th'illustrious beames display, </l>
            <l>And make our night seeme a continuall day. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e30310">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-052-b"/>
            <head>A Wart on a Gentlewomans arme. </head>
            <l>WHat's that so neere your skin ally'd </l>
            <l>and will not thence, </l>
            <l>His head is in your colours dy'd </l>
            <l>without offence. </l>
            <l>His perfect red and white hath mixt, </l>
            <l>So long with your pure blood he's fixt, </l>
            <l>and will not part </l>
            <l>Without much trouble to your heart: </l>
            <l>but why </l>
            <l>D'you hide it now, and set a Dye </l>
            <l>upon your cheeks, </l>
            <l>As being bashfull, cause it seeks </l>
            <l>the light, </l>
            <l>It cannot sure appeare more white </l>
            <l>than on your arme; </l>
            <l>Nor weare a better coat of red, </l>
            <l>Than your chast blood hath mingled </l>
            <l>most sweet and warme; </l>
            <l>So Strawberries suck the gentle streame </l>
            <l>Of fresh and most delitious Creame. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e30560">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-053-a"/>
            <head>To one professing and swearing love to all Women. </head>
            <l>'TIs not Love thy pulses beat, </l>
            <l>But the Itch of base desire; </l>
            <l>Whose impure unlawfull heat </l>
            <l>Sets both life and soule on fire. </l>
            <l>Love delights not in those things </l>
            <l>Which disgrace and ruine brings. </l>
            <l>Love is figur'd as a Childe, </l>
            <l>Emblem of pure Innocence: </l>
            <l>Passionate, but undefil'd, </l>
            <l>Zealous, without a pretence. </l>
            <l>Love doth carry in his eye </l>
            <l>Constant flames that never dye. </l>
            <l>
              <hi></hi>Love's not subject unto change, </l>
            <l>Nor doth his affection move, </l>
            <l>Where time-pleasing Fancies range </l>
            <l>Epicures with freedome prove; </l>
            <l>'Tis not to each face that's faire, </l>
            <l>Hee doth his all●geance beare. </l>
            <l>Nor is't Oathes that make a Lover: </l>
            <l>Flying vowes to ev'ry shee </l>
            <l>May intemperate lust discover, </l>
            <l>Where consuming follies bee. </l>
            <l>Love is simple of himselfe, </l>
            <l>And respects nor praise, nor pelfe. </l>
            <l>
              <hi></hi>Love's not guided unto feare </l>
            <l>By the Tongues deceiving Art, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-053-b"/>
            <l>Raptures that intrance the eare. </l>
            <l>What he covets, is the Heart, </l>
            <l>On the which hee doth display </l>
            <l>Beames farre clearer than the day. </l>
            <l>At Loves sacred Altar lyes </l>
            <l>Hearts as stainlesse as the Dove, </l>
            <l>Mutuall in their sacrifice </l>
            <l>To the purity of love, </l>
            <l>Which with Nuptiall kisses smother, </l>
            <l>Growing flames in one another. </l>
            <l>Then if thou intend'st to ayme </l>
            <l>At a Lovers part, be just; </l>
            <l>Punish that destroyes the same, </l>
            <l>Prick thy <hi>sw●lling veynes </hi>of Lust, </l>
            <l>Let thy rank pollution run, </l>
            <l>Hee'l adopt thee then his sonne, </l>
            <l>While thou seek'st to please thy eye, </l>
            <l>Never hope to taste true bl●ss●s, </l>
            <l>When the appetite doth fry, </l>
            <l>Surfeits so, it pleasures misses; </l>
            <l>For the blest desire of Love, </l>
            <l>'s by inspiration from above. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="song" xml:id="ep000824-e31340">
            <head>A Song to the picture of a Lover in his absence. </head>
            <l>COme, oh come away my Deare, </l>
            <l>Let me not for ever languish: </l>
            <l>Lest I buy my joyes too deare; </l>
            <l>Sighs my tender Heart will vanquish; </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-054-a"/>
            <l>For thee I have out-watch'd the night, </l>
            <l>While angry starres did read my story, </l>
            <l>And silver Cynthia hid her light, </l>
            <l>As envying at my wisht-for glory; </l>
            <l>When thus upon thy lips I plaid, </l>
            <l>Making a soft impression there, </l>
            <l>The jealous Goddesse then dismaid </l>
            <l>For her Endym●on, left her sphere, </l>
            <l>And ever since hath harbour'd here. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e31520">
            <head>Seeing a Gentlewoman making her ready in a window. </head>
            <l>WHat new light's you that breaks and wraps man's sence </l>
            <l>Into a world of wonder, excellence </l>
            <l>Discypher'd to the life; some good protect </l>
            <l>My eyes lest they transgresse; I could affect </l>
            <l>Each amorous glance or gesture she bestowes </l>
            <l>On the reflecting Flatterer, how she throwes </l>
            <l>Odours 'gainst odours, and her snow-white hands </l>
            <l>Distilleth oyle of Roses, she commands </l>
            <l>The Sunnes retirement, and for him does light </l>
            <l>My Fancie to rare objects infinite. </l>
            <l>See, see the Twins of Miracle, her Brests </l>
            <l>Whiter than new falne snow the spycie Nests, </l>
            <l>And Pillowes for Love● lips to rest upon! </l>
            <l>Now she disroabes her night-clothes, now goes on </l>
            <l>Her rich Carnation sattin to intice </l>
            <l>Men to forsake their hope of Paradice. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-054-b"/>
            <l>Delusion, vanish; doe not think to win </l>
            <l>Me from that blisse I have possession in, </l>
            <l>Though my <hi></hi>Clarinda's lost, I will not be </l>
            <l>Polluted with thy vile immodesty. </l>
            <l>Thy skin though white shall ne're infect my eyes, </l>
            <l>Or staine my cheeks with blushes, nor surprize </l>
            <l>A thought of mine; no Counterfeit; I doe </l>
            <l>Abhorre thy actions and thy colours too; </l>
            <l>Wilt not yet leave t'allure me? by that power </l>
            <l>Dwells in my Mistresse name, I doe conjure </l>
            <l>Thy absence from that casement which lets in </l>
            <l>Nought but the stragling fantasmes of sin: </l>
            <l>Oh: art thou slunk away, had her pure name </l>
            <l>Sufficient skill to make thee know thy shame, </l>
            <l>And now in some obscure unhallowed place </l>
            <l>Thou pin'st (unpittied) at thy owne disgrace. </l>
            <l>Pardon me dearest Mistresse, that I have </l>
            <l>Made use of your blest name as ayde to save </l>
            <l>Me, from the errors I was leaning to, </l>
            <l>And heretick-like forgot my faith in you. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e31980">
            <head>To a coy Mistresse. </head>
            <lg>
              <l>THink not coy Mistresse, I am one </l>
              <l>So fond, that can affect a stone, </l>
              <l>Or some such thing, unlesse I see </l>
              <l>There's something in't will pleasure me. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>I cannot tye my Heart on looks, </l>
              <l>Angle whole Summers in the Brooks. </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-055-a"/>
              <l>In expectation of a dish </l>
              <l>Of Salmon; 'cause a Princely fish. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>I cannot dwell on such delayes, </l>
              <l>Or stay in hope of Halcyon dayes; </l>
              <l>If I possesse my pleasures now, </l>
              <l>No happier dayes will I allow. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Why should I hope for things to come, </l>
              <l>That may be had with ease of some; </l>
              <l>So trifle pretious Tune away </l>
              <l>For empty hopes, and fruitlesse play? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Because y'are something faire, must I </l>
              <l>Wait your coy leasure to reply, </l>
              <l>When with some other long e're this, </l>
              <l>I might have felt a Lovers blisse? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>I can as well content my sense, </l>
              <l>With one of lesser excellence </l>
              <l>That's not so nice, nor will debate </l>
              <l>The time, when love should actuate. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>I'm earnest (Mistresse); and must try </l>
              <l>(If you refuse) a remedie </l>
              <l>Else-where; you know that youthfull blood </l>
              <l>Consumes it selfe, unlesse withstood. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Then quickly let me know your minde; </l>
              <l>Delayes are childrens play; be kinde </l>
              <l>As you are faire, and let's possesse </l>
              <l>Our Loves, and pleasures numberlesse. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-055-b"/>
              <l>A Cherry gather'd in the Spring, </l>
              <l>Is a choice Present for a King; </l>
              <l>Those that till August hang, you know </l>
              <l>Are rotten, and then common grow. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Those Roses too that have desire </l>
              <l>To dwell still with their mother Bryer, </l>
              <l>Must at the last (though let alone) </l>
              <l>Fall off themselves, when over-growne. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>The Cherry and the Rose would be </l>
              <l>Of little value, did not wee </l>
              <l>For novelty sake, allow them good, </l>
              <l>Their worth would scarce be understood. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Women had long since lost their name, </l>
              <l>Had not wee men reviv'd the fame. </l>
              <l>You might like things neglected lye, </l>
              <l>As uselesse, were not men you nigh. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Then think on this, and let us prove, </l>
              <l>There is no joy on earth but Love, </l>
              <l>That every simple Lasse may finde </l>
              <l>(As we did) fire of subtle kinde. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Those foolish Girles that feele a heat, </l>
              <l>Their bashfulnesse dare not repeat: </l>
              <l>When they by us know what to doe, </l>
              <l>They'l banish feare, and fall to woe. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And so by our example, they </l>
              <l>That have beene stubborne, will obey; </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-056-a"/>
              <l>And Girles that stay 'till fifteene, will </l>
              <l>Repent the time they spent so ill. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>All sorts of people from the age </l>
              <l>Of twelve to thirty shall presage </l>
              <l>Our happinesse, and joyntly come </l>
              <l>To crowne <hi>our Loves El●zium</hi>. </l>
            </lg>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e33050">
            <head>Meeting a peece of Mortality val'd. </head>
            <lg>
              <l>VNvale thy selfe, and shine as bright </l>
              <l>As sunne by day, or starres by night. </l>
              <l>What pitty 'tis to hide a face </l>
              <l>Enricht with such a comely grace! </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Thy Haire like Hemlocks carelesse fall, </l>
              <l>To deck thy amorous eyes with all, </l>
              <l>As fierie as the evening, where </l>
              <l>We read the next day will be faire. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Thy curious forehead to us shew, </l>
              <l>Where Ca●buncles in number grow; </l>
              <l>But the beauties of thy Nose </l>
              <l>Would fright a man out of his clothes, </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>To dance a naked round delay, </l>
              <l>When on th'Tobacco Pipe you play; </l>
              <l>And the pale brightnesse of thy lips, </l>
              <l>Would force the Sunne to an eclipse. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-056-b"/>
              <l>Thy cheeks of fat and foggy stuffe, </l>
              <l>Like th' running Dropsie, swell and puffe: </l>
              <l>But oh! the Apples on 'em grow, </l>
              <l>I think were rotten long agoe. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Thy pretious neck and brests display </l>
              <l>Thy skins antiquity, for they </l>
              <l>Like a <hi>dri'd dunghill</hi>, chop and break, </l>
              <l>Untill thy snowt begins to leak. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Thy parched fists defie the Sunne; </l>
              <l>For all the malice he hath done, </l>
              <l>Cann't change thy hyde, nor any stayne </l>
              <l>Corrupt it, for it's dy'd in grayne. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Thy spacious belly and thy waste, </l>
              <l>Have grease sufficiently to baste </l>
              <l>A Heard of Swine, the' have such a store, </l>
              <l>A Shambles cannot purchase more. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Thy Thighes like two Colosses seeme </l>
              <l>Proportion'd, with thy bodies Teeme, </l>
              <l>And those which beare thy <hi>ponderous Britch</hi>, </l>
              <l>Are mighty Columns full of itch. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>But some that have thy Hoofes espy'd, </l>
              <l>With feare the fooles fell downe and dy'd; </l>
              <l>Yet all this while I have forgot, </l>
              <l>Thy Tongue as still as Cannon-shot. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>All parts of thine I cann't display, </l>
              <l>The rest unseene, the Devill may. </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-057-a"/>
              <l>Thou art the Wonder of this age, </l>
              <l>And wantest nothing, but a Cage. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Which thou in time, maist purchase too, </l>
              <l>If that the Beadle will but doe: </l>
              <l>Then come and joyne thy Vice with me, </l>
              <l>Blesse Nature for her Prodigie. </l>
            </lg>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e33930">
            <head>To his Friend upon saying his Mistresse was not faire. </head>
            <l>WHy do'st thou think my Mistresse is not faire, </l>
            <l>Because shee is not as most Women are, </l>
            <l>Unprofitably proud, nor will admit </l>
            <l>Of scorne, to tart the sweetnesse of her wit; </l>
            <l>'Cause shee in actions (most irregular </l>
            <l>To Loves choice Edicts) will not, Will prefer </l>
            <l>Above her Reason, nor was ever knowne </l>
            <l>To boast of Beauty, more than was her owne; </l>
            <l>Shee's not precisely coy, nor yet too free </l>
            <l>In her bestowing Favours, but to me. </l>
            <l>She never us'd a Dram of Vicious Art </l>
            <l>To take mans eye, and afterwards his Heart. </l>
            <l>Shee needs no Ivory Teeth, no Spanish Red, </l>
            <l>Or Powders of Inticement: she is sped </l>
            <l>In Natures Properties; let it suffice </l>
            <l>I love her, 'cause she loves not a Disguise. </l>
            <l>Disdaine did ne're usurp her Ebon Brow, </l>
            <l>Nor does she tip her language with a Thon </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-057-b"/>
            <l>In base derision; her sweet Lenity </l>
            <l>With her Minds object shares of Purity. </l>
            <l>Greece glori'd much of Helens beauteous Rayes; </l>
            <l>But Troy lamented more at the decayes </l>
            <l>And ruine follow'd it. Do'st think that I </l>
            <l>Governe my actions solely by my eye; </l>
            <l>Beauty is but a Garment us'd to hide </l>
            <l>Some imperfection, which if once espi'd </l>
            <l>Discretion bids us shun; then't may appeare. </l>
            <l>Beauty with V●rtue seldome do's coheare; </l>
            <l>But where th'are Relatives, 'tis so much rare, </l>
            <l>That Beauty is Divinely singular, </l>
            <l>And merits much; yet let my Mistresse be </l>
            <l>Black as a Crow, she seemes a Swan to me; </l>
            <l>She's not defam'd, nor curtail'd of that shape </l>
            <l>Nature bestowes on any, your Court-Ape </l>
            <l>Is not contented with, and to appeare </l>
            <l>More excellent, will buy their Painting deare, </l>
            <l>Which on their cheeks lyes thick, to shew their store </l>
            <l>Like parched Walls new whiten'd, Oker'd ore. </l>
            <l>Was not her face I courted, but th' refin'd </l>
            <l>Inestimable Iewell of her minde. </l>
            <l>She has within her that which can declare </l>
            <l>A soule sufficient to create her faire; </l>
            <l>And her conditions sweetnesse to each eye </l>
            <l>Appeares th'Appendix where felicity </l>
            <l>Doth sit enthron'd; All these perfections dwells </l>
            <l>In her alone. Humanity excells, </l>
            <l>And is so much Divine, her <hi>firme faith </hi>can </l>
            <l>Translate to immortality fraile man. </l>
            <l>Punish thy errors friend, and that I may </l>
            <l>Assure my selfe th'art penitent, obey. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-058-a"/>
            <l>By thy subscribing, that 'tis onely shee </l>
            <l>Imploy'd on earth for our eternity. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="prologue" xml:id="ep000824-e34890">
            <head>A Prologue spoken upon removing of the late Fortune Players to the Bull. </head>
            <l>WHo would rely on Fortune, when shee's knowne </l>
            <l>An enemie to Merit, and hath shewne </l>
            <l>Such an example here? Wee that have pay'd </l>
            <l>Her tribute to our losse, each night defray'd </l>
            <l>The charge of her attendance, now growne poore, </l>
            <l>(Through her expences) thrusts us out of doore. </l>
            <l>For some peculiar profit; shee has t'ane </l>
            <l>A course to banish Modesty, and retaine </l>
            <l>More dinn, and incivility than hath been </l>
            <l>Knowne in the <hi>Bearwards Court</hi>, the Beargarden. </l>
            <l>Those that now sojourne with her, bring a noyse </l>
            <l>Of <hi>Rables, Apple-wives </hi>and Chimney-boyes, </l>
            <l>Whose shrill confused Ecchoes loud doe cry, </l>
            <l>Enlarge your Commons, Wee hate Privacie. </l>
            <l>Those that have plots to undermine, and strive </l>
            <l>To blow their Neighbours up, so they may thrive, </l>
            <l>What censure they deserve, wee leave to you, </l>
            <l>To whom the judgement on't belongs as due. </l>
            <l>Here Gentlemen, our Anchor's fixt; And wee </l>
            <l>(Disdaining Fortunes mutability) </l>
            <l>Expect your kinde acceptance; then wee'l sing </l>
            <l>(Protected by your smiles our ever-spring;) </l>
            <l>As pleasant as if wee had still possest </l>
            <l>Our lawfull Portion out of Fortunes brest: </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-058-b"/>
            <l>Onely wee would request you to forbeare </l>
            <l>Your wonted custome, banding Tyle, or Peare, </l>
            <l>Against our curtaines, to allure us forth. </l>
            <l>I pray take notice these are of more Worth, </l>
            <l>Pure Naples silk, not Worstead; we have ne're </l>
            <l>An Actour here has mouth enough to teare </l>
            <l>Language by th'eares; this forlorne Hope shall be </l>
            <l>By Us refin'd from such grosse injury. </l>
            <l>And then let your judicious Loves advance </l>
            <l>Vs to our Merits, them to their Ignorance. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e35440">
            <head>To a Vow-breaker leaving this land. </head>
            <lg>
              <l>GOe perjur'd Wanton, and invite </l>
              <l>With thy forg'd Language for a night, </l>
              <l>The eares of thy new-fangled Mate, </l>
              <l>Knowledge of thee begets a hate. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Goe, and with thee take all the sin </l>
              <l>Thy Sexes frailty have liv'd in </l>
              <l>Since Adams fall; for thou art worse </l>
              <l>Than Eve, or serpent, Mans chiefe curse. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>What dire pretence, what fained cause </l>
              <l>Has made thee violate Loves lawes; </l>
              <l>And all those vowes which once to me </l>
              <l>Thou mad'st, before his Deity. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-059-a"/>
              <l>What strange ecclipse is in, thy Youth, </l>
              <l>Which once did shine as cleare as Truth </l>
              <l>In her best lustre, to my eye, </l>
              <l>For it could not thy Faith discry? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Has some new flame possest thy blood, </l>
              <l>Which will consume, if not withstood, </l>
              <l>Thy soules chiefe portion, and strive </l>
              <l>To make thy shame alone survive? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Or did the nicenesse of my love </l>
              <l>From those immodest Acts which move </l>
              <l>Perhaps in some, beget in thee </l>
              <l>A thought of such impiety? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Some sencelesse Wretch that never knew </l>
              <l>Lusts debts, and th'payments that ensue, </l>
              <l>Tis likely, has to please his sence, </l>
              <l>Deflour'd thy <hi>Beauties excellence</hi>. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And thou made stupid with his praise, </l>
              <l>Regardlesse how thy Youth decayes, </l>
              <l>By thy intemp'rate VVill, dost run </l>
              <l>A course without Religion: </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Tend'ring to His unlawfull suit, </l>
              <l>Each day that blest forbidden fruit, </l>
              <l>VVhich Heav'n did give thee, and ordain'd </l>
              <l>Thy Prayers should have kept unstain'd. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>How are our Beauties happy made, </l>
              <l>That thou hast left thy Native shade </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-059-b"/>
              <l>To wander to th' Iberian Coast, </l>
              <l>VVhere thou may'st of thy falsenesse boast? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Hadst thou continu'd longer here, </l>
              <l>Some strange infection we might feare; </l>
              <l>Our Beauties would have drawne from thee. </l>
              <l>Thou banisht, they from it are free. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Each creature now with fresh desire, </l>
              <l>May safely warme 'em at Loves sire, </l>
              <l>And not suspect those flames unjust </l>
              <l>You us'd, consuming Hearts to dust. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Do'st think fond VVoman, by thy flight, </l>
              <l>To hide thy shame from the quick sight </l>
              <l>Of thy owne conscience? it alone </l>
              <l>Shall be thy Guilts companion: </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>VVhich shall surround thy spotted brest </l>
              <l>VVith such black thoughts, that if exprest </l>
              <l>Either by Pen, or else by Breath, </l>
              <l>VVould fright a timorous Maid to Death. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>The gentle winds that now appeare, </l>
              <l>Milde as the breath of Lambs, shall beare </l>
              <l>Upon their wings in furious rage, </l>
              <l>Thy Crimes to ev'ry Forraigne Stage. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>The tatling bushes in the Groves, </l>
              <l>Shall tell the Story of our Loves: </l>
              <l>VVhich well observ'd, they'l all conspire </l>
              <l>VVith Lightning, and consume with fire. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-060-a"/>
              <l>Both thee and thy Familiar, so </l>
              <l>Unlook'd for my revenge will grow, </l>
              <l>And thy example will so strike </l>
              <l>In some, they'l feare to doe the like. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Thou canst not passe by Brook or Spring, </l>
              <l>But hearing their soft murmuring, </l>
              <l>Thy conscious soule will guesse that straight </l>
              <l>It whispers thy unhappy Fate. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Goe where thou wilt, and use thy charmes, </l>
              <l>To circle him within thy armes; </l>
              <l>Thou for a time will dote on, then </l>
              <l>Returne unto thy Fate agen. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Tis past my Creed, to think that you </l>
              <l>Now false to me, can long be true </l>
              <l>To him: for why? <hi>new faces </hi>breed </l>
              <l>
                <hi>New appetites</hi>, whereon to feed. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Had he each various way to please, </l>
              <l>And held a surfeit no disease; </l>
              <l>Yet that thy custome still may swell, </l>
              <l>Thou'lt mix, though with some Infidell. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>His faith with thine may best agree, </l>
              <l>There's such a fatall sympathy </l>
              <l>In your affections, every part </l>
              <l>Resembles thine, when heart in heart. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Then take my counsell and possesse </l>
              <l>Some uncouth shaggy Wildernesse. </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-060-b"/>
              <l>There take Plantation, and be wise; </l>
              <l>Both wanting faith, all faith despise. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>There mingle limbs, and procreate </l>
              <l>Some Prodigy may ruine Fate; </l>
              <l>So keepe those dangers off, which they </l>
              <l>Intend shall be thy Youths decay, </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And suddenly will fall on thee, </l>
              <l>For this thy vilde Apostacie, </l>
              <l>Which a Nuns penance cannot call </l>
              <l>Merit, t'purchase Mercie withall. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Thy travailing friend when he does finde </l>
              <l>Thy want of faith, to the next Winde </l>
              <l>Will beg a whaftage, to be rid </l>
              <l>Of thee, which sacred lawes forbid </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Conversing with; thy sinnes are growne </l>
              <l>So foule, they needs must be thy owne </l>
              <l>For perpetuity; then hee </l>
              <l>Is mad that stayes to share with thee. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>When throughly thou hast div'd into </l>
              <l>Thy owne defects, 'twill puzle you </l>
              <l>To hope forgivenesse, when you see </l>
              <l>With blushes your deformity, </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>And every spot which will declare </l>
              <l>Thee black as night, though once as faire </l>
              <l>As Summers noone-tyde in her pride, </l>
              <l>Thou wert as neare to Heaven ally'd; </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-061-a"/>
              <l>Had'st thou not lost that Essence, which </l>
              <l>By faith all Women doth enrich, </l>
              <l>And play'd away at one poore vye </l>
              <l>Thy soules entire security. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Thou which hast so profusely spent </l>
              <l>Thy Youth, and Beauties Ornament, </l>
              <l>Canst hope to live, 'till age doth pour, </l>
              <l>Upon thy head a silver shour? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Or if those hopes may have successe, </l>
              <l>Thou that hast tasted the excesse </l>
              <l>Of pleasures, canst thou looke to have </l>
              <l>More comfort than th'insatiate Grave? </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Our present pleasures vade away, </l>
              <l>But those to come will ne're decay, </l>
              <l>Reserv'd in Heaven; be not remisse </l>
              <l>In seeking (then) such future blisse. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Farewell, And when that thou hast ta'ne </l>
              <l>A full survey of what I faine </l>
              <l>Will follow: </l>
              <l>For all my wrongs, but teach thy eye </l>
              <l>To shed a teare; and so will I. </l>
            </lg>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e37560">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-061-b"/>
            <head>To a Gentlewoman being fearfull upon the water, by reason of the roughnesse of't. </head>
            <l>WHy doe you tremble <hi>faire one</hi>, why has feare </l>
            <l>Displanted the best Beauties of the yeare </l>
            <l>From their <hi>warme beds </hi>your cheeks? what? does the sight </l>
            <l>Of the rough waves your timorous heart affright, </l>
            <l>Cause in the conflict with the boysterous winde, </l>
            <l>You doubt they'l to your passage be unkinde? </l>
            <l>Let not such thoughts invade you; though the skie </l>
            <l>Is with th'unruly stood in Mutinity: </l>
            <l>Yet your firme faith is of sufficient power, </l>
            <l>To calme the greatest tempest, in an houre, </l>
            <l>Should they mix elements, and every blast </l>
            <l>From the <hi>contentious North </hi>threaten a waste </l>
            <l>To the distemper'd water, so afflict </l>
            <l>The Vniverse with terror, wee'd direct </l>
            <l>Our motions o're 'em, where our Boat shall play </l>
            <l>As free as when an East winde guides the way; </l>
            <l>Then be more confident of your owne worth, </l>
            <l>While we as Prodigies admir'd, launch forth. </l>
            <l>Mistake me not, 'tis not a selfe-conceit </l>
            <l>Of my deserts, kindles in me this heat </l>
            <l>Of resolute boldnesse, but 'tis in you </l>
            <l>To whom all Attributes of worth are due. </l>
            <l>Under your blest protection I shall be </l>
            <l>Fixt as a Rock, that scornes their injury. </l>
            <l>Doe you observe, as soone as you appeare, </l>
            <l>How they retreat as glad to see you here, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-062-a"/>
            <l>To end their difference, Boreas does retire </l>
            <l>To use his force t'encrease the Cyclops fire. </l>
            <l>Now with an amorous breath begins to move </l>
            <l>The golden tramells of your haire to love, </l>
            <l>Now mildly steales a kisse; it's no sin to say </l>
            <l>He courts you as his faire Orythia. </l>
            <l>The waves have smooth'd their wrinckles to, and doe </l>
            <l>(Learning by Boreas in what forme to wooe;) </l>
            <l>With smiling aspect, seeke to re-invite </l>
            <l>You from your feares, to note how they delight </l>
            <l>To beare your blessed waight, and while they skip </l>
            <l>For joy, the sunne is playing with your lip, </l>
            <l>All Rivals in such blisse, the streames dash in, </l>
            <l>Wantonly kisse your garments, not your skin: </l>
            <l>That as a thing forbidden, they adore, </l>
            <l>But dare not touch as warn'd from it before: </l>
            <l>The'are all officious safely to co●vey </l>
            <l>Vs to the place we looke for, while sad they </l>
            <l>Mourne for your absence, each dissolve to teares, </l>
            <l>So drowne themselves for drowning you with feares. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e38360">
            <head>To his friend, advising him from Love. </head>
            <l>WHen to my faire Clarinda I gave breath, </l>
            <l>My expectation was not present death, </l>
            <l>Her unjust doome on me, nor did I looke </l>
            <l>For such a change, that had some freedome tooke </l>
            <l>In her Hyperboles. All that have seene </l>
            <l>Her Beauty, and my Praises, would have beene </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-062-b"/>
            <l>My witnesse 'gainst her, how much I deserv'd </l>
            <l>In her best thoughts, whose studies had preserv'd </l>
            <l>Her Name unto eternity, had not shee </l>
            <l>Discover'd her whole sexes infamie </l>
            <l>By her revolt, that my enforced Pen </l>
            <l>(Against its Nature, us'd for sonnets when </l>
            <l>I call'd her Mine) did charactize her shame </l>
            <l>Blacker than Inke could make it; for the flame </l>
            <l>My vitalls once possest, when it did know </l>
            <l>Hers was declining, would not stronger grow: </l>
            <l>But by degrees extinguisht, else 'twould prove </l>
            <l>Our <hi>paines injustice, motives </hi>not of Love. </l>
            <l>Had'st thou but knowne her Will, thou would'st have said </l>
            <l>Shee was a pretty, handsome, well-fac'd Maid, </l>
            <l>Though not endu'd with those perfections I </l>
            <l>Did boast of to the <hi>World; Poets </hi>may lye </l>
            <l>As well as seeming Prophets, for w●at shee </l>
            <l>Enjoy'd 'bove Natures bounty, sh'ad from mee, </l>
            <l>My lines at first did pollish every l●mb; </l>
            <l>But pencilling her heart, my eyes grew dim; </l>
            <l>Both Pen and Fancie fail'd me, I gave o're, </l>
            <l>Finding her heart stain'd with the leaprous sore </l>
            <l>Of base deceipt, and left her with that poore </l>
            <l>Implicite Beauty which shee had, before </l>
            <l>My verse had nourisht it; what cans't expect </l>
            <l>For all thy service, more than such neglect? </l>
            <l>Should'st thou make ev'ry line swell with conceit, </l>
            <l>And sing her praises in each Epithite; </l>
            <l>Yet thy reward at last will be like m●ne. </l>
            <l>Oh friend! all vvomens Fancies doe decline </l>
            <l>With houres and minutes, and the greatest blisse </l>
            <l>Poore Man can hope for, is but in a kisse </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-063-a"/>
            <l>The shadow of content, which having got, </l>
            <l>It fires his soule, and yet it pleaseth not. </l>
            <l>Why should wee make an Idol of a face </l>
            <l>Of the same mould as ours, and add a grace </l>
            <l>To't by our Homages; so enthrall our eye, </l>
            <l>When Heaven and Nature gives it liberty. </l>
            <l>What though the strange Ideas of our minde, </l>
            <l>Transforme our thoughts to every shape and kinde: </l>
            <l>That wee approve that best that's worst of evils, </l>
            <l>Hold Women Saints, cause some are glorious devils? </l>
            <l>Shall wee persist, committing sacriledge </l>
            <l>'Gainst Heaven and goodnesse, give them priviledge </l>
            <l>'Bove <hi>mother Nature</hi>, make that hand 'cause white </l>
            <l>A miracle: that eye 'cause cleare and bright. </l>
            <l>The Deity I worship, so prophane </l>
            <l>Heavens purity and leave a lasting staine </l>
            <l>On our discretion, make a foolish toy, </l>
            <l>A Puppet to be plaid with, our chiefe joy </l>
            <l>And best of hopes, loosing all the pride </l>
            <l>Rests in true manhood, and our youth beside, </l>
            <l>For one, fram'd our inferiour, the weake thing </l>
            <l>Of peevish woman, which in mentioning </l>
            <l>Declares their first creation, and from whence </l>
            <l>They doe derive (forsooth) their Excellence? </l>
            <l>What pleasure is't to dally with the Fan </l>
            <l>Of thy fine Mistresse, or be lesse a man, </l>
            <l>And kisse her Glove, gaine from her eyes a glance, </l>
            <l>That may thy <hi>easie heart </hi>a while entrance, </l>
            <l>Fett'ring with golden hopes thy <hi>giddy youth</hi>, </l>
            <l>Hanging Dispaire upon the heeles of Truth? </l>
            <l>Their Loves are like ones breath on purest steele, </l>
            <l>No sooner on, but off, they never feele </l>
            <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000824-063-b"/>
            <l>Nor understand affection; what we call </l>
            <l>
              <hi></hi>Beautie's a thing most prejudiciall </l>
            <l>To our humanity, how e're it seeme, </l>
            <l>A <hi>pretious object </hi>in our eyes esteeme, </l>
            <l>Wee gaze on it as th'Porcupine on th'starres, </l>
            <l>'Till Ruine overtakes us in the Warres. </l>
            <l>We hold with our owne errors, and should wee </l>
            <l>Enjoy this new set up Idolatry, </l>
            <l>Our States were yet uncertaine, for they still </l>
            <l>Would have some fetch to satiate their will. </l>
            <l>They are infirme in loyalty, and bee </l>
            <l>Like th' <hi>golden Apples </hi>hanging on the tree </l>
            <l>O're Tantalus, which if but toucht, will fall </l>
            <l>Straight into ashes, so that little All </l>
            <l>Of good in Women is compounded so; </l>
            <l>The least breath of temptation they'l yeeld to. </l>
            <l>There is so many sleights us'd by vilde Woman, </l>
            <l>That th'custome (like themselves) is now grown common. </l>
            <l>They can instruct their eyes to weepe, when they </l>
            <l>Like Crocadiles are readiest to betray </l>
            <l>Our lives to eminent danger; they doe make </l>
            <l>Love 〈◊〉 knots of ●ushes, which in twisting breake. </l>
            <l>The sweets they give us, treacherously assumes, </l>
            <l>To stifle up our sences with Perfumes. </l>
            <l>If we from Gall can extract Honey, then </l>
            <l>Sin may produce such Vertues. Simple men </l>
            <l>Aptly may credit: but beleeve me Friend, </l>
            <l>Those that are bad, their Mischeifes have no end. </l>
            <l>They are to theire affections so unjust, </l>
            <l>They banish chast Love to comply with Lust. </l>
            <l>I have bin long a Scholler in Loves Schoole, </l>
            <l>Experience made me a Proficient foole, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-064-a"/>
            <l>I know the desperate effects ensue </l>
            <l>This apish love, and would advertise you </l>
            <l>(As one that friendship and your knowing merit </l>
            <l>Has fasten'd in a cordiall tye;) inherit </l>
            <l>(Deare Sir) that blessed freedome, which the name </l>
            <l>Of Worth in Man can challenge, temper th' flame </l>
            <l>You have receiv'd: let not your female creature </l>
            <l>(Knowes how to work upon so good a Nature,) </l>
            <l>Take you up wholly, so your friends to be </l>
            <l>Depriv'd of what they love; Your company </l>
            <l>Which they hold pretious to 'em. Gentle Sir </l>
            <l>Let not your course runne so irregular: </l>
            <l>But limit so your passion, that we may, </l>
            <l>Despight of Love or Venus, have a day, </l>
            <l>Or two, or three to consecrate to mirth, </l>
            <l>And give our hopes in you a second birth. </l>
            <l>You that are one that shares in all the parts </l>
            <l>Of Natures blessings, and sublimist Arts, </l>
            <l>You that know all, that Man should know, is good, </l>
            <l>As worthy in your actions, as by blood </l>
            <l>Of your prime Ancestors, you that justly can </l>
            <l>Instruct in knowledge the illitterate Man </l>
            <l>By exact rule; be so much now your selfe, </l>
            <l>And let your judgement banish th'scurvy Elfe, </l>
            <l>Your too much doting Love, a thing that none </l>
            <l>But fooles and mad-men will be seene to owne: </l>
            <l>Dotage is incident to yeares fourescore; </l>
            <l>But you as yet have not seene twenty foure: </l>
            <l>It dulls the sence, and stupifies the wit, </l>
            <l>And to reside with them it is most fit. </l>
            <l>I know thy wit's as active as the fire, </l>
            <l>And subtill as the ayre. Kill that desire </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-064-b"/>
            <l>Would list thee 'mongst such Idiots. I know </l>
            <l>A nobler way than that for thee. Then goe </l>
            <l>Unto thy Study, see how ruinate </l>
            <l>It's growne, and through thy absence desolate. </l>
            <l>See how thy Bookes lye speechlesse, how they mourne </l>
            <l>(Like true observants) till thy sweet returne. </l>
            <l>And see what Randevous the Mo●thes have made; </l>
            <l>Here lyes a member of an Iliade, </l>
            <l>Compacted once, was Homers: Now it lyes </l>
            <l>Unto their spoile an humble Sacrifice. </l>
            <l>Correct these faults my friend, and thou shalt see, </l>
            <l>That childish Love's not worth thy Librarie. </l>
            <l>But I have div'd too deepe, and may suspect </l>
            <l>(Your Temper being mov'd) you will correct </l>
            <l>Me as the rest, taking on me a task </l>
            <l>Which may be doubtfull to you; yet I'le ask </l>
            <l>No mercie from you; what I've done, 'tis fit </l>
            <l>You should conceive was zeale, so tender it. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="ode" xml:id="ep000824-e41050">
            <head>To the truly vertuous and his much honoured Lady, the Lady <hi>Iane S. </hi>an Ode. </head>
            <lg>
              <l>YOu, that are shee </l>
              <l>Which every Woman ought to be, </l>
              <l>The glory of our age; </l>
              <l>Whose sweet demeanour shewes </l>
              <l>Where Love and Vertue flowes, </l>
              <l>Where Beauty and Delight doth dwell, </l>
              <l>Wee cannot finde your Parallell </l>
              <l>In all this Terren stage. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-065-a"/>
              <l>You that are shee </l>
              <l>Whose youth is from corruption free, </l>
              <l>My Fancie dare uphold. </l>
              <l>Were there more such as you, </l>
              <l>To noble Actions true, </l>
              <l>Men need not feare to say they did </l>
              <l>Possesse some <hi>heavenly treasure</hi>, hid </l>
              <l>E're since the age of gold. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>You that are shee </l>
              <l>Compos'd of <hi>Natures Rarity</hi>. </l>
              <l>Cherries in Winter grow </l>
              <l>Upon your lips, which tell </l>
              <l>How much you doe excell </l>
              <l>The Summers pride: but on your brest </l>
              <l>The Phoenix builds her spicie nest, </l>
              <l>Without dissolving snow. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>You that are shee, </l>
              <l>The <hi>top branch </hi>of that glorious tree, </l>
              <l>for Pious acts renown'd, </l>
              <l>Departed hence, but are </l>
              <l>Each of them fixt a starre </l>
              <l>In Heavens bright firmament, while you </l>
              <l>Inherit here as your just due </l>
              <l>Honour with Vertue crown'd. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>You that are shee, </l>
              <l>Distinguish can formality </l>
              <l>From needlesse pride; when wee </l>
              <l>Seeke for some beauteous face, </l>
              <l>Adorn'd with <hi>modest Grace</hi>. </l>
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-065-b"/>
              <l>A Lady that's so well enclinde. </l>
              <l>Shee beares a Seraphinian minde; </l>
              <l>Whose sacred Meditations to us shew, </l>
              <l>Shee's mark't a Saint, wee need not farther goe, </l>
              <l>For you are onely shee. </l>
            </lg>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e41820">
            <head>To the right Worshipfull Sir <hi>I. B. K. </hi>upon encouraging him in Poetry. </head>
            <l>MY Muse as cold as clay, from your quick Rayes </l>
            <l>Promethean like grew Masculine, her Bayes </l>
            <l>Receiv'd a freshnesse, your AEtheriall fire </l>
            <l>Ranne through her faculties 'till her desire </l>
            <l>Met with my wishes jointly to begin </l>
            <l>Our votes to you; yet stay; it were a sin </l>
            <l>Should shee omit <hi>your Lady</hi>, and your Race, </l>
            <l>The perfect figures of the sum of Grace. </l>
            <l>And honour'd Sir, to you, whose powerfull name </l>
            <l>Merits above the Donatives of ●ame: </l>
            <l>You that are great in goodnesse, whose blest Fate </l>
            <l>Makes you a Pillar of this Brittish state: </l>
            <l>May you be free from sorrow, free from care, </l>
            <l>That may disturb your quiet, to declare </l>
            <l>You onely mortall. May you live to see </l>
            <l>A Nestors age in blest felicity. </l>
            <l>May you continue ever in that seat </l>
            <l>Your merits, and not Fortune, have made great. </l>
            <l>May you enjoy your wishes full content, </l>
            <l>To crowne your latter dayes till they are spent. </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-066-a"/>
            <l>May you embrace a Fathers comfort, by </l>
            <l>Your children in succesfull Progenie, </l>
            <l>May they in it be happy, and may health </l>
            <l>Purchase the keeping you, and your just wealth </l>
            <l>From others deprivation, may Encrease </l>
            <l>For ever crowne the Harvest of your peace. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e42390">
            <head>A Sigh. </head>
            <l>POst happy sigh upon the wings </l>
            <l>Of some blest Cherubin, that sings </l>
            <l>Continuall Anthems in the Quire </l>
            <l>Of Heaven, there finish thy desire. </l>
            <l>Thou wert not borne for the poore use </l>
            <l>Of Mistresse, but my sinnes abuse; </l>
            <l>And 'tis not fit thou should'st endure </l>
            <l>A mixture with this ayre impure; </l>
            <l>Thou drew'st thy breath from me, and art </l>
            <l>The issue of a contrite heart. </l>
            <l>As Mothers, e're their time be runne, </l>
            <l>With anguish bring a breathlesse sonne </l>
            <l>Into the world; so I did thee, </l>
            <l>With griefe and unfain'd misery. </l>
            <l>Th'art of as little use, unlesse </l>
            <l>Thy Innocence can winne accesse </l>
            <l>To enter heavens eares; wee need </l>
            <l>Some Cherubin to intercede </l>
            <l>For us; expence wee need not feare, </l>
            <l>Bribes have no power to enter there: </l>
            <l>Or if thou doubt'st (because but one) </l>
            <l>Thou canst not well expresse a groane, </l>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-066-b"/>
            <l>Nor justly plead for mercie, I </l>
            <l>Will send thee Legions more, shall buy </l>
            <l>My soule from death, When all agree </l>
            <l>To fill the heavens with Harmony. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="poem" xml:id="ep000824-e42810">
            <head>To his friend <hi>J. W. </hi>a Meditation. </head>
            <l>DId wee consider rightly what a store </l>
            <l>Of imperfections waites to ruine man </l>
            <l>From's infancie to's grave; Vice makes a sore </l>
            <l>Upon his soule incurable, that can </l>
            <l>Precipitate his glories to th' Abysse, </l>
            <l>Once banisht from the Paradise of Blisse. </l>
            <l>His first breath is a cry, His last a groane; </l>
            <l>Yet happy in that groane, if hee dy'd well, </l>
            <l>Angels shall wait his soule's ascension, none </l>
            <l>Of Vertues instruments but shall excell </l>
            <l>In joy each other, that mans penitence </l>
            <l>Has brought him to that place of excellence. </l>
            <l>Th'unbridled Youth giving his folly raines, </l>
            <l>Disclaimes all councell that his errors show, </l>
            <l>Untill a second mischiefe binds in chaines </l>
            <l>The giddy Colt, and then he findes his woe. </l>
            <l>All that his Parents left him once consum'd, </l>
            <l>He will appeare a Peacock, but unplum'd. </l>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text>
        <front>
          <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000824-e43130">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-067-a"/>
            <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000824-067-b"/>
            <p>LOVE CROWNES THE END. </p>
            <p>A PASTORALL PRESENTED BY THE SCHOLLEES OF BINGHAM in the County of Notingham, in the yeare 1632. </p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Io. Tatham </hi>Gent. </p>
            <q>
              <gap extent="1" unit="line"></gap>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON: Printed by <hi>I. N. </hi>for RICHARD BEST, and are to be sold at his Shop neere Grayes-Inne-gate in Holborne. 1640. </p>
          </div>
        </front>
        <body>
          <div type="masque" xml:id="ep000824-e43270">
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-068-a"/>
            <div type="prologue" xml:id="ep000824-e43280">
              <head>The Prologue. </head>
              <l>YOu starres of Honour, brighter than the day, </l>
              <l>Or new rais'd Phoebus in his morning Ray; </l>
              <l>A● rich in Wisedome as in Vertues rare; </l>
              <l>Accept the choicest dish our wits prepare, </l>
              <l>As a third course to please your eye, which still </l>
              <l>Covets to have of novelties its fill. </l>
              <l>We have not bundled up some Kickshawes here </l>
              <l>To bid you welcome; Wee doe hate such geere. </l>
              <l>Our <hi></hi>braine's the Kitchin, and our wit's the meat, </l>
              <l>Preparitive to which, wee bid you eat, </l>
              <l>If lik't, if not refrain't; you Judges sit </l>
              <l>To damne or save our not yet ripen'd wit: </l>
              <l>So rest upon your goodnesse; if <hi>you frowne</hi>, </l>
              <l>Our poore endeavours then are troden downe. </l>
            </div>
            <div type="dialogue" xml:id="ep000824-e43580">
              <pb xml:id="ep000824-068-b"/>
              <head>Love crownes the end. </head>
              <stage xml:id="ep000824-e43600">
                <hi>A Grove discover'd, and in an obscure corner thereof </hi>Cliton <hi>as being a sleepe. To him </hi>Alexis. </stage>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e43630">
                <speaker>ALEXIS. </speaker>
                <l>HOW still the morning is, as if it meant </l>
                <l>To steale upon us without Times consent, </l>
                <l>And pry into our errors. I have beene </l>
                <l>Searching in every Thicket, Wood, and Greene </l>
                <l>To finde my Lamb, and many dolefull cryes </l>
                <l>Enter'd my eares e're day. What's this that lyes </l>
                <l>In such an obscure place, where none scarce tread, </l>
                <l>Unlesse the Ghosts of the disturbed dead? </l>
                <l>Blesse me great Pan, I see it's Clitons face </l>
                <l>With a sword drawne; how happy was my chace </l>
                <l>This way! I hope his folly has not made </l>
                <l>Himselfe a Beast, as butcher'd with this Blade; </l>
                <l>'T may be he sleepes: I'le speake to him, and try; </l>
                <l>Yet I halfe doubt him 'cause he here doth lye. </l>
                <l>Cliton, awake, the Night's dislodg'd, and now </l>
                <l>Bright Morne is trimming of her Virgin brow, </l>
                <l>To court the Sunne, when from the Westerne deepe </l>
                <l>And Thetis lap his glimmering beames doe peepe </l>
                <l>T'ascend his glorious Carre. Cliton— awake, </l>
                <l>And with thy sleepe all dreames of horror shake </l>
                <l>That may affright thee. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e43920">
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-069-a"/>
                <speaker>CLITON. </speaker>
                <l>Kinde Alexis, thanks, </l>
                <l>How found you me? </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e43970">
                <speaker>ALEXIS. </speaker>
                <l>Walking those flowry banks, </l>
                <l>'Twixt the greene valley, and the place which wee </l>
                <l>Have consecrated to Loves Deity: </l>
                <l>Seeking a stray'd Lamb, I did heare sad moanes </l>
                <l>Proceed from some like peales of parting groanes, </l>
                <l>Which I pursu'd, but in my search I found </l>
                <l>None but your selfe: you resting on this ground </l>
                <l>I wonder'd much to see you! </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e44070">
                <speaker>CLITON. </speaker>
                <l>So you might. </l>
                <l>But when y'ave heard the cause on't, 'twill affright </l>
                <l>Your easie brest. Doe you observe this Hand, </l>
                <l>This fatall Hand, at my unjust command </l>
                <l>Did:— Oh, I could destroy't! </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e44140">
                <speaker>ALEXIS. </speaker>
                <p>For what offence? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e44170">
                <speaker>CLITON. </speaker>
                <l>This hand has spilt the blood of Innocence, </l>
                <l>My Florida's. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e44220">
                <speaker>ALEXIS. </speaker>
                <p>How? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e44250">
                <speaker>CLITON. </speaker>
                <l>And when I'd done </l>
                <l>(As I might well) did hide me from the Sunne, </l>
                <l>Fearing his eye would be the onely cause </l>
                <l>To finde me out; and here from men and lawes </l>
                <l>I have obscur'd my selfe, and could not say </l>
                <l>'Twas justly night, when night: Nor day when day; </l>
                <l>My fact had sulled both. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e44390">
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-069-b"/>
                <speaker>ALEXIS. </speaker>
                <p>What urg'd thee to such inhumanity? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e44420">
                <speaker>CLITON. </speaker>
                <l>Onely suspition of her loyalty, </l>
                <l>Dreaming Lysander had enjoy'd her love, </l>
                <l>My jealousie to cruelty did move: </l>
                <l>I slew her three dayes since, and since have bin </l>
                <l>Each night at that place I stain'd with my sin, </l>
                <l>To seeke the body, but some sacred Power, </l>
                <l>For none else durst approach her purity, </l>
                <l>Has certainly made her immortall, and </l>
                <l>Convey'd the body to some holier land. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e44540">
                <speaker>ALEXIS. </speaker>
                <p>Is the body gone then? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e44570">
                <speaker>CLITON. </speaker>
                <p>Or else my eyes doe faile me as an▪ abject not worth their help. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e44600">
                <speaker>ALEXIS. </speaker>
                <l>Thy crime requires contrition; to that end, </l>
                <l>Thou shalt with me. Thy dayes to come shalt spend </l>
                <l>In holy uses; I'le prepare for thee, </l>
                <l>In the best forme I can, each property </l>
                <l>Belonging to a pensive man. You must </l>
                <l>Forget all youthfull pleasures, think on dust, </l>
                <l>And penitence the onely meanes to bring </l>
                <l>Thy soule to rest after this wandering. </l>
                <l>Will you with me? </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e44710">
                <speaker>CLITON. </speaker>
                <p>To death, or otherwise, since Florida is dead. <stage xml:id="ep000824-e44750">Exeunt. </stage>
                </p>
              </sp>
              <stage xml:id="ep000824-e44760">Cloe <hi>pursu'd by a lustfull sheepheard</hi>. </stage>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e44780">
                <speaker>Lustfull Sheepheard. </speaker>
                <l>●tay my darling, doe not flye, </l>
                <l>This place is private, here's none nigh. </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-070-a"/>
                <l>Feare not Wench, I'le doe no harme, </l>
                <l>But embrace thee in my arme; </l>
                <l>Cull and kisse, and doe the thing </l>
                <l>Shepheards doe at wrasteling, </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e44860">
                <speaker>CLOE. </speaker>
                <l>Oh help, if any Shepheards, neere, </l>
                <l>Heare my laments. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e44900">
                <speaker>Lust. Shepheard. </speaker>
                <l>Yet creature, doe not feare: </l>
                <l>But if you with coy disdaine, </l>
                <l>Doe think to leave me in my flame, </l>
                <l>I'le force those golden locks of thine </l>
                <l>To lye beneath these feet of mine; </l>
                <l>Then yeeld and here enjoy such sweet </l>
                <l>As with our embraces meet. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e45000">
                <speaker>CLOE. </speaker>
                <p>Oh haplesse Maid, no ayde will come. <stage xml:id="ep000824-e45030">Lysander steps forth. </stage>
                </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e45040">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <l>Feare not Virgin; here is some </l>
                <l>Natures monster; Villaine, why </l>
                <l>Does thy flame now burne so high? </l>
                <l>Will no other serve thy turne </l>
                <l>To quench the heats that in thee burne, </l>
                <l>But so faire a soule as shee? </l>
                <l>Villaine hence, or else I'le bee <stage xml:id="ep000824-e45130">Lustfull shep. gazeth on him, then runnes in. </stage>
                </l>
                <l>Thy Butcher. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e45150">
                <speaker>CLOE. </speaker>
                <l>Kinde Youth, to whom am I </l>
                <l>Bound for this faire courtesie? </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e45190">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <l>First unto Heaven faire Creature; next to me </l>
                <l>A poore unworthy Shepheard. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e45230">
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-070-b"/>
                <speaker>CLOE. </speaker>
                <l>May your Sweetest whom you love, </l>
                <l>Ever constant to you prove. </l>
                <l>Be shee brighter than the Sunne, </l>
                <l>Pleasing as our day at noone; </l>
                <l>Fresher than the morning dew: </l>
                <l>Sweeter than a new kill'd Ewe; </l>
                <l>Like Aurora deckt with flowers, </l>
                <l>Or the welcome Aprill showers. </l>
                <l>May shee love you, and you be </l>
                <l>The mirrour for true Constancie; </l>
                <l>Goe gentle Youth, and this day prosperous be </l>
                <l>Amongst our Swaines in your Activity. <stage xml:id="ep000824-e45380">Exit. </stage>
                </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e45390">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <l>A thousand thanks reward you </l>
                <l>Pan be my guide, and thou faire Gloriana, </l>
                <l>Whose beauty has encinder'd my poore heart </l>
                <l>Almost to nothing this day; thou shalt finde </l>
                <l>Thou hast a power above our humane kinde. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e45480">
                <speaker>DAPHNES. </speaker>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e45500">Exit. </stage>
                <l>Bright sunne, why do'st thou shine on me? </l>
                <l>Is it to mock me? keepe thy light; for I </l>
                <l>Had rather live in darknesse, and so dye. </l>
                <l>Or do'st thou shew thy lustre in disdaine, </l>
                <l>Because I have so oft with speech prophane </l>
                <l>Blasphem'd against thy goodnesse, And in praise </l>
                <l>Of a poore earthly creature spent my dayes? </l>
                <l>Do'st thou yet smile? forgive me, and I'le bee </l>
                <l>No more her servant, but will honour thee. </l>
                <l>Keepe thou thy brightnesse Phoebus, and this day </l>
                <l>From all our Swaines I'le bring the prize away. <stage xml:id="ep000824-e45630">Exit. </stage>
                </l>
              </sp>
              <stage xml:id="ep000824-e45640">
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-071-a"/>
                <hi>Leon, Gloriana, and Francisco. </hi>
              </stage>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e45660">
                <speaker>FRANCISCO. </speaker>
                <l>Fairest, this day, be pleas'd to smile on me, </l>
                <l>And let those hidden favours yet unshewne, </l>
                <l>Flow in abundance, that Swaines may see </l>
                <l>None e're can conquer me, but you alone. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e45720">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <l>My favours friend is past, and you have tasted </l>
                <l>So much of my poore bounty, that it's wasted. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e45760">
                <speaker>LEON. </speaker>
                <l>We stay too long sonne, pray make haste, </l>
                <l>Let us not spend time in waste. </l>
                <l>Daughter, you shall goe with mee, </l>
                <l>Where their pastime wee may see. </l>
                <l>Heark, I heare 'em make a noyse; <stage xml:id="ep000824-e45830">A noyse within. </stage>
                </l>
                <l>Oh my hearts my bonny boyes, </l>
                <l>Play your parts; when I was young </l>
                <l>I was full as stout and strong. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e45890">
                <speaker>FRAN. </speaker>
                <l>Dearest, I must part; this calls me hence. </l>
                <l>Father, I leave you. <stage xml:id="ep000824-e45930">Exit Fra: </stage>
                </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e45940">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <l>For ever I hope, would I could prophesie, </l>
                <l>And be effectuall; it should be so. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e45980">
                <speaker>LEON. </speaker>
                <l>Daughter, this way let us high; </l>
                <l>I am old, I'le not come nigh: </l>
                <l>Nor shalt thou my dapper Girle, </l>
                <l>Lest those staves that often whirle </l>
                <l>Hit thy face. What againe! <stage xml:id="ep000824-e46050">
                    <hi>A●w● againe</hi>. </stage>
                </l>
                <l>Nay then I feare wee goe in vaine. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e46080">
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-071-b"/>
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <l>Yet Father let us goe, that w● </l>
                <l>May know who gain'd the victory. <stage xml:id="ep000824-e46120">Exeunt. </stage>
                </l>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e46130">
                  <hi>The lustfull sheeph●●rd like a Satyre. </hi>
                </stage>
                <l>Because Dame Nature, pox of all her tricks, </l>
                <l>Has not dealt so well with me as shee ought, </l>
                <l>Making me but a lump of rough-hew'n stuffe, </l>
                <l>The pettish Wenches will not play with me, </l>
                <l>Nor tick nor toy, and cause I'm apt for sport: </l>
                <l>How e're I'm form'd, I've put on this disguise, </l>
                <l>To fright the baggages, when getting some </l>
                <l>'Twixt these my armes, ●'le force 'em to my will, </l>
                <l>Yet passe unknowne. Thus I my sences fill. </l>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e46240">Scrub within. So ho, so ho, so ho. </stage>
                <l>What noyse is yon? </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e46260">
                <speaker>SCRVB. </speaker>
                <p>Through the Woods, and through the Woods have I run after the Run-away my Master.— What art thou in the devils name? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e46290">
                <speaker>Lust. shepheard. </speaker>
                <l>Sirrah, I am— </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e46320">
                <speaker>SCRVB. </speaker>
                <p>A devil, I knew't before: Thou should'st be a leacherous devill by thy hayrie hide: but I am no Succubus goodman devill. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e46350">
                <speaker>Lust. shepheard </speaker>
                <p>Do'st thou feare me? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e46380">
                <speaker>SCRVB. </speaker>
                <p>Oh Lord, me Sir. I have met such another devill as thou art, in my Porridge dish. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e46410">
                <speaker>Lust. shepheard. </speaker>
                <p>And didst thou know him? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e46440">
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-072-a"/>
                <speaker>SCRVB. </speaker>
                <p>Know him? how doe you meane know him? I should be loth to know him or thee, or hee thee, or thy grand-Master me for any ill; for I have defi'd the devill and his works ever since the generall Earthquake, and that my Mothers Cat miscarried in the horse Pond. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e46470">
                <speaker>Lust. shepheard. </speaker>
                <p>Was thy Mother a Witch? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e46500">
                <speaker>SCRVB. </speaker>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e46520">Offers to strike. </stage>
                <p>How a Witch you devill— I'le witch you. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e46540">
                <speaker>Lust. shepheard. </speaker>
                <p>Hold man: shee was an honest woman. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e46570">
                <speaker>SCRVB. </speaker>
                <l>Nay, now thou ly'st, and thou be'st the devils devill: </l>
                <l>For I have heard her soberly say, shee had six— </l>
                <l>Bastards by a Sowgelder before shee pigg'd me. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e46620">
                <speaker>Lust. shepheard. </speaker>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e46640">Offers again. </stage>
                <p>Hold, hold man. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e46660">
                <speaker>SCRVB. </speaker>
                <p>The devill afraid of blowes! I'le make you spet fire. </p>
              </sp>
              <stage xml:id="ep000824-e46690">Runnes after him. </stage>
              <stage xml:id="ep000824-e46700">
                <hi>A great sh●wt</hi>. Lysander <hi>with a Garland on's head, and scarfes on's armes, </hi>Cloe <hi>following him</hi>. </stage>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e46740">
                <speaker>CLOE. </speaker>
                <l>Friendly Swaine, the day is yours; you see </l>
                <l>My prayer it seemes succesfull was to thee. </l>
                <l>Pitty my mayden teares; till now, I ne're </l>
                <l>Su'd to a shepheard, but the shepheards were </l>
                <l>My suiters. </l>
                <l>Nor deeme me light▪ because my love is such; </l>
                <l>I love indeed, and feare I love too much. </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-072-b"/>
                <l>You sav'd my life, my chastity, what more? </l>
                <l>Take me as one that was your owne before. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e46850">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <l>How much I grieve faire Shepheardesse, my Fa●● </l>
                <l>Will not allow me such a just proportion, </l>
                <l>To render thee, as thy deserts have merited </l>
                <l>From me. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e46910">
                <speaker>CLOE. </speaker>
                <l>Oh friend! </l>
                <l>I●le be your servant, and your flocks will keepe. </l>
                <l>I'le nightly watch while you doe sweetly sleepe▪ </l>
                <l>And in the morne I'le willingly to field, </l>
                <l>While you doe taste the sweets Loves valleyes yeeld, </l>
                <l>And with industrious labour against noone, </l>
                <l>Will get your dinner ready, so you will </l>
                <l>But smile on me, and say well done. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e47010">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <l>To starve your hopes from furder prosecution in this suit. </l>
                <l>Know I've already fixt my resolution </l>
                <l>To love none but faire Gloriana, shee </l>
                <l>Is the Commandresse of my life, and fortunes: </l>
                <l>So much I pitty you, that I could wish </l>
                <l>I had two hearts, that you might share in one </l>
                <l>As a just recompence for your love, but why do I </l>
                <l>Entertaine such frivolous unnecessary talk. </l>
                <l>May you live happy, and enjoy as rare, </l>
                <l>And constant Shepheard as your selfe is faire. <stage xml:id="ep000824-e47140">Exit. </stage>
                </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e47150">
                <speaker>CLOE. </speaker>
                <l>Is my face wither'd? or has Nature so </l>
                <l>Deform'd me lately that I am not Cloe? </l>
                <l>For thee poore Cloe Shepheards have pitcht the Barre, </l>
                <l>Wrastl'd, and leap'd, and showne the feats of Warre. </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-073-a"/>
                <l>For thee each strove to gaine thee as his Dove; </l>
                <l>But thou did'st sleight and scorne their simple love. </l>
                <l>How many Verses have the Shepheards made, </l>
                <l>In praising of thy Beauty, whil'st thou laid </l>
                <l>Thy heart on him that hates to heare thee nam'd, </l>
                <l>And thy delight is still to have him fam'd? </l>
                <l>How many Rings and Gloves hast thou receiv'd </l>
                <l>From the poore Swaines thou often times deceiv'd? </l>
                <l>For thee on Holy dayes they often would </l>
                <l>Meet on the Heath next to the Pinders fold, </l>
                <l>Where they with Musick, and such sweet content, </l>
                <l>Would spend their time to make thee merriment. </l>
                <l>Since then my love is not one mite rewarded, </l>
                <l>And that my Beauty is no more regarded: </l>
                <l>I'le teare these golden locks, that shepheards may </l>
                <l>Leave off their sport, and make no Holy-day. </l>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e47390">SINGS. </stage>
                <l>I will follow through yon Grove, </l>
                <l>Where I soone shall meet my Love; </l>
                <l>Then with sweet embraces wee </l>
                <l>Will clip, and cull, and none shall see. </l>
                <l>A willow Garland I will make, </l>
                <l>And sweetly weare it for his sake. </l>
                <l>Then through Thickets, Woods, and Plaines, </l>
                <l>I will hide me from the Swaines? </l>
                <l>Hy da, hy da, what art thou? <stage xml:id="ep000824-e47490">As she is running in, meetes her. </stage>
                </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e47500">
                <speaker>DAPHNES. </speaker>
                <p>You were not wont to question that; how fares my dearest Love? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e47530">
                <speaker>CLOE. </speaker>
                <l>Hence thou coward, hence from me: </l>
                <l>Blush at thy disloyal●y. </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-073-b"/>
                <l>Did'st not tell me thou would'st gaine </l>
                <l>Me reputation by thy fame; </l>
                <l>And suffer'st now a stranger beare </l>
                <l>The prize, and thou to have no share? </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e47610">
                <speaker>DAPHNE. </speaker>
                <l>Your frownes my Fairest, and not hee, </l>
                <l>Gain'd from me the victory. </l>
                <l>Had you smil'd as you did frowne, </l>
                <l>All his strength I'd mauger'd downe. </l>
                <l>What has disturb'd my Love? who has committed </l>
                <l>This injurie to thy person? </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e47690">
                <speaker>CLOE. </speaker>
                <l>Ha, ha, ha; foole, foole! see you now foole? </l>
                <l>Foole! kisse— kisse— kisse— <stage xml:id="ep000824-e47730">Exit. </stage>
                </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e47740">
                <speaker>DAPHNES. </speaker>
                <p>What fickle things are women? yet they are such men cannot be without; our too much doting on 'em makes 'em proud; for loving them, they'd make us hate our selves. I doe suspect this bad distemper in her proceeds from some deniall Lysander has given her to her unlawfull suit, knowing my love to her. 'Tis so. I must not let her suffer in too high a nature. <stage xml:id="ep000824-e47780">Exit. </stage>
                </p>
              </sp>
              <stage xml:id="ep000824-e47790">
                <hi>A place discover'd all greene mirtles, adorn'd with Roses, a Title written over't thus. </hi>LOVERS VALLEY. </stage>
              <stage xml:id="ep000824-e47810">Lysander and Gloriana. </stage>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e47840">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <l>Dearest Love, faire as the Easterne morne, </l>
                <l>When with her Summers roabe shee decks the Plaines, </l>
                <l>And hangs on every bush a liquid pearle, </l>
                <l>In Mayes triumphing moneth▪ sweet as the ayre, </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-074-a"/>
                <l>The Phoenix does expire in, sit while I play </l>
                <l>The cunning Thiefe, and steale thy heart away, </l>
                <l>And thou shalt stand as Judge to censure me, </l>
                <l>To recompence thy losse I must agree; </l>
                <l>To give my heart, which being understood, </l>
                <l>'Tis but exchange, I keepe your heart, you mine. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e47960">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <l>Content my Love thus, shee would court thee, </l>
                <l>And thus and thus shee'd play a Wantons part: </l>
                <l>Doe I not blush Adonis. <stage xml:id="ep000824-e48020">Kisse him. </stage>
                </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e48030">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <l>Oh, you must not blush! you spoile the jest on't, </l>
                <l>I'le span thy Waste, and doe as Wantons use; </l>
                <l>I'le be Adonis, but will not refuse. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e48090">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <p>Nay fie, you stray beyond your limits. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e48120">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e48140">Kisse. </stage>
                <p>Modesty allowes such undefiled mixtures. </p>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e48160">To them FRANCISCO. </stage>
                <p>Ah! where are my eyes? what curst unruly windes Have blowne 'em out, and in their stead plac'd these base counterfaits! Oh you Deities? you are unjust to suffer this? If these eyes be my owne may they be blasted, that without my Lycence <q>
                    <l>Durst see this object: but yet let reason </l>
                    <l>Sway my passion. </l>
                    <l>Why doe I wish a mischiefe on my selfe </l>
                    <l>That must see their destruction? I have long </l>
                    <l>Suspected him by reason of her Necios, </l>
                    <l>And the continuall scorne dwelt on her brow </l>
                    <l>When I did proffer love, were I provided </l>
                    <l>I'd rush upon 'em, and from his base armes </l>
                    <pb xml:id="ep000824-074-b"/>
                    <l>Snatch the false Girle, but I'le stand secure </l>
                    <l>A while and over-heare 'em. </l>
                  </q>
                </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e48290">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <l>'Tis time to part, w'ave dally'd Time too long. </l>
                <l>Lysander, will you walk? </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e48340">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <l>Thinks Gloriana </l>
                <l>That Time is lost that's spent with her Lysander </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e48400">
                <speaker>FRANCISCO. </speaker>
                <l>Deluding devill </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e48430">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <l>I could Lysander. </l>
                <l>(Might it not staine my Mayden-yeares) live onely </l>
                <l>By gazing on thy Beauty. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e48490">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <l>Nay, now you mock me; but I hope e're long </l>
                <l>Wee shall with more security enjoy </l>
                <l>What our hearts wish for. Where shall wee next meet? </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e48540">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <p>In this very place to morrow be sure you meet. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e48570">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e48590">Exeunt. </stage>
                <l>I will not faile. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e48610">
                <speaker>FRANCISCO. </speaker>
                <l>Nor I to meet you both. Oh my best starres! </l>
                <l>How I shall weave my selfe into revenge just, just Gods </l>
                <l>y'ave stampt my braine for mischiefe▪ which on them </l>
                <l>I'le execute. </l>
                <l>And none shall pry into my faults within. </l>
                <l>Revenge has Coverts, fit to hide his sin. </l>
              </sp>
              <stage xml:id="ep000824-e48690">Exit. </stage>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e48700">
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-075-a"/>
                <speaker>CLOE </speaker>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e48720">mad. </stage>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e48730">SINGS. </stage>
                <l>Hey downe a downe derry, </l>
                <l>And shall not wee be merry? </l>
                <l>A fire on thy hole, </l>
                <l>'Tis as black as a cole, </l>
                <l>And thy nose is as browne as a berry. </l>
                <l>Hi ho. What a thing this love is? </l>
                <l>When Love did act a womans part, </l>
                <l>
                  <stage xml:id="ep000824-e48820">Shee sings .</stage>Shee could have dy'd with all her heart, </l>
                <l>It swell'd her so in every part; </l>
                <l>Shee swore 'twas winde, and then did— </l>
                <l>Hi, hi, hi, hi, </l>
                <l>Nymphes to her </l>
                <l>Sing about her. </l>
                <l>Love cannot chuse but pitty yeeld, </l>
                <l>He never liv'd in tented field, </l>
                <l>'Mongst iron hearted men, </l>
                <l>He knowes both how, and when </l>
                <l>Thee to restore </l>
                <l>To what thou wert before. </l>
                <l>He has a tender brest, which knowes </l>
                <l>Your wants by the tormenting woes </l>
                <l>He's subject to himselfe. </l>
                <l>Then doe not you despaire, </l>
                <l>That are both young and faire. </l>
                <l>Thus wee convay you hence. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e49000">
                <speaker>CLOE. </speaker>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e49020">Takes Cloe <hi>with 'em</hi>. </stage>
                <p>Where doe you leade mee? <stage xml:id="ep000824-e49060">Exeunt. </stage>
                </p>
              </sp>
              <stage xml:id="ep000824-e49070">Lysander and Gloriana. </stage>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e49100">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <l>How blest are wee, that Fortune hath </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-075-b"/>
                <l>So much befriended us in this happy? </l>
                <l>Convenient opportunity? </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e49150">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <l>'Tis an unaccustom'd favour, </l>
                <l>And we ought in duty to acknowledge </l>
                <l>A thankfulnesse for it. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e49200">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e49220">Shee sits downe. </stage>
                <l>So sits the pride of Nature to out-vye </l>
                <l>Each glorious Beauty of the chequer'd field, </l>
                <l>And Flora's richest Wardrobe. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e49270">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <l>I perceive </l>
                <l>Y'ave practis'd long in th'flattering Rules of love. </l>
                <l>What wil reward you? </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e49320">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <l>A kisse is more than I can merit. </l>
                <l>Will you sing. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e49360">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <p>And you'l give me another for my paines. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e49390">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <l>Put it to the tryall, </l>
                <l>You shall not loose your labour. </l>
              </sp>
              <stage xml:id="ep000824-e49430">SONG. </stage>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e49440">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <l>Sit while I doe gather flowers, </l>
                <l>And depopulate the Bowers. </l>
                <l>Here's a kisse will come to thee; </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e49490">
                <speaker>Lysander. </speaker>
                <l>Give me one, I'le give thee three. </l>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e49520">BOTH. </stage>
                <l>Thus in harmlesse sport wee may, </l>
                <l>Passe all idle houres away. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e49550">
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-076-a"/>
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <l>Hark, hark how fine </l>
                <l>The Birds doe chime, </l>
                <l>And pretty Philomel </l>
                <l>Her moane doth tell. </l>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e49620">BOTH. </stage>
                <l>Then pitty, pitty love, and all is well. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e49640">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <l>Here's the Violet, Pink, and Rose, </l>
                <l>The sweetest breathings for the nose. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e49680">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <l>Yet thy breath to me doth yeeld </l>
                <l>More fragrant sents than all the field. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e49720">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <l>Love cares not for flowers or toyes, </l>
                <l>Play games for your apish Boyes. </l>
                <l>Nor superstition </l>
                <l>For his condition </l>
                <l>Is for to know </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e49790">
                <speaker>Lysander </speaker>
                <p>— if you love or no? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e49820">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <l>Then answer, love I or no. </l>
                <l>But yet me thinks that face should be </l>
                <l>The Modell of true constancie: </l>
                <l>Therefore no reason have I, </l>
                <l>To suspect thy loyalty, </l>
                <l>Here's another kisse for thee. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e49900">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <l>Give me one, I'le give thee three. </l>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e49930">BOTH. </stage>
                <l>Thus in harmlesse sport wee may, </l>
                <l>Passe all idle houres away. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e49960">
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-076-b"/>
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <l>Hark, hark how fine </l>
                <l>The Birds doe chime, </l>
                <l>And pretty Philomel, </l>
                <l>Her moane doth tell▪ </l>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e50030">BOTH. </stage>
                <l>Then pitty, pitty Love, and all is well. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e50050">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <l>Y'ave sung me most a sleepe, my eyes are dull and heavy, </l>
                <l>Faith I must make thy lap my pillow. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e50090">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <l>Repose thy gentle head on't. Alas! </l>
                <l>I'm heavy too, and must obey my destinie. <stage xml:id="ep000824-e50130">Sleepe. </stage>
                </l>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e50140">The Destinies. </stage>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e50150">SING. </stage>
                <l>Sleepe on, sleepe on, </l>
                <l>For wee have so decreed, </l>
                <l>That thou must bleed: </l>
                <l>Sleepe on, sleepe on, </l>
                <l>And maist thou never rise, </l>
                <l>For blood the shepheard cryes. </l>
                <l>Sleepe on, sleepe on. <stage xml:id="ep000824-e50230">Exeunt. </stage>
                </l>
              </sp>
              <stage xml:id="ep000824-e50240">A heavenly messenger in white. </stage>
              <q>
                <floatingText>
                  <body>
                    <div type="song" xml:id="ep000824-e50280">
                      <head>SONG. </head>
                      <l>Rise, rise Lysander to prevent </l>
                      <l>What the Destinies decreed. </l>
                      <l>Thou art constant, permanent, </l>
                      <l>And must not bleed▪ </l>
                      <l>Thy constant seed </l>
                      <l>Shall be the shepheards joy, </l>
                      <l>No annoy </l>
                      <pb xml:id="ep000824-077-a"/>
                      <l>Shall attend </l>
                      <l>Such a friend </l>
                      <l>As the Lasses need. </l>
                      <l>Rise, rise, awake! </l>
                      <l>And sleepe off shake; </l>
                      <l>The Heavens are pleas'd thy part to take, </l>
                      <l>For thy Love's sake. <stage xml:id="ep000824-e50450">Exit: </stage>
                      </l>
                    </div>
                  </body>
                </floatingText>
              </q>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e50460">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e50480">They stirre. </stage>
                <l>Lysander, where ar't? Lord how my fancie's troubled! </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e50510">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <l>How fares my Gloriana? I have had </l>
                <l>Strange thoughts that would have dispossest </l>
                <l>Me of my rest, had I not tooke it here </l>
                <l>On your sacred lap. </l>
              </sp>
              <stage xml:id="ep000824-e50580">Francisco disguis'd with others▪ </stage>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e50590">
                <speaker>FRANCISCO. </speaker>
                <l>That is the man: upon him instantly </l>
                <l>While I attach his Mistresse. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e50630">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <p>Ah me Lysander, what meanes these sad spectacles▪ </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e50670">
                <speaker>1. VILLANE. </speaker>
                <p>Wee must have life and death. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e50710">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <p>Both life and death: how can that be? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e50740">
                <speaker>FRAN. </speaker>
                <p>Thy life, and thy Lysanders death. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e50780">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <l>I've heard that voyce e're now </l>
                <l>Afford more milder language. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e50820">
                <speaker>FRAN. </speaker>
                <l>Stop her mouth lest shee does charme me </l>
                <l>Unto pitty. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e50860">
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-077-b"/>
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <p>Are you but men, and dare doe this? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e50890">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <p>Oh spare Lysander, sheath your swords in me. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e50930">
                <speaker>FRAN. </speaker>
                <p>Wee'l not expostulate: take that. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e50960">
                <speaker>2. VILLANE. </speaker>
                <p>And that. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e51000">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e51020">They take her with them. </stage>
                <l>Oh Lysander! </l>
                <l>Stay, stay, let me but breath my last </l>
                <l>Upon her lips, and I'le forgive this Butchery. </l>
                <l>Cowards, Villaines, Miscreants, have you left me? </l>
                <l>But oh my fairest, whether art thou fled? </l>
                <l>Feare has made pale those cheekes that were so red. </l>
                <l>I'le follow thee: they shall not dare to touch </l>
                <l>The least hem of thy garments. But oh, I faint; </l>
                <l>And must surrender up to earth that part </l>
                <l>I tooke from her. Gloriana, oh Gloriana! </l>
              </sp>
              <stage xml:id="ep000824-e51160">Claudia and Florida. </stage>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e51170">
                <speaker>CLAVDIA. </speaker>
                <l>Wee may for recreation walk, </l>
                <l>And use some pretty harmlesse talk. </l>
                <l>Religion does not tye us to </l>
                <l>A stricter course than wee can doe. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e51230">
                <speaker>FLORIDA. </speaker>
                <l>Tis dangerous walking, every field </l>
                <l>Doth nought but sounds of horror yeeld, </l>
                <l>And to my fancie doth appeare </l>
                <l>Poore slaughter'd Maids; the Butchers beare </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-078-a"/>
                <l>The name of Lovers, and can finde </l>
                <l>A way in killing to be kinde. <stage xml:id="ep000824-e51310">Lysander. Oh! </stage>
                </l>
                <l>Ah me, whence came that groane? </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e51330">
                <speaker>CLAUDIA. </speaker>
                <p>It is a Shepheard wounded sore. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e51360">
                <speaker>FLORIDA. </speaker>
                <l>Sure I've seene this face before! </l>
                <l>Oh 'tis Lysander th' truest Swaine, </l>
                <l>That ever breath'd on Grove or Plaine. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e51420">
                <speaker>CLAUDIA. </speaker>
                <p>What, is hee mark'd for present death? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e51450">
                <speaker>FLORIDA. </speaker>
                <l>No, there is hopes of life: his breath </l>
                <l>I feele come coldly. <stage xml:id="ep000824-e51490">Take him with 'em. </stage>
                </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e51500">
                <speaker>CLAUDIA. </speaker>
                <l>Help him in. </l>
                <l>Pan be just, reward this sin. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e51550">
                <speaker>SCRUB. </speaker>
                <p>The devill and his dam I think have carri'd away my Master; I cannot finde him in never a Wenches placuit, (pocket I should say) and yet I have beene in a simple many since I came among these Mutton-Mongers, these sheepe-eaters, unlesse they have hid him amongst their wooll, I cannot imagine where hee should be I will weare my shooes to peeces but I'le finde him. <stage xml:id="ep000824-e51580">Exit. </stage>
                </p>
              </sp>
              <stage xml:id="ep000824-e51590">Lysander, Claudia, Florida, and Cloe. </stage>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e51600">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <l>Religious Matron, from your divine hand </l>
                <l>I have receiv'd my life next to heavens providence: </l>
                <l>Sure my wounds were not desperate, or else </l>
                <l>Some Angell did afford a soveraigne Balsome </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-078-b"/>
                <l>To cure 'em in such an instant: but howsoever, </l>
                <l>I must ascribe it to your pious care: </l>
                <l>For which I owe you more than I can pay, </l>
                <l>Unlesse it be my life. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e51700">
                <speaker>CLAUDIA. </speaker>
                <l>The Surgery I use is sent from Heaven, </l>
                <l>And you owe them your life, not me. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e51740">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <l>But Florida, </l>
                <l>Did you ne're heare of your Cliton since? </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e51800">
                <speaker>FLORIDA. </speaker>
                <l>Never. </l>
                <l>Yet I would gladly see him, did I know </l>
                <l>By what meanes to atchieve it? </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e51850">
                <speaker>CLOE. </speaker>
                <l>Deare friend, the stories of us both if weigh'd </l>
                <l>In an equall ballance, would poize each other </l>
                <l>Yet to put her love to the Test, I'le undertake your message. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e51900">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <p>Thou wilt endeare me to thee then, about it. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e51930">
                <speaker>FLORIDA. </speaker>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e51950">Exit Cloe. </stage>
                <p>You heard how Cloe came to our happy Cure. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e51980">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <p>Never. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e52010">
                <speaker>FLORIDA. </speaker>
                <l>The Wood Nymphes brought her to our Cell, finding </l>
                <l>Her stray'd where ever since sh'as bin. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e52050">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <l>If you will with mee, <hi></hi>I'le promise you, you shall see your Cliton: </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e52100">
                <speaker>FLORIDA. </speaker>
                <p>On those conditions I will. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e52130">
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-079-a"/>
                <speaker>CLAVDIA. </speaker>
                <p>Whether now? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e52160">
                <speaker>FLORIDA. </speaker>
                <p>No farther than with your consent, and if you please, yo● may goe with us. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e52190">
                <speaker>Clau. </speaker>
                <p>I am contented. <stage xml:id="ep000824-e52220">Exeunt. </stage>
                </p>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e52230">Gloriana distracted. </stage>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e52240">SINGS. </stage>
                <l>I know Lysander's dead, </l>
                <l>Then farewell maydenhead; </l>
                <l>Thou art but one: </l>
                <l>When I am gone: </l>
                <l>It never shall be said— hy ho, ho. </l>
                <l>Oh Lysander. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e52330">
                <speaker>CLITON </speaker>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e52350">like a Hermit. </stage>
                <l>Save you faire Maid, I wish you joy, </l>
                <l>Free from ought that may annoy </l>
                <l>Your quiet, or disturb your sence; </l>
                <l>Send you health and penitence. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e52400">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <p>Ha, ha, ha, what, are you Lysander? what, with that beard there's a great beard indeed: heark you Fryer Tuck, doe you see you handsome shepheard Lysander? </p>
                <l>Why did you say he was dead? </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e52470">
                <speaker>CLITON. </speaker>
                <l>You are mistaken, I'm a Hermit that can cure </l>
                <l>All wounds, but what sinne makes impure; </l>
                <l>And those are cur'd by one above: </l>
                <l>I can help those ills that move </l>
                <l>Man to distraction, jealous feares, </l>
                <l>In man or woman. I have yeares </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-079-b"/>
                <l>Has gain'd experience to apply </l>
                <l>For all sorts a safe remedy. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e52570">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e52590">SINGS. </stage>
                <l>Doe you see where he doth stand, </l>
                <l>With a Crosse-Bow in his hand. </l>
                <l>I will follow thee my Deare, </l>
                <l>Though the Goblins keepeth there. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e52640">
                <speaker>CLITON. </speaker>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e52660">Offers to goe in. </stage>
                <p>Stay pure Mayd. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e52680">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <l>Why doe you hold me old man? insooth you shall not. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e52710">
                <speaker>CLITON. </speaker>
                <l>●f you will be rul'd by mee, </l>
                <l>You shall your Lysander see. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e52760">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <l>●hall I indeed now? </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e52790">
                <speaker>CLITON. </speaker>
                <l>Come with me and you shall know </l>
                <l>More, if you will but patient grow. <stage xml:id="ep000824-e52830">Exeunt. </stage>
                </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e52840">
                <speaker>Leonand Alexis. </speaker>
                <p>Good Father, be patient. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e52870">
                <speaker>LEON. </speaker>
                <l>〈◊〉 not my daughter lost, my onely daughter, </l>
                <l>●he onely staffe whereon my age did rest, </l>
                <l>And onely comfort which I had on earth? </l>
                <l>Oh! I am miserable. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e52930">
                <speaker>Leon and Alexis. </speaker>
                <p>●here's hopes yet left to finde her. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e52960">
                <speaker>LEON. </speaker>
                <l>●ever. Some rude and savage hand has kill'd my Girle, </l>
                <l>●aving deflowr'd her of her virgin honour. </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-080-a"/>
                <l>Talk not of patience, 'tis the onely meanes </l>
                <l>To cure a bad distemper, to grow worse, </l>
                <l>And fire it out of him. Oh my Alexis! </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e53040">
                <speaker>ALEXIS. </speaker>
                <l>I'm lost in loosing her. </l>
                <l>Let us endeavour to finde her, </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e53080">
                <speaker>LEON. </speaker>
                <l>I'le take thy counsell, goodnesse guide me still, </l>
                <l>Sometimes are Parents crosse against their will. </l>
              </sp>
              <stage xml:id="ep000824-e53120">Exeunt. </stage>
              <stage xml:id="ep000824-e53130">Lysander. Claudia. Florida. </stage>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e53140">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <l>W'are almost at his Cell, where hee do's waste </l>
                <l>Himselfe away with griefe, thinking you are </l>
                <l>A Citizen in Heaven, and that wrong </l>
                <l>He did you, has so defil'd his soule, </l>
                <l>It cannot be purg'd off but by such penitence. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e53210">
                <speaker>FLORIDA. </speaker>
                <l>Y'ave mov'd my heart that it dissolves to teares, </l>
                <l>Of blood, and water, for the strictnesse hee </l>
                <l>Has undergone for mee. <stage xml:id="ep000824-e53260">Enter Cloe and Daphnes. </stage>
                </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e53270">
                <speaker>CLOE. </speaker>
                <l>I'm glad I've found you; doe you see w'are coupl'd as </l>
                <l>Lovers ought to doe: but your Gloriana is lost beyond </l>
                <l>Recovery. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e53330">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <p>How? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e53360">
                <speaker>DAPHNES. </speaker>
                <l>Shee hearing of your death fell frantick, and </l>
                <l>Since I have not seene her ne're our Groves. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e53400">
                <speaker>LYSANDER </speaker>
                <l>Let us put wings to our pursuit to finde her; </l>
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-080-b"/>
                <l>And first wee'l search his Cell. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e53440">
                <speaker>CLAVDIA. </speaker>
                <p>Great Pan send all things well. <stage xml:id="ep000824-e53480">Exeunt. </stage>
                </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e53490">
                <speaker>FRANCISCO. </speaker>
                <l>Oh Conscience, how thou do'st buz into my eares; despaire </l>
                <l>The thing attends my guilt, Gloriana lost: </l>
                <l>For whose sweet sake I heap't new sinnes upon me? </l>
                <l>What has my fury purchas'd nothing? Yes! </l>
                <p>Hell, and destruction, which onely by a haire hangs o're my head, which blowne by the least winde, falls downe and sinks me. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e53570">
                <speaker>SCRVB. </speaker>
                <p>You sirrah, madcap, that creepes like a Crab there: Hark you, doe not you know one Francisco and Pisander, two vagabonds, that cannot live in peace with Poultry, but they must flye after sheepe? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e53620">
                <speaker>FRANCISCO. </speaker>
                <p>I owe that wretched name Francisco. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e53660">
                <speaker>SCRUB. </speaker>
                <p>Who? you with that face! pray where's Pisander then? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e53700">
                <speaker>FRANC. </speaker>
                <p>I left him at the Court when I came thence. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e53730">
                <speaker>SCRUB. </speaker>
                <p>I see you shepheards will lye abominably, hee has beene from the Court ever since seven yeares before hee was borne. </p>
              </sp>
              <stage xml:id="ep000824-e53760">Lysander. Leon. Gloriana. Claud. Florida. Cloe. Cliton. Daphnes. Alexis. </stage>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e53770">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <p>Friends, wee are happy made, Fortune and Love reserv'd these blisses to crowne the end of things. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e53800">
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-081-a"/>
                <speaker>CLITON. </speaker>
                <l>The story you related Florida. </l>
                <l>How this divine Matron did take your body, </l>
                <l>Finding it warme, and did apply such Balsames </l>
                <l>As hath preserv'd your life, makes me most happy. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e53870">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <p>I'm blest in my Gloriana. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e53910">
                <speaker>DAPHNES. </speaker>
                <p>I in my Cloe. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e53950">
                <speaker>CLITON. </speaker>
                <l>And I in Florida. </l>
                <stage xml:id="ep000824-e53990">Leon, Alexis, Claudia, and Florida. </stage>
                <l>And wee to see you possesse such blisse. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54010">
                <speaker>FRAN. </speaker>
                <p>Ah! Protect me some blest power: keepe farther off. I am yet reconcil'd with heaven. I doe confesse I kill'd you! Oh be mercifull for their sweet sakes, whose innocence cannot see, or be disturb'd by thee. There they are by thee; thy once deare Gloriana. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54050">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <p>What a distemper's this? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54080">
                <speaker>FRANCISCO. </speaker>
                <p>What will appease thy Ghost? give me but time to aske forgivenesse of those sacred powers I've most offended, by depriving thee of life and being, and thou shalt have my life for thy just sacrifice. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54110">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <p>I apprehend his guilt: shepheard, feare not; your hate grew not to such desperate effects as you expected. Feele, I live and breath! </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54140">
                <speaker>FRAN. </speaker>
                <p>Delude me not, 'tis impossible. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54170">
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-081-b"/>
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <p>These shall witnesse it. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54200">
                <speaker>OMNES. </speaker>
                <p>Wee doe. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54230">
                <speaker>FRAN. </speaker>
                <p>Can you forgive then my attempt? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54260">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <p>With a true heart. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54290">
                <speaker>OMNES. </speaker>
                <p>Lysander's still himselfe, noble and wise. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54330">
                <speaker>FRANCISCO. </speaker>
                <p>And can you Fairest wipe that Ignominy off, I deserv'd from you? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54360">
                <speaker>GLORIANA. </speaker>
                <p>
                  <hi>My Lysanders </hi>word sufficeth for us both. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54400">
                <speaker>FRAN. </speaker>
                <l>Then may you both live happy many yeares: </l>
                <l>May your joyes, never be disturb'd by feares. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54440">
                <speaker>SCRUB. </speaker>
                <p>Heark you sir, now all your talk is over, I would know one thing of you? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54470">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <p>And what's that? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54500">
                <speaker>SCRUB. </speaker>
                <p>Have you met with one <hi>Pisander, Leon</hi>, and Francisco in your Travailes? </p>
                <p>The Duke is dead that banisht good old Leon, and could I finde him; his lands shall be restor'd. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54570">
                <speaker>LEON. </speaker>
                <p>I am that Leon that with my sonne and daughter here have liv'd e're since in this Rurall way. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54610">
                <pb xml:id="ep000824-082-a"/>
                <speaker>OMNES. </speaker>
                <p>Blessings doe follow blessings. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54640">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <p>Then I am that Pisander that left the Court, to gaine thy Daughters love by the name of <hi>Lysander. Scrub</hi>, do'st thou know me now? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54690">
                <speaker>SCRVB. </speaker>
                <p>A pestlence on't, you are hee indeed. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54720">
                <speaker>FRAN. </speaker>
                <p>Pisander, embrace thy friend Francisco. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54770">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <p>Francisco! thou cloy'st me with joy. <stage xml:id="ep000824-e54810">Embrace. </stage>
                </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54820">
                <speaker>FRAN. </speaker>
                <p>I left the Court for the same end you did. </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54850">
                <speaker>LYSANDER. </speaker>
                <p>Shee's mine now Sir, is shee not? </p>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="ep000824-e54880">
                <speaker>LEON. </speaker>
                <l>As fast as th' Priest can make her, </l>
                <l>Fortune has made all happy: Yet 'tis fit </l>
                <l>If they will wed, your hands should licence it. </l>
              </sp>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
              <q>Amor finem coronat. </q>
            </epigraph>
          </div>
        </body>
        <back>
          <div type="to_the_reader" xml:id="ep000824-e54960">
            <p>GEntle Reader, there are some faults which (through the obscurity of the Coppie, and absence of the Author) have passed the Presse; To particularize them were needlesse; But favourably looke o're them, and with thy Pen courteously correct such defects as thou shalt finde, not condemning the Presse or injuring the Author. </p>
            <pb xml:id="ep000824-082-b"/>
          </div>
        </back>
      </text>
    </group>
  </text>
</TEI>
