<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000773" xml:lang="eng">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Londinum triumphans : Londons triumphs celebrated in honour of the truely deserving Sir Anthony Bateman, Knight, Lord Maior of the honourable City of London, and done at the costs and charges of the Right Worshipful the Company of Skinners, the 29th of October, 1663 / by John Tatham.</title>
        <author>
<!--Tatham, John-->
          <persName>
            <forename>John</forename>
            <surname>Tatham</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="dracor">DraCor</publisher>
        <idno type="URL">https://dracor.org/</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence>
            <ab>CC0 1.0</ab>
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Licence</ref>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl type="digitalSource">
          <name>EarlyPrint Project</name>
          <idno type="URL">https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A63188.xml</idno>
          <availability>
            <p>
            This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is available for reuse, according to the terms of
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>
            . The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
          </p>
          </availability>
          <bibl type="originalSource">
            <biblFull>
              <titleStmt>
                <title>Londinum triumphans : Londons triumphs celebrated in honour of the truely deserving Sir Anthony Bateman, Knight, Lord Maior of the honourable City of London, and done at the costs and charges of the Right Worshipful the Company of Skinners, the 29th of October, 1663 / by John Tatham.</title>
                <author>Tatham, John, fl. 1632-1664.</author>
              </titleStmt>
              <extent>[2], 18 p.</extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Printed by W.G. for Henry Brome ...,</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                <date>1663.</date>
              </publicationStmt>
              <notesStmt>
                <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
              </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </bibl>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listEvent>
      <event type="written" when="">
        <desc/>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000773-e10">
        <pb xml:id="ep000773-001-a"/>
        <pb xml:id="ep000773-001-b"/>
        <p>LONDINUM TRIUMPHANS. </p>
        <p>LONDONS TRIUMPHS CELEBRATED: In Honour of the truely Deserving Sir ANTHONY BATEMAN Knight, LORD MAIOR of the Honourable CITY of LONDON. AND DONE At the Costs and Charges of the Right Worshipful the Company of SKINNERS, The 29 th. of October, 1663. </p>
        <p>By <hi>John Tatham</hi>. </p>
        <p>London, Printed by <hi>W. G. </hi>for <hi>Henry Brome </hi>at the Gun in Ivy-Lane. 1663. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="text" xml:id="ep000773-e150">
        <pb xml:id="ep000773-002-a"/>
        <pb n="1" xml:id="ep000773-002-b"/>
        <head>The Ordering and Marshalling of the dayes businesse. </head>
        <p>ABout Eight of the Clock at Skinners-Hall, to attend his Lordship according to Order, meet, </p>
        <list>
          <item>First, the Master, Wardens, and Assistants, in their Gowns faced with Foynes, and with their Hoods. </item>
          <item>Secondly, the Livery in their Gowns faced with Budge, and their Hoods. </item>
          <item>Thirdly, Fifty Foynes Batchelors in Gowns and Sattin Hoods. </item>
          <item>Fourthly, Fifty Budge Batchelors in Gowns and Sattin Hoods. </item>
          <item>Fifthly, Sixty Gentlemen Ushers in Plush Coats, each of them a Chain of Gold about his shoulder, and a white Staff in his hand. </item>
          <item>Sixthly, Fifteen other Gentlemen, for carrying Banners and Colours, eleven of them being in Plush, the other four in Buff. </item>
          <item>Seventhly, the Serjeant Trumpet, and thirty six Trumpets more, whereof 16. are His Majesties Servants, <pb n="2" xml:id="ep000773-003-a"/>four the Duke of York's, and four the Duke of Albemarle's; The Serjeant Trumpet wearing not onely a Scarfe of the Lord Maior's Colours (allowed by his Lordship as his Fee) but also another of the Companies Colours. </item>
          <item>Eighthly, the Drum-Major to His Majesty, wearing a Scarfe of the Companies Colours crosse his shoulders; four more of His Majasties Drums and a Fife attend the service; also seven other Drums and two Fifes more, each of them (except His Majesties Servants) are habited in Buff coloured Doublets, black Hose, and Scarfes about their Wasts. </item>
          <item>Ninethly, the two Marshalls for the City, with like Scarfes, they have fix persons to attend them. </item>
          <item>Tenthly, the Foot-Marshal with the like Scarfe, and his six attendants. </item>
          <item>Eleventhly, the Master of Defence, with the like Scarfe, and ten persons to attend him. </item>
          <item>Twelfthly, seventy Pentioners in red Gowns, red Sleeves, and red Caps, each of them carrying a Javelin in one hand, and a Target in the other, wherein is painted the Coat of Arms of their Benefactors. </item>
          <item>Lastly, the said Gentlemen bearing Enfignes, Serjeant Trumpet, Drum-Major, and each other Trumpet, Drum and Fife, together with the several Marshalls, Master of Defence, and the other Attendants, have each of them the Companies Colours in their hats. </item>
        </list>
        <pb n="3" xml:id="ep000773-003-b"/>
        <p>Hereupon, the Foot Marshal divides the persons so met into seven Divisions, ranked out two by two, beginning with the inferiour part, the Standard-Bearers; and in the head of them are placed two Drums, one Fife, and one Gentleman, bearing the Companies Ensign. </p>
        <p>In the Rear of those Standard-Bearers fall in six Trumpets, two Gentlemen bearing Banners, being the Arms of Deceased Benefactors; after them march the aged Pentioners in Gowns, and in the Center of them fall in two Drums beating the Switzers March. </p>
        <p>In the Rear of them fall in two Drums, one Fife, and two Gentlemen in Plush Coats, bearing two Banners or Ensigns; after them, fall in six Gentlemen Ushers, and in the Rear of them fall in the Budge Batchellors. </p>
        <p>In the Rear of them, fall in six other Trumpets; after them two other Gentlemen bearing two other Banners or Ensigns; after them fal in eight Gentlemen Ushers▪ and after them the Foynes Batchellors. </p>
        <p>In the Rear of them, fall in the Duke of York's, and the Duke of Albemarle's eight Trumpets; after them two Gentlemen bearing two other Banners or Ensignes, then 12 Gentlemen Ushers, and after them the Livery. </p>
        <p>In the Rear of them fall in the Drum-Major, and His Majesties four Drums and Fife; after them two other Gentlemen, the one bearing the Lord Maiors, the other the Cities Banners, and after them twelve Gentlemen Ushers, and after them the Court of Assistants. </p>
        <pb n="4" xml:id="ep000773-004-a"/>
        <p>In the Rear of them fall in the Serjeant Trumpet and sixteen other of His Majesties Trumpets, and a Kettle Drum in His Majesties Livery; after them three Gentlemen bearing three Banners, the one the Kings, the other the Duke of York's, and the third the Banner of St. George marching Triangular; after them fall in twelve Gentlemen Ushers, and in the Rear of them the present Master and Wardens. </p>
        <p>In this Equipage two by two, they march from Skinners-Hall towards the Lord Maior's House in Mincing-lane, the Foot Marshal and his attendants, make a Lane to receive his Lordship and his attendants, together with the old Lord Maior and his attendants, which having done, the Foot Marshal ranks them as formerly, and the whole body march towards Guildhall, and from thence to <hi>three Crane Wharf </hi>in the Vintrey, his Lordship enters his Barge at the Stairs next Westminster, the Company enters theirs at <hi>Merchant Taylors Stairs</hi>, and the rest of the Companies at several other places: but the Gentlemen Ushers Budge and Foynes Batchellors, repair to their place of refreshment. </p>
        <p>The Lord Maior and the several Companies of London being thus imbarqued, they make all speed to Westminster, where by the way several peices of Ordinances are discharged, placed on the Bank-side to that purpose, for congratulating his Lordship. </p>
        <p>The Companies being landed at Westminster, they set themselves as a Guard on both sides, from <hi>Westminster Bridge </hi>to the Hall, in which likewise they make a Lane for the Company of Skinners to passe, <pb n="5" xml:id="ep000773-004-b"/>the Lord Maior, the old Lord Maior, Aldermen, and their attendants, but the Livery and their attendants return to their Barge, the Assistants, the Master, Wardens, and their several attendants, march up the <hi>Exchequer Stairs</hi>, and from the stair head to the <hi>Exchequer Bar</hi>, make a Lane, through which the new and old Lord Maiors with the Recorder passe, the new Lord Maior on the right hand of him; and the old Lord Maior on the left, where the Recorder makes a Speech. </p>
        <p>A Writ being sealed at the <hi>Chancery, Kings Bench</hi>, &amp; <hi>Common Pleas Bar</hi>, and the accustomed Ceremonies performed, his Lordship and the rest in order repair to their several Barges, and hasten to <hi>Baynards Castle, Pauls Wharf</hi>, and other places, in order to their making a Guard or Gallory, from <hi>Pauls Chain Hill</hi>, and <hi>Pauls Church Yard</hi>, to Cheapside, through which the Company of Skinners, the Lord Maior, and Aldermen, with their Attendants pass. </p>
        <p>His Lordship being landed, and all things in a readinesse in reference to it; he is saluted by one Scene being two Leopards richly set out, on whose Backs are seated two Negroes, habited very costly after their manner, two Girles likewise placed on the Stage thereof, one in the Front, the other in the Rear, and accommodated accordingly; the Negroes hold each a Banner of the Cities Arms in one hand, and the Arms of the Company in the other, the Girles hold the like. </p>
        <p>This Scene moves all the Morning with other Pageants up and down Pauls Church-yard, and upon <pb n="6" xml:id="ep000773-005-a"/>his Lordships approach retreat towards Foster-lane end, where a Pageant relating to the Companies Trade receive them; The Leopards (as they are Supporters of the Companies Arms) flank each side thereof. </p>
        <p>This Pageant is made in manner of a Wood or Wildernesse, the Stage thereof being fourteen foot long, and eight foot broad; the Front thereof is arched over with a Wilde Arbour, in which sits a living Figure representing Faunus. His head is Circled with a Crown of Wool inter-mixed with Ermyns, the upper part of his body habited like a Forrester in Green; his nether part like a Woodman in Russet; He wears a long loose Robe over it lined with Fur, and inter-mixed with Ermyns; In one hand he holds a Javelin, in the other a Bugle Horn. His attendants are three Satyres habited accordingly, who are in continual Motion, playing on several rude Instruments, singing and dancing. Upon four Pedestalls sit four Girles, alluding to the Nymphs of the Wood and Forrests, called Dryades, and habited accordingly. On the Stage are placed several Boyes in the shapes of Bears, Monkeys, and several other beasts relating to the placed several Boyes in the shapes o f Bears, Monkeys, and several other beasts relating to the Companies Trade, who likewise are in continual action. </p>
        <p>Faunus is said to be God of the Woods and Forrests, and Father of all the Rural gods. </p>
        <p>[He is reported to be the Ancient'st of all the Kings in Italy, and was the first that brought in any Form of Religion thither. He Consecrated Groves, gave <pb n="7" xml:id="ep000773-005-b"/>Names unto Cities, erected Temples, ordained Sacrifices; from whom the Churches, as some say, were named Fana.] </p>
        <p>Upon his Lordships approach Faunus directs himself in these words; </p>
        <div type="speech" xml:id="ep000773-e1010">
          <head>Faunus's SPEECH. </head>
          <l>E'Re scarce the face of Government was known, </l>
          <l>Or superstitious Ceremonies shown, </l>
          <l>E're Rome received from Romulus a Law, </l>
          <l>(Which did the Sabines to Subjection draw;) </l>
          <l>Or that her Gods into request became, </l>
          <l>And Altars on her Holy <ref target="A63188-e1130-b">* </ref>
            <note corresp="A63188-e1130-a" n="*" place="margin">* Mount Aventine. </note>Mount did flame, </l>
          <l>I lead the way to those mysterious rights. </l>
          <l>By the Pale Tapers of Instinctive lights: </l>
          <l>For nature (then) us Heathens reason lent </l>
          <l>To worship what we held Omnipotent. </l>
          <l>When now there are a sort strive to deface </l>
          <l>With Oaths and Blasphemy the Seat of Grace, </l>
          <l>Worser then Heathens live; past sense of shame, </l>
          <l>From Christian into Atheist change their Name, </l>
          <l>We were devout in what we did not know, </l>
          <l>They know, and yet will not devotion shew; </l>
          <l>In Woods and Groves (at first) we sacrific'd, </l>
          <l>And then we Temples to erect devis'd. </l>
          <pb n="8" xml:id="ep000773-006-a"/>
          <l>As we grew up in Knowledge we the more </l>
          <l>Our unknown Gods did Honour and Adore, </l>
          <l>These sort of Men your Temples do despise, </l>
          <l>And to their lusts do (onely) sacrifice; </l>
          <l>That such who thus your Government displease </l>
          <l>Deserve the name of Satyrs more then <ref target="A63188-e1430-b">* </ref>
            <note corresp="A63188-e1430-a" n="*" place="margin">* pointing to the Satyrs. </note>these. </l>
          <l>Licentious liberty obdurates hearts, </l>
          <l>And man from virtue more then beasts departs; </l>
          <l>For they forsake not theirs, And as we do </l>
          <l>Order our Beasts, let them be order'd too; </l>
          <l>Wild Beasts are Tam'd by men, and wild-men may </l>
          <l>Be brought in time to be as Tame as they. </l>
          <l>'Tis Wisdome in the Magistrate that must </l>
          <l>Crumble all such Prophaneness into dust. </l>
          <l>Let such as in your Church no service lovee </l>
          <l>Confin'd be to a Forrest, Wood, or Grove. </l>
          <l>Let them be Company for Beasts not Men, </l>
          <l>Till they return unto the Truth agen. </l>
          <l>By this their Punishment you will appear Unto the World, more Vertuous then Severe. </l>
          <p>The speech ended, his Lordship and his Retinue move towards the place where Cheapside-Crosse stood, and there he is entertained by another Scene or Pageant, being <pb n="9" xml:id="ep000773-006-b"/>a stately Fabrick made after the Dorick order, on the Top whereof is seated a lively Figure representing Albion or England, taking her Name from the White Cliffs; her hair is of a Flaxen colour dishevelled, her Temples are Circled with an Imperial Diadem, her Neck ornamented with a Collor of SS, her Garment Cloth of Silver, about her shoulders a loose flying scarf of Gold: In one hand she holds a Shield whereon is figured the Heptarchy, (or the seven petty Kings that once ruled here), kneeling and tendring their Crowns to her; in the other hand she holds a rich Banner, whereon the Arms of England and Portugall is impal'd. At her Feet upon a Pedestall is seated a living Figure representing the City of London; her hair of a light Brown, on her head a Coronet of Gold, her Garment white sarsnet fring'd with Gold, over her shoulders she has a loose flying Green sarsnet scarfe fringed with silver: in one hand she holds a Banner of the Cities Arms, in the other one of the Companies. </p>
          <pb n="10" xml:id="ep000773-007-a"/>
          <p>On either side of the Pageant sit two more living Figures, representing two Cities, York and Bristoll; and in the Rear sits another figure representing Worcester. </p>
          <p>York is habited in a Flame coloured Sarsnet Robe, her hair a dark Brown dishevel'd, on her head a Coronet of Gold, in one hand she holds a Banner with the Arms of that City, in the other the Arms of England. </p>
          <p>Bristoll is habited in a Limon-coloured Sarsnet Robe, her hair dishevel'd, on her head a Coronet of Gold; in one hand she holds a Banner with the Arms of that City, in the other the Arms of England. </p>
          <p>Norwich is habited in a Crimson coloured Srasnet-Robe, her hair dishevel'd, on her head she has a Coronet of Gold, in one hand she holds a Banner with the Arms of that City, and in the other the Arms of England. </p>
          <p>All these Banners are made of Silk, about the Pageant is painted the Figure of every City in little. </p>
          <p>His Lordship and the rest drawing neer, Albion directs her self to him in these words; </p>
        </div>
        <div type="speech" xml:id="ep000773-e1930">
          <pb n="11" xml:id="ep000773-007-b"/>
          <head>Albions SPEECH. </head>
          <l>Albion that not long since was left forlorn, </l>
          <l>Her Bosom ransackt, and her Garments torn </l>
          <l>By her unnatural Children, now presumes </l>
          <l>Your presence, and her antient State assumes. </l>
          <l>Bless'd be the happy Change, the Sacred Cause </l>
          <l>Of our <hi>Religion, Liberty</hi>, and Laws. </l>
          <l>So great a Work could not accomplish'd be, </l>
          <l>Without restoring Heaven-born Monarchie; </l>
          <l>How happy are you, could you prize your good, </l>
          <l>And your Conditions rightly understood; </l>
          <l>Now Peace has got the upper hand of War, </l>
          <l>And Plenty hath exiled Famin far </l>
          <l>Remote from hence our fields are clad with Corn </l>
          <l>Whose laden Ears do listen to be shorn. </l>
          <l>The Husbandman hides not his Cattel, now, </l>
          <l>Lest that they shall be taken from the Plough; </l>
          <l>The Shepherd fears not those Sheep stealing men </l>
          <l>(Far worse then Wolves) of late, but laughs agen. </l>
          <l>And to his harmless flock tunes forth the Praise </l>
          <l>of Peace, and our Revived Halcion dayes. </l>
          <l>Thrice happy England in so bless'd a King, </l>
          <l>Vnder whose Government the Clergy sing </l>
          <pb n="12" xml:id="ep000773-008-a"/>
          <l>The Songs of Sion in the sacred Tongue, </l>
          <l>Converting old Men and Informing young. </l>
          <l>Where vile Oppression is supprest by Law, </l>
          <l>And Clemency doth more then rigour Awe. </l>
          <l>Then London, and my other Daughters, know </l>
          <l>How much to God for such a King you owe; </l>
          <l>And let no dirty thoughts Rebellious, prove </l>
          <l>The dark rewarders of his Serene love. </l>
          <p>The Speech ended, his Lordship and his Retinue move towards Milk-street, and there he is saluted by another Scene or Pageant, made in manner of a Chariot, in the Front whereof sits a living Figure, representing a Turk (alluding to his Lordships Quality, a Turkish Merchant, and so to Trade) his Habit is very rich, apted to the Fashion of that Countrey; in the body of the Pageant are three Turks more habited accordingly, and three Slaves employed in ordering and making up Commodities. </p>
          <pb n="13" xml:id="ep000773-008-b"/>
          <p>Upon his Lordships adproach, the Turk salutes him in these words; </p>
        </div>
        <div type="speech" xml:id="ep000773-e2580">
          <head>Turks SPEECH. </head>
          <l>HAil to the honour that attends your name, </l>
          <l>We that ne'r stoop to fear, yet must to fame; </l>
          <l>We that dare Grapple with the Universe, </l>
          <l>And mak't our Glory (only) to Converse </l>
          <l>With horrid Slaughter, do appeal to you, </l>
          <l>And for your Amity and Comerce sue: </l>
          <l>Nor is it such a monstrous thing to be </l>
          <l>In league with us▪ rather securitie: </l>
          <l>The trembling Nations where our Sultan comes </l>
          <l>Surrender up their rights, and quit their homes; </l>
          <l>Our numerous host staggers the Christians faith, </l>
          <l>And our successe like admiration hath: </l>
          <l>Th' Inveigling French we neither love, nor fear, </l>
          <l>Your deeds abroad draw our affections here. </l>
          <l>England's the seat of honour, and the flower </l>
          <l>Of Chivalry, Valours Imperiall Bower; </l>
          <l>Her Prince inur'd to Arms, and rugged war, </l>
          <l>Her Souldiers (like to Alexanders,) are </l>
          <l>So expert in their Discipline, not one </l>
          <l>But may a Title of Commander own. </l>
          <pb n="14" xml:id="ep000773-009-a"/>
          <l>Her Magistrates are <hi>sober, grave</hi>, and wise, </l>
          <l>Not <hi>Kickshaw-pated-fellows, Butterflies</hi>, </l>
          <l>But such as Rome did in her Pride select </l>
          <l>For Government, to Traffique, and Protect, </l>
          <l>And as to her, remotest parts did bow, </l>
          <l>Let us not shame to doe the like to you. </l>
          <p>The Speech ended, his Lordship and the rest move on towards Soper-lane end, the four Pageants by whom his Lordship past, falling into the Rear. At Soper-lane end, another Pageant waits his Lordship, being a stately Building, in the Front whereof sits Minerva; her Hair dishevell'd, on her head she wears a silver Helmet with a Plume of red and white Feathers, her Garment of changeable coloured Sarsnet, alluding to her Properties, as she is <hi>Pallas, Bellona</hi>, and Minerva; in one hand she holds a Lance, in the other a Shield, whereon is figured several sorts of Books and Instruments of Musick, as she is Goddesse of Arts and Arms; upon the four Pedestals of the Pageant, sit four Nymphs in several coloured habits, richly set forth, circled with Wreaths of <pb n="15" xml:id="ep000773-009-b"/>Roses, and holding a sheild and a Banner in each hand, on one whereof is figured the head of Medusa, on the other the Lord Mayors Arms. </p>
          <p>On the Top of the Pageant is placed an other lively Figure representing Mercury; his habit, and basis are Cloth of silver: There are three Children more which represent the three Graces habited accordingly. </p>
          <p>His Lordship drawing neer Minerva Addresseth her self to him in these words. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="speech" xml:id="ep000773-e3420">
          <head>Minerva's SPEECH. </head>
          <l>IN all the primitive times Learning did shine </l>
          <l>Like to the Sun both speculative, and divine; </l>
          <l>The more she spread her self, the more she grew, </l>
          <l>In veneration and esteem; This drew </l>
          <l>The youth of famous Athens to admire </l>
          <l>Not only her rich beauty, but acquire </l>
          <l>Her as a Bride; for which their Genii strove, </l>
          <l>And in their several Orbs exprest their love. </l>
          <l>But as the Sun cannot be said to give </l>
          <l>Life to one Plant (though all by him do live) </l>
          <pb n="16" xml:id="ep000773-010-a"/>
          <l>So Learning from her various Rayes imparts </l>
          <l>The several Species of both Arms and Arts. </l>
          <l>While they did flourish she was in request, </l>
          <l>And held a Iewel for a Prince's breast; </l>
          <l>When now her Glory is Ecclips'd, and she </l>
          <l>Wanders in Rags, and despis'd Povertie. </l>
          <l>Let parts be what they will, Fools onely scan </l>
          <l>The Out-side, not the Inside of a Man. </l>
          <l>If she addresse her self to Court (the place </l>
          <l>Where she should find acceptance, and a Grace) </l>
          <l>The wanton leere of a betraying Eye </l>
          <l>Bespeaks her (straight) a scornful Injury. </l>
          <l>The Country knows her not; they with all right, </l>
          <l>But hardly to her Help will add a Mite; </l>
          <l>To what place must her Miseries repair, </l>
          <l>But unto Athens? of the which you are </l>
          <l>By Divine hand appointed Magistrate </l>
          <l>Oh! let her not be starved at your Gate, </l>
          <l>Encourage her, and for your Cities Fame. </l>
          <l>Both Arts and Arms shall gloryfie your Name. </l>
          <l>Perpetuate your Memory, and raise </l>
          <l>From this dayes Basis Pyramids of Praise. </l>
          <p>The Speech ended, his Lordship and his Attendants retire to Guild-Hall to Dinner, <pb n="17" xml:id="ep000773-010-b"/>and the Companie to the place of their Refreshment; and after Dinner are again by the Foot Marshal set in Order as in the Morning, only the Pentioners carry in stead of Javelins and Targets, Torches to attend my Lord, the Aldarmen, and Companies from St. Pauls, to which place his Lordship directs his passage, and the Pageants to wait his Coming from thence, hasten towards his Lordships house in Mincing-lane, and the Pageants are placed in <hi>Grace Church-street</hi>; and at Mincing-lane end neer Cloth-workers-Hall; his Lordship (upon his Return from Pauls) is Accosted by the person representing the Turk in these words; </p>
        </div>
        <div type="speech" xml:id="ep000773-e3940">
          <head>SPEECH. </head>
          <opener>
            <salute>MY LORD, </salute>
          </opener>
          <l>THe Company on whom I waite, </l>
          <l>Command me to salute you at your Gate </l>
          <l>With their fraternal-hearty-wishes; May </l>
          <l>Your Joyes exceed the Glory of this Day. </l>
          <l>May never Night approach them, never Ill </l>
          <l>Divine them, but be fair and rising still. </l>
          <pb n="18" xml:id="ep000773-011-a"/>
          <l>May you in Traffique no Disaster know, </l>
          <l>Your Riches never Ebb, but ever Flow. </l>
          <l>Piety be your practice, and the poor. </l>
          <l>Never go Empty-handed from your dore. </l>
          <l>May you grow up in Honours seat, and prove </l>
          <l>A Subject for your King, and Cities love. </l>
          <l>May you live Centuries of years, and see </l>
          <l>Your-self still young in your posteritie: </l>
          <l>And so your Company bids (in your own right) </l>
          <l>Good Morrow to your Glories, not Good night. </l>
          <p>Which ended, and his Lordship entred his house, all depart in order (as the Conveniency of Night will admit) And the several persons appointed to attend the service of the day take especiall care to lodge the silk-works and Triumphs in some secure place til they can remove them to Skinners-Hall, in regard they are of some weight, and the burthen of the day was heavy to the Undertakers. </p>
        </div>
        <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="license" xml:id="ep000773-e4340">
        <p>Licensed October 27, 1663. </p>
        <p>ROGER L'ESTRANGE. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="supplied_by_editor">
        <head>Notes, typically marginal, from the original text</head>
        <div corresp="A63188-e150" xml:id="ep000773-e150-n">
          <head>Notes for div A63188-e150</head>
        </div>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
