<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ep000776" xml:lang="eng">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     London's triumph, or, The goldsmiths jubilee containing a description of the several pageants and speeches, made proper for the occasion, together with a song, for the entertainment of His Majesty, who, with His Royal Consort, the Queen Dowager, Their Royal Highnesses the Prince and Princess of Denmark, and the whole Court, honour His Lordship this year with their presence / by M. Taubman.
    </title>
    <author>
     <!--Taubman, Matthew-->
     <persName>
      <forename>
       Matthew
      </forename>
      <surname>
       Taubman
      </surname>
     </persName>
    </author>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher xml:id="dracor">
     DraCor
    </publisher>
    <idno type="URL">
     https://dracor.org/
    </idno>
    <availability>
     <licence>
      <ab>
       CC0 1.0
      </ab>
      <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
       Licence
      </ref>
     </licence>
    </availability>
    <idno type="wikidata" xml:base="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/"/>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl type="digitalSource">
     <name>
      EarlyPrint Project
     </name>
     <idno type="URL">
      https://texts.earlyprint.org/works/A63358.xml
     </idno>
     <availability>
      <p>
       This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is available for reuse, according to the terms of
       <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
        Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
       </ref>
       . The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
      </p>
     </availability>
     <bibl type="originalSource">
      <biblFull>
       <titleStmt>
        <title>
         London's triumph, or, The goldsmiths jubilee containing a description of the several pageants and speeches, made proper for the occasion, together with a song, for the entertainment of His Majesty, who, with His Royal Consort, the Queen Dowager, Their Royal Highnesses the Prince and Princess of Denmark, and the whole Court, honour His Lordship this year with their presence / by M. Taubman.
        </title>
        <author>
         Taubman, Matthew, d. 1690?
        </author>
       </titleStmt>
       <extent>
        [4], 12 p.
       </extent>
       <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>
         Printed by J. Leake ...,
        </publisher>
        <pubPlace>
         London :
        </pubPlace>
        <date>
         1687.
        </date>
       </publicationStmt>
       <notesStmt>
        <note>
         Without the music.
        </note>
        <note>
         "Printed and published by authority."
        </note>
        <note>
         "Performed on Saturday, October XXIX, 1687, for the confirmation and entertainment of the Right Honourable Sir John Shorter, Kt., Lord Mayor of the city of London."
        </note>
        <note>
         "All set forth at the proper costs and charges of the Worshipful Company of Goldsmiths."
        </note>
        <note>
         Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.
        </note>
       </notesStmt>
      </biblFull>
     </bibl>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
   <profileDesc>
    <particDesc>
     <listPerson>
      <person xml:id="ep000776-devil">
       <persName>
        Devil
       </persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ep000776-stdunstan">
       <persName>
        St. Dunstan
       </persName>
      </person>
     </listPerson>
    </particDesc>
   </profileDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <standOff>
  <listEvent>
   <event type="written" when="">
    <desc/>
   </event>
  </listEvent>
 </standOff>
 <text>
  <front>
   <div type="title_page" xml:id="ep000776-e10">
    <pb rend="simple:additions" xml:id="ep000776-001-a"/>
    <p>
     <hi>
      London's Triumph
     </hi>
     , OR THE Goldsmiths Jubilee: PERFORMED, On
     <hi>
      SATVRDAY, October
     </hi>
     XXIX. 1687.
    </p>
    <p>
     For the Confirmation and Entertainment OF THE RIGHT HONOURABLE Sir John Shorter, Kt. Lord Mayor of the City of LONDON.
    </p>
    <p>
     CONTAINING A Description of the several PAGEANTS and Speeches, made, proper for the Occasion. Together with a SONG, For the Entertainment of His Majesty, who, with His Royal Consort; the Queen Dowager; their Royal Highnesses, the Prince and Princess of Denmark, and the whole Court, honour his Lordship, this Year, with their Presence.
    </p>
    <p>
     All set forth at the proper Costs and Charges of the Worshipful COMPANY of GOLDSMITHS.
    </p>
    <p>
     By
     <hi>
      M. TAVBMAN
     </hi>
     .
    </p>
    <q>
     <l>
      Aurea prima sata est aetas, quae&#8212;
     </l>
     <l>
      &#8212; fidem rectumque colebat.
     </l>
     <bibl>
      Ovid.
     </bibl>
    </q>
    <p>
     <hi>
      Printed and Published by Authority
     </hi>
     .
    </p>
    <p>
     LONDON, Printed by
     <hi>
      J. Leake
     </hi>
     , in Jewin-street, 1687.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000776-e280">
    <pb xml:id="ep000776-002-a"/>
    <pb xml:id="ep000776-002-b"/>
    <head>
     TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE Sir John Shorter, Kt. Lord Mayor of the CITY of LONDON.
    </head>
    <opener>
     <salute>
      My Lord,
     </salute>
    </opener>
    <p>
     YOVR Advancement this Year to the Praetorial Chair of this Renowned City, may render you the Object of our Wonder, but not our Envy; especially when it is considered, it was Your right some Years before; With Justice now reassuming Your seat, it is a motive rather of Joy than Regret, and an Argument to gratulate your Establishment with greater Alacrity. The Ship that in a Storm over-shoots the Port, may toss a while upon the driving Bellows, but the next favourable Gale she Tacks about, and makes the expected Haven with greater Expressions of Joy and Welcome. We will not descant on the singular Favours of the Monarch, which is a boundless Ocean; nor on those extraordinary Indowments that have this Year deservedly advanced You to the Chair. It is sufficient You have had the Choice and Approbation of the most Judicious and most Discerning Prince in the World; to whose Royal Favours Your Essential Merits have most justly preferr'd You. It is He who with His breath can give You a successful passage into that Port from which You were retarded by contrary Winds, who has this Year made You His Vicegerent in His Imperial City, to bear that Sword of Justice, of which He is himself the immediate Lord and Soveraign: And it is hoped, by Your wise Conduct and Management of this great Trust, the Effects will be such, that Your Lordship will render Him no less than reason to approve the Works of His own Hands. But these few Sheets are a Description, not a Directory; a Scheme of Pageantry, not a Scale of Government; nor will I in a short Dedication exceed the narrow bounds of,
    </p>
    <closer>
     <salute>
      MY LORD,
     </salute>
     <signed>
      <hi>
       Your Lordship's Most devoted humble Servant,
      </hi>
      Matt. Taubman.
     </signed>
    </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="dedication" xml:id="ep000776-e390">
    <pb xml:id="ep000776-003-a"/>
    <head>
     TO THE Worshipful Company OF GOLDSMITHS.
    </head>
    <opener>
     <salute>
      Gentlemen,
     </salute>
    </opener>
    <p>
     THE Triumphs of London, this Year, may well be stiled the
     <hi>
      Goldsmiths Jubilee
     </hi>
     ; the King, by His Favours, has made it so; this being the second Year of their Majoralty, in which this Worshipful Company has been honoured with the Royal Presence: The former in 74 by the Approach of His late Majesty, of Renowned Memory, and this of the present Monarch, which is the first Honour, of this kind, done to the Imperial City since his Majesty's Accession to the Crown. Your costly Preparations, prudent Contrivance, and bounteous Contributions towards so glorious an Entertainment, is not only a demonstration of your Respects to his Lordship, but also your high Sense and Acknowledgment of so Princely a Favour. That his Lordship, by his prudent Management, may answer your Expectations, and the end for which His Majesty committed this great Trust to his Hands, to the Satisfaction of Prince and People, shall be the unfeigned Wishes of,
    </p>
    <closer>
     <signed>
      Your most obsequious Humble Servant,
      <hi>
       M. T.
      </hi>
     </signed>
    </closer>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <div type="text" xml:id="ep000776-e510">
    <pb n="1" xml:id="ep000776-003-b"/>
    <head>
     <hi>
      London's Triumph
     </hi>
     , OR THE Goldsmiths Jubilee.
    </head>
    <p>
     AMIDST all the memorable Triumphs of all Ages, Ancient and Modern, the Ovations of the Caesars, or triumphal Arches of the neighbouring Monarch, there's none exceeds the Lustre of London this Day; which, for the Antiquity of its Institution, the Grandeur of the Preparations, the Splendor of the Pageantry, and the Magnifice of the Entertainments, may properly be styl'd Triumphant above all the Cities in the Universe. It is a liberal and unanimous Assembly of all the Chiefs of the Imperial City of the most flourishing Kingdom in the Universe. This Year adorn'd with the Presence of their most Sacred Majesties, the King, Queen, Queen Dowager, Prince and Princess of Denmark, with all the chief Nobility and principal Officers of the Court; the Arch-Bishop of Canterbury, and chief Prelates of the Church: The Lord Chancellour, Lord Chief Justice, and all the learned Judges in the Laws; with all foreign Ministers, Embassadours, Envoys, Residents, who having observed the Tables of the most Puissant Princes, and seen the most hospitable Preparations of Foreign Nations, rest here amaz'd at the
     <hi>
      Ne plus altra
     </hi>
     of all Entertainments.
    </p>
    <p>
     Before we describe the Magnificence of the Pageantry, we must not omit the stateliness of the Morning Procession, and Progress by Water to Westminster, where his Lordship once a Year (as the Duke of Venice to the Sea) weds himself to the Thames, with a Ring of surrounding Barges, that being also a part of his Dominion, of which, this Day he takes Possession, and thus he exercises his double Sovereignty both by Land and Water: Of which in their Order.
    </p>
    <div type="list" xml:id="ep000776-e640">
     <head>
      The Order of the Morning Procession.
     </head>
     <p>
      THE most eminent and most accomplished Citizens, selected for the Management of this Days Triumph, assemble together, at Seven of the Clock in the Morning at
      <hi>
       Goldsmiths Hall.
      </hi>
     </p>
     <list>
      <item>
       I. The Master, Wardens, and Assistants, in their Gowns fac'd with Foyns.
      </item>
      <item>
       II. The Livery, in Gowns faced with Budge, and their Hoods.
      </item>
      <item>
       <pb n="2" xml:id="ep000776-004-a"/>
       III. Several Foyns Batchellors in their Gowns and scarlet Hoods.
      </item>
      <item>
       IV. Thirty Budge Batchellors in Gowns and scarlet Hoods.
      </item>
      <item>
       V. Sixty Gentlemen Ushers in Plush, and some in Velvet Coats, each of them a Chain of Gold about his Shoulders, and a white Staff in his Hand.
      </item>
      <item>
       VI. Thirty other Gentlemen for carrying Banners and Colours, some of them being in plush Coats, the other in Buff.
      </item>
      <item>
       VII. The Serjeant Trumpet, and Thirty six Trumpets more, whereof Sixteen are his Majesties: The Serjeant Trumpet wearing Two Scarfs, one of the Lord Mayors Colours, the other of the Companies.
      </item>
      <item>
       VIII. The Drum-Major to his Majesty, wearing a Scarf of the Companies Colours cross his Shoulders, with Four more of his Majesties Drums and Fifes.
      </item>
      <item>
       IX. Seven other Drums, and Two Fifes more, each of them (except his Majesties Servants) habited in Buff-coloured Dublets, black Breeches, and Scarfs about their Wasts.
      </item>
      <item>
       X. The Two City Marshals riding each on Horsback, and Six Persons attending with Scarfs and Colours of the Companies.
      </item>
      <item>
       XI. The Foot Marshal and Six Attendants with like Scarfs and Colours.
      </item>
      <item>
       XII. The Master of Defence, with the same Scarf and Colours, having Persons of his own Science to attend him.
      </item>
      <item>
       XIII. Several poor Men, Pensioners, accommodated with Gowns and Caps, each of them imployed in bearing of Standards and Banners.
      </item>
      <item>
       XIV. Divers other Pensioners in green Gowns, red Sleeves and Caps, each of them carrying a Javelin in one Hand, and a Target in the other, whereon is painted the Coat Armour of the First Founders and Benefactors of the Company.
      </item>
     </list>
    </div>
    <div type="part" xml:id="ep000776-e830">
     <head>
      Placed in this Order:
     </head>
     <p>
      THE Foot Marshal divides them into several Companies, and ranks them out Two by Two, beginning with the Pensioners in Gowns; and in the Front of them placeth the Companies Ensigns, Four Drums, and one Fife, which is the lowest Division.
     </p>
     <p>
      In the Rear of them fall Four Drums and one Fife.
     </p>
     <p>
      After them the several Pensioners in Coats, bearing several Banners and Standards. After them Four Trumpets. After the Unicorns and Justice, the Supporters and Crest of the Ensigns of the Company, Six Gentlemen Ushers. After them the Budge Batchellors, which conclude the next Division.
     </p>
     <p>
      In the Rear of those fall six Trumpets: After them Two Gentlemen bearing Two Banners, the one of the Cities, the other of the Companies Arms. After them follow Eight Gentlemen Ushers, and then the Foyn Batchellors, which make up the Third Division.
     </p>
     <p>
      After them Two Gentlemen Ushers bearing Two Banners. After them Ten Gentlemen Ushers, habited as before; and after them the Livery.
     </p>
     <pb n="3" xml:id="ep000776-004-b"/>
     <p>
      In the Rear of these fall other of the City Trumpets, and after them Two Gentlemen bearing the Banners of the City and my Lord Mayor; and then the Gentlemen and the Court of Assistants, which conclude that Division.
     </p>
     <p>
      In the Rear of them fall in Four Drums, and six Trumpets: After them Three Gentlemen, bearing the King's, Queen's, and City's Banners; and after them Foor Gentlemen Ushers, with Four Pages attending; and after them the Masters and Wardens, which concludes all, and is the last Division.
     </p>
     <p>
      In this Order they march from
      <hi>
       Goldsmiths Hall
      </hi>
      to his Lordships House, beginning with the Pensioners, until the Marshal comes and makes a Halt at the Gate, till such time as the Lord Mayor and Aldermen are mounted.
     </p>
     <p>
      Which being done, the whole Body march towards Guild-Hall, and at Guild-Hall Gate the New Lord Mayor joineth with the Old Lord Mayor and his Attendants; so all of them march through Cheapside to
      <hi>
       Three-Crane Warf
      </hi>
      , and then the Lord Mayor, Aldermen, and their Attendants, at the West End of the said Wharf take their Barge; the Court of Assistants, the Livery, and the Gentlemen Ushers of those Three Divisions at the East End of the said Wharf, whilst the rest of the Retinue, some Gentlemen Ushers, the Budge Batchellors and Foyn Batchellors remain behind to attend their Return.
     </p>
     <p>
      His Lordship, the Aldermen, and Company of Goldsmiths, in their Barges, with the Barges of the respective Companies attending, make towards Westminster; several Pleasure-Boats, adorn'd with Flags and Streamers, saluting his Lordship all the way with Drakes and great Guns. His Lordship, the Aldermen and Company of Goldsmiths, with some other Companies, landing at Westminster, have a Lane made from Kings-Bridge to Westminster-Hall; where having taken the accustomed Oaths, before the Lords and Barons of the Exchequer, they return to their Barges (a Lane being made as before) to the Water-side; the Barges all the way echoing with most Harmonious Wind-Musick, viz. Flutes, Ho-boys, Trumphets, &amp;c. and adorned with various Streamers, Flags, and Banners of the respective Companies; which Solemnity by Water is not the least Addition to the Lustre of this Day.
     </p>
     <p>
      His Lordship, with the Companies attending him, land at Black-Friars-Stairs, where they are saluted by the Famous Artillery-Company, led by Sir
      <hi>
       William Pritchard
      </hi>
      , and brought up by Colonel Friend; the Granadeers led by Colonel Kelk, and brought up by Lieutenant Bell; all adorned in their Martial Ornaments, in Buff and shining Head-Pieces, many whereof are Massy Silver.
     </p>
     <p>
      From Black-friars they march before my Lord Mayor and Aldermen from Cheapside to Guild-Hall. The Pensioners and Banners being set in order, the Foot Marshal in the Rere of the
      <hi>
       Artillery Company
      </hi>
      , leads the way through Ludgate-Hill, into St. Paul's Church-Yard, and so into Cheapside; where, over against the Half-Moon, his Lordship is entertained with the first Scene, or Pageant.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="1" type="pageant" xml:id="ep000776-e1290">
     <pb n="4" xml:id="ep000776-005-a"/>
     <head>
      The First PAGEANT,
     </head>
     <p>
      IS a spacious Triumphant Chariot of Gold curiously contriv'd with all the Elegancy of Art and Invention, gloriously set round with precious Stones and various colour'd Jewels of inestimable Value, adorn'd with several pleasant and delightful Figures, as well Artificial as Natural, lively Representing and properly appertaining to the Solemnity of the Day. About the middle of this glorious Structure, on an Ascent of State up to a Throne, sits ASTRAEA the Goddess of Justice, a person of Majestick Aspect, attired in a long Robe of Silver, a Crimson Mantle fringed with Silver, a Veil of Silver fringed with Gold; and on her head a Coronet of Silver set with Stars. In her right hand she beareth a Touchstone, the distinguisher of Sterling from Counterfeit, Truth from Falshood; and in her left hand a Golden Beam or Balance, with Silver Scales, to weigh every thing Impartially according to the Standard of Truth and Equity. She is placed between Two Leopards heads, as the Stamp and Standard of the Company, invested with a wreath of Stars, as an Emblem of the Celestial Sphere from whence she Descended.
     </p>
     <p>
      On each Arm of this Celestial Goddess are placed two other Cardinal Vertues, PRVDENCE and TEMPERANCE, as the necessary supporters of Justice; and on a Descent, remote from the former, two other attending Vertues, COVRAGE and CONCORD.
     </p>
     <p>
      PRVDENCE, a Grave Matron in a golden Robe fringed with Silver, and silver Mantle fringed with Gold, a Chaplet of Flowers, a Shield Vert charged with a Dove Argent, bearing a Banner of the City's.
     </p>
     <p>
      TEMPERANCE, in a white Robe of Silver, a green Mantle fringed with Gold, a Chaplet of white Lilies and Roses. In one hand bearing a Shield with a golden Cup; in the other a Banner of the Company's.
     </p>
     <p>
      COVRAGE, a Person of an Heroick Aspect, in Armour, with a black Peruque, tied in a silken Bag behind. A black Velvet Cap with a plume of red and blew Feathers, and a red and blew colour'd Scarf about his waste. In his right hand holding a Sword with a Coronet of Gold elevated on the point, and in his left hand a Standard of the King's with this Inscription,
      <foreign xml:lang="lat">
       Audaces fortuna juvat
      </foreign>
      .
     </p>
     <p>
      CONCORD, a fair Virgin in a Crimson coloured Robe, a Sky colour'd Scarf fringed with Silver, fair bright Hair, and about her Head a Garland of red and white Roses, representing the Concord and Union of King and People, the Court and City, in the Honour this Day conferred upon them by his Majesty's Presence. In her left hand she bears a shield of polished Gold, charged with a Grove of Myrtles, for such is the nature and harmonious concord of those Trees, that although they be planted a good space one from another, they will meet and one Embrace the other. In her right hand she bears a Banner of the Company's.
     </p>
     <pb n="5" xml:id="ep000776-005-b"/>
     <p>
      This stately Chariot is drawn by Two golden Unicorns, excellently carv'd and painted, with equal proportion, to the Life; with Trappings of Gold and Silver; their Bridles richly beset with precious Stones, Jasper, Topaz, and Sapphire. On the Forehead a large Amathyst, and on their Crests the Leopards Heads in Massy Silver richly imboss'd, as the Stamp and Badge of the Worshipful the Company of Goldsmiths.
     </p>
     <p>
      On the backs of these two Unicorns are mounted two beautiful young Negroes, brought over from Barbary and Guinnea, their places of Traffick, attired according to the richest Dress of those places; with Coronets on their Heads beset with plumes of divers colour'd Feathers. In their left hands they bear Two displayed Banners, one of the King's, the other of the City's, intimating their submission to the powerful Monarch of
      <hi>
       Great Britain
      </hi>
      , as absolute Sovereign of Sea and Land, and their ambition to preserve an amicable correspondence and commerce with this renowned City. ASTRAEA, or the Goddess of Justice drawn in this Triumphant Chariot represents the Crest; the Unicorns as an Enblem of Strength and Unity, the supporters of this ancient and worshipful Company. Beneath the supporters are added seven other Figures properly attired.
     </p>
     <p>
      Lastly, To the supporters, the Unicorns which draw this Chariot, is added a Postillion, the Hieroglyphick of CONDVCT, in a Vest of Cloth of Silver, and Trunks of Crimson Velvet, a Crimson Cap with red and blue Feathers, and pearl-colour'd Buskins lined with Crimson, bearing in the one hand a golden Truncheon, and in the other a Banner of the Lord Mayors. His Lordship taking a short survey of this surprizing Object, is thus saluted by Astraea.
     </p>
     <div type="speech" xml:id="ep000776-e1610">
      <head>
       The First SPEECH by ASTRAEA.
      </head>
      <l>
       DOwn from the Regions of the spangled Skies,
      </l>
      <l>
       Where I sate Crown'd amongst the Deities,
      </l>
      <l>
       ASTRAEA in a golden Throne descends,
      </l>
      <l>
       To grace those Walls, which Warlike JAMES defends.
      </l>
      <l>
       Once in the golden Age of former days,
      </l>
      <l>
       I amongst Mortals had assign'd a place:
      </l>
      <l>
       But Justice fled, Astraea with her flies,
      </l>
      <l>
       And makes her new Apartment in the Skies.
      </l>
      <l>
       Those happy days again reviv'd in you,
      </l>
      <l>
       I view the World from whence I then withdrew:
      </l>
      <l>
       With Temperance and Prudence on each side,
      </l>
      <l>
       To be this Year Your Conduct and Your Guide.
      </l>
      <l>
       The Leopards heads that guard our Throne, imply
      </l>
      <l>
       The Stamp and Standard of the Company;
      </l>
      <l>
       That no Alloy corrupt Your brighter Mass,
      </l>
      <l>
       And Justice may again for Sterling pass.
      </l>
      <l>
       This equal Balance guides you as a Scene,
      </l>
      <l>
       'Twixt both Extreams to hold the Golden Mean.
      </l>
     </div>
    </div>
    <div n="2" type="pageant" xml:id="ep000776-e1890">
     <pb n="6" xml:id="ep000776-006-a"/>
     <head>
      The Second PAGEANT.
     </head>
     <p>
      WHich is the Hieroglyphick of the Company, is a large and spacious Laboratory or Work-house, containing several conveniencies and distinct apartments, for the several Operators and Artificers, with Forges, Anvils, Hammers, and all Instruments proper for the Mystery of the Goldsmiths. In the middle of the Frontispiece, on a rich golden Chair of State, sits St. DVNSTAN, the ancient Patron, and Tutelar Guardian of the Company, canonically attired in his pontifical Ornaments, properly expressing his Prelatical Dignity and Canonization, in a Robe of finest white Lawn, over which he wears a Cope, or vest of bright shining Cloth of Gold, which reacheth down to the ground; on his Reverend hoary Head a golden Mitre, beset with all sorts of precious Stones, from the Topaz to the Sapphire. In his left hand he holds a golden Crosier as an Emblem of his prelatical Function, and in his right hand a pair of Goldsmiths Tongues, as an Emblem of his Patronage.
     </p>
     <p>
      Behind him are placed ORPHEVS and AMPHION, playing upon several melodious Instruments, as well for his Lordship's Diversion as to preserve a Harmony and Decorum amongst the Artificers; the one, that with his excellent Musick drew after him wild Beasts, Woods and Mountains; the other, who by his Eloquence, taught the rude Savages to lead a civil Life, and by the harmonious Charms of his Musick built the City Thebes.
     </p>
     <p>
      ORPHEVS, an old grave Patron with a white Beard and long gray Hair; in a Crimson colour'd Robe, and blue Buskins; between his Arms a Harp.
     </p>
     <p>
      AMPHION, a young Man of a ruddy Complexion, in a Robe of Crimson Velvet, on his Head a Coronet of red and white Flowers, playing upon an Instrument.
     </p>
     <p>
      In a degree more forward are placed the CHAM of Tartary and the Grand SVLTAN, in Robes and Turbants, peculiar for the dress of the Ottoman Court; who being Conquered by the Christian Harmony seem to sue for a Reconcilement.
     </p>
     <p>
      Beneath these steps of Ascention to the Canonical Chair, in opposition to the Patron, is planted a Goldsmiths Forge and Furnace, with Fire, Crucibles and Gold in it, a Work-man blowing with the Bellows. On either Hand there is elegantly set up a large Press of Gold and Silver Plate, representing a shop of formal Trade. And further, towards the front, are several Artificers and Jewellers at Work, with Anvils and Hammers, with Stones, Sparks, and other Instruments, fit for Enamelling: The several Artificers beating out Plate, fit for the Fashioning and Formation of several Vessels of Gold and Silver. In these Shops are also divers Wedges or Ingots of Gold and Silver. A step below St. Dunstan, sitteth an Essay-Master, with his Class, Frame and Balance for trying of Gold and Silver according to the Standard. In another apartment is also Disgrossing, Flatting and Drawing of Gold and Silver Wyre: In another are included your
      <pb n="7" xml:id="ep000776-006-b"/>
      Finers, Melting, Smelting, Fining, Refining and Separating Gold and Silver, both by Fire and Water.
     </p>
     <p>
      In a Forge before this Office are divers Miners in Canvas Breeches, red Wastcoats and red Caps, bearing Spades, Pick-axes, Twibbles and Crows, fit to sink Shafts, and make Addits. The Cham of Tartary and Grand Sultan having made their Obeisance, are rejected. The Devil also appearing at the latter end of the Speech, is catch'd by the Nose by St. Dunstan. When the Speech is over the great Anvil is set forth, with a Silversmith holding on it a Plate of Massy Silver, and Three other Work-men at work, singing, and keeping time upon the Anvil.
     </p>
     <p>
      His Lordship having viewed the curiosity of its Design, is addressed by St. Dunstan, in these Words:
     </p>
     <floatingText>
      <body>
       <div type="drama" xml:id="ep000776-e2250">
        <head>
         The second Speech by St. Dunstan.
        </head>
        <l>
         WAked with this Musick from my silent Vrn,
        </l>
        <l>
         Your Patron Dunstan comes t'attend your Turn.
        </l>
        <l>
         Amphion and old Orpheus playing by,
        </l>
        <l>
         To keep our Forge in tuneful Harmony.
        </l>
        <l>
         These pontificial Ornaments I wear,
        </l>
        <l>
         Are types of Rule and Order all the Year.
        </l>
        <l>
         In these white Robes none can a fault descry,
        </l>
        <l>
         Since all have liberty as well as I:
        </l>
        <l>
         Nor need you fear the Shipwrack of your Cause,
        </l>
        <l>
         Your loss of Charter or the Penal Laws,
        </l>
        <l>
         Indulgence granted by your bounteous Prince,
        </l>
        <l>
         Makes for that loss too great a Recompence.
        </l>
        <l>
         This Charm the
         <hi>
          Lernaean Hydra
         </hi>
         will reclaim;
        </l>
        <l>
         Your Patron shall the tameless Rabble tame.
        </l>
        <l>
         Of the proud Cham I scorn to be afear'd;
        </l>
        <l>
         I'll take the angry Sultan by the Beard.
        </l>
        <l>
         Nay, should the Devil intrude amongst your Foes,
         <stage xml:id="ep000776-e2510">
          Enter Devil.
         </stage>
        </l>
        <sp who="ep000776-devil" xml:id="ep000776-e2530">
         <speaker>
          Devil.
         </speaker>
         <p>
          <hi>
           What then
          </hi>
          ?
         </p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="ep000776-stdunstan" xml:id="ep000776-e2570">
         <speaker>
          St. Dunstan.
         </speaker>
         <p>
          &#8212;
          <hi>
           Snap, thus, I have him by the Nose.
          </hi>
         </p>
        </sp>
       </div>
      </body>
     </floatingText>
     <p>
      The Speech being ended, the Pageant moves easily, being led by a Guard of Twenty four in the front, Twelve of which are Lictors in Roman Habits, bearing Axes in their Hands, with Head-pieces, and Leopards Heads on each Shoulder, as also on their Buskins; and Twelve Yeomen, bearing Blunderbusses, apparell'd after the same manner, with Head-pieces and Buskins; besides Green-men, Swabs, Satyrs, and Attendants innumerable.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="3" type="pageant" xml:id="ep000776-e2650">
     <pb n="8" xml:id="ep000776-007-a"/>
     <head>
      The Third PAGEANT.
     </head>
     <p>
      THE Company, as a farther testimony of their Bounty, present his Lordship with a
      <hi>
       Ship; The Vnity of
      </hi>
      London; a Merchant-Adventurer to Norway and Denmark. This Ship is Laden with Deals, Masts, Beams, Trees, and all sort of Timber, for building Ships, Houses, and all other sort of Architecture; as representing his Lordships way of Traffick and Adventure into those Countries. It is in length from Poop to Stern One hundred forty five Foot by scale, Forty five Foot high, from the Water to the top of the Stern in proportion of building. She beareth Twenty two Guns, with Ancients and Pendents, Streamers, Flags, Standards, Tackling, Braces, Bowlings, Cables, Anchors, Cordage, and all sorts of Rigging appertaining to a Merchantman of that Burden. On board this Ship are a Captain and his Mate, a Gunner and his Mate, a Boatswain and Mariners, every man at work in his proper station, some at the main Tack, others the main Braces, others the Bowlings; some climbing up the Ladders to the main Top, and others sitting cross the Yards Arm. On the Stern is painted the Arms and Crest of the Company, for Boltsprit the Unicorn which is the supporters of the Worshipful Company of Goldsmiths.
     </p>
     <p>
      The Captain, who with several Trumpets is placed on the Stern, is dress'd in Indian Silk with a rich Fur Cap; the rest of the Mariners in Indian stripes and ruggid Yarn Caps, blue, white and red. The Boatswain having given his signet by his Whistle, and commanded silence, the Captain accosts his Lordship in these Words.
     </p>
     <div type="speech" xml:id="ep000776-e2760">
      <head>
       The Captain's SPEECH.
      </head>
      <l>
       SOme Years ago we bore up to this Port,
      </l>
      <l>
       But different Winds preventing, we fell short.
      </l>
      <l>
       Now having stemm'd the Currant of the Tide,
      </l>
      <l>
       In this calm Bay, we safe at Anchor ride.
      </l>
      <l>
       We have with double Cheer this Voy'ge contriv'd,
      </l>
      <l>
       To see you in your proper Haven arriv'd,
      </l>
      <l>
       Where may all prosperous Gales your Course direct,
      </l>
      <l>
       May all the Gods of Sea and Land protect,
      </l>
      <l>
       With Drake to guide you through the Gulph this Year,
      </l>
      <l>
       Where you through Scylla and Charybdis stear.
      </l>
      <l>
       If you this steady Compass can maintain,
      </l>
      <l>
       You need not fear an after Hurricane.
      </l>
      <l>
       You shall subdue the Foes insulting Rage,
      </l>
      <l>
       And bring the Pirates to the Weather-gage.
      </l>
      <l>
       If any dare resist your juster Power,
      </l>
      <l>
       This Ship shall make 'em to your Standard Lower:
      </l>
      <l>
       And all the World (while you are plac'd at Helm)
      </l>
      <l>
       Strike Sail to th' Admiral that guides the Realm.
      </l>
     </div>
    </div>
    <div n="4" type="pageant" xml:id="ep000776-e3020">
     <pb n="9" xml:id="ep000776-007-b"/>
     <head>
      The Fourth PAGEANT.
     </head>
     <p>
      THE Temple of JANVS of the Compositive Order, most elegantly contriv'd, being a composition of all the five Orders, the last and finest. This Temple is erected on a Rock, whereon are four Pyramids, elevated and adorned with Laurels of Victory, and Coronets of Honour, beset with Emeraulds and Topaz, Rubies, Sapphires, Amathysts, Chrysolites, and all manner of precious Stones. On the top of these Pyramids is exalted the Sun and Moon, in opposite Angles one against the other; the Sun as an Emblem of heat, by which the Minerals are reduced into Gold and Silver, fit for the Goldsmiths operation; and the Moon for its Transparency and Brightness, representing the spendor and shining Quality of such Metal. On the top of this Temple is exalted FAME, holding a Banner of the Lord Mayors, trampling upon ENVY, as a Trophy of his Lordship's Triumph over his Enemies. At the Temple-gate stands JANVS wearing on his Head a Crown, in manner of a Globe, part Celestial and part Terrestrial, alluding to the Revolution of the Year; his Head of Hair thin and lank, but white; his Beard broad and long, as he is suppos'd to be the Father of Time; his Garment part Purple, part Russet, close girt, in one hand a Scepter, in the other a Plough-share, the one relating to his kingly Office, the other to Agriculture and Tillage. He is figured with Two Faces alluding to his Wisdom; that judgeth by things past what will ensue; on the forehead of his Face, directed towards the Lord Mayor, is fixed a Star, on his breast another of more Magnitude, relating to his Deification. About that part of the Garment which is purple, are fixed several small Stars; and that of Russet several Crescents alluding to Plenty, the Fruits of Peace and Industry. At the basis of the Pyramids, surrounding the God of Time, as Attendants, sit the Seven liberal Sciences, as Daughters of
      <hi>
       Experience, Time
      </hi>
      and Industry, viz.
      <hi>
       Grammar, Arithmetick, Geometry, Astronomy, Astrology, Rhetorick
      </hi>
      and Logick, attired in their proper Habiliments. GRAMMAR, distinguished by holding in one hand a Book, and a Banner of the Cities in the other. ARITHMETICK, in a Vest of Cloth of Gold, with a Label charged with Figures. GEOMETRY, bearing a Castle upon her head, a green Mantle fringed with Silver, in her right hand a silver Wand, in her left a Banner of the Cities. ASTRONOMY, in an Azure Mantle, a watched Scarf with golden Stars, with a silver Crescent on her forehead. ASTROLOGY, in a Robe of Cloth of Silver, seeded with Stars, holding a Telescope erected towards the Heavens. RHETORICK, with the right Palm Expanded, and LOGICK with the same hand shut and close fisted, the one implying the copiousness of Elocution, the other the closeness of Logick, and syllogistical Argument.
     </p>
     <p>
      On an ascent above these sit
      <hi>
       Wisdom, History
      </hi>
      and Government.
     </p>
     <p>
      WISDOM, in a silver Robe and blue Mantle, seeded with Stars and fringed with Silver, purple Buskins, in the one hand bearing a Label with this Inscription,
      <foreign xml:lang="lat">
       Sapientia docet
      </foreign>
      ; in the other a Banner of the Cities.
     </p>
     <pb n="10" xml:id="ep000776-008-a"/>
     <p>
      HISTORY, a Reverend grave Matron in a Robe of Cloth of Gold, and Mantle of Crimson Velvet, holding in her Hand a Roll of Parchment expanded, bearing a History of the Foundation and Antiquity of the Worshipful the Company of Goldsmiths; who were Confirmed and Incorporated in the 16 th. of Richard the Second; and who had the Honour to be the First Lord Mayors of London: Together with a Catalogue of those Worthy and Famous Citizens,
      <hi>
       (Goldsmiths
      </hi>
      ) that had the Diginity of the Majoralty of this City some Years before; as the memorable
      <hi>
       Leofstane, Goldsmith
      </hi>
      , who was Provost of London in the Reign of Henry the First:
      <hi>
       Henry fitz Leofstane
      </hi>
      , in the Reign of Richard the First, Mayor:
      <hi>
       Gregory Rochley
      </hi>
      chief Say Master of the
      <hi>
       King's-Mint, Goldsmith
      </hi>
      , Mayor in the Third year of Edward the First, and continued Seven years. Then Alderman Faringdon of Faringdon-Ward, in the Ninth of the same, as appears upon Record; with many others.
     </p>
     <p>
      GOVERNMENT, in Armour of Silver and a Helmet, with a plume of red and white Feathers, a Gold Truncheon in the right hand, a crimson Scarf fringed with Gold, and crimson Stockings; in the Left a Banner of the King's.
     </p>
     <p>
      In the other Niches sit Three other Figures, being Votaries to Peace,
      <hi>
       Providence, Liberty, Honour
      </hi>
      .
     </p>
     <p>
      PROVIDENCE, a Lady lifting up both her hands to Heaven, and in a Shield these words inserted,
      <foreign xml:lang="lat">
       Providentia deorum
      </foreign>
      ; her Robe or Garment green, fringed with Gold, at her Foot a Scepter and Cornucopia, her Mantle yellow, fringed with Silver, on her head a Garland of Poppeys.
     </p>
     <p>
      LIBERTY, in a cherry-coker Robe fringed with Silver, a purple Mantle fringed with Gold, a Coronet Murrey with a silver Chaplet of divers Flowers, in one hand bearing a Shield with this Inscription,
      <hi>
       Liberty of Conscience
      </hi>
      ; in the other, a Banner of the King's.
     </p>
     <p>
      HONOVR, in a purple Robe wrought with Gold, a Crown with several Cities bearing the Arms of England; a Mantle of white Silk fringed with Crimson, bearing in her right hand my Lord Mayor's Banner, in her left a Shield of the Company.
     </p>
     <p>
      His Lordship having viewed the variety and regular contrivance of this Design, Janus addresses himself to him in these words.
     </p>
     <floatingText>
      <body>
       <div type="speech" xml:id="ep000776-e3710">
        <pb n="11" xml:id="ep000776-008-b"/>
        <head>
         The Fourth SPEECH by JANVS.
        </head>
        <l>
         HEre Times gray Emblem from this Temple-Gate,
        </l>
        <l>
         Which Mortals to my Fame did Dedicate,
        </l>
        <l>
         JANUS descends t'attend your brighter State.
        </l>
        <l>
         My Brows with lasting Ornaments are Crown'd,
        </l>
        <l>
         And all the Arts and Sciences Surround:
        </l>
        <l>
         This Old-young, double Vifage I assume,
        </l>
        <l>
         Implies both what is past, and what's to come.
        </l>
        <l>
         In a Celestial and Terrestrial Sphere,
        </l>
        <l>
         To shew the Revolutions of this Year,
        </l>
        <l>
         In which you have a harder Course to run,
        </l>
        <l>
         Than since with Infant Time your Course begun.
        </l>
        <l>
         To guard you through this Scene, I have apply'd
        </l>
        <l>
         Wisdom and Providence to be your guide;
        </l>
        <l>
         With
         <hi>
          Liberty of Conscience
         </hi>
         to be just,
        </l>
        <l>
         That You with Honour may discharge your Trust.
        </l>
       </div>
      </body>
     </floatingText>
     <p>
      The Speech being ended, the Foot Marshal placing the Assistants, Livery, and Companies on both sides of King's-Street, and their Pensioners with the Targets hung on the tops of their Javelins, in the Rear of them, and the Ensign-Bearers, Drums and Fifes in the Front; he hastens the Foyns and Budge Batchellors, together with the Gentlemen Ushers to Guild-Hall, where his Lordship is again saluted by the Artillery-Men, with three Volleys more, which conclude their Duty. His Majesty having before pass'd on Horse-back through the City with a large Guard to attend him, led up by the Duke of Northumberland, and the Foot Guard by the Lord Craven. The Lord Mayor being arrived at Guild-Hall, (which is hung round with the richest Tapistry) repairs to Dinner with the Companies, where to make the Feast more famous, he is this Year dignified with the presence of the King, Queen, Queen Dowager, their Royal Highnesses the Prince and Princess of Denmark, the Archbishops, Bishops, and all the principal Clergy, all the Lords of the Privy-Council and principal Officers of State, all the Judges and Serjeants at Law and their Ladies; together with all foreign Ministers, Envoys, Residents and Embassadors. His Majesty with the Queen, Queen
      <hi>
       Dowager, &amp;c.
      </hi>
      Dine at a Table raised upon the Hustings at the East end of the Hall; the foreign Embassadors, the Lords of the Council and others of the Peerage and Nobility, at the two next Tables raised on each side of the Hall; the Lord Mayor and the Aldermen Dine at a Table raised at the West end of the Hall, and the Citizens of the Liveries at several Tables, which fill the whole body of the Hall.
     </p>
     <p>
      His Lordship beginning their Majesties Healths, the Hall is filled with Huzza's and Acclamations. At Dinner before the Banquet, his Majesty is entertained with the following Song.
     </p>
     <floatingText>
      <body>
       <div type="song" xml:id="ep000776-e4090">
        <pb n="12" xml:id="ep000776-009-a"/>
        <head>
         SONG. To the KING.
        </head>
        <lg n="1">
         <head>
          I.
         </head>
         <l>
          HOW great are the Blessings of Government made,
         </l>
         <l>
          By the excellent Rule of our Prince;
         </l>
         <l>
          Who, while Troubles and Cares do his Pleasures invade,
         </l>
         <l>
          To his People all Joys does dispense:
         </l>
         <l>
          And while he for us is still Caring and Thinking,
         </l>
         <l>
          We have nothing to mind, but our Shops and our Trade,
         </l>
         <l>
          And then to Divert us with Drinking,
         </l>
         <l>
          And then to Divert us with Feasting and Drinking.
         </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
         <head>
          Chorus.
         </head>
         <l>
          From him we derive all our Pleasures, our Pleasures and Wealth;
         </l>
         <l>
          Then fill me Glass; nay, fill it up, fill it up higher:
         </l>
         <l>
          My Soul is a thirst, for his Majesty's Health;
         </l>
         <l>
          Then fill, fill, fill it up higher,
         </l>
         <l>
          My Soul is a thirst for his Majest'y Health,
         </l>
         <l>
          And an Ocean of Drink cannot quench my Desire.
         </l>
         <l>
          Since all we Enjoy to his Bounty we owe,
         </l>
         <l>
          'Tis fit all our Bumpers like that should o'er-flow;
         </l>
         <l>
          'Tis fit all our Bumpers, 'tis fit all our Bumpers,
         </l>
         <l>
          Like that should o'er&#8212; flow.
         </l>
        </lg>
        <lg n="2">
         <head>
          II.
         </head>
         <l>
          Then whilst in a Consort the Minstrela do play,
         </l>
         <l>
          Let a Health to Great Caesar go round:
         </l>
         <l>
          He who crowns with His Presence the state of this Day,
         </l>
         <l>
          Whom all conquering Laurels have Crown'd.
         </l>
         <l>
          And whilst we Enjoy the inestimate Blessings,
         </l>
         <l>
          The extent of his Freedom, each Man his own way,
         </l>
         <l>
          Let's show it in thankful Caressing,
         </l>
         <l>
          Let's show it in thankful, in thankful Caressing.
         </l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
         <head>
          Chorus.
         </head>
         <l>
          From him we derive all our Pleasures, our Pleasures and Mirth;
         </l>
         <l>
          Then fill me a Glass, &amp;c.
         </l>
        </lg>
       </div>
      </body>
     </floatingText>
     <p>
      The Song being ended, and the whole Entertainment managed with as good Order and Decency as the Circumstance, can permit, nothing being omitted by the City, that may express their Duty to their Majesties, and the humble sense they have in particular of their Royal Appearance; Their Majesties return in the same order to White-hall, and his Lordship to Grocers-Hall, which (as well as the former Lord Mayor) for the Convenience of its Situation and other Accomodations he hath chosen this Year, for the seat of his Majoralty. When his Lordship is Housed, those that attend him depart in decent and regular Order to their, respective Habitations; the Fire-works and Rockets lighting them all the way. The Triumphs, Pageants and Silk Works are taken into the special Care and Custody of the Masters, Painters and Artificers; who over-joy'd with the success, in contributing to this Solemnity, repair to drink his Lordships Prosperity; and all crown the Day with a Health to His Majesty;
      <hi>
       Whom Heaven long Preserve
      </hi>
      .
     </p>
    </div>
    <trailer>
     FINIS.
    </trailer>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
